<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Examiners Censure:
March. 16. 1620.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106549_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16864</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3767</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106549</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Examiners Censure:
March. 16. 1620.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A consolation for our grammar schooles: or, a faithfull and most comfortable incouragement, for laying of a sure foundation of all good learning in our schooles, and for prosperous building thereupon : More specially for all those of the inferiour sort, and all ruder countries and places; namely, for Ireland, Wales, Virginia, with the Sommer Ilands, and for their more speedie attaining of our English tongue by the same labour, that all may speake one and the same language. And withall, for the helping of all such as are desirous speedilie to recouer that which they had formerlie got in the grammar schooles; and [to] proceed aright therein, for the perpetuall benefit of these our nations, and of the churches of Christ</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 84, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="afterword">
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <head>❧ The Examiners Censure:
<date>March. 16. 1620.</date>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as this Author, still desirous to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
all the new comforts, which
God hath vouchs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fed him in his long
and painefull trauels, for the generall
good, and specially for our Grammar-schooles; and
fearing lest in anie matter he should deceiue himselfe
or others, hath intreated vs to make some further
triall of the things which he hath written h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rein, for
the better confirmation of himselfe and of all others;
we could not denie his so honest a request. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> Labours in this kinde, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
of <hi>Worcester,</hi> at the first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
of his Gramm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r-schoole, as appeares in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
Preface before it, and by other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
since; yet now that it is to come foorth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>,
much more compleate and perfect after so much
long trauell and experience) we haue her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>upon made
new and further triall accordingly. In which we haue
<pb facs="51"/>
found so much content in euery forme, from the lowest
to the highest, for the time which we then had, as
perswaded vs of the trueth of whatsoeuer he hath
written concerning the same; and giues vs withall
much assurance of a very great blessing to be hoped
for, both to Church and Common-wealth in all places
for which he hath trauelled, by these his happie La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
rightly put in practise: which all well-willers
to Religion and Learning are to wish to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
and by all meanes to promote, for the good of
the present and of all succeeding ages.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IAMES VSSHER Doctour and Professor
of Diuinitie in the Vniuersitie of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
      </signed>
      <signed>DANIEL FEATLY Doctour of Diuinity,
and Chaplin in house to his Grace of
<hi>Canterburie.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="51"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>