<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my approued good Friend,
Mr. Nicholas Okes.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106113_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106113</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my approued good Friend,
Mr. Nicholas Okes.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology for actors : Containing three briefe treatises. 1 Their antiquity. 2 Their ancient dignity. 3 The true vse of their quality. Written by Thomas Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_printer">
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <head>To my approued good Friend,
M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> Nicholas Okes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE infinite faults escaped in my
booke of <hi>Britaines Troy,</hi> by the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
of the Printer, as the misquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
mistaking of sillables, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing
halfe lines, coining of strāge
and neuer heard of words. These be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
without number, when I would haue taken a
particular account of the <hi>Errata,</hi> the Printer answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
me, hee would not publish his owne disworke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship,
but rather let his owne fault lye vpon the
necke of the Author: and being fearefull that others
of his quality, had beene of the same nature,
and condition, and finding you on the contrary, so
carefull, and industrious, so serious and laborious to
doe the Author all the rights of the presse, I could
not choose but gratulate your honest indeauours
with this short remembrance. Here likewise, I must
necessarily insert a manifest iniury done me in that
worke, by taking the two Epistles of <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Helen,</hi>
and <hi>Helen</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> and printing them in a lesse vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume,
vnder the name of another, which may put
the world in opinion I might steale them from him;
and hee to doe himselfe right, hath since published
them in his owne name: but as I must acknowledge
<pb facs="33"/>
my lines not worthy his patronage, vnder whom he
hath publisht them, so the Author I know much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
with M. <hi>Iaggard</hi> (that altogether vnknowne
to him) presumed to make so bold with his name.
These, and the like dishonesties I know you to
bee cleere of; and I could wish but to bee
the happy Author of so worthy a worke
as I could willingly commit to your
care and workmanship.</p>
   <signed>
      <hi>Yours euer</hi>
THOMAS HEYVVOOD.</signed>
   <pb facs="33"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>