<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE and my very good L. Ambrose, Earle of War∣wike, Baron Lisle, of the most excelent or∣der of the Garter knight, Generall of the Queenes Maiesties Ordinance, with in her highnes Realms and Dominiōs, Bernabe Rych, wisheth long lyfe, increase of ho∣nor, with all happy successe.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106077_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10718</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20998</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106077</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE and my very good L. Ambrose, Earle of War∣wike, Baron Lisle, of the most excelent or∣der of the Garter knight, Generall of the Queenes Maiesties Ordinance, with in her highnes Realms and Dominiōs, Bernabe Rych, wisheth long lyfe, increase of ho∣nor, with all happy successe.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A right exelent and pleasaunt dialogue, betwene Mercury and an English souldier : contayning his supplication to Mars: bevvtified with sundry worthy histories, rare inuentions, and politike deuises. wrytten by B. Rich: gen. 1574</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Disle (Disley, Dizle), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE and my very good <hi>L. Ambrose,</hi> Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike, Baron Lisle, of the most excelent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Garter knight, Generall of the Queenes Maiesties Ordinance, with in her highnes Realms and Dominiōs, <hi>Bernabe Rych,</hi> wisheth long lyfe, increase of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, with all happy successe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I HAD FINISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this little treatise, (right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) I called to mynde, the order of Wryters, who vsually are accustomid to dedicate their labors to some noble personage, to whome they doe beare some zelous afection, or any other dewtiful good wil, which example I determined to follow, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to present this same to your honor, but whē I called to my remembraūce my own ignorance in the knowledge of wryting, &amp; the slender fēce of that I had wrytten, it vtterly discouraged me, so that I was at a controuersie in my selfe, what I might do: in the ende, presuming more of your Honorable &amp; curtious inclynation, then on my owne skil. I haue auentured to present your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor with this little booke, which I haue entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led▪ <hi>A Dialogue betwene Mercury and an English Souldier, contayning his Supplication to Mars</hi>▪ wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue descrybed▪ certayne noble facts &amp; other high exploytes, achiued by great &amp; mighty Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other valiaunt Captaines, also not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting to manifest the great abuse that is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vsed, in the setting forth of Souldiers, in the tyme of seruice which I my selfe haue seene and marked, and although I do know my selfe to be
<pb facs="3"/>
the simplest of a great number, &amp; the worst able to performe this that I haue taken in hand, yet I haue presumed to consecrate the same &amp; the rest of my beneuolent mynde to your Honour, for to whome may the facts &amp; exploytes of noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages be rather offred, then to him whose vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt acts hath made him famous in his Coūtry, but in specially to the straunger, vvho hath felt the force and puissaunce thereof, to vvhom may the orders, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ests and courses of martyall affayres, be more aptly remembred▪ then to him vvho can throughly deeme of such labours, and hath pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed so many brunts in the same. Most humbly desiring your Honor to accept this same, as the base and barren style of a simple Souldiers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, rather then the lerned lynes proceding from such as hath bene trayned vp in Scoles, beseching God, long to preserue your Honour, with wished increase, and to prolong your dayes, vvith most happy delight.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most humble, at commandment Barnabe Rych.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>VAL. MAX.</bibl>
      <q>¶The happy and quiet estate of blessed peace, doth onely consist in the bosome and custody of knowledge in warres.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>