<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106219_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03361</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13480.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106219</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and pleasaunt treatise, intituled, Naturall and artificiall conclusions: written first by sundrie scholers of the Vniuersitie of Padua in Italie, at the instant request of one Barthelmewe a Tuscane: and now Englished by Thomas Hill Londoned [sic], as well for the commoditie of sundrie artificers, as for the matters of pleasure, to recreate wittes at vacant tymes</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Copland, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kitson, Abraham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here of late (gentle Reader) in my Preface of that treatise, of the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of sundrie dreames, bothe of Iosephes and Salomons togethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I did there promise to set forth a little treatise of Naturall &amp; Artificiall Conclusions, whiche now I haue performed, wishyng the Reader to giue his fauourable reading &amp; report of them not set foorthe for any necessitie of them, but rather for the recreation of wittes at vacant tymes. And yet I must confesse that some of them bee necessarie for sund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie Artificers to knowe, and the rest for matters of pleasure, as in the readyng of them shall appeare. Whiche (gentle Reader) takyng in good part, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struyng my meanyng vnto the beste, then promise to further you shortly with my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of Problemes, and then naturall answeres annexed, and that aptly answered.</p>
   <p>And a brief Herball verie rare, for the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous matters, &amp; that naturall, taught in the same. And a treatise of the rare and straunge wonders seen in the aire, for these many yeres paste in sundrie Realmes and Countries right pleasaunt to reade. All whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> he gentle Reader, looke for at the Printers handes so short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as maie bee. In the meane tyme buye, and giue the readyng of these vnto the better hope of the rest.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>