<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
           <author>Lyly, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106953_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06607</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17070</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 <author>Lyly, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Euphues and his England : Containing his voyage and his aduentures, myxed with sundrie pretie discourses of honest loue, the discription of the countrey, the court, and the manners of that isle. Delightful to be read, and nothing hurtfull to be regarded: wherein there is small offence by lightnesse giuen to the wise, and lesse occasion of looseness proffered to the wanton. By Iohn Lyly, Maister of Arte. Commend it, or amend it</title>
                 <author>Lyly, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <publisher>Cawood, Gabriel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 132 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, Euphues is come at the length though to late, for whose ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, I hope three badde excuses, shal stande in steede of one good reason.</p>
   <p>First in his trauaile, you must think he loytered, tarying many a month in Italy viewing the Ladies in a Painters shop, when hee should haue bene on the Seas in a Merchaunts ship, not vnlyke vnto an idle huswife, who is catching of flyes, when she should sweepe downe copwebs.</p>
   <p>Secondly being a great start from Athens to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, he thought to stay for the aduantage of a Leape yeare, and had not this yeare leapt with him, I think he had not yet leapt hether.</p>
   <p>Thirdly being arriued, he was as long in viewing of London, as he was in comming to it, not farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from Gentlewomē, who are longer a dressing their heades than their whole bodyes.</p>
   <p>But now he is come Gentlemen, my request is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bid him welcome, for diuers ther are, not that they mislike the matter, but that they hate the man, that wil not stick to teare Euphues, bicause they do enure Lyly: Where-in they resemble angry Dogges, which byte the stone, not him that throweth it, or the cholaricke Horse-rider, who being cast from a young Colt, &amp; not daring to kill the Horse, went into the stable to cutte the saddle.</p>
   <p>These be they, that thought Euphues to be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="8"/>
and yet wer neuer troubled with drying of his clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, but they gessed as they wished, and I woulde it had happened as they desired.</p>
   <p>They that loath the Fountaines heade, will neuer drinke of the lyttle Brookes: they that seeke to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the Fish, will neuer eate the spawme: they that lyke not mee, will not allowe anye thing that is mine.</p>
   <p>But as the Serpent Porphirius, though he bee full of poyson, yet hauing no teeth hurteth none but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, so the enuious, though they swell with malyce till they burst, yet hauing no teeth to bite, I haue no cause to feare.</p>
   <p>Onely my sute is to you Gentlemen, that if anye thing bee amisse, you pardon it: if well, you defende it: and how-soeuer it bee, you accepte it.</p>
   <p>Faultes escaped in the Printing, correcte with your pennes: omitted by my neglygence, ouerslippe with patience: committed by ignoraunce, remit with fauour.</p>
   <p>If in euery part it seeme not alyke, you know that it is not for him that fashioneth the shoe, to make the graine of the leather.</p>
   <p>The olde Hermit will haue his talke sauour of his Cell, the olde Courtier, his loue taste of Saturne, yet the last Louer may happely come somewhat neere Iuppiter.</p>
   <p>Louers when they come into a Gardeine, some gather Nettles, some Roses, one Tyme, an other Sage, and euery one, that, for his Ladyes fauour, that shee fauoureth: insomuch as there is no Weede almoste, but it is worne. If you Gentlemen, doe the lyke in reading, I shall bee sure all my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses
<pb facs="8"/>
shall be regarded, some for the smell, some for the smart, all for a kinde of a louing smacke: Lette euerye one followe his fancie, and say that is best, which he lyketh best. And so commit euerye mans delight to his own choice, &amp; my selfe to all your courtesies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to vse,
Iohn Lyly.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>