<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Leake, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106749_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05205</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15342</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Leake, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foure sermons : preached and publikely taught by Richard Leake, preacher of the word of God at Killington, within the baronrie of Kendall, and countie of Westmerland: immediately after the great visitation of the pestilence in the fore-sayd countie</title>
                 <author>Leake, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 80, 77-116 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occasion (good reader) of my offering this poore mite into the Lords treasurie, and of sending abroade this fruit, which the increase of my small talent bringeth forth vnto the Lords familie, was this: I pleased God by the space of two yeares together, to giue our country (in the North parts of this land) a taste of his power in iudgement, being prouoked there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by our manifold enormious sinnes: he vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited vs with many and grieuous sicknesses, as first with the hot feuer, after, with the bloodie issue, and lastly, most fearefully with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame disease of the pestilence, inflicted vpon many, and shaken at all in our whole countrie. And albeit neither I, nor any of the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my charge, were infected therewith, yet had we all of vs, the cause thereof within our sinfull hearts, as well as any others: it had inuironed
<pb facs="10"/>
vs almost round about, we had scarcely any way to turne vs, but mourning might be heard; so that we expected no better than neighbours fare. Furthermore, in this time, and before (as it is well knowne) the Lord our God▪ did cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten and punish this whole land with dearth and famine of bread, and scarcitie of other victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als in diuers places, since which time of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, it hath pleased him (who is God, blessed for euer amen) to make knowne his power in mercie, as he had before manifested the same in iudgement. For be gaue plentie and cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of bread and all kinde of victuals in stead of scarcitie and dearth: hee extinguished the heate of sickenesses in those places where it was most feruent, &amp; with-held it from those places vnto which it was most fearefully threatned, so that then might be heard amongst vs, mirth in stead of mourning, songs in stead of doleful sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; gladsome salutations in meetings, in stead of diligent shunning each of others presence, for feare of infection. The boistrous stormes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions now driuen away, and calme showers of comfort descending: the cloudes of his heauie displeasure now being dispersed, and the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his fauourable countenance shining vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: sicknesse now ceased and health restored: famine taken away, and plentie ministred; I thought it high time not onely to preach vnto the people of my owne charge, these sermons
<pb facs="10"/>
following (which teach plainely what vse we are to make of these and such like workes of God, and what dutie they binde vs vnto) but also to publish them for the benefite of all such as the doctrine doth pertaine vnto. This occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and opportunitie offered (being well conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all them who shall reade these Sermons) may serue sufficiently to excuse me of all such wants as shall be espyed in me: for the prouerbe is not more olde than true: a little betime is worth much too late. <hi>How good is a word in due season?</hi> (saith <hi>Salomon) Pro. 15.25.</hi> as if he had said, <hi>Oh who is able to declare how good a word is, which commeth in due sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son?</hi> He himselfe afterward sheweth whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it may bee compared: <hi>A worde</hi> (saith hee) <hi>spoken in his place, is like apples of golde, with pictures of siluer, Chapter 25. verse 11.</hi> Now sure am I, that there is no wise bodie can denie, but these Sermons were spoken in season, and also published in season, except some shall say, that they had better haue come sooner, which I could not remedie: and yet I feare not their comming too late: for the dangers are lately passed, the deliuerance newly obteyned, the prints or markes of his correcting rods, are yet to be seene in many great townes, whose ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations are as yet scarcely replenished: the noyse of their mournings and gronings, which
<pb facs="11"/>
were sore chastened, are as yet sounding in some of our eares: his gracious blessings are as yet euen in our mouthes; so that neither his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon the wicked, his chastisements vpon his children, nor his seuerall blessings vpon them both, now againe multiplied, can possiblie be out of memorie. If any say that they (such as they are) be published ouer hastely, because peraduenture they may seeme to preuent the publishing of some more learned mans worke taken in hand vpon the like occasion: I answer, that euen for this purpose I stayed these my Sermons a whole season, gladly desiring, and earnestly expecting the publishing of some of their labours, vpon the same occasion, and to the same end, that I haue published these: yea, so long I stayed, till I feared, that if I should haue lingered any longer, the fitnes of the time would haue stolen away; and yet could I heare of none which went about or intended any such matter. Wherefore thus long I stayed, looking for some mans labours to doe more good, and no longer would I deferre, least there should be no mans labours set forth vpon the same occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, which might doe any good.</p>
   <p>Now then (the premises considered) I pray thee Christian reader, to take in good part, this my labour, and then it shall be as an earnest pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of some riper fruits out of my poore garden,
<pb facs="11"/>
when God shall minister a fit season to gather them, and to send them abroode, I ayme at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing herein, but the glorie of God, the benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of others, and the discharge of my owne dutie, if by any meanes I might attaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, though but in some small measure: and though I misse thereof with men; yet not with God, who regardeth and accepteth the will and desire. As for the malitious and enuious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and scorners, who haue Eagles eyes to see motes in godly mens labours, but blinde as Moales, to see beames of wickednes in their own liues; readie to censure others of all wants, but sooth themselues in their owne wayes, if they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie me, it is but their propertie, if rashlie they censure, and iudge amisse of me, it is their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, if they with open mouth barke at me, I haue therein many to take part with me, whose bookes I scantly am worthie to beare after them: none whereof could euer write so lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, deliuer the trueth so zealously, or doe any worke so profitably, but either Atheist, Papist, sectarie, one wicked person or other, was readie at hand eyther priuily or openly, to labour by power and policie, perswasion or threatning to hinder the good successe of those their labours. I therefore account all their malitious carping and scornefull censuring, the fruit which their profane lips do daily bring forth. But vnto such
<pb facs="12"/>
as feare God and haue need to be increased by the mutual helpe of their brethren (I say) reade these sermons diligently, &amp; meditate vpon thē, that ye may see the works of god, and the vse yee ought to make of them, when God hath chaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you by sicknesses or any other way, humble your selues before God repent and turne neerer vnto him, and againe when he hath mercie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and granteth vnto you ease &amp; comfort, then beware, sinne no more least a worse thing come vnto you, which, that it may be fruitfull, God for Christ his sake grant through the mightie working of his holy spirit, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which one God, Father, Sonne and holy Ghost, be glory and praie for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord:</hi> Richard Leake.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>