<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE CONCERNING DAVID, his Life and Acts.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106799_Fr7_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">219</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106799</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE CONCERNING DAVID, his Life and Acts.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Annotations upon the five bookes of Moses, the booke of the Psalmes, and the Song of Songs, or, Canticles : VVherein the Hebrevv vvords and sentences, are compared with, and explained by the ancient Greeke and Chaldee versions, and other records and monuments of the Hebrewes: but chiefly by conference with the holy Scriptures, Moses his words, lawes and ordinances, the sacrifices, and other legall ceremonies heretofore commanded by God to the Church of Israel, are explained. With an advertisement touching some objections made against the sinceritie of the Hebrew text, and allegation of the Rabbines in these annotations. As also tables directing unto such principall things as are observed in the annotations upon each severall booke. By Henry Ainsworth</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 172, 156, 184, 206, 2, 168, 28, 189, 7, 59, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="463"/>
   <pb facs="463"/>
   <head>A PREFACE CONCERNING DAVID, his Life and Acts.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>AVID <hi>the sonne of Iesse, of the tribe of Iudah, of the linage of Abraham in the</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">1 Chron. 2. Matth. 1. 1. 17.</note>
      <hi>fourteenth generation, was borne in Bethlehem (a towne in the tribe of Iudah, in the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,) about 2917 yeares after the creation of the world, in the daies when Samuel the Prophet was Iudge of Israel. He was the</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">1 Chro. 2. 15.</note>
      <hi>seventh and youngest of all Iesses sonnes, of least esteeme among them, and set to keepe his fathers</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 11.</note>
      <hi>sheepe. In the three and twentieth yeere of his life, he was by Samuel the Prophet privately in Bethlehem anointed</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 13.</note>
      <hi>King over Israel, in the midst of his brethren, and the Spirit of the Lord came upon him from that day forward. He was</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Vers. 12.</note>
      <hi>ruddy, of a beautifull countenance, and goodly to looke to; a</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Vers. 18.</note>
      <hi>cunning player on the Harpe, a mightie valiant man of warre, and prudent in speech, and a comely person, and the Lord was with him: Who also gave him these testimonies and promises;</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 13. 22.</note>
      <hi>I have found David, the sonne of Iesse, a man after mine owne heart, which shall fulfill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> my will.</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Psal. 89. 19.</note>
      <hi>I have laid helpe on one that is mighty, I have exalted one chosen out of the people, with whom</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Vers. 21.</note>
      <hi>my hand shall be established, mine arme also shall streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him; I will</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Vers. 23, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>beat downe his foes before his face, and plague them that hate him. In my name shall his horne be exalted; I will set his hand in the sea, and his right hand in the rivers; I will make him my first-borne, higher than the Kings of the earth. My mercy will I keepe for him for ever, and my covenant shall stand fast with him; his seed will I make to endure for ever, and his throne as the daies of heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>After Davids anointing in Bethlehem, he went againe and fed his</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 19.</note>
      <hi>fathers sheep: but the Spirit of God wrought mightily in him. He killed</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.</note>
      <hi>Goliath, the Philistian Giant, from whose face</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Vers. 24.</note>
      <hi>all the men of Israel fled away for feare: David overcame him (in the name of the Lord of hosts) with a sling and with a stone. He was a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Musitian; and</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 23.</note>
      <hi>playing on his Harpe with his hand, he refreshed King Saul, tho was vexed with an evill spirit from the Lord. He was imployed in warres against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Philistians: and</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 5.</note>
      <hi>whither soever Saul sent him, he behaved himselfe wisely and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ospered, and was accepted in the eyes of all the people; so that the women of Israel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>g of him,</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Vers. 7.</note>
      <hi>Saul hath slaine his thousands, and David his ten thousands. But that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aise</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">Vers. 8, 9.</note>
      <hi>procured him envie from Saul ever after, and he sought to slay him: but</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">Vers. 16.</note>
      <hi>all Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ael loved him. And though he after tooke to wife Michal, Sauls daughter; yet</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">1 Sam. 19. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Saul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ontinued his hatred against his sonne in law; and first secretly, then openly sought his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>fe: so that David was faine to flee and hide himselfe in the land of Israel, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>range countries, to the</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">Psal. 120. 1 Sam. 26. 19.</note>
      <hi>great affliction of his soule.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>When Saul was dead, and David</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">2 Sam. 5. 4.</note>
      <hi>thirtie yeares of age, the men of Iudah</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 2. 4.</note>
      <hi>anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="464"/>
him King the second time, in Hebron, over the house of Iudah. Ishbosheth, Sauls son, resisted him; but David waxed stronger and stronger. Then</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">1 Chron. 11. 1, 3.</note>
      <hi>all Israel anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him King over them, and he reigned in Ierusalem. So the time of all his reigne was</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 5. 4, 5.</note>
      <hi>forty yeares. In Hebron he reigned over Iudah seven yeeres and six months, and in Ierusalem he reigned 33. yeares over all Israel and Iudah. During which space, the Lord still exercised him with many</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">1 Chron. 14. &amp; 18. &amp; 19.</note>
      <hi>wars abroad, and troubles at home; as by the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his daughter</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">2 Sam. 13. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Thamar, the killing of his son Amnon, the treason and death of his son Absalon, the rebellion of Sheba, and other like sorrowes which God</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 10.</note>
      <hi>for his sins chastised him with, so many and so great, that the</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">2 Sam. 22. 5, 6.</note>
      <hi>pangs of death compassed him about, the flouds of Belial (the ungodly men) made him afraid, the cords of hell compassed him, the snares of death prevented him; his</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Psal. 55. 4, 5.</note>
      <hi>heart was sore pained within him, and the terrours of death fell upon him; fearfulnesse and trembling came upon him, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour overwhelmed him. His</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Psal. 31. 11.</note>
      <hi>life was spent with griefe, his yeares with sighing, his strength failed, and his bones were consumed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But alwaies in his feares</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Psal. 56. 3, 4.</note>
      <hi>he trusted in God, and was not afraid what flesh could doe unto him; in his distresse</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 22. 7.</note>
      <hi>he called upon the Lord, and cried to his God, who heard his voice out of his Temple, and drew him out of</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Vers. 17, 18, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>many waters, from his strong ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and from them that hated him, and brought him forth into a large place, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him, because he delighted in him. Hee gave him the</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Vers. 36, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>shield of his salvation, and girded him with strength to battell, and gave him the neckes of his enemies, that he destroyed those that hated him. Therefore he gave thanks unto the Lord</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Vers. 50.</note>
      <hi>among the nations, and sang praises unto his name,</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Psal. 57. 8.</note>
      <hi>awaking up his glory, awaking up his Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Harpe, awaking himselfe early, to praise the Lord among the peoples, and to sing unto him among the nations: so he sang of his</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">Psal. 59. 16.</note>
      <hi>power, he sang loud of his mercy in the morning, that God had beene his defence and refuge in the day of his distresse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And hereof this booke of Psalmes (most whereof David made) is a glorious testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; wherein by manifold Psalmes, and Hymnes, and spirituall Songs, he set forth the praises of God, his owne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aith in his Word, exercise and delight in his Law, with nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Gods former and present mercies, and prophesies of future graces to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in Christ, whom he (being a Prophet)</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 2. 30.</note>
      <hi>knew that hee should be the fruit of his loines concerning the flesh, and should sit upon his throne; whose incarnation, afflictions, death, resurrection, ascension, and eternall glorious kingdome and priesthood, he sang by the Spirit, with such heavenly melody, as may not only delight, but draw into admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration every understanding heart, and comfort the afflicted soule with such consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as David himselfe was comforted of the Lord.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And these his Psalmes have ever since, by the Church of Israel, by</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1. 16. 42. Rom. 4. 6. &amp; 11. 9.</note>
      <hi>Christ and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, and by the Saints in all ages, been received and honoured as the oracles of God, cited for confirmation of true religion, &amp; sung in the publike assemblies, as in Gods Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and Temple, where they sang praise unto the Lord, with the</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">2 Chron. 29. 30.</note>
      <hi>words of David▪ and with the instrumēts which</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">2 Chron. 7. 6.</note>
      <hi>he had made over their</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">2 Chron. 29. 25, 27, 28.</note>
      <hi>burnt-offerings &amp; sacrifices▪</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now because many things, both for phrase and matter, are difficult to such as ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> not acquainted with Davids language, I have (out of my slender store) annexed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> few briefe notes, comparing the Scriptures, and conferring the best Expositors, espe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> ally the ancient Greeke and Chaldee versions, whereby if any helpe of understand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> may arise, the praise be to God, the comfort to his people.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>