<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106710_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16915</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3806</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three questions ansvvered : I. Question. What should our meaning be, when after the reading of the fourth Commandement, we pray; Lord incline our hearts to keepe this law? II. Question. How shall the fourth Commandement, being deliuered in such forme of words, binde vs to sanctifie any day, but onely the seauenth, the day wherein God rested, &amp; which the Iewes sanctified? III. Question. How shall it appeare to be the law of nature to sanctifie one day in every weeke?</title>
                 <author>Broad, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 38, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>Errata.</head>
   <p>Pag. 1. line 8. <hi>strike out,</hi> had p. 3. l. 4. <hi>strike out</hi> your. p. 5. l. 4. <hi>for</hi> here likeneth, <hi>read</hi> here he likeneth. p. 5. l. 16. text <hi>read</hi> type. p. 6. <hi>in marg.</hi> If the Sabbath were a shadow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 9. l. worke <hi>r.</hi> weeke. p. 10. l. 16. <hi>after</hi> Remember the Sabbath to sanctifie it, <hi>read</hi> this should be a more generall commandement, then if hee had said, Remember the seauenth day to sanctifie it. p. 12. l. 3. vs <hi>r.</hi> me. p. 18. l. 3. commanding, <hi>r.</hi> commanded. p. 26. The saying of Chrysostome should be placed last of all, after the note touching the Lords day. p. 27. l. 7. to make it more Christian and lesse Iewish. <hi>Other faults escaped in printing the Reader may amend.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>