<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the most reuerend, godly, and vigilant Bishops of the noble Realme of England, L. Edmund Grindall Archb. of Yorke, L. Richard Coxe Bishop of Elye, and L. Iohn Iewell Bishop of Salisbury, my right honourable Lordes and most deare brethren in Christ, the Praeface of Henry Bullinger, Elder.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106868_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17167</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4044</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106868</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the most reuerend, godly, and vigilant Bishops of the noble Realme of England, L. Edmund Grindall Archb. of Yorke, L. Richard Coxe Bishop of Elye, and L. Iohn Iewell Bishop of Salisbury, my right honourable Lordes and most deare brethren in Christ, the Praeface of Henry Bullinger, Elder.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutation of the Popes bull which was published more then two yeres agoe against Elizabeth the most gracious Queene of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, and against the noble realme of England : together with a defence of the sayd true Christian Queene, and of the whole realme of England. By Henry Bullinger the Elder</title>
                 <author>Bullinger, Heinrich</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 86 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶To the most reuerend, godly, and vigilant Bishops of the noble Realme of England, L. Edmund Grindall Archb. of Yorke, L. Richard Coxe Bishop of Elye, and L. Iohn Iewell Bishop of Salisbury, my right honourable Lordes and most deare brethren in Christ, the Praeface of <hi>Henry Bullinger,</hi> Elder.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight reuerend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Christ, my right honorable lords and most deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I acknowledge my self greatly bound vnto your goodnesse, that wheras we be set so farre a sunder, you dwelling beyond the sea in England, and I liuing here in Swicerland not farre from the Alpes: yet neuerthelesse you of your goodnes do by your often writing earnestly maintaine, preserue, yea and by daily increasing, more and more aduaunce the frendship and brotherhood long agoe begonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs. In respect wherof I ought of right to shew my selfe by all meanes thankfull &amp; seruiceable vnto you. And wheras now of late, by sending to me the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth, bishop of Rome (which I had not seen nor heard of afore) you haue ministred oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casiō vnto me, to do, or at least wise to attempt som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for the glory of Christ our onely redemer, and for the welfare of his Church which is among you in Englād, against the Romish Antichrist: behold, I
<pb facs="6"/>
dedicate vnto your Lordships this confutation of mine set against the Bull: submitting the same to your most exact iudgements, wholy to stand or fall according to your good pleasure. Neuerthelesse I beseech you to accept in good worth this indeuour and good will of mine, most desirous both to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so good a case, and also to pleasure your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships. Otherwise I freely confesse mine own abilitie to be very small, and your learning to be right great, so as ye could haue handled this matter farre better than I, if it had pleased you. Notwithstāding foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I haue perceaued, that by this my simple trauell I shall pleasure your Lordships: I would not that you should finde any want in me. Christ our Lord graunt that my treating therof may be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dātly frutefull vnto many. I beseech you vouchsaue to salute my right reuerend Lords &amp; most deare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brethrē L. <hi>Rob. Horne</hi> Bishop of Winchester: L. <hi>Edwin Sandes</hi> Bish. of London: L. <hi>Iohn Parkhurst</hi> Bish. of Norwich: L. <hi>Iames Pilckinton</hi> Bish. of Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: and also M. <hi>Iohn Aelmer,</hi> M. <hi>Sampson,</hi> M. <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey,</hi> M. <hi>Leuer,</hi> M. <hi>Foxe,</hi> and the residue, somtime cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of your exile in Swicerland and Germany: to the prayers of all whom I cōmend my selfe. And all the Ministers and brethren that be here, wish all prosperitie to you all, in our Lord Iesus Christ. The Lord Iesus blisse the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of your good Lordships, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue you from all euill.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Zuricke
<date>in the moneth of February, the yeare of our saluation. 1571.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>