<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVE∣rend father in God, my VERY GOOD LORD GERVASE by the pro∣uidence of God, Lord Bi∣shop of Worcester.</title>
           <author>Sauage, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106433_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11532</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21781</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106433</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVE∣rend father in God, my VERY GOOD LORD GERVASE by the pro∣uidence of God, Lord Bi∣shop of Worcester.</title>
                 <author>Sauage, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A conference betvvixt a mother a devout recusant, and her sonne a zealous protestant : seeking by humble and dutifull satisfaction to winne her vnto the trueth, and publike worship of god established nowe in England. Gathered by him whose hearts desire is, that all may come to the knowledge of God, and be saued</title>
                 <author>Savage, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 131, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>father in God, my</hi> VERY GOOD LORD GERVASE by the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, Lord</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Worcester.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat maketh me willing to publish this pamplet, your L. will easily iudge by the argument; what helpes I haue had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, so many as haue hard your Lorships publike exhortations or priuate conferences in matter of religion, will as easily coniecture, it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede nothing els but a gleaning of your L. great haruest, and a cluster of your owne vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. And therefore what cause I haue to sue for your honourable approbation, I neede not proclaime vnto the world, saue that I must needes confesse my selfe by many many bonds, more then I may well make knowne, to be ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all duty vnto your L. to whome next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der almightie God and her sacred Maiestie I owe whatsoeuer I haue besides this corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man. I may not particularize your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and innumerable fauours, least I exceede
<pb facs="3"/>the limits of a preface, and breake the bonds of sobrietie, and so incurre the iust displeasure of your Lordship. Only I craue pardon herein to acknowledge that as once in the Vniuersity by your Lordships happie hand I was brought into the sheepfolde of the great sheapheard, so in your honours seruice I haue beene led con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually by the same gratious hand in and out to the greene pastures and pleasant streames of euer liuing water, and learned that which may stead me all my life long, and in the worlde to come for euer, it I be not wanting vnto my selfe. Wherefore may it please your Lordship, to vouchsafe me your wonted honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to couer whatsoeuer my defects in this attempt, and to accept this testimonie of my true and due affection to your L. I shall be still more and more bounde, and I hope alwaies mindfull to bowe the knees of my heart vnto the highest, (whose recompence is a sufficient reward) for the continuāce of his gratious eye vpon you, and all your honourable affaires for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your L. humble chaplaine <hi>Francis Sauage.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>