<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HONOVRA∣BLE Lord, Henrie Cary, of the most noble order of the Garter Knight, Baron of Hunsdon, gouernour of the Queenes Maie∣sties towne of Barwicke, &amp; Lord Warden of the East Marches of England, anemptest Scotland, &amp; one of the Queenes maiesties honorable Counsaile, his singular good Lord: Stephan Batman wisheth; the feruent zeale of Gods truth, and long continuaunce of prospe∣rous health, vvith the increase of much honour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106624_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05237</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1538</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106624</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HONOVRA∣BLE Lord, Henrie Cary, of the most noble order of the Garter Knight, Baron of Hunsdon, gouernour of the Queenes Maie∣sties towne of Barwicke, &amp; Lord Warden of the East Marches of England, anemptest Scotland, &amp; one of the Queenes maiesties honorable Counsaile, his singular good Lord: Stephan Batman wisheth; the feruent zeale of Gods truth, and long continuaunce of prospe∣rous health, vvith the increase of much honour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Batman vppon Bartholome : his booke De proprietatibus rerum, newly corrected, enlarged and amended: with such additions as are requisite, vnto euery seuerall booke: taken foorth of the most approued authors, the like heretofore not translated in English. Profitable for all estates, as well for the benefite of the mind as the bodie. 1582</title>
                 <author>Bartholomaeus, anglicus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 426 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶TO THE RIGHT HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE Lord, Henrie Cary, of the most noble order of the Garter Knight, Baron of Hunsdon, gouernour of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties towne of Barwicke, &amp; Lord Warden of the East Marches of England, anemptest Scotland, &amp; one of the Queenes maiesties honorable Counsaile, his singular good Lord: Stephan Batman wisheth; the feruent zeale of Gods truth, and long continuaunce of prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous health, vvith the increase of much honour.</head>
   <p>THE prudent and most wise king of the world, Solomon, in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, among many sentences of profound sapience, saith, that those which be wise shal haue honor in possession: Also that the prosperity of the right Honourable shall not decay, because they shall be had in an euerlasting remembraunce, O happie birth wherevnto many are borne, to double honour: among men on Earth, among Angells in Heauen. Seeing therefore that wisdome is the onely preferrour to honour, how much is he, to be had in speciall reuerence, who in very deed sayth. I Wisdome dwell with Counsaile,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.</note> and find out Knowledge and Vnderstanding. By me Princes reigne, beare rule, and Noble men doe iudge the Earth, I haue bene from euerlasting, I was before the foundations were laide, therefore harken vnto me: Doe iustice, heare the oppressed, defend the innocent, forget not to doe good to al men, but specially to those, that are of the householde of Faith: let not your hands be open to receiue, and shut when you should giue: Be mercifull, for our heauenly Father is mercifull, who in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deede is the Wisedome, whereof I haue spoken, and the same, from whome all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of good directions proceedeth: by whose incomprehensible grace I haue ben made able to renew and finish an olde auncient booke, containing the properties of sundrie things, the discription of Countries, dispositions of creatures, operation of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, effects of simples, and such lyke, no lesse needfull then profitable, as shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, by perusall thereof: Beseeching your honour to accept this my Dedication, (not as a defendour of some friuolous fantasie) but as this booke shall deserue, being read ouer, wherein I doubt not, but that your honour shall finde many things to your contentation. This I end, depending on your honourable furtheraunce, when Oppertuniti shal minister Occasion, and in the meane time, I shall not cease to pray vnto God, whose merciful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence guide you, with his endlesse prosperitie, and all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an magistrates.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours Chaplaine, at commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. S.B.M.</signed>
   </closer>
   <postscript>
      <p>Vesper. Accept the trauaile of him that wisheth prosperitie to his Countrie: for the gift of knowledge is greater, then the patrimonie of many friends.</p>
   </postscript>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>