<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL THE Maister, Wardens, Assistantes, and fellowly Fraternitie of Chirurgians in London: and from them to all godly, true and zealous professours of Medicine, throughout this Realme of England, Iohn Banister wisheth the testimonie of a cleare conscience, before the highest Auditor.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106942_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03467</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1359</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106942</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL THE Maister, Wardens, Assistantes, and fellowly Fraternitie of Chirurgians in London: and from them to all godly, true and zealous professours of Medicine, throughout this Realme of England, Iohn Banister wisheth the testimonie of a cleare conscience, before the highest Auditor.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of man : sucked from the sappe of the most approued anathomistes, in this present age, compiled in most compendious fourme, and now published in English, for the vtilitie of all godly chirurgians, within this realme, by Iohn Banister, Master in Chirurgerie, and practitioner in phisicke</title>
                 <author>Banister, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 112, 4 leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_surgeons_and_physicians">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL THE Maister, Wardens, Assistantes, and fellowly Fraternitie of Chirurgians in London: and from them to all godly, true and zealous professours of Medicine, throughout this Realme of England, <hi>Iohn Banister</hi> wisheth the testimonie of a cleare conscience, before the highest Auditor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>fter the publication of my vnpolished Booke of vlcers (most graue Patrons) withdrawyng my selfe into my naked study, and deuising how best to performe my promise therein, but first considering, and in deede more deepely waying (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the state of tyme, and present want) whiche way I might most of all seeke the aduauncemēt of Chirurgerie in England, in the which cogitatiō (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) my zeale hath long tyme turned: At last I called to remembraunce, that the greatest want that raigneth in Chirurgians at this day, is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce in the subiect of their worke, waying also on the other side, that no English Authour, which hitherto hath written, hath suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently applyed his tyme to the amendement therof. Then was I wholly ouercome in this purpose, and then did I clearely see, how that to write Methodes or meanes to cure the affected partes of the body, the partes them selues beyng altogether vnknowen, or falsely imagined of, might rather be a meane to indurate the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taract of inscience, then to eate it through, or take it away. So thus I decreed to chaunge my purpose, that is, in steede of the Booke of Tumours, which I had before promised, to compile some worke of Anathomy, whiche might occupy fufficient scope to entreate of all the partes of man.</p>
   <p>But as the wanton child, that cryeth oft to handle that thyng which his strength is not able to meddle, but rather to endamage or hurt him selfe: Euen so did I full litle vnderstand the waight of my burden, till I had it on my <hi>Caluisius</hi> shoulders: when as it<note place="margin">Caluisius Sabin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> immediately had dissolued my good enterprise, had not then the flames of zeale accensed the courage of <hi>Hercules</hi> in my brest. By<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> meanes whereof although the same be now finished, yet so, as I determine nothyng lesse then hereby to hinder the proceedyng of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the lyke cause, nay rather I am resolued, that hereby I shall instigate and set forward the endeuours of such as are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mynded, to the aduauncement of the famous Arte Chirurgerie. For, as to the buildyng of some riche tower, or strong castle, beside the deuisours of the woorke and free Maso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s, there are required
<pb facs="5"/>
sondry inferiour Officers and labouryng persons, neither all to one ende, vse, or office, but some to digge, some to square stones, some to carie them to woorkemen, &amp;c: Euen so I, not hauyng the knowledge to deuise, nor the pollicie to digge for the best stone, neither the skill to temper the mortar, nor yet the reason rightly to square the stone, notwithstandyng because my zeale is nothyng inferiour to the chiefe Masons, haue had the will to gather the stones, and lay them by the workemen, now also hopyng that some cunnyng Mason will reache his hand to my heape, and lay of the stones of my gatheryng to the buildyng of this famous tower of health: since I shall conceiue incredible felicitie, if I may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in viewyng this renowmed buildyng (for so I hope surely to see it) cast myne eye vppon those stones whiche my homely handes had so rudely congested, and see them cunnyngly wrought, and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed to the buildyng.</p>
   <p>Into which consideration of me I first beseech you (most graue Seniors and Christian brethren) to enter, before you take any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to accuse me of temeritie, whiche crime I had worthely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred if zeale should not mediate my cause, so do I hope, that you will not onely fauour the fruites of my labours, and adde to them your helpyng handes, but also be (in my behalfe) the shield of <hi>Pallas,</hi> agaynst such Serpentine tounges as duely seeke to prophane of all godly endeuours.</p>
   <p>But to returne to my first determinatiō, whē I had wholly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē my consent to this end, I might see first a farre of, what sondry &amp; great mutatiōs nature hath vsed in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of mā since <hi>Galen</hi> wrote in Anathomy: and omitting diuers old writers, whose workes had not all equall successe, I came at length to <hi>Vesalius,</hi> whose whole worke seemed as tedious as his Epitome ouerculled &amp; short. But whē I saw <hi>Fuchsius</hi> to haue extract a notable Epitome out of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salius</hi> &amp; <hi>Galen,</hi> I had thought to looke no further till <hi>Collumbus</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in my sight: whose labours then reuoluyng, and seyng him in some thynges vse sufficient prolixitie, as in his Bookes of Bones and Muscles, &amp; in other causes to be somewhat brief (because <hi>Vesa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> had sufficiently hādled them) as in the nutritiue partes, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately I refused to bynde my selfe to any peculiar translation, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing rather to picke a posie of the chiefest flowers frō all their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, the opinion of <hi>Fernelius</hi> and others not beyng vtterly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, as throughout the History is diligently noted.</p>
   <p>And somuch the rather I esteemed this the best, because that way I perceiued I might both more playnly describe the partes to the iudgement of the Reader, as also vse sufficient scope vpon the dissention of Authours in the most notable causes. These conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations vsed, I set foreward in this matter, purposing (to speake briefly) to penne it in fourme of a History, least the Uolume of the
<pb facs="5"/>
booke should ouer hastely encrease, whereby I might be inhibited to vse requisite prolixitie in conuenient causes.</p>
   <p>And now finally beyng finished, as I may, not as I would, I (the least of the number) do offer the first fruites thereof vnto you, the auncient fraternitie of Chirurgians in London, and conse quently from you, to all Godly, and single professours of the Arte of Chirurgerie, throughout this Realme of England: into whose myndes, I beseech God to inspire the grace of his holy spirite, that we may all (yet at length) with one consent together, endeuour, study, searche, knocke, and call at the gate of Gods mercy, for the guidyng of his holy spirite, that, in all our proceedynges, beyng thereby protected, we may seeke the aduauncement of the glory of God, in healyng our afflicted brethren, whereto his diuine power shall (so oft as it pleaseth him) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and appoynt vs Ministers, that (I say) with the testimonie of a cleare conscience, we may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our vauntaged talentes vnto the high Auditour, in the day of commyng, which, we know not how neare, approcheth.</p>
   <p>As for you, O ye chaffe of the earth, ye stinge of the Godly, ye Impes of Hell, and children of wrath, you (I say) that, vnder pretence of the sacred Arte of Medicine, deuoure the sheepe of Gods pasture, slea the laboures in his Haruest, and denye your Lord the fruites of the Uineyard: since no warnynges may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monishe you, no exhortation amende you, no lawes bridle you, no punishementes tame you, nor any feare of God sinke into your brestes: behold, all the true professours of Christ Iesus, and who carefully endeuour Godly to discharge their functions, do cry for vengeaunce from heauen vppon you. And I (in these my labours) from the depth of my hart renounce you, hopyng assuredly, that from none of the flowers of this Garden any of you shall take o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to sucke that, whiche may maintaine the infection of your pestilent wretchednesse hereafter. If therefore I haue any where frequented a phrase aboue the common vse of our Englishe language, or vsed woordes litle different from the Latin, esteeme the same to be done onely for your cause, since (as much as in me lyeth) I haue endeuoured euery where, to shade the kernell with a harder shell then you shalbe able to cracke. Away therefore you Uipers. Let these my simple labours, whatsoeuer they are, be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in the handes of thee true, vertuous, and honest Artistes, and professours of Chirurgerie, that my expectation may be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Arte rightly aduaunced, and God duely worshipped.</p>
   <p>And now returnyng to you agayne (most Godly gouernours, for whose sakes I was most encouraged to perseuer in this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise) consideryng your Godly affection towardes me heretofore, and that it hath euer pleased you to esteeme of me, farre more, then the vttermost of my power, at any tyme, may merite, I thought
<pb facs="6"/>
it not onely the office of pietie, by this meanes, to pricke foreward the myndes of some of the learned sort, but also to commit this vnto you, as a pledge of my vnfeyned zeale to the Arte of Chirurgerie, and consequently to you the chief pillours thereof in this Realme: which, beyng thankefully receiued of your gratefull hartes, may testifie for me, that inwardly I wishe, whiche outwardly I am not able to manifest.</p>
   <p>Haue now therfore this History of Man, picked from the plenty of the most noble Anathomistes aboue named, wherein I haue earnestly, though rudely, endeuoured to set wyde open the closet doore of natures secretes, whereinto euery Godly Artist may safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter, to see clearely all the partes, and notable deuises of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the body of man. From the Female, and that (as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) for sundry good considerations, I haue wholly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stained my pēne: least, shunnyng <hi>Charibdis,</hi> I should fall into <hi>Scylla</hi> headlong. No more, but vouchsafe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Sinaetes</hi> faythfull offer, and protect this handfull of water, from the pollution of straunge beastes.</p>
   <closer>Farewell from Nottingham.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>