<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the high and migh∣ty Prince, Henry the seuēth, by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, and of Fraunce, Lorde of Irelande. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106025_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02817</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12950</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the high and migh∣ty Prince, Henry the seuēth, by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, and of Fraunce, Lorde of Irelande. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of graunde Amoure and la bell Pucel, called the Pastime of plesure : co [n] teining the knowlege of the seue [n] sciences, [and] the course of mans life in this worlde. Iuuented [sic] by Stephen Hawes, grome of kyng Henry the seuenth his chamber</title>
                 <author>Hawes, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wayland, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>216 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>To the high and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince, Henry the seuēth, by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, and of Fraunce, Lorde of Irelande. &amp;c.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>RIght mighty prince, &amp; redoubted souerayn</l>
      <l>Sayling forthe well, in the shyp of grace</l>
      <l>Ouer the waues of this life vncertayne,</l>
      <l>Ryght towarde heauen, to haue dwellyng place</l>
      <l>Grace dothe you guyde, in euery doubtfull case</l>
      <l>Your gouernaunce, doth euer more eschewe</l>
      <l>The synne of slouthe, enemy to vertue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <l>Grace stirreth well, the grace of god is great</l>
      <l>Whych you hath brought to your ryall se,</l>
      <l>And in your ryght, it hath you surely sette</l>
      <l>Aboue vs all, to haue the soueraintie:</l>
      <l>Whose worthy power, and regall dygnitie</l>
      <l>All our rancour, and our debate gan cease</l>
      <l>And hath vs brought, both welthe, rest, and peace.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>From whom dyscendeth, by the ryghtful lyne</l>
      <l>Noble prynce Henry, to succede the crowne</l>
      <l>That in his youth, doth so clearely shyne</l>
      <l>In euery vertue, casting the vyce adowne:</l>
      <l>He shall of fame, attayne the hye renowne</l>
      <l>No doubte but grace, shall hym well enclose</l>
      <l>Whych by true ryght, sprang of the red rose.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Your noble grace, and excellent hyenes</l>
      <l>For to accepte I beseche ryght humbly,</l>
      <l>Thys little boke, opprest wyth rudenes</l>
      <l>Without rethoryke, or colour crafty:</l>
      <l>Nothynge I am experte in poetry,</l>
      <l>As the monke of Bury, floure of eloquence</l>
      <l>Which was in the time of great excellence,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Of your predecessour, the. b. kyng Henry,</l>
      <l>Unto whose grace, he dyd present</l>
      <l>Ryght famous bokes, of parfit memory:</l>
      <l>Of hys fayuyng wyth termes eloquent.</l>
      <l>Whose fatall ficcions, are yet permanent.</l>
      <l>Grounded on reason, wyth cloudy fygures</l>
      <l>He cloked the trouth of al his scriptures.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <l>The light of trouth, I lacke cunnyng to cloke</l>
      <l>To drawe a curtayne, I dare not to presume</l>
      <l>Nor hyde my matter, with a misty smoke</l>
      <l>My rudenes cunnyng, dothe so sore consume</l>
      <l>Yet as I may, I shall blowe out a fume</l>
      <l>To hyde my mynde, vnderneth a fable</l>
      <l>By couert coloure, well and probable.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Besechyng your grace, to pardon mine ignoraunce</l>
      <l>Whiche this fayned fable, to eschue idlenes</l>
      <l>Haue so compiled, nowe without doubtaunce</l>
      <l>For to present, to your hye worthines</l>
      <l>To folowe the trace, and all the perfitenes</l>
      <l>Of my master Lydgate, with due exercise</l>
      <l>Suche fayned tales, I do fynde and deuise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For vnder a coloure, a truthe may arise</l>
      <l>As was the guise, in olde antiquitye</l>
      <l>Of the Poetes olde, a tale to surmise</l>
      <l>To cloke the trouthe, of their infirmitye</l>
      <l>Or yet on ioye, to haue moralitye</l>
      <l>I me excuse, if by necligence</l>
      <l>That I do offende, for lacke of science.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>¶ Your graces most boūden seruaūt Stephen Hawes, one of the gromes of your maiesties Chamber, the. xxi. yeare of your prosperous raygne.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>