<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106684_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04902</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15042</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106684</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures of John Knewstub, vpon the twentith chapter of Exodus, and certeine other places of Scripture : Seene and allowed according to the Queenes maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Knewstubs, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 355, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="187"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>Suche faultes (Christian Reader) as haue escaped in the imprinting of this booke, the greater parte whereof here vnderplaced, and corrected, and the residue (beeing few or none, and of litle weight,) omitted, we desire thee to conferre in reading, &amp; charitably to correct that which, beside these, is else-where to be amended, bothe in the poynting and in the matter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Page 5. for Exo. 3.9. read 6.3. p. 6. For Ezec. 38.28.36.26. ibi. line. 19. for renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, remouing. p. 8. l. 28. an, on. p. 14. l. 5. it, them. p. 15. l. 24. obediēce, disobediēce. ibi. l. 29. all, as. p. 19. l. 25. abeating, abating. p. 26. l. 2. not, no. ibi. l. 9. out, vs. p. 34. l. 9. vntoward, outward. p. 39. l. 21. put out, they are. 57. l. 22. we, vnlesse we. ib. Heb. 6.16. p. 58. l. 7. it, in. p. 60. l. 1. Sonne, sinne. ibi. in the margine. Prou. 13.13. p. 61. l. 19. gadned, gained. p. 64. l. 16. nature. In, nature, in, &amp;c. p. 67. l. 9. Ezechiel, and, Ezechiel. And. ibi. l. 9. Apostles. The, Apostles, the. 70. l. 26. no iustice but his, no, his iustice. p. 72. l. 20. this, this age. p. 75. l. 21. put out of. p. 83. l. 23. as, it. p. 85. l. 10. of, as. p. 86. l. 29. them, them the. p. 90. in the margine. Rom. 12.10. p. 97. l. 28. of the, of not. p. 105. l. 5. heart, heate. 109. l. 1. offered, offer. 117. l. 20. he, she. 119. l. 11. be had, hyde it. 124. l. 17. writeth, witeth. 130. l. 19. put out (and.) 138. l. 17. ouer, our. 142. l. 8. debt, double. 144. l. 30. by the their, in their. 148. l. 25. and as. 153. l. 26. we do, do we. 156. l. 29. to him, them. 172. in the mar. 2. Thes. 6. &amp; 15 173. l. 17. lest, least of all. p. 174. l. 8. would haue, would not haue. p. 176. l. 31. some sinne. 185. l. 4. hath, had. 194. l. 17. his, this. 195. l. 5. put out, not. p. 199. marg. Iam. 3. Iames. 1.27.212. l. 2. be one: as, be as, 214. l. 7. not, not so. 220. l. 3. preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, pursuing. 223. l. 20. twiteth, witeth. 231. l. 24. the, that. 238. l. 3. prouiding, prouing. ibi. l. 6. prouiding, prouing. 140. li. 17. put out, the. 244. l. 6. put out, and. 245. l. 29. summoned, summed. ibi. l. 30. put out, in. 247. l. 30. put out, what are. 263. l. 28. withstand, stande. 275. l. 15. He that, that he. 277. l. 10. put the point after the word iustification. 278. l. 14. follow, flowe. ibi. Ephe. 2.4.5.282. l. 6. of, for. 286. l. 28. payde, appaide. 300. l. 8. secure, secrete. 302. l. 10. wandering, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering. 318. l. 10. on, in. 319. l. 6. let, will let. 325. l. 26. lightly, likely. 330. l. 5. prayes, prayers. 344. l. 7. set the plaine point after same.</p>
   <pb facs="187"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>