<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Translator'S Dedication]</title>
           <author>Frampton, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106484_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07388</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17771</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106484</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Translator'S Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Frampton, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of nauigation : wherein is contained all the rules, declarations, secretes, &amp; aduises, which for good nauigation are necessarie &amp; ought to be knowen and practised: and are very profitable for all kind of mariners, made by (master Peter de Medina) directed to the right excellent and renowned lord, don Philippe, prince of Spaine, and of both Siciles. And now newely translated out of Spanish into English by John Frampton. 1581</title>
                 <author>Medina, Pedro de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 42, 45-83 leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>¶To the right woorshipfull, master Edwarde Dier Esquier,
Iohn Frampton wisheth health, and perfit felicitie with
increase of honour.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering with my selfe (right worshippefull,) that friendshippe and
bounden duetie, doth force many times men to doe thinges, which if they
were in the free choyse of him that doth thē, to leaue thē vndone without
any conceaued discurtesie, not only hee woulde not doe them, but also,
not asmuch as thinke of them. This I say that forced by friendshippe, and
also mooued by persuasion of certaine pylottes, and Masters of shippes, I determined to
translate this booke of the arte of Nauigation, compiled by Master Peter de Medina a spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niarde,
in the yeere of our Lorde Iesus Christ. 1545. And because the worke is so prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalle
that in our time, the like in all respectes hath not beene sette forth in our tongue,
considering it instructeth, and teacheth all the whole arte of Nauigation in all pointes, and
is in as like sorte necessary for the Mariner, as the accidens is for the Gramarian, the
weapon for the soldier, the Toole for the workeman, the Guide for the blinde, the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
for the learner: and finally, comparable to a glasse, wherein all the course of the
worlde, the Seas, the Windes, the Altitudes of the sunne, Moone, and Starres, are to
bee seene, and knowne, as farre as naturalle reason may extende to. And beesides, the
pleasure that I minded to doe, to the aforesaide persons, who mooued mee thereunto, as
also to satisfie my good and continual desire, which I haue, to helpe, and bringe to light
this good and profitable arte of Nauigation, whereby all men that are desirous to knowe,
the secreete of this noble arte, may profite themselues threewith by reading it in our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishe
tongue, especially the Pylottes, Masters, and Mariners, considering their liues and
lyuinges doe stand there vpon. And seeing as I belieue and trust, they shall gather much
fruite theer by, and that by little and little, these sciences shall remaine aswell in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
as in any other whatsoeuer. And seing this worke so necessary for the cōmon wealth,
setting all other priuate busines aside I tooke in hande to translate this booke, being peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
and alowed by the chiefe Pilot, &amp; learned Cosmographers of the famous contractaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
house of Seuil for the increase &amp; knowledge of matters of Nauigation, for the subiects
of Spaine, which worke so excellent tried &amp; approued by the learned: And for this our
Englād so fit, &amp; by me now thus translated out of Spanish into English, I dedicate to your
worship before al others, for that I know you to haue the arte of Nauigation inhigh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
&amp; as highly to esteeme al men that indeuour the knowledge of the same, beseeching
you to accept of my good wil and to be a protector of the same worke. And so beseeching
the almightie, to giue your worshippe long life, and the aduancement in this common
weale, that the good people wish vnto you, that aucthoritie may enable you to doe, that
good, that your good inclination doth naturally moue you vnto. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London <date>this
fourth of August. 1581.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your worshippes to commande.
Iohn Frampton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>