<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106657_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00113</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1011</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106657</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The right plesaunt and goodly historie of the foure sonnes of Aimon : the which for the excellent endytyng of it, and for the notable prowes and great vertues that were in them: is no les pleasaunt to rede, then worthy to be knowen of all estates bothe hyghe and lowe</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Copland, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walley (Waley), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, clxxiiii leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Philosopher in the fyrst booke of hys methafysyque sayth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euery man naturally desireth to know and to con newe thynges▪ And therfore haue the Clerkes &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of great vnderstandynge desyred and coueite to lerned sciences and to know vertues of thinges. Some by Phylosophy, other by Poetrye, and other by Historyes and cronyckes of thynges passed. And vpō these three they haue greatly laboured in suche y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thanked be God, by theyr good dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence and laboures: they haue had greate knowledge by innumerable volumes of bookes, whiche haue be made and compyled by great studye &amp; payne vnto thys day. And bycause that aboue all thinges the princes &amp; lordes of hie estate and entendement desyre to see thy storyes of the ryght noble and hye vertues of the prode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours whiche ben digne, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of remembraunce of perpetuall recommendacion. Therfore lace at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> request and commaundement of the ryght noble and vertus Erle Iohn Erle of Oxeforde my good synguler and especial lorde I reduced &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated out of Frenche into our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and Englyshe tongue the lyfe of one of his predecessoures na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Robert Erle of Oxeforde tofore sayd w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> diuerse &amp; many great myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles whiche God shewed for him as wel in his lyfe as after his death, as it is shewed all a longe in hys sayde booke. And also that my sayd Lorde desyreth to haue other Hystories of olde tyme passed of vertues chyual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reduced in lykewyse into our Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lishe tōgue: he late sent to me a booke in Frenche conteynyng thactes and faytes of warre do one and made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great Emperour and king of Fraunce Charlemayne by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .iiii. sonnes of Aymon, other wyse named in Frenche, Les quatre sylz Aymon. whyche booke accordynge to hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest I haue endeuorde me to accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyshe and to reduce it into our eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe, to my great coste and charges as in the translatinge as in enpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the same, hopyng &amp; not doub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng but that hys good grace shall rewarde me in suche wise that I shal haue cause to pray for his good and prosperus welfare, And besechynge his said noble good grace to pardon me of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rude and this simple worke For accordyng to the coppy whyche he sēt to me I haue folowed as nigh as I can, and where as any defaute shall be founde I submyt me to the correccion of them that vnderstande the cronycle &amp; hystory besethyng thē to correcte it &amp; amende there as they shall fynde faute. And I shall praye almighty God for them that so doo to rewarde them in suche wyse that after this shorte and transytory lyfe we all may come to euerlastyng lyfe in heuen. Amen.</p>
   <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the prologue.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>