<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The well-affected Reader.</title>
           <author>Boye, Rice</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106818_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16543</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3450</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The well-affected Reader.</title>
                 <author>Boye, Rice</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The importunate begger for things necessary, or necessity, without deniall : Or a treatise, wherein is shewed the lawfullnesse of praying absolutely for necessary temporall things, without doubting or wavering, and that the saints of God may and ought, as absolutely depen upon God, for their dayly bread, as they may for the pardon of their sinnes, and that the cause is in themselves, who doe not obtaine them. Whereunto is annexed an answer to Mr. Norrice his 5 arguments, which were framed against it, together with an answer to his Prosopopeia, wherein, as well the insufficiency of those arguments, as the deceitfullnesse of his collections, is plainely manifested by R.B</title>
                 <author>Boye, Rice</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 81, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO</hi> The well-affected Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I first conceaved and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Treatise (gentle Reader) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning praying for temporall blessings, it was farre from my thoughts, that ever it should come abroad to the publike view of the world: it being (as it were) but a Letter sent to <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Norrice</hi> in private, wherein (by his speciall intreatie) I unfolded myself unto him, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the subject before specified, as allso what I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his 5 Arguments intentively framed by him, to crosse or contradict what I before affirmed to him in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, concerning the point of <hi>praying absolutely for tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall necessaryes.</hi> I say, I did not once imagine, that this which I thus wrote to a freind in private, should ever have bene printed and made publike. That which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioneth me now (contrary to my former thoughts) to commit it in a publike manner to every mans eye and censure, is <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Norrice</hi> his slanderous misconstructions and false reports of my writings, which he caused long since (about 5 yeares) to fly up and downe the Country: And now (fearing belike they were forgotten) they are againe renued and revived by him. For no sooner had I
<pb facs="3"/>sent him in writing (according as hee desired me) what I conceived of the point above named, together with an answer to his 5 Arguments, but presently hee gave out (and that in writing) that my writings contained in them divers errours and absurdities, if not blasphemyes, as in my answer to his Prosopopeia is fully manifested.</p>
   <p>Those false reports and injurious slanders being (as I suppose) allmost forgotten, are againe renued by him, and now on foote as fresh as ever: by reason whereof I undergoe many heavy censures, which to me is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding grievous, both in respect of the inward and outward man: for as the soule is wounded, so a mans good name by such dealing is stained. Wherefore I could not chuse, but commit it to the view of all, choosing rather to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my self and writings, to the various censures of the multitude, then that the truth (through my silence) should be smothered by the foggy mists of falshood, and the least occasion given for any one to thinke, that those scandalls, which are falsly layd upon me, are but justly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served blame.</p>
   <p>I have no liberty to add too, or dimunish any thing from the first coppy, but as I wrote it to <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Norrice,</hi> and as he hath it coppyed in his hands, so I am compelled to publish it; and that for 2 reasons. First lest hee should say and affirme, that these are not the writings which hee had from me, and so free himself (at least as some may take it) from some (if not from all) of that deserved blame, which is layd upon him, for abusing my writings. And secondly that his slanderous collections and asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions cast upon me, in respect of my writings, may be plainly seene by them that read my writings, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with his speeches, together with his colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions hereafter mentioned.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p> Now seeing there is a necessity layd upon me (as thou seest curteous and well-disposed Reader) to publish these my writings without correction, either of matter or words, I would intreate thee to deale with me, as (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume) thou (being in the same case with me) wouldest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire others to deale with thee, even charitably to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue all things, and interpret them in the better part. Looke not so much (it being written to a freind in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate) for curiously composed sentences, and elegancie of phrase, as upon the truth of the matter, and the comfort which the right imbracing of the same, will bring unto thy soule; for it will not onely uphold thee as an ancre in the midst of the foming waves of this worlds calamities, but allso free thee from innumerable inconveniences, which otherwise are like to befall thee.</p>
   <p>If upon thy perusing my writings, thou findest any such errours of matter as are reported of me, and canst mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest them unto me as my sinne, I shall willingly confesse my fayling, and give publike satisfaction. I need say no more for present, in regard I have given thee some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertisements in the Epilogue or Conclusion of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Treatise: onely I desire thee to take due conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as well of those advertisements, as allso of those other truths, contained in these few sheets, and weigh them all in the balance of the Sanctuary, and not (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of thy prejudicate opinion of the Author) to deprive thy self of those priviledges, which the right imbracing of those truths, hereafter manifested, will bring unto thee. Howsoever my hearts desire and prayer to God is, that the truth may still flourish, notwithstāding the many subtill delusions of the adversaries, who with their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning arguments, doe like Iannes and Iambres, those Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian juglers, secretly resist the truth: yea my desire is,
<pb facs="4"/>that it may evidently and with speed appeare, that the Truth hath devoured errour, as the serpent of Moses did the Enchanters: Thus (assuredly exspecting Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of my desire) I commit what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to thy consideration, and thee to Gods protection, wishing thee to use what I have written to thy comfort, praying the Lord withall, to make thy heart stable and unblamable in holinesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in all good affection</hi> RICE BOYE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>