<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the Christian reader,
Iohn Bradforde wyssheth the
true knowledge and peace of Iesus Christ,
oure alone and omnisufficiente
sauiour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106825_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16590</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3496</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106825</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the Christian reader,
Iohn Bradforde wyssheth the
true knowledge and peace of Iesus Christ,
oure alone and omnisufficiente
sauiour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon of repentaunce, made by Iohn Bradforde</title>
                 <author>Bradford, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wight (Wyght, Wayght, Whyte?), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the Christian reader,
Iohn Bradforde wyssheth the
true knowledge and peace of Iesus Christ,
oure alone and omnisufficiente
sauiour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat and heauie
is Goddes anger agaynst
vs, as the moste greuous
plague of the death of our
late kynge (a prince of all
that euer was sithen chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes
ascention into heauen
in anye region pereles)
nowe fallen vpon vs, doth pronosticate. For
when Goddes iudgemente hath begonne wyth
his chylde thus oure deare dearlynge, let other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
thynke as they can, I surelye cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swaded
otherwyse, but that a greuous and byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
cuppe of Goddes vengeaunce is readye to be
powred oute for vs Englyshmen to drynke of.
The whelpe God hath beaton to fraye the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dogge.<note place="margin">1. Pe. ii<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
Iudgement is begonne at Gods house.
In Goddes mercye to hym wardes he is taken
awaye, that his eyes shulde not see, the miseries
we shall fele:<note place="margin">Heb. xi.</note> he was to good to tarrye with vs
so wycked, so frowarde, so peruerse, so obstinate,
so malicious, so hypocriticall, so couetous, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,
vntrue, prowde, carnall. &amp;c, a generation.
I wyll not goe about to paynte vs oute in oure
coulours. All the worlde which neuer saw En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande,
by heare saye seeth England. God by his
plagues and vengeaunce I feare me wyll paynt
<pb facs="3"/>
vs oute, and poynte vs oute▪ we haue so mocked
with hym and his Gospell, that we shall feele it
is no bourdyng w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> him. Of longe tyme we haue
couered our couetousnes &amp; carnalitie, vnder the
cloke of his Gospell, so that all men shall see vs
to oure shame▪ when he shall take his Gospell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye,
and geue it to a people that wyll brynge
forth the frutes of it, then shal we appeare as we
be. To let his Gospell tary with vs, he can not,
for we despyse it, contempne it, are glutted with
it, we disdayne his Manna, it is but a vyle meat
thynke we: we woulde be agayne in Egypt, and
syt by the greasy fleshe pottes, to eate agayne our
garlike, onions, and leekes. Sithen Gods gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
came amongest vs, we saye now we had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
plentye,<note place="margin">Ie. x<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iiij</note> therefore agayne let vs goe and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shyp
the quene of heauen.<note place="margin">Hie. vij.</note> Chyldren begynne to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gather
stickes, the fathers kyndle the fyer, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
wemen make the cakes to offer to the quene of
heauen, and to prouoke the lorde to anger. The
earth can not abyde now the wordes &amp; sermous
of Amos:<note place="margin">Am. vij.</note> the cause of all rebellion is Amos and
his preaching,<note place="margin">Act. xvij</note> It is Paul and his felowes, that
makes all out of order. Summa, the Gospell is
nowe <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
the outcaste and curse of the realme: and
so are the preachers, therfore out of the doores w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
them. So that I saye, God can not let his Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
tary w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vs, but must nedes take it away to do
vs some pleasure therein, for so shall we thynke
for a tyme:<note place="margin">Gen. xix.</note> as the Sodomitanes thought when
Lot departed from them,<note place="margin">Gen. vi.</note> as the old world thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght
when Noe crept into his arcke: as the Iero
solomytances thought when the apostles wente
thence to Peltis. Thē were they mery, thē was
<pb facs="3"/>
all pastyme:<note place="margin">Ex. xxxij.</note> When Moyses was absente, then
went they to eatynge and drynkynge, and rose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne
to playe. Then was al peace, al was wel,
nothynge amysse. But alas, sodenlye came the
floude and drowned them, the fyer and burnte
them vp, Titus and besieged them, Gods wrath
waxed hote agaynst them. Then was weale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye,
mournynge and woe: then was cryenge
out, wringing of handes, renting of clothes, sob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byng
and sighynge for the miseries fallen, out of
the whiche they coulde not scape. But oh you
morners &amp; cryers out: ye renters of clothes, why
mourne you: what is the cause of your mysery?
The Gospell is gone, goddes word is lytle prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched,
you were not disquieted with it? Noe trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bleth
you not, Lot is departed, the apostles are
gone? what now is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cause of these your miseri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es?
Wyll you at y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> length confesse it is your sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?
Naye now it is to late. God called vpō you
and you would not heare hym, therfore yell and
crye out now, for he wyl not heare you: You bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
your eares from hearyng of Gods law, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
your prayer is execrable. But to come again
to vs Englishmen, I fear me I say, for oure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes
sake, for our impietie and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
as God hath taken awaye our kinge, so wil
he take awaye his gospel: yea so we would haue
it, then shoulde all be well thinke manye. Wel, if
he take that awaye, for a tyme perchance we shal
be quyet, but at length we shall fele the want to
our woe, at length he wyll haue at vs, as at So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
at Ierusalem▪ and other places. And now
he begineth to brew such a brewing, wherin one
of vs is like to destroy an other, &amp; so make an opē
gappe for forren enemies to deuoure vs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy
vs. The father is against the sonne, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="4"/>
agaynste the brother. And lorde w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> what cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science?
Oh be thou merciful voto vs, &amp; in thyne
anger remember thy mercy, suffre thy selfe to be
intreated, be reconciled vnto vs, naye reconcyle
vs vnto the. Oh thou god of iustice, iudge iustly
oh thou sonne of God which camest to destroy y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
workes of Sathan,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Ioh. iij</note> destroye his furoures nowe
smokinge, and almooste sette on fyre in this
real me. We haue synned, we haue sinned, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
art thou angrye. Oh be not angrye for euer.
Geue vs peace, peace, peace, in the lorde, Set vs
to warre against synne, against Sathan, against
our carnall desyres, and geue vs the vyctory this
waye. This victorye we obtayn by fayth. This
fayth is not without repentaunce, as hir gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
vssher before hyr. Before hir. I say in discer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge
true fayth from false fayth, lyppe fayth,
Englishmens fayth: for els it sprynges oute
of true fayth. This vssher then of repentaunce, if
we trulye possessed, we shoulde be certayne of
true fayth, and so assured of the victorye ouer
death, hell, and Sathan: his workes then which
he hath styrred vp, woulde quayle: God woulde
restore vs politike peace, ryght should be right &amp;
haue ryght, Gods Gospel should tarry with vs,
religion shuld be cherished, superstition suppres<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed,
and so we yet somethynge happye, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge
the great losse of our moste graciouse
liege soueraygne Lorde. All these woulde come
to passe you see, yf the gentleman vssher I spake
of, I meane repentaunce, were at ynne with vs.
As if he be absēt, we may be certayn y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lady faith
is absent, wherfore we cā not but be vanquished
of the world, the flesh, and the deuyll, and so will
Sathans workes prosper though not in al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges,
to bleare our eyes, yet in that thinge which
<pb facs="4"/>
the most of all desyreth. Therfore to repentaunce
for our selues priuatelye, and for the realme and
churche publikely eueryone shoulde laboure to
styrre vp both oure selues &amp; others. This, to the
ende, that for my parte I myghte helpe, I haue
presently put forth a sermon of repētaunce, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
hath lyen by me halfe a yeare at the leaste, for
the most parte of it. For the laste sommer as I
was abroade preachynge in the countreye, my
chaunce was to make a sermon of repentaunce
the whiche was earnestlye of diuerse desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
of me, that I shoulde geue it them written
or els put it forth in prynt. The whiche thynge
to graunte, as I coulde not (for I had not wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
it) so I told them that had so earnestlye desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
it. But when no naye woulde serue, but I
muste promyse them to wryte it as I coulde: I
consented to their requeste that they shuld haue
it at my leasure. This leasure I prolonged so
longe, that as I wene I offended them, so didde
I please my selfe, as one more gladde to reade
other mennes wrytynges, then in suche sorte to
publyshe my wrytynges for other men to reade,
not that I wolde others not to profyt by me: but
that I knowing how short my suppellex &amp; store
as, woulde be loth for the enemies to haue iuste
occasion of euyll speakynge and wrestinge that
whiche symplye is spoken. But when I consy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
this present tyme, to occasion men now to
loke vpon all thinges in suche sorte as myghte
moue them to Godlynes, rather then to anye cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouse
questioninge, I for the satisfienge of my
promyse, and profytinge of the simple ignoraunt
and rude, haue nowe caused this Sermon to be
prynted, the which I beseche God for his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes
sake, to vse as a meane whereby of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb facs="5"/>
it maye please hym to worke in me and manye
others true hartye repentaunce for oure synnes,
to the glorye of hys name. Thus fare thou
well in the Lorde. The. xij. of Iulie.
Anno. M. D. LIII,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>