<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Rogers, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106572_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3733</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106572</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods treasurie displayed: or, the promises, and threatnings of Scripture, &amp;c : Methodically composed, for the helpe of weake memories: and contrived into question, and answere, for the comfort of Sions mourners, and for the awakening of the Laodicean-like secure</title>
                 <author>Bridges, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Clifton, Fulke</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 550, 2 pages, folding table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the Lord in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, of his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and mercy hath left vnto vs his poore people on ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th, his holy &amp; bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed word, to be a light to our feet, and a Lanthorne to our paths, which is able to make vs wise to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and absolute to every good worke, to guide vs well and safely through this dangerous world, and to bring vs home to himselfe at the last in peace: And hath given vs charge to <hi>search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> as they <hi>that testifie of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rist Iesus,</hi> and in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch <hi>wee looke to haue Eternall life,</hi> and that it should dwell plenteously in vs in all <hi>wisdome,</hi> and hath given vnto vs in this Land peaceable, and happy times af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording vs leaue, and opportunity to exercise
<pb facs="5"/> our selues in the same, yet such is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame folly, and sinfulnesse of the heart of man, that the most part of people cumber themselues about many things; profits, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures lusts, or any thing, and neglect that one thing that is necessary, few chusing the <hi>good part, that neuer shall bee taken</hi> from them that haue it, but spend their time, and strength of affection vpon fading vanities, that will leaue them without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in their greatest need; having a <hi>price in their hand to get wisedome</hi> (which is farre beter than all pearles) but <hi>haue no hart,</hi> nor doe vnderstand the things that belong to their peace, in this day of their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitation. Wherefore as the Lord may take vp the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke complaint against vs, as hee did against his Israel long agoe: <hi>(Hos. 8.12.)</hi> That hee had written vnto them the great things of his Law, but <hi>they had counted them a strange thing:</hi> so may he also haue a Controversy against vs, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them: <hi>(Hos. 4.1.2.)</hi> For that there is <hi>no mercy, nor truth, nor knowledge of God in the Land,</hi> for the generality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="6"/> too true with vs. And therefore he may iustly take away the Gospell of the Kingdome frō vs, &amp; giue it to thē that will more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly esteeme it, make better vse, &amp; bring forth more fruit of the same: <hi>(Math. 27.43)</hi> And send vs a <hi>Famine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ot of bread, and thirst of water,</hi> but of that <hi>bread of life,</hi> the good word of God, that Spirituall Manna, so much loathed or at least so little regarded: <hi>(Amos, 8.11.12.)</hi> Yet as our gracious and good God forbeareth this sinfull, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull Nation, with admirable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable patience beyond expectation, so ceaseth he not by many meanes to bring vs to a greater care and Conscience of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this behalfe of exercising our selues (I meane) in his most blessed and good word; partly sending vs of later yeares, many Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictians, and Crosses, and dayly threatning more, that finding trouble and sorrow in the world, we might be glad to seeke Comfort in God, and in his blessed word. He calles on vs also heereto by the daily Ministery of his Servants the Prophets, together with their holy bookes and writings. And that
<pb facs="6"/> no meanes might be left vntried to doe vs good, or leaue vs without excuse, loe here to you which are the people of God, how hee hath raised vp one from among your selues, of the common order of men (a priuate Christian I meane) for your Conviction, for your Instruction. To convince you how much wisedome and vnderstanding may be obtayned euen of priuate pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sons, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, and painefull Reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ioyned with a diligent attendance on the publike ministery of the word: as may well appeare by this worthy worke that this Author presenteth vnto you: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the humble, and wellminded Readers may be whetted on to the like diligence in the Scriptures, which heere they shall see, and that not without hope of attaining that which may be worthy of Iheir paines, that so they may become wise and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dtrstanding Christians. For want of which, it proves a great <hi>fault</hi> euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the better sort of people, that they hold the points of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the mouth of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,
<pb facs="7"/> and not from the voice of God in the Scriptures, and so build, as if but a Foxe runne vpon it hee shall breake downe their stony wall. If one of like parts, and place shall teach the contrary they will bee shaken and ready to bee removed especially if hee bee backt with Authority: whereas if every Truth he holds in Religion, hee had it well grounded on a plaine testimony of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, two or three, he should not bee moued with every wind of contrary Doctrine, but stand firme, and vnmoueable as Mount <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and having withall the loue of the Truth in his heart, all the men, and meanes in the world could, nor should not remoue him from his stedfastnesse, which is the honour of a Christian endeed.</p>
   <p>And this wisedome, skill and ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ty, every man may see by this his worke, to bee in the Author of this Booke, who hath brought foorth so innumerable places of Scripture for his severall purposes, with that soundnesse of Iudgement, singular dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, and great vnderstanding, as is not to be expected from a private Christian. But
<pb facs="7"/> hee having beene a dayly hearer of the word, and that from Zealous and fruitfull Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, having made vse also of the same with great d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gence, and constancy in his Fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly; and besides these, spent very much time in private reading and study, hee hath obtained a great degree in the Faith, and is higher by head and shoulders, (as it is said of <hi>SAVL</hi>) than the rest of his owne ranke.</p>
   <p>For I count that Interpretation and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the sense of Scriptures as it is a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, so a peculiar worke to the Ministers of God (ordinarily) and not to be adventured vpon by Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ans in their Families, or private meetings, any further than they haue good bottome from that which they haue learned by the Ministery of the Word, nor to write such Bookes as this, wherein is occasion of the vse of so much Scripture, least there should be found many mistakings therein, which were both sinfull and dangerous, and yet most likely. But God hath very mercifully guided this Author, in this his worke, which may, and I hope will be of much fruitfull and good vse in
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
         <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/> the Church of God: For as it may helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinary Christian, yea or Minister with more paralell places, than may bee hee would haue at hand of himselfe, so it will helpe well to the vnderstanding of many places of Scriptures, seeing heere, in what sense, and to what purposes they are brought and applyed. The paines hath beene very great no doubt to one man, but if the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit may be much, and good to many, and so God be glorified, the Author no doubt, will thinke his labour happily bestowed, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly rewarded, which is my great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and humble and earnest prayer also, who is the true, though weake, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant of the Church of God,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN ROGERS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>