<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A BRIEFE VIEVV OF the sfe, and vertues of the Authour.</title>
           <author>P., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106820_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16562</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3468</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106820</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A BRIEFE VIEVV OF the sfe, and vertues of the Authour.</title>
                 <author>P., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Remaines of that reverend and famous postiller, Iohn Boys, Doctor in Divinitie, and late Deane of Canterburie : Containing sundry sermons; partly, on some proper lessons vsed in our English liturgie: and partly, on other select portions of holy Scripture</title>
                 <author>Boys, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Robinson, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 189, that is 192, 191-293, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A BRIEFE VIEVV OF the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>fe, and vertues of <hi>the Authour.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ive mee leaue to put thee in mind, (because I knovv thou art not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of it,) that <hi>Man,</hi> notwithstanding hee hath but a dolefull <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse</hi> into the world, and a miserable <hi>Progresse</hi> in this world, yet can scarce brooke (if natures Statute could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed) a willing <hi>Egresse,</hi> out of the world. And I thinke it a reason suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, because while wee are alive; wee thinke, <hi>A liuing dogge better then a dead Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 9. 4.</note> From whence this inbred desire of <hi>Man</hi> proceeds to labour so much, for the
<pb facs="3"/>
continuance of this <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Oh sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> mee a</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal., 9. 13.</note>
      <hi>little,</hi> saith <hi>Dauid, before I goe hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> being loath to loose an haires bredth of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Spanne,</hi> allotted vnto him; And that being, which nature denies in our selues, we desire may be continued in those that spring from our loyns, from whence <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> called <hi>Mariage,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>A deuice to bring Immortalitie into the world;</hi> thus good<note place="margin">1. Sam 1.</note>
      <hi>Hann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h</hi> seekes for a <hi>Samuel,</hi> with teares,<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>0. 4.</note> and impatient <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>el</hi> was earnest for children, whose birth afterward cost her her owne life; And yet though wee in our selues, and in our children, which are our <hi>Images,</hi> pay Nature her <hi>Tribute;</hi> Yet stil we draw on the line of life, by a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Succession, and when wee cannot be thus much beholding to <hi>Nature;</hi> but that there must bee some <hi>Barren Mount,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1 21.</note> like that of <hi>Gilboa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> vpon which the <hi>Deaw of Heaven falls not,</hi> Yet then wee devise other Artificiall meanes, for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. Sam. 18. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> of our memories; Thus <hi>Absalom</hi> will haue his <hi>Pillar</hi> reared in the Kings dale; <hi>Dixerat enim non est mihi filius,</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="3"/>
the curse of the wicked man, that his name shall be as <hi>rottennes, and dung vpon the earth, and his memory cleane put out,</hi> But for the righteous, they shall be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d in <hi>Euerlasting remembrance:</hi> Of such men<note place="margin">Psal. 112. 6.</note> speaketh the sonne of <hi>Syrach, Their bodies</hi>
      <note place="margin">ecclus. 44 14.</note>
      <hi>are buried in peace, but their name liueth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, The people spea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e of their wisedome, and the congregation talke of their praise.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Amongst which men, I may (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice to any) ranke a worthy and famous <hi>Diuine</hi> of our age, <hi>Mr. Iohn Boyse, Dr. in Diuinity,</hi> and sometimes <hi>Deane</hi> of the <hi>Metropolitical</hi> Church of <hi>Canterbury, who being dead, yet speakes;</hi> And why terme I him dead? <hi>Numquid enim non vivitur? uti{que} et beatè; visus est oculis insipientium mori, ille autem vivit in pace:</hi> One indeed that hath discharged natures debt; <hi>Et non est illi filius,</hi> He hath no child to continue his name here among vs, yet hee reared him else, while he was aliue, A <hi>Pillar in the Kings dale,</hi> He that was <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>lumna spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> called <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>) a brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>Pillar,</hi> hath left behind him a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument
<pb facs="4"/>
of his fame, which Time cannot deface, nor the rotten tooth of <hi>Enuy</hi> euer obliterate; At whose death some <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed Stones</hi> were found, which now the Presse hath fitted, for the inlarging of his former building.</p>
   <p>And hath hee had all this care for vs? A thankefull heart will be desiring with<note place="margin">2 King. 4. 13.</note>
      <hi>Elisha, what we shall doe for him?</hi> The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thē that followed our Sauiour from <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>le,</hi> will bee a good patterne, who (though the good <hi>Arimathean</hi> had decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Luke. 23 35.</note> enterred the body of our <hi>Sauiour</hi>) could not be content till they had prepared, and brought their odours to the Sepulchre; In like manner, though his louing wife hath done as much for him, as <hi>Iaacob</hi> dif for<note place="margin">Gen 35. 20.</note> his <hi>Rachel,</hi> set a Pillar vpon his graue; Yet would I, who had no small share in his loue, present some Odours, and I would be as willing to beg, as I am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to buy some of the sonne of <hi>Syrachs Perfume,</hi> made by the hand of a skilfull <hi>Apothecary,</hi> If this <hi>Alabaster boxe of spikenard,</hi> had not beene so lately broken, so that the
<pb facs="4"/>
smell is not yet gone; It shall suffice then for my part, to rub a little the spices, that grew in this pleasant garden, and leaue the sequel to your Christian discretion, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering both the custome, and vse of such like <hi>Panegyricks, quibus ipsi grati sumus er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga mortuos, et ipsi de vita nostra cautiores,</hi> The first commanded by the sonne of <hi>Syrach,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ecclus. 7.</note>
      <hi>Mortuo non negabis gratiam,</hi> the other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by him, as profitable for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,<note place="margin">44▪ 16.</note> saying, that <hi>Enoch was translated for an example of repentance, to the generations;</hi> Concerning whose life, we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter set it downe, by answering the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauids</hi> three interrogatories, <hi>What am I? and what is my life? and what is the family of my father in Israel?</hi> The resolution of these three <hi>Quaeres,</hi> concerning this party, shall end this discourse; beginning with the last.</p>
   <p>He was borne at <hi>Eythorne,</hi> a village in <hi>East-kent,</hi> a place wherein, as he sucked his first breath, so there he vented his last gaspe; A place for ayre, (if the purenesse of it adde any helpe to ingenuitie,) that
<pb facs="5"/>
sure the pleasant temperature of it yeelded some furtherāce to his sweet &amp; witty dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, whose fathers house, was not lik the <hi>Prophet Isayes Casula in deserto;</hi> Nor was he takē with <hi>Dauid from the sheepfolds,</hi> But hee sprang from a worthy &amp; ancient family, and who knows not that <hi>Gemma in Auro,</hi> whē the precious <hi>Gemms</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> are set and placed in a golden nature, they must needes giue a goodly luster? <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ sayd <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides in Hecuba,</hi> and the tree may easily be discerned by the fruite; as <hi>S Basil</hi> speakes well, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, The Parents worth best knowne, by their care, in bringing vp their children, and therefore <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Theage,</hi> professed, that hee knew not vpon what any one thing a wise man could better bestow his best endeauours; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, then that his sonne should grow vp to the height of virtue and goodnes, hence was this and another Oliue branch, springing from the same root, transplanted into the famous Nursery of good literature, the <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersity</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> wherein they grew to that Maturity and ripenesse, that the one was fit for any honour in the <hi>Church,</hi> the other for any imploiment in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;</hi> so that I may truly say of them, as the <hi>Hystorian</hi> of <hi>Anthemus,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>The second Question is, <hi>What am I?</hi> If any had asked so much while hee was aliue, I know his modest soule, would haue replyed with the <hi>Prophet Dauid, I</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal▪ 22 6.</note>
      <hi>am a worme, and no man;</hi> his humility and meekenesse of mind, did witnesse no lesse: Those two vertues which St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
      <note place="margin">Serm. de assumpt.</note> tells vs, are <hi>Collactaneae▪</hi> like the poore man, and his one only sheepe in <hi>Nathans</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam 12.</note> Parable, they are nourished vp together, they eate of the same morsels, and drinke of the same cup, both which manifest themselues by the same meanes, so that we may easily guesse where they dwell, if wee find in any man these three pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, that there is; <hi>In vultu serenitas, in opere gratia, in corde ad omnes dulcedo.</hi> (As the same father speaketh) there is true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,
<pb facs="6"/>
and lowlinesse of mind; which, whosoeuer knew him, knew well to bee in him, vvhich made him not an ordinary man; (Though <hi>Trismegistus</hi> boasts much of that priviledge of nature, making man no lesse then a miracle) but as <hi>Melancthon</hi> esteemed <hi>Luther, Miraculum inter homines,</hi> hauing as many vertues cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched together, in that little house of clay, as was almost possible for that fraile ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell to containe: Neither was he <hi>Angusti oris Uasculum,</hi> a straight mouthd vessell, as vvilling to retaine to himselfe, vvhat vvas due to others, wee know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that the streames of his goodnesse, flowed abroad plentifully, to the refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many a dry &amp; barren land, where no water was, so that there were in his time, and yet are few soules in our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church,</hi> that taste not of his brookes that ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne in the way. Hee needed not in a fearefull iealousie, haue asked them about him, <hi>Whom, or what men doe say that I am? Loquatur invidia;</hi> I dare trust this <hi>Daniel</hi> amongst such lyons, whose
<pb facs="6"/>
mouthes sure his goodnesse would stop, being truly such a man, as <hi>Dyon</hi> reports <hi>of Marke Anthony,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, a constant man, no change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and his constancy was grounded vpon a good foundation, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> such a man he was of whom that Noble <hi>Elogie</hi> which <hi>Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> gaue to <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> may with some moderation, I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>re say truely, in part bee applied to him, <hi>Fuit Ecclesiasticae Dictionis Tullius, Sacrae Theologiae Homerus, Rationum Fidei Aristotles, Authoritatis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicae Petrus, et in Christiano Pulpito Paulus.</hi> Only for mine owne sake, and for my Brethrens sake, of the <hi>Linnen E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod,</hi> I must take vp S. <hi>Bernards</hi> wish vpon the death of <hi>Malachy,</hi> the <hi>Irish Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, Vtinam sic nos post trahat, vt pertrahat in tam recenti virtutum eius adore avidius, alacrius{que} currentes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And now the last <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>uaere</hi> comes in, which cannot well bee distinguished from the second; <hi>What is my life?</hi> It is easily answered, being nothing else, but
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, And I will make it as briefely a compendium of so large a Volume as I can.</p>
   <p>His parents as they gaue him <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, so they were not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the chiefe, and last thing which the <hi>Philosopher</hi> requires at Parents hands, which is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> a care to bring him vp in instruction, and information of the Lord; So that after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e had sucked the milke, vvhich the lesser schooles afford; for imitating of youth in the countrey, he was sent to the <hi>Vniuersity,</hi> where in due time by his paines and proficiency, he was made <hi>Candidate,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>of Artes,</hi> After vvhich honour, hee thinkes not presently, (as many doe) that hee was come, ad <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, to his perfection; nor stayes hee there long deliberating, what profession he should take vpon him, (as many <hi>Vniuersity</hi> men doe, whose distract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed studies, hinders their proficiency,) but betakes himselfe to the study of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, for the attaining of which hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly knowledge, he vsed the best means
<pb facs="7"/>
both for his entrance into his course of study, as also for his proceeding therein; procuring the acquaintance, and after gaining the heart of a famous <hi>Professour in Diuinitie,</hi> then, and after a most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and eminent <hi>Prelate</hi> of this land, <hi>Dr. Ouerall,</hi> Who like a good <hi>Palinure,</hi> taught him the way hovv to become a skilfull Steeres-man, in the little barke of Gods Church.</p>
   <p>And hauing once tasted the sweetnes of this hony, as <hi>Ionathan</hi> did, but with the typpe of his rod; hee would not giue ouer, till hee had gotten Saint <hi>Pauls</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1 13.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that plat-forme of sound Doctrine, which after made him famous; Which well did witnesse his paines in reading Sacred Scripture, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsing the <hi>Fathers, Schoole-men,</hi> and what else might make him, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, more serious he was at his booke, then <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> of whom <hi>Aelian</hi> reports, that hee did<note place="margin">De v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r. hist. lib. 13.</note> but <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>extremit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tes fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum comeder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> For hee was rather <hi>Hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>o Librorum,</hi> eating whole r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ules (with the
<pb facs="8"/>
Prophet of Sacred learning; When he had gathered his <hi>Omer</hi> full of <hi>Manna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> at the Schooles of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> then he leaues the <hi>Vniversitie,</hi> thinking it high time to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribute that hony, which like a labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Bee,</hi> hee had gathered in the garden of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> So that his countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, at his returne, needed not to haue asked that question, for the time past, which the Spouse doeth for the present <hi>Tell mee, O thou whom our soules loue, where</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cant. 1▪ 6.</note>
      <hi>hast thou f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>dde?</hi> Because they might easily discerne; bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>h where, and how hee had fed; for as <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ctetus</hi> telleth vs, how wee may know by tvvo infallible tokens, <hi>Quantum ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s comed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rint, viz Lana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t Lacte,</hi> So might they easily guesse, <hi>Quantum hic Gregis Aries,</hi> (as <hi>Augustine</hi> calles such as<note place="margin">Epistola 89.</note> he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>) <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Lana &amp; Lacte,</hi> by his skarlet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eece, a robe of the greatest ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that his Mother <hi>Vniversitie</hi> could bestow vpon him; and that plenteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of milke▪ which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ad gotten by his choice and of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n feeding, in <hi>Dauids</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eene Pastures, by the still waters; which
<pb facs="8"/>
hee as freely distributed to others, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee receiued, for hauing a priuate charge of his ovvne in the countrey, there hee spent much time, feeding his ovvne flocke at home, by his continuall preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto them, and others also, when he began <hi>Fauos facere,</hi> to make his ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>y combe, that sweete booke of his <hi>Postill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> whose sweetenesse as it giues repast to many painefull Bees, so contrary to his intention feedes some idle droanes in our Mother Church.</p>
   <p>And here (if the boundes of a preface would permit) I might set foorth a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of his vertues, seeing by this time he vvas come to his full Maturity, and ripenesse; reckoning his vertues <hi>Naturall</hi> as a <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>Morall</hi> as a <hi>Good man,</hi> or <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall,</hi> as a <hi>Religious man,</hi> or <hi>Pastorall</hi> as a <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Ministeriall man,</hi> commending him for them, as <hi>Melancthon</hi> doth <hi>Luther,</hi> for his learning, <hi>Pomeranus est Grāmaticus, ego sum Logicus, Iustus Ionas et Orator, sed Lutherus est omnia in omnibus;</hi> So was hee for his vertues, <hi>All the fresh springs</hi> they
<pb facs="9"/>
were in him, He had purposed to spend himselfe, and end his dayes in priuat, had not his countreyes loue, especially the Gentries care, drawen him out of this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate course of life, not leauing him till they see him at the sterne of <hi>Christs Church</hi> in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> whereof hee liued and died a loving, and carefull <hi>Deane;</hi> The greatest part of which worthy society, can yet witnesse his paines in preaching every weeke▪ if not at his owne charge, yet there where was more need, his deuotion in frequenting publique prayers, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy in his studies; his studious vigilancy for the publike affaires, both of the <hi>Church</hi> &amp; the <hi>Common wealth;</hi> So that hee might with as little Ostentation, haue spoken of himselfe, as <hi>Luther</hi> did of himselfe, <hi>Ego sum oneratiss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>mus, psalterium exigit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum hominem, totum eundem Concio ad Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum, totum preculae &amp; instituti m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>i cultus, totum negotio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>um alienorum occupatio;</hi> I am burdened more then any man my paines in my Pesth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ls▪ require a whole man, My Preaching to the people, a whole man,
<pb facs="9"/>
My priuate and publique deuotions, a whole man; common affaires belonging to my place in the Church, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, a whole man: So that I may compare his life to such an one as <hi>S Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> wished <hi>Eudoxius</hi> the <hi>Abbot</hi> to lead, <hi>Inter ignem et Aquam, Inter Apicem, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biae</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epistola. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>1.</note>
      <hi>et voraginem Desidiae,</hi> Neither incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Pride on the right hand, nor idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse on the left; Wheresoeuer he liued, leauing some remarkeable token of his goodnesse; Witnesse his mother <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> who will still remember him as truely for his learning as <hi>Trithemius</hi> did for <hi>Algerus: Vir fuit in sanctis Scripturis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> studio exercitatus, veterum quo{que} Lectione Diues, at{que} in Secularibus literis magnifice doctus, ingenio cautus et disertus eloquio▪</hi> And for his life, the like Testimony may be easily procured, that there was none in the <hi>Vniversity</hi> more obseruant of Order, Habit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>xercises, both publique and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate; I haue heard it from his owne mouth, (and hee had, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) that he neuer missed publique Sermon at St.
<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>Maries,</hi> during all the time of his abode there, saue twice; I am loath to defile mine owne nest, Yet I feare, <hi>Aetas Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, peior Avis tulit nos nequiores:</hi> Witnesse likewise the Church in generall, for whom willingly hee would haue spent himselfe; so that few are left behind, but are loosers by his death, Heauen only a gainer, in whose blessed mansions hee now rests, fully satisfied with the melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious harmony of that <hi>Supernall Quire,</hi> Part of which musicke I thinke he heard before he departed this life, for the night before he dyed, all his discourse was of musicke, and being demanded whether he heard any, or what musicke he meant, his answere was; <hi>O Gabriel, Gabriel,</hi> Sure the blessed Choristers of Heauen, were ready to carry his soule with ioy into his Masters ioy.</p>
   <p>I will conclude with him, as <hi>S▪ August▪</hi> concerning his deare beloued, <hi>Nebridius▪ Nunc vivit in sinu Abrahae Boysius meus, dulcis amicus meus, nam quis alius tali animae Locus?</hi> My deare friend now rests in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
bosome, for sure there is no othe place for so Diuine a soule.</p>
   <p>Thus gentle Reader haue I giuen thee a short suruey of the life of him, whom perhaps thou knewest (though not in his person) yet in his workes; If I haue come short of what his desert might iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenge, (as the relation of <hi>Salomon</hi> did to the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi>) I must craue craue pardon for my weakenesse in this kind, it being thanke worthy for him that hath no better <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or if I haue shot my few arrowes ouer the marke with <hi>Ionathan,</hi> I shall be well content with <hi>S. Augustines</hi> censure vpon <hi>Tully,</hi> for his large commendations of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi> (So it may bee with his glosse) <hi>Dicebat hoc tam Magnus Laudator, aut tam Magnus Adulator sed si Laudator talem noverit, si au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem adulator talem esse debere ostendebat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To conclude, if this last worke of his, finde but that acceptation with thee, which vttered <hi>Viva Voce,</hi> it gaue to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, or if this, <hi>Prol s Posthuma</hi> haue but some resemblance with his former off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring,
<pb facs="11"/>
that it be not thought altogether Spurious, I doubt not but thou wilt bee easily induced together with mee, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that haue bene bettered by the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly example, and heauenly labours of this holy man, to glorifie the <hi>Author of euery good and perfit gift,</hi> who will not cease to raise vp such excellent instruments for his owne glory, and the Churches good: To whose blessed Protection I commit thee, Euer Resting▪</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in what hee may R. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>