<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Practitioner.</title>
           <author>Porter, Walter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106103_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09858</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20124.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106103</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Practitioner.</title>
                 <author>Porter, Walter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Madrigales and ayres : Of two, three, foure and fiue voyces, with the continued base, with toccatos, sinfonias and rittornellos to them. After the manner of consort musique. To be performed with the harpesechord, lutes, theorbos, base violl, two violins, or two viols. Published by Walter Porter, one of the gentlemen of his Maiesties royall chappell</title>
                 <author>Porter, Walter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 104 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_performer">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Practitioner.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>GEntle</hi> Practitioner, I haue boldly aduentred to publish these Madrigals and Ayres; thou mayst blame my presumption, yet thou canst not, if there be any goodnesse in thee, blame my intention and end, which is no other, but by this meanes to be free from burying that poore talent which God hath giuen me; and by this little, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his great goodnesse, and my will, if I had greater abilitie: and to expresse in some meane manner my thankfulnesse vnto my Noble and worthy Friends, which, if they like any of them, I shall acknowledge my selfe well satisfied for all my labour and charge; if they come to any of your hands, before you censure (which I know you will, and they that vnderstand least most sharply) let me intreate you to play and sing them true, according to my meaning, or heare them done so; not in steed of singing, to howle or bawle them, and scrape in steed o playing, and performe them falsly and say they are naught; In so doing if they were nere so good, you'd spoyle them; for I must tell you, a Composer, when he hath set a Song with all the art he can, hath done but halfe the worke, the other halfe is the well performing or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing that in singing or playing which he hath done in composing, howsoeuer I now must be content, yet thus I could wish it; I haue exprest in the part of the <hi>Harpsechord,</hi> the <hi>maior</hi> and <hi>minor</hi> sixses, by Flats and Sharpes, the figures I haue put ouer the head of euery Note as neere as I could, I haue made the singing Base also a thorow Base, in which you are not to sing but where there are words or this signe {repeat} of Repetition; in the Songs which are set forth with Diuision, where you find many Notes in a place after this manner <gap reason="music">
         <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
      </gap> in rule or space, they are set to expresse the <hi>Trillo:</hi> I have made vse of these <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> words, because they shall not mistake, and sing them, if they were expressed in English, being mixed amongst the other wordes, <hi>Tace</hi> which is, that the Voyces or Instruments, are to be silent, or hold their peace, till such or such things be performed, also the word <hi>forte,</hi> which is strong or loud, I haue set before most of the Songs, <hi>Toccatos, Sinfonias,</hi> and <hi>Rittornellos,</hi> which besides the delight and varietie they beget, they are good for the respiration of the Voyce, for which end they are vsed; Thus much I thought good to certifie thee; what shall be wanting as through Bases, for the other Instruments, which is to be vsed to make vp the body of Musicke, according as I haue set downe, thou must take a little paines to write out, as I haue taken a great deale to make them, and to haue them printed, and when thou hast done, let a little Charitie be in a part of thy censure, And I shall striue, if this haue but indifferent acceptation, to doe something for thee more vsefull, till which time and euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>I rest thine in all loue,</salute>
      <signed>Walter Porter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>