<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The summe and graces of Daniel.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106760_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15998</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2785</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106760</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The summe and graces of Daniel.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Daniel his Chaldie visions and his Ebrevv: both translated after the original: and expounded both, by reduction of heathen most famous stories vnto the exact proprietie of his wordes (which is the surest certaintie what he must meane:) and by ioyning all the Bible, and learne tongues to the frame of his worke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Young (Yong), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simson, Gabriel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 4 leaves of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The summe and graces of Daniel.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> telleth what Kingdomes shall oppresse <hi>Dauids</hi> house from <hi>Iudahs</hi> captiuitie vnto the birth of our Lord:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Few wordes containe the whole sūme of Daniel for all his chiefe heads.</hi>
      </note> and endeuour to controll their Religion. Also of our Lord he sheweth: his continuall protection, and payment of his foes, his coming into the world, his making strong the Couenant for all nations, his precious death, his glorious ascention, and his kingdome ouer all nations. And lastly how he will destroy the Citie and Temple, finishing the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie which he gaue by <hi>Moses,</hi> that Iewes and Gentiles may be equally Gods people. Those kingdomes which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> setteth forth, are first the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>What king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel oppresse the religion of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
      </note> who destroyed the Citie, Temple, Kingdome and house of <hi>Salomon</hi>: and meant in Babel to haue set vp idolatrie. The next is a ioynt power of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> who ouerthrew them and would haue made their owne kings as Gods, &amp; stayed the building of Gods Temple, and sought to destroy the Iewes nation. The third is compact of all the States of Greeke-land (who put downe the former): In <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> power, which King in his pride earnestly laboured to be holden as a God: and caused the Leuites to name their sonnes <hi>Alexanders,</hi> and all the Iewes to take their dates from his reigne. The fourth and last, is of the same natiō for their Kings (called <hi>Seleucidae</hi> and <hi>Lagidae,</hi> by the first of their houses) dwelling North and South from <hi>Iuda</hi> situated betwixt them both. By these <hi>Iuda</hi> was most ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, and endeuour vsed to haue abrogated the holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant. At our Lords birth these nations were fully spoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of all gouernement, and<note n="*" place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Romanes, that medled not with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>How euerie kingdome is seuen times spoken of.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> another set vp, to whom tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute was payd ouer all the world. In plentifull varietie <hi>Daniel</hi> setteth them forth. First in a huge image of foure mettals beaten to powder: and he expoundeth the Image so, that by a prophane king he is therefore highly aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Long after he seeth them in a sort fit for a spirituall
<pb facs="7"/>
man to iudge of: in foure sauage beasts cast into the fire: &amp; ioyneth a most heauenly exposition and comfort of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: how from his people, an eternall kingdome shall fill all the earth. Againe, the kingdome of <hi>Babel</hi> is figured by a Tree, touching in height the heauens, in breadth the corners of the earth: and to that also <hi>Daniel</hi> affordeth an exposition. Likewise the other kingdomes are semblanced by a Ramme and Goat-bucke, and both in sundrie hornes: and now all the Nations are plainly named,<note place="margin">
         <hi>This vision should haue cut off all doubt for Daniels king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domes. This special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly might end all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie.</hi>
      </note> who be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained. So sixe times euery one State is declared all ouer, the later declarations adding clearenesse to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Moreouer, the seuenth Narration most plaine (as teaching in proper language) is not wanting: for the coming vp, idolatrie chastisement, and ouerthrow of these kingdomes. A skilfull Reader must fetch from others the dayly dealings, which the wisedome of God knew at need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse to foretell by <hi>Daniel</hi>: and therefore he passeth them ouer; in their due places the Reader shall find them mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in obseruations vpon the Prophet. The comfort of the holy people is most sweete in this Booke.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The degrees of his visiōs.</hi>
      </note> Christ in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane eyes is a base stone, and heathen Kings goodly met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals: but he beateth them to dust, and becometh a great mountaine. In <hi>Daniels</hi> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en they are beasts cast into fire, and the Sonne of man coming in the clouds into the world: afterwards going vnto the Ancient of dayes, he, sitteth on an eternall throne.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The times 2300 dayes. Chap. 8.</hi>
      </note> Sundry other heauenly apparations <hi>Daniel</hi> hath: as when the wonderfull Numberer (called in <hi>Daniel, Palmoni)</hi> calleth an Angel, <hi>Gabriel:</hi> and biddeth him teach <hi>Daniel</hi> the verie dayes from the first of the rage against <hi>Moses</hi> lawes, vnto the last of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> dealing against the Temple. And after that his senses had bene acquainted with so exact an accompt vnto the very day, for a particular hinderance of the truth, he seeth a hand writing,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Chap. 5. Chap. 9.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>MENE MENE</hi>: and soone the former Angel numbreth most exactly the time vnto
<pb facs="7"/>
our Lords death. And againe, soone after he hath a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion like that of Christ in the <note n="*" place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Chap. 1.13. Chap. 12. Three yeres and half, and dayes 1290 and dayes 1335 al these are, the first from the pol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luting of the holy Temple vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie: the other two: vnto seuerall comforts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Antio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chus: which the present Age should marke, euen to the exact dayes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>The whole summe of Daniel is 600 yeares: frō since the Chaldeans tooke Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem, vntill the Romans toke it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>The tongues of Daniel.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> Reuelation, and of three Angels, one silent, another teaching him the summe of his booke in plain speeches: another asking a question of times, and taking an answer, with the very particular dayes of two famous neare matters. These two confirme the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull accompt of Christ his owne set time for redemptiō. Dan. <hi>9.24.</hi> Farther then which the date of times might not go in the Prophets, beyond the glorifying of the King: but therein it was to rest. By like reuolutions, men might know, that Christ would graunt them the like space to repentance, that they losed not their land: as he gaue in the wildernesse to prepare them that should enter into the land. And so it fell out alike: <hi>40.</hi> yeares they spent in the wildernesse, <hi>40</hi> after our Lords death in the land. And so the whole warning that <hi>Daniel</hi> gaue the Iewes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of their Deluge, is iust in space the same that <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech</hi> gaue to the old world at <hi>Noahs</hi> birth, <hi>600</hi> yeares afore the flood. From <hi>Nebuchadnezers</hi> first yeare, <hi>70</hi> of captiuitie: thence <hi>7</hi> times that space in expressed wordes, layd downe in Scripture, and <hi>40</hi> afterwards not recorded, nor to haue bene recorded in scripture, but marked of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then by the euent. This is the compasse of <hi>Daniels</hi> times: which they that cast not aright, shal be disturbed.</p>
   <p>The state of the world when he wrote, and the tongues vvhich he vsed, call vs to farther admiration. His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie was written in the most distressed times of the world, to be such a iewell, that being seene, it might haue redressed the calamities of those dayes. For, when the kingdome of Iudah was to be plagued by the tust God: all the world was plagued also, with more alterations of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and warres then had bene afore.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The Zohar noteth this, truely and wonderfully</hi>
      </note> And then God by <hi>Daniel</hi> writeth first in the heathens language the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aque or Chaldy tong: which East &amp; South best knew. In that he sheweth how the Image of the worldly pōpe, &amp; all
<pb facs="8"/>
the wicked are made as dust before the winde: and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Empires are as beasts troubling the sea of life:<note place="margin">
         <hi>A generall knowledg of Law &amp; Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is taught in Daniel by kingdomes, many peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing &amp; one standing.</hi>
      </note> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing at the last in a fierie lake: frō the throne of a Iudge euerlasting, with whom there is no shadow of change. Also he telleth of the kingdome that cannot be corrupted, set vp by one like the Sonne of man coming in the cloudes, and going againe vnto the ancient of dayes, to sit for euer in glory. All this, and other matters of the present Age, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> penneth in the language most knowne of any one: that the heathen might be benefited. Notwithstanding the Iewes haue in this worke their prerogatiue. For in the tongue vsed onely of them; he penneth the selfe same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: naming plainly what people he afore spake off, and that in sundrie sortes for exact certaintie. And he limiteth the time,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The phrase of 70 seuens, being cōpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, wil shew that God ruled al times of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah: in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der easie to consider.</hi>
      </note> when all nations should be brought into the holy couenant, in a more wonderfull sweet speech, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent matter, and for the frame of all the Bible, then a mans minde could euer haue thought vpon. Yea though one had an hundred mouthes and an hundred tongues, &amp; a voyce of steele, he should not be able to shew the vse of his two tongues, how plentifull commodities they haue, his <hi>Chaldy</hi> or <hi>Syriaque,</hi> and his <hi>Hebrew.</hi> We haue no <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> saue two Chapters of <hi>Ezra,</hi> so ancient as his by <hi>400.</hi> yeares. And of such as write thence in <hi>Chaldy,</hi> translating the <hi>Hebrew,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Chaldy, Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aque, Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opian, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique: all foure vse Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niels Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aque.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Onkelos</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and the author of <hi>Targum Ierusalemy</hi> vpon the Law, <hi>Ionathan Ben Vziel</hi> vpon the Prophets, and the vncertaine translaters of the other holy bookes, all their workes make great vse of halfe his, the <hi>Chaldy</hi> part: and so doth the Syriaque translater of the New testament continually frequent his style. Neither was the<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Dan.2.26. is in no Chaldy, but in the Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opian. Heb. 2. and 4. &amp;c.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Aethiopian</hi> ignorant of him, or negligent to vse his phrases. Also the <hi>Arabique</hi> Translaters of both Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staments, chalenge as good a part in him as any of the former: And although none, but Linguists, can throughly iudge of this commoditie, yet any man may see what great
<pb facs="8"/>
honour God gaue to the Prophet, that draweth his little <hi>Chaldy</hi> through so many and so large workes of those di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse nations.<note place="margin">
         <hi>A wonderful recompence to the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans for v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Daniel well.</hi>
      </note> Euen as the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> gaue cups of cold water to <hi>Daniel</hi> when he requested it, rather than of the Kings wine, God would not haue them loose their reward: but made that language which they taught him, to haue honour through all the world vnto this day. I omit how his <hi>Chaldy</hi> style teacheth to distinguish old Rabbines in either Talmuds from new, by the tenour of the Grammer, and stirreth iudgement to marke by the style later Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines from the elder. Yet I may not choose but warne somewhat of this. Also in our dayes the Chaldy para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrastes are beholding to him. For whereas they were so confused, that to Grammer of them could be made, the learned <hi>Mercerus</hi> and others after him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Daniels Chaldy cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes new ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in our age: so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall is the holy mans glorie. Elias Leuita mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether the Chaldy could bee brought to Art. That Gordiā knot was cut, by breaking all their vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinty with Daniels sword by our learned Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stians.</hi>
      </note> vowell them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Daniels <hi>Chaldy,</hi> to their great honour, and all wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens contentment. Nowe touching his Hebrew style, wherein he penneth the vision of the Ramme and Goate, his owne heauenly prayer, <hi>Gabriels</hi> speech for the name and office of Christ, containing all skill of knowledge: an heauenly vision of Christ, in holy view, the Hebrew style of all this: and yet more specially for a long oration of the stouter <hi>Persian</hi> kings fall: of great <hi>Alexander,</hi> his rising and fall: his houses rooting out: his Captaines, many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the spoyle, but foure principall: and of them two hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses dealers with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and their particular dealings vnto <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi>: his rage from placing of his Idoll three yeares and an halfe, his falles after the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of that Idoll, one at the day <hi>1290.</hi> another at the day <hi>1335.</hi> his comfort by an argument from the resurrection in all these troubles: this rare matter hath not onely wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but wit for specialty of style; that blasphemous <hi>Porphyry</hi> and all might haue seene more than a mans wit in the Hebrew phrase. Such his matter and languages be. To conclude, we see how in troubles he pictures the cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb facs="9"/>
of the Angels about Christs seruants, what ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies they should haue, and what those should suffer, how and when Christ by him selfe vvould make reconciliation for sinne, and sit on the throne of glorie: how in the most common tongue, the matter is spoken, so farre as men then could quietly accept it: how peculiarly it was spoken for the peculiar persons, and in a peculiar phrase: vvhere the wicked otherwise would haue raged intollerably. And we may see how <hi>Daniel</hi> ioyneth both Testaments, ending the Ceremonies, and breaking the partition vvall of the old: and laying the foundation and groundworke of the New. Also how God (perfect in all knowledge) draweth the Heathen Stories (from <hi>Herodotus</hi> vnto <hi>Liuie</hi>) to be ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants vnto Diuinitie:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prophecies in the East tongues, for matter recor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded in the Westerne, should stirre studie &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of studie for both.</hi>
      </note> that vvhen all the world had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked all the particulars of the Persians and Greekes, fallen out according as it vvas foretold, they might assure them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues, that the matters touching their calling into the heauenly Ierusalem, should be likewise in due time accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished. This much may be holden in some sort the summe of the gracious <hi>Daniel</hi> his Graces: but the thūder of Gods power (as <hi>Iob</hi> speaketh in a like matter) vvho but he in his text, or one of <hi>Daniels</hi> vvisedome is able to declare? Now let vs hasten to his matter: taking by the vvay the Kings of his narrations: and vsing grauē pictures to the pictures of his pen in due place. But by the vvay the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der must be shewed faults of printing.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>