<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣BLE, AND RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, Iohn Lord Bishop of Lin∣colne, Lord Keeper of the great Seale; And one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie COVNCELL: The true Honour of a good Conscience in the Church Militant, and the reward of true Ho∣nour in the Church Triumphant.</title>
           <author>Bourne, Immanuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106813_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16503</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3416</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106813</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣BLE, AND RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, Iohn Lord Bishop of Lin∣colne, Lord Keeper of the great Seale; And one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie COVNCELL: The true Honour of a good Conscience in the Church Militant, and the reward of true Ho∣nour in the Church Triumphant.</title>
                 <author>Bourne, Immanuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of conscience : Or a threefold reuelation of those three most secret bookes: 1. The booke of Gods prescience. 2. The booke of mans conscience. 3. The booke of life. In a sermon preached at the generall assises holden at Derby, in Lent last. 1623. By Immanuel Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, Immanuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 42, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</hi> Lord Keeper of the great Seale; And one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie COVNCELL: The true Honour of a good Conscience in the Church Militant, and the reward of true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Church Triumphant.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O many are the Bills of Complaint <hi>(Right Honorable)</hi> of those who are dayly petitioners vnto your Lordship, for your graue and Conscionable Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters of <hi>Equity,</hi> that there needeth no further testimonie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the Consciences of all those, who mourne for the iniquities of the <hi>Times:</hi> That eyther <hi>Conscience</hi> is fled already from <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>Heauen,</hi> (as it was long since complained of <hi>Iustice</hi>) or else the most of men are euen now <hi>plotting</hi> to banish her out of the world; exercising themselues (contrary to the practice of S. <hi>Paul</hi>) to haue alwayes their <hi>Consciences</hi> not voyd, but full of offences both towards God and towards men. But praised be the Lord of mercy, who hath shewed kindnesse towards his Seruants; and placed your <hi>Honor</hi> as the <hi>Lord-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> of <hi>Conscience,</hi> in these perillous times of her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution.
<pb facs="3"/> Amongst diuers others whose hearts-desire is bent, to manifest their thankefulnesse to God for his Grace already shewed; and to pray for a dayly encrease of happinesse vnto your Lordship: I am emboldened to send this <hi>Anatomie of Conscience,</hi> to be reuiued with the warmth of your Honorable fauour in this cold and frozen Age of the world. It was at first preached before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and worthy <hi>Iustices</hi> of <hi>Assise</hi> for the County of <hi>Derby;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sir Henry Hobart, Sir Edward Bromely.</note> the memory of whose free Approbation (with the rest of that worthy Auditory,) hath since emboldened mee to cast an eie ouer it once againe; and that I might satisfie the desire of some few, to publish it for the benefit of many. And now if it please your Lordship to vouchsafe vnto it a shadow of <hi>Protection;</hi> I shall not cease to pray (in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, as I doe in publike,) That the Lord will so guard you with his glorious <hi>Angels;</hi> &amp; guide you by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his gracious <hi>Spirit;</hi> That all your <hi>Counsels,</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> may tend to the Glory of his holy <hi>Name,</hi> the <hi>Reliefe</hi> and <hi>Comfort</hi> of the <hi>oppressed,</hi> the good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> And thus commending you to the <hi>safe Tuition</hi> of the great <hi>Lord-Keeper</hi> of <hi>Israel,</hi> I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London,</hi>
         <date>Iuly <hi>14. 1623.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble and dutifull Chaplaine IMMANVEL BOVRNE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>