<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the moste high and most vertuous ladie, and our most gracious soueraigne, Mary by the grace of God, Quene of Englande, Fraunce, Naples, Hierusalem, and Irelande, defendour of the fayth, Princesse of Spaigne &amp; Sicilie, Archeduchesse of Austria, Duchesse of Mil∣laine, Burgundie and Brabant, Countesse of Has∣purge, Flaunders and Tyrole. Your Maiesties most faythful, louyng and obedient seruaunt Miles Hogarde, wissheth al grace, long peace, quiet raigne, from God the fa∣ther, the sonne, and the holy Ghost.</title>
           <author>Hogarde, Miles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106229_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03431</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13559</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the moste high and most vertuous ladie, and our most gracious soueraigne, Mary by the grace of God, Quene of Englande, Fraunce, Naples, Hierusalem, and Irelande, defendour of the fayth, Princesse of Spaigne &amp; Sicilie, Archeduchesse of Austria, Duchesse of Mil∣laine, Burgundie and Brabant, Countesse of Has∣purge, Flaunders and Tyrole. Your Maiesties most faythful, louyng and obedient seruaunt Miles Hogarde, wissheth al grace, long peace, quiet raigne, from God the fa∣ther, the sonne, and the holy Ghost.</title>
                 <author>Hogarde, Miles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mirrour of loue, which such light doth giue, that all men may learne, how to loue and liue. Compiled and set furth by Myles Hogarde seruaunt to the quenes highnesse</title>
                 <author>Huggarde, Miles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caly, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the moste high and most vertuous ladie, and our most gracious soueraigne, Mary by the grace of God, Quene of Englande, Fraunce, Naples, Hierusalem, and Irelande, defendour of the fayth, Princesse of Spaigne &amp; Sicilie, Archeduchesse of Austria, Duchesse of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, Burgundie and Brabant, Countesse of Has<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purge, Flaunders and Tyrole. Your Maiesties most faythful, louyng and obedient seruaunt Miles Hogarde, wissheth al grace, long peace, quiet raigne, from God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the sonne, and the holy Ghost.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I considered, oh most noble Quene,</l>
      <l>Howe God in time hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully wrought,</l>
      <l>In reducinge vs home, whiche so longe hath beene</l>
      <l>Out of his true church, yet nowe to be brought</l>
      <l>Into his church agayne, it came to my thought</l>
      <l>What loue by your grace god to vs did showe</l>
      <l>When hope was almost past as al men do know.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This loue (I say) thus comming to my mynde,</l>
      <l>I thought to the worlde somwhat to expresse,</l>
      <l>But yet then thinkyng, how I am assynde</l>
      <l>By thacceptation of your goodnesse,</l>
      <l>To serue your grace, though most vnworthinesse,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>Appeareth on my part, I did thinke, I say:</l>
      <l>The fruits of my wit, to your grace first to pay.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet doth my hand shake that scarse I can write</l>
      <l>Considryng your highnes most royal estate,</l>
      <l>Sith I so simply dyd this boke indite,</l>
      <l>Beyng both of wit and learning frustrate,</l>
      <l>Wherwith such a worke ought to be ornate:</l>
      <l>But yet your highnes great benignite</l>
      <l>Shewed to all men dyd much encourage me.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Therfore when I had this worke finished,</l>
      <l>Which is but short and compendious,</l>
      <l>Containyng matter mete to published,</l>
      <l>Unto all men, syth it doth playne discusse,</l>
      <l>The great loue of God shewed vnto vs,</l>
      <l>Not in high learning, but in termes plaine,</l>
      <l>Which euery simple wit may easely attayne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Also they may learne howe them selues to loue,</l>
      <l>As nature doth teach, and accordingly</l>
      <l>To loue their neighbour, as that loue doth moue,</l>
      <l>And by the way, I do shew openly,</l>
      <l>How their actes both hath, and also doth trie,</l>
      <l>That thei this loue in order haue not kept,</l>
      <l>Sith obedience, they haue not accept.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Now make I humble request to your highnesse,</l>
      <l>If it with your gracious fauour maye stande,</l>
      <l>That this simple worke, may haue such successe,</l>
      <l>To passe furth in prynt, that it may be skande,</l>
      <l>Of al men to learne, to kepe the true bande,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>Of charite, and then I winne myne entent,</l>
      <l>For to that ende I it onely ment.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Of my minde this is thonly pretence,</l>
      <l>Most humbly beseching your noble highnesse,</l>
      <l>To take it in worth, though intelligence,</l>
      <l>To set furth this worke to the worthinesse,</l>
      <l>Doth lacke on my part, yet neuerthelesse,</l>
      <l>My wit is good, I woulde al thinges were wel,</l>
      <l>Thus as my wit is, my wyll furth I tell.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your highnesse humble seruaunt Miles Hogarde.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>