<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ADMONITION TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106114_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10174</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20451</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106114</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ADMONITION TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A shorte declaration of the lives and doctrinde [sic] of the Protestants and puritans : vvher by [each] one of independent iudgment may knovv the holinesse of their religion</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Michel, Marin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>ADMONITION TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Sonne of God (Gentle Reader) Sheweth vs in the Gosoell of S.<note place="margin">mat. <hi>1Z.</hi>
      </note> Mathewe that as the good tree is knowen by the good frutis: so the euill tree is knowen by the euill fruits Christ by this similitude teacheth vs how wee may know and distingish the Godly Pastours &amp; doctours of the true Church of God, from the decitfull troupres of heretiques, which come to vs clothed in the Sheepes skine of pietie and sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie but yet within are Rauening wolues killars of mens Soules for as the Godly Pastours of the Church of God are knowen by their good workes so the seditious troups of hereiques are knowen by their Euil workes yf any man will compare the puritie of doctrine &amp; holy Liues of the Pastours and Doctours of the Catholique Romaine Church with the pestilent Doccaine and abhominabll liues of our Protestants and Puretane, he shall find as great differnce betweene
<pb facs="3"/>
them as is betwene light and darknesse, life, and death, good and Euill.</p>
   <p>As concerning the holy Ancient Fathers you shall see them agree amōgst them selues in vnitie of doctrine, allth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ought they haue beene seueered one frō ane other in diuerse places and ages of the world, adorned with rare holynesse of life and Innumerabll Miraclee as an Infallible testimonie of God approouing both their liues and doctrine as aceep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto him.</p>
   <p>But yf you will considder our Protes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and Puritans liues and doctrine you sheall see such a confusion in their doctrine different one from an other, &amp; abhominable liues without all Miracles, that it is a wonder how anie man setled in his naturall witts should followe such vnrullie sellwes to Euident perdition.</p>
   <p>As concerining their doctrine 3 thing are to be considered. The confesion of their erroneous opinions. The libertie they giue to all kind of Euill. The con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt of good woorks as not profitalle to Saluation.</p>
   <p>Toiching the confusion of their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous opinions, you must vnderstand that in the smoeke of Luthers heresie
<pb facs="3"/>
more then tow hundreth damnable opinions were Ingendred by diuerse loftie braines (as Rhetius in his athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sms deelareth) which haue dasled the Eyes of manie Ignorant soules with such a thic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e mist of diuerse heresies that manie thousand soules not knowing what they doe goe astray with a wandr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foete from the way of Saluation to Euident perditon.</p>
   <p>As there is but one lyne to leuell righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly to the marke, a hundereth wayes to shut a stray: so there is but one true faith and Religion, whereby true Chr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istians goe to Heauen but an hundreth false faiths and Religions which lead Ignorant soules and vn Godly men to Eternall damnation.</p>
   <p>when the Catholiques reprotch the Protestants of their desagreeing in the Chiefest heads of Religion, manie of them now a dayes answere, that a man maybe saued in any Religin that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, pouyding he beleue to be saued in the Blood of Christ.</p>
   <p>This is the cause wherefore they say althought the Maesse, praying to the Saincts, honoring of Images in Temples be Idolatrie neuerthelesse that good Papists may be saued in any Religion,
<pb facs="4"/>
because they beleeue in Christ this is ane of the greatest deceits that Sathan could inuent for the damnation of man when he persuadetd him that he may be saued in anie Religon that is professed in the world prouyding he beleeue to be saued in the Blood of Christ for when a man is surely persuadetd to be saued this way, he careth not of what Relagion he be, whether he be a Protestant or Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, Trinitar or Anabaptist, Caehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que or heretique beeause that all Relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions are a like to him prouyding he beleeue in Christ, and so by this persuas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of Sathan he abideth with alse great securitie in a false Religion, which lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Ignornt soules to Euident perdition as yf he were in a true Religion, which is but one. and likewise the only sure way to saluation.</p>
   <p>Moreouer according to the false opinion of Protestants all heretiques which euer were since the birth of Christ (how blasphemous that euere their her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esies were against God) should be saued, as Arrius which deny the diuinitie of Christ, Pelagius which affirmed that man might be saued by hes owen proper vertue without the grace of God and all
<pb facs="4"/>
other suchlike blasphemous heretiques, because they did belue in Christ and presesse them selues to be Christians &amp; so euery one should goe as securely to Heauen with a false faith and blassphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Religion, which opinion is so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapie to the holy Scaripture and vprig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ht Reason that it is a wonder how such an opinian should enter in the braine of man.</p>
   <p>For S. Paule sayeth, that there is but one faith as there is but one God▪<note place="margin">Ephes. <hi>4.5.</hi> hebr. <hi>12.6.</hi>
      </note> so he that hath not this faith which is but one and worshipe not this God truly which is also but one can nowise be saued, for it is Impossible sayeth S. Paule to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God without faith, where S. Paule speaketh of true faith which is but one, &amp; not false faiths which are manie for. Turques Iewes &amp; heretiques beleeue all in God but all by false faiths, and likewiise serue him by a false Religion.</p>
   <p>Christ to this purpose sayeth: he that will not heare the Church let him be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the as an heathen man and publicane.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 18 17.</note> It is most sure that heathē Infidells haue no participation with Christ and his passion, nor yet heretiques and Schism<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiques seuered from the Church of
<pb facs="5"/>
God by Excōmunication, which Christ compareth to heathen Infidells, because they will not heare or obey the Church of God as Christ Cōmandeth them to doe.</p>
   <p>So a man which hath not the true faith of Christ which is but one, and is not within the true Church of God, which is also but one can nowise attaine to Saluation.</p>
   <p>This opinion is also contrarie to vprig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ht Reason▪ because (as is mentioned, aboue) there is but one way to lenell Rightly to the marke but an hundreth wayes to shute by: so there is but one true faith and Religion to goe to Heau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, but an hundreth false faiths and Raliginos whereby Ignorant soules goe to Endlesse miseereic.<note place="margin">Luther in cap. ad Galall. in serm. de Moyse et in cap. <hi>20.</hi> exoe <hi>20.</hi> exod Caluin. lib. <hi>2.</hi> inst. cap. <hi>7.</hi> sect. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> Thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their manifolde heresies and confusiō of our new Gospellers doctrine.</p>
   <p>The second point which is to be remarked in their doctrine is that they teach men to be made free from the keeping of all Lawes as much of God as of man by their faith in Christ &amp; libertie of their Gospell. so according to this doctrine men may adore Idolls, blasp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme the Name of God contemne and
<pb facs="5"/>
disobey their Father &amp; Mother, cōmite Murther and Slaughter, Incest, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; adulterie, thifte periurie or any other suchlike crimes without any scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of conscience, because they are not bound in conscience to keepe the Lawe of God, as Luther, Caluine and all our Protestants and Puritans doe teach vs whose proper words you shall see herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fter cited in the. 54. Chapter, wherein wee prooue that the Protestants and Puritans by their Pestilent doctrine lead Ignorant soules to a theisme and plaine Infidelitie.</p>
   <p>The third point which is to by mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their doctrine is that they teach that the best workes,<note place="margin">Luther in assert. drt <hi>31.32.36.</hi> Cal. lib. <hi>3</hi> Inst. cap. <hi>12.</hi> sect, <hi>4.</hi> et cap. <hi>14</hi> sect. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> which Issue from Godly Chrstians are but deadly sinnes, when they are weighted in the Iudgme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nt of God, so according to this rule of their doctrine it is all a like to adore God or to worshipe an Idoll, to praise God or to blaspheme his holy Name, to hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his parents or contemne them to kill a man or saue his life, to sleepe with his Nighbonrs wife or with his owen, to with holld his Nighbours goods or to render them, to declare in Iudgment the truth or to foresware him selfe, to
<pb facs="6"/>
keepe promise or to breach the same, to fast and praie, or to spend his time in wan to nesse and Banqueting, to spoile a poore man or giue him almes, for doe what you list in all these or suchlike other things, all your workes are but deadly sinns in the Iudgment of God, whiche deserue no other reward but damnation.</p>
   <p>By this same rule of doctrine when man goe to their Churches to preach or heere the preaching, to giue or rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iue the cōmunion to fast and prair vpon sonday to Excōmunicat Catholiques for not obeing their lawes. all these workes of Religion are but deadly sin̄es, which is the seruice of Sathan and not of God because sinne is from Sathan &amp; acceptable seruice done to him, as S. Ihon writteth, and contrariwise it is hatefull and odiouis to God as cotraria to his holy will.<note place="margin">
         <hi>1</hi> Ihon. <hi>3.8.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>They teach by the same rule that it is but folie to a man to paine him selfe to doe anie good workes, because that when he hath done all that lyeth in his power it is but a deadly sinne, which can not helpe him to Heauen. wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> should a man doe then in this Religion
<pb facs="6"/>
but passe his time in the mirriesse, and so beleeue to be saue in the Blood of Christ, and so he shall goe mirrily to Heauen without all paine and strife.</p>
   <p>Now good Reader yf you will Iucge sinccrly according to the truth, all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie, will you not say that this Rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igion of the Protestants is more like to Epicurus Religlon, where all libertie is giuen to satisfie the concupissonce of the fleyh than the Religion of Chaist, which restrineth the concupissance in all disordained desires by preacaing of penitence in asses and Secke Cloth, by diligent watching in fasting &amp; praying to keepe vs from tentation of the flesh the Deuill and the wordl. The Religion of Christ cōmandeth to figbt lawfully against the concupissanee of the Eyes the sinnefull lust of the flesh, and disord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ained pleasours of the word: but the Religion of the Protestōts is altogether Effeminaate which yeeldeth obedience to the lust of the flesh, concupissance of the Eyes, and worldly pleasours which may content the concupissance. The Religion of Christ cōmandeth vs to enter vnto Heauen by the steraite way of vertue &amp; penionce. But the Religion
<pb facs="7"/>
of the Protestants leadeth wordly man mirryly to Hell by the broad way of carnall libertie and concupissence of the flesh to thie same, so that freely without all scruple of conscience they may cōmit any sinne they please, because they are mad free from all lawes by libertie of their Gospell.</p>
   <p>Yf Sathan wold haue transformed him self in the shape of a Minister to preach in a Pulpite, what Greater libertie wold he haue giuen men to sinne then our Gospellers haue giuen to their auditours by the libertie of their Gospell, for good works are contemned by them as nowise profitable to saluarion, and sinne is Cheerihed amongst them ts nothing hurtfull to saluarion these are the heads of Religion which may of the Ministers of England professe,<note place="margin">Referie Exode Guliel. Reginal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus lib. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>10.</hi> ct <hi>20.</hi>
      </note> as VVilliame Kei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold a learned English man reporteth.</p>
   <p>First such are deceiued as thinke to be saued by many good workes.</p>
   <p>Secondly ti is not necessarie to worke good workes to attainae to Saluation, because wee are sure thereof by faith.</p>
   <p>Thirdly that it is a great errour to thinke that good workes may helpe to Saluation,</p>
   <p>Fourthly sinne doth not diminish the
<pb facs="7"/>
Glorie of God, all the domage is in the slaunder of our Nighbour.</p>
   <p>Fyftly Iesus Christ by his Blood hath deliuered vs not only from sinne, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so from all lawes doth obliedge vs in Conscience, thence is that wee are free from the ten Cōmandements of the Morall lawe &amp; precepts of the Sacramēts</p>
   <p>Sixtly thou ought no other thing to God but only faith whereby thou conf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esseth Iesues Christ, and beleeuest that he is risen from death to life, and so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou shalt be saued.</p>
   <p>So according to this doctrine doe what you please, beleeue in Christ and you shall be saued. there libertie giuen to cōmite all crimes and mischiefe the world without all scruple of conscience.</p>
   <p>Now yf you will consider their persons they are conforme in their liues to this same doctrine.</p>
   <p>First yf you will behold Luthers life there you shall see his familar friends<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hipe, and conference with Sathan, in whose felloweshipe he did eate a bushell of Salt as he affirmeth him selfe in A Dutch Sermon to the people: you shall see his breach of theie Godly vo wes, puoertie, Chastitie &amp; obedience a mons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous comunction of a foresworne frier
<pb facs="8"/>
with an apostatisse Nunne in an Sacr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilegious bedde, and how he could no more keepe him selfe hrom venus game then he could doe from spitting, as he writteth of him selfe in his booke of Matrimonie, likewise he thinketh no shame to say yf the wife refuse to come, the hand maid shalbe welcome, because the fellowshipe of weemen was as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efull to him as sleepe meate and drinke.</p>
   <p>He sheweth also his intollerable pride in so much that he sayeth that Kings, Princes and the Pope him selfe are not worthie to lose the latchets of his shoes and that a Thouand Cyprians and a Thousand Augustins are not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to him.</p>
   <p>He sheweth also his great crueltie &amp; sedition when he did stirre vp the rude cōmon people of Germanie against their Prelats and temporall Lords in such a fashion that a hundreth Thousand man of the cūmon people wer slaine, &amp; thrie hundreth Castells ouerthrowen. in one prouince of Germanie called Franconia.</p>
   <p>Yf you will considder the liues of Caluin and Beza there you shall see their Extreeme pride to oppose their priuie Iudgment to the whole antiquitie of the the Ancient Fathers,</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>You shall see likewise in their liues, thift Sacriledge homicide, cruell sedit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion sttrred vp by them in France, adult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erie, sodomie and bougrie.</p>
   <p>Yf you please to viewe Sir Ihon Knox life the holy Apostle of Scotland there you shall see Incest cōmitted by him with his owen good Mother in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nekill or killogie. adulterie wtih an other mans wife his Necromancie and familiar friendshipe with Sathan, whose Example many of the Minissers of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land did follow as you shall see herefter in the description of their liues.</p>
   <p>Considering (Gentle Reaeer) that the tree is knowen by the fruis (as Christ sayetd) you may Easely Iudge by the fruits and morall workes of our New Gospellers,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>7.</hi> vngodly doctrine vngodly Religion.</note> as much taught by their doctrine as practised in their liues whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Relegious tree be good or no when the tree it selfe is nothing else but a confused mas of olde heresies patched together like an beggere olde Clocke, which were condemned long, agoe in olde heretiques by the ancient Fathers. and the fruits thereof a libertie to liue after the pleasours of this world and concupissance of the flesh in all pleasant voluptie of eating and drinking, and
<pb facs="9"/>
Exercise of venus game, and to cōmit anie sinne that is as homicide, adulterie, thifte periurie, Sodomie, and other su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chlike crimes, without scruple of Cons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, because men are made free from the keeping of all lawes by their faith in Christ and libertie of their Gospell.</p>
   <p>Sathan him selfe could not haue geuen a mor pernitious Religion to mortall men then to giue a confused mas of olde condamned heresies, and to teach men that they should neuer paine them selues to doe anie good worke because that all good workes are but deadly sinnes in the Iudhment of God, which can not further our Saluatiō but rather procure our damnation &amp; that men should not be feared to cōmit any sinne that may pleasour him: because that no sinne can condemne him, prouyding he beleeue to be saued in the blood of Christ, for so teaching all good workts are banished away as vnprofitable to Saluation and libertie giuen to man to cōmit all sinnes that may pleasour him without all feare of damnation I praie God to saue vs frō such a pestient Relinion and to graunt vs grace to abide constantly in the bos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome of the catholique Romaine Church.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>