<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>IOANNES LODOVICVS VIVES to the renowned Prince HENRY the Eight, King of England, Lord of Ireland, &amp;c. Salutations.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106897_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">916</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>IOANNES LODOVICVS VIVES to the renowned Prince HENRY the Eight, King of England, Lord of Ireland, &amp;c. Salutations.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>St. Augustine, Of the citie of God : vvith the learned comments of Io. Lod. Viues. Englished by I.H</title>
                 <author>Augustine, of Hippo, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 921, 11 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <head>IOANNES LODOVICVS VIVES to the renowned <hi>Prince</hi> HENRY <hi>the Eight, King of England, Lord of Ireland, &amp;c. Salutations.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is so ordered by nature of mens dispositions, most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous King, as we admire them truely and heartely, whom wee perceiue excell in that knowledge, which pleaseth vs most, and is approued amongst all: diuers are giuen to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers studies and exercises, nature doth so ordaine, as by this variety the world should consist both beautifull and wonderfull: and yet, as hee speakes, <hi>Euery mans owne is fairest to himselfe.</hi> Your Maiestie long since hath beene
<pb facs="4"/>
esteemed, yea and admired, for your opulency and large extended Empire, not conquered by armes &amp; homicide, but lineally conuaied from your parents as, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so for your strengh of minde and body, and for your warlike prowes. But now since you haue also giuen good proofe and essaies, how able are you in strength of wit and studies of wisdome, you are growne much greater and more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble among all learned men, not, but that they highly esteemed you before, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for that you ioyne mildnes with maiesty, goodnes with gouernment, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to appeare a louelier and liuelier image of the <hi>Prince of Nature,</hi> who as hee is greatest, so is he best, yea best before he proued greatest. But men giuen to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning do not so much bewonder your wealth or your power, as with exceeding loue they imbrace &amp; adore, that you are good &amp; gracious: not deeming it to be admired that you are King, since euen wicked men haue oft beene Kings, yea and remarkeable for fayre endowments of the body. But when your defence of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> came forth, thē which nothing can be more elegāt, more pure, more religious, and in one word more christian, the reputation of your minds good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was much more confirmed, if more it might be: for it was now infixed in the minds of al, most firme &amp; assured by many examples as if fastned with nailes, and admiration thereof arose in all men: yea euen in those who thinke nothing more honorable, more maiesticall then the power of a King; &amp; those that place riches aboue al things, &amp; that ascribe exceeding much to the gifts of the body, to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, brawny strength, and agility, and that are students in the arts of war, as if war were the omnipotent cōmander of al things: wher-hence it comes to passe, that all Princes, by all meanes &amp; mediations they may, do ambitiously striue to hold frindship with you, al affecting to be ioined to you, or by confederacy, or which is more wished by alliance. Nor want you the studies of priuate men, which by the splender of your vertues you haue raised, alluring some with your benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, or eather magnificeuce, others with your humanity and sweetnesse of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor, al with wisdom &amp; iustice, two vertues indeed for a King. You being such I do insooth confesse my impudency, that oft times I did affect to be known vnto you: for this is my opinion, that it is no meane praise to be but knowne of you. And whereas at all other times fit occasion was wanting, it now voluntary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented it self, my <hi>Commentaries</hi> vpon S. AVGVSTINES <hi>bookes de ciuitate dei,</hi> being in a readines: which whē I bethought me to whō I might dedicate in such sort, as both I might win some fauor worth the esteeming, for my labor, and he to whō they shold be presēted, might not think so much learning as leasing, so much stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as stubble, not a book, but a burthē or bundel were profered vnto him; as also I might send them to a <hi>Censor</hi> as graue as gratious, who only allowing thē, they might seeme approued and commended by the applause of all men, you onely came to mind for many reasons and respects. First, for that such is your vertue and learning, as euen to you I should haue presented them, if you had bin a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man: next did I see this was the next way to attaine my desire, which erst I had conceaued and in my selfe avowed. Moreouer, as they tell that haue tryed, you are open-handed, &amp; hearted to such kind of presents, then which scarse any may be more welcome to you. For who should offer you gold, filuer or gems, garments, horses or armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, should power water into the sea, and bring trees to the wood. And truely as in all other thinges, so in this, you do most wisely, to thinke that glory, beseeming your vertue and deserts, is purchased with al poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by bookes &amp; monumēts of learned men, if not by mine or those like me, yet surely by shewing your selfe affable and gratious to learned men, you shall light
<pb facs="4"/>
vpon some one, by whose stile, as a most conning pencill, the picture of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and al-surmounting minde, purtraied and polished may be commended to eternity, not to bee couered with the rust of obliuion, nor corrupted by iniury of after ages, but that posterity an vncorrupted witnesse of vertues, should not be silent of what is worthy to bee spoken of, both to the glory of your selfe, when you are restored to heauen, though that be the best and best to be regarded, and also, which is principall and most to be aspired, to the example of them that shall then liue. Besides all this, this worke is most agreeable to your disposition and studies, wherein Saint AVGVSTINE hath collected (as in a treasury) the best part of those readings, which hee had selected in the ancient authors; as ready to dispute with sharpest wits best furnished with choisest eloquence and learning. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is fallne out, that he intending another point, hath preserued the reliques of some the best things, whose natiue seate and dwelling, where they vsed to be fet and found, was fouly ouerturned. And therfore some great men of this later age haue bin much holpen by these writings of AVGVSTINE, for VARRO, SALVST, LIVY, and TVLLIE <hi>de republica:</hi> as HERMOLAVS, POLITIANVS, BLONDVS, BEROALDVS: all which you shal so read, not as they were new or vnheard-of, but recognize them as of old. Adde herevnto, that you and Saint AVGVSTINES point and purpose in writing, seeme almost to intend &amp; attaine the same end. For as you wrote for that better <hi>Rome</hi> against <hi>Babylon,</hi> so Saint AVGVSTINE against <hi>Babylon</hi> defended that ancient, christian and holier <hi>Rome.</hi> This worke, not mine, but Saint AVGVSTINES, by whom I am protected, is also sutable vnto your greatnesse, whether the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor bee respected, or the matter of the worke. The author is AVGVSTINE, (good GOD) how holy, how learned a man, what a light, what a leane to the christian common-wealth, on whom onely it rested for many rites, many statutes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, holy and venerable ceremonies! and not without cause. For in that man was most plentifull study, most exact knowledge of holy writ, a sharpe and cleare iudgement, a wit admirably quick and piercing. He was a most diligent defender of vndefiled piety, of most sweet behauior, composed and conformed to the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Gospell, renowned and honored for his integrity and holinesse of life; all which a man might hardly prosecute in a full volume, much lesse in an Epistle. It is well, I speake of a writer knowne of all, and familiar to you. Now the worke is not concerning the children of <hi>Niobe,</hi> or the gates of <hi>Thebes,</hi> or mending cloathes, or preparing pleasures, or manuring grounds, which yet haue beene arguments presented euen to Kings: but concerning both <hi>Citties,</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and GOD, wherein Angells, deuills, and all men are contained, how they were borne, how bred, how growne, whether they tend, and what they shall doe when they come to their worke: which to vnfold, hee hath omitted no prophane nor sacred learning, which hee doth not both touch and explane; as the exploites of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> their gods, and ceremonies, the Philosophers opinions, the originall of heauen and earth, of Angells, deuills, and men: from what grounds Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple grew, and how thence brought along to our LORD CHRIST. Then are the <hi>Two Citties</hi> compared, of GOD and the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Assyrian, Sicyonian, Argiue, Attick, Latine,</hi> and <hi>Persian</hi> gouernments induced. Next what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, both Heathenish, and Iewish, did foretell of CHRIST. Then speaking of true felicity, he refuteth and refelleth the opinions of the ancient Philosophers concerning it. Afterwards, how CHRIST shall come, the iudge of quick and dead, to sentence good and euill. Moreouer of the torments of the damned. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the ioyes and eternally felicity of Godly men. And all this with a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="5"/>
wit, exceeding sharpenesse, most neate learning, a cleare and polisht stile, such as became an author trauersed and exercised in all kinde of learning and writings, and as beseemed those great and excellent matters, and fitted those with whom hee disputed. <hi>Him</hi> therefore shall you read most famous and best minded <hi>King,</hi> at such houres, as you with-draw from the mighty affaires and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiles of your kingdome to employ on learning and ornaments of the minde, and withall take a taste of our <hi>Commentaries;</hi> whereof let mee say, as <hi>Ouid</hi> sayd of his bookes <hi>de Faestis,</hi> when he presented them to GERMANICVS CaeSAR.
<q>
         <l>A learned Princes iudgement t' vnder goe,</l>
         <l>As sent to reade to <hi>Phaebus,</hi> our leaues goe.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Which if I shall finde they dislike not you, I shall not feare the allowance of others, for who will be so impudent, as not to bee ashamed to dissent from so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a iudgement? which if any dare doe, your euen silent authority, shall yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me. <hi>Farewell worthiest King, and recon</hi> VIVES <hi>most deuoted to you, in any place, so he be reconed one of yours. From</hi> Louaine <hi>the seauenth of Iuly. M. D. XXII.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>