<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PATRONAGE AND protection of the high and mightie Prince, Henry, eldest Sonne of our Soueraigne Lord the King, Prince of Wales &amp;c. President of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106306_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13960</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24269</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106306</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PATRONAGE AND protection of the high and mightie Prince, Henry, eldest Sonne of our Soueraigne Lord the King, Prince of Wales &amp;c. President of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fierie tryall of Gods saints : as a counter-poyze to I.W. priest his English Martyrologie. And the detestable ends of popish traytors</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40, 24, 10, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE PATRONAGE AND protection of the high and mightie Prince, <hi>Henry,</hi> eldest Sonne of our Soueraigne Lord the King, Prince of Wales &amp;c. President of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S that in one place was well sayd by Heathen <hi>Tullie; Non nobis solùm nati sumus, sed partē patria, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem parentes, partem liberi, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem amici, partem propinqui &amp; familiares, peculiaritèr sibi vendicant:</hi> So else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where was it spoken no lesse Christian-like. <hi>Non quid quis fecerit, sed quo animo &amp; studio fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ponderandum est.</hi> Of these sayings, the first seemed vnto me, to Challenge at my hands A speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Dutie to my Prince and Country, which I knew not how to performe, but in this kind: The second I assumed as an Apologie for my weake and slender performāce of that Duty. If my desire (noble Prince) to pay that debt for which by obligation Diuine, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and Nationall I stand obliged, hath transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me beyond that wherevnto I am able, of your Princely clemency, I humbly beseech you, winke at that amisse, and of your Heroicall and Magnanimous Spirit, Shield me from the Darts of the mightie and maleuolent. Your Kingly Father out of the goodnes of his nature, (for to iudge the worst, is dissonant to a good Disposition) hath been obserued to conceiue of things illment, (or which at least might be doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken) well: you certainly being the true Heire as
<pb facs="4"/>
of his Kingdomes so also of his vertues, cannot adiudge of that which is well ment, ill. The cause which I handle is not mine owne, but my Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, wherein what I haue done, I the rather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke to publish at this time and in this Kind by reason of those encouraging Woordes of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, then Bishop of Chichester, now of <hi>Ely,</hi> in his Booke, <hi>Cuititulus est, Tortura Torti, in Episto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la dedicatoria ad Regiam Maiestatem,</hi> his wordes are these, <hi>Iam, vbi in Discrimen adducta causa communitatis, Spectator nemo sit, Actor quis{que} &amp;c.</hi> My Intentions herein are right, wherein I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, <hi>prodesse principi &amp; patriae, non obesse</hi>: If I faile in my purpose, that is not want of will, but of power: If I haue performed ought herein that good is, that same also is, <hi>Multò plus votis, quam factis.</hi> Therefore for that sometimes noble Q. Elizabeths sake, (for she deserued to be loued, <hi>etiam post mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem)</hi> whose fame shall neuer die, (<hi>nam virtus post funera viuit:)</hi> For the King your Fathers sake, who according to his names signification is, a <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer</hi> (of our peace): for the Common wealths sake, which is the Crowne of your Glory: For your owne sake who are our Hope, yeald me, as the reading here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, so also your fauourable and Princely protection; then shall I not care for the faces of mine enemies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The Faithfull Subiect of my Lord the King, and your Highnesse. <hi>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>monogram incorporating the letters FRANCIS BTO (?and U)</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>