<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106037_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106037</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Scrutamini scripturas : the exhortation of a Spanish conuerted monke: collected out of a Spanish authours themselues, to reade and peruse the holy scriptures; contrary to the prohibition of the Pope and Church of Rome, whose tyranny in this point plainely appeares to euery mans view. With other occurrences of no small importance</title>
                 <author>Tejeda, Fernando de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harper, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 61, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll the beatitude &amp; felicity of man, consisteth in the not failing to chuse aright that, which most cōcerneth him, and to discerne what it is he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquisheth, and what it is hee imbraceth; and this the Philosophers call prudence, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to be <hi>recta ratio rerum agendarum,</hi> and teacheth a man to order all his actions by the rules of reason: There is a worldly wisedome, and a celestiall wisedome; the first hath the earth for its scope and obiect; the second aymes at heauen. Some mens liues are full of errours and blurres, both in corporall and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall matters; other mens comportments are discreete and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable: the difference floweth from the qualitie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, whereof some are prudent, others are imprudent: the one sort fasteneth on that which is good, the others grope euen as blinde men at mid-day. If a man erre in temporall things, the dammage is not great; for all sublunary occurrences are of small consequence, and to miscary in a slight affaire, imports little. For his errour is repairable, in that there is another life; but if a man erre in matter of eternity, which is for euer permanent, and incapable of any amendment or alteration; this is the greatest detriment a man can incurre. For the declining whereof, God hath giuen the sacred Scripture, the onely meanes to know, vnderstand, and distinguish which is the true, and which the false Religion, what kinde of worship, and manner of seruice and honour hee enioyneth and approoues of, and what hee inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and detesteth: but Sathan, the father of lies, and author of darkenes, perceiuing that by this way alone, his fraud is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulled, his darkenesse dissipated, and the vanity on which his
<pb facs="7"/>kingdome is grounded luculently detected, whence results his eminent ruine. Finding by the long experience of his losses, that such miserable men as he hath captiuated vnto death, and bound with the chaines of ignorance and blindnesse, being irradiated with this heauenly light, doe escape out of his prison, and are transported into the liberty of the sonnes of God. Hence it comes to passe that though by the quality of his peruerse and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed disposition, he abominates and persecuteth all the means that ten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to the good and saluation of mankinde, yet with more sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular diligence, and extraordinary violence, he hath euer oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, &amp; will neuer intermit to resist (vntil God altogether bridle him vp) the bookes of sacred Writ. Now amongst all the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and wars which he hath stirred vp against it, that which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by the interuention of his trusty Agents, the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> and the Inquisitors of <hi>Spaine,</hi> doth at this day prosecute against it, is, without all comparison, most tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent and cruell. For (to omit those other infamous aspersions they cast vpon it) there being allowed, in those countreys, where the Inquisition reigneth, an infinite number of bookes repleate with a thousand blasphemies, superstitions, delusions, lyes, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honesties, and turpitudes, to the great preiudice and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of numberlesse soules, they prohibite the reading of holy Scripture vnto the common people, quite exiling it from them, and most shamefully calumning it to bee the cause and occasion of errours, and the instigatrix to vice. It is true, that <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth gaue order to the Bishops and Inquisitors, that with the consent of the Parson, or Confessor, they should licence the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Scripture in the vulgar tongue, to such as could reade it with fruit: Hereby intimating, and that not obscurely, that his meaning was not, that they should reade it, who were incited thereunto by a desire of knowing and inquiring into the trueth, but onely such as by auricular confession, their course of life, and behauiour, had giuen sufficient testimony, that they were most obstinate Papists, and such as had sworne vnto the Popes words.
<pb facs="7"/>But let the beneuolent Reader obserue, that all that was granted by <hi>Pius,</hi> were it much or little, yet so much as hee permitted, hath been all abrogated and annihilated by a Bull of the most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentle <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth of infamous memory, as may bee seene in <hi>Castigatione indicis librorum prohibitorum;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably whereunto are interdicted all the holy Scriptures in the vulgar tongue, in the Catalogue of prohibited bookes made by the Cardinall <hi>Quirogua,</hi> in his sixt rule; as also in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent one compiled by the order of Cardinal <hi>Bernardo de Rojas</hi> and <hi>Sandoual,</hi> in the fourth Rule: and yet not thus content, the said ministers of Sathan, send into all parts their familiars (which are other incarnate deuils, of inferiour authoritie to them, but of no lesse cruelty and sagacitie) who night and day goe from house to house, and from company to company, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themselues to bee friends and familiars withall, being in trueth enemies and familiar deuils. And by this meanes they knowe and discouer, if there bee any, that flying the contagion of dissolute bookes, betake themselues to the Sanctuary of the holy Scriptures, labouring to reade them in the vulgar tongue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they vnderstand not the other languages in which they are composed, if they take a Lay-man that's skill'd onely in the Spanish with this Diuine booke in his hands, it were better for him, they had surprized him coyning false money, or machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting some notable treason against his Prince or naturall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, for that his offence and rebellion should be lesse cruelly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened, then the reading of holy Writte in the mother tongue is wont to bee.</p>
   <p>This great truculency and vnheard Tyranny of the Pope and Inquisitors, the deplorable blindnesse, and the lamentable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude of those that are subiect vnto them, especially of those of my Nation, haue caused me to take vp my penne, to doe that in my owne language, which many graue and religious Doctors haue happily accomplished in other tongues, to the wonderous and plentifull benefit of the faithfull; to wit, to euince and
<pb facs="8"/>point out as with the finger, the precise necessitie and obligation that all sorts and conditions, both of men and women haue to reade and meditate on the holy Scriptures, whether they be rich or poore, learned or vnlearned, small or great ones; and that not onely if the Prelats permit it, but also though they should all inhibite it. The reasons and arguments which I will alleadge for this purpose, are either drawne word for word, or collected by necessary consequence out of Spanish bookes (two or three La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine bookes excepted) all which are imprinted in <hi>Spaine</hi> with priuiledge, and (as you may see in the Frontispice of all of them) haue been examined and approoued, not by one, but by man Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and not by the lesse but by the most learned men, and not by those that were the least, but the greatest Papists; so that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Catholique Romane, especially if he bee a Spaniard, may reade and peruse this my booke without any scruple of conscience, and cannot chuse but giue credit to what he readeth in it. My intendement herein hath been to gratifie my Nation, as also that forreine nations, which professe the true Religion and faith, and particularly the Noble English Nation, in which it flourisheth more then in all the rest, and to which I stand more obliged then to all others, may see, that the strength of the truth we maintaine, is so forcible, that maugre all the power of Hell, Pope and Inquisitors, it is manifested &amp; diuulged by the mouth of it's enemies. And this will be more perspicuous in those other Tractates, which if God vouchsafe me his Diuine grace, and my necessitie and pouertie affoord me time, place, and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I will bring to light. In which I will prooue, by authorities I haue already gathered out of Spanish Authors and Bookes, the principall points of our English Religion against the Romane. God grant it may all be to the honour of his holy Name, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his Church, which shall be the maine remuneration and guerdon I most desired of the labour I bestowed in this Worke, and the residue I purpose to imprint hereafter; which how great it hath been, <hi>iudicium sit penès doctos.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>