<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right VVorshipfull Samuell Cranmer, and Henry Pratt, the two Sheriffs of the Honourable Citty of London, Lately Elected.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106212_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03234</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13351</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106212</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right VVorshipfull Samuell Cranmer, and Henry Pratt, the two Sheriffs of the Honourable Citty of London, Lately Elected.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons ius honorarium : Exprest in sundry triumphs, pagiants, and shewes: at the initiation or entrance of the Right Honourable George Whitmore, into the Maioralty of the famous and farre renouned city of London. All the charge and expence of the laborious proiects, and obiects both by water and land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Worshipfull, the society of the Habburdashers</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right VVorshipfull <hi>Samuell Cranmer,</hi> and <hi>Henry Pratt,</hi> the two Sheriffs of the Honourable Citty of <hi>London, Lately Elected.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>Right Worshipfull,</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He cheife Magistrats next vnto the Lord Maior▪ are the two sheriffes, the name <hi>Sherife</hi> implyeth as much as the Reeue and Gouernour of a Sheare, for <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e:</hi> is <hi>Graue Count</hi> or <hi>Earle</hi> (for so saith Master <hi>Verstigan:</hi>) and these, were of like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with the <hi>Censors,</hi> who were reputed in the prime and best ranke amongst the Magistrates of <hi>Rome?</hi> They were so cal'd a <hi>Cessendo,</hi> of ceasing, for they set a rate vpon euery mans estate: registring their names, and placing them in a fit century: A second part of their Office consisted in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of maners, as hauing power to inquire into euery mans life and carriage. The Embleame of which Authority was their <hi>Tirgula▪ censoria</hi> borne before them: they are (by others) resembled to the <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the people, and these are cal'd <hi>Sacro Sancti,</hi> whose persons might not be <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, nor their names any way scandaliz'd▪ for whosoever was proued to be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent in either, was held to be <hi>Homo sacer▪</hi> an excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated person, and hee that slew him was not liable vnto any iudgement: their Houses stand open continually, not onely for Hospitality, but for a Sanctuary to all such as were dist<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st: neither was it lawfull for them to be absent from the Colledge one whole day together, during their Yeare. Thus you see
<pb facs="4"/>
how neere the Dignities of this <hi>Citty,</hi> come neere to these in <hi>Rome,</hi> when it was most slourishing. The first <hi>Sheriffes</hi> that bore the name and office in this <hi>Citty,</hi> were <hi>Peter Duke,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Neale,</hi> Anno <hi>1209.</hi> The nouissimi, now in present <hi>Samuell Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Henry Pratt.</hi> Anno <hi>1631.</hi> To whom I direct this short Remembrance.</p>
   <p>Your Worships euer Attendant,</p>
   <p>Thomas Heywood.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>