<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE S. FRAVN∣CIS WALSINGHAM KNIGHT, chiefe Secretarie to her Maiesty, Chan∣cellor of the order, &amp; one of her highnesse priuye Counsell, all grace and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Prime, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106107_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10112</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20370</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106107</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE S. FRAVN∣CIS WALSINGHAM KNIGHT, chiefe Secretarie to her Maiesty, Chan∣cellor of the order, &amp; one of her highnesse priuye Counsell, all grace and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Prime, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fruitefull and briefe discourse in two bookes: the one of nature, the other of grace : with conuenient aunswer to the enemies of grace, vpon incident occasions offered by the late Rhemish notes in their new translation of the new Testament, &amp; others. Made by Iohn Prime fellow of New Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Prime, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 211, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE S. FRAVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIS WALSINGHAM KNIGHT, chiefe Secretarie to her Maiesty, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the order, &amp; one of her highnesse priuye Counsell, all grace and peace in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW a long time, there hath bene, no lesse lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then large writing in our English tong, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the iust confutatiō of sundrie pointes in poperie, specially of their priuat Masse, Praiers in a strāge language, Transsubstantiation, the real presence, the Supremacie, and the like. But all this while concerning the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, and of the Grace of God, of Free will in nature, of concupiscence in the regenerate, of meritoriouse per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb facs="3"/>faith, works, &amp; the whole sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of iustification, the aduersaries haue brought vs hitherto no great mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Of late in their English Rhemish notes as the great mistresse, and in M. Martins discouery as the handmaide therunto (for so he tearmeth his book) there is somwhat said, &amp; shifts deuised. The most of al, that may seme materiall is borrowed of M. Stapletons dictates, their controuersie reader at Doway. In regard whereof &amp; in som other respects in this discours I haue dealt more with him, then with any Latine writer else, &amp; yet so that the greatest benefit therof may redound to thē that haue greatest neede, and can not happily so well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the Latine tong, from whence most of their slights are first deriued, &amp; now put foorth into English scholies &amp; smal pamphlets. Wherin if this my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shall displease M. Stapleton, more then he would, or I wish, as perhaps it maye, may it please him (for they of Rhemes are otherwise like to be occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied)
<pb facs="3"/>wast vagaries set apart, euen as in the sight of God, without fraud &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguitie, plainly, directly and shortly, to oppose as him liketh, for more triall herein, and he shall soone perceaue, that the seruaunts of truth, will not be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in due sorte by replie, to declare whose seruauntes they are. The whole book of his lectures in conueniēt time shalbe answered (if God will) by a most godly, learned, and painefull father. In the meane season (right honourable sir) this present dutie, which I haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, without recitall of farther circun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances in many wordes, alwayes trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome to greater affaires, I offer in most hūble maner I may, to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours fauourable, &amp; experienced pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. The Lord God blesse and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue your honours person, your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouse Ladie, your godlie cares and counsels all in Christ Iesus alwayes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours most hūble and bounden <hi>IOHN PRIME.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>