<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ADVERTISEMENTS
TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106779_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04498</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106779</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ADVERTISEMENTS
TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of the glorious bishop S. Patricke apostle and primate of Ireland : Togeather with the lives of the holy virgin S. Bridgit and of the glorious abbot Saint Columbe patrons of Ireland</title>
                 <author>Jocelin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seutin, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>xix, 1, 216, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="xvij" facs="9"/>
   <head>ADVERTISEMENTS
TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST (gentle Reader) I would haue thee
vnderstād, that in this Translation of S.
<hi>Patrickes</hi> life, I haue followed <hi>Iocelinus
of Tornesio,</hi> who had written it in latin
aboue 400. yeares agone, at the intreaty of <hi>S. Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi>
Bishop of <hi>Conerthen,</hi> of the right Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in God <hi>Thomas,</hi> Lord Primate of Ireland, &amp; of
the honorable Knight Syr <hi>Iohn de Curcy,</hi> as himself
signifyeth in his Preface, which togeather with many
other celebrious and note-worthy thinges, I haue wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
left out, contenting my selfe in this present edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
to publish a summary abridgment of the matters,
that are most remarkable, and best befitting our tymes.
If I learne that this my labour will proue gratefull, I
will God willing, put my hand to an entiere edition.</p>
   <p>Secondly, I would haue thee know, that in seuerall
Chapters and passages, I haue for the latin word <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tānia,</hi>
translated <hi>England,</hi> wherof I would haue none
to take aduantage. I know the English lay clayme to
<pb n="xviij" facs="10"/>
      <hi>S. Patricke,</hi> so doe the French, so doe the Moderne
Scots. Therefore it was not my minde, or meaning to
giue a decissiue verdict or suffrage in a matter so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable
on all sides, or to depriue any of the former na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of the right, or title they haue to him. For <hi>S.
Patricke</hi> is too rich a iewell, to be lost but vpon good
euidence, and better then I haue alleadged.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, concerning <hi>S. Bridgits</hi> life, I haue
translated it partly out of <hi>Cogitosus</hi> her nephew (as
some do thinke) and partly out of <hi>Capgraue,</hi> &amp; haue
my slefe distinguished it by Chapters and Paragraphes
otherwise then it is in the latin, thinking that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode
I obserued therein, would be more for thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
profit, the ornament of the worke, and perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity
of the life it selfe.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, this summary of S. <hi>Columbes</hi> life,
I haue abridged out of S. <hi>Adamnan,</hi> whome I haue
preferred before many other authors, supposing that
none will be so impudent, as to deny what hath beene
deliuered from so holy, and innocuous a pen Further
for the latin worde <hi>Scotia,</hi> I haue most commonly
translated <hi>Ireland,</hi> in regard that Ireland was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
called <hi>Scotia,</hi> by the conspiring confession and
vniforme consent of all learned Writers, and especia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
because it is cleerer then midday, that my Authour
meaneth by the latin word <hi>Scotia, Ireland,</hi> which he
<pb n="xix" facs="10"/>
calls sometymes <hi>Scotia,</hi> and sometimes <hi>Hibernia,</hi> in
one and the selfe same paragraphe, whereof see cleere
and vndenidable proofes <hi>lib. 2. cap. 6. §.</hi> 1. and
<hi>lib. 3. cap. 2. §.</hi> 1. Which we haue faythfully
translated as they lye in the latin, to show with what
sincerity and candour, and vpon what iustifyable
groundes, we haue proceeded in this matter.</p>
   <p>Fiftly gentle Reader, I trust that as the desire of
of aduancing thy spirituall profit, made me vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
this translation: so thou wilt be pleased of thy
curtesy to correct patiently, or to couer charitably, the
faults escaped both in the English, and print. Truly
were I able (as I was not) to inuest these Saints liues in
a lofty and magnificent stile, yet would I preferre a
a plaine and simple phrase. I know that would sound
sweetest in the eare, but this sinketh deepest into the
hart, whereof holy Scriptures written in a phrase
plaine inough, giue aboundant testimony. But as for
the faults of the presse, they could not but be many, by
reason of my owne absence from the Print: the most
principall I haue noted downe in the correctiue table,
the rest I leaue to thy fauourable correction, Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>