<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his right worshypfull Brother Syr Philyppe Hobye knight, M. of ye Kin∣ges maiesties ordinaunce, Thomas Hobye wishethe grace and peace throught our lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106007_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17084</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3963</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106007</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his right worshypfull Brother Syr Philyppe Hobye knight, M. of ye Kin∣ges maiesties ordinaunce, Thomas Hobye wishethe grace and peace throught our lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gratulation of the mooste famous clerke M. Martin Bucer : a man of no lesse learninge and lyterature, then godlye studie and example of lyuing, vnto the churche of Englande for the restitucion of Christes religion. And hys answere vnto the two raylinge epistles of Steue [n], Bisshoppe of Winchester, concerninge the vnmaried state of preestes and cloysterars, wherin is euidently declared, that it is against the lawes of God, and of his churche to require of all suche as be and must be admitted to preesthood, to refrain from holye matrimonie. Translated out of Latin in to Englishe</title>
                 <author>Bucer, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jugge, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his right worshypfull Brother Syr Philyppe Hobye knight, M. of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maiesties ordinaunce, Thomas Hobye wishethe grace and peace throught our lorde Iesus Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Monge the sundrye and manifolde benifittes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che from my tender child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod I haue foūde in yow, and receaued at your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des (most especiall good brother) thys is not the leaste: that ye haue now af la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dayes, of the good zeale ye beare to Gods worde (which at all tymes hath byn moste feruent in you) caused me to be sent not only in to such a regiō whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re as florissheth Gods worde, all good letters bothe holye and prophane, all honestie, &amp; puritie of lyfe, &amp; men in all artes and sciences moste cunning and experte: But also to such a man who is of no lesse wisdom, knouledge, &amp; godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, then of fame, reporte &amp; renoune, &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
by all godly mens iudgementes, one of the perfectest, and greatest Clerkes nowe lyuinge namelye M. Martyne Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>, in whose daylye conuersation and companye, and by whose wisdome learninge, and documētes, I shoulde re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue and learne, that shoulde belonge not onlie to myne owne fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>herance &amp; profyt, but also to the consolation and comfort of you, &amp; all my frendes, whō hytherto I haue founde moste benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall towardes me. Sythe therfore it hath thus chaunced by your most godly procurement &amp; prouision, that I should for a season here remaine with this pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>founde and famous Clerke, ye myght not vnworthelye &amp; in dede, with iuste cause, impute vnto me, either the vyce of igname, or els obliuion and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of your moste large and ample benefittes, if I should let slippe suche a mete, apt, and necessarye epistle of his, and especiallie beinge writtē and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the whole churche, or congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Englande, bothe learned &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, &amp; in the which he expresseth not only the assured and vnfained loue that
<pb facs="3"/>
he beareth, &amp; at all tymes hathe borne towardes this realme, and rulars and ministers of the same, but also very euidentlye declareth, and with moste manifeste testimonies of scripture, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth furthe at large suche thinges as maye be to the profitt and furtherance of many, and wherin he hath confuted (not al, for it were in maner an infinite worke to stande aboute all, but) as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sophisticall &amp; wranglinge schoolishe reasons, as are of any probabilitie or likehoode, whiche my lorde of Uvyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester (farre vnsemely for a sober Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppe) hath expressed &amp; set forthe in his two moste cōtumelious &amp; railing epist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les agaīst him, winkīg at, &amp; ouerhippīg his wel most innumerable opprobrious wordes, checkes, tauntes, rebukes, qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rellinges scoffinges, reuilīges &amp; scoldin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges railinges, wherwith they are filled as full, as they may be heaped to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In the which are so fewe argumē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or reasons of any probabilitie: that had not the vrgēt and instant requeste of his frendes, certain of oure coūtray men bien, he wold neuer once haue put
<pb facs="4"/>
penn to the paper, nor yet haue made anye a do about them, but wolde haue left them to the iudgemēt &amp; arbitrimēt of the reader, notwithstanding now of late dayes it chaunced that he gate a lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le vacant tyme to do the same (seing he promised it to certaine) from his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde impedimentes, &amp; necessarie eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical busines (wher with we knowe such men are no smale dele let) &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile him selfe (which the Bisshoppe scornfullye, after his olde wōte, casteth in his tethe) to his brother, before he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ay his offringe vpon the altare. The whiche thoughe it be brefe, and cōpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious &amp; not set forth to the largeste, yet is it verye dilucidious, pithie, &amp; full of argumentes concluded not onlye vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy gostes vnfained decrees, apoīt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and ordinaunces, but also the olde and holye doctores of the church, and for the brefnes of tyme sufficient inough. The which when he had finis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, I furthe with toke in hande acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my childishe talent, to translate into our vulgare and cōmune speache, and haue sent it vnto yow to then<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent
<pb facs="4"/>
some well disposed and better learned which purchaunce wyll not bestowe so moch tym as the translation therof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, maye yet at the least wyse pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruse it acording as he thinketh beste, so that at lengthe it may be worthy to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me abroade for the profit and instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ignoraunt, whiche haue not receaued the knowledge of the Latin tonge, because it is written to them, as wel as to the other. Wherin I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre yow to accept my good wyll, as thought it colde extende farther and do moch better, which yf ye do, it shalbe a great incourage and vrgent cause vnto me to employ and bestowe the reste of my studie, dilygence and laboure her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in other affayres, which I truste shalbe no lesse acceptable vnto yowe, then great furtherance to myne onne profyt &amp; vtilitie. The spirite of treuthe be with yow, who guide yow in all your pathes, acording to his will, and lead yow into all go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tlye knowlege. Amen. At Argentyne, Kalendis Februarij.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>