<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE AND RENOWNED, George, Earle of Downbarre: Lord Howme of Ber∣wicke: Lord Norham: Lord-High-Treasurer of Scotland: One of the Lords Lieutenants of the middle shires of great Britaine: Lord-Gouernour of the Towne and Garrison of Berwicke: Knight of the most Honorable order of the Garter, and one of the Lords of his Maiest∣ies most Honorable priuie counsell in both Kingdomes:</title>
           <author>Sauile, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106267_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11536</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21785</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106267</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE AND RENOWNED, George, Earle of Downbarre: Lord Howme of Ber∣wicke: Lord Norham: Lord-High-Treasurer of Scotland: One of the Lords Lieutenants of the middle shires of great Britaine: Lord-Gouernour of the Towne and Garrison of Berwicke: Knight of the most Honorable order of the Garter, and one of the Lords of his Maiest∣ies most Honorable priuie counsell in both Kingdomes:</title>
                 <author>Sauile, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Adams garden : A meditation of thankfulnesse and praises vnto the Lord, for the returne and restore of Adam and his posteritie: planted as flowers in a garden, and published by a gentle-man, long exercised, and happilie trained in the schoole of Gods afflictions</title>
                 <author>Savile, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland (Haveland), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 27, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND RENOWNED,</hi> George, <hi>Earle</hi> of Downbarre: <hi>Lord</hi> Howme of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke: <hi>Lord</hi> Norham: <hi>Lord-High-Treasurer</hi> of Scotland: One of the <hi>Lords Lieutenants</hi> of the middle shires of great <hi>Britaine: Lord-Gouernour</hi> of the Towne and Garrison of <hi>Berwicke: Knight</hi> of the most <hi>Honorable</hi> order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> and one of the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Maiest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies</hi> most <hi>Honorable</hi> priuie counsell in both Kingdomes:</head>
   <head type="sub">Thomas <hi>Sauile</hi> wisheth all true Honour and <hi>Magnanimitie of mind, in the course of his Rule and</hi> Estate; which may be a perpetuall peace vnto his desires.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it please your <hi>Lord-ship,</hi> I was bold (of late) to present you a little pamphlet of my writing; which you did please so verie fauourablie to accept (with declaration of your happie delight in such things) as hath incouraged me to rippe vp all my faculties, and deepest comprehensions, to offer your <hi>Lord-ship</hi> a further view, of such my poore bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted gatherings, as may sort to the same end with the former. Verie great surelie, is the loue and seruice I owe your most <hi>Honourable</hi> selfe, and euer must: For whether I regard, the wonderfull degrees of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,
<pb facs="3"/>gentle (and not vainelie exalted minde) in speeches, and affoorded graces by countenance and acceptation; or that which is much more, your open hand and purse vnto my fainting estate (a fauour which I protest, I neuer tasted from any other <hi>Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of the world:) for my good <hi>Lord,</hi> it is wel knowne till of late yeeres, that my times haue beene disposed and spent in giuing and not taking. I must therefore and doe deuote my selfe, to loue and admire your <hi>Lord-ship</hi> before the rest. Bee pleased therefore (my beneficiall <hi>Lord</hi>) to receiue this poore pawne of my resigned affections; and take view how strange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations the Lord quilteth vpon the orphaned, such as hee doth correct; euen to make them finde light in darknesse, and much confidence of reioicing in their forsaken and abandoned estate. I am bold to put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Lord-ship,</hi> the broydure of not being vainelie exalted; a true note of your wisdome, and that you know your selfe, state and calling, (and whatsoeuer in this mortalitie) fading, euen in Kings and Monarchs of the earth, the period vncertaine of dissolution: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, if the Lord should afford you all the works of his hands, in full fruition, and withdraw his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and presence from you; all you enioy in the world, shall bee found but comfortlesse comforts, when the change (which certainelie doth attend all mortalitie) shall bee designed. It is the heart that the Lord respecteth and accepteth; and being resigned and ankored in his will, hee will loue and establish the proceedings thereof, for his verie owne delight in what alteration or change soeuer: So that what sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, trouble, greefe or crosse, may befall you, they
<pb facs="3"/>shall but be as his messengers, to bring you a seale and assurance of his fatherlie indulgence and care; and that hee will haue your heart himselfe in keeping (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>use with him there is no change at all) and so will build you vp, vnto that assurance of hopefull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, wherein you shall find prepared, all peace, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, perseuerance, and what in the world may bee most desired, for the type of euer-during feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city: which the Lord in all his fauourable enlargements giue you. And so I praie pardon.</p>
   <p>A gentle-man long trained in her late Maiesties ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, vnder that euer famous Lord-Treasurer <hi>Burleigh:</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Now your Lord-ships faithfull seruant <hi>Thomas Sauile.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>