<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my good Friends and Fellowes,
the Citty-Actors.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106113_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106113</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my good Friends and Fellowes,
the Citty-Actors.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology for actors : Containing three briefe treatises. 1 Their antiquity. 2 Their ancient dignity. 3 The true vse of their quality. Written by Thomas Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To my good Friends and Fellowes,
the Citty-Actors.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vt of my busiest houres, I haue spared
my selfe so much time as to touch some
particulars concerning vs, to approue
our Antiquity, ancient Dignity, and
the true vse of our quality. That it
hath beene ancient, we haue deriued
it from more then two thousand yeeres agoe, successiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to this age. That it hath beene esteemed by the best
and greatest: to omit all the noble Patrons of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
world, I need alledge no more then the Royall
and Princely seruices, in which we now liue. That
the vse thereof is authentique, I haue done my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
to instance by History, and approue by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
To excuse my ignorance in affecting no florish of
Eloquence, to set a glosse vpon my Treatise, I haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to say for my selfe but this: <hi>A good face needs
no painting, &amp; a good cause no abetting.</hi> Some ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious
haue too liberally taxed vs▪ and hee (in my
thoughts) is held worthy reproofe, whose ignorance
cannot answere for it selfe: I hold it more honest for
the guiltlesse to excuse, then the enuious to exclaime.
And we may as freely (out of our plainnesse) answere,
as they (out of their peruersnesse obiect) instancing
my selfe by famous <hi>Scalliger,</hi> learned Doctor <hi>Gager,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Doctor <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and others, whose opinions and appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
arguments on our part, I haue in my briefe discourse
altogether omitted; because I am loath to bee taxed in
borrowing from others: and besides, their workes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
extant to the world, offer themselues freely to euery
mans perusall. I am profest aduersary to none, I rather
couet reconcilement, then opposition, nor proceedes this
my labour from any enuy in me, but rather to shew them
wherein they erre. So wishing you iudiciall Audiences,
honest Poets, and true gatherers, I commit you all to the
fulnesse of your best wishes.</p>
   <signed>Yours euer,
T. H.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>