<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An admonition to all Ministers ecclesiasticall.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106160_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03549</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13669</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106160</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An admonition to all Ministers ecclesiasticall.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second tome of homilees : of such matters as were promised, and intituled in the former part of homilees. Set out by the aucthoritie of the Queenes Maiestie: and to be read in euery parishe church agreeably</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 <publisher>Cawood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jugge, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>588, 3, 593-599, 601-616, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="admonition">
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ An admonition to all Ministers ecclesiasticall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR that the Lorde doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of his seruaunt whom he hath set ouer his house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, to shewe both fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse and prudence in his office: it shalbe necessarye that ye aboue al other do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue your selfe moste fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diligently in your so hygh a function: that is, aptly, playnely, and distinctly to reade the sacred scriptures, diligently to instruct the youth in their Catechisme, grauely and reuerently to minister his most holy Sacramentes, prudently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to choose out such Homilees as be most meete for the time, &amp; for the more agreeable instruction of the people committed to your charge, with such discretion, that where the Homilee may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to long for one readyng, to diuide the same to be read part in the fore noone, and part in the after noone. And where it may so chaunce some one or other chapter of the olde Testament to fal in order to be read vppon the Sundayes or holye dayes, whiche were better to be chaunged with some other of the newe Testament of more edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: it shalbe wel done to spende your tyme to consyder wel of such chapters before hand, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by your prudence and diligence in your office may appeare, so that your people may haue cause to glorifie God for you, and be the redyer to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace your labours, to your better commendatiō, to the discharge of your cōsciences &amp; their owne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>