<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Autor to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106725_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16955</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3845</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106725</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Autor to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie in briefe assertions defending that our Lord died in the time properly foretold to Daniel : For satisfaction of some students in both vniuersities. H. Broughton</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Kearney (Carney, Kerny), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Watkins, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>86 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Autor to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ouching the iudgement of those Diuines,
which I cyte, for their exposition of <hi>Daniels</hi>
prophecie, it were long to bring their whole
style: the summe is this, <hi>That from the end
of the Babylonian captiuitie, the first sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
must be reckoned: and the last hath
in it our Lords death.</hi> With that mure aduersarie once agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
yet goeth against himself, saying, <hi>that the Angel meant
no certaine time: and that 107. yeeres are betwixt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,
and the building of the Temple.</hi> 75. more than I
hold, and 5, lesse thence to <hi>Tiberius</hi> than I make. The whole I
make 70. seauens, and stand to that: he once 70. and againe 80.
and againe a number vncertaine: which he thinketh, that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympiades
can bring to certaintie of, not 490. yeeres, but 560.
precisely. And he thinketh for this to disanul the common iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Greekes</hi> vppon the Scripture: and that
accompts from Olympiades with <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans</hi>
can make his cause good. This I am to ouerthrow, by that wit,
learning, and religion, vtterly forbid to hold vncertainty, where
the limits be certain in <hi>Daniel</hi> for our Lords redemption. And
that particulers from the Prophets, holden of Church and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue,
as I doo, are holden aright; and that prophane testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
faile him. In handling prophane testimonies: The fall of
<hi>Troy, Olympiades, Cyrus</hi> Monarchie, <hi>Xerxes</hi> warre, <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanders,
Alexanders:</hi> the distaunces of these I am driuen to
handle, &amp; proue that in all these, euen faithles <hi>Greeks</hi> disproue
them, whom mine aduersarie followeth: and also they whom he
most alloweth, do him vtterly confute. He reading among men
yong in yeres, yonger in these studies, and not putting in print
his Lectures: I entered abruptly into the cause, to meete with
striuers, hastie to broach streames of errors.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>