<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An inforced Conclusion.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106718_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3834</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An inforced Conclusion.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discouerie of certaine errours published in print in the much commended Britannia. 1594 : Very preiudiciall to the discentes and successions of the auncient nobilitie of this realme. By Yorke Herault</title>
                 <author>Brooke, Ralph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Judson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 77, 11 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="conclusion">
   <pb facs="44"/>
   <pb facs="44"/>
   <head>An inforced Conclusion.</head>
   <p>WHen as I had collected readie for the Presse, so many of your defectes and errors, (published in your so highly commended <hi>Britannia</hi>) as might well haue satisfied the worlde, that I vndertooke not this worke in vaine, nor yet without good cause me moouing thereunto. Then was I stayed in the printing thereof, by the disturbance and indirect dealing of your friendes the Stationers, (who heretofore haue made no small gaine of your foure former Impressions) and thereby constrayned abruptly heere to make an ende, suppressing a great part of my first pretended purpose: yet before I doe ende, I thinke it my duetie, heere to put the Nobilitie in minde, that your Booke now going in hand, may be both seene, and alowed, before it goe to the Presse, by such as haue both skill, and authoritie so to doe: (I meane the Earle Marshall) and not to passe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath done, to the preiudice of so many honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Families. And to the ende the worlde may know with whose plumes you haue heretofore fethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your nest (besides the Heraults) I haue hereunto annexed a New-yeeres gyft, dedicated to king Henrie the eight in the. 37. yeere of his reigne, by that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and learned Englishe Antiquarie Maister Iohn Leyland, concerning his sixe yeeres trauayle, and
<pb facs="45"/>
laborious Iourney for the search of Englandes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities, vpon the sayd Kinges commission and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: by which it may appeare vnto the indifferent Reader, who was the first Author and contriuer of this late borne <hi>Britannia,</hi> either he whose name is cleane razed and blotted out, or you that haue both ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the tytle and whole credite thereof to your selfe. Also, I may not heere let passe the wordes of Maister Iohn Bale in his declarations vpon the same worke, dedicated to King Edward the sixt: which are these following. <hi>Blessed be the man which shall set this worthy worke abrode: and contrarywise, Cursed be he for euer and euer, that shall in spight of his Nation, seeke thereof the distruction.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>