<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>M. Doctor Humfrey in his Booke which he writeth of the life and death of Iuel. Pa∣gina. 49.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106654_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04477</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14609.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>M. Doctor Humfrey in his Booke which he writeth of the life and death of Iuel. Pa∣gina. 49.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon made in latine in Oxenforde : in the raigne of King Edwarde the sixt, by the learned and godly father Iohn Iuel, late Bishop of Sarisburie, and translated into Englishe, by R.V. Dedicated vnto the Bishop of London, as appeareth in the Commentarie of Ma. Caluine, vpon the Galathians, in Englishe</title>
                 <author>Jewel, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>M. Doctor Humfrey in his Booke which he writeth of the life and death of Iuel. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina. 49.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vam autem in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo <hi>Diuae Mariae concionē habuerit, quàm latinè, qùā comptè, quàm Theologicè, me silēte ipsa loquetur Oratio, cuius exemplū mutilum, vt potui, aliquantulum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitum &amp; correctius exhibere ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lui, quàm omninò supprimere, quae &amp; Concionatores multa vtiliter cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monefacit, &amp; progradu Baccalaurea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus suscepto recitata videtur, verbis ex 1. Pet. 4. desumptis, dominica in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Octau. Ascensionis.</hi>
      </hi>
   </p>
   <p>But what maner of sermon he made in S. Maries Church, in how excellent Latine he made it, how finely &amp; how like a Diuine he did it, his matter shal shew not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding I holde my peace;
<pb facs="3"/>
the vnperfecte example whereof, beinge as well as I coulde some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what perused and amended, I had rather sette out, then altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther suppresse it or keepe it backe, which profitably putteth in mind and warneth preachers of manye things, and seemeth to haue bene preached when he toke his degree of Bachelaure in Diuinitie, the wordes being taken out of the first Epistle of Peter the 4. Chapiter, vpon the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day within the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauois of the Ascensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>