<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Valentine Leighe to the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106757_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15416</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106757</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Valentine Leighe to the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The moste profitable and commendable science, of surueying of landes, tenementes, and hereditamentes: drawen and collected by the industrie of Valentyne Leigh. Whereunto is also annexed by the same authour, a right necessarie treatise, of the measuryng of all kyndes of lande, be it meadow, pasture, errable, wood, hill, or dale, and that aswell by certaine easie and compendious rules, as also by an exact and beneficiall table, purposely drawen and deuised for that behalfe</title>
                 <author>Leigh, Valentine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 3 folded leaves of plates, diagrams, tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Valentine Leighe to the <hi>gentle Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eyng that J doe novve at this tyme entreate, not of any vaine fable or triflyng toye, but of suche earnest and serious matter, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the profite of moste men, and the benefite and commoditie of eche maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone: J humbly beseche all men (inasmuche, as the thyng it self, appertaineth to euery manne) that in readyng thereof, thei vvill vouchsafe, to harken, attribute, and graunte, suche diligent and vvillyng eare, mynde, and attention, as thei are accustomed, and vse to doe, in those, or suche cases, vvhiche thei accoumpt moste vvaightie, graue, and necessarie; &amp; vvhiche thei are moste desirous to knovv, learne and vnderstande. And firste, let this one thyng, bee vvell pondered emongeste you, vvho is it of vs all, that hauyng any thing (vvhatsoeuer it be) vvhich maie bee made double or treble more profitable, to hym by good gouernemente, vsage, and ouersighte thereof, then the same is at this present, and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther suffer it to runne to losse, and decaie, then he vvould once (by giuyng a little earneste attentiue
<pb facs="3"/>
diligence) read, heare, and vnderstande the meanes by vvhiche he maie, or might, not onely better the thyng vvhiche he possesseth, but also thereby so muche encrease his aduauntage, grovvyng by the same.</p>
   <p>And seyng the sciēce of Surueiyng of landes, is the matter, vvherupon this present booke entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, vvhiche teacheth the gouernmente of the Mannours, landes and tenementes of eche persone, and hovv to make a perfecte Surueye of the same, to moste profite. And also, hovv to engrosse your terrors and Rentalls thereof. And finally, hovv to measure all kindes of lāde, be it Meadovv, Pasture, Errable, VVoodde, ill, or dale, &amp; in vvhat forme or figure so euer it is fashioned, or cōmōly lieth, vvith the forme, hovv to vnderstande the contentes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, asvvell by a beneficiall Table, already &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made for that behalfe, as othervvise by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Rules to the same appertainyng. All vvhiche thinges, I haue (gentle Reader) not vvithout pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trauell for thy commoditie, hereafter described.</p>
   <p>J shall therefore, for my revvard, or recompēse thereof request no more at your handes, for my trauell therein, but onely, that it maie please you, to
<pb facs="3"/>
take my poore good vvill, and intente in thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parte, and the rather, because J humbly submit my vvhole vvorke, vnto the correction of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if J haue (by ouersight or othervvise) mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the matter.</p>
   <p>And although some perchaunce shall thinke, thei could haue doen the same muche better then J haue doen, J vvill not muche contende, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessyng and grauntyng thereof. But yet seyng I am one of the first, that attempted the collectyng of the same Arte into a volume, to the publication there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for the benefite of the common vvealthe, J doe not mistruste, but euery indifferent persone, vvill thinke these my labours (ioyned vvith some stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and taken in hande for his instruction) at the leaste vvise, so muche vvorthe, as the deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of a bare good vvorde, and frendlie reporte: alvvaies remembryng, that although moste men, can perhappes amende a deuise once begun, yet that euery first deuise, in euery thyng, is moste harde, &amp; troublesome: and therefore albeit here novv, not so exquisitely handled in euery point at the first, as it maie be hereafter, beyng (as the Prouerbe saith) muche easier to amende, then to inuente: yet I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie
<pb facs="4"/>
praie thee, not by carpyng or othervvise, to depraue the aucthors honest meanyng. And J as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure thee, by this thy frendlie acceptation of these firste fruites of my simple studies, thou maiest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce so animate my vvillyng mynde, that thou shalt gaine to thy self thereby, the fruition and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, of my other like studies in suche behalfe. And thus I can saie no more, but vvishe euery man asmuche profite, and benefite in readyng here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as my vvillyng attempte herein hath entended them. And so J ende bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng thee gentle Reader moste hartely vvell to fare.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>This .xxvij. of October. Anno Christi. 1562.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="4"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>