<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Dowland, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106690_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20695</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106690</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Dowland, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pilgrimes solace : VVherein is contained musicall harmonie of 3. 4. and 5. parts, to be sung and plaid with the lute and viols. By Iohn Douland, Batchelor of Musicke in both the vniuersities: and lutenist to the Right Honourable the Lord Walden</title>
                 <author>Dowland, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barley, William, Assignee(s etc.) of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                            <distributor>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Gentlemen, and my louing Countrymen; mooued by your many and fore-tasted courresies, I am constrained to appeare againe vnto you. True it is, I haue lien long ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scured from your sight, because I receiued a Kingly entertainment in a forraine climate, which could not attaine to any (though neuer so meane) place at home, yet haue I held vp my head within this Horizon, and not altogether beene vnaffected else where. Since some part of my poore labours haue found fauour in the greatest part of Europes, and beene printed in eight most famous Cities beyond the Seas. <hi>viz: Paris, Antwerpe, Collein, Nurenburge, Franckfort, Liepsig, Amsterdam,</hi> and <hi>Hamburge:</hi> (yea and some of them also authorized vnder the Emperours royall priuiledge,) yet I must tell you, as I haue beene a stranger; so haue I againe found strange entertainment since my returne; especially by the opposition of two sorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that shroude themselues vnder the title of Musitians. The first are some simple Cantors, or vocall singers, who though they seeme excellent in their blinde Diuision-making, are meerely ignorant, euen in the first elements of Musicke, and also in the true order of the mutation of the <hi>Hexachord</hi> in the <hi>Systeme,</hi> (which hath ben approued by all the learned and skilfull men of Christendome, this 800 yeeres,) yet doe these fellowes giue their verdict of me behinde my backe, and say, what I doe is after the old manner: but I will speake openly to them, and would haue them know that the proudest Cantor of them, dares not oppose himselfe face to face against me. The second are young men, professors of the Lute, who vaunt themselues, to the disparagement of such as haue beene before their time, (wherein I my selfe am a party) that there neuer was the like of them. To these men I say little, because of my loue and hope to see some deedes ensue their braue wordes, and also being that here vnder their ownenoses hath beene published a Booke in defence of the Viol de Gamba, wherein not onely all other the best and principall instruments haue beene abased, but especially the Lute by name, the words, to satisfie thee Reader I haue here thought good to insert, and are as followeth: <hi>From henceforth, the statefull Instrument Gambo Violl, shall with ease yeeld full various, and deuicefull Musicke as the Lute: for here I protest the Trin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ie of Musicke, Parts, Passion, and Deuision, to be as gracefully vnited in the Gambo Viol, as in the most receiued Instrument that is, &amp;c.</hi> Which Imputation, me thinkes, the learneder sort of Musitians ought not to let passe vnanswered. Moreouer that here are and daily doth come into our most famous kingdome, diuers strangers from beyond the seas, which auerre before our owne faces, that we haue no true methode of application or fingering of the Lute. Now if these gallant yong Lutenists be such as they would haue the world beleeue, and of which I make no doubt, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that their skill lyeth not in their fingers endes: <hi>Cucullus non facit Monachum.</hi> I wish for the Honor therfore and generall benefit of our Countrie, that they vndertake the defence of their Lute profession, seeing that some of them aboue other, haue most large meanes, conuenient time, and such encouragement as I neuer knew any haue, belceue me if any of these obiections had beene made when those famous men liued which now are thought worthy of no fame, not derogating from these skillfull men present; I dare affirme that these obiections had beene answered to the full, and I make no doubt but that those few of the former time which liue yet, being that some of them are Batchelors of Musicke, and others which assume vnto themselues to be no lesse worthy, wilbe as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to preserue their reputation. Perhaps you will aske me, why I that haue trauailed many countries, and ought to haue some experience, doth not vnder goe this busines my selfe? I answere that I want abilitie, being I am now entered into the fiftieth yeare of mine age: secondly because I want both meanes, leasure, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But (Gentle Reader to conclude, although abruptly) this worke of mine, which I here haue published, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth such things as I my selfe haue thought well of, as being in mine opinion furnished with varietie of matter both of Iudgement and delight, which willingly I referre to the friendly censure, and approbation of the skilfull: hoping it will be no lesse delightfull to all in generall, then it was pleasing to me in the composition, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend
Iohn Douland.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>