<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the worshipfull, his verie louing Cowsen M. Edwarde Eliotte Esquier, the Queenes Maiesties Sur∣ueyour of all her Honours Manours, Landes and pos∣sessions within her highnes County of Essex.</title>
           <author>Hake, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106018_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02476</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12605</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106018</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the worshipfull, his verie louing Cowsen M. Edwarde Eliotte Esquier, the Queenes Maiesties Sur∣ueyour of all her Honours Manours, Landes and pos∣sessions within her highnes County of Essex.</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commemoration of the most prosperous and peaceable raigne of our gratious and deere soueraigne lady Elizabeth by the grace of God of England, Fraunce and Irelande, Queene &amp;c : Now newly set foorth this. xvii. day of Nouember, beyng the first day of the. xviii. yeere of her Maiesties sayd raigne. By Edw. Hake. Gent</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the worshipfull, his verie louing Cowsen M. Edwarde Eliotte Esquier, the Queenes Maiesties Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyour of all her Honours Manours, Landes and pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions within her highnes County of Essex.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Einge entred (worshipfull and</hi> my beeloued Cowsen) into the meditacion of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rare gouernment of our renowmed Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> so high and so aboundaunte matter of admyration offered it selfe to the view of mine vnderstanding, that I felt my thoughts in such sorte surprised with the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof, that (for the solace of my minde) I yeelded my selfe a ioyfull man to set downe in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge some superfitiall discourse vpon the same: such, as (at the least within mine owne soule) might styrre vp and procure the prayses of God, and draw forwards a dewe thankfulnes vnto his maiesty for the wonderfull benefites that largely (thereby) haue accrewed to the whole body and to euery particuler member of this our Englishe Nacion. And loe, no sooner had I accomplished this mocion of my mind (in such sorte as you may see it heere set downe in printe) but another Cogitacion began with impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie
<pb facs="3"/>
to assayle me a freshe: for beholdinge (with the feruencye of my harte) the truthe of that matter which I had already compyled, and seeing yet (far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) so gloryous and so plentifull a treasourie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning to be discouered, and that, <hi>In perpetuam rei memoriam</hi>: I could not choose but so farre mislike with the sclendernes of that which I had alreadye done, as I wished (and not slightly) that it woulde please almighty God (to the eternall praises of his holy name) to stirre vp the zeale of some learned and well approued member to geue abroade for an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall view, to all Countreies and Nacions of Christendome, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heroyicall garnishment of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and truth, an exact historye and declaration of the same. And in this cogitaciō, repairing vnto your house for the comforte of your friendlye confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, it was the good will of God that I shuld dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close mine affections (that way) vnto you, as also y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I shoulde offer vnto you the hearing of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as it was at that time, thus vnlearnedly pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: where findyng by the like good fauour of god, your learned &amp; friendly neighbour, it was recokned for Gods diuine prouidence, that I should require him also to be a hearer of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. Which learned man (as you know) vpon the hearinge thereof, so largely dispensed with al those wantes that by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning might (peraduenture) haue binne supplyed in this booke, as that by fauoryng &amp; chiefly regarding the vndoubted truth of the matter, he perswaded that it wold grow no blemysh at all vnto my credit, neither in respect of the breuitie of the woorke, nor yet for the playnesse and rudenes of the stile, yf I should agree to the publishing of the same in prynt:
<pb facs="3"/>
whervnto on the one parte, the admyrable works of God so exceedingly, aboue humane reason, shininge forth vnto the world in the royal person &amp; regiment of our most louing &amp; gracious Queene, and on the other parte, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> silence of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> learned sort (silence I may terme it in respect of that vehemency which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cause requireth) &amp; the more then stoical &amp; colde consideraciō of al our english people, who are for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greatest part so far from thanking, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they haue no thinking of the same: these motions I say, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fauorable cēsure &amp; encouragemēts of your said learned neighbor at one instant concurringe, I was zealously bold to cast abroad into the view of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world, this my smalle treatise, as it were to prouoke the pen of some renowmed <hi>Homer,</hi> &amp; to prepare the harts of al her highnes subiects to a further &amp; deper consideratiō of Gods exceeding &amp; superaboundaunt mercies, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in the thankfulnes and sinceritie of their hartes, they might (not for one day supersticiously, but for euer) kepe holy vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>cōmemoratiō</hi> of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most prosperous &amp; peaceable raigne of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same our gracious &amp; dere soueraigne lady queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> And now (my worshipful cowsen) bicause y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> forces of these my priuate motions haue in this sort effected, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nedes they must breake forth (I trust to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> honor of the highest) and the same not meanely by occasion of the encouragemēts which I receiued in your house: I cānot resist, but (coactedly as it were by loue) I must confer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dedication thereof (digested into this litle boke as you see) vpon you, before &amp; aboue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rest of my beloued friends: assuring you y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> (in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great ioy of my hart) I haue founde you so equall vnto mine affections in the fauouring of this cause, and in the
<pb facs="4"/>
comfort that you take by beholdyng the blisful daies of our sanctified <hi>DEBORA,</hi> as also so Ialous for the Regestryng of her highnesse prayses (or rather y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prayses of our God) vnto posteritie, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> if I knew by what other meane, more acceptably, then thus by the first view of these my trauayles (employed to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> glory of god) I might manifest vnto you the sincerity of mine affection, vndoubtedly you shuld finde me so for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward to accomplishe the same, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> deede it self, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vtmost limit of my poore degree, shuld be enough to make knowne what vnfayned loue I do beare you. And wheras the dedication of all other bookes (for the most part) doe seeme to craue countinaunce and defence at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hands of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> patron, this my small booke (assure your self) for the dignitie of the personage of whom it treateth, as also for the truth of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it conteineth, shalbe able enough (besides the defence of it selfe) to geue both countinaunce and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to your person, being indeede, the verye man (amongst men of your place and calling) whose loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all harte and religious minde (besides the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of priuate duties of loue) may challenge frō me such affection as best of al becōmeth a christian louer to his friend so wel approued. And though the booke be but litle, yet y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> personage of whō it treateth is great: and so great, as that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Booke may sooner be countenaunced with the royaltie of her highnesse name, than be able (by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thowsande parte) to show foorth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> number of her princely vertues, much lesse, of the large benefites that infinitely arise vnto our common wealth of <hi>England</hi> and to euery member of the same, by the goodnesse of her rarest gouernment: Some particuler partes whereof are (as before is
<pb facs="4"/>
declared) in these Quaires, though brieflye, yet truely discoursed.</p>
   <p>But nowe, that you may some way answere the name of a Patron of this my Booke: although the matter of the same hath defence sufficient in it selfe, &amp; in the truth thereof, is able enough to stand against the faces of al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enimies of truth: Yet because there is a sorte of people, which I feare me, more of enuy, then of any true zeale or care of my well doynge (as hauyng an awstere regard vnto my vocation, which in deede, resteth in the Study, or rather in a meane place of practise of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmon lawes of this Realme) will recken it a matter more then ordinary that I should after this sorte so transcende the limits of my sayd vocation, as spendyng my time, or at the least, some parte of the same, in thyngs by semblaunce, so far discrepaunte from my profession: let my defense be so made, I beseeche you, that it may in equall sort be considered, or at the least wise by you enforced, not only how muche and how largely <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ue and zeale are hable to woorke and brynge to passe in men other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whyles conuersaunt in the consideration of thynges high and precious, but also how seemely a thyng it is and how well agreeable with euery vocation to aduaunce and set foorth the high prayses of vertue and vertuous personages, as also to batter &amp; beate downe the enforcementes of vyce and vicious mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</p>
   <p>And for my selfe, I haue boldly to affirme vnto all suche discontented myndes (especially vnto those that haue the common lawes for theyr profession) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the matter of this my littel booke is not so voyde of excuse, but that by view of the substaunce &amp; ful scope
<pb facs="5"/>
therof, it may yeelde foorth a stronge and ryghtfull defense agaynst these nice and ouer curious repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: for, as it concerneth the speciall prayse of God in the <hi>Commemoration</hi> of the Queenes Maiesties most prosperous and peaceable gouernment: So, it is not vnknowne that touchinge the Regiment of Princes, the nature of Lawes, the office of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saylers, and the authorytie of Iudges, the volumes of our Lawes are not so barrein, but that they may and do minister matter aboundantlye to the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors and students of the same, whereby to discerne and to deeme indifferently of them all: for whether we would consider the good and godly gouernment of a Prince by often pardoning of offences in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, or by sharplie punishing of offenders in iustice, by planting of good &amp; wholsome lawes, or by repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of euill and vnnecessary Statutes: Not onely <hi>Bracton,</hi> but also the worthy and worshipfull Knight master <hi>Forescue</hi> in sundrye places of his litle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, verie copiously geue foorth matter for the furtherynge of studious wittes in the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracion thereof. And no lesse may be gathered tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng a difference and sownd censure of honourable Counsayllers: but especially of Iudges &amp; of lawes. Wherupon I trust I may inferre, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> to praise and extolle the admirable gouernment of our renowmed Soueraigne, or to commende the sowndnes of her lawes, or to aduaunce and set forth the wonderfull vertues of her highnes counsayllers, or to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the rare learning &amp; holynesse of her reuerende Iudges: so far forth as they be matters (though but superfitially) to be discerned and descyphred by the Bookes of our Lawes, so farre, they are not to be
<pb facs="5"/>
thought discrepaunt or impertinent for a student of the lawes to treat or to write of.</p>
   <p>But wherfore should I thus carefully seeke to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that, which I suppose, nedeth no reprehension? why shuld I not rather challenge that liberty that is graunted to euery vocation of learninge, yea to the lawyer himself? namely, to intermingle with painful trauayles of the minde, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pleasures of some exercise more plausible and milde, especially, where the same may be practised to the glory of god &amp; to the profit of our brethren, as I trust, this is, or at the leastwyse was intended. Well, if all this notwithstanding, these curious carpers wil neuer be satisfied, let them at their pleasures blow abroade what they list, and holde on in their myslikings, vntyll in the vanytie of their purposes, and the rage of their enuie, they shal at the length be glutted with the fulnesse of ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure and vnciuill reproches. You (finally) I doubt not, wyl take this gyfte as I meane it, and deeme of it as a thing not vnnecessarily sent abroad at this in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stant. God graunt vnto it such effect in the harts of all those vnto whom it specially appertayneth, that they, or rather euery English soule may say in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency of a sownde faith: <hi>Domine, quid ego retribuam tibi pro omnibus quae tribuisti mihi?</hi> What reward shall I geue vnto thee (O Lord) for all the benefittes that thou hast done vnto me?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 116.</note> In which prayer I think it conueniēt here to make an ende At <hi>Barnards</hi> Inne this ioyfull Eue of our 17. day of <hi>Nouember.</hi> 1575. with his hande whose hart loueth this instaunt day and you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Edward Hake.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>