<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To them that are opposite to this worke.</title>
           <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106113_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106113</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To them that are opposite to this worke.</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology for actors : Containing three briefe treatises. 1 Their antiquity. 2 Their ancient dignity. 3 The true vse of their quality. Written by Thomas Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To them that are opposite to this worke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>CEase your detracting tongues contest no more,</l>
      <l>Leaue off for shame to wound the Actors fame,</l>
      <l>Seeke rather their wrong'd credit to restore,</l>
      <l>Your enuy and detractions, quite disclaime:</l>
      <l>You that haue term'd their sports lasciuious, vile,</l>
      <l>Wishing good Princes would them all exile;</l>
      <l>See here this question to the full disputed:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Heywood,</hi> hath you, and all your proofes confuted.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Wouldst see an Emperour and his Counsell graue,</l>
      <l>A noble Souldier acted to the life,</l>
      <l>A <hi>Romane</hi> Tyrant how he doth behaue</l>
      <l>Himselfe: at home, abroad, in peace, in strife?</l>
      <l>Wouldst see what's loue, what's hate, what's foule ex-cesse,</l>
      <l>Or wouldst a Traytor in his kind expresse▪</l>
      <l>Our Stagerites can (by the Poets pen)</l>
      <l>Appeare to you to bee the selfe same men.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>What though a sort for spight, or want of wit,</l>
      <l>Hate what the best allow, the most forbeare,</l>
      <l>What exercise can you desire more fit,</l>
      <l>Then stately stratagemes to see and heare.</l>
      <l>What profit many may attaine by playes,</l>
      <l>To the most critticke eye this booke displaies,<note place="margin">Vid. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note>
      </l>
      <l>Braue men, braue acts, being brauely acted too,</l>
      <l>Makes, as men see things done, desire to do.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And did it nothing but in pleasing sort,</l>
      <l>Keepe gallants from mispending of their time,</l>
      <l>It might suffice: yet here is nobler sport,</l>
      <l>Acts well contriu'd, good Prose, and stately rime.</l>
      <l>To call to Church, <hi>Campanus</hi> bels did make,</l>
      <l>Playes, dice, and drinke inuite men to forsake:</l>
      <l>Their vse being good then vse the Actors well,</l>
      <l>Since ours all other Nations farre excell.</l>
   </lg>
   <signed>AR: HOPTON.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>