<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Readers, grace and peace from God, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>W., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106486_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07767</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18146</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106486</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Readers, grace and peace from God, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>W., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations vpon Psal. 101. Written first in French, by Philip Mornai lord of Plessis, and by him dedicated to Henrie the fourth, the French king. And now translated into English, for the benefit of the christian reader, by T.W</title>
                 <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 174 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian Readers, grace and peace from God, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beseech you all, of what state soeuer, with carefull attendance, and serious thoughts, to view and read ouer this Treatise following. This motion I make, not for any doubt or suspition J haue of any vnsound matter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for J am persuaded it containeth in it the truth of God: But because I am acquainted with, or at the least wise not ignorant of those ordinarie stops and lets, that hinder our growth in goodnes by good things, as Sathans malice, our blind and ignorant harts, our carelesse minds, discouragements from others, and sundrie such like: by means whereof, men are many times misseled: and because also I am sure
<pb facs="7"/>these things may, nay will fall out, in perusing and reading euen the best things, I can not but againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine entreat you herein also to haue a good eye to your selues and your own soules. Assuredly you shall find (spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if you weigh things well, as in deed you should) that you haue great and good cause so to doe: for besides that the points handled therin are not meane, neither of any simple subiect, and therefore would be regarded and receiued with care and conscience of them: the very manner of handling of them (according to the vsuall course and practise of the Author) is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and pithie, and therefore also will require a diligent and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing heart: The treatie was first written in French by a worthy Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of that country, and therfore doth most properly appertain to that state.
<pb facs="7"/>That which peculiarly belongeth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, vnderstand it of, and referre it to the same. The rest that is common, and according to general truth, make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but yet good vse withall of it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so. And this premonition I think ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meet to giue, as knowing before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand how ready men are to snatch and catch at that which belongeth not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, their times, and states: a point arguing great curiositie, and no small lightnesse of mind, and lacke of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: as also carelesly to neglect, yea securely to contemne that which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth them much, a matter bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carelesnes at the least, if not sence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesnesse of heart; from both which, as all other extreames, I wish the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reader, as my selfe, in this and in all other things of the like nature, to be freed and purged, and on the other side to be fulfilled with all sound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="8"/>and carefulnesse of spirit, that so from this and other good things, we may alwaies learne to know what that good, holy, and acceptable will of his is, and may be enabled by the blessed spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, stedfastly to beleeue the same, and carefully to walk in the obedience ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now the very God of peace sanctifie you thorowout: and I pray also, that your whole spirit and soule, and bodie, may be kept blamelesse, vntill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Iesus Christ, to whom euery where, but specially in the church, be praise for euer &amp; euer. Sobeit.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer in Christ. <hi>T. W.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>