<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL WEAKE Christians that haue a desire to be saued.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106042_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14114</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24421</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106042</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL WEAKE Christians that haue a desire to be saued.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A siluer vvatch-bell : The sound wherof is able (by the grace of God) to win the most profane worldling, and carelesse liuer, if there be but the least sparke of grace remaining in him, to become a true Christian indeed, that in the end he may obtaine euerlasting saluation. Whereunto is annexed, a treatise of the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Cotton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 128, 131-277, pages 248, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL WEAKE Christians that haue a desire to be saued.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a necessary rule in pollicie (dearely beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ) that those ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties shuld be garded round, which are besieged round, and it was <hi>Cambices</hi> counsell too, that Citizens which would keepe their Cities in safety, &amp; flourishing esta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, should euer bee watchfull, as if the enemies were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching. As this is good pollicie for Cities or Garrison townes, so also Christ Iesus in the Gospell, knowing
<pb facs="3"/> that his Church should haue manie enemies, and foreseeing the danger that might come vnto it by securitie, cōmendeth, &amp; cōmaundeth watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to his Disciples &amp; seruants: for security hath euer greatly endāmaged Gods church. Security made <hi>Bethel, Bethauen:</hi> the sweet valley, a valley of salt: <hi>Syon,</hi> a den for Foxes: &amp; <hi>Hierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Hieruschica:</hi> that is, a most home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; vnpleasant place. And who seeth not, that the greater number of men at this day, are so lulled a sleepe in the chaire of securitie, by the loue of the world, by the sinfull delights of the flesh, and by the subtile suggestions of Sathan, (which they suspect not) that they can as hardly be awaked, as <hi>Endymion</hi> from his endlesse sleepe? In the one eare, Security sounding, It is not yet time: In the other eare, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption singing, It will be time still. And thus with the Dolphin they swim in delights, when destruction
<pb facs="3"/> is nearest: till at the last, Desperation, the handmaide of Securitie, plaieth her part, sheweth them the houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glasse, and wofully telleth them the time is past.</p>
   <p>The consideration hereof moued me (Christian reader) according to my simple art and skill, to frame this booke, as a <hi>Watch-bell,</hi> to sounde in the eares of all men, not one stroke alone, but twelue, in twelue seuerall Chapters: which may serue as the wheeles of a Watch-bell, to inforce it to yeeld forth the more shrill sound, thereby to awake the most drowsie harted sinners, from their security &amp; carelesse liuing, to enter into a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratiō how their case standeth with God, &amp; finding themselues, by their forepassed wicked life, not worthy of the least of Gods mercies, they may reforme their liues, and seeke speedily to be reconciled vnto Christ.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>And I doe hartily wish that this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of mine, may be vnto all those, (which desire to be heires of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting kingdome of Christ,) so sweet a creation in soule, as were the 12. fountaines of water in <hi>Elim,</hi> to the people of <hi>Israel: Num.</hi> 3.3. and that it may yeelde a healing plaster to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wounded soule, no lesse effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, then the leaues of the tree of life, which bare 12. seueral fruites, to heale the nations. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. Reade it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fote diligently, and with a single hart, and I doubt not but in the ende thou wilt praise God both for the booke and the Author, as some wel disposed haue done, who haue confessed, that it was the first meanes vnder God, that wrought their conuersion, and haue bene importunate suters for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing of the same: wherein I haue done my endeuour, and commend the successe vnto God, and to him I will euermore pray, that it may worke
<pb facs="4"/> the like effect in many, that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Church may be daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>