<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Hutton, Luke</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106173_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03921</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14029</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106173</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hutton, Luke</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blacke dogge of Newgate : both pithie and profitable for all readers</title>
                 <author>Hutton, Luke</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Simson, Gabriel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Readers, for my Repentance was so welcome, and so much the better because it was mine: in some parte to satisfie your courtesies, I thought it my part to present you with thankes, and more, with my se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond labour: which albeit, it be both my especiall cost and trauell, yet it is yours: and so I may say, for you are willing to paye the prize of the Black Dogge of Newgate. Meruaile not Gentlemen, that you pay so deare for a Dogge, indeed a Curre: I wish you all well, and though three halfe-pence be a Dogs price, yet if you according to my Poesie, accept my Penne and Paper, it will counteruaile the charge of six pence. You haue knowne me better if you euer knew me, and neuer worse if you now know me: But for I haue read some bookes of Philosophie, I thought it best to be my selfe, not as I was, for I hope you are otherwise perswaded, but as I am, and so to liue or die. But for it is no better then the Blacke Dogge of Newgate: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you not to thinke your time ill bestowed in the reading, nor the prise great which you gaue for it. When you haue perused it, if you like it not, say the Dogge came from New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, hang him vp, and rend the Paper in peeces, and I will be your debter a worke of better acceptance, yet let me giue you to vnderstand by the way, that this Dogge, and many Dogs of his kinde, haue I knowne a great while, and if I had not had great occasion, I would neuer haue bestowed so much time <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>: Nay more, that you shall not thinke
<pb facs="4"/>
this Dogge nor any of his kinde to be as they haue beene, the murtherers and vtter vndooing at the least of an infinite number, to be shadowed by the name of Seruant at Newgate, at this time I thought good faithfully to giue you to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that he who was euer able to keepe a good Dogge, and now to make choyse of his seruants in Newgate, did in my sight, thrust this Dogge by the head and shoulders out of Newgate, making choise of men insteed of Dogges: and more I dare say, neuer shall a Curre in shape of man commit the like abuses, during his time in Newgate. No more for the Dogge of Newgate, but for this Dogge of mine, wish me still well, I will neuer doe you ill, so to your content as I wish, I leaue you and me to my better content when God will.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>For euer fare you well,</hi> Luke Hutton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>