<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Here after folowe the prologue of the four last thinges</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1479</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106511_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5758</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106511</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Here after folowe the prologue of the four last thinges</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Thus endeth the prologue of this book named. Cordʿyal. Whiche treteth of the four last and final thinges that ben to come</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caxton, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Westminster</pubPlace>
                    <date>1479</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>156 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <head>Here after folowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the prologue of the four last thinges</head>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>
      <hi>MEmorare nouissima et ineternum non pecca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis. Ecclesiastici. septimo capitulo. Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>asticus</hi> saith in his seuenth chapiter thise wordes <abbr>folowyng</abbr>. Bere wel in thy mynde the last thingis. and thou shalt neuer fal in synne. Also. <hi>Seynt Austyn.</hi> saith in his book of meditacions. That man ought rather haue in fere <abbr>and</abbr> eschewe thabhominacion̄ &amp; filthe of synne than ony other crueltees of thinfernal turmentis. Lo then̄e how the knowlege of these four last thinges and <abbr>fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quentyng</abbr> the memorye <abbr>and</abbr> remembraunce of them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us from synne / <abbr>and</abbr> draweth us to vertu / <abbr>and</abbr> confor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth vs to alle <abbr>good</abbr> werkis. Wherfor by the helpe of the deuyne inspiracion I haue <abbr>purposed</abbr> to reherse and saye a lytyl of these four thingis As which they be / and what they be. And also to declare somwhat of euery of them sin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gulerly by them self / precyously <abbr>and</abbr> dignely by seyngis <abbr>and</abbr> auctoritees of seyntis / <abbr>and</abbr> generally by examples <abbr>and</abbr> seyngis of auctorised clerkis. It is to be noted that after the <abbr>seyng</abbr> of seyntes men seye comynly / ther be foure the last thnigis. And whiche they be it apperith clerly by the wordes of seynt <hi>Bernard</hi> in a sermon Where he seyth in al thi werkes haue remembraunce of thy last thingis. Whiche be four. That is to wete first. Deth bodely. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde. The day of Iugement. Thirde. The peynes of helle Fourth The glorie of heuen. O what thinge is more hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible than deth. What <abbr>thing</abbr> is more <abbr>dredefull</abbr>
      <abbr>and</abbr> terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the day of Iugement. What <abbr>thing</abbr> is more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable to be suffred / than the gehenne and peynes of helle And what is a more <abbr>Ioyefull</abbr> blysse / than celestial glorie
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Seint Bernard</hi> seyde in the same sermone. These ben the four wheles of the chare / wherof the remembrance bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth mannes sowle to the <abbr>euerlasting</abbr> glorie of paradys These ben also foure moeuynges / that awake the spiryte of man to that ende / that he disprayse <abbr>all</abbr> worldly thinges and retorne vnto his creatour and maker. Lo it is then̄ bothe conuenient <abbr>and</abbr> prouffitable that they be <abbr>had</abbr> conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuelly in remembraunce. <abbr>And</abbr> therfor seyth the. Wise man. in the xxviij chapitre of <hi>Ecclesiasticus.</hi> Bere in thy mynde the last <abbr>and</abbr> final thinges. <abbr>And</abbr> loke alweye perfyghtly vpon them to thentent that they may be seurely <abbr>fixed</abbr>
      <abbr>and</abbr>
      <abbr>printed</abbr> in thy memorie. Now syn al this pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cesse principally and soueraynly enforseth hym self tenduce euery creature to haue an <abbr>assured</abbr> mynde <abbr>and</abbr> an hole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraūce of these four last thinges / and that they may cordyally be <abbr>enprinted</abbr> with in your hertes. Therfor it is consonant <abbr>and</abbr>
      <abbr>accordyng</abbr> / yf it so may plese / that this present trayttye may be <abbr>entitled</abbr>
      <abbr>and</abbr> bere the name of the. <hi>Cordyal.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>¶Thus endeth the prologue of this book <abbr>named</abbr>. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyal.</hi> Whiche treteth of the four last <abbr>and</abbr> final thinges that ben to come. ¶<abbr>And</abbr> here beginneth the first parte of the seide four last thinges.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>