<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106548_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04534</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14656</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106548</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Duke of Saxonie his iubilee : with a short chronologie. Both shewing the goodnesse of God, in blessing the Gospel of Christ, since Luther first opposed the Popes pardons</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader; It is an abhorred custome of the Synagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> to publish <hi>common prayers</hi> in a straunge tongue: it would be (at least) a blame worthy ouersight in these our home planted Churches of Christ not to publish <hi>common prayses</hi> in our vulgar tongue. The former taketh away the possibility of saying <hi>Amen</hi> with our owne spirits: the latter neglecteth a iust oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of finging a ioynt (though as yet an earthly) <hi>Halelu-iah</hi> with Gods Saintes: Receiue therefore here offered to thine hands <hi>common praises</hi> in thy propper language, to wit, a <hi>Iubile</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued in <hi>Saxonie,</hi> &amp; by the translation of a worthy Minister in our London Dutch Church, made a reioycing assumed in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> Were it not translated, it could not be vnderstood, were it not vnderstood it could not be a reioycing to the English, which get it ought to be, because it ministreth matter of praises to God common to them with the Dutch. Our rule willeth it should be common. For when the <hi>Proper</hi> in <hi>(Psal. 102.)</hi> had made it a note of all Gods seruants that <hi>they take pleasure in the ston<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s of Zion,</hi> and a promise of their Maister that <hi>he would build vp Zion,</hi> he concludeth in <hi>Psal. 18.</hi> that <hi>This shall be written for the generations to come, and the people which shall be created shall praise the Lord.</hi> Now wee and all Gods people wheresoeuer, make vp all but one body, the Church (which is <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) the requickening and recollecting of whose members was in part, by <hi>Luther</hi> effected: we haue all but one head, Christ, the functions of whom, and sole effecacy of whose merits were by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> cleared, and defended: we haue all but one Faith &amp; Gospell, which in fundamentall pointes was by <hi>Luther</hi> professed, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated. Seeing therefore this requickening of the Churches members, this defence of Christs merits, this profession of the true Faith made in the beginning of the next preceding age are
<pb facs="3"/>
here ioyfully recognized let that promise of the rearing of <hi>Zion,</hi> once written, now performed, stirre vp vs the generations follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>England</hi> as well as in <hi>Germany,</hi> to praise the Lord. Hereby shall we shew the feeling of fellow members, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saint-like beleeuers in preferring <hi>Ierusalem</hi> aboue our chiefest ioy: <hi>Psal. 137.6.</hi> Adde we to our rule commanding, the examples of others prouoking to make this matter of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing common. Diuerse other partes of <hi>Germany</hi> in a godly imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation haue Iubilized with <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and in some places, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath caused new coynes to be stamped with sentences compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the letters numerall of the yeere. <hi>1617.</hi> terminating the Age since <hi>Luther</hi> first set vp his propositions. These let vs follow howsoeuer, perhaps, not in stamping the letters of the yeere v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our coynes, yet in imprinting the glad tidings thereof in our hearts. You see (gentle reader) that this Iubile ought to bee common: now that it may be more common, vnderstand that it is Christian. Here is not any Popish rite, sauouring of iudaisme, thrust vpon any of the Churches. For why? <hi>Rome,</hi> in an apish (because vnwarranted) imitation of the Iewish Church, retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yeares of Iubile as a perpetuated rite of the Gospell: the Churches of Christ doe not so: <hi>Rome</hi> appointeth state or set times for her Iubilies: the Churches of Christ doe not so. This presented Iubile of <hi>Saxonie</hi> is my warrant. The occasion whereof was taken from a prophecy currantly receiued among the Papists (though as blinde in the vttering, as false in the euent) namely, that <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine should breath out its last, with the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of an hundreth yeeres. Which being layed and weighed in the ballance by the Christian Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and other Princes, together with their owne experimentall knowledge of the now more then euer, flourishing and roote-taking of the doctrine of the Gospell both throughout <hi>Germany,</hi> and in other countries, they not onely founde that Prophecy to light and the Prophets therof vaine, but also thought fit, by way of an holy Triumph, and Feast (as it were) of shouting, thankefully to solemnize the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their manumission from the thraldome of Antchrist, by the hand of God vpon <hi>Luther,</hi> and through <hi>Luther</hi> iust an hundreth yeeres before. So that the occasion &amp; time hereof being
<pb facs="3"/>
of so extraordinary nature, no doubt but God is hereby much glorified, in that by the same the hearts of his people are more quickened to the more affectionate embracino of his truth so graciously continued And here, if thou wilt giue me leaue I will aduenture to make a surer Prophecy then thr Papists did, <hi>viz.</hi> The second comming of Mahomet for the strengthening of the Turkish Infidel, and the exterpation of <hi>Luthers</hi> purer doctrine for the confirming of the Popish, shall fall out both in a yeere. When this will bee, let the Pope enquire of the Musti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and in meane time that I presage truely bee thou pleased to gather out of the Preface of a learned man in <hi>Scotland</hi> before the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Spalato</hi> his reasons of departure or there printed. Which, being full of most worthy obseruations helping to fill vp the measure of our ioy, I haue hereunto prefixed. Neither haue I onely prefixed these, as helping to fill, but also adioyned to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, celebrated in the last, a <hi>Chronologie</hi> continued yeerely from the first of that hundreth since <hi>Luther,</hi> as fulfilling that measure of ioy. This was penned in Latine by students in <hi>Worms</hi> and printed at <hi>Heidelberge</hi> and now translated into English. For a more cleare insight into the prosperous successe of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, therein but touched, I referre thee to an Oration of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend and learned, <hi>Scultetus</hi> made in the <hi>Arch-Palatine</hi> Court, and called a <hi>Secular Sermon.</hi> Now this <hi>Chronoligy,</hi> I say, fulfilleth our ioy, in that whereas among the Iewes fifty yeeres fourtie nine were of <hi>seruice,</hi> the last onely of <hi>releasing,</hi> euery one of our hundreth assureth vs of the release of some either Churches or Persons, from <hi>Romes</hi> Aegiptian bondadge and Babilonish captiuitie, howsoeuer in (indeede) <hi>Marke-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie de Dominis</hi> may well make the last notoriously solemne. This in breife of the Gospells Iubile, with a word more of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish, I will conclude. The Papists (forsooth) hearing of this Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing of Christ his Churches thought it stood not with the policy of there kingdome to sit still leaning on their elbowes, and hanging their eares. How then? They put good faces on it, force out a laughter; and celebrate a <hi>Iubile.</hi> Did they not feare, may we thinke, that the report of our ioyfull release would cause many to free themselues from their bonds? But see we what the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate.
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>A Iubilee,</hi> surely but <hi>verba-tenus</hi> in name onely, <hi>reate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in nature, a Fast. Yea, <hi>Simulatum Iubelaeum fit duplex jeiunium:</hi> Their Iubile fained makes their Fast doubled. Wherefore I may apply that to the Synagogue of Rome which the Poet spake of another, <hi>Spem vultu simulat, prem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t alto corde dolorem,</hi> Whilst hope in face sits counterfeit, heart-pressing greife makes pulses beate. Behold their Iubile which should argue ioy; and ioy the Spirits dilatation, is become a <hi>Fast,</hi> whose associate is greife, and greifes the Spirits compression. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their clapping of handes is nought else but wringing of hands; their shoutings, groanings; their release, bondage; their feastings, fastings. And iustly may they so do. For such fasting is to them a signe that our bridegrome Christ is not among them: for if the Bridgrome were with them how could they mourne? <hi>Mat. 9, 15.</hi> But I desire they may still mourne, and be inwardly vexed not so much for the downefall of their abhominations, as for their abhominations themselues, and doe thou (good Reader) take vp with me in their behalfe the prayer of the Prophet <hi>Psal. 83.19. Fill their faces with shame O Lord, that they may know thy name.</hi> This is the worst I wish them, with which and mine earnest wishes to thee that thou wouldest clappe hands with those in exultation with whom thou art to claspe handes in holy profession, I leaue these treatises to thy view, and thy selfe to the watchfull eye of Gods prouidence: <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>