<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull Hugh Perry, and Henry Andrewes▪ the two Sheriffes of the Honourable City London, last Elected.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106209_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03228</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106209</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull Hugh Perry, and Henry Andrewes▪ the two Sheriffes of the Honourable City London, last Elected.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londini artium &amp; scientiarum scaturigo. Or, Londons fountaine of arts and sciences : Exprest in sundry triumphs, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honorable Nicholas Raynton into the Maiorty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious proiects both by water and land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Haberdashers. Written by Thomas Hayvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull <hi>Hugh Perry,</hi> and <hi>Henry Andrewes▪</hi> the two Sheriffes of the <hi>Honourable City</hi> London, <hi>last</hi> Elected.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>ight Worshipfull, and euery way wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; Your <hi>Armes</hi> display'd in the Front of this Show, approue your Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and your Trafficke and Commerce, (being free Merchant-aduentures) testifis to the World your Noble Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; as Trading in the <hi>East-Indies, Turkey, Italy, Spayne,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. to the Honour of our Nation abroad, and singular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits redounding to the <hi>Realme</hi> at home. Your more priuate Imployments heretofore, aswell in furthering Arts, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coureging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rmes, adding no common Luster to these Offices, vnto which Time and your owne Demerits haue at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent called you. Then as that Publicke weale is most blest and flourishing where the Gouernours are aswell beloued in their Persons, as feared in their Places: So likewise it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to all such as are in Authority, to fieare themselues
<pb facs="4"/>
by the rule of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that is, <hi>To heare courteously, answere discreetly, consider seriously, and sentence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially.</hi> But I presume not to aduise, where I rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to be instructed; shatting vp my present Seruice with that of <hi>Seneca, Id facere laus est quod decet, non quod licet.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to bee commanded.
<hi>Thomas Heywood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>