<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTUOUS AND NOBLY DISPOSED. Gentlewomen, Mistris FRANCIS FORTESCU, wife unto Ma. JOHN FORTESCU: And Mistris ELIZABETH DUNCOMB, wife unto Ma∣ster WILLIAM DUNCOMB of Badlesden.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106882_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22608</idno>
           <idno type="STC">907</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTUOUS AND NOBLY DISPOSED. Gentlewomen, Mistris FRANCIS FORTESCU, wife unto Ma. JOHN FORTESCU: And Mistris ELIZABETH DUNCOMB, wife unto Ma∣ster WILLIAM DUNCOMB of Badlesden.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tragi-comicall history of our times, under the borrowed names of Lisander and Calista</title>
                 <author>Audiguier, Vital d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 247, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTUOUS AND NOBLY DISPOSED. Gentlewomen, Mistris FRANCIS FORTESCU, wife unto Ma. JOHN FORTESCU: And Mistris ELIZABETH DUNCOMB, wife unto Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster WILLIAM DUNCOMB of Badlesden.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My most Honoured,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His French Knight and his Lady be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing importuned, contrary to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe, and the fashion of this time (which is almost all French) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to publick view in this their Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish habite; and knowing how subject strangers are to malignant humours (a disposition growne so common, that like a contagious disease, it hath infected almost the whole world) they have made humbly bold to expose themselves abroad under your auspicious and candide names, hoping they may be more free from censure, and more boldly tell their Loves, their Feares, their Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, their Imprisonments, their Jealousies, and their Joyes. They have in their native country served under the protection of a great King, where the gentlenesse of
<pb facs="3"/>
their spirits had a generall approbation; and now their hope (let it not be accounted presumption) is, that you, according to your accustomed noble goodnesse, will not refuse it unto them here, where they are poore strangers, at the least that they may (resting by you) await your leisure, when, by their conversation, they may endevour to rob away tediousnesse though but from one houre, to which the greatest mortals are at sometime subject. This is their highest ambition; and my only end (not capable of greater expression) is to witnesse my affection to your services, from intending whereof onely death shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most humble and most devoted servant, <hi>W.D.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>