<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Commendatorie Epistle.</title>
           <author>Elton, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106649_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16890</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3786</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106649</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Commendatorie Epistle.</title>
                 <author>Elton, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The third part of The true vvatch : containing the call of the Lord, to awake all sorts to meet him with intreatie of peace, and to turne unto him by true repentance: shewing what causes we have forthwith to betake our selves to watching and prayer. Taken out of the visio of Ezekiel, chap. 9. By Iohn Brinsley</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>74, 568, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter_of_commendation">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A Commendatorie Epistle.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Author (Christian Reader)
having desired first my censure,
now sundrie yeeres agoe, and
since my joint testimonie, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
this worke, that by the mouth
or two or three witnesses, God
might make it more effectuall, for
accomplishing all the good his heart desireth; I could
no way justly denie the same: seeing as the ends,
which it propoundeth and wholly aimeth at, are
only to helpe to further the way to our unfained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
for the generall happinesse of us all, yea even
of every soule; and that our glory may be continued
to us, and to our posteritie; so he hath long tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled
in the same, and used all holy meanes of triall
and examination, that there might be nothing in it,
but that which is necessarie to these ends, and which
might stand before the Lords Tribunall. For the
Author himselfe, though I have knowne him from
my childhood, being borne neere unto him, brought
up in the same Grammar Schoole, and after, in the
same Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and ever since beene
most familiarly acquainted with him, and therefore
could speake more in this case then I take to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient,
yet I may wholly spare that paines; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
his owne faithfull and happy labours have so
long agoe commended him, and made him and his
holy affection for the good of all, so well knowne
<pb facs="4"/>
to the Church of God. As first, the first part of this
<hi>True watch, the Rule of Life,</hi> so much approved of all
religious Christians, to whose hands it hath come,
that it hath now the ninth time seene the Presse, and
gone thorow the triall,<note n="*" place="margin">See the Preface before it to the Christian Reader.</note> Wherein he hath set out to
the view of all, the holinesse and integritie of that way
of life, which we all jointly professe (according to
Gods sacred word, and the good Lawes of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Commonweale) to the justifying of our Church
against the Separatists, to be the true Church of Iesus
Christ, and that whosoever so walketh shall undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
finde eternall life, and in the meane while all
heavenly boldnesse, peace and joy. And not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
them, but also against the superstitious and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous
Papists, who herein slander our Religion, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming
it to be a religion of carnall libertie, theirs of
holinesse, ours full of divisions and uncertaintie, theirs
of perfect unitie, thereby to draw our people to a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
of the eternall truth of our blessed God, and to a
liking of that popish way, which is nothing but meere
superstition in outward shews of devotion, according
to mens inventions, and such as God never comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
or required; nay such as God hath most expresly
forbidden, as tending to utter perdition, both of soules
and bodies. So secondly, the second part of this <hi>True
watch, the Rule of Praier,</hi> in which he hath manifested
his holy desire and unfained love to the Church of
God and his native Countrie, for a perfect peace and
unitie, with all happinesse in the same, and hath so la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured
to trace out the most sure and plaine way, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
the direction of our blessed Saviour, as that
whosoever striveth so to watch &amp; pray, shall undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
be amongst them that are as the Chariots and
<pb facs="4"/>
horsemen of Israel, and helpe to save the Iland. And
in the third place in his Schoole labours, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
of our children and posteritie, he hath fully witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
his longing desire of the perpetuall flourishing of
this our Church and Nation; concerning which tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell,
(to omit all other)<note n="a" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hali</hi> Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorie Preface. The Iesuites have wonne much of their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and stollen many hearts with their diligence: in this kinde we may outstrip them if wee want not to our selves. Behold heere, not feet, but wings offered to us; neither are these directions of meere spec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lation, but such as for the most part, to the knowledge of my selfe, and many abler judges, have beene and are daily answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his experience and practise, with more then usuall suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse What remaines therefore, but that the thankfull accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of men, and his effectuall labours should mutually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he may be encouraged by the one, and they by the other bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ited, &amp;c.</note> that one testimonie of the
learned Doctor <hi>Hall,</hi> that worthie Deane of Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,
in his Commendatorie Preface before his booke,
called <hi>Ludus Literarius,</hi> or the Grammar Schoole, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated
to Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> and Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> (speaking
out of his owne experience and of sundry other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
many yeeres agoe) may fully suffice. And much
more now of late, that more then ordinarie witnesse
by that learned<note n="b" place="margin">The Preface of Mr. <hi>Butlours</hi> Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, by <hi>I. M.</hi> to the Reader.</note> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Butlour</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> in his fourth
Edition of his Rhetoricke, who in stead of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations
of many other of principall note, which
especially in <hi>Oxford</hi> are wont to be prefixed before
any worke of speciall worth as that is; taketh only
the testimonie of this Author, in a place or two in his
Grammar-Schoole, and sets it before his booke, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead
of many; there commending him for that worke,
as having by it deserved worthily of all good lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
Therefore seeing in all his labours his good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
towards the Church of God, our dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,
with all his royall Progenie and dominions,
doth cleerely appeare,<note place="margin">Si in Authoris ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>isve laudem (studiose lector) multorum hîc, pro more, suffragia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiras; instar multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum sit hoc vnum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terati illius, &amp; ob ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitam docend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodum, de bonis l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru optimè merit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistri <hi>Iohannis Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flei:</hi> cujus in suo Lud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> literario, <hi>or the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar Schoole,</hi> cap. 16. hac sunt verba, &amp;c.</note> seeking only the wealth of all,
and to unite all hearts, as unto the Lord of heaven, so
to our Soveraigne Lord and King, and to his royall
seed for our happinesse for ever, with what thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
acceptation are all his labours to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?
And this above all the former, wherein he now
only strives to helpe to awaken us out of our dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest
securitie, in the midst of our extremest perill,
<pb facs="5"/>
and necessitie; and when the times call us to watch
and pray, yea to fast and pray, if ever heretofore.
First I say to rise up and watch, that we may pray.
To pray for the distressed state of all the poore Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
and our brethren abroad, who mourne and
wring their hands by reason of their slaveries,
butcheries, manifold feares and miseries, both of
their soules and bodies: above all for them of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia
and the Palatinate, the very chiefe of them a
principall part of our selves; and withall for our
brethren of France now in great tribulation for the
profession of Christs Gospell; taking their case to
heart as feeling members, little knowing how soone
it may be our owne, and ever fearing that terrible
curse from the Angell of the Lord;<note place="margin">Ier. 5. 23.</note> Curse ye Meroz
(said the Angell) curse the inhabitants thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
they came not out to helpe the Lord against the
mightie. Secondly to watch and pray, yea to mourne
and crie for the fearfull viols of the Lords wrath (in
all likelihood) so neerely readie to be powred
downe upon our own heads, unlesse we speedily meet
the Lord in unfained repentance. If in the yeere 88.
all sorts so generally feared it; when yet at our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
humiliation in fasting and praier by publike
commandement, and our promising amendment,
God heard our cries, deferred the execution of his
wrath upon us; and contrarily fought for us from
heaven, arming the windes and waters for his
Church amongst us, how much more may we justly
feare it now. If then (I say) all joyntly confessed,
that if God had so dealt with us, as he threatned, we
had most righteously deserved it, for all our hainous
abominations, and for that no other meanes could
<pb facs="5"/>
prevaile with us; and if in our severall acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
praiers and thanksgivings upon sundrie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions
since, we have againe and againe confessed as
much, how much more truly may we now at this
present? Seeing the Lord hath granted us since not
one yeere more alone, to see if wee would meet him
truly with intreatie of peace, and unfained submissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but ten, yea thrice ten yeere and more, and also
used all meanes to reclaime us, both by abundant
fatherly corrections, and in his long patience and
commiseration given us our third most dreadfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,
at the powder treason, never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten,
when he even plucked us out of the furnace;
and now that our sinnes are, in stead of repenting, ten
times more increased through all those meanes (in
the judgement of all who rightly consider of them:)
how can we expect any longer mercy? What can we
looke for now in that we see men so generally (chiefly
most of our Gallants) to make but a mocke of sinne,
yea of all Gods admonitions at home and abroad,
hating all true pietie, and scorning it under most
odious names? Or how can we thinke truly that our
land is purged of any of our abominations, but
stands presently guiltie of them all, having now fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
up our measure, seeing we commit most of those
fearfull abominations so often confessed, with an
higher hand then ever heretofore? Or how can we
imagine that our land is out of danger, seeing many
amongst us begin to doat againe upon the bloudie
Romish Idolatrie; and that now our enemies are so
increased in Malice, Pride, and Multitude, and so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of the infernall Locusts feared to be in the midst
amongst us. My desire therefore is, that as this labour
<pb facs="6"/>
hath beene undertaken for the saving of us all, from
such a vengeance, as upon these grounds we have just
cause to feare, and for our perpetuall happinesse, and
must needs for that cause concerne us all, that every
one would take notice of it, and consider seriously of
every point, as God gives him opportunitie; especially
they who have leisure (and spend many houres, yea
many dayes and yeeres, either wickedly or at least
vainly, which will bring them nothing but sorrow in
the end) to helpe hereby to turne away the wrath, or
at least to save their owne soules. The worke is large
(I grant) but too large thou canst not thinke it, seeing
the Author of it desireth to make all plaine to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie
of the simplest, and truly to awake every soule,
and for that I know not of any point in it which doth
not directly tend hereunto, or can well be made shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
without hurt to the whole; chiefly the generall
good considered; that every sinner that repents not,
turning from his evill way, must die. And therefore
doubtlesse no man shall haue just cause to repent him
of his labour spent in hearing or reading of it, but if
God give him an heart by the right applying of it to
helpe to appease the wrath, or at least to turne, and to
seeke to cause others to turne, he shall have cause to
blesse the God of heaven for it; which that every one
may doe, and that we may all instantly set our selves
to seeke his face and favour, I humbly intreat his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
Majestie to grant, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus,
<hi>Edward Elton</hi> B. in D. and Pastor
of S. <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondsey
neere London.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>