<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vnto his worthy Friend, and industrious Artist, Master IOHN BABINGTON.</title>
           <author>Bate, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106893_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11293</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1099</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106893</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vnto his worthy Friend, and industrious Artist, Master IOHN BABINGTON.</title>
                 <author>Bate, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pyrotechnia or, A discourse of artificiall fire-works : in which the true grounds of that art are plainly and perspicuously laid downe: together with sundry such motions, both straight and circular, performed by the helpe of fire, as are not to be found in any other discourse of this kind, extant in any language. VVhereunto is annexed a short treatise of geometrie, contayning certaine definitions and problemes, for the mensuration of superficies and sollids, with tables for the square root to 25000, and the cubick root to 10000 latus, wherein all roots under those numbers are extracted onely by ocular inspection. VVritten by Iohn Babington gunner, and student in the mathematicks</title>
                 <author>Babington, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 72, 4, 80, 200 pages, 2 folded plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>Vnto his worthy Friend, and industrious Artist, Master IOHN BABINGTON.</head>
   <l>VVHen as <hi>I</hi> did thy Booke by chance espie,</l>
   <l>With divers figures grac't, most curiously</l>
   <l>Contriu'd, all new, and of thine own invention,</l>
   <l>With sundry Engines made by iust proportion:</l>
   <l>I did admire thy skill, thy active braine,</l>
   <l>Whereby those things thou didst so well attaine:</l>
   <l>Justly I might, for of no Nation yet,</l>
   <l>There's any hath this path so fully beat;</l>
   <l>Nor laid those grounds that thou hast done, whereby</l>
   <l>We might attaine to things that tend so high.</l>
   <l>For sencelesse things with life thou seem'st to fill,</l>
   <l>Making them wondred at by common skill.</l>
   <l>Thou sundry doubts unfold'st, and with much ease,</l>
   <l>Thou teachest us to measure Land and Seas.</l>
   <l>When as I thought on these, and knew how rare</l>
   <l>Men thus addicted, and thus given were,</l>
   <l>My mind, my hand, my hand did force my pen,</l>
   <l>T' offer my mite of thankes 'mongst other men.</l>
   <l>Accept it then, and let it no lesse bee</l>
   <l>Pleasing, then greater gifts are unto thee.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy truly affectionate, and wel-wishing Friend,</hi> John Bate.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>