<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106344_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06516</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16989</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106344</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A right comfortable treatise : containing fourteene pointes of consolation for them that labor and are laden: VVritten by D. Martin Luther to Prince Friderik Duke of Saxonie, he being sore sicke, thereby to comfort him in the time of his great distresse. Englished by W. Gace</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 84 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apostle Paul in the 15. chapter of his Epistle to the Romanes speaking of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian comfort, sayth: Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, VVhatsoeuer things haue ben written afore time, were written for our learning, that we through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and comfort of the Scriptures might haue hope. VVhereby he plainly teacheth that our comforts must be taken out of the holy Scriptures. Nowe the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vse two sortes of comfort, inasmuch as they commend vnto vs the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two sortes of things, namely of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill things and of good things, according as the wise man sayth: In the day of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction remember prosperitie: &amp; in the day of prosperitie be mindful of affliction. For the holy Ghost knoweth that euery thing is of such sort &amp; so great to man, of what sort and how great his opinion is thereof. For that which is counted vile &amp; nothing esteemed, doth litle moue, either with loue if it come, or with griefe if it depart. VVherefore he laboureth most earnestly
<pb facs="7"/>to call man from the opinion &amp; affection of thinges, which vvhen he hath brought to passe, all thinges are then indifferent. Novve forasmuch as this calling is done especially by the vvorde, vvhereby the opinion is transferred from the thinge, vvhich is presently felt to the thing vvhich either is absent or not presently felt, it is by good reason that vve shall haue no cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort but by the Scripture, which in the day of affliction calleth vs to the considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of prosperitie, vvhich is either present or to come: also in the day of prosperitie calleth vs to consider affliction. But that these considerations may be more easie vnto vs, vve vvill diuide either of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to seuen partes. To the former shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the euills vvhich are to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a man: First vvithin him selfe: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly before him: Thirdly behind him: Fourthly beneath him: Fiftly on the left hande: Sixtly on the right hand: Seuenthly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue him.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>