<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errata</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106782_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00665</idno>
           <idno type="STC">108</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106782</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errata</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary or, exposition vpon the diuine second epistle generall, written by the blessed apostle St. Peter. By Thomas Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bloome (Blome), Jacob</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 764, 2, 801-1634, 28 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>Errata</head>
   <p>PAge 16. line vlt. read <hi>Et.</hi> p. 17. l. 26. r. <hi>Timorous.</hi> p. 32. l. 27. r. <hi>Peace.</hi> p. 47. l. 50. r. <hi>Stocke.</hi> p. 97. l. 29. r. <hi>Heaven.</hi> p. 114. l. 30. r. <hi>Ierome.</hi> p. 156. line vlt. r. <hi>Me nothing.</hi> p. 159. l. 27. r. <hi>Not.</hi> p. 162. l. 10. r. <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God.</hi> p. 175. l. 44. r. <hi>This Name.</hi> p. 179. l. 51. r. <hi>Trust our.</hi> p. 186. l. 22. r. <hi>Beleeve not.</hi> p. 227. l. 14. r. <hi>Over.</hi> p. 229. line vlt. r. <hi>Iustitiary.</hi> p. 240. l. 37. r. <hi>Everlasting.</hi> p. 271. line vlt. r. <hi>The day.</hi> p. 282. l. 52. r. <hi>Weary.</hi> p. 289. l. 39. r. <hi>Is infidelity.</hi> p. 284. l. 34. r. <hi>Likenesse.</hi> p. 297. l. 47. r. <hi>Apprecate,</hi> p. 333. l. 14. r. <hi>Compasse us,</hi> p. 389. l. 30. r. <hi>Let me grone.</hi> p. 367. l. 2. r. <hi>Closure.</hi> p. 372. l. 2. r. <hi>Maimed.</hi> p. 392. l. 52. r. <hi>Treasures.</hi> And l. 54. blot out <hi>Shuts heaven where Christ shuts it;</hi> p. 403. l. 18. r. <hi>Panted.</hi> p. 415. l. 32. r. <hi>Fame.</hi> p. 456. l 35. r. <hi>And silkes.</hi> p. 479. l. 35. r. <hi>Averte</hi> And l. 41. r. <hi>One that shuts.</hi> p. 483. l. 6. r. <hi>Though.</hi> And l. 38. r. <hi>Impietie.</hi> p. 486. l. 1. r. <hi>Wakens my.</hi> p. 493. l. 46. <hi>God! How.</hi> p. 542. l. 6. r. <hi>Tells.</hi> 543. l. 15. r. <hi>Foure.</hi> p. 545 l. 29. <hi>It was.</hi> p. 546. l. 23. r. <hi>Willing.</hi> p. 550. l. 7. r. <hi>Ascend.</hi> And l. 20. r. <hi>Ejus.</hi> p. 552. l. 5. r. <hi>Planets</hi> And l. 12. r. <hi>Curtains.</hi> p. 557. l. 11. r. <hi>Grosse.</hi> p. 559. l. 53. r. <hi>be proud.</hi> And l. 54. r. <hi>rich.</hi> p. 564. l. 15. r. <hi>Ocnus.</hi> p. 618 l. 17. r. <hi>Should we not as.</hi> p. 744. l. 30. r. <hi>On.</hi> p. 745. l. 9. r. <hi>No.</hi> p. 1147. l. 26. r. <hi>This was not the.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There be diverse other misplacings, mispointings, and mistakings of words, with which no ingenious and ingenous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will charge the Author: who had neither leisure to overlooke the Presses in the printing, nor to review the coppy after it was finished. These which I transiently found, by reading some few lines of a point, as I was to make up the Index, I have set downe. By which you may ghesse at the rest, and in your faire charity pardon all.</p>
   <pb facs="828"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>