<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To such Ministers of
the Gospell as would seeme desirous of
reformation; and yet haue sub∣scribed
to the Arch-Bishop
of Canterburie his
Articles.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106214_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13963</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24273</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106214</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To such Ministers of
the Gospell as would seeme desirous of
reformation; and yet haue sub∣scribed
to the Arch-Bishop
of Canterburie his
Articles.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A triall of subscription : by way of a preface vnto certaine subscribers; and, reasons for lesse rigour against non-subscribers. Both modestly written; that neither should offend</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 28 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To such Ministers of
the Gospell as would seeme desirous of
reformation; and yet haue sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed
to the Arch-Bishop
of Canterburie his
Articles.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EVEREND Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
The</hi> reasons
<hi>following were writen
(as I am perswaded)
vpon occasion of that
godlie, wise, and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable
motion, which
was made in the last
Parliament for convenient fauour to be shewed
to godlie &amp; profitable Ministers, touching</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription
<hi>and vse of</hi> ceremonies. <hi>Whether
the author be a Minister or no, or what he is, I
am not for my part, any whit inquisitiue; and
doe wish, That all they who doe loue peace and
trueth, would diligentlie and charitablie consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the reasons without hearkening after the
reasoner, Least they occasion trouble to him,
who seemeth to desire the good of our Church.
But whosoeuer he bee, I presume on his patience
to publish his labours, For that (in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of sundry wise, and learned both Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="3"/>
&amp; other, they be thought worthy (for their
pith and modestie) such publication, and may
prooue (through</hi> Gods <hi>blessing) an happie
meane somewhat to calme that tempest, which
(too long) hath tossed the little Arke of Christe
his Church. And therfore, I hope, that none will
be offended, if I help forward that good which
(no doubt) the author intended. If none: Then
why should I feare that any of you will be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
with mee?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 41.</note>
      <hi>And yet I knowe</hi> the weaknes
of the flesh, bee the spirit neuer so wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<hi>to doe well.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note>
      <hi>For</hi> the wisedome of the
flesh (<hi>which is</hi> enemitie against God) <hi>will
readilie suggest; That these apologeticall</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<hi>will cause you to be worse thought of; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
yee either disclaime your</hi> subscription,
<hi>or publickly iustifie the same with sound reasons
from</hi> Gods <hi>worde. One of which I pray</hi> God
<hi>ye may haue grace to doe, That sincere teachers
of the same trueth, may either bee conformable
togither, or seeke reformacion togither. I will
not preiudice your iudgement, much lesse with</hi>
Aquila <hi>presume to</hi> expound vnto Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los
the waye of God more perfectlie:<note place="margin">Act. 18. 24. 25 26. 2. 3.</note>
      <hi>Yet, seeing</hi> Apollos <hi>humbled himselfe to the
informacion of a</hi> tentmaker; <hi>I persuade my
selfe, That ministers of the Gospell will giue me
leaue (being none of the greatest clearks) to seeke
resolutiō of this my doubt. For I freelie confesse,
That as yet I cannot see, but that ye haue sinned
againste the trueth by your conformitie. Yet
so, That I reuerence you as Fathers for your
<pb facs="3"/>
worke sake; and regard you as brethren for your
profession sake, your sinne of conformitie (if it
be a sinn) notwithstanding. For we are taught,</hi>
to consider one another,<note place="margin">Heb. 10. 24, 25.</note> to prouoke
vnto loue, and good workes; and not
to forsake the fellowshippe which we
haue among our selues, as the manner
of some is.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The groundes (if I may so speake) of my doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
be two: First, The euidence (so seeming to
mee) of certaine scriptures. Secondlie, The
weaknesse (in my poore opinion) of your excuses.
I meane not to quote manie places for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose;
and I cannot knowe all, you pretend for
your selues. I must and will therefore content
my selfe with some fewe: yet the most pregnant
(as I iudge) of either.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>From the former (quoted in the margent)
I take occasion (and I thinke vpon good ground)
to speake to your consciences in these wordes: If</hi>
woe be vnto them,<note place="margin">Esay. 5. 20. &amp; 445.</note> that speake good of
euill, and euill of good; <hi>If hee that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribeth</hi>
should subscribe to the Lorde,
<hi>that is, By subscription professe himselfe to bee
the Lordes; If hee,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 18. and 3. 3.</note> that buildeth againe
the things, that he hath destroyed, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
him selfe a trespasser; <hi>If they bee</hi>
foolish <hi>that</hi> after they haue begunne
in the Spirite; (<hi>that is, insinceritie of the
Gospell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reason. 1</note>
      <hi>(as the</hi> Reasoner <hi>speaketh</hi>) would
now bee made perfect by the flesh; <hi>and
if</hi> halting betweene two opinions,<note place="margin">1. King. 18. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
<pb facs="4"/>
a iust reproofe: Then I may admonish
you,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tim 5. 1.</note> as Fathers, <hi>to</hi> make straight steppes
vnto your feete, least that which is hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
bee turned out of the way.<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 13.</note>
      <hi>For in
the wisedome of the flesh you speake good (by</hi>
subscription) <hi>of carnall rites; whiche here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
ye haue reprooued in the spirite, and yet
mislike in your best iudgemente: So that yee
build againe the thinges yee haue destroyed, and
seeme (with some scandall) to halt betweene
two opinions. But I pray you, let vs enter with
humble heartes into consideration of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuses.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>First, It is auowed by some, That they haue
not subscribed</hi> simplie; <hi>but with</hi> protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<hi>and exceptions, Though they be not recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
Which (say they) is not their fault. And
(say I vnder correction) The</hi> Bb. of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie
<hi>and his associates doe well in not recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
such</hi> protestations <hi>and exceptions. For;
If they require a lawfull and godlie</hi> subscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<hi>Why then should they blemish their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
with recorded</hi> protestations? <hi>But,
Suppose their vrged</hi> subscription <hi>bee vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
doe ye not perceiue, How the not recording
of</hi> protestations <hi>doeth checke the weakenesse
of subscribers, who (by protestation doe solemne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
accuse their present subscription? Trulie (me
thinkes) you should either subscribe without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation;
Or, if you protest, you should not sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe.
For, Is not this</hi> Protesting <hi>againste
some thinges, and</hi> Subscribing <hi>to all, to halt
<pb facs="4"/>
betweene two wayes, and to haue an heart and
an hearte? One hearte for the mouth, and an
other for the hande?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esa. 29. 13. 14</note> If the wisedome of
wise mē shall perish, <hi>when</hi> people come
neere vnto God with their mouth, and
remooue their heart farre from him:
<hi>May not I aduise you to repent, That yee haue</hi>
suffered your mouth to <hi>increase the</hi> sinn
of your hand;<note place="margin">Ecclef. 5. 5.</note>
      <hi>and to take heede, That yee
say</hi> not before the Angell, <hi>That it was
with protestation? For</hi> why should God be
angry with your voyce, &amp; destroy the
worke of your handes?<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 22.</note> o blessed is hee
that condemneth not himselfe in that
thing, which he alloweth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Other woulde iustisie themselues, Because
(as they say) It is not affirmed by their</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription,
<hi>That all thinges in the Bookes of
Common prayer, and of ordeyning Bishoppes,
Priests, and Deacons, be agreeable to the worde
of</hi> God; <hi>but onelie saide, That those Bookes
conteyne</hi> nothing contrarie <hi>to the worde of
God. I might appeale to your consciences, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
you thinke not some thinges in those Bookes
to bee</hi> contrarie <hi>to</hi> Gods <hi>worde? But in my
conscience (as I am yet perswaded) This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction
cannot satisfie your conscience. For, If
Christ doeth say,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 11. 23.</note> He that is not with me,
is against mee: <hi>May it not bee saide, That
whatsoeuer is</hi> not according <hi>to the word, in
Gods publike worship and seruice, is</hi> contrarie
<hi>to the same? And the rather, because Esay hath
<pb facs="5"/>
set it down for a rule;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay. 8. 20.</note> If any speak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to this word; it is because there
is no light in them? <hi>I pray ye consider, That
howsoeuer, hee bee a good subiect, who doeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge
contrarie to the lawes of his Prince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
the positiue lawes of men be imperfect, as
their makers bee: Yet a good Christian ought to
indeauour in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e obedience of faith, That all his
actions in Gods worshippe (which shall be surely
iudged in the day of Iesus) bee iustifiable by the
word:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal.19. 7.</note>
      <hi>because</hi> The Lawe of the Lorde is
perfect: <hi>and the Scriptures are so sufficient,
That</hi> thereby the man of God may bee
made absolutely wise vnto saluation.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 15. 17.</note>
      <hi>I
can hardlie withhold my self from disputing this
case; Because I see, That this distinction ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
a gate to sinne and superstition. For, as he
who teacheth, That all thinges in Gods worship
(for which we must aunswere before God) must
be according to the word: restraineth mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentiōs,
&amp; occasioneth the godly more through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
to reley on the scriptures: so, he, who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
That it is sufficient that nothing be contrary
to the word, giueth too much occasion of libertie
to mans inventions, and causeth wise men (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the flesh) to be lesse zealous in search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and depending on the scriptures. But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
the humble and godly to consider, whether
ceremonies, and an ecclesiasticall gouernement
may be thrust vpon Christ his Church (which is
his kingedom) without any warrant from Gods
word?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. 25. 28. 40. and 31.</note>
      <hi>Seeing</hi> Moses (<hi>that extraordinarie
<pb facs="5"/>
Lawgiuer) and</hi> Bezaleel,<note place="margin">1, 2, 6, 7. and 39. 42. 43.</note>
      <hi>&amp;</hi> Aholiab <hi>(mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouslie
inspired with cunning) coulde not
make any thing about the Tabernacle (no not a
payer of</hi> snuffers), <hi>by their owne invention;
but according to the patterne which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
had shewed vpon the mountaine: and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
our state and Church doeth forbidde setting
vp of</hi> candles,<note place="margin">Iniunction 3.</note>
      <hi>Because it is a worke deuised by
mans phantasie besides scripture; condemneth</hi>
Reseruation of the Sacrament, <hi>Because
it is not by Christe his ordinance,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Articles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion artic. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>and is earnest
against</hi> setting vp of Images in temples,
<hi>though they be not worshipped,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Homil. of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of Idolat.</note>
      <hi>Because it is not
lawfull &amp; agreeable to Gods word, so to doe. To
come somewhat neerer the point: Suppose such a
distinctiō in God his matters may be admitted:
yet examine your hearts, whether that figg leafe
will couer your nakednesse: Sith the Bishoppes,
Priests, and Deacons of our Church are saide in
the Booke of Consecration to bee called to their
seuerall ministrations according to the will of
our Lord Iesus Christ: And by your subscription
to the thirde of the ArchBb. Articles ye prosesse,
That ye beleeue all the articles conteined in the
Book of Articles of Religiō set forth Anno 1562
(the 36. whereof allowed Bishopps &amp;c.) to bee
agreeable to God: yet notwithstanding ye haue
bene &amp; still seeme to be perswaded in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,
That our Bishops haue not their calling
from God; but were set vp by man, and setled by
custome for vnities sake.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A thirde sorte of</hi> subscribers <hi>would couer
<pb facs="6"/>
their heads with the shield (not of faith,) but of
humaine pollicie and stand to it, That</hi> of two
euils the lesse is to be chosen: <hi>And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
some things are to be tolerated, rather than
the Church should lose the benefite of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reason. 5.</note>
      <hi>Wherevnto though the</hi> Reasoner
<hi>hath well aunswered by opposing the wisedom of
the Spirite, which forbiddeth vs</hi> to lye, <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
thereby the veritie of God might more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde
vnto his glorie, and by shewing, Howe
this</hi> lye, <hi>or politique</hi> subscription <hi>draweth a
curse, and not a blessing vppon the ministerie of
subscribers against their owne conscience: Yet
giue me leaue to speak somewhat to this excuse.
I will not vrge the opiniō of that most reuerend,
learned,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist.12.</note>
      <hi>and godlie diuine Maister</hi> Beza; <hi>who
can giue no other coūcel, than that Ministers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
testified their innocencie, and tried all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies
in the feare of the Lord, should giue place
to manifest violence when they be commaunded
not onlie to tollerate the ceremonies, and ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall
gouernement of our Church, but also to
allowe them by their hand writing. For there
is great difference betweene toleration, and
subscription. But I would learne, whether that
ground of pollicie be not to be vnderstood rather
of</hi> the euils of payne and punishment,
<hi>than of</hi> the euils of sinne and guiltines:
<hi>Sith by the doctrine of our Church, No sinne is
veniall or pardenable in it selfe. And I make
this</hi> Quaere, <hi>Whether silence inforced, or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing
subscription, be the greater euill? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="6"/>
the former, This is my perswasion, That
as God,<note place="margin">Iob. 13. 7. 9</note> (who needeth not</hi> the lye <hi>of politique
subscription, but can butide his Church as hee
will) doeth not giue an ordinarie blessing to the
ministerie of such subscribers: so the very silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
of faithful ministers that</hi> stād fast in the
libertie,<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 1. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l 2. 20.</note> wherewith Christe hath made
vs free against the bondage of mans
inventions,<note place="margin">Philip. 1. 12.</note>
      <hi>doeth turne rather (as Paules</hi>
bands) to the furthering of the Gospel.
<hi>For, If an hundred godlie ministers were suspen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
for not subscribing to all the ArchBishoppes
Articles, I doubt not but that their silencing
would preach reformation very effectuallie:
Wheras your temporizing subscriptiō doth hurt
many wayes. For therby the ArchBb. is so har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened
in his course, that he hath resolutelie said:
That</hi> sith God hath so blessed him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
that fewe of any accoumpte with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
the same, hee would not giue it
ouer now. <hi>Is not then your politique subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing
the cause, why those few be so hardlie dealt
with, That no mediation can prevaile in their
behalfe? To say nothing of</hi> prosessours, <hi>who
seeing you (who haue stood in the gappe) to</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe
<hi>at the last, do thinke those few that now
stand, more precise than wise, and become ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
lesse comfortable to them than they haue
bin. But answer me: Is not this affliction added
to their sufferings by your fault? I say more, By
your</hi> subscripriō <hi>ye may seeme (in some sort)
guilty of preiudicing your brethren, not onely for
<pb facs="7"/>
the time present, but for euer hereafter; except
by the standing out of some, prescription be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted.
For as many things enacted by Law,
are antiquated by non vsage: so many thinges
not cōmanded by law are established by custome
and prescription. This is not all: For as Peters
example</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2. 12, 13.</note> drew not onely the Iewes, but
Barnabas also into dissimulation with
him: <hi>so your temporizing subscription hath
bene and daily will be an occasion to many weak
ones, if not of falling, yet of stumbling; if not of
going backe into</hi> Egypt, <hi>yet of looking backe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
Sodome. <hi>So that few be now so zealous
for reformation, as they haue bene. Which must
needes be a great offence, and that giuen by you,
If (in your iudgement) there be neede of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.
Shall I tell you, That hee who</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 12.</note>
      <hi>woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
weake consciences,</hi> doeth sinne against
Christ, <hi>who pronounceth an heauie iudgment
against him,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 6. 7.</note> that offendeth any of his
litle ones? <hi>Nay rather I beseech you by the
mercies of God, That</hi>
      <note n="“" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 20</note> If your own heart
condemne you <hi>for subscribing against your
conscience: ye would feare him that is</hi> greater
than you hearte:<note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 2. 5.</note> remember from
whence yee be fallen, repent, and doe
the first workes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>