<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT RE∣VEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND VERTVOVS LADIE, the Ladie Ioane Barkley, Ab∣besse of the English Nun∣nes in Brussels.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106100_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09670</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19940</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106100</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT RE∣VEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND VERTVOVS LADIE, the Ladie Ioane Barkley, Ab∣besse of the English Nun∣nes in Brussels.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Virgin Maries life : Faithfully gathered out of auncient and holie fathers. Togeather with meditations and documents vpon the same. Writen first in Italien by the reuerend father Lucas Pinelli, of the Societie of Iesus. And now translated in to English by R.G</title>
                 <author>Pinelli, Luca</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND VERTVOVS LADIE, the Ladie Ioane Barkley, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besse of the English Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Brussels.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Haue beene so bould, Religious and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Madame, as to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect this litle booke to you, and make you a present thereof, as one vvorthie to receaue &amp; keepe such a iewel. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie J saie, to receaue it, because of your rare vertu, so manie vvayes and yeares vttered to the vvorld, by your both Religious vocation and maners: vvorthie to keepe it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause J knovv right vvel, how much more you doe value and esteeme spiritual, then temporal tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asures.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>The tooke, Madame, is in quā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie verie smal, but in substance pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing greate. For that it conteineth the life of our blessed Ladie, that is, of the most excellent, most vvorthie, and most holie person (Christ IESVS her sonne onlie excepted) that either liued at anie time in this vvorld, or now raigneth glorious in heauen. Jn somuch that, al dulie considered, for me to commende you this woorke it selfe, vvere a thing superfluous: to request you to accept it, vvere a thing needeles: to praie you to take it in your custodie and keepe it, vvere but to make estimation of you, farre othervvise then your godlie &amp; vertuous state doth deserue.</p>
   <p>This one thing J vvil adde and end therevvithal, that if my smal paines taken in the translating of it,
<pb facs="3"/>may anie vvise benefit your spiritual good and consolation, and aduance you in the deuotiō of this blessed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mother of God, I vvil thinke them vvel employed. And so desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as vvel to be remembred in your feruent deuotions, as also that this offer, such as it is, may serue for vvitnes of my duetiful affection, to further that of your good selfe and yours to vvards this mother of mercie and her svveete sonne JESVS, J commend your to them both, and humblye take my leaue: vvishinge you in this vvorld, Madame, al abundance of heauenlie grace and contentement, and in the vvorld to come, euerlasting felicitie and ioye.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours,</signed>
      <salute>Madame,</salute>
      <signed>in Christ Iesus, to commaunde R. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>