<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A preface to the Reader as touching the principall Voyages and discourses in this first part.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106753_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02495</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12626a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A preface to the Reader as touching the principall Voyages and discourses in this first part.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The principal nauigations, voyages, traffiques and discoueries of the English nation : made by sea or ouer-land, to the remote and farthest distant quarters of the earth, at any time within the compasse of these 1600. yeres: diuided into three seuerall volumes, according to the positions of the regions, whereunto they were directed. The first volume containeth the worthy discoueries, &amp;c. of the English toward the North and Northeast Sea, as of Lapland, Scriksinia, Corelia, the Baie of S. Nicholas, the Isles of Colge... V...z, and Newa Zembla, toward the great rive ob, with the mightie Empire of B... the Caspian Sea, Georgia, Armenia, Media, Persia, Boghar in Battia, and diuers Kingdomes of Tartaria: together with many notable monuments and testimonies of the ... forren trades, and of the warrelike and other shipping of this Relame of England in former ages. Wherunto is annexed a briefe comentarie of the true state of Island, and of the Northren seas and lands situate that way: as also theme morable defeat of the Spanish huge Armada, Anno 1588. The second volume comprehendeth the principall nauigations, voiages, traffiques, and difcoueries of the English. Nation, made by sea or ouer-land, to the south and south-east parts of the world, as well within as without the streight of Gibraltar, at any time within the compasse of their 1600 yeres : Diuided into two severall parts, &amp;c. By Richard Hakluyt preacher, and sometime student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Hakluyt, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3 volumes (24, 619, 1, 16, 312, 204, 16, 868 pages), folded plates, map, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ A preface to the Reader as touching the principall Voyages and discourses in this first part.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>HAuing for the benefit and honour of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> zealously bestowed so many yeres, so much traueile and cost, to bring Antiquities smothered and buried in darke silence, to light, and to preserue certaine memorable exploits of late yeeres by our <hi>English</hi> nation atchieued, from the greedy and deuouring iawes of obliuion: to gather likewise, and as it were to incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into one body the torne and scattered limmes of our ancient and late Nauigations by Sea, our voyages by land, and traffiques of merchandise by both: and hauing (so much as in me lieth) restored ech particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, being before displaced, to their true ioynts and ligaments; I meane, by the helpe of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie and Chronologie (which I may call the Sunne and the Moone, the right eye and the left of all history) referred ech particular relation to the due time and place: I do this second time (friendly Reader, if not to satisfie, yet at least for the present to allay and hold in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spense thine expectation) presume to offer vnto thy view this first part of my threefold dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course. For the bringing of which into this homely and rough-hewen shape, which here thou seest; what restlesse nights, what painefull dayes, what heat, what cold I haue indured; how many long &amp; chargeable iourneys I haue traueiled; how many famous libraries I haue sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into; what varietie of ancient and moderne writers I haue perused; what a number of old records, patents, priuileges, letters, &amp;c. I haue redeemed from obscuritie and perishing; into how manifold acquaintance I haue entred; what expenses I haue not spared; and yet what faire opportunities of priuate gaine, preferment, and ease I haue neglected; albeit thy selfe canst hardly imagine, yet I by daily experience do finde &amp; feele, and some of my entier friends can sufficiently testifie. Howbeit (as I told thee at the first) the honour and benefit of this Common weale wherein I liue and breathe, hath made all difficulties seeme easie, all paines and industrie pleasant, and all expenses of light value and moment vnto me.</p>
   <p>For (to conteine my selfe onely within the bounds of this present discourse, and in the midst thereof to begin) wil it not in all posteritie be as great a renowme vnto our <hi>English</hi> nation, to haue bene the first discouerers of a Sea beyond the <hi>North cape</hi> (neuer certainly knowen before) and of a conuenient passage into the huge Empire of <hi>Russia</hi> by the bay of S. <hi>Nicolas</hi> and the riuer of <hi>Duina;</hi> as for the <hi>Portugales</hi> to haue found a Sea beyond the Cape of <hi>Buona Esperanza,</hi> and so consequently a passage by Sea into the East <hi>Indies;</hi> or for the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> to haue discouered vnknowen landes so many hundred leagues Westward and Southwestward of the streits of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> &amp; of the pillers of <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules?</hi> Be it granted that the renowmed <hi>Portugale Vasquez de Gama</hi> trauersed the maine Ocean Southward of <hi>Africke:</hi> Did not <hi>Richard Chanceler</hi> and his mates per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the like Northward of <hi>Europe?</hi> Suppose that <hi>Columbus</hi> that noble and high-spirited <hi>Genuois</hi> escried vnknowen landes to the Westward of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Africke:</hi> Did not the valiant <hi>English</hi> knight sir <hi>Hugh Willoughby;</hi> did not the famous Pilots <hi>Stephen Burrough, Arthur Pet,</hi> and <hi>Charles Iackman</hi> accoast <hi>Noua Zembla, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goieue,</hi> and <hi>Vaigatz</hi> to the North of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Asia?</hi> Howbeit you will say perhaps, not with the like golden successe, not with such deductions of Colonies, nor attaining of conquests. True it is, that our successe hath not bene correspondent vnto theirs: yet in this our attempt the vncertaintie of finding was farre greater, and the difficultie and danger of searching was no whit lesse. For hath not <hi>Herodotus</hi> (a man for his time, most skilfull and iudicial in Cosmographie, who writ aboue 2000. yeeres ago) in his 4. booke called <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomene,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
signified vnto the <hi>Portugales</hi> in plaine termes; that <hi>Africa,</hi> except the small <hi>Isthmus</hi> between the <hi>Arabian</hi> gulfe and the <hi>Mediterran</hi> sea, was on all sides enuironed with the Ocean? And for the further confirmation thereof, doth he not make mention of one <hi>Neco</hi> an <hi>AEgyptian</hi> King, who (for trials sake) sent a Fleet of <hi>Phoenicians</hi> downe the Red sea; who setting forth in Autumne and sailing Southward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> till they had the Sunne at noonetide vpon their sterbourd (that is to say, hauing crossed the <hi>AEquinoctial</hi> and the Southerne <hi>tropique</hi>) after a long Nauigation, directed their course to the North, and in the space of 3. yeeres enuironed all <hi>Africk,</hi> passing home through the <hi>Gaditan</hi> streites, and arriuing in <hi>AEgypt?</hi> And doth not <note n="‖" place="margin">
         <hi>Lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> nat. hist. cap. 67.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> tel them, that noble <hi>Hanno,</hi> in the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing time and estate of <hi>Carthage,</hi> sailed from <hi>Gades</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> to the coast of <hi>Arabia foelix,</hi> and put downe his whole iournall in writing? Doth he not make mention, that in the time of <hi>Augustus Cesar,</hi> the wracke of certaine <hi>Spanish</hi> ships was found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>loating in the <hi>Arabian</hi> gulfe? And, not to be ouer-tedious in alleaging of testimonies, doth not <hi>Strabo</hi> in the 2. booke of his Geography, together with <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi> and <hi>Plinie</hi> in the place before named, agree all in one, that one <hi>Eudoxus</hi> fleeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rom king <hi>Lathyrus,</hi> and valing downe the <hi>Arabian</hi> bay, sailed along, doubled the Southern point of <hi>Africk,</hi> and at length arriued at <hi>Gades?</hi> And what should I speake of the <hi>Spaniards?</hi> Was not diuine <note n="‖" place="margin">
         <hi>In Tim. 10.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Plato</hi> (who liued so many ages ago, and plainely described their West <hi>Indies</hi> vnder the name of <hi>Atlantis</hi>) was not he (I say) in stead of a Cosmographer vnto them? Were not those <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians</hi> mentioned by <hi>Aristotle lib.</hi>
      <note n="‖" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>de admirabil. auscult.</hi> their forerunners? And had they not <hi>Columbus</hi> to stirre them vp, and pricke them forward vnto their Westerne discoueries; yea, to be their chiefe loads-man and Pilot? Sithens therefore these two worthy Nations had those bright lampes of learning (I meane the most ancient and best Philosophers, Historiographers and Geographers) to shewe them light; and the load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arre of experience (to wit those great exploits and voyages layed vp in store and recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) whereby to shape their course: what great attempt might they not presume to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake? But alas our <hi>English</hi> nation, at the first setting foorth for their Northeasterne discouery, were either altogether destitute of such cleare lights and inducements, or if they had any inkling at all, it was as misty as they found the Northren seas, and so obscure and ambiguous, that it was meet rather to deterre them, then to giue them encouragement.</p>
   <p>But besides the foresaid vncertaintie, into what dangers and difficulties they plunged themselues, <hi>Animus meminisse horret,</hi> I tremble to recount. For first they were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselues vnto the rigour of the sterne and vnco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th Northren seas, and to make triall of the swelling waues and boistrous winds which there commonly do surge and blow: then were they to saile by the ragged and perilous coast of <hi>Norway,</hi> to frequent the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunted shoares of <hi>Finmark,</hi> to double the dreadfull and misty North cape, to beare with <hi>Willoughbies</hi> land, to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n along within kenning of the Countreys of <hi>Lapland</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relia,</hi> and as it were to open and vnlocke the seuen-fold mouth of <hi>Duina.</hi> Moreouer, in their Northeasterly Nauigations, vpon the seas and by the coasts of <hi>Condora, Colgoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eue, Petzora, Ioughoria, Samoedia, Noua Zembla,</hi> &amp;c. and their passing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne through the streits of <hi>Vaigatz,</hi> vnto what drifts of snow and mountaines of yee euen in Iune, Iuly, and August, vnto what hideous ouerfals, vncertaine currents, darke mistes and fogs, and diuers other fearefull inconueniences they were subiect and in danger of, I wish you rather to learne out of the voyages of sir <hi>Hugh Willoughbie, Stephen Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, Arthur Pet</hi> and the rest, then to expect in this place an endlesse cataloque thereof. And here by the way I cannot but highly commend the great industry and magnanimity of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who within these few yeeres haue discouered to 78. yea (as themselues affirme) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>1. degrees of Northerly latitude: yet with this prouiso; that our <hi>English</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion led them the dance, brake the yee before them, and gaue them good leaue to light their candle at our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orch. But nowe it is high time for vs to weigh our ancre, to hoise vp our sailes, to get cleare of these boistrous, frosty, and misty seas, and with all speede to direct our
<pb facs="5"/>
course for the milde, lightsome, temperate, and warme <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean, ouer which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portugales</hi> haue made so many pleasant prosperous and golden voyages. And albeit I cannot deny, that both of them in their East and West <hi>Indian</hi> Nauigations haue indured many tempests, dangers and shipwracks: yet this dare I boldly affirme; first that a great number of them haue satisfied their fame-thirsty and gold-thirsty mindes with that reputation and wealth, which made all perils and misaduentures seeme tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vnto them; and secondly, that their first attempts (which in this comparison I doe onely stand vpon) were no whit more difficult and dangerous, then ours to the Northeast. For admit that the way was much longer, yet was it neuer barred with yee, mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, or dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but was at all seasons of the yeere open and Nauigable; yea and that for the most part with fortunate and fit gales of winde. Moreouer they had no forren prince to intercept or molest them, but their owne Townes, Islands, and maine lands to succour them. The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> had the <hi>Canary</hi> Isles: and so had the <hi>Portugales</hi> the Isles of the <hi>Açores,</hi> of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to santo,</hi> of <hi>Madera,</hi> of <hi>Cape ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d,</hi> the castle of <hi>Mina,</hi> the fruitfull and profitable Isle of S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> being all of them conueniently situated, and well fraught with commodities. And had they not continuall and yerely trade in some one part or other of <hi>Africa,</hi> for get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of slaues, for sugar, for Elephants teeth, graines, siluer, gold, and other precious wares, which serued as allurements to draw them on by little and litle, and as proppes to stay them from giuing ouer their attempts? But nowe let vs leaue them and returne home vnto our selues.</p>
   <p>In this first Volume (friendly Reader) besides our Northeasterne Discoueries by sea, and the memorable voyage of M. <hi>Christopher Hodson,</hi> and M. <hi>William Burrough, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1570. to the <hi>Narue,</hi> wherein with merchants ships onely, they tooke fiue strong and warrelike ships of the <hi>Freebooters,</hi> which lay within the sound of <hi>Denmark</hi> of purpose to intercept our English Fleete: besides all these (I say) thou maiest find here recorded, to the lasting honor of our nation, all their long and dangerous voyages for the aduauncing of traffique by riuer and by land to all parts of the huge and wide Empire of <hi>Russia:</hi> as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Richard Chanceler</hi> his first fortunate arriuall at <hi>Newnox,</hi> his passing vp the riuer of <hi>Dwina</hi> to the citie of <hi>Vologda</hi> for the space of 1100. versts, and from thence to <hi>Ya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruslaue, Rostoue, Peraslaue,</hi> and so to the famous citie of <hi>Mosco,</hi> being 1500. versts trauell in all. Moreouer, here thou hast his voiage penned by himselfe (which I hold to be very authentical, &amp; for the which I do acknowledge my selfe beholding vnto the excellent Librarie of the right honorable my lord <hi>Lumley</hi>) wherein he describeth in part the state of <hi>Russia,</hi> the maners of the people and their religion, the magnificence of the Court, the maiestie, power, and riches of the Emperour, and the gracious entertainment of himselfe. But if he being the first man, and not hauing so perfect intelligence as they that came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, doeth not fullie satisfie your expectation in describing the foresayd countrey and people; I then referre you to <hi>Clement Adams</hi> his relation next following, to M. <hi>Ien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinsons</hi> discourse as touching that argument, to the smooth verses of M. <hi>George Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beruile,</hi> and to a learned and excellent discourse set downe, pag. 475. of this volume, and the pages following. Vnto all which (if you please) you may adde <hi>Richard Iohnsons</hi> strange report of the <hi>Samoeds,</hi> pag. 283. But to returne to our voyages performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of <hi>Russia,</hi> I suppose (among the rest) that difficult iourney of <hi>Southam</hi> and <hi>Sparke,</hi> from <hi>Colmogro</hi> and S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Baie, vp the great riuer of <hi>Onega,</hi> and so by other riuers and lakes to the citie of <hi>Nouogrod velica</hi> vpon the West frontier of <hi>Russia,</hi> to be right woorthy of obseruation; as likewise that of <hi>Thomas Alcock</hi> from <hi>Mosco</hi> to <hi>Smolensko,</hi> and thence to <hi>Tirwill</hi> in <hi>Polonia,</hi> pag. 304. &amp; that also of M. <hi>Hierome Horsey</hi> from <hi>Mosco</hi> to <hi>Vobsko,</hi> and so through <hi>Liefland</hi> to <hi>Riga,</hi> thence by the chiefe townes of <hi>Prussia</hi> and <hi>Pomerland</hi> to <hi>Rostok,</hi> and so to <hi>Hamburg, Breme, Emden, &amp;c.</hi> Neither hath our nation bene contented onely throughly to search into all parts of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and to view the Northren, Southerne, and Westerne frontiers, but also by the riuers
<pb facs="6"/>
of <hi>Moscua, Occa</hi> and <hi>Volga,</hi> to visite <hi>Cazan</hi> and <hi>Astracan,</hi> the farthest Easterne and Southeasterne bounds of that huge Empire. And yet not containing themselues within all that maine circumference, they haue aduentured their persons, shippes, and goods, home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and outwards, foureteene times ouer the vnknowen and dangerous <hi>Caspian</hi> sea; that valiant, wise, and personable gentleman M. <hi>Anthonie Ienkinson</hi> being their first ring-leader: who in <hi>Anno 1558.</hi> sailing from <hi>Astracan</hi> towards the East shore of the <hi>Caspian</hi> sea, and there arriuing at the port of <hi>Mangusla,</hi> trauelled thence by <hi>Vrgence</hi> and <hi>Shelisur,</hi> and by the riuers of <hi>Oxus</hi> and <hi>Ardok,</hi> 40. dayes iourney ouer desert and wast countreys, to <hi>Boghar</hi> a principall citie of <hi>Bactria,</hi> being there &amp; by the way friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, dismissed, and safely conducted by certaine <hi>Tartarian</hi> kings and <hi>Murses.</hi> Then haue you a second Nauigation of his performance to the South shore of the foresayd <hi>Caspian</hi> sea, together with his landing at <hi>Derbent,</hi> his arriuall at <hi>Shabran,</hi> his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto <hi>Shamaky,</hi> the great curtesie vouchsafed on him by <hi>Obdolowcan</hi> king of <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> his iourney after of 30. dayes Southward, by <hi>Yauate, Ardouil,</hi> and other town<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s and cities to <hi>Casben,</hi> being as then the seate imperiall of <hi>Shaugh Thamas</hi> the great <hi>Sophy</hi> of <hi>Persia,</hi> with diuers other notable accidents in his going foorth, in his abode there, and in his returne home. Immediately after you haue set downe in fiue seuerall voiages the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of M. <hi>Ienkinsons</hi> laudable and well-begun enterprise, vnder the foresayd <hi>Shaugh Thamas,</hi> vnder <hi>Shally Murzey</hi> the new king of <hi>Hircan,</hi> and lastly our traffique with <hi>Osman Basha</hi> the great Turkes lieutenant at <hi>Derbent.</hi> Moreouer, as in M. <hi>Ienkinsons</hi> trauel to <hi>Boghar</hi> the <hi>Tartars,</hi> with their territories, habitations, maner of liuing, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, food, armour, &amp;c. are most liuely represented vnto you: so likewise in the sixe <hi>Persian</hi> Iournals you may here and there obserue the state of that countrey, of the great <hi>Shaugh</hi> and of his subiects, together with their religion, lawes, customes, &amp; maner of gouernment, their coines, weights and measures, the distances of places, the temperature of the climate and region, and the natural commodities and discommodities of the same.</p>
   <p>Furthermore in this first Volume, all the Ambassages and Negotiations from her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie to the <hi>Russian</hi> Emperor, or from him vnto her Maiestie, seemed by good right to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge their due places of Record. As namely, first that of M. <hi>Randolph, 1568.</hi> then the emploiment of M. <hi>Ienkinson 1571.</hi> thirdly, Sir <hi>Ierome Bowes</hi> his honorable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission and ambassage 1582. and last of all the Ambassage of M. Doct. <hi>Fletcher 1588.</hi> Neither do we forget the Emperours first Ambassador <hi>Osep Napea,</hi> his arriuall in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> his most honourable entertainment and abode in <hi>England,</hi> and his dismission into <hi>Russeland.</hi> In the second place we doe make mention of <hi>Stephen Tuerdico,</hi> and <hi>Pheo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data Pogo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ella;</hi> thirdly, of <hi>Andrea Sauin;</hi> and lastly, of <hi>Pheodor Andrewich Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semski.</hi> And to be briefe, I haue not omitted the Commissions, Letters, Priuileges, Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Obseruations, or any other Particulars which might serue both in this age, and with all posteritie, either for presidents in such like princely and weightie actions to bee imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or as woorthy monuments in no wise to bee buried in silence. Finally, that nothing should be wanting which might adde any grace or shew of perfection vnto this discourse of <hi>Russia;</hi> I haue prefixed before the beginning thereof, the petigree and genealogie of the <hi>Russian</hi> Emperors and Dukes, gathered out of their owne Chronicles by a <hi>Polonian,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in briefe many notable antiquities and much knowledge of those partes: as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise about the conclusion, I haue signified in the branch of a letter, the last Emperour <hi>Pheodor Iuanowich</hi> his death, and the inauguration of <hi>Boris Pheodorowich</hi> vnto the Empire.</p>
   <p>But that no man should imagine that our forren trades of merchandise haue bene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised within some few yeeres, or at least wise haue not bene of any long continuance; let vs now withdraw our selues from our affaires in <hi>Russia,</hi> and ascending somewhat higher, let vs take a sleight suruey of our traffiques and negotiations in former ages. First there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reader may haue recourse vnto the 124 page of this Volume, &amp; there with great
<pb facs="6"/>
delight and admiration, consider out of the iudicial Historiographer <hi>Cornelius Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that the Citie of <hi>London</hi> fifteene hundred yeeres agoe in the time of <hi>Nero</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, was most famous for multitude of merchants and concourse of people. In the pages folowing he may learne out of Venerable <hi>Beda,</hi> that almost 900. yeeres past, in the time of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the said citie of <hi>London</hi> was <hi>multorum emporium populorum,</hi> a Mart-towne for many nations. There he may behold, out of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmesburie,</hi> a league concluded betweene the most renoumed and victorious <hi>Germane</hi> Emperour <hi>Carolus Magnus,</hi> and the <hi>Saxon</hi> king <hi>Offa,</hi> together with the sayd <hi>Charles</hi> his patronage and protection granted vnto all English merchants which in those dayes frequented his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. There may bee plainly see in an auncient testimonie translated out of the <hi>Saxon</hi> tongue, how our merchants were often woont for traffiques sake, so many hundred yeeres since, to crosse the wide Seas, and how their industry in so doing was recompensed. Yea, there mayest thou obserue (friendly Reader) what priuileges the <hi>Danish</hi> king <hi>Canutus</hi> obtained at <hi>Rome</hi> of Pope <hi>Iohn,</hi> of <hi>Conradus</hi> the Emperour, and of king <hi>Rudolphus</hi> for our English merchants Aduenturers of those times. Then if you shall thinke good to descend vnto the times and ages succeeding the conquest, there may you partly see what our state of merchandise was in the time of king <hi>Stephen</hi> and of his predecessor, and how the Citie of <hi>Bristol</hi> (which may seeme somewhat strange) was then greatly resorted vnto with ships from <hi>Norway</hi> and from <hi>Ireland.</hi> There may you see the friendly league betweene king <hi>Henry</hi> the second, and the famous <hi>Germane</hi> Emperour <hi>Friderick Barbarossa,</hi> and the gracious authorizing of both their merchāts to traffique in either of their dominions. And what need I to put you in mind of king <hi>Iohn</hi> his fauourable safe-conduct, whereby all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren merchants were to haue the same priuileges here in <hi>England,</hi> which our English merchants enioied abroad in their seuerall countreys. Or what should I signifie vnto you the entercourse of league and of other curtesies betweene king <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinus</hi> king of <hi>Norway;</hi> and likewise of the free trade of merchandise between their subiects: or tell you what fauours the citizens of <hi>Colen,</hi> of <hi>Lubek,</hi> and of all the Hanse-townes obtained of king <hi>Edward</hi> the first; or to what high endes and purposes the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, large, and stately Charter concerning all outlandish merchants whatsoeuer was by the same prince most graciously published? You are of your owne industry sufficiently able to conceiue of the letters &amp; negotiatiōs which passed between K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. &amp; <hi>Haqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the <hi>Noruagian</hi> king; of our English merchants and their goods detained vpon arrest at <hi>Bergen</hi> in <hi>Norway;</hi> and also of the first ordination of a Staple, or of one onely setled Mart-towne for the vttering of English woolls &amp; woollen fells, instituted by the sayd K. <hi>Edward</hi> last before named. All which (Reader) being throughly considered, I referre you then to the Ambassages, Letters, Traffiques, and prohibition of Traffiques, concluding and repealing of leagues, damages, reprisals, arrests, complaints, supplications, compositions and restitutions which happened in the time o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> king <hi>Richard</hi> the 2. and king <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. between the said kings and their subiects on the one partie; and <hi>Conradus de Zolner, Conradus de Iungingen,</hi> and <hi>Vlricus de Iungingen,</hi> three of the great masters of <hi>Prussia,</hi> and their subiects, with the common societie of the Hans-townes on the other partie. In all which discourse you may note very many memorable things; as namely first the wise, discreet, and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>telous dealing of the Ambassadors and Commissioners of both parts, then the wealth of the foresaid nations, and their manifold and most vsuall kinds of wares vttered in those dayes, as likewise the qualitie, burthen, and strength of their ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the number of their Mariners, the maner of their combates at sea, the number and names of the English townes which traded that way, with the particular places as well vpon the coast of <hi>Norway,</hi> as euery where within the sound of <hi>Denmark</hi> which they frequented; together with the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eterate malice and craftie crueltie of the <hi>Hanse.</hi> And because the name, office, and dignitie of the masters generall, or great Masters of <hi>Prussia</hi> would otherwise haue bene vtterly darke and vnknowen to the
<pb facs="7"/>
greater part of Readers, I haue set downe immediatly before the first <hi>Prussian</hi> ambassage, <hi>pagina 144</hi> a briefe and orderly Catalogue of them all, contayning the first originall and institution of themselues and of their whole knightly order and brotherhood, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of reuenues and wealth which befell them afterward in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> and the great conquests which they atchieued vpon the infidels of <hi>Prussia, Samogitia, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Liefland, Lituania,</hi> &amp;c. also their decay and finall ouerthrow, partly by the reuolt of di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ers Townes and Castles vnder their iurisdiction, and partly by the meanes of their next mightie neighbour the King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>After all these, out of 2. branches of 2. ancient statutes, is partly shewed our trade and the successe thereof with diuers forren Nations in the time of <hi>K. Henry</hi> the sixt.</p>
   <p>Then followeth the true processe of <hi>English</hi> policie, I meane that excellent and pithy treatise <hi>de politia conseruatiua maris:</hi> which I cannot to any thing more fitly compare, then to the Emperour of <hi>Russia</hi> his palace called the golden Castle, and described by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Chanceller</hi> pag. 238. of this volume: whereof albeit the outward apparance was but homely and no whit correspondent to the name, yet was it within so beautified and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned with the Emperour his maiesticall presence, with the honourable and great assembly of his rich-attired Peers and Senatours, with an inualuable and huge masse of gold and sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer plate, &amp; with other princely magnificence; that well might the eyes of the beholders be dazeled, and their cogitations astonished thereat. For indeed the exteriour habit of this our <hi>English</hi> politician, to wit, the harsh and vnaffected stile of his substantiall verses and the olde dialect of his worde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is such; as the first may seeme to haue bene whistled of <hi>Pans</hi> oaten pipe, and the second to haue proceeded from the mother of <hi>Euander:</hi> but take you off his vtmost weed, and beholde the comelinesse, beautie, and riches which lie hid within his inward sense and sentence; and you shall finde (I wisse) so much true and sound policy, so much delightfull and pertinent history, so many liuely descriptions of the shipping and wares in his time of all the nations almost in Christendome, and such a subtile discouery of outlandish merchants fraud, and of the sophistication of their wares; that needes you must acknowledge, that more matter and substance could in no wise be comprised in so little a roome. And notwithstanding (as I said) his stile be vnpolished, and his phrases some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what out of vse; yet, so neere as the written copies would giue me leaue, I haue most reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously without alteration obserued the same: thinking it farre more conuenient that himselfe should speake, then that I should bee his spokesman; and that the Readers should enioy his true verses, then mine or any other mans fained prose.</p>
   <p>Next after the conclusion of the last mentioned discourse, the Reader may in some sort take a vieu of our state of merchandise vnder <hi>K. Edward</hi> the fourth, as likewise of the establishing of an <hi>English</hi> company in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and of all the discreet prouisoes, iust ordinations, &amp; gratious priuileges conteined in the large Charter which was granted for the same purpose.</p>
   <p>Now besides our voyages and trades of late yeeres to the North and Northeast regions of the world, and our ancient traffique also to those parts; I haue not bene vnmindefull (so farre as the histories of <hi>England</hi> and of other Countreys would giue me direction) to place in the fore-front of this booke those forren conquests, exploits, and trauels of our <hi>English</hi> nation, which haue bene atchieued of old. Where in the first place (as I am credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out of <hi>Galfridus Monumetensis,</hi> and out of <hi>M. Lambert</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) I haue pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished vnto the world the noble actes of <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Malgo</hi> two <hi>British</hi> Kings. Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time <hi>K. Edwin</hi> his conquest of <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Anglesey,</hi> and the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Bertus</hi> into <hi>Ireland.</hi> Next succeedeth <hi>Octher</hi> making relation of his doings, and describing the North Countreys, vnto his soueraigne Lord <hi>K. Ecfrid.</hi> After whom <hi>Wolstans</hi> Nauigation within the Sound of <hi>Denmark</hi> is mentioned, the voyage of the yong Princes <hi>Edmund</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> into <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Hungarie</hi> is recorded, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the mariage of <hi>Harald</hi> his daughter vnto the <hi>Russian</hi> duke <hi>Ieruslaus.</hi> Neither is
<pb facs="7"/>
that <hi>Englishman</hi> forgotten, who was forced to traueile with the cruel <hi>Tartars</hi> into their Countrey, and from thence to beare them company into <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause those Northeasterne Regions beyond <hi>Volga,</hi> by reason of the huge deserts, the colde climate, and the barbarous inciuilitie of the people there inhabiting, were neuer yet throughly traueiled by any of our Nation, nor sufficiently knowen vnto vs; I haue here annexed vnto the said <hi>Englishmans</hi> traueile, the rare &amp; memorable iournals of 2. Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who were some of the first Christians that trauailed farthest that way, and brought home most particular intelligence &amp; knowledge of all things which they had seene. These Friers were sent as Ambassadours vnto the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uage <hi>Tartars</hi> (who had as then wasted and ouerrunne a great part of <hi>Asia</hi> and had pierced farre into <hi>Europe</hi> with fire and sword) to mitigate their fury, and to offer the glad tidings of the Gospel vnto them. The former, namely <hi>Iohannes de Plano <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>arpini</hi> (whose iourney, because he road sixe moneths poste directly beyond <hi>Boristhenes,</hi> did, I thinke, both for length and difficultie farre surpasse that of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, vnto the riuer of <hi>Indus</hi>) was in the yeere 1246. sent with the authoritie and commission of a Legate from Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the fourth: who passed through more garisons of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and wandered ouer more vast, barren, and cold deserts, then (I suppose) an army of an hundred thousand good souldiers could haue done. The other, to wit, <hi>William de Rubricis,</hi> was 1253 by the way of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> of the <hi>Euxin</hi> sea, and of <hi>Taurica Chersonesus</hi> imployed in an ambassage from <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King (waging warre as then against the <hi>Saracens</hi> in the Holy land) vnto one <hi>Sartach</hi> a great duke of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> which <hi>Sartach</hi> sent him forthwith vnto his father <hi>Baatu,</hi> and from <hi>Baatu</hi> he was conducted ouer many large territories vnto the Court of <hi>Mangu-Can</hi> their Emperour. Both of them haue so well played their parts, in declaring what befell them before they came at the <hi>Tartars,</hi> what a terrible and vnmanerly wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming they had at their first arriuall, what cold intertainment they felt in traueiling towards the great <hi>Can,</hi> and what slender cheere they found at his Court; that they seeme no lesse worthy of praise then of pitie. But in describing of the <hi>Tartars</hi> Countrey, and of the Regions adiacent, in setting downe the base and sillie beginnings of that huge and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spreading Empire, in registring their manifolde warres and bloody conquests, in making relation of their hords and mooueable Townes, as likewise of their food, apparell and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and in setting downe their vnmercifull lawes, their fond superstitions, their bestiall liues, their vicious maners, their slauish subiection to their owne superiours, and their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull and brutish inhumanitie vnto strangers, they deserue most exceeding and high commendation. Howbeit if any man shall obiect that they haue certaine incredible rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: I answere, first, that many true things may to the ignorant seeme incredible. But suppose there be some particulars which hardly will be credited; yet thus much I will boldly say for the Friers, that those particulars are but few, and that they doe not auouch them vnder their owne names, but from the report of others. Yet farther imagine that they did auouch them, were they not to be pardoned as well as <hi>Herodotus, Strabo, Plutarch, Plinie, Solinus,</hi> yea &amp; a great many of our new principall writers, whose names you may see about the end of this Preface; euery one of which hath reported more strange things then the Friers between thē both? Nay, there is not any history in the world (the most Holy writ excepted) whereof we are precisely bound to beleeue ech word and syllable. Moreouer sithens these two iournals are so rare, that <hi>Mercator</hi> and <hi>Ortelius</hi> (as their letters vnto me do testifie) were many yeeres very inquisitiue, and could not for all that attaine vnto them; and sithens they haue bene of so great accompt with those two famous Cosmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, that according to some fragments of them they haue described in their Mappes a great part of those Northeastern Regions; sith also that these two relations containe in some respect more exact history of those vnknowen parts, then all the ancient and newe writers that euer I could set mine eyes on: I thought it good, if the translation should chance to swerue in ought from the originals (both for the preseruation of the originals
<pb facs="8"/>
themselues, and the satisfying of the Reader) to put them downe word for word in that homely stile wherein they were first penned. And for these two rare iewels, as likewise for many other extraordinary courtesies, I must here acknowledge my selfe most deepely bounden vnto the right reuerend, graue, and learned Prelate, my very good lord the Bishop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> and L. high Almner vnto her Maiestie; by whose friendship and meanes I had free accesse vnto the right honor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> my <hi>L. Lumley</hi> his stately library, and was permitted to copy out of ancient manuscripts, these two iournals and some others also.</p>
   <p>After these Friers (though not in the next place) foloweth a testimonie of <hi>Gera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Mercator,</hi> and another of M. <hi>Dee,</hi> concerning one <hi>Nicholas de Linna</hi> an English <hi>Franciscan</hi> Frier.</p>
   <p>Then succeedeth the long iourney of <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Derbie,</hi> and afterward king of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Prussia</hi> &amp; <hi>Lithuania,</hi> with a briefe remembrance of his valiant exploits against the Infidels there; as namely, that with the help of certaine his Associates, he van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished the king of <hi>Letto</hi> his armie, put the sayd king to flight, tooke and slew diuers of his captains, aduanced his English colours vpon the wall of <hi>Vilna,</hi> &amp; made the citie it selfe to yeeld. Then mention is made also of <hi>Tho.</hi> of <hi>Woodstock</hi> his trauel into <hi>Pruis,</hi> and of his returne home. And lastly, our old English father <hi>Ennius,</hi> I meane, the learned, wittie, and profound <hi>Geffrey Chaucer,</hi> vnder the person of his knight, doeth full iudicially and like a cunning Cosmographer, make report of the long voiages and woorthy exploits of our English Nobles, Knights, &amp; Gentlemen, to the Northren, and to other partes of the world in his dayes.</p>
   <p>Neither haue we comprehended in this Volume, onely our Trades and Voiages both new and old; but also haue scattered here and there (as the circumstance of times would giue vs leaue) certaine fragments concerning the beginnings, antiquities, and grouth of the clas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sical and warrelike shipping of this <hi>Island:</hi> as namely, first of the great nauie of that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious <hi>Saxon</hi> prince king <hi>Edgar,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Florentius Wigorniensis, Roger Houeden, Rainulph</hi> of <hi>Chester, Matthew</hi> of <hi>Westminster, Flores historiarum,</hi> &amp; in the libel of <hi>English policie,</hi> pag. 202. and 203. of this present volume. Of which Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors some affirme the sayd Fleet to haue consisted of 4800. others of 4000. some others of 3600. ships: howbeit (if I may presume to gloze vpon the text) I verily thinke that they were not comparable, either for burthen, strength, building, or nimble stirrage vnto the ships of later times, and specially of this age. But howsoeuer it be, they all agree in this, that by meanes of the sayd huge Fleet he was a most puissant prince; yea, and some of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme together with <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> that he was not onely soueraigne lord of all the British seas, and of the whole Isle of <hi>Britaine</hi> it selfe, but also that he brought vnder his yoke of subiection, most of the Isles and some of the maine lands adiacent. And for that most of our Nauigators at this time bee (for want of trade and practise that way) either vtterly ignorant, or but meanely skilfull, in the true state of the Seas, Shoulds, and Islands, lying between the North part of <hi>Ireland</hi> and of <hi>Scotland;</hi> I haue for their better encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement (if any weightie action shall hereafter chance to drawe them into those quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) translated into English a briefe treatise called, <hi>A Chronicle of the Kings of Man.</hi> Wherein they may behold as well the tragical and dolefull historie of those parts, for the space almost of 300. yeeres, as also the most ordinarie and accustomed nauigations, through those very seas, and amidst those Northwesterne Isles called the <hi>Hebrides,</hi> so many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres agoe. For they shall there read, that euen then (when men were but rude in sea-causes in regard of the great knowledge which we now haue) first <hi>Godredus Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan</hi> with a whole Fleet of ships, throughly haunted some places in that sea: secondly, that one <hi>Ingemundus</hi> setting saile out of <hi>Norway,</hi> arriued vpon the Isle of <hi>Lewis:</hi> then, that <hi>Magnus</hi> the king of <hi>Norway</hi> came into the same seas with 160. sailes, and hauing subdued the <hi>Orkney</hi> Isles in his way, passed on in like conquering maner, directing his course (as it should seeme) euen through the very midst, and on all sides of the <hi>Hebrides,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
who sailing thence to <hi>Man,</hi> conquered it also, proceeding afterward as farre as <hi>Angle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey;</hi> and lastly crossing ouer from the Isle of <hi>Man</hi> to the East part of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Yea, there they shall read of <hi>Godredus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Olauus</hi> his voiage to the king of <hi>Norway,</hi> of his expedition with 80. ships against <hi>Sumerledus,</hi> of <hi>Sumerled</hi> his expedition with 53. ships against him; of <hi>Godred</hi> his flight and second iourney into <hi>Norway;</hi> of <hi>Sumerled</hi> his second arriual with 160. shippes at <hi>Rhinfrin</hi> vpon the coast of <hi>Man,</hi> and of many other such combates, assaults, &amp; voyages which were performed onely vpon those seas &amp; Islands. And for the bringing of this woorthy monument to light, we doe owe great thanks vnto the iudiciall and famous Antiquarie M. <hi>Camden.</hi> But sithens we are entred into a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the ancient warrelike shipping of this land, the Reader shall giue me leaue to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row one principall note out of this litle historie, before I quite take my leaue thereof: and that is in few words, that K. <hi>Iohn</hi> passed into <hi>Ireland</hi> with a Fleet of 500. sailes; so great were our sea-forces euen in his time. Neither did our shipping for the warres first begin to flourish with king <hi>Iohn,</hi> but long before his dayes in the reign of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor,</hi> of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> of <hi>William Rufus</hi> and the rest, there were diuers men of warre which did valiant seruice at sea, and for their paines were roially rewarded. All this and more then this you may see recorded, pag. 17. out of the learned Gentleman M. <hi>Lambert his Perambulation of Kent;</hi> namely, the antiquitie of the Kenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h <hi>Cinque ports,</hi> which of the sea-townes they were, how they were infranchised, what gracious pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges and high prerogatiues were by diuers kings vouchsafed vpon them, and what ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices they were tied vnto in regard thereof; to wit, how many ships, how many souldiers, mariners, <hi>Garsons,</hi> and for how many dayes each of them, and all of them were to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish for the kings vse; and lastly, what great exploits they performed vnder the conduct of <hi>Hubert</hi> of <hi>Burrough,</hi> as likewise against the Wels<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>men, vpon 200. French ships, and vnder the commaund of captaine <hi>Henry Pay.</hi> Then haue you, pag. 117. the franke and bountifull Charter granted by king <hi>Edward</hi> the first, vpon the foresayd <hi>Cinque portes:</hi> &amp; next thereunto a Roll of the mightie fleet of seuen hundred ships which K. <hi>Edward</hi> the third had with him vnto the siege of <hi>Caleis:</hi> out of which Roll (before I proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) let me giue you a double obseruation. First, that these ships, according to the number of the mariners which were in all 14151. persons, seeme to haue bene of great burthen; and secondly, that <hi>Yarmouth</hi> an hauen towne in <hi>Northfolke</hi> (which I much wonder at) set foorth almost twise as many ships and mariners, as either the king did at his owne costs and charges, or as any one citie or towne in <hi>England</hi> besides. Howbeit <hi>Tho. Walsing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> maketh plaine and euident mention of a farre greater Fleete of the same king; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of 1100. shippes lying before <hi>Sandwich,</hi> being all of them sufficiently well furnished. Moreouer, the Reader may behold, pag. 186. a notable testimonie of the mightie ships of that valiant prince king <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. who (when after his great victory at <hi>Agincourt</hi> the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> to recouer <hi>Harflew</hi> had hired certaine <hi>Spanish</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> ships and forces, &amp; had vnited their owne strength vnto them) sent his brother <hi>Iohn</hi> duke of <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> to encounter them, who bidding them battell, got the victory, taking some of their ships, and sinking others, and putting the residue to dishonorable flight. Likewise comming the next yeere with stronger powers, and being then also ouercome, they were glad to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a perpetuall league with K. <hi>Henry; &amp; propter eorum naues</hi> (saieth mine Author) that is, for the resistance of their ships, the sayd king caused such huge ships to be built, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les non erant in mundo,</hi> as the like were not to be found in the whole world besides.</p>
   <p>But to leaue our ancient shipping, and descend vnto later times; I thinke that neuer was any nation blessed of <hi>IEHOVAH,</hi> with a more glorious and wonderfull victory vpon the Seas, then our vanquishing of the dreadfull <hi>Spanish Armada, 1588.</hi> But why should I presume to call it our vanquishing; when as the greatest part of them escaped vs, and were onely by Gods out-stretched arme ouerwhelmed in the Seas, dashed in pieces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Rockes, and made fearefull spectacles and examples of his iudgements vnto all
<pb facs="9"/>
Christendome. An excellent discourse whereof, as likewise of the honourable expedition vnder two of the most noble and valiant peeres of this Realme, I meane, the renoumed Erle of <hi>Essex,</hi> and the right honorable the lord <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> lord high Admirall of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> made 1596. vnto the strong citie of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> I haue set downe as a double <hi>epipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nema</hi> to conclude this my first volume withall. Both of which, albeit they ought of right to haue bene placed among the Southerne voyages of our nation: yet partly to satisfie the importunitie of some of my special friends, and partly, not longer to depriue the diligent Reader of two such woorthy and long-expected discourses; I haue made bold to straine a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle curtesie with that methode which I first propounded vnto my selfe.</p>
   <p>And here had I almost forgotten to put the Reader in mind of that learned and Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical treatise of the true state of <hi>Iseland,</hi> and so consequently of the Northren Seas &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions lying that way: wherein a great number of none of the meanest Historiographers and Cosmographers of later times, as namely, <hi>Munster, Gemma Frisius, Zieglerus, Krantzius, Saxo Grammaticus, Olaus Magnus, Peucerus</hi> and others, are by euident arguments conuinced of manifold errors: that is to say, as touching the true situation and Northerly latitude of that Island, and of the distance thereof from other places; touching the length of dayes in Sommer and of nights in Winter, of the temperature of the land and sea, of the time and maner of the congealing, continuance, and thawing of the Ice in those Seas, of the first Discouerie and inhabiting of that Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nd, of the first planting of Christianitie there, as likewise of the continuall flaming of mountains, strange qualities of fountains, of hel-mouth, and of purgatorie which those authors haue fondly written and imagined to be there. All which treatise ought to bee the more acceptable; first in that it hath brought sound trueth with it; and secondly, in that it commeth from that farre Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren climate which most men would suppose could not affoord any one so learned a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone for it selfe.</p>
   <p>And thus (friendly Reader) thou seest the briefe summe and scope of all my labours for the common-wealths sake, and thy sake, bestowed vpon this first Volume: which if thou shalt as thankefully accept, as I haue willingly and freely imparted with thee, I shall bee the better encouraged speedily to acquaint thee with those rare, delightfull and profitable histories, which I purpose (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) to publish concerning the Southerne and We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne partes of the World.</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>¶ Postscriptum.</head>
      <p>Not knowing any other place so conuenient, I am here to aduertise the friendly Reader of certaine faultes escaped in the printing of this booke, and to request him that in the Page 54. and in the last line saue two, hee would in stead of Kine, read Swine, and he shall thereby auoid a great contradiction: likewise pag. 187. that hee would vnto the ende of the second verse of the Prologue to the English Policy, make supply of the word Rest, which is there wanting: also pag. 221. lin. 29. for woorthinesse read woorthies, &amp;c. Other faults (if there bee any) are (I doubt not) easily corrigible.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>