<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROLOGVE of the Translator.</title>
           <author>Day, Angel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106624_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05237</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1538</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106624</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROLOGVE of the Translator.</title>
                 <author>Day, Angel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Batman vppon Bartholome : his booke De proprietatibus rerum, newly corrected, enlarged and amended: with such additions as are requisite, vnto euery seuerall booke: taken foorth of the most approued authors, the like heretofore not translated in English. Profitable for all estates, as well for the benefite of the mind as the bodie. 1582</title>
                 <author>Bartholomaeus, anglicus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 426 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_prologue">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PROLOGVE of the Translator.</head>
   <p>TRue it is, that after the noble &amp; expert doctrine of wise and well learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Philosophers, lefte &amp; remaining with vs in writing, we knowe that the properties of thinges followe and ensue their substannce. Héerefore it is, that after the order and the distinction of substaunces, the order and the distinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the properties of things shall be and ensue. Of the which things, this worke of all the bookes ensuing, by the grace, helpe and assistaunce of Almighty God, is compiled and made. Meruaile not ye wittie &amp; eloquent readers, that I thiu of wit, and boid of running, haue trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this booke from latin into our vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar language, as a thing profitable to me, and peraduenture to manye other, which vnderstand not Latine, nor haue not the knowledge of the properties of things, which things be approued by the bookes of great and cunning Clearkes, and by the experience of most wittie &amp; noble Philosophers. All these properties of things be necessarie and of great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew, to them that will be desirous to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the obscurities or darknesse of holy Scriptures, which are giuen to vs vnder figures, vnder parables &amp; sēblance or likelihoods of things naturalls &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificialls. S. <hi>Denis</hi> that great philosopher and solemyne Clearke, in his booke na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>The heauenly Hierarchies of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells,</hi> testifieth and witnesseth the same, saieng in this manner: Whatsoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man will coniect, faine, imagine, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, or say: it is a thing impossible, that the light of the heauenly diuine bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse couered and closed in the Deitie or in the Godhead, should shine vpon vs: if it were not by the diuersities of holy couertures. Also it is not possible, that our wit or intendement might ascende vnto the contemplation of the heauenly Hierarchies immaterials, if our wit be not led by some materiall thing, as a man is ledde by the hande: so by these formes visibles, our wit may he ledde to the consideration of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greatnes or mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude of the most excellent beauteous claretie, diuine and inuisible. Also, the blessed Apostles <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epistles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth this, saieng: that by these things visibles, which are made and be visible, man may sée and know by his inwarde sight intellectuall, the diuine, celestiall, &amp; godlye things, which are inuisibles to this our naturall sight. Deuout Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Theologie or Diuinitie, for this consideration, prudently and wisely read and vse natural philosophie and morall, and Poets in their fictions and fayned informations, vnto this fine and end, so that by the lykelihoode or similitude of things visible, our wit or our vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding spiritually, by cléere and skilfull vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraunce of words, may be so well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and vttered, that these things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls may be coupled with things spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualls, and these things visibles maye be conioyned with things inuisibles. Excited by these causes to the edifieng of the people contained in our Christian faith of Almightie Christ Iesus, whose maiestie diuine is incomprehensible, and of whom to speak it becommeth no man but with great excellent worship and honour, and with an inwarde breadfull feare. Loath so offend, I purpose to say somwhat vnder the correction of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent learned Doctours, and wise men: what euery creature reasonable ought to beléeue in this our blessed christian faith.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS PROLOGI.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>