<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRULY NOBLE, AND WOR∣THILY HONOVRED, SIR HENRY MARTEN KNIGHT; IVDGE OF HIS MAIESTIES HIGH Court of the Admiraltie, and Deane of the Arches Court of Canterbury.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106782_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00665</idno>
           <idno type="STC">108</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106782</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRULY NOBLE, AND WOR∣THILY HONOVRED, SIR HENRY MARTEN KNIGHT; IVDGE OF HIS MAIESTIES HIGH Court of the Admiraltie, and Deane of the Arches Court of Canterbury.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary or, exposition vpon the diuine second epistle generall, written by the blessed apostle St. Peter. By Thomas Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bloome (Blome), Jacob</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 764, 2, 801-1634, 28 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRULY NOBLE, AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THILY HONOVRED, S<seg rend="sup">IR</seg> HENRY MARTEN <hi>KNIGHT;</hi> IVDGE OF HIS MAIESTIES HIGH <hi>Court of the Admiraltie, and Deane of the Arches Court of</hi> Canterbury.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>Noble</hi> SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Merchant that hath once put to SEA, and made a prosperous <hi>Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> is hardly with-held from a second <hi>Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> It hath beene my forwardnesse, not vvithout the Instinct of our Heavenly <hi>Pilot,</hi> the most Blessed <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, to make one <hi>Adventure</hi> before: For he that publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth
<pb facs="3"/> his <hi>Meditations,</hi> may be well called an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer.</hi> God knowes what <hi>returne</hi> hath beene made to his owne glorie: If but little, (and I can hope no lesse, though I have ever prayed for more) yet that hath beene to mee no little <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi> I am now <hi>put forth</hi> againe, upon the same <hi>Voyage,</hi> in hope of better successe. For my <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission</hi> I sue to <hi>You:</hi> who have no small power, both in the deciding of <hi>Civill</hi> differences, and in the disposing of <hi>Navall</hi> affaires, and matters of such commerce: being knowne well worthy of that <hi>Authority</hi> in both these <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> and <hi>Civill</hi> Courts of Iudicature: That <hi>You</hi> would bee pleased to blesse my Spirituall <hi>Trafficke</hi> with <hi>Your</hi> auspicious <hi>Approbation.</hi> I dare not commend my owne <hi>Merchandize:</hi> yet, if I had not conceived somewhat better of it, than of my former, I durst not have been so ambitious, as to present it unto <hi>You;</hi> of whose cleare understanding, deepe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and sincere integrity, all good men among us have so full and confess'd an experience. Yet besides <hi>Your</hi> owne candid disposition, and many reall encouragements to me <hi>Your</hi> poore servant; this may a little qualifie my boldnesse, and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate me from an over-daring presumption: That
<pb facs="3"/> my aime is <hi>Your Patronage,</hi> not <hi>Your</hi> Instruction; Not to informe <hi>Your wisedome,</hi> which were to hold a taper to the Sunne: but to gaine <hi>Your</hi> acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and faire allowance: That under <hi>Your</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd <hi>Name,</hi> it may finde the more free enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, wheresoever it arrives: which (I am humbly perswaded) <hi>Your</hi> Goodnesse will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. That Noble <hi>Favour</hi> of <hi>Yours,</hi> shining upon these my weake endevours, will encourage me to publish some maturer thoughts, which otherwise have resolved never to see the light. The sole <hi>Glory</hi> of our most Gratious <hi>God,</hi> the Edification and comfort of his <hi>Church,</hi> with the true felicity of of <hi>Your selfe</hi> and <hi>Yours,</hi> shall bee alwayes prayed for, by</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your ever honour'd Vertues humble and thankfull servant, <hi>THOMAS ADAMS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>