<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Stubbes, Phillip</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106904_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05358</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15511a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Stubbes, Phillip</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent and learned treatise of apostasie made by the most reuerend and godly learned man M. Iohn de l'Espine minister of the word of God in the churche of Angers in the dukedome of Anjou. Directed against the apostates in the churches of France. Written first in the French tongue by the author him selfe, and now faithfully translated into English. The contentes of the booke appeare in the page following</title>
                 <author>L'Espine, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <publisher>Morris, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 209, that is 98 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is some space of time expired since, that I purposed to write some litle treatise of Apostasie, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since the slaughter committed on Saint Bartholomewe his day, in the which there chaunced a most horrible &amp; fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reuolting in all our Churches, so that of three partes two of them at the least slipped backe, of those which in the beginning entered into it with so great readinesse and courage, that it seemed they would continually abide in it, without a mind euer to departe, whatsoeuer temptation shoulde offer it selfe vnto them. Neuerthelesse I had hitherto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the same hoping that the feare being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed, which as a storme and vehement wind, had carried them away from the sheepefold, and hauing had leisure to settle themselues and gather their wits together, they might either of themselues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, or else be easily called backe againe by the voice of their pastors. But perceiuīg that the most part of the Apostates, do not only slumber &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den themselues in their sins: but also become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of God, and blaspeme without shame his
<pb facs="6"/>word and the true religion, and not content with this, striue by all meanes to withdrawe those from the house of God which continued stedfast in his seruice, and to hinder those that desire to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it againe. I deemed it not meete to dissemble any longer, but to be necessary to put in execution the charge which God hath giuen his seruants whom he hath placed in the Church, not onely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce remission of sinnes, to all those who by a liuely faith vvill lay hold of it through the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Ghospell: but also the vvithholding of the same, from all those, vvho vvith an hard and obstinate heart, do stillre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ect the vvordes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of saluation. Which must not seeme strange, seeing the Ministers of the Ghospell be not onely ordained to vnloose &amp; absolue those that beleeue, but also to binde and condemne those that remaine obstinate in their infidelitie. For vvhich cause God seeing the stubbornnes and hardnes of the Ievves, doth send vnto them his Prophet Esay, to blind and harden them yet more.
<note place="margin">Esay. 6.9.</note>
      <hi>Go</hi> (saith he) <hi>and say vnto this people ye shall heare in deede, but ye shall not vnderstand: ye shall plainely see, and not perceiue. Make the heart of this people fat, make their eares heauy, and shut their eyes, least they see with eyes, and heare with eares, and vnderstand with their hearts, and conuert, and he heale them.</hi> Which afterward was often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb facs="6"/>alledged against the Iewes by Iesus Christ,
<note place="margin">Matth. 13. Mark. 14. Luk. 8. Acts. 28. Rom. 11.</note> &amp; his Apostles, to condemne their obstinacy. And as Moses publishing the law, said to the people, that in it he set before their eies life &amp; death, according to their obedience or disobedience towardes the same, so S. Paule writeth, that the one &amp; the other are represented in the Gospell, according as the men to whom it is preached, are faithfull or vnfaithful. <hi>We are,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.15.</note> (saith he) <hi>vnto God the sweete sauour of Christ, in them that are saued, and in them that perish:</hi> that is to say, <hi>to the one the sauour of death vnto death, &amp; to the other the sauour of life vnto life.</hi> And Iesus Christ also, as Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on said to the Virgin, <hi>is not he as well appointed for the fall, as for the rising againe of many in Israell?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 2.34.</note> And as he is to some sanctification and saluation, is he not likewise to others a blocke of stumbling, and of offence, a snare and a net vnto all those which abide in vnbeleefe? If then it chance that any Apostates or delayers of time vvill spare so much leisure as to reade this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise: I desire them that it may be with great attention, and that vvithout any passionate or preiudicate minde, they vveigh all the reasons and argumentes of the same, setting alvvayes that before their eyes, vvhich Iesus Christ spake to his Apostles: that vvhatsoeuer they shoulde binde on earth by his vvorde shoulde be ratified
<pb facs="7"/>&amp; firmly bound in heauē. To the end they may not deceiue themselues in their discourses &amp; vaine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations, esteeming the thoughtes of God to be as their thoughts, &amp; his waies as their wayes: cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto that which the Prophet sayth. Let all of vs therefore giue place vnto the worde of God, and let vs beleeue that it shall be sure for euer &amp; endure eternally. And considering that by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and irreuocable ordinance of God it is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary that all knees should bende to do homage vnto Iesus Christ: let vs rather choose to acknowledge and embrace him nowe for a Sauiour, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of life, then in the ende be constrained to auouche him and finde him, as the Deuils, a iudge that will not be intreated, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming fire.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>