<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>P., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106976_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17337</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4182</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106976</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>P., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The orator : handling a hundred seuerall discourses, in forme of declamations: some of the arguments being drawne from Titus Liuius and other ancient vvriters, the rest of the authors owne inuention: part of which are of matters happened in our age. Written in French by Alexander Siluayn, and Englished by L.P</title>
                 <author>Le Sylvain</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 176, 175-245, 244-436 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince he is to be counted a discreet man
(gentle Reader) that prouoked with
the desire of glorie, and kindeled with
good affection, indeuoreth to profit his
neighbour by vertue, and procure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
a life and residence in the memory of posterities:
I haue thought good (in hope to aduantage my selfe
with the same title) to present thee with certaine Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricall
Declamations, the vse wherof in euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
in our Commonweale, is as necessary, as the abuse
of wilfull ignorance is odious. In these thou maiest
learne Rhethoricke to inforce a good cause, and art to
impugne an ill. In these thou maiest behold the fruits
and flowers of Eloquence, which as <hi>Tully</hi> saith in his
Orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r, <hi>Bene constitutae ciuitatis est quasi alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi>
vse them to thy profit good Reader, and accept
them with as good a mind as I present them with a
vertuous intent. If thou studie law, they may helpe
thy pleadings, or if diuinitie (the reformer of law)
they may perfect they persuasions. In reasoning of
<pb facs="4"/>
priuate debates, here maiest thou find apt metaphors,
in incouraging thy souldiours fit motiues. Fathers
here haue good arguments to moue affections in their
children, and children vertuous reconcilements to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
their displeased fathers: briefly euery priuate
man may in this be partaker of a generall profit, and
the grossest vnderstanding find occasion of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
The benefits then so generall, and my intent so
honest, I heartely intreat you to keepe <hi>Talions</hi> law in
this, and pay me like for like, giue me good thoughts
for great studies, and at leastwise shew me this court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
courtesie, to affoord me good words (which cost you
nothing) for serious thoughts hatcht vp with much
consideration. Thus commending my deserts to
the learned, and committing my labour to
the instruction of the ignorant, I
bid you all heartely
farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>L. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>