<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An Admonition to the godly and gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>Stockwood, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106625_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12991</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23284</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106625</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An Admonition to the godly and gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>Stockwood, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse on Barthelmew day, being the 24. of August. 1578 : Wherin, besides many other profitable matters meete for all Christians to follovv, is at large prooued, that it is the part of all those that are fathers, householders, and scholemaisters, to instruct all those vnder their gouernement, in the vvord and knovvledge of the Lorde. By Iohn Stockvvood scholemaister of Tunbridge</title>
                 <author>Stockwood, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 174, that is 188 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ An Admonition to the godly and gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE earnest sute, and often calling vpon of certain god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brethren (most gentle and friendlye Reader) hathe at the length won at my hāds, the publishing of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in print, concerning the which, I am thus much briefly to admonish thee, namely, that al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit there be more here set down, than in deede was vttered at the Crosse, yet was the whole ment there to haue bin spokē, had not time cut off so much of it as was hādled at another place in the afternoon. Hauing therfore the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a good conscienc,e that herein is nothing auouched, which may not well by the word be warranted, I haue thoughte good to set downe the whole, and the rather, for that bothe the seconde and thirde partes, as well as the firste
<pb facs="6"/> (whiche onely was entreated at the Crosse) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine profitable admonitiō for these our times: at the whiche, although the euill disposed may quarrell: and the wicked being galled, winche and kicke (for I haue not learned to sowe soft pillows vnder their elbows, to lull them asleepe in their sinne) yet those, that are wel giuen, and godly minded, may (I doubt not) learne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lessons, whiche being putte in practise, will tourne to their profite and amendment of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. As for those that are offended (if there be anye suche) the cause is not in mee, but in themselues, whiche, if they can see (as I praye GOD hartily they maye:) I hope they wil be careful, to reforme such things in themselues, as they are here blamed for, and their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences crieth out vnto them to bee amisse: Nay there is no estate or condition of men, no not of the verye beste and moste godly, but that Cornelius may be a glasse vnto them, in which they maye see moste clearely represented, such vertues as oughte to bee in a true Christian, the wante whereof, as it is in a greate manye, yea, earneste professoures, to bee founde, so I praye GOD, that after the diligent viewe of them in thys glasse howe
<pb facs="6"/> comelye they are in a true Christian, and howe well they doe beseeme a righte godlye man, they maye with speede be carefull to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse them in a godly life, and holy conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Farewel, and make thine earnest and harty prayers vnto GOD, to blesse his Churche wyth a riche store of faithful teachers, and a moste plentifull encrease of godly, learned, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Ministers, that may open vnto his people, the true meaning and vnderstanding of hys holy and heauenly worde, and that the people may liue there vnto accordingly, for his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes sake.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy poore brother in Christ IOHN STOCKVVOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>