<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVE Generall Patron of all Muses, Musitians, Poets, &amp; Picture Drawers, Syr Christopher Clutch-Fist, Knighted at a very hard Peny-worth; nei∣ther for eating Musk-millions, Hauchouis, or Caueare; but for a costlier Exployt, and a Hundred pound Feate of Armes; Oliuer Hubburd, brother to the Nine-wayting-Gentlewomen, the Muses, wisheth the decrease of his Lands, &amp; the Encrease of his Legges, that his Calues may hang downe like Gamashioes.</title>
           <author>Hubburd, Oliver</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106483_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14778</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17874.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106483</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVE Generall Patron of all Muses, Musitians, Poets, &amp; Picture Drawers, Syr Christopher Clutch-Fist, Knighted at a very hard Peny-worth; nei∣ther for eating Musk-millions, Hauchouis, or Caueare; but for a costlier Exployt, and a Hundred pound Feate of Armes; Oliuer Hubburd, brother to the Nine-wayting-Gentlewomen, the Muses, wisheth the decrease of his Lands, &amp; the Encrease of his Legges, that his Calues may hang downe like Gamashioes.</title>
                 <author>Hubburd, Oliver</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Father Hubburds tales: or the ant and the nightingale</title>
                 <author>Middleton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cotton, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVE Generall Patron of all <hi>Muses, Musitians, Poets,</hi> &amp; <hi>Picture Drawers,</hi> Syr <hi>Christopher Clutch-Fist,</hi> Knighted at a very hard Peny-worth; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for eating <hi>Musk-millions, Hauchouis,</hi> or <hi>Caueare;</hi> but for a costlier Exployt, and a Hundred pound Feate of Armes; <hi>Oliuer Hubburd,</hi> brother to <hi>the Nine-wayting-Gentlewomen, the</hi> Muses, <hi>wisheth the decrease of his Lands, &amp; the Encrease of his Legges, that his Calues may hang downe like Gamashioes.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Guerdonlesse Syr Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. Patron, and the <hi>Muses</hi> bad Pay-maister; Thou that owest for all the Pamphlets, Histories, and Translations, that euer hath bin Dedicated to thee, since thou wert one and twentie, &amp; could'st make Water vpō thine owne Lands; but Beware, Sir, you cannot car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it away so, I can tell you, for all your Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-guilt Spurres, and your Brood of Feathers; for there are certaine Lyne-Sharkers, that haue courst the Countries to seeke you out al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie, and they nothing doubt but to find you here this <hi>Candelmas</hi> Tearme, which if it should fall out so, (as I hope your Worship is wiser thē to venture vp so soone to the Chambers of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>) they haue plotted together, with the best Common Play-Plotter in England, to arrest
<pb facs="3"/>you at the <hi>Muses</hi> sute (though they shoote short of them) and to set one of the Serfants of Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or rather the Poultry, to clawe you by the Back, who with one clap on your shoulder, will bruise all the Taffaty to pieces; now what the matter is betweene you, you knowe best your selfe, Syr; onely I heate, that they rayle against you in Booke-sellers Shoppes very dreadfully, that you haue vsde them most vn-knightly, in offering to take their Bookes, and would neuer returne so much as would pay for the Couers; beside the Gilding too; which stands them in somewhat you know; and a yard &amp; a quarter of broad six-peny Riband, the price of that, you are not ignorant of your self, bicause you weare broad shoo-string; and they cannot be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but that you pull the strings off from their Bookes, and so maintaine your shooes all the yeare long; and think verily if the Booke be in Folio, that you take off the Parchment &amp; giue it to your Taylor; but saue all the Gilding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which may amount in time to gild you a a paire of Spurs withall; such are the miserable conceits they gather of you, because you neuer giue the poore <hi>Muse</hi> suckers a peny: wherefore if I might counsell you, Sir, the next time they came with their gilded Dedicatiōs, you should take the Bookes, make your men breake their Pates, then giue them ten Groats a piece, and so driue them away.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships, if you imbrace my Counsel, Oliuer Hubburd.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>