<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the insuing Praiers and Meditations</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106420_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19772</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106420</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the insuing Praiers and Meditations</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine short prayers and meditations vpon the Lords prayer and the Ten commandements : With other particular prayers for seuerall purposes. Written by the right worshipfull Sir Iames Perrott Knight</title>
                 <author>Perrott, James, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Swaine (Swayne), Robert 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 207, that is 211, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface to <hi>the insuing Praiers and Meditations</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THE Reader may easily finde the Writers weakenesse: yet in reading per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance he may finde sowmewhat, though it be but simple, that may informe his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and stirre vp his minde to better
<pb facs="6"/>meditations. By vsing that is good, our incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations grow to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter goodnes; as by the bad, that that which is euil becoms worse. In this small and slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tract of mine, of Prayers on the Lords Prayer, and on the Decalogue, or Tenne Commandements.</p>
   <p>The first containing the rule of all our Prayers, deliuered by our Lord and Sauiour, who taught vs how, to whom, and for what to pray. This Doctrine being the
<pb facs="6"/>fountaine, and so from it, by vs, there may flow stremes of pious Prayers, though our cesternes are but shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, yet the conduit, or rather Conductor of them, may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by water the fields of our soules, and hearts with piety, felicitie, &amp; fertilnesse, that so our selues and our poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities may receiue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of all spirituall &amp; temporal blessings. The true practise of Prayer, is as the Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to heauen, the guide of our life on
<pb facs="7"/>earth, the remoouers of such Remoras, and rubbs as doe hinder vs here, and doe stay vs from eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse hereafter: For our true beliefe, <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendorum,</hi> of things to bee beleeued, which we call the Creede, is <hi>Regula</hi> &amp; <hi>via vitae,</hi> the rule and way of life. So the Decalogue, or ten Cōmandements, being <hi>regula faciendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the rule of things to be done, is <hi>vita viae</hi> the life of this way. both these making vp by feruent, frequent
<pb facs="7"/>and faithfull prayers, our progression vnto eternall life. This as a gate, the other as goles vnto eternall glory; betwixt these two, Prayers are as the Sayles, &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit as the wings that carries vs thorow the troblesome waues of this world, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs vp in all tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, afflictions, and calamities. In the vse of Prayers, as of the other parts of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Humility is the ground, Faith the foundation, Petition
<pb facs="8"/>and thankesgiuing the walles, eleuated Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations the roofe, &amp; knowledge ioyned with conscience, the props and pillars. So is holy prayer made <hi>scala caeli,</hi> the ladder that leades vs to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend vnto heauen. Prayer then being the precious balme of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> that cures the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string sores of our sinnes; I craue pardon to publish these my weake conceptions of Prayers and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from no other
<pb facs="8"/>purpose, but to helpe the weake and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in their well dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed devotions. To such I say, it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to pray much, long and often, except it bee done with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generat, a deuout, and an vnderstāding hart, although the saying was ancient: <hi>Breuis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio penetrat caelum;</hi> short Praier pierceth the heauens. Yet it is neither the length, nor shortnes of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that mooues God vnto mercy, vnlesse they be ioyned with
<pb facs="9"/>a godly and conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vse of them, in clensing and casting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our corruptions, distractions, dulnesse, coldnesse, carnal cares &amp; vaine imaginations, which presse vpon vs in the time of Prayer, when it is not the voyce, or the sound of words, but the holy affection and pure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of the heart, with the assistance of Gods holy spirit, that makes our prayers vnto God profitable, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as the olde verse hath it.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <q>
      <l>Non vox, sed votum; non cordula musica, sed cor:</l>
      <l>Non clamans, sed amans, cantat in ore Dei.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Which signifieth thus much,
<q>
         <l>Not voyce, but vowes; not musick but the heart,</l>
         <l>Not cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>es but loue; sweet songs to God impart.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>If any man questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, why so many trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises of prayer being published; my selfe or any other should set foorth any more; therein yet I conceiue it is with the readers, and specially with the vsers and learners of Prayers, as with Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians
<pb facs="10"/>who seeking simples to cure their Patients, goe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to one garden, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or fielde to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, but vnto many: for in some places there grows of one kind, in some an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other sort. So in the relish, vse, &amp; choise of prayers, which is that herbe of grace; Some desire such as are short and pithy, others make vse of them that are of good length &amp; waight. Besides, this consideration, though I acknowledge there
<pb facs="10"/>are diuers excellent treatises of Prayers, yet I haue seldome seene any, that haue closly and punctually handled the Petitions of the Lords Prayer, and the parts of the Ten Cōmandements, with a strict mixture of Doctrinall Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the forme, and to be vsed as prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, containing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their contents, which I haue indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my weake skill and iudgement. First, for mine owne
<pb facs="11"/>exercise, and then for the use of such as shal neede, and desire it as much as I doe. Which I haue done the rather, because I see how feareful, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and common a thing it is, to finde such multitudes of people, who vsing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lords Prayer, or reading the Tenne Cōmandements, with out premeditation or knowledge what ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them contains, do yot think that they haue sufficiently ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God, when they
<pb facs="11"/>know little, or vse not that aright they shold know, and doe better. To knowe much and doe little, doth little auaile in diuine or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things: to doe much &amp; to know little proues vnprofitable, if not hurtfull. Yet not to finde fault with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but to come home vnto my selfe: for these my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, such as they are I leaue them with the readers and vsers of them, to the direction of Gods holy Spirit.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>