<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Reader, the Translator sendeth gree∣ting in Christ Iesu.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106678_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19891</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106678</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Reader, the Translator sendeth gree∣ting in Christ Iesu.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summe of the Guisian ambassage to the Bishop of Rome, founde lately amongst the writinges of one Dauid an aduocate of Paris, and translated out of French into Latin, and from Latin into English</title>
                 <author>David, Advocate of Paris</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian Reader, <hi>the Translator sendeth gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> in Christ Iesu.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His little Pamphlet,</hi> (good Reader) being fyrst ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in French, and after trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Latin, came vnto my hands by chaūce, perusing other bookes which were brought from <hi>Franckford:</hi> and ouerrunning shortly the same, and percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that it contayned the discouerye of a very da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngerous and mischeuous practise of the Papistes in Fraunce, especially of the <hi>Guisian</hi> faction, which vnder pretence of the maintenaunce of the Catholick or Romish faith, (as it may seeme) beeing thereunto by the Pope, and his fauorers induced for the vpholding of his pride and ambicion, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Haeriticall and erronious doctrine, which by the Gospell in the noble Realme of Fraunce, as in all other places in Christendom is now laide open and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted, to their no small losse &amp; griefe, seeke
<pb facs="3"/> I speake rather to aspire to the tytle of the Crowne of that mighty Kingdome, by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye claiming vnto thēselues, the right ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as the heyres discending lineallye from <hi>Charles</hi> the great: and pleading the <hi>Valoys,</hi> with the <hi>Borbones</hi> to be but vsurpers, and intruders: who at this daye are the right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunt heyres thereof: I thought good to publish the same to the view of the worlde, leauing the creadit thereof to the Reporter, that it may appeare both how cruell and bloodthirsty a generation these Papistes are, who can neuer be satisfyed with the shedding of their breathernes bloode, and that from <hi>Rome</hi> that spirituall <hi>Babilon,</hi> as from a Fountaine flowing into all Christē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the continuall discords, contentions, tumults, warres vprores, treasons and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions wherewith the same is lamentably at this day oppressed, and ouerwhelmed: as also to shew how vniustlye they burthen and charge the godly, and zelous nobility, and Subiectes of that Realme and other places with Treason and rebellion against theyr Soueraignes, and Princes, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="3"/> being most giltye thereof, when they withstand with all reasonable, and lawfull meanes the vniust, violent, tirrannicall, and vnnatural oppressions, and inuasions, prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised against them, besydes all lawe of God and man, by the Pope, abusinge the Scepters and aucthorite of Princes, to the establishing of his longe vsurped primacie, Pride and Ambition, in the Church of Christ. For how so euer he colloureth his purposes with faire showes: yet is it euident to those that are not blinded with affection malice, or by the iust iudgements of God cast into a reprobate sence, that he seeketh his owne and not those thinges which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto Christ, and that he discrieth him selfe to be very Antichriste, in settinge vp his owne kingdom, with the ouerthrow of the kingdom of Christ, and his Gospell, (as much as lyeth in him,) knowing, &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by experience, to his great griefe (Gods name be praised therefore) that the one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not stand with the other.</p>
   <p>Therefore when it pleased God to make manifest to the world, by the glorious light
<pb facs="4"/> of the Gospel of his sonne, how trayterous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, wickedlye, and blasphemouslye in the middest of grose and palpable darcknesse, he hath vsurped &amp; intruded vpon the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his Christ, and he begins to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine possession thereof, and shaketh, like a tottering wall, the kingdome of <hi>Antichrist:</hi> he perceiuing the ruine of his vsurped ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny to be threatned in all Christendome, and Christ like to recouer his owne posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion againe, ioyned with his confederats, &amp; laid their heads together, sundry and diuers times, especially in the late pretended coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell holden at <hi>Trent,</hi> and considered what was best to be donne in this so desperate a state: and when they had sought by diuers meanes to bringe the same to passe, as by writing of bookes for their defence, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing sum what to haue bin amisse, and to promisse redresse thereof (which they neuer ment in trueth) by often promising of a generall, lawfull, and free counsel, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer performing it, by threatnings, sometime force and warres, and vsinge the same some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, &amp; by diuers other suttle deuises, which
<pb facs="4"/> neuerthelesse by the prouidence of God came to nought. Then they determined at last in theyr sayd pretenced Counsell of <hi>Trent,</hi> that seeing by no other waye they were able to compasse theyr intent, and to hold and proppe vp theyr ruynous state, (which they make more accoumpt of then the glory of God): that ther should be made (forsooth) a holy league betweene the holy father, and all his obedient Children which kisse his feete, against all the professours of the Gospell in Christendome: with a full resolution, that it should be lawful for them by the dispensation of the holy Father, to vse all Treachery, deceite, periury, violence and crueltye against them, as beeing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, and condemned by the sayde holye Counsell of <hi>Trent.</hi> And that the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof might be donne with more heede, and dylligence, some were in all Countreys appointed who shoulde vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the same. And herehence, hath sith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens rysen the Fyre and Flame of discenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, mutynes, and tumultes in all Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>This I thought good (gentle reader) to admonish thee of, that in reading of this small discourse, thou mightest with more light and iudgement, looke into the popish practises therein contayned. The Lorde God make vs wise in foreseeing their perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious coūsels, &amp; auoiding the same in time. For as they haue in that noble Realme of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and in other places shewed theyr malitious intents, so mynd they to do the like, it is to be feared in England, if God doo not of his mercy let them, which he graunt, for Iesus Christe his sake. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>