<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Rawley, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106909_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01552</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1168</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106909</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Rawley, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sylua syluarum: or A naturall historie : In ten centuries. VVritten by the Right Honourable Francis Lo. Verulam Viscount St. Alban. Published after the authors death, by VVilliam Rawley Doctor of Diuinitie, late his Lordships chaplaine</title>
                 <author>Bacon, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Lee, William 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 266, 16, 47, 5 pages, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>HAuing had the Honour to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
with my <hi>Lord,</hi> in compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
of this <hi>Worke;</hi> And to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
therein; I haue thought it
not amisse, (with his Lordships
good leaue and liking,) for the better satisfaction
of those that shall reade it, to make knowne some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
of his Lordships Intentions, touching the
Ordering, and Publishing of the same. I haue
heard his Lordship often say; that if hee should
haue serued the glory of his owne Name, he had
been better not to haue published this <hi>Naturall
History:</hi> For it may seeme an Indigested Heap
of Particulars; And cannot haue that Lustre,
which Bookes cast into Methods haue: But that
he resolued to preferre the good of Men, and
that which might best secure it, before any thing
that might haue Relation to Himselfe. And hee
knew well, that ther was no other way open, to
vnloose Mens mindes, being bound; and (as
it were) Maleficiate, by the Charmes of decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
Notions, and Theories; and therby made
<pb facs="5"/>
Impotent for Generation of VVorkes; But onely
no wher to depart from the Sense, and cleare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience;
But to keepe close to it, especially in the
beginning: Besides, this <hi>Naturall History</hi> was a
Debt of his, being Designed and set downe for a
third part of the <hi>Instauration.</hi> I haue also heard
his Lordship discourse, that Men (no doubt)
will thinke many of the <hi>Experiments</hi> conteined in
this Collection, to bee Vulgar and Triuiall;
Meane and Sordid; Curious and Fruitlesse: And
therfore he wisheth, that they would haue perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
before their Eyes, what is now in doing;
And the Difference betweene this <hi>Naturall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story,</hi>
and others. For those <hi>Naturall Histories,</hi>
which are Extant, being gathered for Delight and
Vse, are full of pleasant Descriptions and Pictures;
and affect and seeke after Admiration, Rarities,
and Secrets. But contrariwise, the Scope which
his Lordship intendeth, is to write such a <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
History,</hi> as may be Fundamentall to the Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
and Building of a true <hi>Philosophy:</hi> For the
Illumination of the <hi>Vnderstanding;</hi> the Extracting
of <hi>Axiomes;</hi> and the producing of many Noble
<hi>Works,</hi> and <hi>Effects.</hi> For he hopeth, by this meanes,
to acquit Himselfe of that, for which hee taketh
<hi>Himselfe</hi> in a sort bound; And that is, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement
of all Learning and Sciences. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
in this present VVorke Collected the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls
for the Building; And in his <hi>Novum
Organum</hi> (of which his Lordship is yet to publish
<pb facs="5"/>
a Second Part,) set downe the Instruments and
Directions for the Worke; Men shall now bee
wanting to themselues, if they raise not Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
to that perfection, whereof the Nature of
Mortall men is capable. And in this behalfe, I
haue heard his Lordship speake complainingly;
That his Lordship (who thinketh hee deserueth
to be an Architect in this building,) should be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
to be a VVork-man and a Labourer; And to
digge the Clay, and burne the Brick; And more
then that, (according to the hard Condition of the
<hi>Israelites</hi> at the latter end) to gather the Strawe
and Stubble, ouer all the Fields, to burn the Bricks
withall. For he knoweth, that except hee doe it,
nothing will be done: Men are so sett to despise
the Meanes of their owne good. And as for
the <hi>Basenes</hi> of many of the Experiments; As long
as they be Gods VVorks, they are Honourable
enough. And for the <hi>Vulgarnes</hi> of them; true <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiomes</hi>
must be drawne from plaine Experience,
and not from doubtfull; And his Lordships course
is, to make VVonders Plaine, and not Plaine
things VVonders; And that Experience likewise
must be broken and grinded, and not whole, or
as it groweth. And for <hi>Vse;</hi> his Lordship hath
often in his Mouth, the two kindes of <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
Experimenta Fructifera,</hi> and <hi>Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta
Lucifera: Experiments of Vse,</hi> and <hi>Experiments
of Light;</hi> And he reporteth himself, whether he
were not a strange Man, that should thinke that
<pb facs="6"/>
Light hath no Vse, because it hath no Matter.
Further, his Lordship thought good also, to add
vnto many of the <hi>Experiments</hi> themselues, some
<hi>Glosse</hi> of the <hi>Causes;</hi> that in the succeeding work of
<hi>Interpreting Nature,</hi> and <hi>Framing Axiomes,</hi> all
things may be in more Readines. And for the
<hi>Causes</hi> herein by Him assigned; his Lordship
perswadeth Himselfe, they are farr more certaine,
then those that are rendred by Others; Not for
any Excellency of his owne Witt, (as his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
is wont to say) but in respect of his continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Conuersation with <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Experience.</hi>
He did consider likewise, that by this Addition of
<hi>Causes,</hi> Mens mindes (which make so much hast
to find out the <hi>Causes</hi> of things;) would not think
themselues vtterly lost, in a Vast VVood of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi>
but stay vpon these <hi>Causes,</hi> (such as they
are) a little, till true <hi>Axiomes</hi> may be more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
discouered. I haue heard his Lordship say al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so,
that one great Reason, why he would not put
these Particulars into any exact <hi>Method,</hi> (though
he that looketh attentiuely into them, shall finde
that they haue a secret Order) was, because hee
conceiued that other men would now thinke,
that they could doe the like; And so goe on
with a further Collection: which if the <hi>Method</hi>
had been Exact, many would haue despaired to
attaine by Imitation. As for his Lordships loue
of Order, I can referr any Man to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships
Latine Booke, <hi>De Augmentis Scientiarum;</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
which (if my Iudgment be any thing) is written
in the Exactest Order, that I know any Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
to bee. I will conclude with an vsuall Speech
of his Lordships.<note place="margin">This Epistle is the same, that should haue been prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this Booke, if his Lordship had liued.</note> That this Worke of his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
History,</hi> is the <hi>World,</hi> as GOD made it,
and not as Men haue made it; For that it hath
nothing of Imagination.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>W: Rawley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>