<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS LOVING Kinsman, and approued Friend, Mr. HENRY CHOLMELY Esquire: WILLIAM HORNBY wisheth all health and happinesse.</title>
           <author>Hornby, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106238_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03688</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13815</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106238</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS LOVING Kinsman, and approued Friend, Mr. HENRY CHOLMELY Esquire: WILLIAM HORNBY wisheth all health and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Hornby, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scourge of drunkennes. By William Hornby Gent</title>
                 <author>Hornby, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bailey (Baily, Baley, Bayly), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS LOVING Kinsman, and approued Friend, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. HENRY CHOLMELY Esquire: WILLIAM HORNBY wisheth all health and happinesse.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue presum'd to Dedicate this Booke</l>
      <l>Vnto your selfe (Kinde Sir,) vouchsafe to looke</l>
      <l>Into the same: and with indicious eyes</l>
      <l>View here the difference twixt the foole and wise.</l>
      <l>I count them fooles, which night by night doe sit</l>
      <l>In Tauernes for to foolifie their wit;</l>
      <l>Suffring strong wine to domineire and braue,</l>
      <l>And so make Reason a poore captiue slaue:</l>
      <l>Who with Hell-smoaking vapours doe delight</l>
      <l>To turne night into day, day into night:</l>
      <l>In which they Time, Wealth, Wit, and all doe wast,</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Because to beggery they soone would hast.</l>
      <l>I deeme them wise which can this sinne eschew,</l>
      <l>And blesse themselues from such a damned crew</l>
      <l>Of hate full hell-hounds, in all sinnes growne ripe,</l>
      <l>Which daily daunce before the Diuels Pipe:</l>
      <l>There's not a vice, but they'r expert in all,</l>
      <l>And ready into Hels wide mouth to fall.</l>
      <l>At <hi>Bacchus</hi> Altars they their sinnes deplore:</l>
      <l>And <hi>Venus</hi> for their Goddesse doe adore.</l>
      <l>All vertuous thoughts they from their hearts expell,</l>
      <l>And neuer thinke of Iudgement, Heauen, or Hell.</l>
      <l>Then blest are they (I say) which sober liue,</l>
      <l>And not an eare to their inticements giue:</l>
      <l>Which keepe <hi>decorum</hi> euer in their wayes,</l>
      <l>Both to Gods glory, and their endlesse praise:</l>
      <l>By this they shall preserue their wealth and name</l>
      <l>From preiudice, from scandall and from shame:</l>
      <l>By this they shall be honor'd and renown'd,</l>
      <l>Where speciall vertues in them so abound,</l>
      <l>'Tis euer best a golden meane to keepe,</l>
      <l>And not to cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mbe too high, nor wade too deepe,</l>
      <l>Lest climbing high, the greater be their fall,</l>
      <l>And by deepe wading they be drown'd withall.</l>
      <l>To keepe vs then from falling eyther way,</l>
      <l>Vpon this staffe let our affections stay</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Of blessed Golden Meane, there let vsrest;</l>
      <l>So liue, so dye; and dying so, be blest.</l>
      <l>Thus hoping you will kindely this receiue,</l>
      <l>The rest vnto your generous thoughts I leaue.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Kinsman to be commanded, WILLIAM HORNBY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>