<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface vppon the Lamentations of the Prophet Ieremiah.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106039_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11581</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2779.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106039</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface vppon the Lamentations of the Prophet Ieremiah.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentations and holy mourninges of the prophet Ieremiah : with a lamentable paraphrase and exhortation, meete euery way to be applyed vnto these our dayes: for the comforting of all the true faithfull children of God that are vnder the crosse and feele their miseries and for the awaking of all those that haue no feeling of their miseries: not-with-standing the great calamities which haue fallen and still are like to fall vpon these our dayes. Published by Daniel Toussaine, and translated out of French into English, by Tho. Sto. gent</title>
                 <author>Tossanus, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bate, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 264 pages, coat of arms, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface vppon the <hi>Lamentations of the Prophet</hi> Ieremiah.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S men in times past, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to set vppe pillers or stakes, as markes for those whiche trauelled through Champion coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, to knowe the way by, which some mē called, Mercuries marks: And as men giue a bunch of keyes to those which would goe into an house to view and see all the chambers and closets of the same: Euen so likewise hath it beene a custome, for the setting of Readers in a right &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable way of reading any book, to set foorth some preface, for the laying open eyther of the phrase or argument, eyther else of the Methode or order, or of the vse of that book which a man wil take in hande to interpret. Some there are that make much a do in set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth and aduauncing those authours, vpon whose workes they intende to coment, as <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> writing vpon <hi>Paule</hi> his
<pb facs="5"/> Epistles, hath done. Howbeit, it is a thing of all others, least necessarie, namely when the Authors are sufficiently knowen, &amp; of such note and marke, as that in too too much cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of them, it is but a darkening of their commendacions, as of the ouer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of the Prophetes, and of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles. And therefore it shall not be needeful, to make any great narration in the commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> who was a right faithfull seruaunt of the Lordes, and a valiant preacher of his iust iudgementes, and therefore out of all measure, more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, tossed and tourmoyled, and crossed than any of all the other Prophets euer were, yea euen put to a thousand deathes: who issued and descended from the rest of the stocke of the Priests, that were resiant in <hi>Anathoth,</hi> belonging to the ligne of <hi>Beiamin,</hi> descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high Priest, whom king <hi>Salomon,</hi> as in the <hi>2.</hi> Chap. of the <hi>1.</hi> Booke of the kinges, we reade, had bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed thether.</p>
   <p>It shall suffice therefore at this present, that we aduertise the Readers of foure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie pointes to be obserued, in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of these Lamentations of Ieremie.</p>
   <p>First, of the Title, or inscription of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Booke.</p>
   <p>Secondarily, of the occasion, and of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <pb facs="6"/> argument, or subiect thereof.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, of the Methode, or order which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Prophet keepeth.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, of the vse of this Treatise, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> how requisite the consideration thereof is, for the dayes wherein we liue.</p>
   <p>The first point then that in this litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise must be regarded, which the Hebrewes alwayes accustomed to cut off, and separate from the prophesie of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and place it after the bookes of <hi>Moses,</hi> among the holie collections (as we call them) that is to say, The Canticle of Canticles, Ruth, Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astes, the booke of Hester, and such other like, is this, That the Jewes in the bodie of the Bible, called this commonly by none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name, but by the first worde wherewith the Lamentations beginne, which worde is, ECHA, that is to saye, HOWE, And this worde, according to the iudgement of the Hebrewes, is encountered not without some mysterie, thrice in the beginning of three of the Chapters of these Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to wit, in the beginning of the first, seconde, and fourth: some supposing, that these three encounters of one and the selfe same worde, haue regard vnto the thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in trinitie: some others taking it as for a perfect number, haue regard to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, whole, and totall desolation of the citie
<pb facs="6"/> of Jerusalem, and of the countrey round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, when as the Hebrewes make mention of this booke in their commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they call it, CINOTH, that is to say, Lamentations or mournings, proceeding from a lamentable voyce, hauing alwaies an vndoubted regarde to the principall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Booke. For, although we finde in this little booke, consolations and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers mixte together, especially in the fifte Chapiter: yet beareth it iustly and of very right, the name of the chiefe argument, and principall matter, and is a verie fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling sorrowe and griefe, and a most liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly representation of the ignominie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch, which at that time lighted vpon <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> and vpon the whole countrey of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The seauentie interpreters vnto whome the Greeke translation is attributed, and the common latine translation also, for the helping of the argument, haue put in these wordes in the beginning thereof: <hi>And it came to passe, that after Israell was ledde captiue, that the Prophet Ieremiah sate weeping, and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ouer Ierusalem, with this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, sighing and groning in the bitternesse of his heart; and saying,
<pb facs="7"/> as followeth. &amp;c.</hi> Howbeit we can finde no such thing written in the Hebrew text.</p>
   <p>As concerning the argument, subiect, and occasion of this shorte Treatise of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, there is no likelihoode, as <hi>Rabe Salomon</hi> and some others thinke, that it should be the same booke, whereof mention is made in the <hi>30.</hi> Chapter of <hi>Ieremie</hi> his prophecie: which when <hi>Ieremie</hi> had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to <hi>Baruch</hi> by worde of mouth, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde, read to the people: and after, that king <hi>Ioachim,</hi> had once gotten it into his handes, he foorthwith cut it in pieces with a penneknife, and threw it into the fire. For there expresse mention is made, that there were no Lamentations conteyned within that Booke, but the threatninges of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Iudith:</hi> yea euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same demonstrations, which the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> had before, liuely made, which <hi>Baruch</hi> describing, was ouercome with sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing and sighing, as in the <hi>45.</hi> chapter of <hi>Ieremie</hi> we may reade.</p>
   <p>Neither must we thinke, that that which is saide in the beginning of the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Lamentations: <hi>I am the man, that hath seene affliction in the rodde of his indignation, and that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth,</hi> any whit fauoureth the foresaide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pinion: as though <hi>Ieremie</hi> would frame a
<pb facs="7"/> complaint only of his particular aduersities, and of the tormentes which the Jewes had vsed against him before the taking of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem.</hi> For, we knowe well inough, that it is a customarie thing with the Prophets, to represent, and as a man would saye, inuest, and put vpon them the person of the people, aswell, the more to stirre vp the Auditorie, and strike their heartes, as also because it is the nature of Charitie, to appropriate the publike myseries to her selfe, and so take them as if they particularly touched euerie one of vs. Such a great and notable courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie and faithfulnes was in the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi> as that although the people of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> had, through their stubbernnesse, and rebellion, heaped vpon themselues such mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series in that they had despitefully, &amp; arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly contemned, and trode vnder foote, the holy aduertisementes of this good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: yet would hee not but be partaker of their sorrowe and ruine, as if the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had particularly lyen vpon himselfe. O tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> and singular strict and straite line of heartie and tender loue. Such a heartie loue also had that excellent Martyr <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> when writing vpon those, that in the time of persecution had stumbled and slidde, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it downe in these termes, I am partaker of the heauie burden of their griefe: J la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="8"/> with those that lament: I account my selfe among those which are abased and cast downe: A brotherly affection suteth me in the same bunch of my forlorne brethren, &amp;c. And thus much as concerning the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide opinion.</p>
   <p>Howbeit there are some, and that verie great Clerkes and learned personages, which are of the opinion, that these Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie</hi> were written immediately after the death of that good King <hi>Iosias,</hi> and that by reason of the Lamentable discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyture, in the fieldes of Mageddo. Which they grounde vppon two principall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. First vpon that that is recited in the <hi>35.</hi> Chapiter of the seconde of the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, That the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> lamented the death of <hi>Iosias.</hi> But this me seemeth to be a verie weake reason. For certes, this is out of all doubt, that <hi>Ieremie</hi> had manie griefes, and in his dolourous life, made many Lamentations: aswell because of the greeuous sinnes of the people, and their hardnesse of heart: as also by reason of the desolations which he fore sawe: and otherwhile, eyther for the death of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sias,</hi> or else for some other good and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orous men. Alas, howe this good seruaunt of God powred out sighes and riuers of bloudie and bitter teares, as amonge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="8"/> thinges in the ninth, <hi>10.12.14.</hi> and <hi>20.</hi> Chapiters of his Prophesie appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
   <p>But it is one thing to Lament for some particular accidentes, or for the death of a <hi>Iosias,</hi> for whome all the people, and all the singing men and singing women lamented: and an other thing to bewayle the whole destruction and ouerthrowe of an Estate and Kingdome, yea, and that of the moste famous and Noble Citie that then was in all the worlde, and which was, as it were, the verie Theater of all the most rare and singular fauourers of the Lorde, which verely deserueth an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse treatise, and such especiall Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations as in this booke wee see: and it is, J say, a good thing to see, how the Prophet had hereunto in these lamentations a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall regarde.</p>
   <p>The other reason, which they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre these Lamentations to the dayes of <hi>Iosias,</hi> is the place in the fourth of these Lamentations, where mention is made of the taking of the annoynted of the Lorde. Vnder whose shadowe, the people sayde, they should liue, among the Heathen. But in this reason there seemeth no probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, because that King <hi>Iosias</hi> was not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb facs="9"/> but hurt, and foorthwith carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ierusalem</hi> by his people, where he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately died.</p>
   <p>Other later learned interpreters seeme to followe an opinion betweene both, that they might reconcile both the one and the other, saying, that in very deede the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and first occasion of the myseries of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and Lamentations of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> was the death of the valiant king <hi>Iosias,</hi> but that notwithstanding these Lamentations exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded euen to the going forwarde of the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which continued vnto the captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the vtter ouerthrowe of all <hi>Iudah.</hi> As in verie deede after the death of <hi>Iosias,</hi> there was no great quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in <hi>Iudah,</hi> but that great and huge billowes of all sortes of myseries arose one in an others necke, because, as in the <hi>34.</hi> chapter of the seconde of the Chronicles we reade, that hardly could the horrible furie of God his iustice, which <hi>Manasses, Iosias</hi> his predecessor, had prouoked, be appeased: such a fearefull thing it is once to fall into the hands of the Almightie, and to force his patience.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ioachas,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Iosias</hi> reigned on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three monethes. After him, the king of <hi>Aegypt</hi> established <hi>Ioachim,</hi> king: whom <hi>Iechonia</hi> succeeded and in his dayes, the
<pb facs="9"/> Babylonians spoyled the citie, and soone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter destroyed it, by reason of <hi>Zedechia</hi> his rebellion. Thus we see that after the death of <hi>Iosias</hi> there was nothing, as it were, but a full and through continuance of miseries.</p>
   <p>But seeing J am freely to speake my minde, which of their opinions is most like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, J willingly yeelde to them, that thinke these Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie</hi> not to bee so much a prophesie, or a denunciation, or portrayture of a thing to come, as a sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, greeuing, and complayning of a most notorious and euident extreame present ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie: whether it was that <hi>Ieremie</hi> wrote them in pryson, whiles the citie was a sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: or whether it was that he put them in writing sythence, whiles he was with <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doliah</hi> in <hi>Masphat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For, at the verie first entrance,<note place="margin">Iere. 40.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of euerie Chapter, hee lamenteth not any particular accident, but a generall ruine and deluge of myseries, which fell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole countrie: to be short, a totall turning vp side downe as well of the citie of <hi>Ierusalem</hi> (which <hi>Plinie</hi> himselfe hath placed in the ranke among the chiefest Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the East) as also of the whole seruice and worship of God: likewise of the ciuill policie, and of the whole gouernement both spirituall and temporall: a thing, which is
<pb facs="10"/> able mightily to wounde true setled heartes, to see the couenaunt of GOD, as it were frustrated, and the right religion derided and reproched, whiche hath mooued the Prophet to aggrauate, and engraue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this notable Booke, for Posteritie to come, all these disorders, and confused dealinges: to the ende to cause the people that then were, and the generation that should come after, feele the wrath and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God his iust vengeaunce, and howe foolishe they are, that giue their mindes to hearken vnto priuie deceauers and false Prophetes, which lulle worldlinges asleepe in their sinnes, and fourde them on in a vaine hope, as though God for the loue of the outwarde temple, for the loue of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, for the loue of an outward profession, and for the loue of the name of the Church, should surcease the execution of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō reward for plaine and sound dealing.</note> as the people of <hi>Iudah</hi> were often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too too much falsely deceaued by these enchauntments: wishing to good <hi>Ieremie,</hi> that dealt plainly and faithfully with them an euill death, because hee soundely and roundly tolde them of the mischiefe which hunge ouer their heades, and because also, that for their daily exceeding in all kindes of sinnes, they must looke for none other paiment but vtter desolation. Thus wee
<pb facs="10"/> see the matter, J saye, which the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> heere handled in these Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
   <p>Nowe hee handeleth, and setteth it downe in such manner, as that the whole Booke seemeth rather to bee his Historie, than a foretelling of a thinge to come: hee so liuely and earnestly pictureth out and setteth before our eyes all sortes of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or else all the occurrauntes and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstaunces of this Lamentable destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> which the <hi>Assyrians</hi> shall bring to passe, and of the captiuitie aswell of the Princesse, as of the people. True it is, because hee right well knewe, that this shoulde not bee the last destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that in the ende of <hi>70.</hi> yeares, the Lorde God would restore againe the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiued people vnto their pleasaunt countrey and restablish both them-selues and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion within their Citie: hee entermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth as it were all ouer holy prayers and consolations, to comforte the heartes of good menne with-all, to the ende they shoulde not bee vtterly discouraged, and hopelesse. Nowe, the like comfortes and promises the Jewes had not in the laste siege and destruction, when <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Vespasian</hi> came against them: For at that time, the Prophetes of GOD gaue
<pb facs="11"/> them cleane ouer, because their wickednesse was come now to the full ripenesse, when as they vtterly reiected and crucified the great Prophet of Prophetes, and the Doctor of Doctors, Christ Iesus our Lorde, banished, murdered, and persecuted his Prophetes: and to be short, would not vnderstande the time of their visitation. And thus much as touching the argument of the Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
   <p>Now followeth, that we consider of the Methode or order, and artificiall handling of this writing: which no man can suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently admire, if he looke well to the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For, although the Orators haue nere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found out and inuented many wayes and mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, eyther for the highly commending of any great and excellent thing, eyther else for the bewayling or lamenting of certaine sorrowes and griefes, which kinde of speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing Tully in the <hi>3.</hi> of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, reputeth to be the most rich and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and most profitable kinde of order for common-weales: yet the fardle of mans elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, commeth nothing neere the nature and dexteritie of the Lamentations, which the spirite of God hath framed in <hi>Ieremie</hi> his heart, and vttered foorth by mouth to the vse of all the Hebrewes. And although in this Treatise, the Prophet enterlaceth
<pb facs="11"/> prayers and exhortations to repentance, &amp; withall consolations: yet they are all so pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall, or of such notable feeling as is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible: and it is the principall scope whereat he aimeth, to discouer, in lamenting the geatnesse of God his wrath, and so conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the greatnesse of the iniquities and sinnes of the people, that they might serue him, as it were for matter and woode, to set such a fire on a light flame. Moreouer, the Prophet so Lamenteth the case, as that hee keepeth him-selfe still within his limites, without soaring a-loft in the ayre in long discourses, which haue not the grace, so liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to touch mens heartes, as graue, natural, and short sentences, proceeding from out of a sorrowefull and wounded heart, which is vnmeete for long or affected speaches: as this Romaine Oratour <hi>Tullie</hi> also testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, It is an hard matter, sayth he, to keepe men long while in a very passioned behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any myserie, because it is a thing that sooner dryeth vp, than the teares of a mans eyes. And such are the stile, and words of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in these Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that is to saye, graue, and feeling,</p>
   <p>Beautified with liuely portraytures, and verie fitte comparisons, which lead the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders euen vnto the behoulding of the verie same thinges that are spoken of. If then
<pb facs="12"/> by the art Oratorie, mens heartes are made flexible to compassion, when as there shalbe tould and figured out vnto them, the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine chaunges and reuolutions from great prosperitie to extreame beggerie, from an high estate, vnto a base and myserable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: then of verie right ought a man to be mooued by these Lamentations of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie:</hi> which art is aswell practized here, as any Oratour in the worlde is able. And it is a great deale lesse suspected, because hee lamenteth not any particular mishappes, but the spoyling of an whole countrey, and the verie ruine thereof. And this J say, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> so artificially and orderly handleth, as that it is no maruel that <hi>Gregorie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzene</hi> wrote as he did, when he sayde: That hee neuer reade the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie</hi> without teares. And to say the truth, who would not be mooued to see these holy Lamentations, proceeding from the loue of God: the loue of a mans Countrey: the loue of pure and holy Religion: the loue of order and policie: the loue of his fellowe Citizens, and of so many &amp; so many fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, who with a worlde of young children are seene lead in exile, or else to the shambles, and euerie estate turned vpside downe. For, the greater, the more surpassing, and the more singular that the benefits of God were
<pb facs="12"/> vnto the Citie of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> the more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable was her destruction. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was verie well sayde of <hi>Tully,</hi> when he sayde, That there was nothing more to be pitied, then to see a man that hath beene in great prosperitie, and aduaunced to high degree of honour, to be cast downe into great myserie and pouertie.</p>
   <p>Nowe, although in verie deede, a man shal here and there meete with many mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges and lamentations in the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as among the rest, with that which we reade in the first of the <hi>2.</hi> of Samuel, where <hi>Dauid</hi> hartely and tenderly mourned and lamented for the death of King <hi>Saul:</hi> most affectionately bewailing the lamentable dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture which came to passe in the mount <hi>Gelboa:</hi> yet shall we finde nothing so am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, serious, and enriched with all sortes of excellent comparisons, neither yet grounded vppon so great and manifest reasons, as are the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie:</hi> about which, are fiue whole Chapters spent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any superfluous kinde of matter in them, but diuersely handled with manie excellent and straunge protractions, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uishing sometimes mens mindes with asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, and casting them downe, as it were, into a bottomlesse depth, &amp; sometimes againe raysing thē vp, into an hope of Gods
<pb facs="13"/> grace and fauour, bringing them thereby, vnto true and vnfeyned repentance. But all set out with a most comely grace: represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting first of all in generall, the miseries of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> vnder the person of a poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate widdowe, or of a Princesse, suddenly throwen downe from the highest degree of honour, into a most miserable seruile estate. And after all this, there are liuely represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the tryumphes and braueries of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, by which they thought to breake euen the very heart stringes of these mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable afflicted people.</p>
   <p>In the seconde chapter, the Prophet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to particularize euerie charge, and to descifer by piece meale, the notablest losses that that countrey of <hi>Iudah</hi> had, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Egyptians at that time, furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously entred, and chiefely and aboue all the rest he bewayleth, as a man would saye, the losse of the two eyes, and two perles of the countrey, which are Religion, and politicke gouernement, The order of Priesthoode and kingly state: dolefully lamenting their scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, and the rest of the thinges depending vpon them as the ruine of the Prophetes, Nazarites, fortresses, castles, and such other like thinges.</p>
   <p>Jn the thirde chapter, the Prophet ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpō him, the person of the people, very
<pb facs="13"/> fitly expresseth &amp; representeth the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al conflictes, which the poore afflicted soules in their great distresses were wont to suffer together with the issue &amp; victorie, which the faithfull through faith obtayned.</p>
   <p>The fourth Chapter setteth out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and layeth open a way and meanes to heale the wound, by setting down a forme of free confession of sinnes. For, the first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to heale a wounde, it to haue a through feeling of the griefe and paine, and after to seeke the remedie. The Prophet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in this chapter, addeth a propheticall foretelling of the destruction of the enemie: thereby continually to ease the wounde and sore of the Jewes, and aduaunce their hope.</p>
   <p>Jn the fifte Chapter, wherein the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie</hi> concludeth &amp; endeth his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, there is a verie fitte and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie prayer, to keepe all the poore people at once, in all humilitie and true contrition: and likewise in a sure trust and hope of their deliuerance. Thus we see, that after he had throughly lamented and sorrowed, yet that he must at last be driuen to this point, euen in the middest of these extreamest desolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to bring our heartes and mindes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto this great God, that quickneth the dead, and who indeed is such a Surgeon,
<pb facs="14"/> as that there is no wound nor sore but he can heale, when as in a true and liuely fayth, he is sought vnto, and called vpon. Moreouer, we are here especially to note one thing, that whensoeuer the Prophetes summon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to repent, or appease the wrath of God, they neuer sende men to their owne satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions or merites, but to the only free mercie of this good God: And <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon <hi>Luke,</hi> rightly speaking of <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> sayth in this sorte: I reade (sayth he) in the Gospel of <hi>Peters</hi> teares,<note place="margin">Peter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented and made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes in teares, and not in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.</note> but nothing of his satisfactions. Thus wee some what plainly see, what is to be noted touching the order and continuation of the Chapters of these Lamentations.</p>
   <p>Some greatly maruell why <hi>Ieremie</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this sort made these Lamentions, seeing the Lorde God in the <hi>16.</hi> Chapter of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie, ver. <hi>5.</hi> sayde thus vnto him: <hi>Thou shalt not enter into the house of mourning, neyther shalt thou goe to lament for them; for I haue taken my peace from this people, saith the Lord: and so haue I also my mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion, &amp;c.</hi> But here we are to note in the first place, that the Lorde forbiddeth him not simply to lament: but yet so lament, &amp; to such an ende, as that the iudgementes of god against the people might not take effect:
<pb facs="14"/> As if God should haue sayde thus: Thou hast lamented fairely but it will not serue, for this people must needes be chastized. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, our God in this place alleaged, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not vtterly to take away hope of grace from his people: But speaketh of that that should generally fall out vnto the people, and to the obstinate and rebellious multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, who altogether hardened their hearts against the Lorde, So that the Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ieremie</hi> were not written so much for him, as they were written to serue the peoples turne, &amp; to be vnto them as a glasse to beholde their miseries in: and a paterne of true and pitifull mourninges, following true repentance and conuersion vnto the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together good and almightie God.</p>
   <p>Whilest we are nowe in speaking of the Lamentations, wee are to note by the way, that the foure first Chapters are written ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Hebrewe alphabet, saue that in the <hi>3.</hi> Chapter, there are sometimes moe verses contained in euerie letter. This order of the Alphabet, is kept also among some of the Psalmes. <hi>S. Ierome</hi> thought it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the poesie, and trauelled to define what kinde of verses they were, and in the ende he tooke the lamentations to bee such kinde of verses, as are called Saphique, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging for testimonies <hi>Origene,</hi> &amp; <hi>Philo</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/> the Jewe: and yet he himselfe in his preface vpon <hi>Isaiah</hi> affirmeth, that the Prophetes wrote in plaine prose. And although in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deed the Iewes vsed poesie, which <hi>Reuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> and <hi>Munster</hi> in our time, haue verie carefully and painefully laboured to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse: yet the moste parte of the learned and wiser sorte say, that no man is able at this day certainely to shewe any poesie, or kinde of verse which the Jewes vsed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they may as yet haue their poeticall accentes. And it should seeme, that when the harmonie of their commonwealth and estates was dissolued, their fine musicque and poesie, withall their excellent singing notes, were eftsoones lost and quite ouerthrowen with the temple of Jerusalem. Thus we see what a thing it is, not to agree and be at one with the great God of heauen, and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe our selues from his seruice and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Jt should seeme that this order of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the verses with the Alphabet, is obserued for breuities sake of the graue sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences entersuing, which are of maruelous weight, and for the better imprinting of them in memorie, and the making of those sentences to be as familiar as the Alphabet it selfe: without some wrangling companie will start vp and saye, that the Prophet, by running through the whole Alphabet, ment
<pb facs="15"/> to shewe the great continuance of the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that then were.</p>
   <p>It remayneth now, that we speake of the latter point of this preface, which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the vse of the Lamentations of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and the fruit and commoditie which all the faithfull may gather out of them. For, their opinion is not to be receaued, which thinke that such writinges are but olde wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens tales, which only concerne the people of olde time, and vs no whit at all: seeing we are taught by the scriptures,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4</note>
      <hi>That what soeuer things were written afore time were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the scriptures might haue hope:</hi> And that whatsoeuer came to passe vnto our fathers, are euen so many examples for vs, and that such things are written to admonish vs vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon whom the endes of the worlde are come. In verie deede as it is not a gift giuen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man to knowe howe to reioyce as hee ought (according to the saying of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauid in his <hi>89.</hi> Psalm ver. <hi>15. Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed are the people that can reioyce in thee, &amp;c.</hi>) no more is it cōmon to all men, to knowe howe to lament: J meane, so to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that their Lamentations bee not made in the ayre, but to good purpose, and such as please this good God. For <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/> in his Epistle which he wrote to <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorian</hi> sayth,<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be: tvveene the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the faithfull, and of the vnfaithfull.</note> that there is as great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the mournings and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the faithfull, as there is betweene sweete clarified oyle, and the Lees thereof: <hi>Because the faithlesse</hi> (as the Prophet Oseah in his <hi>7.</hi> Chapter ver. <hi>14.</hi> sayth) <hi>cry not truely vpon the Lorde with their hearts: but lie howling and lamenting vpon their beds for the losse of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges.</hi> Wee reade sufficiently in the Heathen histories of very passioned Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and mourninges: yea and so pitiful, as that the Poetes make mention of them, as if the toppes of the houses, and the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses themselues had melted into mourninges: some lamenting the death of their friendes, and other some the destructions and desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of certaine Noble and famous Cities: as the Cities of <hi>Troy, Thebes, Carthage, Rome,</hi> and such other like: And therefore it may well be saide that that went some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neere vnto the Lamentations of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</hi> But it is an other manner of of spirite that guideth and pusheth forward <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his Lamentations, and it is also an other maner of argument when he lamenteth this peerelesse and royall Citie of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> a Citie, whereas the Lorde had, as it were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen and set vp his throne: a citie which was
<pb facs="16"/> a figure and type of the Church of God: And againe, Ieremie aimed at an other maner of marke, than did either the heathen Poets, or historiographers, because he did it to this end to make mē trēble vnder the iust iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and hange downe their heads before his Maiestie, that hee might bring them vnto true repentance. To be short, he squared &amp; seasoned his Lamentations with an assured faith and hope of Gods fauour, and with verie excellent and well knit and conioyned prayers, thereby to pricke men forwarde to returne vnto the Lorde, whome they had offended.</p>
   <p>But if there be any that would finde fault with vs and say,<note place="margin">An obiecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note> that the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> himselfe once passed his limites, when a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (as in the <hi>20.</hi> Chapter of his Prophesie ver. <hi>14.</hi> we reade) <hi>He cursed the day wherein he was borne:</hi> wee aunswere him with the wordes of that auncient Doctor <hi>S. Hylarie</hi> writing vpon the <hi>119.</hi> Psalme, who proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sayth, that he did not then curse the day of his birth, because he right well knew that he was sanctified from his mothers wombe, and ordeyned to the office of a Prophet: but rather by reason of the long continuance of so yrkesome a charge, and the consideration of the hatefull times, that then were. But be it that we did graunt, that <hi>Ieremie</hi> was
<pb facs="17"/> sore troubled in mind, and that he sustained some temptation: yet it appeareth that hee was not swallowed vp therof: but kept such a temperaunce in his lamentations, as that he grieued no man, neyther shewed any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spite against the Lorde: but rather all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence vnto his Maiestie.</p>
   <p>And as for that which the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the <hi>9.</hi> of Jeremie, ver. <hi>17. 18. That they should call for the mourning wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and sende for the skilfull women to take vp a lamentation, and cast out teares vnto the people:</hi> No whit fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vaine and fained worldly lamentations and hired mourners, whom the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then themselues laughed to scorne: howbeit these phrases of speech; are vttered as it were scoffingly, to awaken the people, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paint out the wonderfull hardnesse of their heartes, which was such as that they were faine to hire, and cause come, all the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning men and women of the worlde, to make them shed teares.</p>
   <p>In verie deede it is good that a meane be kept in all things, as on the one side to keepe vs from hypocrisie, and from fayned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessiue sorrowing: &amp; on the other side, from that Stoike blockishnesse. And to be short, wee must all rule and season our passions, which this great Creatour hath not in vaine
<pb facs="17"/> engrauen in euery of vs: For, there is a time to be merie, and a time to be sorie: and all thinges haue their certaine limites and rules: and aboue all, it is meete that both the one and the other be moderately, and to good purpose done. For they that looke for nothing else, but for happy and merrie daies in this worlde: they are they whom the Lord chiefeliest meaneth, and whom he in the <hi>8.</hi> of <hi>Amos.</hi> ver. <hi>10.</hi> in very deede threatneth,<note place="margin">A sharpe threate.</note>
      <hi>That he will turne their songes of ioy and pleasure, into lamentation and mourning.</hi> And therefore (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> himselfe in the <hi>3.</hi> chapter of his <hi>2.</hi> booke of his Ethickes maketh mention) it was verie well saide of <hi>Plato,</hi> that men in their youth should be so brought vp, as that they should knowe how and when to be merie, and howe and when to be sorie, because sayth <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> it must needes be, that they greatly are deceaued, which thinke vertues to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but senselesse &amp; blockish benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mednesse: so that a man may be merrie and sorie as he will, and when he will: so it be with such a proportion and temperance as is seemely and meete. To be short: let no man thinke so to leade his life here in this world, as to be voide of paine and griefe,<note place="margin">Sinne the cause of all our mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> seeing we carr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vs the verie matter and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sorrowes, which is sinne, and
<pb facs="18"/> is the cause of all the tormentes that we suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this miserable life.<note place="margin">Nothing more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaseth God, then when he by his chastise<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to repentance and we wil not cut off the least iot of our pleasures.</note> And there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the whole worlde that more displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth God, then when he by his notable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisements, calleth vs to mourning and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, we in the meane while, in a brauerie to despite him withall, bath our selues in all our delightes, and will not once cut off anie of our least pleasures and follies, to winne him vnto vs againe. For which great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnesse, the Lord God in the <hi>22.</hi> of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> most sharpely reproueth the people of the Iewes.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thus then we see the first vse of these La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of Ieremie, which learne vs Christianly to lament, and teach vs what the very occasion of Lamentations &amp; mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges is: which is to be sorrowfull when we offende the Maiestie of God, when we see the Church vnder the crosse, and his pure ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice turned vpside downe: and not lament and weepe like children for apples or nuts: who are more a fraide, as <hi>Chrysostome</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Of such kind of mē it is to be seared ther are ouer many in these daies euerie where.</note> of their owne shadowes, and of visers, than of a sworde or of the fire: euen such kinde of men are they, which sorrowe for the losse of a fewe temporall &amp; transitorie goods and for a handfull of money, neuer greatly troubling themselues for the ouerthrowe of k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngdomes, of iustice, of pietie, of schooles of
<pb facs="18"/> learning, and of all holy discipline, no not for the sacking and spoyling of their owne countrey, so it touch not themselues any way particularly.</p>
   <p>As for the seconde, the lamentations of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <hi>Ieremie</hi> doe teach vs, what the true cause of the calamities and miseries which come vnto vs are: whereof we are wonted diuers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fondly to iudge: some attributing the cause of their woe and miserie vnto pure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and reformation of the worshippe of God: and some other also, because the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Jdols and of false Gods is banished; say with those people, of whome mention is made in the <hi>44.</hi> of Jeremie. ver. <hi>10.</hi> after this manner,<note place="margin">They cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Moone the Queene of heauen.</note>
      <hi>Sithence wee left burning of incense vnto the Queene of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and powring out of drinke offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes vnto her, as we haue done, we haue had scarsenesse of all things, and haue beene consumed by the sworde and by famine.</hi> But <hi>Ieremie</hi> telleth them that it is cleane contrary: that is to say, that it is the contempt of God, of his worde, and of his sincere worship, that are the causes of all our aduersities, which thing <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> also writing to <hi>Demetrian,</hi> verie well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth. Othersome there are which attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all ill thinges that come to men, vnto fortune: not giuing credite vnto the wordes
<pb facs="19"/> written in the <hi>3.</hi> Chapter of the Prophet <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> where it is sayde: <hi>Is there any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie in the citie, but by the iust or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God.</hi> Some of the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers laye and attribute the whole desolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of countries, and other lamentable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters vppon, and to a certaine dissolute harmonie of the starres and planets: As did the Philosopher <hi>Secundus,</hi> when as hee comforted <hi>Pompey,</hi> after the iourney of <hi>Pharsale,</hi> in which that great Romaine captaine lost the battel against <hi>Iulius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neuerthelesse, this we say: that kingdoms and cities haue their times set, aswell as the life of man hath, and their flourishing and decaying also: but yet we must bee driuen to confesse thus much, that the eternal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,<note place="margin">VVhen sinnes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and grovve to a full ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in a presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in anie kingdome then is it like suddē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stroyed.</note> giueth and taketh away kingdomes to whom, from whom, and when it pleaseth him: and that when sinnes encrease &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply then kingdomes decaye and come to naught: especially, when those iniquities are growen to such a full ripenesse, as are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with an arrogant and presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous securitie. And <hi>Salomon,</hi> in the <hi>14.</hi> of his Prouerbs, ver. <hi>34.</hi> sayth thus, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice exalteth a people, but sinne is a shame vnto Nations.</hi> And in the <hi>16.</hi> Chapter, ver. <hi>18.</hi> hee sayth thus, <hi>Pride
<pb facs="19"/> goeth before destruction, and an high minde before the fall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Hereupon ensueth, that syth we our selues are the cause of our owne miseries, and pull vpon vs Gods scourges, through impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: wee are therefore patiently to beare the miseries which we our selues haue beene the occasion of, and frame a complaint rather against our sinnes, than sophistically reason against the eternall.</p>
   <p>Now for the thirde, the Lamentations of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
      <hi>Ieremie</hi> doe teach vs that we must not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse the patience of our God.<note place="margin">A fearefull thing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused the patience &amp; long suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring of the Lorde. Rom 2.</note> For the longer he deferreth &amp; surceaseth his punishments and chastisementes, the roughlier dealeth he with vs, as by the captiuitie of Babylon, &amp; sacking of Jerusalem may appeare. And therefore it is better for vs to suffer our selues to be tolde of our faultes, and yeelde vnto the holy admonitions of our teachers, then contemne the riches, clemencie, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of God, and his long tarrying, which calleth vs to repentance.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, we are in these Lamentations <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">A king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with sinne, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion also to smell thereof.</note> manifestly to note that saying of an auncient Poet, which saide, that what soeuer Region is corrupt, the Religion also smelleth thereof, and the Church likewise, whether it bee placed either in Prouinces, Cities, or kingdomes of the worlde, suffreth
<pb facs="20"/> the same.<note place="margin">2. Kings. cap. 24.</note> Wee see that Zedechias king of Iudah, in falsifying his oth &amp; promise vnto the Babylonians, troubled the peace of the whole common wealth, drew the enemie, and a sore warre vppon himselfe and the whole countrey, whereupon ensued the destruction both of the temple and also of the citie: and therefore all occasions of vnnecessarie tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes and warres and all other foolish gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiles are to be auoyded: that we may walke in the feare of the Lorde, and in whatsoeuer vocation he calleth vs vnto, incessantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending vnto him the publique peace and estate of those kingdomes, wherein wee liue, and dwell.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift vse, that we learne by these la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentions of <hi>Ieremie</hi> is this,<note place="margin">VVhat the duety of all good men, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the Pastors, ought to be in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.</note> that it is the dutie of all good men, but especially of the Pastors of the Church during the publique calamitie, to pray earnestly vnto God, for the restablishing of the countrie, and of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere religion: and to goe before the people in good example of life, accordingly as it is set downe in the <hi>3.</hi> of Ioel: neither must we loue the Church, or our countrey any whitte the worse, because they are ignominious, &amp; desolate, and too too vnthankefull and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull. For, was there euer any man worse intreated by his owne countrey men, thē was this good Ieremie? And yet we see, how the
<pb facs="20"/> spoyling of his countrey,<note place="margin">It is vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnlawful for any man to be ill minded towards his Countrey, much lesse towardes the Church of God.</note> which he himselfe had foretolde, wroong, and tormented him at the verie heart. Surely, it is vtterly vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man to set himselfe, or to bee ill minded against his countrey, much lesse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Church: considering that as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the <hi>102.</hi> Psalme, ver. <hi>14.</hi> sayth: <hi>That the Seruantes of God delight in the stones of Syon, and haue pitie on the dust thereof.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>By the sixt vse, we may gather out of these <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Lamentations,<note place="margin">The Lord oftentimes causeth the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his people which haue the truth of his word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst thē, as, the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians did the Ievves fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> a time.</note> that wee must not iudge by the outwarde euentes of Religion, whether the same be good or bad. For who doubteth that the Iewes had not the true worship of God: that <hi>Moses</hi> lawe was not holie: and contrariwise, the Babylonians, prophane heathen Jdolaters. And yet it pleased the Lorde to let the Babylonians, and other barbarous Nations ouer runne them, and take their pleasure vppon them: and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme the Iewes with a deluge of miseries, as among other thinges, the Lamantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> doe testifie. For, the Lorde many times, punisheth other sinnes, besides Jdolatrie and false Religion: &amp; as <hi>S. Peter</hi> in the <hi>4.</hi> of his <hi>1.</hi> Epistle sayth: <hi>Beginneth first with his iudgementes at his owne house, without forgetting neuertheles to be most horribly aduēged of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
<pb facs="21"/> and persecuting Nations,</hi> whome he will haue for a time, to serue him, for the chastizing of his owne people. And to prooue this to be true, we may reade in the <hi>14.</hi> and <hi>33.</hi> of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> that hee spared not the Babylonians, but that they had their course and turne. And experience in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath giuen vs to vnderstande, that this great God is iust:<note place="margin">Psal. 57.</note> for although he hath for a season giuen vnto his owne people a cuppe of bitter drinke: yet hath he made the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked drinke the lees and dregges thereof in the ende.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Lastly, the Lamentation of <hi>Ieremie</hi> should make vs thinke the matter nothing so straunge,<note place="margin">Vnfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse vnto God vnder the Gospel is far more greeuous vnto his Maiestie, than the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sse of the Iewes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the lawe.</note> although the Lorde maketh vs mourne and lament, and beholde great deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, seeing he hath not spared the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall braunches: and that our vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse vnder the time of grace, and of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, is without all comparison more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous than the vnthankefulnes of the Iewes, that were brought vp in <hi>Babylon.</hi> And therefore let vs learne not to trust and dwell securely vpon the iolly titles of the Church, vpon Religion, and vpon the Temple of the Lorde, who regardeth not the outward shew, and is able of verie stones to raise vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> and repeople and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue his Church, although she seeme to bee
<pb facs="21"/> like a fielde full of drie and bare bones, as God in the vision of the Prophesie of Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell right well sheweth. For it was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saying in Babylon, <hi>That the childrē of Israell were, as it were, buried: and their estate vtterly ouerthrowen.</hi> But nowe the time is come, that God hath wyped away their teares, and restored the desolate places: so that our dutie is to liue by faith, and holde vs in a good hope, looking pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for the appointed time, staying our selues vppon the infallible promisses of the Lorde, who against the gates and power of hell, will alwayes conserue his little flocke, and a fewe humbled people, which shall call vpon his holy name: so that the most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable saying of our Sauiour Christ in the <hi>5.</hi> of <hi>S. Mathewe,</hi> is most true, where hee sayth: <hi>Blessed are they that mourne, for they shall be comforted:</hi> Alwayes prouided, sayth <hi>S. Hylarie,</hi> writing vpō this place, that we mourne not so much for our priuate losses, as for our offending of God.</p>
   <p>Go to then, let vs learne from this great Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> rightly to lamēt. A know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, alas at this day too too much requisite and necessarie: considering that the moste men, as if they meant euen of set purpose, to despite God, after so many ciuill warres, spoyles, and murders, and hauing the knife
<pb facs="22"/> euen at their verie throats, are more proud, dissolute and hypocriticall, then euer they were. This is it, which <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his <hi>5.</hi> chapter speaketh of, saying: <hi>Thou hast smytten them, &amp; they haue not mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thou hast made them of no repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiō, but they haue refused to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, they haue made their faces, harder than stones.</hi> Awake vs therefore (O God) and let vs not lie still, either in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spayre, or in foolish mourning for the things of this worlde, neyther let vs any longer kicke against the pricke: But let vs lift vp our pure handes, and contrite heartes vnto heauen:<note place="margin">It is a great deale bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be in the house of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vveeping for a time that vve might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: then in the house of ioy and myrth to die euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stingly.</note> let vs pearse the cloudes, and the tender affectioned heart of our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with holy Lamentations: let vs rather goe into the house of mourning and weeping for a time, then into the house of ioye and mirth: that we may reioyce eternally, and that God may chaunge this so disfigured an estate of our miserable Christian prouinces, which looke like olde walles readie to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a peaceable, blessed, and sure estate. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce againe, O Lorde, the great numbers of dissolute Churches, and renue a people that will feare and call vpon thee, and sing vnto thee, holy and condigne prayses. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>