<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable Sir Christopher Hat∣ton Knight, Lord Chancellor of Eng∣land, William Byrd wisheth long life, and the same to bee most healthie and happie.</title>
           <author>Byrd, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106994_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17432</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4254</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106994</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable Sir Christopher Hat∣ton Knight, Lord Chancellor of Eng∣land, William Byrd wisheth long life, and the same to bee most healthie and happie.</title>
                 <author>Byrd, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Psalmes, sonets, &amp; songs of sadnes and pietie : made into musicke of fiue parts: whereof, some of them going abroad among diuers, in vntrue coppies, are heere truely corrected, and th'other being songs very rare and newly composed, are heere published, for the recreation of all such as delight in musicke: by William Byrd one of the Gent: of the Queenes Maiesties royall chappell</title>
                 <author>Byrd, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>240 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="26"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir Christopher <hi>Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Knight, Lord Chancellor of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, William Byrd wisheth long life, and</hi> the same to bee most healthie and happie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE often desires of many my good friends, Right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the consideration of many vntrue incorrected cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of diuers my songs spred abroade, haue beene the two causes, chiefly mouing my consent at length to put in Print the fruits of my small skill and labors in Musicke. Then the dutie, honor, and seruice due from mee vnto your Lordship, together with the remembrance of your iudgement and loue of that Art, did moue &amp; imbolden mee to present this first printed worke of mine in English, to passe vnder your L. fauour &amp; protection: vnworthie I confesse, the view or Patronage of so worthie a Personage. Yet remembring that small things sometime do great seruice, &amp; that repose is best tasted by bodies foreweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: I hoped that (by this occasion) these poore songs of mine might happely yeeld some sweetnesse, repose, and recreation vnto your Lordships mind, after your dayly paines &amp; cares taken in the high affaires of the Cōmon VVealth. Most humbly beseeching your Lordship, that if my boldnesse heerein bee faultie, my dutifull good will, and good meaning may excuse it: which if I may so fortunately perceiue, it shall incourage mee to suffer some other things of more depth and skill to follow these, which beeing not yet finished, are of diuers expected and desired. Incessantly beseeching our Lord to make your yeeres happie, and end blessed, I wish there were any thing in mee worthie of your Lordship to be commanded.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Most humblie your L. euer to commaund William Byrd.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>