<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVABLE, THE RIGHT REƲEEND AND WORTHY, H LORD PROƲEST, BAILIFS MINI∣STERS, and remnant selers of EDINBVRGH: All se of grace heere and glor heereafter, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Forbes, David</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106265_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08238</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106265</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVABLE, THE RIGHT REƲEEND AND WORTHY, H LORD PROƲEST, BAILIFS MINI∣STERS, and remnant selers of EDINBVRGH: All se of grace heere and glor heereafter, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Forbes, David</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Chronologia sacra By the high ... Doctor Phil. Nicolai. lib. 2. de regno Christi. Shortly collected and augmented by Neils Michelsone. Cum priuilegio S. R. Maj. Newly translated out of the Germans and Dence tongue into English, by David Forbes. Pervsed, and accompanied with a short treatise and exhortation tending to repentance</title>
                 <author>Nicolai, Philipp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ABLE, THE <hi>RIGHT REƲE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>END AND</hi> WORTHY, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> LORD <hi>PROƲEST, BAILIFS</hi> MINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERS, and remnant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>selers <hi>of EDINBVRGH: All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>se</hi> of grace heere and glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>heereafter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIght Honourable, right Worthie, renowned Senat, and Pastors:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Finding my selfe somewhat bound vnto your benevolent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, therefore I in minde did decree to giue out the first fruits &amp; proofe of my labours, vnder the tuition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of your Honourable wisedomes; and seeing I found this briefe and compendious <hi>German</hi> worke to bee fit for my purpose, especially in those tymes when men are most secure, &amp; sleeping in worldly vanities, I was in a manner incited, through consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="3"/>
for to lay on my Talent, vnto the benefite of mine owne natiue Countrie, &amp; beeing obliged, for to approue that which I did publickly professe, before your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Senat, and within your renowned Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Therefore I could see none more meete to dedicate the proofe of my labours, as vnto the conspicuous &amp; publicke censure of your Honourable Senat: Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Author of this little worke is a <hi>German</hi> Doctor in divinitie to <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Doctor Philip. Nicolaj,</hi> now in the LORD, who appearantly hath beene graced, and indued with a gift of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as experience and event of time, hath testified in his travels, &amp; who is the right fundamentall ground of this worke and prophecie, written by him <hi>33.</hi> yeares since, namely in the yeare of CHRIST <hi>1596,</hi> which was found extant presently after him in Latine, and thereafter translated in the Germane tongue by <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Gothard Artus</hi> to <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssick,</hi> namely in the yeare of CHRIST <hi>1598.</hi> whereout a <hi>Dence</hi> Professor called <hi>Niels Michelsone</hi> hath
<pb facs="3"/>
gathered this briefe worke, and transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againe in <hi>Dence</hi> and Printed lately Anno <hi>1628.</hi> The substance is a briefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie of times conferred with Scripture, out of <hi>Ezekiell, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> containing a Prophecie and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of the Ghospell to the worlds end, &amp; concluded with the Authors protestation, which I thought good to translate, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie with an exhortation to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and benefite mine owne Nation with the same. Heerewith persuading my selfe of acceptance, I doe thrust this poore myte of my travels into the treasurie of your Christian and charitable dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, recommending it vnto the protection and tuition of your Honourable wisdomes, and you and your doings vnto the grace of GOD.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in CHRIST IESVS David Forbes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>