<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader: of Da∣niels plainnesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106760_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15998</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2785</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106760</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader: of Da∣niels plainnesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Daniel his Chaldie visions and his Ebrevv: both translated after the original: and expounded both, by reduction of heathen most famous stories vnto the exact proprietie of his wordes (which is the surest certaintie what he must meane:) and by ioyning all the Bible, and learne tongues to the frame of his worke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Young (Yong), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simson, Gabriel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 4 leaves of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader: of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels plainnesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen this Prophet is cleared, from the opinion of hardnesse, which men do conceiue of him, then with hope of perfecting labour, desire to reade him wil increase. And the holy man must be cleared. For otherwise men would think <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> a tormēter of soules rather th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n a teacher, if he wrote vnto all nations (in their greatest perplexities) mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnfit for their capacitie. Besides the duty of clearing him, facilitie will be at hand. For the matters which onely make him hard, are soone taught. Stale errours still hinder the negligent in the truth, who runne vpon custome, and will take no paines to examine the right. But thus it doth stand. When the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of <hi>Nathan</hi> is considered touching the throne of <hi>Dauid</hi> to stand for euer, and the case of <hi>Salomon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> house weighed, how in <hi>Iech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nias</hi> it fayled vtterly: &amp; then the house of <hi>Nathan</hi> the next brother cometh in, first <hi>Zorchabel,</hi> then two families of him, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biud,</hi> for the Kings right, <hi>Rhesa,</hi> father vnto our Lord, then the hardest part is gone. All must graunt that this hath bene long hid. For scant any of the world marke our Lords right line, from the text. Yet a few words might open it fully. Onely many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of the truth, cause griefe, and thereupon some more difficulty: otherwise all here requisite might be soone knowne. For the matter is the easiest, standing vpon a plaine storie: and the principles are so few, that a child might write them. They are often handled, that such as care for thē may be instructed many wayes. The next matter of darkenesse ariseth touching the nations oppressors and oppressed. The doubt sprang, for that Daniel in his Chaldy visions nameth neither. The solution is easie. In his Ebrew visions he nameth both the one and the other: and they can containe no other matters then the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Therefore the nations in all are doubtlesse. And seeing Cha. 8. in a vision vpon Babels fall, <hi>Elam</hi> first, next <hi>Iauan</hi> haue all the dealings vnto the ende of wrath: the last dealer must be <hi>Iauan.</hi> Also the afflicted in the last dealings are termed <hi>Daniels</hi> people, and the holy people: and they are afflicted for the holy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Where any may see of what times he was to speake. For who knoweth not, that the last afflictions that the holy Iewes had, with loosing their lands reuenues, was vnder <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes.</hi> Now the nations being knowne, the places wil be known. And for vndoubted certenty the land <hi>Tzeby</hi> on the holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is named, The soyle of the afflicted. The middle sea and
<pb facs="6"/>
dead sea haue it betwixt them: and <hi>Tzeby</hi> is in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hute of Iudaea. And the places of the visions are the fittest for these poincts. At <hi>Eular</hi> and <hi>Tigris</hi> the plaine sights were shewed. Which should import dealings from Kings of those quarters. All this while nothing bringeth in the Romanes. They are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued to greater harmes. And such as bring them into <hi>Daniel,</hi> where they are not blamed, disturbe learning as much as they disturbe the world. But <hi>Daniel</hi> is not to blame. He giueth no cause why men should so deceiue themselues. And thus these parcels the most in difficulty are made easie. Another is no lesse vniustly blamed: the time which he hath most cleare, &amp; telleth plainly. Yea onely he telleth when the first captiuitie began: &amp; how he was of it. The end is most famous in him. And the phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses for our Lords death time, would make a learned <hi>Varro</hi> ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: The seuēty <hi>Hebdomades.</hi> We haue here greater matters thē how he at 84. had written seuenty <hi>Habdomades</hi> of books. And ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any could be plainer then he in that. If we will not beleeue him, but heathen forged studies, we should try particulars. So true heathen would beare record vnto <hi>Daniel.</hi> Now, heathen 2000. yeares haue filled all Libraries full of lyes: with forged <hi>Olympiades,</hi> forged <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> forged <hi>Atchontes</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Consuls,</hi> that the vnstayed and vnlearned now adayes can triumph to see, what store of leasings can be brought against <hi>Daniel.</hi> But the same wil not see, how all the milliōs of <hi>Iudah,</hi> &amp; of Christians vpon the other captiuitie writings, checke the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. So againe <hi>Daniel</hi> is cleared. One poinct remaineth, his tongues: where any may see, that in the <hi>Chaldy</hi> he studied for plainnesse: writing in the most generall tongue, yet neare Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique, and so as most generall yet. For his Hebrew, the learned may not complaine: for to them it is easie. And all should be senslesse, if in plaine matters, and matters of daunger, he might not haue leaue to hide his minde from the wicked. Further dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties we haue not in him: after the consideration of <hi>Dauids</hi> throne and two families, <hi>Salomons</hi> falling, <hi>Nathans</hi> standing for euer: of the nations oppressed, long kept close for safetie, in his later speeches named for certaintie: of the oppressors likewise and of their countreys: and last of his times and tongues. The difficulties of which being softened, none can tell what to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine hard. And to mollifie the readers labour, I will contriue into matter following, introductions to his whole summe and Graces: and ioyne the kings and Pictures for him: pictures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore set in another booke: which coming foorth, greater with greater, lendeth <hi>Daniel</hi> the former willingly. To him they belōg.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>