<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, the Lord Zouch. T. B. vvisheth prosperitie in this world, and eternall life in the vvorld to come.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106575_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16851</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106575</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, the Lord Zouch. T. B. vvisheth prosperitie in this world, and eternall life in the vvorld to come.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise, vvherein is declared the sufficiencie of English medicines, for cure of all diseases, cured with medicines : Whereunto is added a collection of medicines growing (for the most part) within our English climat, approoued and experimented against the iaundise, dropsie, stone, falling-sicknesse, pestilence</title>
                 <author>Bright, Timothie</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 127, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, the Lord <hi>Zouch.</hi> T. B. vvisheth prosperitie in this world, and eternall life in the vvorld to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue been (right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and my verie good Lord) since the time your Honour vouchsafed to take knowledge of mee, &amp; to shew both by benefits and other wayes, especiall fauour towards mee, desirous that some testimonie might remain of my duty, &amp; thankfulness again to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: vvhich although it be not able either to carry with it the vvhole affection of my minde, or in any sort match with your
<pb facs="3"/>
L. bountie, yet may it be, as it were, an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say &amp; taste of the performance of that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wherto both I am bound, and my heart gladly yeeldeth vnto. This assay I present you in this my simple New years gift, being a defence of our natiue medicines, with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of those of forrain nations. The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion I once disputed in open place: &amp; being required of certain to shew my mind more at large therin, I thought good to cōmuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it with moe then one or two, adding thereto my reasons to be examined by men of wisdom &amp; vnderstāding, that if I erre in this point, I might haue the moe refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: if my sentence be approoued, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit therof might be reaped of many. Now, my request is vnto your L. that this my simple gift be accepted with regard of my hearty good meaning, rather then of the thing it selfe, beeing too base in respect of your Honors person &amp; desert. You knowe wel the price of schollers gifts, who as their treasures are of the mind, &amp; not of gold, or
<pb facs="3"/>
siluer, so therin lieth the recompence of all good turnes; in which kind I cōfesse in deed my gift might haue been greater then it is: yet presuming of your Lordships taking in good part that which proceedeth from an entire affection, and considering whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer could be on my part, were too little in comparison of your merits, I am bold to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute your Honor with this poore present at this time, publishing the same vnder your Honors name, that if any commodity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the Common-wealth thereby, the thanks might be your L. herein, who pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me to take such kinde of acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your goodnes towards me, as ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with some benefit might also arise vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The Lord of Heauen &amp; Earth bless your Honor with many good New yeares, vvith increase of Honour and good daies, euen to see peace vpon his Israel all your life long.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors bound in the Lord, <hi>T. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>