<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right Honourable, George Whitmore, Lord Maior of this renowned Metrapolis. London.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106212_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03234</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13351</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106212</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right Honourable, George Whitmore, Lord Maior of this renowned Metrapolis. London.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons ius honorarium : Exprest in sundry triumphs, pagiants, and shewes: at the initiation or entrance of the Right Honourable George Whitmore, into the Maioralty of the famous and farre renouned city of London. All the charge and expence of the laborious proiects, and obiects both by water and land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Worshipfull, the society of the Habburdashers</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right Honourable, <hi>George</hi> Whitmore, Lord Maior of this renowned <hi>Metrapolis. London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>Right Honorable,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the speech of a Learned and graue Philosopher the Tutor and Counseler to the Emperour <hi>Gratianus, Pulerius multo parari, quam creari nobilem.</hi> More faire and famous it is to be made, then to be borne Noble, For that Honour is to be most Honored, which is purchast by merrit, not crept into by descent; For you; whose goodnesse, hath made you thus great. I make my affectionate presentment of this annuall Celebration, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which: (without flattery be it spoken) there is nothing so much as mentioned (much lesse enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) in this your <hi>Ius honorarium,</hi> which rather commeth not short, then any way exceedeth the hope and expectation which is now vpon you▪ and therefore worthily was your so free Election, (without either emulation, or competitorship con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd
<pb facs="3"/>
vpon you▪ since of you it may be vndeniably spoken: that none euer in your place was more sufficient or able, any cause whatsoeuer shall be brought before you, more truly to discerne; being apprehended more aduisedly to dispose, being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested, more maturely to despatch. After this short tender of my seruice vnto you, I humbly take my leaue, with this sentence borrowed from <hi>Seneca Decet timeri Magistratum, at plus diligi.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Your Lordships in all obseruance,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thomas Heywood.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>