<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the noble, learned and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Russell, T. L. wisheth affluence on earth, and felicitie in heauen.</title>
           <author>Willymat, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106883_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06169</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16660</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106883</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the noble, learned and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Russell, T. L. wisheth affluence on earth, and felicitie in heauen.</title>
                 <author>Willymat, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A margarite of America. By T. Lodge</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>94 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the noble, learned and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie <hi>Russell, T. L.</hi> wisheth affluence on earth, and felicitie in heauen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam your deep and considerate iudgement your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired honor &amp; happy readings haue drawne me to present this labor of mine to your grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ous hands, and fauorable patronage: wherein, though you shall find nothing to admire; yet doubt I not but you may meet many things that deserue cherishing. Touching the subiect, though of it selfe it seeme historicall, yet if it please you like our English <hi>Sapho,</hi> to look into that which I haue slenderly written, I doubt not but that your memory shal acquaint you with my diligence, and my diligence may deserue your applause. Touching the place where I wrote this▪ it was in those straits christned by <hi>Magelan</hi>; in which place to the southward many wonderous Isles, many strange fishes, many mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous Patagones withdrew my senses; briefly, many bitter and extreme frosts at midsummer continually clothe and clad the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable mountaines, so that as there was great wonder in the place wherein I writ this so likewise might it be maruelled, that in such scantie fare, such causes of feare, so mightie discouragements, and many crosses, I should deserue or eternize any thing. Yet what I haue done (good Madame) iudge and hope this felicitie from my pen, that whilst the memorie ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>of shal liue in any age, your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, learning, nobilitie and vertues shall be eternized. <hi>Oppian</hi> writing to <hi>Theodosius</hi> was as famous by the person to whome hee consecrated his study, as fortunate in his labours, which as yet are not mastered by obliuion; so hope I (Madame) on the wing of your sacred name to be borne to the temple of Eternitie, where though en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie barke at me, the Muses shall cherish, loue, and happie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>. Thus hoping your Ladiship will supply my boldnesse with your bountie and affabilitie, I humbly kisse your most delicate handes, shutting vp my English duety vnder an Italian copie of humanitie and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie. From my house this <hi>4.</hi> of Maie <hi>1596.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all zeale, T. LODGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>