<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Iohn Rainoldes wisheth grace and peace in Iesu Christ to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fenne, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106047_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20623</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106047</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Iohn Rainoldes wisheth grace and peace in Iesu Christ to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fenne, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon vpon part of the prophesie of Obadiah : touching the destruction, as of Idumæans, so of Papists; and meanes whereby it must be wrought: preached at Saint Maries in Oxford by Iohn Rainoldes, on the 28. of October last. 1584</title>
                 <author>Rainolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ <hi>Iohn Rainoldes wisheth</hi> grace and peace in Iesu Christ <hi>to the Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee are commaunded by a wise<note place="margin">Pro. 3. 27.</note> Prince, or rather by the Prince of Princes, <hi>not to withholde good from the owners thereof, when it is in the power of our hande to doe it. The owners of</hi> anye <hi>good</hi> are they called, who stand in neede of it. For God hath made men stewardes of his graces, not all to serue themselues, but eche to helpe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in whatsoeuer they may. Wherefore, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken in hande the exposition of <hi>Obadiah</hi> the Prophet, and preached so on parte of him, as I thought meetest for the place and time, since the Parliament was summoned: being requested to pen and publish that Sermon, by some, who thought it needful for more then were present, I coulde not withhold my simple helpe therin from <hi>the owners</hi> of it, my leysure &amp; notes seruing me <hi>to doo it.</hi> And I pray God that they for whose sakes it is chiefly done, <hi>withholde not goodes</hi> neither <hi>from the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of them.</hi> Sure, vnlesse the world do blind thē, they will not: &amp; what shall it auayle them to winne the whole world, &amp; lose their owne soules? When<note place="margin">2. Chr. 25.</note>
      <pb n="6" facs="3"/>
      <hi>Amasias king of Iuda had hired an army of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael for an</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">A talent is about 18. hundred sicles. A si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is halfe an ounce or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more. So a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred talents amount to aboue twē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand pounds.</note>
      <hi>hundred talents of siluer, to goe with him against Edom: a man of God warned him not to let the army of Israel goe with him; for the Lord is not with Israell. How shall we doo then for the hundred talents (said Amasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as) which I haue giuen them? The man of God answered: the Lord is able to giue thee more thē that. The Lord</hi> is the same now, that he was euer: as highly offended with vnlawfull helpes which we seeke to gayne by; as <hi>able to giue</hi> vs <hi>more</hi> then they cost vs, euen whom they cost most. But if he would not: yet in his loue is life. And better is a little with a good conscience, then the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chest state of the wicked and mighty. The time wil come when men shal feele it. Farewell good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader: and cōmend the cause of the Church (I beseech thee) to God, by thy prayers; to Gods Lieuetenants, by such meanes as he shall blesse thee with: that it may finde fauour in the eies of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and her gratious Maiestie; to the glory of the highest, the saluation of the chosen, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of the State. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> College in Oxford. <date>Nouemb. 22. 1584.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>