<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ L. Blundeston to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106441_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12048</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106441</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ L. Blundeston to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eglogs epytaphes, and sonettes. Newly written by Barnabe Googe: 1563. 15. Marche</title>
                 <author>Googe, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Colwell, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>178 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>¶ L. Blundeston to the Reader.</head>
   <p>TO creepe into thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure (good Reader) with a longe paynted Preamble in prayse of this Auctor, I account it as vain. The Sōne Beames gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues light sufficient. To moue thy Affection with fore promysed plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in reading the voh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me, I think it as Booteles. Gold is of self force and vertue to draw the desire. But w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> flowers of Rethorique fyrst to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyght the, or w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Pythy Reasons to wynne thy good wyll and frendlye Reporte for this my attempte: yf suche tropes &amp; signes were flowing in me to perswade wel thy fauour, or so muche Discrescion wantynge
<pb facs="9"/>
in the to necglecte my good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, I wold eyther enforce my self to vse a better kynde of perswasion or els withdrawe my good wyll from the Sentence of so carpynge and slender a Iudgement: but as I haue felte no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>luddes of the one, so lykewyse I see no Ebbes of the other, that if I weare no more barraygne of the fyrste, then feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the laste: I woulde be then no more sparynge to horde vp my Treasure from the: then I trust to fynde the thankfull now in takyng this Present frō me, which not onely to shewe my good wyll, (as my Preface discourseth more largely) by preseruynge the worthy Fame, and Memorye of my deare frende M. Googe in his absence
<pb facs="9"/>
I haue presumed more bouldely to hazard y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prynting heareof, though this maye suffyce to excuse well my enterpryse, but also to styrre vp thy Pleasure and further thy proffit by readyng these his workes, whiche here I haue Puplyshed: openly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. And so (beyng vnstored my selffe) I seake to satesfie thy learned or willyng desyre with other mens trauaeiles. But wheare the power fayleth the will may suffyce, the gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, not the gyft is to be regarded: preferre Colonus Radyshe roote be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the Courtiers barbed horse.</p>
   <p>Accept my goodwyll and way not the valew, so shalt thou bynd me if power (as it is vnlykely, maye aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere hearafter my meanynge, to gratefie thee with the whole fruits
<pb facs="10"/>
of myne owne indeuour and so shalt thou encourage others to make the partaker of the like or farre greater Iewels who yet doubtyng thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull receyte nigardly keape them to their own vse &amp; priuat com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie. whear as beynge assured of the contrarye by thy frendly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of other mens trauayles, they coulde parhappes be easely entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more frely to lend them abroad to thy greater auayle and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce. Thus therfore to thy good or euill taking I put foorth this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for others to follow in weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyer matters or els to beware by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens harms, in keaping their names vnreproued by sylence.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>¶From my Chambre, <date>the .xxvii. of Maye. 1562.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>