<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE Right worshipfull and Reuer∣end in God, M. GABRI∣EL GOODMAN, D. in deuinitie, &amp; Deane of the Collegiat Church of S. Pecter, at Westminster, Grace, Mer∣cie, and Beatitude abundant in Christ Iesus our Lord and sauiour, euerlasting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106430_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10574</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20844</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106430</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE Right worshipfull and Reuer∣end in God, M. GABRI∣EL GOODMAN, D. in deuinitie, &amp; Deane of the Collegiat Church of S. Pecter, at Westminster, Grace, Mer∣cie, and Beatitude abundant in Christ Iesus our Lord and sauiour, euerlasting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An homelye or sermon of good and euill angels: preached by the Reuerend D. Vrbanus Rhegius, pastor and superintendent of Christes Church at Zelle in Saxony. Anno. 1537. Newly translated into English by Ric. Ro. citizen of London. 1583. Seene, perused, and allowed</title>
                 <author>Rhegius, Urbanus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>92 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE <hi>Right worshipfull and Reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end</hi> in God, M. <hi>GABRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EL</hi> GOODMAN, <hi>D. in deuinitie, &amp; Deane</hi> of the <hi>Collegiat</hi> Church of S. Pecter, at Westminster, Grace, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and Beatitude abundant in Christ Iesus our Lord and sauiour, euerlasting.</head>
   
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>
      <hi>life, from entering in againe any more</hi>. Heerby as al their posterity may decerne, mās great ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for his creation, Sathans scandale in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Lords prouidence in preseruation of his chosen from the beginning: when all beit he expelled them, he would not yet vtterly extinguish them, and though he terrifyed them he would not eternally torment them: But denouncing their enemie accursed aboue all cattell, (and giuing him iudgement that <hi>The seede of the vvoman should breake the Serpents head</hi>,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ibidem vz. 14. &amp;. 15. Col. 3.</hi>
      </note>) he yet dealt so mercifully by the Ministery of his cherubins these Angels with them, that he reserued them by repentaunce to returne into his kingdome by the redemption of his Sonne Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus and through the regeneration of his holy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Great cause haue we therfore the remnant of their posterity in these late dangerous dayes, not onely to be ware by their harmes, but also carefully to indeuour our selues according to his holy word.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ieam. 4.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>To obay God, and to resist the Diuell.</hi> Againe in our liues and conuersations one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, <hi>To be doing of good, and eschew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of euill</hi>.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 34.</hi>
      </note> Finally in all temptations and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations of the world, the flesh, Sathan, sinne, death and hell, to craue of God, for his sonne Christes sake, in our dayly prayers. <hi>That vve may not be ouercome vvith euill: But that vvith good vve may ouercome euill.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn. 18. Rom. 12.</hi>
      </note> And so be thankfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his diuine Maiestie, for his mercie in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery of his holy Angells, whom hee hath made watchmen and superintendents ouer vs. And lyke as he promised to his seruant Moyses in
<pb facs="3"/>
making of the tabernacle: <hi>That the Cherubins should stretch their vvinges on hye, couering the mercie seate vvith their vvinges, so as their faces being one tovvardes another,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod. 25. vs 20. &amp; 22.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>should also bee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes the mercie seate</hi>: And againe, <hi>that from the mercie seate, betvveene the tvvo Cherubins, hee vvould tell them all thinges vvhat he vvould haue giuen in commaundement vnto the children of Israell</hi>: Euen so it would please him of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious goodnes, to bee mercifull vnto his chosen Church dispersed throughout the world, in the building of his sonne Christ &amp; his Gospell, with the sauegarding of his holy Angels: And that by his speciall grace he would be in the midest of his elect, to instruct them in his will that they may warely &amp; worthely walke in the same. For, the Ministers cannot build <hi>Ierusalem</hi> before god laye the first stone: <hi>That is, Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Zach. 2.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>vvhich is full of eyes, both bicause he giueth light vnto others and that all ought to seeke light at him</hi>: As it was spoken vnto <hi>Iehosuah</hi> and his fellowes the Angels who represented the whole nomber of the faithefull. Notwithstanding it is alwayes seene, when God buildeth his Church, Sathan will set vp his Sinagog. And when good <hi>Isaac</hi> prospereth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Genes. 26.</hi>
      </note> the wicked <hi>Palestines</hi> will labour to stoppe vp his pittes: yet hath God promised that <hi>vvhom Isaac blesseth, him vvil he blesse, &amp; vvhom he curseth, him vvill he curse</hi>. And as the enuie of the cheefe <hi>Priestes</hi> and <hi>Scribes</hi> naught auailed against the miracles of Christ:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math. 21.</hi>
      </note> but that in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spite of them he will haue little Children to cry <hi>Osyanna</hi>. Nor the false Apostles shall seduce
<pb facs="4"/>
      
      <pb facs="4"/>
      
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>open and the Angels of God ascending and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending about the sonne of man</hi>, and with him to liue euerlastingly, among al his elect <hi>Angels, Archangels</hi> and Saintes which incessantly shall sing,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel. 19.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Alleluiah, Saluation and honour and glory, and power be vnto our Lord God, for euer Amen</hi>.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At London in Foster lane, neere S. Michaels in Cheape.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Ianuarii. 18. An. 1583.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worthy good Worships most humble &amp; dutifull Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Richard Robinson</hi> Citizen of London.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>