<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ L. Euans to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106730_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05532</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15653</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106730</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ L. Euans to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine tables sett furth by the right reuerend father in God, William Bushopp of Rurimunde, in Ghelderland: wherein is detected and made manifeste the doting dangerous doctrine, and haynous heresyes, of the rashe rablement of heretikes: translated into Englishe by Lewys Euans, and by hym intituled, The betraing of the beastlines of heretykes</title>
                 <author>Lindanus, Guilelmus Damasus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Diest (Coppens van Diest), Aegidius (Gillis)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ L. Euans to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I hadde here (gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Reader) read ouer certaine tables sett furthe by the right reuerend father in God Willm Bushopp of Rurimunde, in Ghelderland, and by him specially written for the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and proffytt of the people of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye: I adiudged fowre of the same to be a trymme token, and meete for me to send in to the coūtrey of England, for the behooue and auayle of Englishemen. wherefore, I thowght it my parte &amp; duetye, to bestowe some piece of my smale talent on such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, such pleasaunt, and suche passyng excellēt a fielde. For in this fielde, I meane in these tables, are founde suche trymme touchestones, as therewith we maie trie the true faithe from the false, true dealinges frō deceitfull, godlines from vngodlines, good people from badd, and true Christians frō raging Antichristes. In these tables is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie comprehended the disorder and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebraine bolde beastlines of heretickes, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein
<pb facs="4"/>
is declared theyr most filthie falling out iarring and debate, herein is cowched the sundrie sortes of their cursed hainows heresies, and herein is opened their vtter brutishe ignorācie, and selfe will in wayng of the Doctors, and scriptures: yea, thow maist hence as from an high towre behold the runneagate course, and restles race of theym. For in the first Table thow seest their wilful departing from the Catholyke faithe, and from the mynde of the Doctors &amp; Martirs of the primatiue churche. In the seconde thow perceauest the bitter braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and mutuall madnes, not onlye of the one against the other, but also (which of all rage is most beastlie) of euery one against him selfe. In the thirde Table, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall child, who forsaking his tender and louing parētes, at the leangth is fallen into the handes and cōpanie of pernicious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasites, &amp; heapes of hell howndes: so these men, hauing forsakē their faithfull &amp; deare frendes, the learned Doctors and meeke
<pb facs="4"/>
Martirs, yea, running away from their most louing mother the Churche, are now (as in the thyrde Table appeareth) fallen in to the handes of suche hateful rakehels: as are not onlie content with the welthe goodes and bodyes of these poore blynded protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: but to shewe further their onsatiable wicked crueltye, all those olde (I say) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred heresie and heretickes, which were in any corner, and at any time nowseled by anie noughtie poysonfull and past shame person: they now bring with them these theyr yong whelpes (ah las) vnto the fierye furnace of hell, there most miserablye with onspeakable tormentes to murther theyr seelye sowles. Further in the fourthe Table they haue as yow see, vttered theyr hole streangthe, they haue shewed all theyr shif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, they haue bewraid all theyr wickednes, and to the open shame of theyr successors, they haue left them selfes all bare in the playne fielde, to be most worthelye flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and spitted at. For, whereas the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="5"/>
people by them seduced, thought all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that they had scriptures and doctors on their syde, nowe they haue wrought so fondlie, as the scriptures and doctors them selfes doe testifie the cōtrarie. in so much y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> truelie it were inowgh for anye, that hadd but one droppe of grace, yf he perceaued them to varie from the Apostles, and from twoe hundreth diuine Doctors of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church, then to cause him to abhorre their beastli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But wee see here that they varie from all godlie men, and from God him selfe, that like theues they fall out amongst them selues, and betray one another: we see that they followe the steappes, and imbrace the doinges of the deuelish foes of all auncient faithfullnes. Those men doe they followe which were enemies vnto Ambrose, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Augustine, and suche others, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whome those holy fathers haue wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and preched. we see howe they haue sclaundered all ancient writers. we see ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we they haue abused the people and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="5"/>
of christendome. and thoughe now all their drudgerie be detected, made manifest and knowē, yeat, their impudent forehea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are suche: as will receaue no kinde of shame, and as will neuer blushe, or receaue any maner of grace to repent. Well, I wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wishe all men to marke, what moued these fonde faytheles men at the first, to fall from their godlie forefathers faythe, from the Apostles beliefe, and that ys from the faythe, and religion of Christe. Let vs first looke vpon Luther, and vnderstande what impelled hym to imbrace this madde myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and onnaturall heate of heresies. And yf wee will waye yt indifferentlie, then (of trothe) we shalbe forced to say, yea, our owne consciences shall cause vs, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the it self shall moue vs to speake, and saye, that filthie desire drawe Luther to lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. oh, we must exclame and say, O Loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some luste, thowe dydst leade Luther to distruction. O vnchaste mynde, thowe wast the cause of Luthers madnes. O carnall
<pb facs="6"/>
desire ouermuche with they filthie flame dydst thowe lurche poore Luther. O who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redome abhominable, thowe thowe yt was that dydst woorke these lunatike mocions in Luther. And fynallie thowe vile Venus with thy craftie boye Cupido hathe puffed vp poore Luther with ouer fearce a fyere, with ouer great and dreadefull a desyre, &amp; withe to muche a long lasting leacherous luste. Therefore wee may say, o vnhappie Luther, o wreached man, o most misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble simple soule. But wee are happie, wee are blessed, and entierely beloued of God, who by the corrupte, rotten, and choked fruicte of thee, may nowe learne to avoyde all the graffes growen, and feadde on thy filthie roote.</p>
   <p>And truelie, tenne tymes happie should we, and others haue bene, yf we had but perceaued the poyson of suche pestilent fruictes when they were greene. For then (ahlas) they infected a great number of the youthe, &amp; sweete mowthed men of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome.
<pb facs="6"/>
there was neuer greene fruicte that bread suche a plague. that plague cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to perishe bothe bodye and soule. and the ayre then, I meane mens myndes, were so infected and corrupted, as a thowsande sowles in one daye were caried headlong into hell. at that tyme might fathers weepe in deede for the deathe of their sonnes, then parentes might pietiefullie howle at the buriall of their youthe, and children. and then, and at no tyme ells, might fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des most bytterlie lament for the losse of their familiars, and acquayntaunce. For wolde yt not rent the harte of anie honest man, to see his deare freende drawen dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie into the bottomeles pyt of hell, there in burning coales to broyle for euer? Oh, yf wee bee men, we must morne at this, and yf wee haue any kindenes, or gentle nature in vs, then must wee wayle, and sighe at the sorowefull state of suche our acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: as shall neuer with vs enioye the blessed ioyes of heauen. Nay, yf we be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable
<pb facs="7"/>
Christiās: and yf wee looke to haue the long lastyng blysse of lyfe euerlasting: then must wee weepe at the erroure and wandring of our breathren: who, throughe the baytes and allurementes of Sathan, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king strange doctrines to defend their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes, are now as damned Phlegias, throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheout the darkenes of hell, sounding fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the with woeful voice these wordes: <hi>Discite iustitiam moniti, &amp; nō temnere Diuos.</hi> of tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, yt makethe me a frayde to thinke on their woe, and I quake when in mynde I conceaue any knowledge thereof.</p>
   <p>But what shall we speake of him, which in this litle booke beholding the misrule, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and most lothesome lyes of hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, will yeat wallowe with them in beast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, &amp; still imbrace nothing els but their blindenes? in deade I feare some suche the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re wil be. But not withstanding as often as I do reade ouer this booke, me thinkes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relye, that there can be none so willfullye madd, nor none so voyde of grace and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.
<pb facs="7"/>
As any longer to lye in the beastlie brawlinge beadd of hatefull heresye. me thinkes, that al the false preachers doe pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vp their bawdie marchandize, and me thinkes that with the consent of all good consciences, they be at the leanght whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with their whoores through out al coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys. Yf this booke I say, be read ouer with an indifferent mynde, yf partialytie be layd a syde, and yf any (renouncing shamefull self will and stowbbornes) will vse the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, where with God at the first dyd endue him: then most certaine I am, that he will say, fy, fy, on these mōstrous ministers, fy on their fonde doctrine, &amp; suttel sectes, and fy on theyr filthie facing, &amp; famyshed faythe.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, seing we doe so manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye perceaue their varieng from auncient holye writers, seing wee see their disagrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes amongst them selfes, seing wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, howe they leane vnto old cancred, and condemned heresies, and seing we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand at the leangth their lewdenes in
<pb facs="8"/>
alleaging of the Diuines and Doctours. Let vs followe the example of the Apostle S. Iohn, the Disciple of Christ, whoe (as I reade) entred into a commune bayne to wash him. But there beholding one Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus, he leapt out immediatlie vnwashed, sayng, let vs flie hence, lest that the baynes them selfes fall downe, in the which Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus is washed: By which sayng, we are admonished to aduoyd yuel companie: for Cerinthus was an open enemye of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and all godlie men. Therefore, let vs I say likwise, when wee see these prating false preachers in pulpittes, fly from them, least the Church fall downe on vs, wherein such blasphemies be breathed out, and fostered. Let all men behold their malice, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hatred heaped vpp in their iniurous iniunctions, against the true Christiās, and imbracers of Christ. And finally, let vs all renoūce this newe nowghtines, this doting doctrine, this self will wantonnes, and these shameful lechearous single soule sectes. Let
<pb facs="8"/>
vs againe with ioyfull countenaunce byd Christ welcome into our countrie. Let vs yelde our selfes vnto his mercye, and let vs obey his statutes, and followe his will. Yf wee doe this, wee shall not only be free frō the fire of hell, and haue perdon for all our peruersenes and treason: but wee also, shall in this lyfe be sure of sundry commodities and pleasures, and in the lyfe to come, wee shal haue lyfe for our soules in deede. Wee shall haue the heauens for our habitacion, and enioye the sweete cōpaine of the Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, with the plesaūt felowship of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, louing acquaintāce, and deare fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: They with vs, and wee with them, in the euerlastinge vnspeakable ioyes, and most bewtifull blisse, to lyue so louingly together for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>