<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FRIEND, Sir Alexander Radcliffe, the accomplishment of his no∣blest Wishes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106313_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16687</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3591</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106313</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FRIEND, Sir Alexander Radcliffe, the accomplishment of his no∣blest Wishes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Whimzies: or, a nevv cast of characters</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Bostock, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ritherdon, Ambrose</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 175, 178-211, 5, 34, 12 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FRIEND, Sir <hi>Alexander Radcliffe,</hi> the accomplishment of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest Wishes.</head>
   <salute>SIR,</salute>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome have I heard affirme, (but more <hi>tari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> I hope, then <hi>truly</hi>) that to bee a <hi>Knight</hi> and a <hi>Scholler,</hi> was the <hi>Mirror of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood:</hi> howsoever the <hi>Tenet</hi> hold, sure I am, that you are
<pb facs="3"/>
this <hi>Mirror.</hi> Being as you are ennobled by <hi>des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ent,</hi> so ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by <hi>desert;</hi> a patron to the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rned professant, and in all le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ing a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ich proficient. This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> was, and this onely, which first induc'd me, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that native di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion everbred in me, so free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to tender my selfe to the knowledge of you; and which hath ever since stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in mee so deepe an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of you. Let others affect your <hi>Title,</hi> while I live to honour <hi>your selfe.</hi> The generous and free goodnesse of your <hi>minde,</hi> is my <hi>object,</hi> than which it is not possible to treate of a more attractive <hi>subject.</hi> This
<pb facs="3"/>
is to bee incomparably va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued above any outward good. Let this serve for the <hi>prelude,</hi> not to delude you, for you are wiser; but to expresse my selfe really un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, whose noble s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse I doe intimately ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. You may bee pleased to remember that at my last entercourse with you, it was my promise upon a precedent purpose to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse some small memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to publike view under your Name, in lieu of those many respects which I beare you. Which promises, I must ingenuously conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>sse, (as in this kinde, so in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers justly grounded) it
<pb facs="4"/>
hath beene ever my course religiously to observe. For in comming short of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance in what wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, argues either a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate rashnesse in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miser, or inconstancie in his resolves, or forgetfulnesse in what he undertakes. It is recommended unto us by authenticke storie, that it was the usuall observation both of a Roman Emperor, and of an English Monarch, never to promise any thing but what they registred and set downe with their owne hands: which rule requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth imitation even of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eriours. An Expression whereof I have here made
<pb facs="4"/>
in the tender of this Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beticall gradation of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters,</hi> to your generous &amp; ingenious veiw. Neither (indeede) without a precee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ground of reason did I make choyse of this <hi>Subject.</hi> For howsoever the <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> may seeme much <hi>bet:</hi> yet in my opinion may it bee much <hi>bettered</hi> both in <hi>style</hi> and <hi>substance.</hi> Many <hi>Characters</hi> (I confesse) have beene published both in former times, when the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the age could scarcely render the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie of the word: as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in these more refined times of ours, wherein, as in habit and attyre, so in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses
<pb facs="5"/>
of this nature, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>rarities</hi> (bee they never so light) can afford delight. But to give them their true and native <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter,</hi> they relished more of <hi>Aphorisme.</hi> than <hi>Character.</hi> For to suite them with their approvedst and reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivest title, what else are <hi>Characters</hi> but <hi>stampes</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressures,</hi> noting such an es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall place, person, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and leaving such a marke or cognizance upon it, as the conceit may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taste of too much lightnesse; nor the cloze of so wittie an observance leave too much bitternesse, nor the whole passage or
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>series</hi> incline to too much dulnesse? Truth is, he that should strive in each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, either for <hi>Style</hi> or <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> to please the various palats of all men, would prove an excellent <hi>Taylour</hi> to <hi>fashion</hi> this age; &amp; might in time make a Coate for the Moone. <hi>Strong lines</hi> have beene inrequest; but they grew disrelishing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they smelled too much of the Lampe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionate singularitie. <hi>Clin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings</hi> likewise were held nimble fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>shes; but affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion spoyl'd all, and disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their levitie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Characterisme</hi> holds good concurrence, and runn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s
<pb facs="6"/>
with the smoothest current in this age; so it bee not wrapp'd up in too much am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguitie. Hee writes best, that <hi>affects</hi> least; and <hi>effects</hi> most. For such as labor too intentively to please them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, they for most part make it their labour to please none but themselves. This hath beene ever my <hi>maxime,</hi> that <hi>singularitie</hi> and <hi>affectation</hi> are <hi>Antypodes</hi> to <hi>Iudgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nt</hi> and <hi>Discre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ion.</hi> Selfe-opinion mak's a mans selfe his owne Minion. He is the true Embleme of <hi>Narcissus,</hi> and doates more on his owne <hi>shadow,</hi> then an others <hi>substance.</hi> But I will not looke too much on
<pb facs="6"/>
these <hi>Glo-wormes;</hi> they are soiles to the purest paper: leaving their spongie La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to the worst of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. For these few dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted papers, (wherein you shall too highly prize mee, if at vacant and retyred houres you daigne onely to peruse mee) I dare confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently avouch, you shall finde me to have preferred the <hi>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h</hi> before the <hi>rinde,</hi> and caused the <hi>Maid</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon her <hi>Mistrisse.</hi> My provision was how to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the maine building: for other ornaments or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellishments of art, they tendered themselves; they were not much sought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb facs="7"/>
Now it resteth that this <hi>Character</hi> or token (for so the word may import) of my true zeale, unto your Noble selfe, retaine that impression in you, which he retaines that honours you. These are more lasting me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morialls than materiall jewels, and to the <hi>judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> more imcomparably pretious. The richest <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet</hi> is the <hi>minde;</hi> the <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures</hi> thereof purer than the <hi>Oare</hi> of any <hi>Mine.</hi> which when wee commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate to our <hi>friend,</hi> wee make him really ours, wee enfeoffe him in ours; yea, wee incorporate him
<pb facs="7"/>
in us, and make him indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidually ours. So may we ever bee, till I surcease to bee</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Clitus-Alexandrinus.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>