<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106758_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07230</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17627</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106758</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dysclosi [n] g of the canon of the popysh masse : wyth a sermon annexed vnto it, of the famous clerke, of worthye memorye. D. Marten Luther</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hitprick, Hans, pseud</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22+ pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>rom the beginnyng or at the fyrst ētra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce,<note place="margin">Genes. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> after the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion (good christē reader) God in him selfe, foreseing the ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mannes harte,<note place="margin">John. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> and how prone and readye it was vnto wyckednes, and howe oblyui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> benefytes that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of his lorde Gods han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">Esay. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> became not thankfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys myghtye God:<note place="margin">Roman. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> But va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysshed in the Imagynacions of hys frowarde fromake,<note place="margin">Ieremy. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> and worshipped the workmanship of the hādes of a caranous car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cas, subdued to all vanytie, &amp; forgat hys creatour: the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch vngentelnes hath bene of al other vices,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>32.</hi>
      </note> moost earnestlye
<pb facs="3"/>reprehended by the mouthe of God euen from the begīning, ād not onelie reprehended, but also wyth sharpe threates and cōmynacions, of hys moost sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woord,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> appoīted to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dampnaciō. Besydes that he gaue them vp to theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes lustes:<note place="margin">Sentere. <hi>28</hi>
      </note> and plaged them w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> swearde, famyne and pestylē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. Therfore (good christen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) lyfte vp thyne eyes, ande beholde, the abhomynacyon of Idolatry,<note place="margin">.1. <hi>John.</hi>
2.</note> so shamefullie vsed in these dayes of our tyme:<note place="margin">.1. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.</note> ād not onelie vsed, but with force and mayne fortefyed ande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden,<note place="margin">Psalm.
<hi>2.</hi>
      </note> wyth fyre and faggot, crudelytie and strength: and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> so sore vpholden,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>15.</hi>
      </note> that the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall woorde of God, is clerelie banysshed, exyled and put too
<pb facs="3"/>bed. Howe sayste thou to thys detestable, ād amōg all other, the moost shamefull mase and gasīg stocke,<note place="margin">Sapien. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> the wycked masse the vpspryng of Sathan, the inuenciō of the deuel, the fayre frute of the Roomysh rauenīg Antechryst,<note place="margin">Daniel. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note> and the laderhous of all his shauen posteritie?<note place="margin">Hieremy.
<hi>15.</hi>
      </note> Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde it, ād abhorre it: or elles take it for a warnīg, God will abhorre the, and cāst the into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lake that burneth with fyre ād brymstone.<note place="margin">Apocal. <hi>20.</hi>
      </note> Wherfore I harte lye besech the, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all brotherly affeccyon,<note place="margin">Phill.
<hi>2.</hi>
      </note> marke in this lytell volume or fewe lynes, the tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of the Dragon, of Gog and Magog, the wasters of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pore flocke of Christe,<note place="margin">Ezechiol. <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </note> the mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of myschefe, the studyers of supersticyon, the fortefyers <pb facs="4"/>of the malignaunt Churche, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gylders of the triple Crowne:<note place="margin">Psalm. <hi>26</hi>
      </note> and thou shalte playnelye par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in an hondreth woordes,<note place="margin">Coloss. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> the shamefull legerdemayne &amp; craftie Iugglīge, that cost thē the study not of a fewe hōdreth yeres,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>13-</hi>
      </note> and the sweate of manie browes: for the whyche bothe their pot and spitte, walke the merelier,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>16.</hi>
      </note> vnto this howre. It is called the Canon of the mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheffat (of the Masse I woulde saye) that is to saye, the rule ād order that they haue taken to fynish theyr slayne sacrifyce; &amp; too brynge it to an ende. But what turmoyling, struggling, wrastlinge,<note place="margin">Luke.
<hi>11.</hi>
      </note> quid pro quo, with my wayes is best, hold thy hā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fro my throte, ther was till they had broughte it to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shapen
<pb facs="4"/>forme, that it is nowe in: Polidorus Virgilius doth playnelye manifest.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Cap
<hi>10.</hi>
      </note> Wherūto also y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> hast a sermō ānexed, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> famous Clerke, &amp; discloser of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Popes Iugglīg box, &amp; of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy memorye. D. Martē Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Reade it (I pray y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>) w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a so<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber Iudgemēt. And conferre y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Idolatries of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> old time, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the abhominable Idolatry in our tyme, after the cōming of Ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryst, the pure &amp; true light: ād y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalt se it farre passe.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> Oh most mightie father, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tēder loue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou barest to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wholl world,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> in that thou delyueredst thyn onelye and swete sonne Iesus Chryste,<note place="margin">Hebr.
<hi>10</hi>
      </note> that holye and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent sacryfice,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>21.</hi>
      </note> for the lyfe of the whole world. Haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pō vs &amp; deliuer vs, frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> snares <pb facs="5"/>of Sathan, ād from the deue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysh yoke of this detestable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye: and open the eyes of oure Magystrates,<note place="margin">Psalm. <hi>45.</hi>
      </note> that they may prosperously,<note place="margin">Coloss.
<hi>4.</hi>
      </note> fortefie thy blessed woorde (as theye haue begōne gracyouslie) and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the bloudye kyngdome of Antechryste. And sende the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie obedient stomackes &amp; hartes,<note place="margin">Apocal. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note> to fortefye their Prī<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces quarell,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>13.</hi>
      </note> in all godlynes ād ryght. And that all christē rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes,<note place="margin">Timoth. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> maye accorde in peace &amp; vnytie, ād so to be incorporate in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mysticall bodye of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye,<note place="margin">Roma.
<hi>12.</hi>
      </note> whose head is chryst Iesus. To whome I cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytt y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the increase of his knowledge, Amen.</p>
   <p>Reade, and then Iudge.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>