<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER, SPECIALLIE THE Rector, and parishioners of Al-hallowes Bread∣street.</title>
           <author>Stocke, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106168_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12982</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23275</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106168</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER, SPECIALLIE THE Rector, and parishioners of Al-hallowes Bread∣street.</title>
                 <author>Stocke, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrine and vse of repentance : necessarie to be practised and vsed of all who looke to sing the song of Moses, and the song of the lambe beyond the glassie sea: Reuel.15.23. Preached in sundrie sermons in the parish church of Alhallowes Bredstreete in London: by Rich. Stock</title>
                 <author>Stock, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 349, 15 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READER, SPECIALLIE THE Rector, and parishioners of Al-hallowes Bread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He rod of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hath now been long vpon vs for our sinnes, which the abuse of Gods mercies, his patience, and our long peace hath brought out: So that wee may well hope, that they haue wrought in vs that of <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 33.16.</note> to wit, that they haue <hi>Opened the eares of vs, euen these corrections, which he hath sealed:</hi> whereby we will willingly heare and receiue this doctrien of repentance, vnlesse that of <hi>Elies</hi> sonnes, (which is not to bee thought of without feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling) should be verified in vs, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.25.</note>
      <hi>That therefore they obeyed not the
<pb facs="9"/> voice of their sather,</hi> being the Lords Priest) <hi>because the Lord would slay them:</hi> So we should not obey the voice of Gods Ministers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Lord hath a purpose to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy vs.</p>
   <p>Which lest it befall vs, it stands all and euery one vpon to repent, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing repented, and yet sinning again, <note place="margin">Iames 3.2.</note> (as who sinneth not in many things and daily?) to renue his repentance, and doe it againe, and againe. <hi>As of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> (saith <hi>Chrysostome</hi>) <note place="margin">
         <hi>Quoties cecide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns in foro, toties ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ges: sic quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties peccaueris, toties peccati poeniteat. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sost. hom.</hi> 9. <hi>de poenitent.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>as thou fallest in the streetes, so often thou wilt rise againe: euen so, as often as thou committest sinne, so often thou shouldest renue thy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Physitians haue a preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue against the plague, which consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of three ingredients: The medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is called flying; the ingredients are these: <hi>Citò, longè, tardè;</hi> flie soone enough, flie farre enough, and make slow haste to returne. By which notwithstanding that men sometimes escape the pestilence, yet they remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="9"/> in their sinnes, are often ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a greater plague: and are in the case which <hi>Amos</hi> speaketh of; <note place="margin">Amos 5.19.</note>
      <hi>As if a man did flie from a Lion, and a Beare met him: or went into the house, and leaned his hand on the wall, and the serpent bit him.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But the Prophets and Saints of God, haue a contrarie preseruatiue, not against this plague only, but all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, either to keepe themselues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched of them, or at least to turne them to their good. And this they call not flying, but returning; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients of this are two, laide downe euery where in the Scripture; <hi>Cease to doe euill, learne to do well, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew euill and doe good.</hi> Yea this is both a restoratiue and a preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, by which men may remoue the present, and preuent greater iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to come.</p>
   <p>Now for the instructing of you in the nature, and for the directing of you, in the vse and practise of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine and duty, at the request of some of you, I laboured in publike to deliuer
<pb facs="10"/> this doctrine, for the benefit of all who heard me: and now at the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of some, I publish it in writing, to the profit, I hope, of many more.</p>
   <p>The order I haue vsed is as famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar and plaine, as I could, labouring to profit rather the most, then to satisfie the learned. I haue begun with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of it, and haue examined the seuerall particulars thereof; then I haue proceeded to the essentiall and naturall parts of it; from them to the causes of it; from the causes, to the subiect and parties to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, and who ought to practise this dutie; from these vnto those seuen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separable fruits or effects, which the Apostle S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the second Epistle to the Corinthes hath deliuered vnto vs. <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.17.</note> Hence I haue descended to the time and place, when and where this dutie ought to be practised. Finally, I haue laboured to remooue some of those principall lets and impediments, which Satan casteth in the way of all men, when they shall but once mind their way to his holie dutie.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>I cannot say, I haue brought here any thing new and vnheard of; <hi>For there is no new thing vnder the Sunne:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 1.9.</note> For matter I meane; yet for the manner and particular han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling of it, I know none, who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended to the capacity of the meanest, as I haue endeuoured, to my power and for my skill, to doe.</p>
   <p>What doe our Lawyers pleade now, but that which hath been pleaded in former times, the same statutes, the same rules of law, the same book cases? onely they applie them to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar causes, and fit them for the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their clients. What doe our Physitians prescribe now, any thing but that which <hi>Galene, Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> and other Physitians haue done before them? the same simples and compounds, the same purges, and preseruatiues, the same cordials and restoratiues; onely by their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and skill, liuing among vs, they discerne of the state of the patient, of his age, strength and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of the disease, whether new or
<pb facs="11"/> old, begun but now, or inueterate; &amp; so they increase or diminish the simples, or the quantitie of thē, making thē ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther milder or sharper, as the state of the party, &amp; disease do require. As lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle able are we to bring any new thing, but only fit them to the times and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, seeing liuing in the same ages, wee may the better bee able to doe it, though we be many degrees inferiour in gifts and knowledge. That I then professe, is the more particular, and familiar handling and applying of these things, which others haue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie deliuered, for the benefit of the Church of God.</p>
   <p>I haue endeuoured to confirme eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie point by the word of truth, and haue added (after my vsuall manner) confirmations &amp; illustrations drawne from reason, similitude, and the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Fathers; not to strengthen the Scriptures, but to helpe and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the hearer and reader, to whom all is little enough, to make him heare with attention and delite, to conceiue with profit, and to carry away for pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise.
<pb facs="11"/> If any dislike my alleaging of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (as some haue done my vsing of reasons to confirme the truth and doctrine, but with very little reason, as I suppose) I must pray them to giue me leaue to vse them, till I can see that vnlawfulnes, which they affirme to be in the practise, and to censure me in charitie for the vse of them, as I doe them for not vsing them. I know wel there may be an abuse in the quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of these; as there may be in citing of Scripture; when either ostentation of memorie, or reading shall be ioyned with it; or when, as <hi>Hierom</hi> speaketh, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eruditionis glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam declinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, eruditissimus habebatur. Ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aiebat, Tertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ani, istud Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ani, hoc Lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tij, illud Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> est, &amp;c. Hie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> epist.</hi> 3. <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>od. Epitaph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potia.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>One affecteth to bee accounted learned, by eschewing the glorie of learning; That,</hi> saith hee, <hi>is it which Tertullian speaketh, that Cyprian, this Lactantius, that Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius,</hi> &amp;c. Or finally, when they shall bee like lights at a great feast, which take vp all the roome vpon the table, and leaue little place for dishes of meat to be set on. I will looke as well to my heart in the vse of them, as God shall enable mee, and when I shall see the
<pb facs="12"/> hurt of them, I wil as much endeuour to auoid them; in the meane time, I will make the best vse I can of them, to edifie the Church of God.</p>
   <p>Those places which I haue here v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, I haue set downe in the treatise in our owne tongue; but, I confesse, not so aduisedly, in the margent, I begun to set them downe in their owne, and hauing so done for three or foure sheetes, I saw it was not so profitable for those whom I most aime to teach, namely the simple; yet I haue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on that course for an vniformitie: yet knowing that many vnderstand the Latine, who doe not vnderstand the Greeke, though I haue vsed some of the Greek Fathers, as <hi>Iustin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> and <hi>Basil,</hi> and somewhat out of those parts of <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> which we haue in Greeke, yet haue I set down the Latin only, lest I should bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome and vnprofitable to moe.</p>
   <p>Many testimonies out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures I haue vrged diuers times, and in seuerall points, euen one and the same, for one place will proue many
<pb facs="12"/> things, and hath many branches. The Lawyers will vrge one and the same law, or booke case to seuerall points, in pleading of the same cause, because of seuerall branches in it, and they are blamelesse. I hope in the vse of the word, we may haue as much libertie, and yet not seeme to haue idle repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and the rather I haue affected this, for the benefit of the simpler sort, that the places of moment may bee more familiar vnto them.</p>
   <p>Now not to detaine you any longer, from the Treatise it selfe; I beseech you reade it with attention, labour to know the particular points with iudgement, and to practise them with conscience. And the God of grace so perswade your hearts, and so open them vnto it, that you may bee like the citizens of <hi>Abel,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 20.22.</note> who at the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion of one wise woman, cut off the head of <hi>Sheba</hi> the Rebell, and cast it to <hi>Ioab,</hi> who blew the trumpet, and all the armies returned from their siege and sacking. So you may cut off your sinnes and cast them to God, that
<pb facs="13"/> the armies of his iudgements may at length retire from the citie, and our land, and his hand be no more stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out. And that <note place="margin">Isai. 1.19.</note>
      <hi>You consenting and obeying, may cate the good things of the land.</hi> And repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and amending, and doing your first workes, the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticke bee not remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of his place. <note place="margin">Reuelat. 2.5.</note>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend and seruant for Iesus sake, <hi>Richard Stocke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>