<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A SPEECH INTEN∣DED TO HAVE BENE MADE VNTO THE KINGS MAIESTIE, in the Towne of Windsore, but not spoken.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106139_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02478</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12607</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106139</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A SPEECH INTEN∣DED TO HAVE BENE MADE VNTO THE KINGS MAIESTIE, in the Towne of Windsore, but not spoken.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of golds kingdome, and this vnhelping age : Described in sundry poems intermixedly placed after certaine other poems of more speciall respect: and before the same is an oration or speech intended to haue bene deliuered by the author hereof vnto the Kings Maiesty</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 57, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A SPEECH INTEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DED TO HAVE BENE MADE VNTO THE KINGS MAIESTIE, in the Towne of Windsore, but not spoken.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Gracious and renowmed King, if we your Highnesse sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this place, be (for the present) to seeke in what sort to applaud the incomparable bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of your royall presence: we are most humbly to beseech your Highnesse to impute the same vnto two causes: The one, the consideration we haue of our owne imperfections, as the same are now to be exposed vnto the censure of your Princely perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The other, the abundance of our ioy which hath so possessed euery part of our thoughts, as that thereby we are vnable to retaine in our speaking either Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode or Decorum: For it cannot be told (most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne) with what insatiable power of our minds we do imbrace &amp; entertaine this ioyfull time of your Maiesties personall repayre into this land, and now particularly to this your Towne and Castell of Windsore: This time I say, most brightsome and cleere, not ouercast with any the least cloud of either trouble present, or danger to come: For it may truly be said of your Maiesty (and that to the glory of God) as it was sometimes said of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> the godly Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: that true piety and felicity haue so met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your royal person, as that true piety hath forced felicity to be present at a l your royall solemnizations whatsoeuer: And why? surely, because your Maiesty hath not onely couered your head with the Imperiall Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme,
<pb facs="3"/>
and inue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ted your person with the Royall Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Crowne, but hath also adorned your mind with the inestimable Iewels of true Religion and Iustice: But what shall I say? Among all the inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blessings which we are now by the goodnesse of God to inioy by your Maiesty, there is one amongst the rest so full of blessednesse, as that it ouerreacheth the measure of common comprehension to dilate it in speech: And what is that? Euen the knitting togither of your two Kingdomes <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> which are now so closed in one Harmony as well of Religion, as of their confining borders and agreeing languages, as that (according to the saying of the Prophet) <hi>Bone</hi> is ioyned to <hi>Bone,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ioynt</hi> to <hi>Ioynt:</hi> Most gracious king, our most beloued Soueraigne, there is one thing that your Maiesty may hold as an vndoubted certainty: namely this, that you are entred into your rule and raigne ouer <hi>Englād,</hi> with as great cōformity of harts of English sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects as euer King or Queene within this Realme. Long may your Highnesse liue: Long may the Scepter sway in your Princely hands: And vnto the King of Kings we bow the knees of our hearts, that he will vouchsafe to graunt vnto your Maiesty a long, a peaceable, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Raigne ouer vs.</p>
   <p>I will not take vpon me to particularize vnto your Maiestie the Nature of <hi>Englands</hi> gouernement, but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally (vnder your Princely fauour) this thereof may be sayd that by the most ancient vsage of <hi>England,</hi> the king hath bin accounted to be <hi>persona mixta, hoc est, vnita cum Sacerdotibus,</hi> aunswerable to that of <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Aristotle: Suprema potestas antiquitus fuit regia &amp; Sacerdota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi> And for that that is holden thereof ciuilly at this day, it is this: we say that our supreme power is <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus tam regalis quam politicus,</hi> the one respecting times of warre, and the other times of peace. And we say also that <hi>principatus regalis &amp; politicus paris sunt potentiae, sed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus regalis difficilioris est exercit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> securitatis.</hi> But of this as also of the Equity of your Maiesties Common
<pb facs="3"/>
lawes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>d,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the Equity of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Court of Chauncery with their differences, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall also of Equity in generall as the same is to be vsed in euery humane law, I your Maiesties most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble subiect, a professor of those Common lawes some certaine yeares past did imploy my labours in writing a plaine &amp; open Treatise thereof in English, whichbe ing here contained in this written Volume, if it might <note place="margin">This booke herein mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, but not by way of dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> stand with your Princely pleasure to vouchsafe your reading of it, I make no doubt but that your Maiestie will find sundry things therein not impertinent, no nor yet vnnecessary for your Princely perusing: The simplicity of the handling alwayes excepted, for the which I must and do most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseech your Maiesties gracious pardon.</p>
   <p>After this, there should haue followed some priuate and particular matters on the behalfe of the sayd Towne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>