<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the ryght worship∣full M. William Louelace, Esquier, Reader of Grayes Inne: (Barnabe Googe) wyssheth health.</title>
           <author>Googe, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106441_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12048</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106441</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the ryght worship∣full M. William Louelace, Esquier, Reader of Grayes Inne: (Barnabe Googe) wyssheth health.</title>
                 <author>Googe, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eglogs epytaphes, and sonettes. Newly written by Barnabe Googe: 1563. 15. Marche</title>
                 <author>Googe, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Colwell, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>178 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶To the ryght worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full M. William Louelace, Esquier, Reader of Grayes Inne: (<hi>Barnabe Googe</hi>) wyssheth health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe lothe I haue ben, beyng of long tyme earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye requyred, to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer these tryfles of mine to cōe to light: It is not vnknowen to a greate nombre of my famyliar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. Who both dayly &amp; hourely moued me therunto, and lytell of long tyme preuayled therin. For I both consydered and wayed with my selfe, the grosenes of my Style: whiche thus cōmytted to the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>synge
<pb facs="6"/>
shewe of euery eye shuld forth with disclose y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> manifest foly of the Writer, and also I feared and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted the disdaynfull myndes of a nombre both scornefull and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge Correctours, whose Heades are euer busyed in tauntyng Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes. Least they shuld other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse interprete my doyngs than in deade I meant them. These two so great mischiefes vtterly diswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me from the folowynge of my frendes perswasions, and wylled me rather to condem thē to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall darkenes, wherby no Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience could happen: than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunger my selfe in gyuynge them to lyght, to the disdaynfull doome of any offended mynde. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>standynge all the dylygence that I

<pb facs="6"/>
coulde vse in the Suppression therof coulde not suffise for I my selfe beyng at that tyme oute of the Realme, lytell fearynge any suche thynge to happen. A verye Frende of myne, bearynge as it semed bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wyll to my doynges than respec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng the hazarde of my name, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted them all togyther vnpoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to the handes of the Prynter. In whose handes durynge his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence from the Cytie, tyll his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of late they remayned. At whiche tyme, he declared the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wholly vnto me: shewynge me, that beynge so farre past, &amp; Paper prouyded for the Impression ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: It coulde not withoute great hynderaunce of the poore Printer
<pb facs="7"/>
be nowe reuoked. His sodayne tale made me at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fyrst, vtterly amazed, and dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ting a great while, what was best to be done: at the lengthe agreyng both with Necessytie and his Counsell, I sayde with <hi>Martiall. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>am edpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ras tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>oresse domi.</hi> And calling to mynde to whom I myght chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye cōmyt the fruytes of my smiling muse: sodaynly was cast before my eyes the perfect vewe of your frend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly mynd (gentle Maister Louelace) Vnto whō for the nombred heapes of sundrye Frendshyps, accoūtynge my selfe as boūde, I haue thought best to gyue them, (not doubtyng) but that they shalbe as well taken, as I do p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esently meane them.</p>
   <p>Desyry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> herein, as all suche as shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> them especiallye to
<pb facs="7"/>
beare with the vnpleasaunt forme of my to hastely fynyshed Dreame, the greater part wherof with lytle aduyse I lately ended, bycause the beginnyng of it, as a senseles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ead separated frō the body was gyuen with the rest to be prynted. And thus desyrynge but for recompence the frendly receyuyng of my slender Gyfte, I ende: wyshyng vnto you good Mayster Louelace in this life the happye enioyeng of prosperous yeares: and hereafter the blessed estate of neuer ceasynge Ioye.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶Yours assuredly <hi>Barnabe Googe.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>