<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface, or Argument of this POESIE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106071_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07424</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3997</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106071</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface, or Argument of this POESIE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great Plantagenet. Or a continued succession of that royall name, from Henry the Second, to our sacred soveraigne King Charles. By Geo. Buck, Gent</title>
                 <author>Buck, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The Preface, or Argument of this POESIE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Amaetas</hi> having long beene a Wood-man, and observed the Natures and Properties of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Trees, apprehended some Mystery and peculiar matter in the <hi>Genest,</hi> more then hee could attaine to, and meeting with <hi>Silenus,</hi> a man of great Learning and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (for hee was held a Prophet) expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth to him his Conceit: <hi>Silenus</hi> by meanes of a late accident, was well able to instruct and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve him: For there had beene a complaint made lately to <hi>Apollo,</hi> against certaine unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fellowes, which presumptuously tooke Garlands off his ancient Tree the <hi>Laurell.</hi> He forthwith calling the <hi>Muses</hi> to Councell in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon,</hi> established Ordinances for the due wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that, and all other Garlands: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the ancient Garlands were abused and prophained with common and unworthy use, he made choyce of a new Tree, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest;</hi> and instituted Garlands thereof, giving them prerogatives above the rest, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated them to one imperiall Family, seated in
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Britania</hi> or <hi>Albion</hi> rather; <hi>vide Stanz.</hi> 13, and is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> in his <hi>Argonaunt,</hi> where Master <hi>Camden</hi> rather readeth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, then <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Albion,</hi> or <hi>Alba,</hi> rather then <hi>Pinaria.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Leucëëssa;</hi> with expresse defence, that none
<pb facs="9"/>else should weare them; that not all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Family should weare Garlands here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but some a <hi>Chappelet,</hi> and some onely a branch, or <hi>Plant;</hi> the compleate Garland re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for his favorite
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Sub</hi> Daphnis <hi>quod nomen in hac Ecloga da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus S.R.</hi> Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, <hi>sicut</hi> Julio Caesari <hi>olim in Ecloga</hi> 5. Virg. <hi>à Pastoribus.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Daphnis.</hi> After <hi>Silenus</hi> declareth more particularly, who, and what these royall Worthies were.</p>
   <p>Beginning with the great <hi>Henry,</hi> sonne of the Empresse <hi>Matilda,</hi> (the first King of this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, surnamed
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Plantagenet</hi> from <hi>Planta-Genistae,</hi> so call'd (as some say) for wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a slip or stalk of broom in his cap or hat, who write that toward his latter days in penance &amp; contrition for his past sins, he undertook to goe to the Holy Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, in the poore and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised habit of a Broome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and to signifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe so, bore a broom-stalk in his cap: as I have read of other Princes, who in great penitece &amp; humblenes for their sins, &amp; for their better privacy &amp; security, have travail'd thither like Carpēters Joyners, &amp; other poore mechanicke Tradesmen, wearing in the same kind somebadge of the trade they seemed to professe. Others say, it was because he scourged himselfe with the stalks of broom, which grew upon the Plaines where once the holy City stood: But I shal expresse this occasion more amply in another place. He was also surnamed <hi>Courtmantle.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Plantagenet</hi>) and so deducing a Geneologie from him, through his Royall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, to our present Sacred Soveraigne <hi>Charles,</hi> his now Heire, whom hee Crowneth with this <hi>Polyanthine</hi> Garland, &amp;c. In whose Sacred Person are joyntly met and coalesced, the Royall bloods, Titles, and Interests not onely of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> but also of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> For <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Crowne and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof, <hi>(missa per innumeros avos)</hi> all men acknowledge his ancient right therein. And his Majesties Title to <hi>Ireland,</hi> will be manifest in the Genealogy herein deduced from the <hi>Great Plantagenet</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the second, the first English Prince of
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Lyonell Planta</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> 3 Son of K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. married <hi>Eliz.</hi> Daughter and Heire of <hi>Will. Mure-Burk.</hi> Earle of <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> Lord of <hi>Conacht,</hi> from whom the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> are descended. <hi>Camden</hi> in <hi>Hiber.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Ireland,</hi> and from his
<pb facs="9"/>Heroicall posterity, (as well <hi>Marches</hi> as others) who have beene continually seized thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day.
<note n="*" place="margin">His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Title to <hi>France,</hi> see it more at large in the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> So likewise his title to the crowne of <hi>France,</hi> sheweth it selfe cleerely, in the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent possessions of these royall <hi>Plantagenets</hi> here presented. His Majesties Progenitors first Dukes of <hi>Normandy,</hi> then of <hi>Aquitaine;</hi> Earles of <hi>Poictou,</hi> of <hi>Aniou,</hi> of <hi>Maine,</hi> of <hi>Touraine,</hi> and of <hi>Britaine;</hi> and after <hi>Angolesme,</hi> and lastly Kings of all <hi>France,</hi> in the right of
<note place="margin">† <hi>Vide Iohn Froissard Tom.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>Isabell,</hi> or <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> sole Daughter, and Heire of <hi>Philip le bell,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> Mother of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third, who made a most renowned and happy entry upon that his Royall inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: And he, his great Heires were not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Titular Lords, but also Actuall possessors of <hi>France</hi> many yeares; and yet to this day (in token of that ancient right) have seisin of a
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Gersey, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesey, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp;c.</hi> are parcels of <hi>Normandy,</hi> &amp; so consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>France;</hi> yet possessed by the King of <hi>England.</hi>
      </note> part of that Kingdome, notwithstanding that counterfeit-heathnish law <hi>Salica,</hi> maintained by al the power of <hi>France</hi> many ages against them.</p>
   <p>His Majesties title and descent from the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Kings of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> (and which is least knowne) may thus readily be derived.
<note n="*" place="margin">His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Title frō the <hi>British</hi> Kings.</note> The Welch Bardes, as also our best Heralds, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord that
<note place="margin">(1) Ruffin.</note>
      <hi>Rhese-ap-Gruffith</hi> (surnamed <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gluid</hi>) Prince of <hi>South-Wales,</hi> about the yeare of our Lord 1196, (and issued from <hi>Cadwallader,</hi> the last British King) had a Daughter named
<note place="margin">(2) Faire <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Gwenlhiam,</hi> married to
<note place="margin">(3) Edmund.</note>
      <hi>Edneuet Vachan,</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>Lord of <hi>Bransencle,</hi> and chiefe Justice of <hi>Wales,</hi> and bare to him a sonne called
<note place="margin">(4) <hi>Gerion,</hi> or <hi>Jeronim.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Grono,</hi> this <hi>Grono</hi> had
<note place="margin">(5) Theodore.</note>
      <hi>Tedor, Tedor</hi> had <hi>Grono, Grono</hi> had <hi>Tedor, Tedor</hi> had
<note place="margin">(6) Veridik.</note>
      <hi>Meredith, Meredith</hi> had <hi>Owen;</hi> which <hi>Owen</hi> married <hi>Katherine,</hi> (Widdow of King <hi>Henry</hi> 5, and Daughter of the French King <hi>Charles</hi> the sixt) by whom he had <hi>Edmond,</hi> created Earle of <hi>Richmont,</hi> by King <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. his Brother <hi>Vterine:</hi> And this <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> was father of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7, who was Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Queene <hi>Margaret</hi> his Majesties great Grandmother.</p>
   <p>And lastly, to finish his Majesties Titles to all those Diadems mentioned in this <hi>Poësie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">His Majesties title from the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings.</note> I have inserted a Genealogie of the Saxon Kings, drawne from the first uniter of the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> and the Godfather of <hi>Anglia</hi> King <hi>Egbert,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Matilda</hi> the Empresse, Daughter and Heire of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. Ancestour of all the English Kings untill this day, from whom this <hi>Poësie</hi> is a continued Pedegree unto his Majesty, and his most excellent Sonne, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>But it may be objected, why I derive not his Title and Genealogie from some of the ancient Monarchs of this Isle <hi>Britons,</hi> or <hi>Saxons,</hi> or at the least from K. <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, I must answere, that to have chosen any of the most ancient Kings, I must have looked so farre backe as I should not onely have beene too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, but also lost my selfe in obscure wayes,
<pb facs="10"/>(as they know, which know what our ancient Stories bee. But as for <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, there bee many reasons why I should not begin with him; (although I goe as neare him as his Sonnes Daughter) for first he was a Bastard,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Vide Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Stephani Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domensis de</hi> Gulielmo Conquestore <hi>editum,</hi> An. Dom. 1603.</note> and yet not that of the blood Royall of <hi>England</hi>) his chiefe Title to the Crowne, being but violence, and his Sword, as he confessed with remorse of conscience, at his Death. Secondly, he was never possessed of one halfe of <hi>Britaine;</hi> for hee had neither <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor <hi>Wales,</hi> and in <hi>Ireland</hi> not one foote. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore <hi>Girard Du. Haillan,</hi> and other French Antiquaries according to their <hi>Salike</hi> Heraldry, say that his line ended in his Sonne King <hi>Hen.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Philosalicus.</note> for all they hold as a Maxime <hi>(La famille se co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuè es masles, et se finist aux filles)</hi> and yet <hi>Du. Haillan</hi> (notwithstanding or forgetting this) affirmeth in another place: that the race of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> issued out of the house of <hi>Aniow, (viz.)</hi> from our great <hi>Henry,</hi> and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours, continueth untill this day; from whom there be many reasons on the other side, why I should deduce the Genealogies of our Kings passed,
<note place="margin">K. <hi>Henry</hi> 2. the greatest King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> and of our present Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Charles:</hi> for this great <hi>Henry</hi> was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rightfull Heire and King of <hi>England,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the greatest King (of whom there is any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Story extant) which hath beene in this Isle of <hi>Britaine,</hi> since the time of the Roman
<pb facs="11"/>Emperours, (who were reputed Lords of all the World) which thus I demonstrate briefly. He was King of <hi>England</hi> in the right of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Matilda,</hi>
      <note place="margin">King <hi>Malcolm</hi> Knighted this King <hi>Henry</hi> 2. at 15. yeares of age. <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brig</hi> who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth much in the honour of this K. <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colm, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 20.</note> the Empresse, Daughter and Heire to King <hi>Henry</hi> the first by <hi>Matilda Bona,</hi> Daughter of King <hi>Malcolm Canmoir,</hi> and of <hi>Margaret</hi> his wife, who was the Daughter of <hi>Edward Exul,</hi> the <hi>Saxon</hi> Prince, the Sonne of <hi>Edmund Ironside,</hi> King of <hi>England, Anno Dom.</hi> 1016. This <hi>Edmund</hi> was Sonne and Heire to King <hi>Etheldred,</hi> who in ancient Charters is written <hi>Totius Britanniae Rex, (quod nota)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause an <hi>Anonymus</hi> in a little booke dedicated to King <hi>Iames,</hi> affirmeth that never any Prince was King of this whole Isle untill then; but hee is deceived; (for besides <hi>Constantius Chlorus</hi> and his Sonne our Country-man, <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, <hi>Constans, Aurelius Ambrosius, Vter,</hi> and others; (which were Lords of all great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi>) <hi>Edgar</hi> also, the Father of this King <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theldred,</hi> was absolute Monarch of this Island, and so puissant in forces both by Land and Sea, as he was surnamed the <hi>Great,</hi> and was styled <hi>Totius Albionis Basileus, &amp; Anglici Orbis Basi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus,</hi> (as <hi>G. Malmsburiensis &amp; Florentius Wigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niensis</hi> witnesse:
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Britaria</hi> ab adventu <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> in insu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Anglica, Ioan. Salisb.</hi> in <hi>Policratico.</hi>
      </note> Whereupon (to note also by the way) some thinke that the word <hi>Anglia</hi> was sometimes used for the whole Isle, and which <hi>Ion Lidgate</hi> disertly assevereth in King <hi>Arthurs</hi> complaint, in these words: Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>now called <hi>England;</hi> and so likewise doth <hi>Geoffry Chaucer</hi> in the <hi>Franklins</hi> tale, <hi>viz.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ranulfus Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geden</hi> in <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chronic.</hi>
      </note> in <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Clepid</hi> was <hi>Britaine,</hi> and <hi>Ranul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Cestrensis,</hi> a graver Authour, peremptorily affirmeth, that King <hi>Egbert</hi> after his Conquests ordayned, and commanded that the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Iutes</hi> should be called <hi>Angles,</hi> and this <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> should be called <hi>England;</hi> but I leave this to be discussed by Antiquaries.</p>
   <p>And to returne to the ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings Progenitors of this <hi>Henry,</hi> and also possessors of the whole Isle, it is to be shewed (for the better confirmation of that, which hath beene said against the opinion of the <hi>Anonymus</hi>) in diuers ancient Records, and Charters of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of these Kings to Monasteries, and to Cathedrall Churches,
<note place="margin">Ex archiv is Ciscestrensis Ecclesiae.</note> and in other ancient Monuments in these styles:
<note n="*" place="margin">Ephoca.</note>
      <hi>Ego Athelstanus Rex Anglorum Dominicae Incarnationis,</hi> DCCCCXXX. <hi>Regni verò mihi gratis Commissi</hi> vj. <hi>Indictione</hi> iij.
<note n="*" place="margin">Ephoca.</note>
      <hi>Epacta</hi> xviij. <hi>Concurrente</hi> iiij. <hi>Nonis Mensis Aprilis</hi> iij. <hi>Lunae rotigerae va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationis,</hi> i. <hi>per ejusdem omni-patrantis dextram totius Britanniae regium solio sublimatus, &amp;c. Ego Edmundus Rex Anglorum, caeterarumquègentium in circuitu persistentium Gubernator &amp; Rector Anno Domini</hi> 945. <hi>Ego Edredus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">King <hi>Edred</hi> was Uncle to <hi>Edgar Ingulf,</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Rex terrenus sub Imperiali potentia Regis saeculorum, aeterniquè Principis, magnae Britaniae, temporale gerens im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium, &amp;c. Anno Domini</hi> 148. <hi>Ego Edgarus
<pb facs="12"/>totius Albionis Monarcha, &amp;c. An. Dom.</hi> 966. and in another; <hi>Ego Edgarus totius Albionis, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti-morum{que} regnum Basileus, An. Domini</hi> 974. These three last styles hath <hi>Ingulfus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Croyland</hi> transcribed by him, from the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Monastery: and the other two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore going, are copied out of the Records of <hi>Chichester</hi> Cathedrall Church, as also these three next following.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ego Eadwis Basileon totius Albionis,</hi>
      <note place="margin">If <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>sub. Rex.</hi> This <hi>Edwis,</hi> or <hi>Edwin</hi> was eldest Brother to the great K. <hi>Eadger. Asser in Histo. de Gestis Eal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridi.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>&amp;c. Anno Domini</hi> Dcccc. Lvj. <hi>Imperij antem i.</hi> And in another place; <hi>Ego Edwin Rex gentium Albio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp;c.</hi> And in the date of a Charter of Bishop <hi>Brighthelmus Anno secundo imperij Edwin toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Albionis Insulae imperantis;</hi> there is also (in <hi>Asser Meneuensis</hi>) <hi>Aelured,</hi> or <hi>Aelfred</hi> a more ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> King then these written: <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Britanium Insulae Christianorum Rector, An. Dom.</hi> 872.</p>
   <p>And <hi>Edward</hi> (surnamed <hi>Pius</hi> and <hi>Confessor</hi>) was from the yeare of our Lord 1050. King of this whole Ile, (if there be any credit to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to our Stories) &amp; was styled <hi>Rex Albionis,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Io. Twinus in Albionicis.</note> as <hi>Iohn Twin</hi> avoweth out of his Charters given to the Abby of <hi>Abington;</hi> and that same King <hi>Etheldred</hi> before cited, was styled in the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Glastonbury, Etheldred Anglicae nationis, caeterarum{que} gentium triniatim intra ambitum Britan. Insulae degentium, &amp;c. Basileus,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother King in old inscription <hi>Britinniae Anax;</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>and many such more which were too long to recite. And some Kings of the <hi>Norman</hi> race, (which is more rare) have beene so styled: For the Lord Bishop of <hi>Bristow</hi> voucheth a Coine of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> wherein is stamped <hi>Ioannes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">In his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise about the Union.</note>
      <hi>Rex Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonum:</hi> But his Grand-child K. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Vide</hi> Th. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singham in K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> in <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note> were greater Monarchs here then he. But this great <hi>Henry Plantagenets</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire extended beyond the bounds of the Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish world; and his greatnesse so farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all other Kings his Ancestours, that hee was styled <hi>Maximus Britaniae Regum,</hi> as I will shew by and by, and by good right,
<note place="margin">Jo. Praesul Carnotensis in Policratico.</note> for besides this his great <hi>Britaine</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> he was pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of a great part of <hi>France</hi> by these Titles: Hee was Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> by right of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance from his Grandfather King <hi>Henry</hi> 1,
<note place="margin">K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> into a Princedome for his eldest sonne <hi>Ed.</hi>
      </note> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> &amp;c. He was Duke of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> (that is) <hi>Gascoine,</hi> and <hi>Guien,</hi> (some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a iKngdome) and Earle of <hi>Poictou</hi> by the marriage of Queene <hi>Elinor,</hi> Daughter and Heire of <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Aquitaine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Jean de la Hay.</note> and Earle of <hi>Poictou,</hi> (whose wife <hi>Ieanne</hi> was daughter of <hi>David,</hi> King of <hi>Scots.</hi> He was Earle of <hi>Aniou,</hi> (Seminary of Kings) of <hi>Touraine</hi> and <hi>Maine,</hi> (his native Countrey) by right of inheritance from his Father <hi>Geoffry le Bel,</hi> Earle of them all: He swayed in little <hi>Britaine,</hi> which authority he acquired partly by the Marriage of <hi>Const.</hi> daughter and heire of <hi>Conan,</hi> Earle of <hi>Brita.</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>with his third sonne <hi>Geoffry,</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> but chiefly by his Sword; as it appeareth by <hi>Gu.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>Cap.</hi> 18.</note>
      <hi>Neuburgensis,</hi> who then lived, and thus writeth; <hi>Cum a potentioribus in Britania inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res premerentur, Regis Anglorum auxilium ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petentes, ejus se ditioni spontanè subdiderunt, &amp;c. ipsos{que} potentes viribus subegit, sic{que} in brevi tot a Britania potitus est.</hi> He also conquered <hi>Auuergne.</hi> For <hi>Ireland,</hi> he twice invaded that kingdome, and by Armes seconded with Letters of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his good Friend Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> (an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishman) hee brought the discording Princes there,
<note place="margin">Girald Cambr. in Hibern. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnata, &amp; G. Canden.</note> to submit their differences and their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to him, and so obtained the possession of the Isle.</p>
   <p>As for those parts and parties in this our <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> viz. of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> which did not acknowledge his Soveraignty) he reduced them in good time, to the ancient subjection and obedience which they owed to the British and Saxon Kings, his Progenitors. The Welch-men in their Stories acknowledge this; but for the other, (if any doubt be made) <hi>G. Neuburgensis</hi> (<hi>veridicus Autor,</hi> as <hi>Polidore Virgill</hi> observeth him) will thus satisfie him, speaking of this King <hi>Henry,</hi> and of <hi>David</hi> K. of <hi>Scots,</hi> his prisoner, being then both at <hi>Yorke, Occurrit ei Rex Scotorum cum universis Regni no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilibus, qui omnes in Ecclesia beatissimi Apostolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Principis, Regi</hi> Angliae, <hi>tanquam principall
<pb facs="13"/>Domino hominum cum Ligeantia, (id est) solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni cautione standi cum eo, &amp; pro eo contra omnes homines (Rege proprio praecipiente) fecerunt; ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se quoquè Rex Scotorum coram universa multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine nobilium utriusquè regni Regem Anglorem modis solemnibus Dominum suum, se{que} hominem &amp; fidelem eius declaravit, eiquè tria praecipua regni sui munimina (scilicèt) Rokesburke, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, &amp; Castellum puellarum loco obsidum tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Iohn Bishop</hi> of <hi>Chartres,</hi> maketh his Empire yet much greater,
<note place="margin">Jo Bish. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notensis in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licratico.</note> for he boundeth it to the Southward with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with the Isle of <hi>Orkney,</hi> and might as well (if it had pleased him) with the North-Pole (as <hi>Giraldus Cambrensis</hi> did) and then styleth him <hi>maximum</hi> Britaniae <hi>Regum,</hi> and goeth further, and compareth him to <hi>Alexander,</hi> and ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth (as some interpret) the first discovery of the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> (which was made by <hi>Madok</hi> a younger sonne of <hi>Owin Gwineth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">D. Powell.</note> Prince of <hi>North-Wales, An. Dom.</hi> 1170.) to this King, because it was done by his auspices: as we may as well also attribute to him the redeeming of our great <hi>Arthur</hi> from the injurious imputation of a fabulous <hi>Heros,</hi> because he caused his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument to be sought out, (which was sunke deepe into the ground in the Isle of <hi>Aualon</hi>) by the occasion of a <hi>Bardes</hi> song,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>D. Powell</hi> in the Hist. of the Princes of <hi>Wales.</hi>
      </note> which he heard in <hi>Pembrooke:</hi> but I will set downe <hi>Gyraldus</hi> his owne words, written in manner of a <hi>Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>to this King elegant enough for those times:
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sil. Giraldus in Tepographia Hiberniae, Cap.</hi> 47. <hi>&amp;</hi> 48. <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>Certant cum orbe terrarum victoriae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strae; à</hi> Pyrenaeis <hi>enim montibus us{que} in occiduos, &amp; extremos Borealis Oceani fines</hi> Alexander <hi>noster occidentalis brachium extendisti. Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum igitur his in partibus natura terras, tantum &amp; victorias extulisti, si excursuum tuorum metae quaerantur, prius deerit Orbis quàm aderit finis. Animoso enim pectori cessare possunt terrae, cessare nesciunt victoriae, non deessse poterunt triumphi, sed materia triumphandi. Qualiter titulis vestris &amp; triumphis Hibernicus accesserit Orbis? Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ &amp; quàm laudabili virtute Oceani secreta, &amp; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culta Naturae deposita transpenetraveris, &amp;c. Qualiter fulguranti adventus vestri lumine atto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti occidentales reguli tanquam ad lucubrum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viculae ad vestrum statim imperiū couvolaverunt.</hi> And much more,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Jo. Salisbur. in Policratico. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.</note> which for brevity I omit: That which the Bishop of <hi>Chartres</hi> writeth of him before mentioned, and promised, is this; <hi>Rex illustris Anglorum</hi> Hen. <hi>secundus Regum</hi> Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae <hi>maximus, &amp;c. circa Garumnam fulminat, &amp; Tolosam faelici (cingens obsidione, non modo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciales, usquè ad</hi> Rhodanum, <hi>&amp;</hi> Alpes <hi>terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, sed munitionibus dirutis populisquè</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Profligatis.</note>
      <hi>subactis, (quasi universis praesens immineat) timore Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes concussit Hispanos &amp; Gallos.</hi> And to these adde onely <hi>William Neuburoughs</hi> Elogie for a Corollary.
<note place="margin">
         <hi>G. Neubourgh Lib.</hi> 11.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Regis supra omnes, qui unquam hactenus in
<pb facs="14"/>Anglia regnasse noscebantur, latius dominantis, (hoc est) ab ultimis Scotiae finibus ad montes us{que} Pyrenaeos, nomen in cunctis Regionibus celebre ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebatur, &amp;c. hunc finem habuit inclytus ille Rex</hi> Henricus 2. <hi>inter Reges terrarum nominatissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; nulli eorum, vel amplitudine opum, vel faelicitate successuum secundus.</hi> Thus much for the testimony of the greatnesse of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, and of his Empire: as for his other great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, his Wisedome, Justice, Magnanimity, Bounty, and other Heroicall Vertues, I shall not neede to produce any proofe; for his wise and politicke administration of his great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and estate, his Victories and high at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chivements secretly intimate them at the full.
<note place="margin">Gyral. Cambr.</note> He was also well learned, as <hi>Giraldus</hi> affirmeth, and which was his best praise, hee was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry charitable and pious <hi>(incomparabilis Eleëmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>synarum largitor, et praecipuus terrae Palestinae sustentator)</hi> And <hi>Radulph de Diceto</hi> writeth, that in the time of an extreame dearth in <hi>Aniou</hi> and <hi>Maine,</hi> hee relieved with bread,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>An. Domini</hi> 1176.</note> tenne thousand people dayly, from Aprill till har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest: And <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Newburrough</hi> addeth, that hee received with great devotion the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the sacred <hi>Militia</hi> for the recovery of the holy land. And afterward (because he was not able to goe by reason of infirmities, and for the great dangers wherein his estate should stand in his absence, which <hi>Giraldus</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>sheweth, he gave towards the expedition the summe of 47.
<note place="margin">Jo. Stoan an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> M. l. or thereabouts. <hi>Iean de la Hay</hi> also writeth that hee built S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> in <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and St. <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Poitiers,</hi> and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Bishops sea there, and enlarged the Towne by the one halfe;
<note place="margin">Fabian.</note> he reedified the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by at <hi>Waltham</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> and the Charter house of <hi>Witham</hi> in <hi>Wiltshire;</hi>
      <note place="margin">He loved hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. <hi>Giral.</hi> he first kept Lyons &amp; made of the armes of <hi>Normandy viz.</hi> the 2 Leopards, and of the single Lyon of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitaine one Coat of armes for England: as it is yet borne: <hi>Nic. Ʋpton. John Carnoten: Lib.</hi> 16. <hi>Cap.</hi> 18.</note> hee repaired and much beautified the Monastery of <hi>Font Everard</hi> (or <hi>Fronteaux</hi>) neare <hi>Ogle</hi> in <hi>Normandy</hi> and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Priories of <hi>Staneley,</hi> and of <hi>Dover:</hi> Hee also beganne the stone worke of London bridge, which was finished by his sonne King <hi>Iohn,</hi> (or caused to bee finished) for it is all one to a common wealth; and hee instituted the circuit of the judges, and not to bee tedious in the enumeration of such particulars, in a word, he was as <hi>Iohn Carnotensis</hi> who knew him well: testifieth, <hi>Rex optimus apud Britanias, Norma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum et Aquitanorum Dux faelicissimus, et primus tam amplitudine rerum, quam splendore virtutum, quam strenuus quam magnificus, quam prudens, et modestus quam pius ab ipsa, (ut ita dicam) infantia fuerit, nec ipse livor silere, nec dissimulare potest: cum oper a recentia, et manifesta sint, &amp;c.</hi> And after these his great workes, his high Atchievements, his victories, Trophees of his Heroicall and Christian vertues, a long and happy Raigne, he departed at <hi>Chinon</hi> in <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> the 35 yeare of his raigne, and the 61
<pb facs="15"/>yeare of his age, An. Dom. 1189. and was with all due funeral Enterred at <hi>Fronteuaux,</hi> and upon his Tombe had this inscription ingraven.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Sufficit hic tumulus cui non suffecerat orbis,</l>
      <l>Res brevis ampla satis, cui fuit ampla brevis.</l>
      <l>Rex invictus eram, mihi plurima regna subegi,</l>
      <l>Multiplici{que} modo dux{que}, comes{que} fui.</l>
      <l>Cui satis ad votum fuerant haud omnia terra</l>
      <l>Climata, terra modo sufficit octo pedum.</l>
      <l>Qui legis haec, pensa discrimina mortis, et in me</l>
      <l>Humanae speculum conditionis habe;</l>
      <l>Quod potes instanter operare bonum, quia mundus</l>
      <l>Transit, &amp; incautos Mors inopinarapit.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Thus this great <hi>Henry</hi> left his great name, and his glory to the world, and his Kingdomes and his Dominions to his posterity, the Princes aranged in this following <hi>Poesy.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>