<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL ESTATES
AND DEGREES, WHO
truly tender their owne Soules, the
Church of God, and their natiue
COVNTREY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106649_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16890</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3786</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106649</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL ESTATES
AND DEGREES, WHO
truly tender their owne Soules, the
Church of God, and their natiue
COVNTREY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The third part of The true vvatch : containing the call of the Lord, to awake all sorts to meet him with intreatie of peace, and to turne unto him by true repentance: shewing what causes we have forthwith to betake our selves to watching and prayer. Taken out of the visio of Ezekiel, chap. 9. By Iohn Brinsley</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>74, 568, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="26"/>
   <head>TO ALL ESTATES
AND DEGREES, WHO
truly tender their owne Soules, the
Church of God, and their natiue
COVNTREY.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now many yeares (Christian
Reader) since by reading those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Prophets which liued next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Captiuitie of Iudah,<note place="margin">Occasion of this watch, feare of Gods iudgements lying vpon vs.</note> who
denounced the same to be ready to
come vpon Gods people for their
sinnes, and by considering and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
the same with the times
wherein we liue, I haue euer fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the life plague or a heauier to be hanging ouer this our
sinfull Nation.<note place="margin">This feare hath not bin vvithout iust cause, as eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nts haue declared.</note> Neither haue I feared without iust cause:
for how neere indeed such a iudgement hath bin vnto vs, and
how the same threatnings haue bin ready to be verified vpon
vs,<note place="margin">Our later d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerances still the greatest.</note> the world is witnesse, euen all they who haue but onely
heard the report of our dangers, and of our wonderfull and
euen miraculous deliuerances. And euer the later perils and
preseruations haue bin the more wonderfull;<note place="margin">The duty of all Gods faithfull Ministers to be euer giuing warning.</note> as that one of
the Powder furnace was aboue all that euer former age heard
of. In the due meditation and regard whereof, I haue taken
it to be my dutie, and of all the faithfull Ministers of Christ,
<pb facs="27"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="27"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="28"/>
to follow the example of <hi>Noah,</hi> and of all those faithfull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 3. 17, 18. &amp; 18. 30.</note>
in giuing warning aforehand, (keeping within the limits
and compasse of our calling) to helpe to open the eyes of all, to
foresee,<note place="margin">Iam. 2. 14.</note> and to cause all to tremble for the anger of the Lord,
also to contend with all our power to turne euery soule from
his euill way:<note place="margin">Ior. 23. 22.</note> that so his wrath may be appeased,<note place="margin">Iam 4 17. &amp; 5. 19, 20.</note> and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
from the dreadfull execution of his heauiest venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 9, 10, 11.</note>
Herevpon in my former feare amongst other causes I
was chiefly emboldned (and that not long before the time of
that bloudie Powder-treason,<note place="margin">A chiefe occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion of the first part of this watch, as the title of it decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</note> as the Lord had so directed it)
to endeuour to set downe truly, and after to publish to all, the
first part of this watch, viz: <hi>The rule of life,</hi> contayning the
couenant which we haue all entred into with our God. To the
end to helpe to keepe all his people from the generall declining
from that his blessed couenant to profanesse and iniquitie, and
from the outragious wickednes of the rest, that we also might
all learne to watch to be preserued in the euill day.<note place="margin">So of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, The Rule of Prayer, to stir vs all vp to watching &amp; prayer, as our sins &amp; dangers still increased.</note> And since
then likewise the second part of the same watch, viz: <hi>The
rule of prayer,</hi> to awaken vs the better, and to stirre vp all
the Lords faithfull seruants the more speedily and instantly
to betake our selues wholly to watching and prayer, not onely
to be accounted worthy to escape the euills approching, but also
that ech of vs may still helpe to preserue the Island; like as
our most compassionate Father hath in the riches of his mercy
vouchsafed to accept vs vntill this day.<note place="margin">The time of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> comming forth of the second part.</note> And this likewise he
in his wisdome directed to come forth at the very instant, yea
in the midst of the last apparant danger, which we in our parts
were in,<note place="margin">The dreadful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of those tunes to many, howsoeuernow forgotten.</note> for the insurrection about inclosures: which howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
it might seeme nothing or small to them who dwelt far
from it; yet to vs who expected the approching of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells
euery houre, and heard how the hearts of the people were
generally bent, it was no lesse terrible than any of the former,
but so much more fearefull, the neerer it was. Now therefore
in the third place:<note place="margin">The cause of this third part, our sins increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</note> forasmuch as all men may behold all kinde
of wickednesse and impietie still increasing fearefully without
hope of redresse, so that vnlesse we will put out our owne eyes,
we must see the iudgement of God hasting faster vpon vs, and
<pb facs="28"/>
being at the very dore, I haue taken it my bounden dutie, and
my best seruice that I could doe and possibly performe, to his
heauenly Maiestie, his Church, and my Country, to adde this
third part: to the end to set before the faces of euery one of
vs, the heynousnesse of our sinnes in euery degree, and so the
equitie of the Lords proceeding against vs: that we may all
be inforced to iustifie his Maiestie, though he come to execute
whatsoeuer he hath so often threatned, when no kinde of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning
can doe vs any good. And also to try if yet at length
he will vouchsafe to recall vs againe to his couenant, and put
new life into vs, to meet him falling vpon our faces in fasting
and prayer, to pacifie his wrath, and that ech of vs may begin
to put that in practise which was intended and sought in the
two former parts, that is, to watch and pray continually, not in
words any longer, but in deed and truth; for the preseruation
and lasting welfare of vs and our posteritie.</p>
   <p>That the heauiest iudgement must needs be feared to be so
much the neerer,<note place="margin">The heauiest iudgment iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feared to be hard at y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> dores.</note> as the anger of the most High is more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
against vs, no man can doubt: and that his wrath is incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
to the vttermost, is most apparent to all, whose eyes he hath
opened, or who doe but beleeue his heauenly word: for that in
stead of hauing any of our greeuous abhominations (which
we may behold set before our faces in the Treatise following,
euen by the Prophets themselues, and forwhich he hath so
often threatned us,) yet vnfeignedly repented of, we haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
increased them many times more.<note place="margin">All of vs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing solemnly entred into co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our God; haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him to threaten to take away his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by our transgression.</note> The couenant of our
God, which the whole land professeth, and ech of vs in our
Baptisme haue solemnely entred into, we haue most grieuously
transgressed. And this many of vs haue done with so high a
hand, as that we haue caused that his heauenly Gospell to be
blasphemed, inforcing him to threaten to take his couenant,
with all his blessings from vs: yea, to leaue vs to be made a
prey and a spoyle vnto our enemies, which thirst after our
bloud continually.<note place="margin">This confessed by all <hi>Anno 1588.</hi>
      </note> This all confessed, when they so despight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
and proudly came against vs, as being ready to swallow
vs vp quicke, and ech of vs then acknowledged, that his wrath
was most iustly kindled against vs for the same: so as if he
<pb facs="29"/>
should then haue cast vs off vtterly, for euer being his people,
or a nation any more, that yet we had most righteously deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
it.<note place="margin">And in all our dangers <hi>Anno 1602. 1603.</hi>
      </note> This we haue in like manner many a time since ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged,
in all our dangers and plagues which we haue had
vpon vs plague after plague, as those ten plagues of Aegypt.
More especially in the grieuous dearths, and chiefly in that
most poysoned plague of pestilence, as the sundry confessions
of sinnes, then made and still extant, doe and shall euer beare
witnesse. But aboue all other times, when we were all ready
to be consumed in the hot fierie furnace at once: yea this we
ordinarily and daily euery one confessed, whilst we liued in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
danger euery houre, before the Lord so miracul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sly
and graciously set vp his Anointed ouer vs.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> euery one then.</note> Euery one then
could say, Our sinnes are so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>heynous, as that we must needes
haue some terrible vengeance without speedie repentance.
This wrath ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fore we must needs acknowledge to be farre
greater now than euer heretofore:<note place="margin">Gods wrath must needs be greater now than euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> not onely for that in stead
of repenting, our sinnes are so growne vp in euery kinde, but
also because we are now so generally, and so much further off
from repentance, or any purpose of amendment, yea of so much
as of any sense of our sinnes, or feare of any iudgement to be
toward vs for the same, than euer we were in former time,
notwithstanding all the meanes which he hath so long vsed to
awaken vs,<note place="margin">This can be no way appeased, but by taking away our sins the cause of it, and turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his Couenant.</note> and to bring vs to repentance. How then can this
fire of the Lords anger be euer quenched, we deliuered from
the violence thereof, that we should not be consumed of it, but
onely by seeking out the principall causes of it, to wit, our
maine transgressions against the couenant of our God, by which
he hath bin so prouoked, and also by confessing and acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
them, and turning backe ioyntly to the humble obedience
of that his most holy Couenant againe: <hi>Israel</hi> cannot stand
before their enemies,<note place="margin">Examples.</note> vntill <hi>Achans</hi> sacriledge be found out
and punished;<note place="margin">Iosh. 7. 10.</note> neither can the dearth be stayed in the dayes
of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m. 21. 1. 14. 24.</note> vntill the causes of it be found out, and the Lord
pacified by taking away the iniquitie. Nor yet can the storme
vpon the Seas be quieted,<note place="margin">Ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 1. 15.</note> so long as <hi>Ionah</hi> lyeth asleepe in his
sinne. How much losse now, when so many <hi>Achan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> be in
<pb facs="29"/>
euery corner, and <hi>Ionah</hi> asleepe euery where in the eyes of all?
As it is with a particular man,<note place="margin">As it is for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> particular man, so for a whole Nation.</note> so is it with a whole Nation.
That like as there must be first a searching out of his sinne,
with confession of it, and turning againe vnto the Lord, before
his anger can be appeased, so must it be for a whole Nation
(so far as we can iustly conceiue) before any sound assurance
can be giuen that his wrath is turned away. This seemes euery
where most euident thorow all the booke of God.</p>
   <p>How Poperie is growne vp againe,<note place="margin">The increase of Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie and all profanenosse, notorious to all.</note> the late proclamation for
preuenting it, and the furie of that bloudie Religion, and for
the preseruation of his Royall Maiestie, and his Seede, set
forth vpon the occasion of the cruell murther of the French
King, doth sufficiently witnesse. And likewise the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
vrging the Oath of Allegeance inforced therevpon: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
so many lamentable experiments, and our ouer-iust feares
for their trecheries expected ech howre. How Atheisme
also, with all kinde of outragious iniquitie, and scorning at all
true pietie, doe ouerflow in euery place, aboue all former
times,<note place="margin">Some sins hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, now tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row custome &amp; commonnesse, become as no sinnes.</note> no man can denie. Indeed some sinnes haue bin odious
heretofore, and especially when they began first to spring vp,
and were cryed out of, as which all the godly feared, that they
would presently bring the vengeance of God vpon vs all, which
now through long custome and commonnesse are made no sins:
as that beastly valour of powring downe wine and strong
drinke, and our glorying in it; pride with all monstrous excesse
therein, oppression, deriding and hating all true godlinesse, and
the power of religion. Though all of them, and many like, are
in a higher degree in the Land, and practised with a farre
higher hand now,<note place="margin">No sinne truely repented of.</note> than euer heretofore. Or if any one abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
be taken away and gone, who can say that it hath bin
generally repented of▪ or left of any conscience, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for feare of
the Lord and awe of his word? And therefore if he be the
same holy God, still hating sinne as much as euer he did, and
who will neuer cleare the guiltie, how should it be but (though
our owne hearts, and all the world doe slatter vs, telling vs
that we shall haue peace) yet as our sinnes are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> increased
and our abhominations gone vp to heauen,<note place="margin">As our sins are m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ltiplied, so his wrath.</note> so his wrath and
<pb facs="30"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ousie must needs smoke against vs,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 34 7.</note> and his curses &amp; plagues
be multiplied vpon vs vntill he hath put out our name from
vnder heauen;<note place="margin">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 18. 19, 20.</note> vnlesse we meet him speedily and appease his
wrath by our humble and vnfeigned turning vnto him. But
these crying sinnes can neuer be taken away,<note place="margin">The cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing sins cānot be taken away, vnlesse y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> causes of them be first repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of.</note> vnlesse also euen
the other sinnes of the Land be likewise repented of. I meane
those from which these proceed, and for which men are so ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
giuen vp vnto these monstrous iniquities. For these
outragious enormities are the heauiest punishments of other
sinnes, and ordinarily the immediate fore-runners of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
temporall iudgement.<note place="margin">We cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vntill we know both the maine prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, &amp; ech our owne sins, with the iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them.</note> Neither can we euer haue any
assurance to be preserued from that extremest vengeance, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
we returne more generally in our hearts, from all our euill
wayes vnto the Conenant of our God: neither yet euer repent
nor turne from them, vnlesse we see both generally the most
heynous prouocations of the Land angring his Maiestie, and
ech of vs our owne seuerall sins particularly, with his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
belonging therevnto. Therefore sith that our most
pitifull father hath,<note place="margin">God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie of our iniquitie to turne away our captiuitie.</note> in the riches of his endlesse compassion,
ordeyned the discouerie of the iniquitie, and of the certaine
approaching of his iudgement to turne away the vengeance,
and that by turning his people from their euill way; and so
he complaines of the Prophets, that they had not discouered
their iniquitie to turne away their captiuitie,<note place="margin">Ierem. 23. 22.</note> and saith plainly
of them,<note place="margin">And his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets standing in his counsell to turne vs frō our euill way.</note> That if they had stood in his counsell, and declared
his words to his people, they should haue turned them from
their euill wayes, and from the wickednesse of their inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
I haue therefore as I say, taken this as my chiefest ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,<note place="margin">This is y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den dutie of all his messengers and their chiefe seruice.</note>
that euer I could performe vnto his heauenly Maiestie,
his Church and people of this our Nation, euen to helpe to
search out our sinne, by his holy word, and to set our iniquities
before our faces, with his most righteous iudgements due vnto
vs for the same, and ready euer to breake in vpon vs like the
raging seas, thereby to helpe amongst others to bring vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.
And the rather for that, howsoeuer euery one of vs
will acknowledge that we must first turne away from our sins
vnto him, before he will turne to vs from his fierce wrath,
<pb facs="30"/>
and also that we must search and finde out our iniquities, and
see the danger which we stand in for them, before we can turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
from them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yet long experience hath confirmed this, that we
being lulled so fast asleepe in our securitie thorough our long
prosperitie,<note place="margin">Because we will neuer search out our sinnes of our selues.</note> can neuer search out our sinne of our selues, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
they be set plainely before our faces, and we awaked and
rowzed by his most terrible denuntiations for the same. If
<hi>Dauid</hi> himselfe such a worthy Prophet,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dauid</hi> must haue <hi>Nathan</hi> to awaken him.</note> a man of a most ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
conscience (as is euident by all his Psalmes) and his wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
his bed with his teares) yet being become secure in his
sinne,<note place="margin">2 Sam▪ 12.</note> must haue <hi>Nathan</hi> to awake him, by setting his sinne
plainely before his face, before that he can see the vilenesse
of it to repent so of it as to finde mercy (though his sin was so
grosse and palpable, and Gods wrath lying vpon him so heauily
in a spirituall manner, and also his vengeance ready to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted
in most fearefull sort.) How much more then haue we
neede of some <hi>Boanarges,</hi> sonnes of thunder, to awaken vs,
being a sinfull and hard-hearted people and dead in our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.
And if those to whom he hath not only spoken once &amp;
twise, but also smitten with sicknesse vpon their beds, that
their soules draw to the graue,<note place="margin">Iob 33. 23.</note> and their life to the buriers,
had neede of a messenger, an interpreter, one of a thousand
to declare vnto them their righteousnesse,<note place="margin">Men smitten with sicknesse drawing neere to the buriers, must haue an interpreter one of a thousand.</note> to set their sinnes
before their eyes, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re they may finde the true righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes,
before they can say they haue sinned, &amp; repent to finde
mercy: How much more we our selues? when most of vs who
haue bin chiefe in this provocation are in health and prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and in no misfortune like other folke, but rather fed in all
pleasure, as against the day of slaughter. And to conclude
this point,<note place="margin">They who had crucified our Sauiour.</note> we see how those three thousand, that crucified our
Lord &amp; Sauiour, could not yet see their bloudy sin, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
all which they had formerly heard and seene in our
Sauiour, and also the dreadfull signes at his passion, vntill
that <hi>Peter</hi> particularly laid open their wickednesse, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it vnto them directly that they were the men, and
then onely are they pricked at their hearts, and cry out,
Men and Brethren, what shall we doe? Now I say, if none
<pb facs="31"/>
of these, no not they whose sinne was so intolerable, and who
had bin so manifestly convinced, can search out their sinnes
of themselues, to be so soundly humbled, as to turne and seeke
to pacifie the Lords wrath; how much lesse hope is there of vs,
a natiō so setled vpon our lees, &amp; so hardned by our abusing the
long patience &amp; forbearance of our most tender father? who
hauing bin in so many dangers, &amp; yet still deliuered frō them
all, do thinke that it shall be so with vs euer, &amp; that now there
can be no more danger toward vs. We therefore had more need
of many such as <hi>Nathan,</hi>
      <note place="margin">We are they y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> haue neede of <hi>Nathan</hi> if euer any.</note> to set our sin most liuely before our
faces, and after to tell vs directly, That we are they with whom
God is now angry, and that aboue all the people of the earth, as
he hath knowne vs aboue all other Nations, like as we shall see
in the sequell.<note place="margin">Amos 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> We haue neede not of that one messenger, that
one of a thousand alone,<note place="margin">Of all Gods faithfull mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers.</note> but of all the faithfull messengers and
men of God, by their preaching, and all holy meanes, to shew vs
our vnrighteousnes: and of <hi>Peter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Of Peter.</note> to giue vs to know for a
suretie, That we are the men who haue crucified the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.<note place="margin">Acts 2. 36.</note>
Yea we haue neede of <hi>Ionah,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Of <hi>Ionah.</hi>
      </note> to proclaime vnto vs, Yet
fortie dayes and <hi>England</hi> shall be destroyed for her sin.<note place="margin">Ionah 1. 2.</note> And
finally, when preaching will not serue to awake vs, we haue
neede of <hi>Ieremie</hi> or <hi>Baruck</hi> to write the sinnes of vs all,<note place="margin">Of <hi>Ieremie</hi> or <hi>Baruch</hi> to write our sins, when all other means faile.</note> with
the plagues which God hath praepared and denounced against
vs for the same; That euery one euen running by may read
them, as written in capitall letters vpon tables: to try if yet
at length by this meanes,<note place="margin">Ier. 36. 2. 3.</note> we may see the greatnes of the anger
that is kindled against vs, and so repent and retùrne euery one
from his euill way, that he may forgiue our iniquitie and sin,
and deliuer vs from the imminent, and all like future
plagues.</p>
   <p>To this very end,<note place="margin">We may here se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> our sins and iudgement set before vs in the sins of <hi>Iudah.</hi> by the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</note> that we may behold the Lord himselfe
discouering vnto vs our iniquities, and so may haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o more
pretence nor cloakes for our sinnes, nor yet surmize the
least partialitie, here we may all see (and that in the very sins
of <hi>Iudah,</hi> for which God brought vpon them that terrible cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie)
the Lord himselfe and not men, setting before our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
both our sinnes in generall, and the transgressions of ech of
<pb facs="31"/>
vs, as in particular, and how we haue thereby deserued such a
iudgement. These I haue laboured to set out more fully, and
to apply them more particularly vnto vs, because of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
acknowledged by all to be necessarie vnto sound repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
in euery one, who lookes to get full assurance of Gods
mercy.<note place="margin">These labored in more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>peci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, bicause of the degrees in true repentance</note> As first a true search, sight and sense of his sinne and
Gods anger for it. 2. Humble confession of it. 3. Griefe of
heart with detestation of the same. 4. Crying for pardon.
5. A lowly offering our selues to his Maeiestie to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lke with
him all our dayes. 6. A faithfull performance of our vowes.
For this cause haue I bent my chiefe studie to helpe somewhat
herevnto, that all these parts of true repentance may be
wrought in vs, and the same made vnfeigned. And to this
end I haue prepared first (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>) and sent before,<note place="margin">The Couenant sent before ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by the learned.</note> the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant
of our God with vs, in the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st part of this watch: that
it might be throughly tryed, like as it hath bin approued for
many yeares, by sundry learned professors of the Gospell, euen
by all to whom it hath come, so far forth as I know, to be that
truth of God, wherein we all agree: and the summe of that
which the Lord requires of vs generally, without which we
cannot be established, and of euery one particularly, if we will
be saued.<note place="margin">The branches of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, set here before our sins.</note> In this part I haue likewise set the seuerall branches
of the same Couenant before sundry of our heynous sinnes,
that by comparing them togither, we may more liuely behold
our transgressions and provocations. Yea I haue striuen thorow
the whole to helpe,<note place="margin">That we may all see &amp; turne to the Couenāt of the Lord.</note> that euery one of vs might returne to that
his blessed Couenant, for the happinesse of vs all, and of euery
particular soule, and to saue vs both from the temporall and
eternall vengeance.<note place="margin">1. For y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> whole Nation.</note> And first in regard of the whole Nation,
because we all stand continually in danger of that anger of
God to be powred out vpon vs, which had formerly almost
ouerwhelmed vs all, and for ought we can imagine, must needs
ouertake vs in the end, vnlesse we more generally repent and
turne vnto his Maiestie.<note place="margin">No policie can secure vs, but our more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall turning.</note> No policie of man nor humane
meanes can euer secure vs from the furie of Babylon, and that
he should not suffer them to execute their malice vpon vs, and
leaue them to be executioners of his plagues so often and so
<pb facs="32"/>
neerely accomplished,<note place="margin">Ier. 18. 7.</note> but this our more generall turning. All
that euer they haue done or doe intend are nothing but the
Lordsthreatnings, denouncing by them to pluck vs vp, to root
vs out, and destroy vs; as we shall see at large in this vision of
<hi>Ezechiel.</hi>
      <note place="margin">All their malice &amp; mischieuous deuises are the Lords denunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations against vs.</note> They are onely Gods axe, his souldiers, his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners,
though themselues know not so much. It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
he may deferre his plagues, or lessen them, at the prayers
of his faithfull seruants, as he hath done many a day and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
vs in the imminent perils;<note place="margin">Isai. 106, 15.</note> but there is nothing (so far as
we can perceiue out of the word of the Lord to giue vs any
securitie) that can cause him to repent of that great plague,<note place="margin">Frō which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can cause him to turne but our turning to him.</note>
and destruction, which he seemeth to haue denounced so plainly
and directly from Heauen against our Realme and Nation, so
to turne it away, but onely our turning from our wickednesse.
We may all behold our pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sent estate in the 18 of <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 18. 5.</note>
written as in great letters for euery one to read, and that so
plainely, as none can pretend ignorance, but it must of necessitie
convince euery conscience in all the Land; for to vs it is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
both to vs all in generall, and to euery soule particularly.
At the 5<seg rend="sup">th</seg> verse of that Chapter,<note place="margin">vers. 5.</note> first he sends <hi>Ieremie</hi> to
the Potters house, that there he might see the Potter breake
the pots in his hand at his pleasure. Then the word came vnto
the Prophet at that very instant, saying,</p>
   <p>O house of Israel, cannot I doe with you, as this Potter,
saith the Lord? Behold as the clay is in the Pottershand, so
are yee in my hand, oh house of Israel. And after he adds
these words, vers. 7. I will speake sodeinly against a Nation
to plucke it vp, and to roote it out, and destroy it. vers. 8. But
if this Nation against whom I haue pronounced, turne from
their wickednesse, I will repent of the plague which I thought
to bring vpon them. vers. 9. And I will speake sodeinly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
a Nation &amp; concerning a Kingdome, to build it vp, &amp;
to plant it. vers. 10. But if it do euill in my sight, &amp; heare not
my voyce, I will repent of the good which I thought to doe for
them. vers. 11. Speake now therefore vnto the men of Iudah
and to the inhabitants of Ierusalem, saying, Thus saith the
Lord, Behold I prepare a plague for you, and purpose a thing
<pb facs="32"/>
against you. Returne now therefore euery one from his euill
way, and make your wayes and your workes good.</p>
   <p>To apply this to our selues:<note place="margin">Application.</note> Did not the Lord shew this
vnto vs much more visibly than he did vnto <hi>Ieremie;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Our destructiō shewed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished in effect.</note> That we
were all as the clay in his hand, that he had not onely power to
dash vs in peeces, but had in effect done it already; saue that
he did (as it were) create and forme vs againe of such a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,<note place="margin">Our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as a new creation.</note>
that we did all wonder at it; and all Nations shall haue
cause to wonder to the end of the world.</p>
   <p>How many wayes,<note place="margin">How many wayes, yea how sensibly &amp; sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly God hath spoken vnto vs may appeare in this whole worke.</note> yea how sensibly and suddenly God hath
spoken vnto vs all, (both proclayming by most infallible to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens,
that his anger is kindled against vs to the vttermost, and
that he is ready to powre out vpon vs the full viols of his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance:
and also on the other side declaring in all his long
forbearance and admirable d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>liuerances, how vnwilling he is
to proceede to the execution, if any other meanes might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime
vs) will euidently appeare to euery one, who with any
conscience or due consideration shall read that which followeth
in this vision.<note place="margin">Nothing can secure vs so as to giue vs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Lords Couenant.</note> And for that other maine point, That nothing
else can truly secure vs from the execution, so as to giue vs
true comfort, but our turning to the Lords Couenant; aske of
all the booke of God of all the places conteyning promises and
theeatnings to whole Nations; whether all the promises be not
made vnto our turning and obedient walking in his Couenant:
and all the threatnings after this manner;<note place="margin">Leuit. 26. 3, 23, 24.</note> That if we walke
more stubbornely against him, he will increase his vengeance
accordingly,<note place="margin">That all holy meanes are to be vsed therto.</note> and plague vs yet seuen times more. So that all
holy meanes are to be vsed to helpe to recall vs to the true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
of that his holy Couenant, that ech may renew the oath
of our obedience to Iesus Christ, for the happinesse of the
whole and of euery soule.<note place="margin">Euery soule who will not returne must die.</note> For God will haue vs all to know,
That whatsoeuer soule will not returne to his Couenant must
dye; it must die eternally. Yea though we liue not in a wilfull
reiecting of all the Couenant,<note place="margin">Ezec. 8. 10, 11.</note> but in any one abomination wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly:
on rary to the same; and much more doing it presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuously
that is, both wittingly and willingly, being warned
and convinced thereof, as the word is most direct. Yea if we
<pb facs="33"/>
doe not turne,<note place="margin">Yea all who seeke not to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>use others to tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ne.</note> and seeke to cause others to turne, chiefly all
those committed to our charge, we must dye. Onely that man
is a iust man, who doth iustice, and endeuours to walke in all
Gods statutes,<note place="margin">Iam 2. 10.</note> and to deale truly, turning and seeking to cause
others to turne,<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 10.</note> that man onely shall liue. Neuer any soule
shall haue any assurance to escape Gods vengeance,<note place="margin">Num. 15. 30, 31.</note> or haue
true boldnesse to appeare before the Lord,<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> but only such a man.<note place="margin">Ezech. 18. 30.</note>
Aske of the holy Scriptures,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18. 9.</note> whether this be not the tenour
of them all:<note place="margin">Who it is whō God accounts a iust man, which shal liue.</note> whether any other be a liuing member of Christ,
or haue any part in his bloud▪ or in that redemption wrought
by him.</p>
   <p>But aboue all,<note place="margin">All obstinate sinners helpe to draw downe vengeance vpō the whole land, beside the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying of their owne soules.</note> this is yet more dreadfull, that whosoeuer
they be, that liue in a wilfull breach of any part of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
of God, and chiefly those who wallow in any one of those
abominations which brought this captiuitie of Iudah, doe not
onely destroy their owne soules, without vnfeyned repentance,
but also doe helpe (so much as one mans sinne can doe) to draw
downe the vengeance of God vpon the whole Land to the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating
both of Church and Common-wealth that bred them.
Euery of our <hi>blasphemers, drunkards, whoremongers, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,
profane Sabaoth-breakers, despisers of the word of
the Lord,</hi> with all other notorious sinners, haue their hands
therein.<note place="margin">The Lord frō heauen cryes to vs all to turne, speaking,</note> Therefore the Lord from heauen speaks vnto vs all,
and cryes loud vnto vs to turne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nto him, that we may escape
his vengeance, He hath here in this vision set such a glasse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
our faces, as wherein we may behold our selues most liuely,
both our present and future estate, what he threatneth to doe
vnto vs.<note place="margin">3. To his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</note> Oh tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the vineyard of the Lord, he shewes vnto
thee that for thy vnfruitfulnes he is about to make thee waste!
You who are the fruitlesse branches behold your condition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
you must bring forth fruit speedily, or else be cut downe
and throwne into the euerlasting fire.<note place="margin">2▪ To all draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere to God with lips alone.</note> You who draw neere
vnto God with your lips in an outward profession, but your,
hearts are so far from him, that by your lines you giue occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
to his enemies to blaspheme his name; he shewes you here th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dgement that he hath prepared for you.<note place="margin">3. To oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors.</note> Open your eyes,
you cruell oppressors, you that flea the poore and needie, and
<pb facs="33"/>
behold here what the Lord is prouiding for you, and what
a destruction you are pulling vpon your owne heads.<note place="margin">4. To all giuen vp to all excess in pride and belly-cheere.</note> You
who spend all your time in pride, belly cheere, and all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse
of ryot, with abundance of idlenesse, neuer regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to strengthen the hands of the poore and needie, but
still to weaken them by plucking from them violently, see
whether you are rushing forward, bethinke your selues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it be too late.<note place="margin">5. All casting away the word of the Lord.</note> You who cast away the word of the Lord,
scorning and hating to be reformed by it, here the Lord fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnes
you what he is bringing vpon you. You that pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
his Sabaoths after the manner of the Gentiles,<note place="margin">6. Polluters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the Sabaoths.</note> to you
he himselfe speakes, that if you will not obserue his rest, he
will make the land to rest when it lyeth desolate, and no
man to passe thorow it.<note place="margin">Leuit. 26. 34.</note> Or that at the least your selues shall
be thrust forth from his eternall rest into the place of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
and crying, where you shall neuer haue rest day nor
night.</p>
   <p>All you who are outragious in your courses,<note place="margin">7. Outragious in their courses &amp; euil fashions.</note> and make the
euill fashions of all Countries about you, euen of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
of Christs Gospell and murtherers of his Saints, to be
your glory, you may here behold how you call in continually
these wicked enemies to auenge the Lords quarrell, and to
be the executioners of his most righteous iudgements vpon
you.<note place="margin">8. All turning backe to the Idolatrie of former times.</note> Oh you that are turning backe or hastning apace to
the vile Idolatrie of former dayes, which sometimes very
children abhorred in seeing the abomination of it: and all
you who would so faine be in Babel againe, you may here
take a view of the terrible vengeance of God vpon your
selues in such extreme blindnesse, and how you are drawing
in the bloudy Babylonian vpon your selues, and posteritie, and
euen the whole Land, so far as you are able, with as ill or a
worse captiuitie than euer came vpon Iudah; which how
neerely you had effected, your owne hearts are witnesses. Here
you may see how that one day alone of Babels crueltie, one of
their powder furnace dayes, shall be inough for you, at least
when you shall nish to stand a far off for feare of her torment:
whereof you are sure to haue your parts, if you will needs
<pb facs="34"/>
be partakers of her sinnes.<note place="margin">9. All challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Lord by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanesse and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme.</note> And you that by your intolerable
profanenesse and Atheisme doe seeme after a sort to challenge
the Lord to his face, to darè him, if he be a God, to shew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
and to hasten his vengeance, and so make your selues
merry with scoffing at all who feare his name, you may in this
heare the Lord himselfe telling you, as from heauen, that you
are the men, for whose cause he cannot spare, for whom he can
haue no more pittie, and that he will make you especially to
feele whether he be a God, a iust and terrible God or no.<note place="margin">All of vs may see y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Lord set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before vs the meanes w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he vsed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime vs and spare vs.</note> Here
finally we may all see the Lord himselfe setting before vs both
our generall and particular estate, with the meanes which he
hath vsed to reclaime and spare vs, the terrour of his anger
and plagues when no other meanes will serue. And lastly▪ the
way how yet we may be deliuered, and not onely be set free out
of the danger,<note place="margin">And how yet we may escape.</note> but also remaine a glorious Nation vntill his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
comming, and how euery one may escape his vengeance.</p>
   <p>Thorow out haue I striuen to shew my loue and earnest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire,<note place="margin">Here is no more but an endeuor to saue all,</note>
not onely to the whole, but also to saue euery soule from
these plague: Yet haue I not indeuoured any more herein
than the Angell for <hi>Lot</hi> in labouring to pull vs out of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction
remayning for the impenitent; nor any more than
<hi>Esay, Ieremie, Ezechiel,</hi> with other the Prophets and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> did before the Captiuitie, in seeking to
turne away that calamitie and all other their miseries from
them;<note place="margin">within the bounds of the word, and within the compasse of the calling of euery Man of God, as God offereth opportunitie &amp; holy meanes.</note> nor going past the bounds of the word of the Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
by those Prophets: Nor yet any more at all, than I take
to be the dutie of euery faithfull Minister and Man of God,
so far as the Lord shall offer him opportunitie, to seeke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
all from Gods wrath, and to plucke euery soule out of the
fire of his vengeance. And this by shewing all sorts their
sinnes, to bring them to repentance thereby, by haling &amp; draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to get euery <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> before the destruction
come.<note place="margin">Ezek. 18. 30, 32.</note>
   </p>
   <p>If any one shall be offended for the discouerie of his sinne
amongst the generall,<note place="margin">The offending of them who are asleepe in the midst of this perill not to be regard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d.</note> without the knowledge and sight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
he cannot be saued, and that onely because he would still
liue in it; or would not be awaked, his displeasure therein is no
<pb facs="34"/>
more to be regarded, than if one in an heauy sleep, in the midst
of an house all on fire about him, now ready to fall vpon his
head, to burne him to ashes: whom God shall enable to pull
forth any such, when he shall awake them and cause them to
see their danger wherein they were, and their gracious deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
then will they magnifie his great name,<note place="margin">They plucked forth will mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie God for vs.</note> that those did so
aduenture themselues for them, and esteeme such aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of the earth. And as for the displeasure of men, better
is it ten thousand times to haue all the world offended with
vs, for our labouring in loue and dutie in our place to saue,
and pull men from vnder Gods wrath, and forth of the very
pit of hell, so much as he shall vouchsafe vs mercy, than to
haue the Lord angry with vs,<note place="margin">Better to haue all men offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vs, than the Lord.</note> for being vnfaithfull in that
which hath beene committed vnto vs, and for neglecting to
saue his people from destruction. Oh what extreme foolishnes
is it to feare man,<note place="margin">Foolishnesse to feare men.</note> whose breath is in his nostrils, and whose
heart is in the Lords hand, to turne as the boates in the waters,
&amp; to incline as pleaseth him, who cānot moue a finger at vs but
by his permission, nor do any more than he wil turne to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> good;
and not to feare him,<note place="margin">Not to regard the horrour of Gods anger, on <hi>Moses Exo. 4. 24.</hi>
      </note> who if he be angry with vs neuer so little,
all our dayes are gone! Who would haue killed <hi>Moses</hi> for
omitting the circumcising of his childe; who brought the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest
on the sea, and would not suffer it to cease, vntill that
<hi>Ionah</hi> was throwne into it,<note place="margin">Ionah 1. 13.</note> because he prouided for his owne
peace, with neglect, or at least through feare of performance
of that dutie inioyned him, which was to goe to <hi>Niniue,</hi> to
preach vnto them, That within fortie dayes <hi>Niniue</hi> should be
destroyed.<note place="margin">Threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Ieremie 1. 17.</hi>
      </note> Who finally threatneth <hi>Ieremie</hi> to destroy him,
before the people, if he feare their faces: and will certainely
whip his dearest seruants▪ vnto his worke, if they begin to loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
We therefore,<note place="margin">Therefore Gods messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers had neede to looke to themselues▪ to help to saue all. To cause all to see his mercy in sparing vs.</note> who are Gods messengers, had neede to
looke vnto it, to indeuour so far as we may, keeping within our
limits, to pull all sorts of sinners with violence out of the fire;
and to striue to set their sinnes before their faces in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
colours. And the rather that so all of vs seeing the
heynousnesse of our owne sinnes, and of the sinnes of our Land,
may come to some more due consideration of the infinitenesse
<pb facs="35"/>
we did not vnderstand them, I take and hold it to be necessarie
still to try further all holy meanes:<note place="margin">Eccles. 12. 1.</note> we know not which the
Lord will blesse. Surely for the greatest part, the most plaine
is the most profitable.</p>
   <p>But if it shall be obiected,<note place="margin">The applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons so plaine to driue vs vnto Christ.</note> that the applications to the
particular kindes of sinnes and sinners are ouer plaine, and
come too neere the quicke. I answer againe, Blessed man is
he who can finde them to come neere to his owne corruption
and sinne.<note place="margin">Act: 2. 36, 37.</note> Is not this the onely way to driue vs to behold the
true brasen serpent,<note place="margin">Numb: 21. 9.</note> when we feele our selues stung at our
hearts?<note place="margin">Iohn 3. 14, 15.</note> Can euer any wretched sinner cry out, Men and
Brethren, what shall I doe, that I may be saued, vntill he
haue his soule thus pierced? Or can any fornicator, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
blasphemer, or any other notorious sinner, finde the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne
cōfort which is in Christs bloud, but only such a one?
Yet this I say vnto euery soule,<note place="margin">If any thing seem to pierce which is not Gods word, or it misapplied, it is no more to be feared than a dart of stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> that if any thing doe seeme
to pierce, which is not the word of the Lord, or is any way
misapplied, that it is not any more to be feared than darts of
stubble. But so far as it is his blessed word, &amp; following necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
out of the same, it will one day certainely wound vs, and
better here, whilest we may haue our wounds cured againe,
by applying that soueraigne remedie of the bloud of the Son
of God, than to be smitten thorow with it, when all hope
of cure is past, and so to haue our hearts galling vs and
vexing vs eternally.</p>
   <p>I therefore here doe also humbly beg of all the worthy
and faithfull seruants of the Lord,<note place="margin">The Authors humble desire to haue this brought to the tryall, and so to more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as all other his labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s.</note> as I haue in my former
labours, to helpe me to bring euery peece of this worke to
the tryall, for the full assurance of euery soule, who is desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
to see his euill way, and would escape the day of the
Lords wrath, or who would seeke to helpe to pacifie his wrath
kindled against vs. If there be in it any one sentence, which
is not either the word of the Lord, or not arising out of it,
and agreable thereto, that it may be reformed; or if it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray
the least partiall affection in leaning to any side, but to
the Lord, and to his manifest truth agreed vpon by vs all,
who soundly professe Christs Gospell; or the least false testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.
<pb facs="35"/>
Our most holy and blessed God, infinite in wisdome &amp;
power, needes not our lye to bring any of his to repentance,<note place="margin">God needs not our lye to bring his to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Iob 13. 7, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
      </note>
nor for setting forth of his glory. No, no, his owne word
is inough, and shall be found aboundantly sufficient to saue
all his elect, to destroy all his enemies, to deliuer his
Church, to get himselfe the victorie. I dare not wittingly
affirme one vntruth, no, not against the bloudie enemie,
nor against Sathan himselfe, no, nor yet wrong any creature
vnder heauen: farre be it from me to giue the Accuser that
aduantage. How then may I doe it for the cause of the Lord,
who abhorreth the very least iniquitie, and with whom no
euill can dwell.</p>
   <p>Moreouer sith all this,<note place="margin">The work ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing of our Couenant for the happinesse of vs and of our posteritie.</note> wholly tendeth to helpe towards
the making and establishing our peace with our God, by
seeking to recall vs all vnto his obedience, that we may
euery one renew our vow and couenant with him, for the
wealth of vs and our posteritie, I haue strictly kept my
selfe within the limits of the first part of this Watch, which
conteyneth the Summe of the Couenant of our God:<note place="margin">Limited within the bounds of the Watch, wherein we all agree.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
we all agree in outward profession, and vnto which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
returneth vnfeignedly to walke in the sincere obedience
of it, shall vndoubtedly haue eternall life: like as euery
impenitent transgressor against it,<note place="margin">For the breach whereof each impenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son stands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the generall verdit of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Christ. The desire of the Author to be a faithfull witnesse.</note> is certainely condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by the generall verdict of all the true Churches of
Christ.</p>
   <p>In all this worke I haue and doe instantly desire of the
Lord, that I may be a faithfull and true witnesse, both
for his heauenly Maiestie, and for his people; and also,
that I may shew in euery part, a right demonstration of
an vnfeigned loue to the Church of Christ, and towards
my Nation, euen to euery soule, for the sauing of ech from
the wrath to come; and withall that I may preserue the
honour due to all in autoritie, chiefly to the highest, to binde
all hearts to their superiours, ech to others, and all of vs to
Iesus Christ, That he may euer remaine our Captaine, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,
<pb facs="36"/>
King and Sauiour, euen he who will one day manifest
all the secrets of the hearts of men, who haue bin with him,
and who against him: who will come quickly, and
reward euery one as their workes shall be.
Amen,<note place="margin">Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c. 22. 20.</note> euen so, come
Lord Iesus.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>