<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his very louing friend and Mai∣ster,
Mr. William Durdant, and his
very friend Maister Francis Moore:
RICHARD WEST, wisheth all
health and happinesse.</title>
           <author>W., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106605_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14955</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25263</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106605</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his very louing friend and Mai∣ster,
Mr. William Durdant, and his
very friend Maister Francis Moore:
RICHARD WEST, wisheth all
health and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>W., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The court of conscience or Dick VVhippers sessions : VVith the order of his arraigning and punishing of many notorious, dissembling, wicked, and vitious liuers in this age. By Richard West</title>
                 <author>West, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To his very louing friend and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,
M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. William Durdant, and his
very friend Maister Francis Moore:
RICHARD WEST, wisheth all
health and happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any and sundry are the gifts and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents
which are sent betweene friend
and friend, of valew according to the
habilitie of the sender. Some present
gifts of great worth, as Plate, Iewels,
and such like, others meaner things.
My selfe finding my owne estate but of
a weake kinde, am bold insteed of such gifts, onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow
part of my braines fruite vpon you both, presuming
that it will be kindly receiued, though it be but of a small
moment or valew. By the one of you I assure my selfe (at
least am in good hope) it will bee kindly receiued as a
simple present from the Seruant to the Maister. The
other (in lue of many good turnes at your hands already
receiued, and not any way requited) I make the rather
bold to connex in the partaking of the same: humblie
requiring you to be a kinde of Side-men in the assisting
<pb facs="5"/>
of <hi>Dick Whipper</hi> and his Iewrie in this session to ayde
them with your iudgements in the pronouncing the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
of condemnation against the malefactors at the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignement,
hauing and being of that opinion, that you
will not onely iudge without partialitie at this time, but
also be ready in your foynes to attend the iudge, at the
next Court day, when I beleeue a greater malefaector will
be brought in, then the worst of these: In the meane
time Ile bespeake a new whip which shall
stick close to his sides as euer
his shirt did.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in any seruice:
R. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>