<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>GENTLE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106585_Bo2_1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04361</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14475</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106585</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>GENTLE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theater of Iaponia's constancy : in which an hundred &amp; eighteene glorious martyrs suffered death for Christ, in the yeare of our Lord 1622. Also, a briefe relation of the many, and wonderfull miracles, it hath pleased God lately to worke, by the merits and intercessio of S. Ignatius, founder of the Society of Iesus, at Munebrega a towne in Spayne, in the moneths of Aprill and May, of the yeare 1623. Both faithfully translated out of Spanish originalls, lately printed at Madrid</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>47, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="28" facs="15"/>
   <head>GENTLE READER.</head>
   <p>This former Relation, or briefe History, was wrytten from <hi>Nangasachi</hi> and <hi>Firandum</hi> (two principall Citties of <hi>Iaponia,</hi> where most of the foresaid Christians suffered death) vnto <hi>Manila,</hi> the Chiefe Citty of the <hi>Philippine</hi> Ilands, by such as were present at the Martyrdoms themselues; and from thence very authentically sent into <hi>Spaine,</hi> to diuers persons there of Credit and Authority: VVhere the same was first published in print at <hi>Madrid,</hi> &amp; afterward at <hi>Seuill,</hi> &amp; other places; and since translated into Latin, and printed at <hi>Bruxells</hi> in <hi>Brabant;</hi> and also into French, and printed in diuers Citties, both of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countreyes,</hi> with licence and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, requisite for the Truth of so notable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable an Accident.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>