<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO HIS BOOKE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106077_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10718</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20998</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106077</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO HIS BOOKE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A right exelent and pleasaunt dialogue, betwene Mercury and an English souldier : contayning his supplication to Mars: bevvtified with sundry worthy histories, rare inuentions, and politike deuises. wrytten by B. Rich: gen. 1574</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Disle (Disley, Dizle), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO HIS BOOKE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WHy shouldest y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> make such hast abroad to be,</l>
      <l>a meane wherby to purchace me defame:</l>
      <l>Yet mightest thou still abyde and stay with me,</l>
      <l>and I therby remayne deuoyd of blame:</l>
      <l>But if I once permit thee scope to trudge,</l>
      <l>I know not I, what euery man will iudge.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>The booke to the Author.</head>
      <l>
         <hi>VVhat doubtes be these that thus doth dul thy braine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>or what conceiptes doth yet thy mynd pursue:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>I know no cause thou shouldst me thus restraine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>but geue me scope to such as list to vow:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Then they no doubt, will thank thee for thy payne,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>as I suppose thou seekest no greater gayne.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>The Author.</head>
      <l>I craue no more in deed, but the good will</l>
      <l>of such, as shall thy simple sence behold:</l>
      <l>But this I doubt my rude and slender skil,</l>
      <l>may geue them cause to iudge me ouer bold:</l>
      <l>So I in steed of thanks may purchace blame,</l>
      <l>so vayne a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oy to set forth in my name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>The Booke.</head>
      <l>
         <hi>And who so redy euer fault to fynde,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>as witlesse head, that least of all doth know:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For none so bold they say, as bayerd blynd,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>nor none more riefe their doultish domes to show:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>VVher wyse men yet will deeme thy doings right,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>what carst thou then for Zoylus cankerd spight.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>The Author.</head>
      <l>Well yet my booke, I geue thee this in charge,</l>
      <l>the maners marke of such as thee peruse:</l>
      <l>If thou perceiuest their tonges do run at large,</l>
      <l>in fynding fault the Author to accuse,</l>
      <l>Tell thou them then, I ment not to offend,</l>
      <l>what they mislike, desire them they wold mend</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>And thus farevvell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>