<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ALEXANDRAEAN TRAGEDIE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106640_Fr3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106640</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ALEXANDRAEAN TRAGEDIE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Recreations vvith the Muses : By William Earle of Sterline</title>
                 <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 253, 5, 326, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="111" facs="62"/>
   <head>THE ALEXANDRAEAN <hi>TRAGEDIE.</hi>
   </head>
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>hen <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, after all his Conquests (shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the glory of innumerable victories) was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe to <hi>Babylon,</hi> where the Ambassadours of the whole world did attend his coming, as one who was expected to command over all: there, being admired by the <hi>Grecians,</hi> adored by the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and as it were drunk with the delights of an extraordinary prosperity, he suffered himselfe to be transported with an inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pleasure; till sitting at one of his feasts by the meanes of the sonne of <hi>Antipater,</hi> one of his Cup-beares, in the best both of his age and fortune, he was suddenly poysoned.</p>
   <p>Incontinent after his death, those who were in greatest estimation with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe daring his life, and then with the Armie, assembled themselves together neglecting for a long time his funerals, whilest busied about the disposing of his Empire: at last (after divers opinions) it was concluded, that if <hi>Roxane,</hi> the widow of their Soveraigne, (who was then at the point to be delivered of her birth) happened to beare a sonne, he should succeed in his Fathers place, and till he were come to some maturity of age, <hi>Perdiccas, Leonatus, Crate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and <hi>Antipater</hi> were appointed to be his Tutors: But the foot-men in a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, that their advice was not required, proclaimed <hi>Arideus, Alexanders</hi> bastard brother, King, and gave him a guard, of which <hi>Meleager</hi> procured himselfe to be made Captaine. At this sudden alteration, the horse-men being troubled, following <hi>Perdiccas,</hi> pitched their Camp without the City, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the end, this tumult being by the eloquence of <hi>Perdiccas</hi> appeased, all the Captains re-assembled themselves, and having divided the Provinces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ade an agreement, which lasted not long.</p>
   <p>For, such was the vehement ambition of those great men, that with all manner of hostility, they studied how to undermine one another, and first of all <hi>Meleager</hi> after a pretende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> recon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>on tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ig <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ple for refuge) was slaine by the appointment of <hi>Perdiccas,</hi> who (after aspiring to a superiority over the rest) whilest he went to warre against <hi>Prolomie</hi> in <hi>Eagypt,</hi> by a sudden mutiny of his owne Souldiers, was miserably murdered. Then the onely Captaine of his faction who remained alive, was <hi>Eumenes,</hi> a man singularly valorous, who encountring with <hi>Craterus</hi> and <hi>Neoptole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> by the death of themselves defeated their Army, whereby being highly advanced, he was greatly envied: and (<hi>Leonatus</hi> having lately before dyed in a conflict betwixt him and the <hi>Athenians.</hi>) <hi>Antigonus</hi> in the nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="112" facs="63"/>the rest, was sent against him with a great Army, betwixt whom there having passed divers skirmishes with a variable successe, and some private confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence without agreement: In the end, he was betrayed by his owne Souldiers, and delivered bound to <hi>Antigonus,</hi> who shortly after caused to take his life.</p>
   <p>Then <hi>Antigonus</hi> (his rivals in the authoritie being removed out of his way) did aspire to that himselfe, from which he was sent to seclude others, and having murdered divers of the governours, he disposed of their Provinces as he pleased: whereof <hi>Cassander, Ptolomie,</hi> and <hi>Lysimachus,</hi> advertised by <hi>Seleucus,</hi> who fled for feare of incurring the like danger; did enter together in a league against <hi>Antigonus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now at this time <hi>Olympias</hi> plagued all the faction of <hi>Cassander</hi> in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonie,</hi> having caused <hi>Arideus</hi> and his Queen <hi>Eurydice</hi> to be put to death; by which, and by some other cruelties (having lost the favour of the people) she was constrained, when <hi>Cassander</hi> came against her, to retyre her selfe within a Town; which (by reason of the scarcitie of victuals (not being able to defend) she rendered, together with her selfe to <hi>Cassander,</hi> by whom notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his promise to the contrary) she was violently deprived of life, and so having proceeded so farre in wickednesse, he thought it no time to retyre till he had extinguished all his Masters race; whereupon he caused <hi>Roxane</hi> and her sonne to be murthered, and soone after, <hi>Hercules, Alexanders</hi> bastard sonne; which multitude of murthers, gave to him the Crowne of <hi>Macedonie,</hi> and to me the subject of this Polytragicke Tragedie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>