<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>F., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106700_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00738</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106700</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>F., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>French court-aires, vvith their ditties Englished, of foure and fiue parts : Together with that of the lute. Collected, translated, published by Ed: Filmer, Gent: dedicated to the Queene</title>
                 <author>Guédron, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough, in the highest times of the most Imperiall Citie of the World, Literature and Musicke were counted the two Mentall Touchstones of a Gentleman (for Wrast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was held but a Corporall one, and therefore, by the Comicke reciting the parts fit for a Gentleman, put in the last place: <hi>Fac periculum in Literis, in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicis, in Palaestra</hi>) yet sole Scholler or Musician, vnlesse eleuated by Academicall Degrees, are held now but Lowe and <hi>Illiberall</hi> Conditions. So that a <hi>Nihilegregiè,</hi> or a <hi>Nequid nimis</hi> is that which preserues such, as are hereunto addicted, in a freedome requisite to Gentilitie, which ought to bee Slaue neither to Booke nor Fiddle. Farre therefore from a desire of testifying that my endeuours in these kinds haue soared aboue the pitch of mediocritie, I here expose to the vsers of my Naturall Tongue this small Labour, as whereby may onely be discouered a Gentle <hi>tincture</hi> of my mind in either, but a Deep <hi>die</hi> in neither of the fore-named Qualities. For, touching the Musicall part of this Booke, I haue onely exercised my <hi>Iudicatiue</hi> strength in the Choice and Collection of the Aires, which is not sufficient to raise on a man the surname of Musician: and, for the Literature or Poetrie of the Ditties, I haue no more then new-colour'd their Forme, by chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their Language, I haue not inuented the subiect, or Made the matter; wherein consists the maine Essence of a Poet, as being the Worke from whence he receiues more properly his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> τὸ Ποιεῖν, then from the Making of a Verse. In so much that hee that traceth a Chronicle sincerely, without any fabulous mixture, may rather be called a Versifying Historian, then a Poet; as not sufficiently shaping himselfe to the fashion of the great and ancient Masters of the Art, that first set-vp the name of Poet. — <hi>Pictoribus at{que} Poetis Quidlibet audendi semper fuit aequa potestas;</hi> neither of them being tied to the Patterne of Truth, but left free to the Reach of Inuention. Nor doe I here labour to shift-of, as ignominious, the gracefull Titles of Poet or Musi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, which Persons farre higher then my selfe haue accepted-of as Ornaments to their other Merits; my purpose being onely to acknowledge, that my sparing diligences and few retir'd houres employ'd these Wayes haue in no wise effected, that I may, without vanitie, either sue for, or admit-of these Names, that I vnfainedly gratulate to such as haue purchased them with Surpassing Desert. —<hi>mediocribus esse Poetis Non homines, non Dij, non concessere columnae.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, for the Worke its selfe, whereunto the Muses haue bee'n assistant with their double Skill (which the two-topp'd Mountaine they inhabit may bee thought to point-at) I meane Musicke and Poetrie, as I confesse that I haue bee'n, generally, more taken with the Musicall part then the Poeticall; so I acknowledge to haue tied my selfe more strictly to the presentation thereof (without swaruing from the first publish'd Copie either in flourish or substance) then of the Other; wherein I haue, sometime, suffered as well my Fant'sie as Reason to thrust mee a little from a punctuall insisting in the Steps of the Originall: vpon what Motiues (or perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture Necessitie) I leaue to the likely coniectures of the judicious Comparer to find-out; hauing held it more workemanlike, vpon well-taken occasions, by a justifiable varying from the Phrase, without losse of the Plot and Scope of the Author, so to translate, that the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later may be said to haue some little share in the Apparell and Dresse, though not in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, of the worke, then (with a Schoole-boyes resolution) to dare to aime no further then at such an interpretation, as may render the most exact account, that may bee, of the <hi>Syntax</hi> of the Originall. Indeed, where <hi>Poems</hi> are chosen to bee translated for no other respect then for their owne eminent and know'n worth, it can sauour of no lesse then presuming selfe-conceit to straine, with new Flashes, to out-shine the primitiue Beames of the Originall; or to intimate a waterish vnsauorinesse in the translated Matter, by sprinkling the Translation with frequent Graines of the Translaters peculiar Salt. But, where Lines are not so much turned into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Language for their owne, as for the Musickes sake that they belong-to and (in a manner) serue, I cannot absolutely conclude, but that the Translat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> may, without the blot of inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, carrie himselfe with a Looser regard to those Pieces of his Patterne that hee shall judge himselfe least Obliged vnto. —<hi>&amp;, quae Desperat tractata nitescere posse, relinquit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, because translated Ditties and Originals differ chiefly in this Preposterous Point, that, whereas the Musicall Notes are fitted to the Originals, the Translations are, contrarily, to be fitted to the Musicall Notes, I haue bee'n forced, by this new Taske, for the more euen Accord with the Musicke, in diuers Aires, to alter the Naturall first Cast of the Verse, and to ordaine, in the proper place of an <hi>Iambicke</hi> Foot, a dissonant <hi>Trochaicke,</hi> as more sutable to the nature of the Note. For this cause, when the most busie Examiners shall, in some of the Ditties, find heere and there <hi>Iambicke</hi> Meeters that seeme to faulter in their Pace, through the vnlawfull frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Trochaicke</hi> Motions, let them forbeare Censure, till they haue tried them with the Streame
<pb facs="4"/> of the Aire or Note; which, though it were blamelesly enough by the Composer adapted to the <hi>French</hi> Verse, yet, now and then, fals out to make a Currant <hi>English</hi> Verse of the same Numbers to runne, as it were, against the Biasse. The reason is, because the <hi>French</hi> syllables, as well in Verse as Prose, are pronounced with a more Continu'd Equalitie of sound, then ours. For that Tongue admits seldome of any Tones or Intentions of the Voice (by Grammatians called Accents) vnlesse at the End of the Clause, or in the <hi>penultims</hi> of words ending in their <hi>c foeminine.</hi> And this their Mother-pronunciation they often apply euen to the <hi>Latine,</hi> and other <hi>acquired</hi> Tongues. From whence it is not vnlikely, that some of them, hauing bee'n ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished by Strangers of this their Vnrulinesse, haue not stucke to maintaine their <hi>dysprosodia</hi> (that I may so call it) or immodulation of the seuerely gouern'd Syllables of the <hi>Latine:</hi> as may appeare by that <hi>grauely</hi>-accented or rather vnaccented and indistinguish'd Piece father'd vpon them <hi>Nòs-Gàllì-nòn-cùràmùs-quàntìtàtém-syllàbàrúm;</hi> erroneously thinking that way of Pronunciation to be Common to Other Tongues, which seemes Proper to their Owne; the Nerues of whose Syllables (in Singing)-neither Crampe of vnnaturall <hi>correption,</hi> nor Racke of vnvsuall <hi>production</hi> can much Torture. Hence therefore it proceeds, that the <hi>French,</hi> when they Compose to a Dittie in their owne Language, being led rather by their free Fant'sie of Aire (wherein many of them doe naturally excell) then by any Strict and Artificiall scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Line, by which they Build, doe often, by disproportion'd Musicall Quantities, inuert the naturall Stroke of a Verse, applying to the place of an <hi>Iambicke</hi> Foot, such Modula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as Iumps rather with a <hi>Trochay.</hi> And this without much violence to their <hi>Poems,</hi> since the Disorder and Confusion of <hi>metricall</hi> Feet in their Verse is as Inoffensiue as Indiscernible, by reason, as is afore-said, of the Euen Pronunciation of Their Tongue: whereas Ours, more frequent and liuely in Accenting all <hi>polysyllables,</hi> bewrayes presently to the Eare, by Our best Measure, the Accent, the Contrarietie betweene the <hi>Trochay</hi> and the <hi>Iambicke.</hi> Now therefore, when the Note, fitted for a <hi>Trochay</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> lights vpon an <hi>Iambicke</hi> in <hi>English,</hi> it strangely Wrests the relucting Syllables from their <hi>genuine</hi> Pronunciation, and changes the Friendly and Equall Conspiring, that ought to be betweene Word and Tune, into Injurious Contradiction; which vnseemely Variance often breakes forth into so lowd a <hi>Cacophonie,</hi> that, thereby, the one seemes to doe no lesse then Reuile the other. In respect whereof, the intent of this Booke being more to please the <hi>Iudicious</hi> Hearer of the Tunes, then the <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Reader of the Lines, I haue chosen rather, wittingly, to tolerate a little roughnesse in the Fluencie of some of the Verses, thereby the lesse to disrellish the Musicke, then, by an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious straining to please in that Part of the worke that concernes my selfe, neglect the better Part, the prayse whereof I am farre from colour of pretending the least Right vnto. Yet herein also I dare not auouch to haue bee'n so <hi>anxious</hi> an Obseruer of the Lawes of the Note in all places, as to distemper the Verse vpon euery slight Becke thereof, but, where I haue thought the Lightnesse of the <hi>dissonancie</hi> might the most easily bee Digested by Good Eares, I haue sometimes permitted the Meeters to March forward with their most decent Steps, without Respect or Obcisance to the Musicall Measure discouer'd in the Face of the Note, to the end that the Poeticall Reader might find the lesse whereat to Trip or be Offended; hauing endeauoured, in this Doubtfull and Distracting Case, to make the Worke as little Scandalous as I could, either to the Grammaticall or Musicall Pervser.</p>
   <p>In conclusion; that I may not too much Disproportion this small Building, by making the Porch of Preface too Bigge to correspond with the Little Roomes within, my moderate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires are, that my Home hearted vnaffectating Countrie-men, Fauourers and Practizers of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, would courteously entertaine this Recopilation as a Worke naturaliz'd chiefly for their sakes; and, whereas our Tailors Shops and Dancing-schooles haue bee'n so employ'd in <hi>French</hi> Imitations, that our more deseruing Masters of Musicke might sometimes, for pleasing No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties sake, daigne to repaire hither for Life of Aire worthy of their more noble Arts Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. And, as for some Rouing Spirits, whose Transitorie View of <hi>France</hi> may haue mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified them with the Scumme onely and Froathie top of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, without diuing into the substantiall Depth by a more piercing diligence therein, I am patiently prouided to heare them Counterblast these my Endeauours with this Airie Position: That it is impossible that any Words but <hi>French</hi> should euer Become the <hi>Loouer</hi> Aires (though they themselues, besides vnderstanding them but to halues, pronounce them to a naturall <hi>French</hi> Eare as Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomingly as euer Crude Forrainer was heard to sing an <hi>English</hi> Ballet) such is the aptnesse of halfe-digested Noueltie to breed in the Stomackes of our yong Countrie-men a Queasie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spising of the, almost-matchlesse, Abilities of their owne Language. But, because I haue learn'd among People of sound Tasts, that, <hi>Contra Gustos no ay que disputar,</hi> There is no disputing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Tasts, I will abstaine to play the ignorant Logician by attempting to raise Arguments on a <hi>Theme</hi> held <hi>Improbable;</hi> but rather, somewhat to gratifie their depraued Palates, haue
<pb facs="4"/> annexed the <hi>French</hi> Ditties in the end of the Booke; by the same meanes testifying, to the skilfull in both Tongues, my integritie (as farre as is formerly professed) in their Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Hauing hazarded to breake the yce to abler pennes, whose happier facultie in this kind may hereafter incite them, with some more rich <hi>English</hi> lining of other <hi>French</hi> pieces of this Musicall stuffe, to venture-for and winne the applause of my indegenerating Countrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Whose present acceptance of the homely threed here prepared to measure these first withall, shall fortifie mee against the future assaults of repentance.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>