<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVE DIS∣couerer of secrets Mounsieur Bacchus, sole Soueraigne of the Iuy-bush, Master-gunner of the pottle-pot ordinance, prime founder of Red lat∣tices, cheerer of the hunger-staru'd Muses, and their thred bare followers, singuler Artist in pewter language, and an obser∣uant linguist for anon anon Sir.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106309_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16682</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3588</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106309</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVE DIS∣couerer of secrets Mounsieur Bacchus, sole Soueraigne of the Iuy-bush, Master-gunner of the pottle-pot ordinance, prime founder of Red lat∣tices, cheerer of the hunger-staru'd Muses, and their thred bare followers, singuler Artist in pewter language, and an obser∣uant linguist for anon anon Sir.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A strappado for the Diuell : Epigrams and satyres alluding to the time, with diuers measures of no lesse delight. By Misosukos, to his friend Philokrates</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Redmer, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 234, 8, 104, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerer of secrets Mounsieur <hi>Bacchus,</hi> sole Soueraigne of the Iuy-bush, Master-gunner of the pottle-pot ordinance, prime founder of Red lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, cheerer of the hunger-staru'd Muses, and their thred bare followers, singuler Artist in pewter language, and an obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant linguist for anon anon Sir.</head>
   <head type="sub">His dere-Canary-Bird, wisheth, red-eyes, dropsie legges, and all other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrements befitting.</head>
   <l>BOttle-nos'd <hi>Bacchus</hi> with thy bladder face,</l>
   <l>To thee my <hi>Muse</hi> comes reeling for a place:</l>
   <l>And craues thy Patronage; nor do I feare,</l>
   <l>But my poore fragments shall be made of there,</l>
   <l>For good reuersions by thy scrambling crew,</l>
   <l>That belch, and reade, and at each enteruiew</l>
   <l>Of a sharpe temper'd line, commend the vaine,</l>
   <l>Digest it, and then rift it vp againe;</l>
   <l>But know thou cup shot god, what is exprest,</l>
   <l>Within these Pages doe deserue the best</l>
   <l>Of thy light-headed Shamroes, nor's my tutch</l>
   <l>For such as loue to take a cup too-much.</l>
   <l>No, no my lines (though I did seeme to stand,</l>
   <l>And begge a poore protection at thy hand,)</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="2" facs="9"/>Shall liue in spite of Time, for Time shall see</l>
   <l>The curtaine of her vices drawne by me;</l>
   <l>And though portraide by a lesse art-full fist,</l>
   <l>Yet he that limm'd them is a Satyrist,</l>
   <l>For th'lines he writes (if ought he write at all)</l>
   <l>Are drawne by inke that's mixed most with gall.</l>
   <l>Yea, he was borne, euen from his infancie,</l>
   <l>To tell the world her shame, and bitterly</l>
   <l>To taxe those crimes which harbour now and then</l>
   <l>Within the bosomes of the greatest men.</l>
   <l>" Yea, nought I doe but I againe will doe it,</l>
   <l>" Nor ought will write, but I will answer to it:</l>
   <l>Yet would I not, great <hi>Bacchus,</hi> haue thee thinke</l>
   <l>My <hi>Muse</hi> can into that obliuion sinke,</l>
   <l>As to become forgetfull so of thee,</l>
   <l>(For so she might vnthankfull seeme to be)</l>
   <l>As neuer to record thy worthy Name</l>
   <l>Since I confesse from thee that spirit came,</l>
   <l>Which first inspir'd my <hi>Muse</hi> (by thee exprest)</l>
   <l>For when she spoke the least, she wrot the best.</l>
   <l>Yea, thou it was, (and so Ile euer hold,)</l>
   <l>That quickned me and made me speake more bold;</l>
   <l>By that rare quintessence drawne from the pine,</l>
   <l>Or from those fluent Hogges-head pipes of thine.</l>
   <l>And I doe thanke thee: yet thus much Ile say,</l>
   <l>For any kindnesse showne me anie waie,</l>
   <l>By thee, or thy attendants, I may sweare</l>
   <l>Not any one did euer yet appeare:</l>
   <l>Nay, I could say (and truly too) far more</l>
   <l>I neuer ran ten shillings on thy skore,</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="3" facs="9"/>Which may seem strange, that I which am so grown</l>
   <l>Into acquaintance, and to thee well knowne:</l>
   <l>"Should in thy booke haue such a diffidence,</l>
   <l>As not be chalkt for want of ready pence;</l>
   <l>Nay, there's an other reason I could shew,</l>
   <l>Which might infer that thou dost duty owe</l>
   <l>To men of our profession, and its this;</l>
   <l>(If my conceipt make me not thinke amisse.)</l>
   <l>Tell me, Where hadst thou Iuie-bush, say where?</l>
   <l>Which as thine ancient liv'rie thou dost weare;</l>
   <l>That garland-sure me-thinks that I should know it,</l>
   <l>From th'Temples sure of some pot-hardy Poet;</l>
   <l>Who, cause he had not wherewithall to pay,</l>
   <l>VVas forc't to leaue his Garland, or to stay</l>
   <l>Till some of's Patrons pittied his estate:</l>
   <l>But he, poore man, cleere out of hope of that</l>
   <l>Hauing discust it often in his minde,</l>
   <l>Did think't more fit to leaue his wreath behinde,</l>
   <l>Then into such apparant danger fall,</l>
   <l>And so did vnto one of th'Drawers call</l>
   <l>To tell thee, if thou would'st be so content,</l>
   <l>He would engage his Iuie-ornament;</l>
   <l>Which thou being glad of, for thy priuate vse</l>
   <l>Wore it thy selfe and cheat'd the Poet thus.</l>
   <l>Now doest thou thinke, that we can brooke to haue</l>
   <l>One of our sort thus iniur'd by a slaue,</l>
   <l>Without all satisfaction: <hi>Bacchus</hi> no,</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes, we'le not be baffelt so.</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> of thy bush againe,</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> thy wreath about the Poets braine.</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="4" facs="10"/>Or satisfie his damage in some sort,</l>
   <l>"Or be thou sure that thou shalt answer for't.</l>
   <l>But thou wilt lightly weigh such threats as these,</l>
   <l>And say thou canst bring vs vpon our knees</l>
   <l>By th'power of thy commaund: true thou canst so,</l>
   <l>Yet (bleere ey'de <hi>Bacchus</hi>) I would haue thee know</l>
   <l>That we do so esteeme thy power and all</l>
   <l>Thy followers, we'le vent thee' gainst the wall:</l>
   <l>Yea euen the kennell shall a witnesse be,</l>
   <l>Of the small respect which we do beare to thee.</l>
   <l>Resigne then what thou owest, or forbeare,</l>
   <l>To taxe our credits when our skore's not cleere.</l>
   <l>For well may'st thou forbeare both them and me,</l>
   <l>Since thou dost owe vs more, then we owe thee.</l>
   <l>Thou know'st it <hi>Bacchus</hi> (if so thou wilt knowe it)</l>
   <l>That garland which thou weares, it was a Poet</l>
   <l>That first empaund it, and thou like a Iewe</l>
   <l>VVilt not restore to him what is his due.</l>
   <l>But thou wilt answer (as I know thou may)</l>
   <l>Yea, I imagine what tis thou canst say:</l>
   <l>" Bacchus cares not for outward signes a rush,</l>
   <l>" Good wine needs not the hanging of a bush.</l>
   <l>Dost not thou vizzard-fac't ingratefull Elfe?</l>
   <l>Yes, for want of a bush thou'd hang thy selfe.</l>
   <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aper like a zuinglian (ô my malice</l>
   <l>Bursts out against thee) titted vnder the gallowes.</l>
   <l>For tell me how should men distinguish thee?</l>
   <l>Thou'lt say by thy fire-sparkling phisnomie,</l>
   <l>Those wink-a pipes of thine, those ferret eies,</l>
   <l>Those bag-pipe cheeks, those speciall qualities</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="5" facs="10"/>Thou art endew'd with true by th'first th'art known,</l>
   <l>But for thy qualities thou hast not one</l>
   <l>To glory in: for speeches ornament</l>
   <l>Anon, anon sit: — peut or complement</l>
   <l>Is all thou canst, and this, thou knowest is such,</l>
   <l>As th'Iay or Parrat they can doe as much;</l>
   <l>But I am loath to taxe each crime of thine,</l>
   <l>For I do know thou lou'st the <hi>Muses</hi> nine,</l>
   <l>And they loue thee, yet it is fit their vs'd</l>
   <l>With more respect, then to be once abus'd</l>
   <l>By any apron-prentice that thou hast:</l>
   <l>Yea, fit it is not they should be out-fac't</l>
   <l>By such vnletterd Animals as these,</l>
   <l>But reuerence the <hi>Muses</hi> on their knees,</l>
   <l>For what be these attend thee, such as lost</l>
   <l>Their tongue to gaine two or three words at most,</l>
   <l>As for example neate and briske, and then</l>
   <l>Anon, anon sir, welcome gentlemen.</l>
   <l>And is it fit that swads of such desert</l>
   <l>Should stay the very quintessence of art</l>
   <l>For a non-payment? or make Sergeants stand</l>
   <l>In a crosse-lane to laie vnhallowed hand</l>
   <l>On <hi>Albions Mercuries?</hi> no, its not fit</l>
   <l>That <hi>Hypocrenes</hi> pure riuelings of wit,</l>
   <l>Should haue their streame with honour doubled)</l>
   <l>By such base tenter-hooks once troubled.</l>
   <l>Let this be then amended (and with haste)</l>
   <l>Lest some of these professors should be plac't,</l>
   <l>Before thy prohibition come to stay</l>
   <l>Thy will-for in, they'le hardlie get awaie.</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="6" facs="11"/>But if I heare thee <hi>Bacchus</hi> after this</l>
   <l>That thou arrests but any one I wish</l>
   <l>Thou should'st exempt I will reuenged be</l>
   <l>Ere many daies, of some of thine or thee.</l>
   <l>And thanks vnto my Genius (as I craue it)</l>
   <l>Without inuention further now I haue it.</l>
   <l>And thus it is: Ile to the Peuterer</l>
   <l>To make thy quart pots greater then they were;</l>
   <l>And so condition with him, as't may be</l>
   <l>Thou wilt confesse one day I begar'd thee:</l>
   <l>Or if I cannot by my meanes intreate</l>
   <l>Thy pottle-pots for to be made more great</l>
   <l>Then th'order is, or th'Citties stampe allowes,</l>
   <l>I hope I shall preuaile wih some of those</l>
   <l>Who are appointed by their charge to know,</l>
   <l>Whether thy pots be sealed yea or no,</l>
   <l>That such as are not seal'd they would reueale them,</l>
   <l>And not take bribes in priuate to conceale them:</l>
   <l>Or if this will not serue, I will deuise</l>
   <l>How to bring th'potts vnto a larger size;</l>
   <l>Which if they do neglect but to performe,</l>
   <l>According to that Nature and that forme</l>
   <l>They are prescrib'd, then on default they shall</l>
   <l>Make presently a forfeiture of all,</l>
   <l>(Which goods confiscate for their great abuse,</l>
   <l>May afterward redound vnto the vse</l>
   <l>Of all such noble skinkers (by confession)</l>
   <l>As were deceiv'd by men of this profession;</l>
   <l>But this's not all Ile doe: <hi>Bacchus</hi> shall knowe</l>
   <l>His naprie-drawers shall not end it so.</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="7" facs="11"/>Surueighers shall be-gett (and well may be)</l>
   <l>(For worser trades haue sought <hi>monopolye</hi>;</l>
   <l>And rais'd their state by't) which shall strictly take</l>
   <l>Examination, whether you do make</l>
   <l>Your pottles to be bruis'd, bough'd, crusht, &amp; bent</l>
   <l>Vpon set purpose and for this intent,</l>
   <l>That you thereby (which is a common crime)</l>
   <l>Might fill your crazie pots with lesser wine,</l>
   <l>For lesser will they hold, through your deceit,</l>
   <l>Being drawne in and made by you more straite:</l>
   <l>Yet haue I left the Coopers all this while,</l>
   <l>Which I do know haue some art to beguile.</l>
   <l>And therefore, if all will not serue; Ile seeke</l>
   <l>And bribe them too, to make your vessels leeke.</l>
   <l>Yea, beside this (know <hi>Bacchus</hi>) I'ue a meane,</l>
   <l>Which put in practice will vndoe thee cleane,</l>
   <l>And thus I lay my proiect: Ile expresse</l>
   <l>What motiues there be of licentiousnesse.</l>
   <l>Within thy brothel closures, and with-all</l>
   <l>Complaine of thy partitions, how the fall</l>
   <l>Of many a simple Virgine (though shee's loath,</l>
   <l>To do't poore-wench) coms from a painted cloath▪</l>
   <l>A curtaine, or some hanging of like sort,</l>
   <l>Which done god-wot, they'ue cause to curse thee for't.</l>
   <l>And that this might better preuented be,</l>
   <l>I will prefer petition instantly,</l>
   <l>That thou nor none of thine should suffer thence,</l>
   <l>(for to auoide this inconuenience)</l>
   <l>Any of different sexes being but payres,</l>
   <l>To goe in priuate manner vp the staires:</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="8" facs="12"/>And this I know (if that my aime be right,</l>
   <l>VVill goe well nie to ouerthrow thee quite.</l>
   <l>If none of these will doe, yet sure I am</l>
   <l>There is a creature call'd the Puritan,</l>
   <l>Who'le ferret thee, and by a strict surueigh</l>
   <l>Fine thee for bouzing on the Sabboath day,</l>
   <l>VVhich if they finde, the <hi>Righteous</hi> they will curse</l>
   <l>Though their example it be ten times worse.</l>
   <l>But I would haue thee to represse all this,</l>
   <l>VVhich thou shalt do by doing what I wish,</l>
   <l>And that with reason, which (as I haue sayd it)</l>
   <l>Is but to giue to our profession credit:</l>
   <l>They'le pay the man, and if the world goe hard,</l>
   <l>VVith them at this time, yet they 'le afterward,</l>
   <l>Regratulate thy loue (paying th'old sko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e)</l>
   <l>VVhich paide they will make bolde to run on more.</l>
   <l>For tell me <hi>Bacchus,</hi> though the world appeare</l>
   <l>To learned men as if no learning were:</l>
   <l>And that the golden age (not as it was)</l>
   <l>Smiles on the silken foole, or golden Asse;</l>
   <l>Yet time will come (yea now it doth begin</l>
   <l>To shew it selfe (as former times haue been)</l>
   <l>VVhen wise <hi>Minerua</hi> shall no honour lacke.</l>
   <l>For all the foole, whose honour's on his backe.</l>
   <l>But I shall stagger <hi>Bacchus</hi> if I stay</l>
   <l>Longer with thee, therefore Ile packe awaie</l>
   <l>Vnto thy sister <hi>Ceres:</hi> —I haue sayd</l>
   <l>— Onely looke to thy plate, for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l is paide.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>