<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VER∣TVOVS AND WOR∣THIE KNIGHT SIR IOHN BOYS of Canterburie, my very good Vncle, Grace and peace.</title>
           <author>Boys, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106819_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16549</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3458</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106819</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VER∣TVOVS AND WOR∣THIE KNIGHT SIR IOHN BOYS of Canterburie, my very good Vncle, Grace and peace.</title>
                 <author>Boys, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the dominical Epistles and Gospels vsed in our English liturgie throughout the whole yeare : Together with a reason why the Church did chuse the same. By Iohn Boys, Doctor of Diuinitie. The winter part from the first Aduentall Sunday to Lent</title>
                 <author>Boys, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 302, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVOVS AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIE KNIGHT SIR IOHN BOYS of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> my very good Vncle, Grace and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, you did first plant my studies, <hi>Archbishop VVhitegift that president of pietie,</hi> watered them, and God gaue increase: to God, as to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all goodnesse, I consecrate all that I haue: to your happy memories, as to the conduits of much good, I dedicate this ensuing <hi>Postill,</hi> especially to your selfe sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuing, as to my best Patron in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where the foundation of this worke was laid; vnto your selfe, as to the chiefe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer of that small Benefice, where the frame was raised; vnto your selfe, as to
<pb facs="3"/>
the liuely paterne of that doctrine, which is here deliuered.</p>
   <p>Accept it as your owne; for it beares your name; and resembling you much, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors to honour you long: so you shall encourage me daily to lessen my debt to the Church, and increase mine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations vnto your selfe, that liuing and dying I may continue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most bounden Nephew, <hi>Iohn Boys.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>