<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT honorable Robert Lord Deuoreux, Earle of Essex.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106742_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04973</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15111</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106742</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT honorable Robert Lord Deuoreux, Earle of Essex.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Babylon is fallen</title>
                 <author>T. L.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 29, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>honorable</hi> Robert <hi>Lord</hi> Deuoreux, Earle of Essex.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eading of late (my Lord) a Chapter of <hi>Esdras,</hi> folding vp in a misticall and darke discours<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, a liuing represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a long time, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the most is past, and so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e little to come: I thought it no lost labour to take my pen and vnfolde the same: that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n we may beholde (which naturally all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to see) as well the issues of thinges to come, as what is past, or is in being: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to qualifie and moderate our hopes, and call our troubled thoughts (which otherwise runne with raines on neck) within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mitation, bounded and drawen from aboue. And finding this prophesie written by a man greatlye beloued of God, and therto (which rare is) a Princes fauourite, high in grace with a King of Persia: I presumed the rather to commend my labour to your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable L. as vpon whome God hath vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed
<pb facs="3"/> like great and rare graces. Suffiseth that your. Honor reade it, greater fauor <hi>Esdras</hi> seekes not. He labors not to praise, or please, which now a daies findes many frends, but to admonish and forewarne, which fataly findes none til be to late. He feares not the learned and noble reprouer of supposed Predictions, for he hath heard him honor the Prophesies of Holy writ, wherin him-selfe hath no lesse ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor gotten, then giuen. His other enemies, hath wild me to conceal, and to reserne them to a more open hearing. But <hi>Esdras</hi> is at the next leafe (my Lord) and craues your Honors pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for an hower.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>