<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>I. Higgins to the Reader.</title>
           <author>H., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106149_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03326</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13443</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106149</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>I. Higgins to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>H., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first parte of the Mirour for magistrates : containing the falles of the first infortunate princes of this lande: from the comming of Brute to the incarnation of our sauiour and redemer Iesu Christe</title>
                 <author>Higgins, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 74 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>I. Higgins to the Reader.</head>
   <p>AMongst diuers &amp; sondry Chronicles of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations, I thincke there are none (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader) so uncertaine &amp; briefe in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge as ours, at which I cannot but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile sith at all times oure Ilande had as learned writers (some singuler men excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) as any Nation under y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Sunne. Againe those, which now are our best Chroniclers as they report haue great Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but what they publish of late yeares may be enlarged in many places by Chronicles of other Nations: whereby it is manifest they are either ignoraunt of the tōgues, orels not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> study of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which they most professe for if they were, me thincks it were easye for them w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> such Antiquities as they brag they haue, to fetch our Distories from the beginning, &amp; make them as ample as the Chronicles of any other Country or Nation. But they are faine in steede of other stuffe to talke of the <hi>Romaines, Greekes, Persians, &amp;c.</hi> and to fill our Distoryes with their facts &amp; fables. This I speake not to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> end I would haue ours quite seperate from other without any mention of them, but I would haue them ther onelye named wher th'af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of both countryes by warre, peace, truce, mariage, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique or some necessary cause or other is intermired. I haue seene no auncient antiquities in writtē hand but two, one was <hi>Galfridus of Munmouth</hi> which I lost by misfortune, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an old Chronicle in a kind of Englishe Verse, beginning at <hi>Brute</hi> and endinge at the death of <hi>Humfrey</hi> Duke of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> in the which and diuers other good Chronicles I finde manye thinges not mentioned in that great tome engroced of late by Maister <hi>Grafton</hi> and that where he is most barraine and wantes matter. But as the greatest heades, the grayest heyres, and best clarkes haue not most witte, so the greatest Bookes, titles and Tomes containe not most mater. And this haue I spoken because in writinge the Tragedies of the first infortunate Princes of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, I was often faine to vse
<pb facs="6"/>
mine owne simple inuention (yet not swaruing from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) because the Chronicles (althoughe they wente out vnder diuers mens names) in some suche places as I moste needed their ayde wrate one thing: and that so brieflye that a whole Princes raigne, life and death, was comprised in three lines. Yea and sometimes mine olde booke aboue mentioned holpe mee out when the rest forsoke mee, as for <hi>Lanquet, Stowe,</hi> and <hi>Grafton</hi> were alwayes nighe of one opinion, but the Floure of Histories somewhat larger, some helpe had I of an olde Chronicle imprinted y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeare 1515. But surely mee thincks and so do most which delite in historyes, it were worthily done if one Chronicle were drawne from the beginning in such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect sort, that all monuments of vertuous men, (to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> eralting of Gods glorye) and all punishments of vicious persons (to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> terrour of the wicked) might be registred in perpetuall remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce. To which thing the right reuerende father in God <hi>Matthew</hi> Archbishoppe of <hi>Canterbury</hi> &amp; Metropolitane of Englande hath brought such ayde as well by printing as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruinge the written Chronicles of this Realme that by his Graces studye and paines, the labour in time to come wilbe farre more easye to them shall take such trauaile in hande. But to leaue with these and declare the cause of my purpose. As I chaunced to reade the <hi>Mirour for Magistrates</hi> &amp; worke by all men wonderfully commended, and full of fitte instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for preseruation of eche estate: takinge in hand y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Chra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, and minding to conferre the times: mee thoughte the liues of a nomber euen at the beginninge the like infortunate Princes, offered themselues vnto mee as matter verye meete for imitation the like admonition, miter and phrase, and seing <hi>Baldwine</hi> by these woordes moued mee some what thereto: <q>
         <hi>It were</hi> (sayth hee) <hi>a goodly and a notable matter to search and discourse our whole story from the beginninge of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting of this Isle, &amp;c.</hi>
      </q> I read the storyes, I considered of the Princes, I noted their liues, and therewith conferred theyr deathes. On this I toke penne in hande, mindinge nothinge
<pb facs="7"/>
lesse then to publishe them abroade: but onelye to trye what I coulde do if neede were or time and leasure were giuen mee to bestow in such wise. I wrote the two first euen as they now are, and because I would not keepe secrete my first labours in this kinde of studye (though I might well haue blushed at the basenes of my stile) I shewed them to a freiude of mine, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his bufayned iudgement in this matter: which when he had read he neuer left intreating mee to write other, til I had ended all to the byrth of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and yet not so content: he desired meet'accomplish the residue til I came to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, (which were welnighe fiftye Cragedies) but wearied with those which I had written, I desired him pause on this, till time and leasure were giuen mee. Yet he makinge rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to other his frendes what I had done, left mee not quiet till they likewise had seene them. Whose perswasion, as it seemed without any suspition of assentation or flatery, so bath it made mee bolder at this present then before. <q>
         <hi>For although</hi> (sayd they) <hi>your Tragedies be simple and not comparable to those which the other before haue written: yet when men consider that many wrote those, but one these: that they are graue writers, you are but yong: the perfection of those sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and th'imperfection of these. Finally the good will you beare to your country, the commendation of vertue, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of vice, the fall of ambition, the horrible ende of traytours, harlots, tyraunts, adulters, enchaunters, murderers and such like. VVhen men (said they) consider these things they cannot (how simple soeuer your Verse bee) but thincke well of the matter.</hi>
      </q> At length with these perswasions and suche like: I was contente (good Reader) to publishe them for thy behoufe, and the publique weale of my countrye. At which if thou enuye: I minde not therefore to enuye my selfe and staye my penne: but God willing thou shalt as fast as I can prepare them, haue other Bookes from my handes which maye please thee againe, and thus with all my harte I bidde the hartelye farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy freinde I. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>