<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
           <author>Brven, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1062_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11815</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3930.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
                 <author>Brven, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summary of the Bible : vvherein the generall heads of the seuerall bookes thereof are so methodically set downe, as may be a helpe to the vnskilfull reader / by Robert Bruen</title>
                 <author>Bruen, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 267 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thou hast here in a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row roome set before thee some helpes (as I conceiue) for thy better and more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie vnderstanding in some poynts, the Contents of the sacred Bible. It is the Booke of bookes, and so sweete to all that conceiue the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="7"/> of godlines, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is said to eate it. And <hi>Dauid</hi> a King, to prize it aboue al riches, and to spend the day and night in the meditation of it. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> professeth himselfe to estimate it, and the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his course therein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his life. Here is the wel from whence the waters of life doe plenteously flow: which who so drinketh shal neuer be more athirst. Here he that is spiritually sicke, may be recouered, according to the power of God that worketh thereby: here the simple may haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing aboue the learned
<pb facs="7"/> Scribe, &amp; such as by a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular proprietie, may make him wise vnto saluation. The treasure thē being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and knowne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to consist, the next thing worthy of our search, should bee how to attaine it; to which we should endeuour, as we do in matters of farre lesse importance. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pēter hath his Rule, the Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sitian his preparatiues. In Arts there are bookes dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue for the attainment of them. And therefore as we commonly lanch forth into the main Ocean, beginning at the Riuers that run ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: And Children are
<pb facs="8"/> led by the hand, before they get the vse of their feete: Euen so, although the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, by which the Scriptures were written, be the inward and Master-teacher, yet as oftentimes we take the benefit of the staffe to walke with, to helpe the body; so is it in the study of good things, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod being as the mindes-waggoner, and that order best, when by generall heads (as markes in the way) we may bee kept the better from erring. Which thing is the ayme of this small ensuing tract, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Reader may see in a
<pb facs="8"/> generall manner, what eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry seuerall Booke of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture principally intendeth, set downe in methodical manner, for the more easie vnderstanding and better retaining of the same in the Readers me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
   <p>And although all Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be giuen by inspiration from God, and euery part of it be of vse for the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly building: yet as some roomes are of different sort in the materiall edifice, so is it in the sacred Story, wherein some parcels are recommended vnto vs, not onely as excellent in
<pb facs="9"/> themselues; but as seruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and keyes to vnlocke other places of Scriptures, and make them more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to the godly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposed Reader. Such as are the Bookes of <hi>MOSES,</hi> to all those that come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the Bookes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> to the Psalmes of <hi>DAVID;</hi> those of the <hi>Kings,</hi> to the <hi>Prophets:</hi> The Acts of the Apostles, to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles. And according to this direction I haue been purposely more prolix and large in setting downe some things in all or most of the forenamed Bookes. As concerning the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
<pb facs="9"/> parts of euery Chapter, (although in some places I haue not been wanting that way) because the same in sundry learned Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of some, &amp; abbreuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of others is set down, I haue forborne to labour therein. If thou hast better helpes in this kind, in the feare of GOD vse them to the improuement of sauing knowledge. If these of mine may any thing auaile thee, here thou hast them before thee: And the Lord blesse them vnto thee, and thee vnto himselfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in, and for</hi> the Lord, <hi>ROBERT BRVEN.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="10"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>