<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106681_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10838</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21111</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106681</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manumission to a manuduction, or Answer to a letter inferring publique communion in the parrish assemblies upon private with godly persons there. By Iohn Robinson</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the godly reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit I be justly sorry for all oppositions against the truth, yet
not so for this occasion of further manifesting that my former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
professed perswasion, that <hi>publique communion with the
parrish assemblies cannot be inferred vppon private with
godly persons though members there:</hi> the constitution and
estate of the same assemblies <hi>rearing up a partitiō wall,</hi> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>so transparent as may be seen thorough,</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>h lesse <hi>so
open as may be passed,</hi> no not in the best <hi>charity,</hi> as this <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuducent</hi>
supposeth: but on the contrary, so grosse, &amp; entyre in evill, as that no
engine of wit, or art can so batter it, as to make a safe passage through it for a good
conscience.</p>
   <p>Needfull it were in a matter of this nature, and weight, that the <hi>manuducent,
or</hi> hand leader should guide men by the playn, and open way of the s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>riptures, as
is the way of the Lord in them layd down, open, &amp; playn, as the King▪ high way:
and beaten by the feet of the Apostolicall churches: &amp; not by subtile <hi>Quaerees,</hi>
and doubtfull <hi>Suppositions,</hi> and such under hand conveyances, as may lead the
vnwary into a maze, and there loose him, but cannot clear the way for an vpright
cōscience. Of the way of Christ it was prophesied of ould:<note n="*" place="margin">Isa: 35. 8.</note>
      <hi>An high way</hi> shalbe
<hi>there, and a way, and it shalbe called the way of holines: the vnclean shall not
pase over it, for he shalbe with these: the wayfareing man, though fooles,
shall not erre therein.</hi> But so many and doubtfull are the wyndeings of this mans
way, as that he who findes it, had need be no <hi>wayfareing man,</hi> but a town-dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
and well acquainted with all the secret turnings thereof: nor a <hi>fool,</hi> as
the Prophet speaketh, but one haveing wit indeed more then a good deal. But let
them <note place="margin">psalm 84. 6, 8.</note>
      <q>
         <hi>in whose hearts</hi> are <hi>the highwayes</hi> of the Lord, that <hi>they</hi> may <hi>goe frō
strength to strength, till they appear vnto God in Sion,</hi>
      </q> let them, I say, not
suffer themselves to be led by the turnings of mans devise whatsoever, but by<note place="margin">Pro: 8. 8. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the
<hi>wordes of</hi> the <hi>wisdom</hi> of God, which are <hi>all in righteousnes;</hi> &amp; <hi>in which there
is nothing wreathed, or perverse:</hi> but <hi>they are all playne to him that will
understand, and straight to him that would fynde knowledge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now for my persvasion about publique, and private communion, it is the same
which I have manifested in my other book: and that, wherein (so far as by the
weak light, which God hath given to shine in my heart, I can discern) I neyther
wrong the good in that Church; (person, or thing), nor partake in the evill of
eyther. My trust is, that God who hath given me my part (though in great infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity)
in the Prophets comfort,<note n="†" place="margin"> Ps. 119. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>with all my heart have I sought thee;</hi> will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
fulfill his request uppon me, <hi>let me not wander from thy commandements,</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>