<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE INSCRIPTION Dedicatorie. FOR THE GLORY OF GOD, AND edification of his Church.</title>
           <author>Allen, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106811_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16736</idno>
           <idno type="STC">364</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106811</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE INSCRIPTION Dedicatorie. FOR THE GLORY OF GOD, AND edification of his Church.</title>
                 <author>Allen, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrine of the Gospel : By a plaine and familiar interpretation of the particular points or articles thereof: with the promises, comforts, and duties, seuerally belonging to the same. VVhereunto is added, a declaration of the danger of not knowing, not beleeuing, or not obeying any one of them. Likewise, a rehearsal of the manifold heresies, wherein many haue erred contrary to them all. Diuided into three bookes. The first whereof, is of beliefe in God the Father</title>
                 <author>Allen, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 257, 15, 619, 5, 122, 6 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE INSCRIPTION Dedicatorie. FOR THE GLORY OF GOD, AND <hi>edification of his Church.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the right worshipfull Sir <hi>Nicolas Bacon</hi> Knight, my singular good Patron, with the vertuous Lady <hi>Anne Bacon</hi> his wife. And to the right worshipfull Sir <hi>Nathanael Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> and to Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Bacon,</hi> Knights: and to the Right worshipfull Maister <hi>Edward Bacon,</hi> one of his Maiesties worthie Iustices of the peace, in <hi>Suffolke</hi> (all louers of Pietie and Iustice, and friendes to the Church of God, through his rich grace, blessed be his name for so great a mercy) as a debt acknowledged most due vnto them, and to the whole posteritie of their right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Father, a most worthy and wise Patron of true Religion, vpright Iustice, and all good learning, in his high place, all his time a most worthy Paterne to bee imitated and followed of all that des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend of him: yea, of all that succeed him in like Office of high dignitie. For a token of gratulatorie-thankfulnes to God, for so inestimable a blessing: and with a holy desire to help forward their holy knowledge, and the precious faith of their eternall saluation. This second part of the Treasurie of Christian instruction (contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a chiefe portion of <hi>the Doctrine of the Gospell</hi>) is both from heart and hand willingly dedicated.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>By their VVorships, among other of the Ministers of the Gospel, one most bounden in the Lord,</hi> Robert Allen.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>