<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>HENRY King of England, to IOANNES LODOVICVS VIVES greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106897_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">916</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>HENRY King of England, to IOANNES LODOVICVS VIVES greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>St. Augustine, Of the citie of God : vvith the learned comments of Io. Lod. Viues. Englished by I.H</title>
                 <author>Augustine, of Hippo, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 921, 11 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>HENRY King of England, to IOANNES LODOVICVS VIVES greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORTHY Sir, and our very welbeloued friend, as soone as Saint</hi> AVGVSTINE de ciuitate Dei, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with your comments came to our hands, being right welcome to vs, it caused vs to doubt, whom wee should most congratulate; either you, by whose so learned labour so ehoise a worke is fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed; or Saint</hi> AVGVSTINE, <hi>who long time imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and obscure, is now at last brought from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to light, and restored to his ancient integrity, or all posterity, whom these your</hi> Commentaries <hi>shall infinitely profit. But whereas it pleased you, to dedicate these</hi> Commentaries <hi>to our name, wee cannot but retaine a gratefull minde, and returne you great thankes, in that especially your minde therein seemeth to manifest no vulgar loue and obseruance towards vs. Wherefore we would haue you perswaded, that our fauor and good will shall neuer faile in your affaires, whatsoeuer occasion shall bee offered, that may tend to your auaile. So fare you happily well.</hi> From our Court at <hi>Greenwich, the</hi> XXIIII. day of Ianuary M. D. XXIII.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>