<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RELI∣GIOVS AND EVERY WAY NOBLE KNIGHT, SIR THOMAS WOTTON of Bocton Malherbe, Sonne and heire to the right honourable EDVVARD Lord WOTTON, Baron of Marleigh, Comptroller of his Maiesties household, Lord Lieutenant of the Countie of Kent, and the Citie of Canterburie, and one of the most Honorable Pri∣uie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Boys, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106196_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68966</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3466a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RELI∣GIOVS AND EVERY WAY NOBLE KNIGHT, SIR THOMAS WOTTON of Bocton Malherbe, Sonne and heire to the right honourable EDVVARD Lord WOTTON, Baron of Marleigh, Comptroller of his Maiesties household, Lord Lieutenant of the Countie of Kent, and the Citie of Canterburie, and one of the most Honorable Pri∣uie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Boys, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the proper Psalmes vsed in ovr English liturgie : together with a reason why the Chvrch did chuse the same. By Iohn Boys, Doctor of Diuinitie. The first part explaining the Psalmes appointed to be read on Christmas and Easter day</title>
                 <author>Boys, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 179, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIOVS AND EVERY WAY NOBLE KNIGHT, SIR THOMAS WOTTON of Bocton Malherbe, Sonne and heire to <hi>the right honourable</hi> EDVVARD Lord WOTTON, <hi>Baron of Marleigh, Comptroller of his Maiesties</hi> household, Lord Lieutenant of the Countie of <hi>Kent, and the Citie of Canterburie, and one of the most Honorable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Counsell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, as the Scriptures excel other writings in veritie; so the Psalmes, other Scriptures in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie: for whereas some sacred bookes are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, as the <hi>Pentateuchue of Moses:</hi> other historicall, as the <hi>Kings, Chronicles, Acts:</hi> a third kinde Propheticall, as the <hi>Ʋision of Esay, Sermons of Jeremie, Reuelation of Saint John:</hi> a fourth Euangelicall, as the <hi>Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels
<pb facs="3"/> and Epistles:</hi> the Psalter (as<note n="a" place="margin">Prolog. in lib. <hi>3</hi> Psalmorum.</note>
      <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Hom. de lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus &amp; virtute Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Basile,</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Praefat. in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Euthymius,</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Athanasius. Chrysostom.</note> other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctors honour it) is a <hi>common trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure-house of all good arguments and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions:</hi> and in this respect aptly tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med<note n="e" place="margin">Caluin. epist. praefix. Com. in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>The Soules Anatomie, the</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Tremel. argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Lawes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitomie, the</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">See Victorinus Strigellius epist. Dedicat. &amp; Tilemanus, Heshusius prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Gospels Jndex;</hi> in one word, <hi>The</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Turrecremat. prolog in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Register,</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Io. Gaineius epist. lect. in od. Dauid.</note>
      <hi>Enchiridion,</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Ex ceteris omnibus quasi Collectus. Hen. Mollerus praefat. in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Summarie pith,</hi> and (as it were)<note n="l" place="margin">Agellius pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. in Psalm.</note>
      <hi>Briefe of the whole Bible.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Vpon this ground the Church in<note n="m" place="margin">Preface Com. Booke.</note> old time, diuiding the Psalmes into seuen portions, inioyned that they should bee read in diuine seruice (thorough) once euery Weeke: and in our time parting them into thirtie, once euery Moneth: where as other parts of holy writ are read thorough but once in the yeere. And the <hi>Nouelists,</hi> howsoeuer they mislike bare reading of <hi>Chapters,</hi> approue notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing by their positions and practise, singing of <hi>Psalmes</hi> in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p>By which it doth appeare that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="3"/> is esteemed generallie more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie for the worshippe of God, then the word of God, and no parcell of the word more full and fit then the <hi>Psalmes;</hi> vnto which I will adde, that no Psalmes are more profitable then the <hi>proper,</hi> as vnfoulding the foure chiefe mysteries of holy beliefe; namely, <hi>Christs Jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, Passion, Resurrection, Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>An exposition whereof I haue begun in the name of the Lord Iesus, and that for his Sions sake; the which I dedicate to your worthie selfe, as being a noble <hi>Theophilus,</hi> that is, a true seruant of God, and obseruant of his Church, affected so right honestly (which is right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) to her doctrine and discipline; that your humble Comportament in Gods house, giueth vnto the world good hope, that you will become <hi>an open booke of vnfained deuotion and pietie.</hi> Now the God of all comfort, according to the multitude of his mercies, and riches of
<pb facs="4"/> his glorie, blesse you and your Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Familie, that you may long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy good dayes on earth, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after eternall happinesse in Heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all good offices of dutie and loue: IOHN BOYS.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Hollingbourn.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>April.</hi> 2.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>