<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my deare Friend and Fellow-Planter, Master Robert Hayman, who with Pen and Person prepares more roome for Christians in the Newfound-World.</title>
           <author>Vaughan, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106081_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02836</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12974</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my deare Friend and Fellow-Planter, Master Robert Hayman, who with Pen and Person prepares more roome for Christians in the Newfound-World.</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Quodlibets, lately come ouer from New Britaniola, old Newfound-land : Epigrams and other small parcels, both morall and diuine. The first foure bookes being the authors owne: the rest translated out of that excellent epigrammatist, Mr. Iohn Owen, and other rare authors: wit two epistles of that excellently wittie doctor, Francis Rablais: translated out of his French at large. All of them composed and done at Harbor-Grace in Britaniola, anciently called Newfound-Land. By R.H. sometimes Gouernour of the plantation there</title>
                 <author>Hayman, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Michell, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smethwick (Smithick, Smythicke), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64, 6, 58, that is 54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To my deare Friend and Fellow-Planter, Master <hi>Robert Hayman,</hi> who with Pen and Person prepares more roome for Christians in the Newfound-World.</head>
   <l>WHilst worldlings most build Castles in the Aire,</l>
   <l>Nibbling on baytes, like <hi>Orpheus</hi> and <hi>Sems</hi> heire:</l>
   <l>You spend your time both with your Muse and hand,</l>
   <l>To edifie our hopefull <hi>Newfound-Land.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To tame the rude, doth argue a braue spirit:</l>
   <l>But to saue soules, are workes of greatest merit.</l>
   <l>To plant and fish, from sloth you those perswade:</l>
   <l>From errors these, to a more heauenly trade.</l>
   <l>Thus whil'st but dorsse some raking slaues ingrose,</l>
   <l>You digge new grounds, and roote vp Trees and Mosse.</l>
   <l>You shew the meanes to cut off suites and strife;</l>
   <l>Meanes for good men, to leade a pleasant life.</l>
   <l>You search the Seas, and anchour with strong cables:</l>
   <l>Which deeds you build on faith, as those on Babels.</l>
   <l>Thus he who borrowed twice sweet <hi>Orpheus</hi> name;</l>
   <l>Poore Cambriols Lord, addes to your rising fame.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true friend <hi>William Vaughan.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>