<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106548_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04534</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14656</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106548</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Duke of Saxonie his iubilee : with a short chronologie. Both shewing the goodnesse of God, in blessing the Gospel of Christ, since Luther first opposed the Popes pardons</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="18" facs="15"/>
   <head>TO THE READER,</head>
   <p>AS before their is a remarkeable example of the exceeding goodnes of God, in glorifiyng the Gospell of his welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Sonne, by the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> of <hi>Spalato</hi> his renouncing of Antichrist, and forsaking his Primacy Ecclesiasticall ouer two Kingdomes for the truth sake, where by the period of the first hundred yeares; after <hi>Luther</hi> had set vp his <hi>Propositions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst tho Popes pardons, was gloriously shut up: So it is thought convenient to commend to thy godly consideration the great, and good worke of our gracious God, the God of Truth, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing his Truth this yeare <hi>1618.</hi> being the first of the second hundred yeares, by discovering the treason of <hi>Barneuil,</hi> and his <hi>Arminian</hi> complices tending to the great impeachment of the same. By delivering up a principall instrument in the same to a reprobate minde, so as he murthered himselfe, after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed the treason, by raysing vp that <hi>Worthy in Israel, Graue Maurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> with admirable policy, diligence, and peace to purge <hi>Arminian</hi> townes of corrupt, and dangerous Magistrats, and to Re-unite Provinces and Cities, which were upon the poynt of <hi>Confusion</hi> so preuayling was the diulish poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Arminian</hi> herisy; and by sanctifiyng the minds of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>States,</hi> in a most religious manner, to call togither the present Nationall <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Dorte.</hi> Whereby, through Gods blessing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the same, <hi>Truth</hi> may be cleared, <hi>Wisedome</hi> iustified, and the <hi>Gospell</hi> haue a freer passage. Which God graunt for his great Names sake: <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="15"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>