<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
AA
</title>
           <author>Harsnett, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106122_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02794</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12925</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106122</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
AA
</title>
                 <author>Harsnett, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Strange and wonderfvll things. Happened to Richard Hasleton, borne at Braintree in Essex, in his ten yeares trauailes in many forraine countries. Penned as he deliuered it from his ovvne mouth</title>
                 <author>Hasleton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Barley (Barlow), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Jeffes, Abel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Pavier, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head type="illustration">
      <figure>
         <p>AA</p>
      </figure>
   </head>
   <head>TO THE VVORSHIPFVLL Maister Richard Stapar, one of the vvorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full companie of the Marchants aduenturers of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable citie ofLondon, trading to Turkie and the Easterne kingdomes. Your worships faithfull welwiller W. Barley, wisheth all fortunate and happie successe in all your enterprises, with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of all worldly worship: and after death the ioyes vnspeakeable.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipfull sir, the manie reportes of your rare vertues, generally spoken of all honest trauailers, who hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the benefit of your bountie, not onely in our home borne countrey where you haue your residence but in those farre countries where your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest factors trade; by whose worshipfull and expresse commaund giuen them, and the good they dayly do for all men which seeke them: your worship is accounted and called the Patterne of bountie, especially of such as are in their trauaile distressed with want, which with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney are releeued, aswell as other great cost their fauour or friendship can procure, so that not onely the poore and needy are pleasured thereby, but those that swim in most aboundance▪ all proceeding of your most kinde and courteous disposition.</p>
   <p>The remembrance of which, mooued a longing desire in me, in some sorte, to explaine your worthinesse and fame by your bountie gained, it had neuer such oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie vntill this time: when perusing my store of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and writings, of sundry mens labours, I chaunced
<pb facs="3"/>
on this Pamphlet, which importeth the troublesome trauailes of our neere neighbour borne at <hi>Brainetree</hi> in Essex, named <hi>Richard Hasleton,</hi> whose miseries as they were many, being in the hands both of Christians and Heathen enemies, for God and our countries cause, and his escapes from death so often and so wonderfull, with the constant enduring of the same: his preseruation, and safe returne to England, where his longing desire so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wished him: all which considered, with your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships loue to all Traua<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ers, imboldned me the rather vnder your worships patronage to publish the same, especiall zeale procuring me therevnto: and partly in regarde of your many fauoures to the said <hi>Hasleton</hi> in his miseries extended, that your worships good ensam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may lighten others to such good actions, hoping your worship will except of it no lesse friendly, then I offer it willingly▪ which if you do, then is my desire satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and my selfe rest bounden to your worships wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse: euer beseeching the giuer of all good to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the number of such worthy minded subiects, by whom our Prince and countrie, are in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine parts so much honoured.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vvorships to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund in vvhat I may, <hi>William Barley.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>