<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO DON PHILIPPE PACHECO, Marquesse of VIL∣LENA, Duke of ESCALONA, and Count of SANTISTENAN, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Pen̄a, Iuan Antonio de la</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106088_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09280</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106088</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO DON PHILIPPE PACHECO, Marquesse of VIL∣LENA, Duke of ESCALONA, and Count of SANTISTENAN, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Pen̄a, Iuan Antonio de la</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A relation of the royall festiuities : and juego de cañas (a turnament of darting with reedes after the manner of Spaine) made by the King of Spaine at Madrid, the 21 of August this present yeere, 1623. To honour the espousall treaties of the illustrious Prince of Wales, with the lady Infanta Maria of Austria. Before the departure of the Prince from his court: towards the sea-side, to take shipping for his returne into England. Composed by Doctor Iuan Antonio de la Peña, natife of Madrid, and faithfully translated out of the Spanish printed copie</title>
                 <author>Peña, Juan Antonio de la</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 22 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO DON PHILIPPE PACHECO, <hi>Marquesse of</hi> VIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENA, Duke of ESCALONA, and <hi>Count of</hi> SANTISTENAN, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Relation requires your Excellencie for a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coenas, aboue a thousand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Titles, because you are a Person more interessed in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of his Maiesty, shewed the day of Turneament to my Lady the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse of <hi>Miranda,</hi> and to my Lady the Marquesse her Neece, when he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured her house with his Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence: And that your Excellencie hath now recouered your health, J thought <pb facs="3"/>good to honour you with this presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in writing, of what you enioyed with your sight and presence, a while to entertaine you, being assured to bee pardoned for those faults, which in this Treatise may occurre the same, beeing as secure to bee freed from all Court-Censure, by such a Patrone, whose life and State Heauen euer make happy.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Doctor <hi>Iuan Antonio de la Pen̄a.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>