<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>These faults I desire the reader to amend before he read the booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106416_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16722</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3622</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>These faults I desire the reader to amend before he read the booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned treatise of the Sabaoth, written by Mr Edward Brerewood, professor in Gresham Colledge, London. To Mr Nicolas Byfield, preacher in Chester. With Mr Byfields answere and Mr Brerewoods reply</title>
                 <author>Brerewood, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Huggins, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 101, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>These faults I desire the reader to amend before he read the booke.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>PAGE 9. line 10. leaue out and, p. 25. l. 13. read consecration, for, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation, p. 27. l. 17. r. not of the, for, not the, pag. 28. l. 2. r. commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for commandements, l. 7. read Gods command, f. God commands, p. 29. l. 26. read greater, for, great. p 30. l. 3. r. per accidens, for, per accidence, l. 15. r. thereof, for, thereon, p. 32. l 4. r. servant, for, seruants, p. 30. l. 21. r. respected, for, expressed, l. 29. r. in the Sabaoth, for, in Sabaoth, p. 42. l. 5 r. of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, for, of commandent, p. 47. l. 14. r. their, for there, p. 54. l. 7. r. haruest, for, heauinesse: p. 68. l. r. perpetuall, for, perpetually, p 79. figure 9. r. volly, for, vally, p. 81.</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Brerewoods <hi>text should be continued, p. 90. r. short, for shord, p. 91. r. for a great part, for, of a great profit, p. 91. l. 23. r. who, for whose, p. 94. (for) should be out,</hi> ib. <hi>the, for, your, p. 95. the gap at (appointment) should not be, nor any point.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Many mispointings, and lesser faults there are, by the darkenesse of the copy, and the oversight of the Printer, which the iudicious reader may easily correct.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>