<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Kings most Excellent Maiestie, CHARLES, by Gods especiall mercy, King of Great-Britaine, France, and Ireland, &amp;c. Emperour of South, and North Vir∣ginia, King of Britaniola, or Newfound-land, and the Iles ad∣jacent, Father, Fauourer, and Furtherer of all his loyall Subjects right Honourable and worthie Plantations.</title>
           <author>Hayman, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106081_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02836</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12974</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Kings most Excellent Maiestie, CHARLES, by Gods especiall mercy, King of Great-Britaine, France, and Ireland, &amp;c. Emperour of South, and North Vir∣ginia, King of Britaniola, or Newfound-land, and the Iles ad∣jacent, Father, Fauourer, and Furtherer of all his loyall Subjects right Honourable and worthie Plantations.</title>
                 <author>Hayman, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Quodlibets, lately come ouer from New Britaniola, old Newfound-land : Epigrams and other small parcels, both morall and diuine. The first foure bookes being the authors owne: the rest translated out of that excellent epigrammatist, Mr. Iohn Owen, and other rare authors: wit two epistles of that excellently wittie doctor, Francis Rablais: translated out of his French at large. All of them composed and done at Harbor-Grace in Britaniola, anciently called Newfound-Land. By R.H. sometimes Gouernour of the plantation there</title>
                 <author>Hayman, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Michell, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smethwick (Smithick, Smythicke), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64, 6, 58, that is 54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Kings most Excellent Maiestie, CHARLES, by Gods especiall mercy, King of <hi>Great-Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> Emperour of South, and North <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> King of <hi>Britaniola,</hi> or <hi>Newfound-land,</hi> and the Iles ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent, Father, Fauourer, and Furtherer of all his loyall Subjects right Honourable and worthie Plantations.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY it please your most Excellent Maiestie, this last right worthy attribute of yours (no way insinuated, but iustly affixed to your more ancient stile) perswades these vnworthy papers to presume (with your gracious leaue and permission) to take the hardines to kisse your sacred hands; hoping of the like successe, that some vnripe eares of corne, brought by me from the cold Country of <hi>Newfound-land,</hi> receiued from some honest, well-minded louers of that action when they saw them: who with much-affected ioy often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them, tooke much comfort in what they saw: but more, when they suppos'd it might be better'd, by industry, care, and honestie. These few bad vnripe Rimes of mine (comming from thence) are in all humility presented with the like intendiment to your Maiestie, to testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that the Aire there is not so dull, or maleuolent, but that if bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wits were transplanted thither, neither the Summers heat would dilate them, nor the Winters cold benumme them, but that they might in full vigour flourish to good purpose. For if I now growne dull and aged, could doe somewhat, what will not sharper, younger, freer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions performe there? They would not walke as I here doe, with short turnes, leaning sometimes on others inuentions, skipping weakly from bough to bough; but with large walkes, with long, and strong flights. I suppose it not fit at this time (but attending the successe of this presumption) in some other larger manner to make knowne vnto your Maiestie, the inestimable riches of the <hi>Seas</hi> circuling that <hi>Iland:</hi> The hopefull improuements of the maine Land thereof: The more then probable, vnualuable hidden treasures therein: The infinite aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of combustible fierce materials fit for such an imployment. It is
<pb facs="3"/>
only the Aire at this time I desire to dignifie, and that which is within that <hi>Horizon:</hi> Yet is my proofe rather in hope of others, then in any actuated performance of mine owne. If your Maiestie will be pleased to giue credit to your meanest subiect, I may ingage my selfe on this as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seueration, That not only in this vnprofitable (though not vnpleasant) Art, better wits would thriue there: but all other sollid learning would walke vprightly without conuulsions. I cannot but know, how al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most all your Royall houres are taken vp in most Reall, serious, sollid imploiments: did I therefore imagine, that either your Maiestie could, or graciously would vouchsafe the reading of these; they would be found some mine owne, the rest, Translations. Meane and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy though they are, yet because some of them were borne, and the rest did first speake <hi>English,</hi> in that Land whereof your gracious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie is the right, and lawfull <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and King, by ancient descent and primary possession, and being the first fruits of this kind, that euer visited this Land, out of that Dominion of yours; I thought it my duty, to present and to prostrate these with my selfe at your Royall feete: For what I haue mistakingly offended herein, or shall hereafter, I humbly beseech your Maiesties gracious, mercifull, generall, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and pardon, vnfeinedly beseeching God to blesse your Maiesty with aboundance of all Earthly and Heauenly blessings. And that you may see an happy successe of all your Forraigne Plantations, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of that of <hi>Newfound-land,</hi> I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties well meaning and loyall Subiect, <hi>ROBERT HAYMAN.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>