<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106025_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02817</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12950</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of graunde Amoure and la bell Pucel, called the Pastime of plesure : co [n] teining the knowlege of the seue [n] sciences, [and] the course of mans life in this worlde. Iuuented [sic] by Stephen Hawes, grome of kyng Henry the seuenth his chamber</title>
                 <author>Hawes, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wayland, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>216 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>SI the that all menne for the most part by a naturall inclination, desire ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to spend their dayes in pleasure and delectable pastimes, then in paineful stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes and tedious labours. And yet neuertheles by the secrete inspiracion of almighty God (all men in general) so insaciately thirsteth for the knowledge of wisdome and learnyng, that some for very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest desire therof (thoughe nature grudgeth) cease not to spend their dayes and houres, with suche cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and importunate trauayle in sekynge the same, that hauyng no regarde to the ouer pressyng of Nature, in searchynge with all diligence for the true vaine of knowledge, do sodainely bryng forth their owne confusion. Some contrariwise (whom nature to muche ruleth) beyng discomforted wyth painefull &amp; tedious study, rather chose to be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the stinkyng floude of ignoraunce, thē wyth so muche sweate and paynes, to sayle (wyth a by wynde) into the pleasaunt Ilande of wisdome and science, which thing cōsidered (most gentle Reader) I offer here vnto the for thy better instruction this little volume, conteynynge and treatyng vpon the seuen liberall sciences, &amp; the whole course of mans lyfe, firste compiled &amp; deuised by Stephen Hawes gentleman, grome of the chamber to the famous Prynce and seconde Salomon, kynge Henrye the seuenth. A man (as by his worckes appeareth) of a pleasaunte wytte, and singuler learnynge, wherin thou shalt finde at one tyme, wisdome and
<pb facs="4"/>
learnyng, with myrthe and solace. So that herein thou mayest easelye fynde (as it were in pastyme) wythout offence of nature that thyng, and in short space, whiche many great clarkes wythout great paynes and trauayle, &amp; long continuaunce of time heretofore coulde neuer obteyne nor get, which as it was firste entituled by the Aucthoure, to be the pastime of pleasure, and vnder the same title so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the sayed worthye Prynce, by the Auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoure therof: so shalt thou good reader wyth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate readyng therof, fynde it not onely the Pastyme of pleasure, but also of profite.</p>
   <closer>Fare wel.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>