<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106394_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16704</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3606</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Luthers life : collected from the writinges of him selfe, and other learned Protestants, together with a further shorte discourse, touchinge Andreas Melanchton, Bucer, Ochine, Carolostadius, Suinglius, Caluine and Beza, the late pretended reformers of religion. Taken from th onely reporte of learned Protestants themselues. By Iohn Brerely priest and author of the Protestants apologie</title>
                 <author>Anderton, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88, 98-105, 105-135, 135-139, 139-165, 165-205 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Einge requested by such as may challenge interest in my labours, to write somewhat in satisfaction of those, whose meaner capacitie is not able to discerne of learned dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cources, nor to wade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the depthe of more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate pointes and questions concerning religion, I coulde not make choise of any thing more fitting in this kinde, then the description of theire liues &amp; proceedinges, who now in this last age vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of reformation, impugned our auncient, and no lesse longe before continued<note n="(a)" place="margin">For the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares last past Simon de Voion in his discource vpon the catalogue of the docters &amp;c. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at London 1598 in the epistle to the reader <hi>post med.</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that <hi>Anno</hi> 605. when pope Boniface was stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the papall throne, then fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode got the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie &amp;c. then was the whole worlde ouer-whelmed in the dreegges of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian filthines abominable super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitions, and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the pope, then was that vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall apostasie frō the faith foretould by Paule. And master Powel in his consideration of the papistes reasons prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1604. page 105. <hi>fine</hi> saith. I grante that from the yere of Christe 605. the professant companie of poperie, hath bene verie visible and perspicuouse: And maister D. Fulke in his answere to a counterfaite catholicke, printed 1577. act. 11. pag. 36. <hi>initio</hi> saithe. The religion of the papistes came in and preuayled in the yere of our Lord. 607. &amp;c. and so vniuersally that (saith he) the reuelation of Antichrist, with the churches flight into the wilderernes, was <hi>anno</hi> 607. whē &amp;c. (see this last in his reioinder to Bristoe printed 1581. pag. 347. <hi>circa med.</hi>) And maister Parkins in his exposition of the creed, printed 1596, and after the last edition of his workes▪ <hi>volum.</hi> 1. printed 1608. <hi>pag.</hi> 266. b. <hi>initio</hi> saith. During the space of 900. yeres from the time of Boniface, the popishe heresie hath spred it selfe ouer the whole earth, and the faithful seruantes of God were but as an handful of wheate in a moūtaine of chaffe which can scarse be discern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d: and Vorstius in his Antibellarminus printed 1610. <hi>pag.</hi> 154. <hi>initio</hi> saith, <hi>quod ad Ecclesiam Romanam hodiernam attinet, tametsi fatemur eam hactenus mille circiter annos, continuo sub hac corrupta formae generatim accepta durasse &amp;c.</hi> Also maister Naper in this treatise vpon the reuelation (for the supposed worth therof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to his maiestie, and reprinted at london 1594. and againe reprinted at london 1611. <hi>cum priuilegio regiae maiestatis,</hi> and as appeareth by the preface thereto, imprinted and sett out diuers times in the frenche and duche tongues, and to be published in latine to the vtilitie of the whole churche) acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a yet longer vniuersall continuance of our religion sayinge. Betwene the yere of Christe 300. and 316. the Antichristian and papisticall reigne beganne reigning vniuersallie, &amp; without any debateable contradictiō 1260. yeres (after the firste edition, proposition 36. <hi>pag.</hi> 68. <hi>prope finem</hi> and after the other edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>pag.</hi> 90. <hi>fine</hi>) and the same so affirmed by him, not in regarde of some or other particuler doctrine of our religion, but so generallie concerninge the whole, that, saith he, gods true churche, most certainlye abode so longe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: (edition. first. <hi>in c.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 191. <hi>initio.</hi>) and inuisible (<hi>ibidem in cap.</hi> 12. <hi>pag.</hi> 161. <hi>col.</hi> 3. <hi>circa med.</hi> and after the 2. edition <hi>pag.</hi> 201. <hi>fine.</hi>) The pope and his clergie possessinge the outwarde visible churche of christians, euen 1260. yeres: (<hi>ibidem in c.</hi> 11. <hi>initio. edit.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 145. <hi>fine.</hi>) And maister Brocard vpon the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations printed. 1572. fol. 110. <hi>à circa med.</hi> affirmeth, that the churche was trodden downe &amp; oppressed by the papacie euen from Siluesters time to these times, duringe (the saide) 1260. yeres: and see him further there fol. 123. b. Lastly maister Brightman in his apocalipsis apocalipseos, printed 1609. in his synopsis placed before the beginninge of the booke in c. 11. and 14. sayth. <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia à tēporibus Constantini per mille ducentes sexaginta annos abscondita fuit &amp;c. per mille annos à Constantino, versante Ecclesia in abditissimis latebris fuit vna cum Christo &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>in Apocal. in c.</hi> 12. <hi>pag.</hi> 341. <hi>paulo ante med.</hi> he saith. <hi>Necessarijs argumentis euincimus, mulierem in solitudinem se recipisse &amp;c. ad illud tempus quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do regnum inibat Constantinus.</hi> And <hi>in c.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 283. <hi>circa med.</hi> he saith. <hi>Acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente Constantino ad regnum, capit Ecclesia se abdere in occulto concedendo à mundi conspectu in quoddam interius penetrare;</hi> and <hi>pag.</hi> 577. <hi>circa med.</hi> he further saith. <hi>Respondeo &amp;c. non expectandam esse vllam aliam cessationem publicae religionis quam quae extitit multis saeculis, à Constantino magno in hunc vsque diem, quo omni tēpore regnauit Antichristus, dum agebat quidem mulier in deserto.</hi>
      </note> then vniuersal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie professed catholicke faith: for seeinge it<note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 7.13.14.</note> is (not the broad but) the straite way that leadeth vnto life, and that accordingly it is euident by all examples and obseruation of former times, that the liues of those were euermore not licentiouse or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute, but austere and sanctified, whom God chose to be the reformers of his churche, or first publis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers or restorers of religion, it cannot but afforde matter of singuler satisfactiō to such as are but euen
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
      <pb n="5" facs="3"/> of meanest vnderstandinge, if vpon due examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion taken in this course it do falle out, that those who are now pretended to haue beene for this last age the<note n="(c)" place="margin">extraordinarie reformers whereof see <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>sec.</hi> 5. <hi>fine.</hi> in the margine at S.</note> extraordinarie reformers of the Christiā worlde, haue in such theire vndertaken endeauor, behaued thēselues as men of more then ordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed &amp; wicked condiciō of life: for our Sauiour saith,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Math. 6.22.23.</note> the lighte of the bodie is the eye, &amp; if this lighte be darke, how greate shall the darknes it self be? to which purpose he further forwarneth say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 7.15.16.17.</note> Beware of false prophets who come to you in sheepes clothinge, but inwardlie are raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge wolues, by theire fruits you shall knowe them: doe men gather grapes of thornes, or figges of thistles? &amp;c. a good tree yeeldeth good fruite &amp;c. from which permisses it necessarilie followeth (maister Whites<note n="(f)" place="margin">wheras maister White in his way to the true churche, printed 1608. <hi>sec.</hi> 38. <hi>nu. 2. &amp; 3. &amp; pag.</hi> 211. <hi>&amp;</hi> 212. alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth sundrie testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to proue that the argument is not good <hi>à mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad doctrinăm:</hi> I answere thereto, that though the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument thereof do not alwayes hould, yett this letteth not, but that in the now speciall case of the first profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors or reformers of religiō yt should be of force, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the testimonies heare nexte before in that behalfe alledged: at b.c. and next hereafter at</note> allegation to the contrarie notwithstanding) that if the now pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of religion, were in such theire action not san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, but of flagitiouse and wicked life, then can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not they possible be the instruments chosen by God to that worke, nor (consequentlie) their doctrine so by them reuealed, be the eternal truthe of the liuing God: An inference yet further made good from the wordes of<note n="(g)" place="margin">
         <hi>in so much as maister Foxe in apocalipsin printed 1597.</hi> in cap. <hi>14.</hi> pag. <hi>468.</hi> post med. <hi>intreatinge</hi> De Ecclesia qua vera fit qua falsa, qua vera eius notae &amp; proprietates, <hi>saith.</hi> Ad fructus vitamque corum nos mittit Christus, ex fructibus inquit corum cogn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>scetis eos, &amp; rursus omnis arbor bona facit fructus bonos &amp;c. <hi>and then concludeth,</hi> pag. <hi>469.</hi> initio, <hi>sayinge.</hi> Ex morum igitur vera innocentia, vitaeque institutione certissimum sumitur indicium &amp;c. Osiander in cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>16.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>65.</hi> pag. <hi>814.</hi> initio <hi>saithe.</hi> Paulus Eberus Theologiae Doctor &amp;c. in cathedram Lutheri collocatus, euangelium docuit vir quidem doctissimus &amp; pius:</note> docter Paulus Eberus successor to Luther in his chaire at Wittemberge, who forbore
<pb n="6" facs="4"/> not to acknowledge, that<note n="(h)" place="margin">Paulus Eberus in prefat. commentar. Philippi in epist. ad Corinth. <hi>saith,</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersa nostra euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica congregatio tot Schismatibus &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendiculis scatet, vt nihil minus sit quam quod se esse gloriatur &amp;c. quae mala cum quisque proprijs ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis intuetur, merito dubitat an noster euangelicus caetus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra sit ecclesia &amp;c. in qua tot &amp; tam enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia vitia conspiciun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</note> the confessed wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes so apparentlie then aboundinge in theire owne euangelicall congregation, mynistred mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of iuste doubte, whether the same were the true churche or not: which his assertion putteth the matter out of doubte, in case it fall out, that theire verie first and principall supposed reformers of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, be no lesse, but rather more discouered and chargeable in that kinde: for so much therfore as it is the constant assertion of our learned aduersaries, that (as maister Iewell saith)<note n="(i)" place="margin">Maister Iewell in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, printed 1571. <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>diu.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 426. <hi>prope fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
      </note> the truth was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne at that time &amp; vnheard of when Martine Luther and Vlricke Suinglius, first came vnto the knowledge and preachinge of the ghospell, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so (as maister Parkins saith) wee<note n="(k)" place="margin">maister Parkins in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of the Creede, printed 1596. <hi>pag.</hi> 400. and in the last edition of his workes, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. 1. printed. 1608. <hi>pag.</hi> 310. <hi>a circa med.</hi>
      </note> saye that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the dayes of Luther for the space of manye hundreth yeres, an vniuersall apostasie ouerspred the whole face of the earth, and that our church, was not then visible to the worlde, but lay hidde vnder the chaffe of poperie: that likewise (as Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicte Morgensten a learned protestant saithe)<note n="(l)" place="margin">so saithe Benedicte Morgenstern. <hi>in tract. de Ecclesia.</hi> printed Francofurti 1598. <hi>pag.</hi> 145.</note> it is manifest to the whole christiane worlde, that before Luthers time, all churches were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with more then cimmeriane darknesse (and that) Luther was diuinely raised vp to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the same &amp; to restore the light of true doctrine: whereto Daniel Chamierus (a learned aduersarie) addeth, that as then,<note n="(m)" place="margin">
         <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell Camierus</hi> in his epist. Iesuitic. part. altera, <hi>printed Geneuae 1601.</hi> pag. <hi>49. saithe.</hi> Arianorum renenum non portiunculam quandam, sed penè totum orbem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminauerat &amp;c. in ea nos tempora denenimus qua etiam excedant Ariani furoris con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusionem: non portiunculam vnam aut alteram error occupauit, sed totum corpus apostasia auertit à Christo.</note> error had possessed, not some or other litle porcion (of the churche) but had
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> auerted the whole bodie from Christ: with much<note n="(n)" place="margin">
         <hi>Caelius secundus</hi> curio in his booke <hi>de amplitudine regni Dei,</hi> printed 1554. <hi>pag.</hi> 212. <hi>post med.</hi> saythe. <hi>Factum est vt per multos iam annos Ecclesia latuerit, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uesque huius regni vix ab alijs, ac ne vix quidem agnosci po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuerit:</hi> and Caluine in his booke of epistles, printed. 1597. <hi>ep.</hi> 141. <hi>pag.</hi> 273. <hi>paulo post med.</hi> saith hereof: <hi>disces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionem à <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ote mundo facere coacti sumus:</hi> And maister Brightman. <hi>in apocalips. in cap.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 283. <hi>prope finem,</hi> answeringe our common demaund, where theire churche was before Luther, saith thereto, <hi>Ecclesia nostra ante Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fuit in abdito Dei sacrario,</hi> other instance he giueth none: also <hi>Ioannes Regius in libro apologetico</hi> &amp;c. printed in 4. Mulhusij 1603. <hi>pag.</hi> 176. <hi>circa &amp; post med.</hi> answeringe the same demand, saithe: The church was then inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible and could not be shewed. And maister Dent vppon the Reuelations, <hi>in cap.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 199. <hi>ante med.</hi> answeringe to the same demand, saithe. Christ (then) had his litle flocke in the wildernes &amp;c. without further naminge ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place or person. In so much as Luther himselfe in respect of this knowne want of any other originall protestant then before in beinge, to ioyne with him at the time of his first begunne pretended reformation, saithe as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth next heareafter. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>sect.</hi> 1. in the margine at l.</note> more no lesse fully affirmed by other learned aduersaries to the same purpose: In so much as Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer forbeareth not, heare vpon to tearme Luther,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Bucer. in epistola ad Episcopum <hi>Hereford.</hi> extant in his scripta Anglicana <hi>printed. 1577.</hi> pag. <hi>675.</hi> ante med. <hi>saithe,</hi> Lutherum primum purioris Euangelij ad nos epistolam honoris causa no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino.</note> the first Apostle to vs of the reformed doctrine, as also maister Iewell calleth Luther,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Maister Iewel in his defence of the apologie printed. 1571. <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>diuis.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 426. <hi>prope finem.</hi>
      </note> a most excellēt man euen sent of God to lighten the whole world: in the midst of darknes. And maister Foxe likewise saithe,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Maister Foxact. mon. printed. 1563. <hi>pag.</hi> 400. <hi>à fine.</hi>
      </note> it pleased the lorde to reforme and reedifie the desolate ruynes of his religion, by the industrie of Martine Luther, sent and set vp by the mightie spirite of God: whereto is further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he was the<note n="(r)" place="margin">see in the foresaid actes and monuments. <hi>pag.</hi> 416. <hi>à initio.</hi>
      </note> Helias conductor and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of Israel, to be reuerenced<note n="(s)" place="margin">
         <hi>Christus habet primas, habeas tibi Paule secundas, at loca post illos, proxima Luther habet:</hi> these verses ar commended for true and godly by Ciriacus Spangenbergius in his Duche booke against certaine catholickes, in the part thereof against Stephanus Agricola: And see further hereafter. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>sect.</hi> 4. <hi>fine at.</hi> *.</note> next after Christ
<pb n="8" facs="5"/> and Paule,<note n="(t)" place="margin">
         <hi>soe saithe,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreas Musculus in presat. in libellum germ. de diaboli ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannide. <hi>And see allso Amsdorphius conc. 8.</hi> de Luthero pag. <hi>88.</hi>
      </note> greater then whome liued not since the apostles times<note n="(u)" place="margin">
         <hi>soe is Luther tearmed by Cōradus Schlussel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge.</hi> catal. haeret. lib. <hi>13.</hi> &amp; vlt. <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 1596.</hi> pag. <hi>314. 316. 489. And Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell Neander</hi> in his theologia chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiana &amp;c. è fonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp;c. <hi>theandri</hi> Lutheri dictis &amp; testimonijs illustrata, <hi>printed Lipsiae. M. D. V C.</hi> pag. <hi>333. saithe.</hi> Lutherus vir Dei fuit, &amp; vere ille Angelus cum aeterno euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelio volans per medium caeli. Apoc. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> the Angell and last trumpett of God, whose callinge was<note n="(x)" place="margin">Maister Carthwright in Maister Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiftes defence, printed. 1574. <hi>tract.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>diu.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 217. <hi>circa med.</hi> saithe. When the churches haue bene by Antichrist euen razed from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, God hath styrred vp euangelistes euen immediatly by his spirite with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any callinge of men, to restore his churches againe, of which sort was &amp;c. Luther &amp; Swinglius</note> immediate and<note n="(y)" place="margin">Maister Parkins in his woorkes printed. 1605. <hi>fol.</hi> 916. <hi>à post med. &amp; b.</hi> affirmeth that the callinge of Wyclife, Husse, Luther, &amp;c. was extraordinarie. And see this pointe further <hi>in Aretius in locis commun.</hi> printed. 1589. <hi>loc.</hi> 63. <hi>de ministerio. pag.</hi> 198. <hi>circa med.</hi> and in Maister Fulkes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue against Bristowes motiues &amp;c. printed, 1580. <hi>pag.</hi> 300. <hi>ante med.</hi> and <hi>in Ioannes Lasciuius de Russorum Muscouitarum &amp; Tartarorum religione,</hi> printed. 1582. <hi>pag.</hi> 39. <hi>ante med.</hi> and <hi>in Daneus in Isagoges Christiana. part.</hi> 4. printed. Geneuae. 1586. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>initio.</hi>
      </note> extraordinarie, and his cominge especiallie<note n="(z)" place="margin">Michael Neander nexte heretofore at. p. and see this pointe further affirmed in the protestant booke entituled, <hi>Antichristus siue prognostica finis mundi,</hi> printed at Basile <hi>per Petrum Pernam. pag.</hi> 12. <hi>fine</hi> 13. <hi>fine</hi> 8. 86. <hi>fine.</hi> and in Mathias Hoe, <hi>in his tract. duo &amp;c.</hi> printed. 1603. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 136. <hi>initio,</hi> and <hi>in Conradus Schlusselberge in his catal. haeret. l.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; vlt.</hi> printed. 1596. <hi>pag.</hi> 314. <hi>&amp;</hi> 316. <hi>post med.</hi>
      </note> foreshewed in the scriptures. Maister Whitaker withall in such like respect professinge for himselfe and his brethren, to reuerence Luther as theire fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Maister Whitaker in his answere to the tenne reasons of Edmond Campian, Englished and printed 1606. <hi>rat.</hi> 8. <hi>fine &amp; pag.</hi> 259. <hi>prope initium,</hi> saithe. We reuerence Luther as a Father, and we embrace the Lutheranes and Suinglians as verie deare brethren in Christ.</note> In regarde of these so euident premisses, I will first begyne with Martine Luther, as beinge, the roote of that reformed alteracion in religion which is as before mencioned and pretended, in which respect I will also entreate of him more at large, with speciall reference in perticuler (as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb n="9" facs="5"/> is ministred) to the first edition of his workes concerninge those pointes wherein the later of Witemberge, or others, are now since his deathe confessedly<note n="(*)" place="margin">confessedly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, for Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius Fabricius a learned Lutheran in his collection of Luthers sayinges intituled, <hi>loci com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes Doct. Martini Lutheri &amp;c.</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 1594. in his preface prefixed therto <hi>circa med.</hi> professeth there to follow the first edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iena, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge there further concerninge the la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter edition of Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temberge, <hi>cur ab editione Witember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gensi discesserim cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sas habeo non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnendas.</hi> Hence it is that Westphalus (a learned Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran) <hi>in apol. contra Calum. cap.</hi> 46. <hi>pag.</hi> 458. chargeth Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine with most foule mutations &amp; corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ions made in certaine of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers workes trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Frenche and printed at Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua: and Luther himselfe <hi>in epist. ad Ioannem Heruagium typographum argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinensem,</hi> chargeth Bucer with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptinge of his woorkes: and Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radus Schlussel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge (a Lutheran of greate note) l. 2. Theolog. Caluine. printed 1594. <hi>fol.</hi> 56. <hi>b.</hi> chargeth the Caluinists with alteration of Luthers woorkes: and the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louse Lutheranes in theire Synode houlden at Altemburge, doe greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of such confessed corruptinge of Luthers woorks, as appareth <hi>in collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quio Altembergensi,</hi> printed. <hi>Anno</hi> 1570. <hi>in respons. ad excuss. cor fol.</hi> 127. <hi>b. circa med. &amp; in</hi> 2. <hi>collat. de Hypothesibus. fol.</hi> 353. <hi>b. circa med. &amp; in Hypothes. de libero arb. fol.</hi> 574. <hi>b. ante med. &amp;</hi> 575. <hi>a. post med.</hi> in soe much as greate contentions arose in Germanie betweene the rigid and softe Lutheranes, concerninge the corrupte edition of Luthers woorkes, whereof see Walterus <hi>contra Aurifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum, de corrupta editione operum Lutheri, anno</hi> 1566.</note> corrupted by the Lutheranes or Caluinistes, as therby either to conceall his grosse absurdities or otherwise, as in pretext of their owne errors: after which I wil (though but more briefly) touche those other branches, whoe yssuinge from Luther haue next to him succeeded in the ministrie of supposed reformation, as namely Iacobus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreas, Melancthon, Bucer, Bernardine, Ochine, Carolostadius, Suinglius, Caluine and Beza, of all whome (in regard most of them stand so priuileged with the applause and likinge of our present state) I will (as no lesse then carefull to auoyde offence) speake but sparingly and reseruedly purposely, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearinge to affirme or reporte any thinge of them as from my selfe, onely I vndertake for to deliuer what is confessed &amp; reported of them by our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aduersaries themselues. I do hereby once for all professe neither to extenuat nor make good, but whollie to refer the same vnto the discretion and Iudgement of eche indifferent reader: to whome this my ensuyinge discourse may perhaps afforde grater satisfaction, in that the argument thereof beinge not concerninge the truthe or vntruthe of questions of faithe, but of onely matter of facte, and the same also confessed by protestants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, it cannot be either peruerted into tropes, and so (as in other pointes vsually) euaded by fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue expositions, neyther yet auoyded or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted against, as deliuered from the testimonie
<pb n="10" facs="6"/> of men to vs affectionate, or but so much as sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected: for the more readie effectinge and perfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of all which, yt shall not seeme greeuouse, but much ease and saueinge of further labour vnto me, for to transcribe and digeste into this one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suinge peculier tract, what I finde sayde pertinente to this purpose, els where more dispersedly, and as all obscured with confusion of other matter, the recollected and enlarged substance whereof is briefly in order as followeth.</p>
   <trailer>The end of the Preface.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>