<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRAGEDY OF JVLIVS CAESAR.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106640_Fr4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106640</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRAGEDY OF JVLIVS CAESAR.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Recreations vvith the Muses : By William Earle of Sterline</title>
                 <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 253, 5, 326, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="185" facs="99"/>
   <head>THE TRAGEDY OF <hi>JVLIVS CAESAR.</hi>
   </head>
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T that time when the Romans travelled with an unsati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ambition to subdue all Nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, by whose over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw they could conceive any expectation, either of glory or profit: <hi>Caius Iulius Caesar,</hi> a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n of a lofty minde, and given to attempt great things, ascending by severall degrees to the Consulship, procured a power to warre against the <hi>Gaules:</hi> amongst whom, after a number of admirable battels and victories (by the approbation of all the world, having purchased a singular reputation both for his courage and skill in Arms) he being long accustomed to command, was so drunke with a delight of sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, that disdaining the simplicity of a private life, he was so farre from denuding himselfe of the authority which he had, that altogether transported with a desire of more, he sent to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>Gaules</hi> prorogated for five yeares: which suit being repugnant to the Lawes (as directly tending to tyranny) was by the people publikely repelled. By which occasion, and some others rising from an emulation between him and <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, pretending a high indignation, hee incontinent crossed the Alpes, with such forces (though few) as he had in readinesse, and with a great celerity came to <hi>Rome,</hi> which he found abandoned by <hi>Pompey,</hi> in whom the Senate had reposed their trust, whom shortly after, by a memorable battell in the fields of <hi>Pharsalia</hi> he discomfited: and having by the overthrow of <hi>Scipio,</hi> death of <hi>Cato,</hi> and flight of <hi>Pompeyes</hi> sonnes, as it were, rooted out all the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faction, hereturned to <hi>Rome</hi> and indirectly by the meanes of <hi>Antonius,</hi> laboured to be proclaimed King: which having rendred him altogether odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; <hi>Caius Cassius, Marcus Brutus, Decius Brutus, Publius Casca,</hi> and divers others (Noble men) conspired his death, and appointed a day for the same: at which time, notwithstanding that <hi>Caesar</hi> was disswaded from going forth, by many monstrous apparitions, and ominous presages; yet being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded by <hi>Decius Brutus Albinus,</hi> he went towards the fatall place, where the Senate was assembled.</p>
   <p>The Conspirators in like manner had many terrors: amongst others, <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> the wife of <hi>Marcus Brutus,</hi> although shee had insinuated her selfe in her husbands secret by a notable proofe of extraordinary magnanimity, yet on the
<pb n="186" facs="100"/>day dedicated for the execution of their designe, through the apprehension of his danger, she fainted divers times, whereof <hi>Brutus</hi> was advertised, yet shrinked not, but went forwards with his confederates to the appointed place, where they accomplished their purpose, every one of there giving <hi>Caesar</hi> a wound, and me a ground whereupon to build this present Tragedy.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>