<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106303_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12821</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106303</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Staffords Niobe: or His age of teares : A treatise no lesse profitable, and comfortable, then the times damnable. Wherein deaths visard is pulled off, and her face discouered not to be so fearefull as the vulgar makes it: and withall it is shewed that death is only bad to the bad, good to the good</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 201, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ifferent, or indifferent <hi>READER,</hi> Health to thy Soule and Bodie. Knoweing vertue to bee of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Sun, that is, she shines as well vpon the bad, as vpon the good; I thought the badde would claime interest in her, as
<pb facs="6"/>
well as the good. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent which, I wrote this treatise: in which I haue layed my selfe open to the world; to the intent, that I may attract the loue of the vertuous, and the hate of all those who continue vitious: for, I hold him to be no honest man, that is beloued of all men. For, in that, he sheweth that he can apply himselfe to the time, be it neuer so viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to the place be it neuer so infamous, to the person, be it neuer so odious. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I giue all men to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that I am a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to Vertue: which I
<pb facs="6"/>
proclaime to the world, by this booke, my Heraulde; and giue defiance to her foes and mine. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer I seeme, now and then, to lend an eare to lewdnesse; it is not that I take pleasure in it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I am loth to diplease the harbourers and diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of it. What soeuer the world thinkes of me, or thinketh me to be: yet this I am. For, being through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted with my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe, I doe not aske ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man what I am. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test it againe and againe, that I depend on Vertue. And, if I wax poore in her
<pb facs="7"/>
seruice, I shall account my selfe richer, then all this wicked worlds wealth can make me: and, if I growe rich without her, I shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme my self poorer then pouerty her selfe can make me. I speake not this, like a Politiciā, to purchase my selfe a greater fame then mine owne worth; No, no▪ We doe not dissemble in those things, in which he first deceiues himselfe, that would others. Wherefore he is iniurious to me, who wicked in himselfe fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a minde to me out of his owne. If my inward man excuse me, what care
<pb facs="7"/>
I, who accuse me? yet doe I not despise an honest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; but, onely warne you this, that it is not in my power to tye loose tongues. And therefore Fame is to be reckoned amongst these externall accidents; as of no moment to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of a quiet and a blessed life. What to be, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth on my part; what I am said to be, on the vaine vulgars. Fame and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science are of two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring properties: the one blazeth a mans deserts; yet makes him neuer the better: the other, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yet neuer the more
<pb facs="8"/>
renowned. I knowe, that my beliefe in God, and not the worlds beliefe of me, shall saue me: yet (by the way) would I not haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man thinke, that I write this by constraint; that is, to cleare my selfe of any imputed Crime: for, I write it not to dispossesse, but to possesse the world of a good opinion of me. I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thinke, that I haue layed my selfe too open, &amp; dealt too plainely in some things contained in this insuing treatise: but, I passe not much. For, as my birth styled me a gentleman; so I would haue my death
<pb facs="8"/>
stile me generous. Prying Policy telleth me, that it is farre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to knowe what a man speaks, then to speak what he knowes: but my harmelesse heart dictates to my pen, not what the world would, but what it should heare of. My soule is an Antipode, &amp; treads opposite to the present world. My intent, in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this book, is twofolde: first, to purchase to my selfe, not so much the title of a learned, as of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man; and secondly (because I knowe not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my vnfortunate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and vnstaied youth
<pb facs="9"/>
may leade me) that the world may be acquainted with the secrets of my soule, and may receiue from me a testimonie of my liuely faith; that so it may iudge the more chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably of mee being dead. Thus much for my selfe. Now, gentle or vngentle Reader; concerning thee, I diuide thee into Learned, and Vnlearned: and the Learned I subdiuide into Iudicial, and Not-indiciall. Seneca saith, that <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mū bonum in iudicio est,</hi> that <hi>mans chief felicity is in iudgement:</hi> and Seali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger calleth it <hi>Animamsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>the soule of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> And therefore he that hath this Wisedomes soule to be the Centre of his soule, I doe not so much feare, as reuerence his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. But hee that hath read neuer so much, and in his discourse will shoote whole Volleis of Volumes at a man, and yet wanteth iudgemente, my Booke turnes his posteriours to him, and bids him shoote there, as a marke too faire for his carping mouth, to aime at. The Vnlearned I rediuide into Prudent, and Impudent. The Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent will not let his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb facs="10"/>
flie aboue his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but, what he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands not, he will with modestie either passe it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, or with discretion en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after it, of some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-knowing spirits. As for impudent asses, who will reprehende vvhat their shallowe vvits can neither apprehende, nor comprehende, and so turne despaire into iudgement, I hold them fitter to read bills, and ballads, then my Booke. And withall I must needes adde this, that I neither feare a Stage, nor the censure of a Woman. And against the Learned,
<pb facs="10"/>
and Vnlearned, Iudiciall and Not-iudiciall, Prudent and Impudent, Women, and the worlds wide Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I bandy that of Iob,<note place="margin">Iob. 31. 35.</note>
      <hi>Behold my signe, that the Almightie will witness for mee; although mine Adnersarie write a booke against mee.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>