<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right Ho∣norable Nicholas Raynton, Lord Maior of this renowned Metropolis LONDON.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106209_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03228</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106209</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right Ho∣norable Nicholas Raynton, Lord Maior of this renowned Metropolis LONDON.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londini artium &amp; scientiarum scaturigo. Or, Londons fountaine of arts and sciences : Exprest in sundry triumphs, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honorable Nicholas Raynton into the Maiorty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious proiects both by water and land, being the sole vndertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Haberdashers. Written by Thomas Hayvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable <hi>Nicholas Raynton,</hi> Lord Maior of this renowned <hi>Metropolis</hi> LONDON.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the Dignity of your place, and Magnificence of your Inauguration: The first equaling, the latter precelling all the famous Magistracies in Christendome. I shall not much stand to dispute, as being a <hi>Maxim</hi> already granted: yet one thing I cannot omit, as most worthy remarke; namely, how many of like Iudicature haue borne the Sword in this famous and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Citty, who breathed their first ayre in the County of <hi>Lincolne</hi>; from whence you deriue your selfe, as Sir <hi>Iohn Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Mercer, borne at <hi>Bratost,</hi> L. Maior 1470. Sir <hi>Nicholas Ald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> Mercer, borne at <hi>Spalding,</hi> L. Maior 1499. Sir <hi>William Rennington</hi> Fishmonger, at <hi>Bosten,</hi> L. Maior 1500. Sir <hi>William Forman</hi> Haberdasher, at <hi>Gainsborow,</hi> L. Maior 1538. Sir <hi>Henry Hobbershorne</hi> Merchant-Tayler, at <hi>Wadingworth,</hi> L. Maior 1546. Sir <hi>Henry Amcoats</hi> Fishmonger, at <hi>Astrop,</hi> L. Maior 1548. Sir <hi>Iohn Langley</hi> Goldsmith, at <hi>Althrop,</hi> L. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior 1576. Sir <hi>Iohn Aldot</hi> Fishmonger, at <hi>Limbergh,</hi> L. Maior 1590. Sir <hi>George Bowles</hi> Grocer, at <hi>Gosperton,</hi> L. Maior 1617. and now in present your Honored selfe <hi>Nicholas Raynton</hi> borne at <hi>Heighington,</hi> L. Maior 1632. not so many hauing attained to the same Dignity bred in any one County, the City of <hi>London</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
excepted. Worthy obseruation it is also, that at one time in the raigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> most of the Prime Officers of State, were Country-men of the same County: As the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Canterbury, Whitguist:</hi> the L. High Treasurer of <hi>England,</hi> L. <hi>Burbeigh Cecill,</hi> the L. Keeper of the Great Seale, Sir <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uckering,</hi> Viz. Chamberlaine and Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the Dutchy, Sir <hi>Thomas Hennidge</hi> one of her Maiesties Priuy Councell: The Lord Chiefe Iustice, Iudge <hi>Wraye,</hi> &amp;c. Moreouer it may be iustly spoken of you to your great Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Honour, that since the yeere 1209. from <hi>Henry Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alwin</hi> the first L. Maior of this Honourable City, and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Duke,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Necle</hi> the first Sheriffes of the same, neuer had any Magistrate a more generall, free, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Election euen to this present Yeere 1632. Now Time and your owne Demerit Right Honourable, haue raysed you to this Eminence and Dignity, the vniversall eye and expectation of all men is vpon you, who well know, that a wise Magistrate preferres consideration before Conclusion: And (according to the saying of King <hi>Agesilaus)</hi> Magistrates who gouerne by iust Lawes, must strengthen them by good example: iudge by Prouidence, Wisedome and Iustice, and defend by Power, Care and Vigilance; and thus I humbly take my leaue of your Lordship with this Sentence, <hi>Non sat est te tuum officium fecisse, si non id fama approbat.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Seruant,
THOMAS HEYVVOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>