<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PRAEMONITION TO ALL KINDE OF READERS of these Translations of Iohn Owens EPIGRAMS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106081_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02836</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12974</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PRAEMONITION TO ALL KINDE OF READERS of these Translations of Iohn Owens EPIGRAMS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Quodlibets, lately come ouer from New Britaniola, old Newfound-land : Epigrams and other small parcels, both morall and diuine. The first foure bookes being the authors owne: the rest translated out of that excellent epigrammatist, Mr. Iohn Owen, and other rare authors: wit two epistles of that excellently wittie doctor, Francis Rablais: translated out of his French at large. All of them composed and done at Harbor-Grace in Britaniola, anciently called Newfound-Land. By R.H. sometimes Gouernour of the plantation there</title>
                 <author>Hayman, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Michell, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smethwick (Smithick, Smythicke), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64, 6, 58, that is 54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="39"/>
   <head>A PRAEMONITION TO ALL KINDE OF READERS of these Translations of <hi>Iohn Owens</hi> EPIGRAMS.</head>
   <l>AS one into a spacious Garden led,</l>
   <l>Which is with rare, faire flowers well garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,</l>
   <l>Where <hi>Argus</hi> may all his eyes satisfie;</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Centimanus</hi> all his hands occupy,</l>
   <l>He will chuse some fine flowers of the best,</l>
   <l>To make himselfe a Poesie at the least:</l>
   <l>Or he will, if such fauour may be found,</l>
   <l>Intreate some Slips, to set in his owne ground:</l>
   <l>So fares it with me, when in <hi>Owens</hi> booke,</l>
   <l>At leasure times, with willing eyes I looke:</l>
   <l>I cannot chuse, but choose some of his flowers,</l>
   <l>And to translate them at my leisure howres.</l>
   <l>But as 'tis not for this admitted Man,</l>
   <l>Manners at once to gather euery one,</l>
   <l>But mildly to cull a few at a time,</l>
   <l>I pray thee doe so too, kinde Reader mine:</l>
   <l>For as a Man may surfet on sweet meates:</l>
   <l>So thou maist ouer-read these quaint conceits.</l>
   <l>Some at one time, some at another chuse;</l>
   <l>As Maidens doe their kissing Confects vse.</l>
   <l>Reade therefore these, His; by translation, Mine:</l>
   <l>As some eate Cheese, a penny-waight at a time.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>