<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106960_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69022</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4137.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106960</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The baiting of the Popes bull. Or an vnmasking of the mystery of iniquity, folded vp in a most pernitious breeue or bull, sent from the Pope lately into England, to cawse a rent therein, for his reentry : With an advertisement to the Kings seduced subiects. By H.B</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>52, 95, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Readers,</hi> Lo here I invite you all to a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
<hi>Bullbaiting.</hi> But me thinks some already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
to quarrell me (as is not vnusuall at such like
exercises) for that they see no such <hi>Bull,</hi> as the
<hi>Baiting</hi> importeth; the <hi>Title</hi> seeming improper for the
<hi>Booke;</hi> as if I meant to feed the spectators with the vaine
expectation of some <hi>New English ioy.</hi> Indeede I must in
some sort acknowledge mine errour, which I hope will not
be made the greater, if I shall ingenuously confesse it to
be purposly committed. I imagined with my selfe (onely
I craue pardon, if I thought amisse) that we lived in a dull
age, which is hardly moved with the consideration of seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
matters, such as most concerne either our owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
or much lesse the generall good; when not the
Drummes orderly beaten, and Trumpetes, yealding <hi>a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
sound,</hi> yet will easily awaken, or prepare vs for the
warre; while not even the <hi>Siluer Trumpets</hi> sounding from
Heauen in the mouthes of divine <hi>Heralds,</hi> prevaile any
more with the most, then as <hi>a pleasant Song,</hi> affecting the
eare for the present, but not the heart, <hi>for afterwards,</hi> each
<hi>running</hi> after his covetousnes, or ambition, or voluptuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
or some darling Idol-sinne; and for as much as matters
of controversie (not in Law-suits at <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> but)
about the Title of our eternall Inheritance, are strongly
cryed downe of many, as perturbers of States, most men,
out of a naturall lasinesse, loathing to haue their witts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised
with a radicall &amp; sound knowledge, their stomacks
being too queasie to digest such strong and wholesome
meates, preferring the <hi>Aegyptian onYons</hi> before the hony of
<hi>Canaan,</hi> and willing to fall a sleepe, are taken napping in a
deepe apostacy from the truth: I thought therefore, that if
I should haue published this little Booke (though great in
Bulke, if weighed, rather then numbred) vnder some plaine
<pb facs="20"/>
and vulgar Title, as, <hi>An answere to the Popes Breeue;</hi> or the
like: I might perhaps haue had as few Readers of it, as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
of a Sermon, especially, when the Authors name
should be found to be <hi>H. B.</hi> Herein therefore, I thought
good to imitate a certaine Father (mentioned by <hi>Cassianus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cassianus lib. 5. cap. 31. Dialog. lib. 2. cap. 1.</note>
and quoted by Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> in his <hi>Dialogue of comfort
against Tribulation)</hi> who speaking of <hi>heaven and heavenly
things so celestially, that much of his audience with the sweete
sound thereof, began to forget all the world, and fell fast a sleepes</hi>
the good Father dissembling their sleeping, and suddenly
telling them a lowd, <hi>I shall tell you a merrie tale:</hi> at this, <hi>they
lifted up their heads, and harkensd after that;</hi> and so their sleep
being broaken, he continued on his speech of the Ioyes of
heauen; and thus were they reproved. Nor is this <hi>Papall
Bull,</hi> or <hi>Breeue,</hi> altogether vnlike our <hi>English Bulls.</hi> For
first, it is the Character of the <hi>Beast Renel.</hi> 13. Besides, it
comes bellowing in, like a fierce and mad <hi>Bull,</hi> with a
Board over the eyes and hornes, betokening his madnesse,
but pretending no great harme; so full it is of <hi>Romish</hi> equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations,
and <hi>Papall</hi> dissimulations, meaning most mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe,
when it is most dissembled.</p>
   <p>Another snaps at me on the other side, that such a poore
<hi>Curre</hi> should dare so much as to barke at such a <hi>Bull,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
sent from so great a Potentate, as the <hi>Pope;</hi> much lesse
so presumptuously to giue an affront vnto it: sith such
high attempts are for the stoutest and strongest<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Molossus,</hi> is a Mastiue dogg.</note>
      <hi>Molosss</hi>
in this famous Isse. But I answere, that even the poore
dogg of the flocke, espying the <hi>Woulfe</hi> approaching, may
and ought to barke, yea and pinch him too, if he can, the
while his Lord and Master is fast a sleepe in his Tent. And
we know, that when but one small contemptuous <hi>Curre,</hi>
smelling a thiefe, falls a barking, though he can doe little
else, yet thus may he provoke all the Doggs and Mastiues
in the towne with eagernesse even to breake their collart
to run to the rescue. I am indeede but a poore dogg of the
flocke, in comparison, but sacred, one among many, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
to keep watch over the <hi>Capit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l</hi> and <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>Sion.</hi>
      <pb facs="20"/>
Should I therefore be a dumbe dog, such as the<note n="*" place="margin">Esai. 58. 10, 11.</note> Prophet
reproveth, not to barke it danger? Or a dastardly <hi>Curre,</hi>
which snaped, dare not barke for feare of strokes? Or a
lawning spanolizing <hi>Spaniell,</hi> silenced with a fatt morsell,
or a little spettle? Or an <hi>Irish mongrell,</hi> or <hi>English,</hi> if ye will,
that will not adventure his hide, but ever on the stronger,
not with the Iuster side? Or a maddrageing <hi>Curre,</hi> that
without difference barkes at all, as well the true man as the
thief? Worthy, if not (as the old heathen <hi>Romaines</hi> served
such foolish dogs) to haue his leggs broken, yet at least to
be well basted for his paines, as whose dulnesse hath beene
no better disciplined, to put more difference betweene
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Another yet pincheth me. And why? Hee knoweth
not well, except it be for making so many, so voluminous
Epistles before such a poore Pamphlett, as this. And is it
altogether without reason? At so famous a <hi>Bull-baiting,</hi>
had wee not need to make large, and well mounted Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds,
wherein all sorts of persons may both the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily,
and safely behold it, having especially to deale with
such a madd Bull, as a thousand to one, but he will breake
loosse, and make havocke, if hee be not the more strongly
tyed, or the more cautelously avoyded?</p>
   <p>But why doe I thus <hi>seeke a knott in a Bulrush?</hi> Is there any
doubt, but that launching out my Bark into such a turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
sea, I should so much the more expose my selfe, and
expect on all sides to bee incountred with violent stormes?
And so much the rather, while I carry a <hi>Ionas</hi> with me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
my selfe a man, whom God hath humbled into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
bottome of Temptations, the very <hi>belly of Hell?</hi> But bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
be his Name, though he hath chaftened mee sore, yet
he hath not giuen me over vnto death. Though hee hath
exposed me to contempt without, to my humiliation: yet
he hath left me abundant cause of comfort within, to my
contentation, He hath sent the <hi>messengers of Satan to buffet
me:</hi> but he hath not denied me his <hi>sufficient Grace, to perfect
his strength in my weaknes.</hi> He hath <hi>of very faithfulnesse caused
<pb facs="21"/>
to be tronbled.</hi> Hee is the wise <hi>husbandman,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
to <hi>spread doung</hi> vpon the face of the naturally <hi>barren
soyle,</hi> to make it the more <hi>fruitfull.</hi> He is the wise <hi>Phisici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
that spareth not by sharpe <hi>Corrosiues</hi> to eat out the dead
<hi>flesh</hi> or carnall sloth and security in his <hi>Patitrus.</hi> Hee is the
wise <hi>Pilot,</hi> that can make vse of <hi>baser earth</hi> for <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> to
pieze the <hi>vessell</hi> wherein the least pearle of grace is stowed,
least it might bee in danger to bee over throwne with the
gusts of popular applawse, filling the sayles of vaine glory.
Hee is the wise <hi>Howse-keeper,</hi> that knowes to preserue his
<hi>Prouision</hi> from putrifaction, by sowcing it in brinish pickle.
Hee is both a just and mercifull wise <hi>Iudge,</hi> who can deliver
vp his servants so to bee condemned of the world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
they may not come to bee <hi>Condemned with the world.</hi> And as
for me, wherein the world can for the least cawse most se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely
condemne me justly: my best apology shalbe, that I
doe infinitely more condemne my selfe. And if through
my exposing myselfe to malice, by taking vp such a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
quarrell as this, I shall exasperate the tongue of detraction
to sucke the pure bloud of my innocency: I know it shall
in the end but lick whole the sacrified sore, which malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
teeth haue envenomed. And if it should stand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
Gods glory, and mine ignominy, that the one must
suffer: I choose much rather, by running on my Christian
course, to provoke all the <hi>Froggs</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> to diue into the
bottome of my whole liues rivulet, there to rayse what
mud they find to the blundering of the streame of my good
name in Christ: then by my silence (becomming as a
stagne or pond, not stirring, for feare of discovering mine
owne filth, which would be contracted in more abundance,
through base and imbellious sloth) to betray Gods truth
and glory to reproch. And God forbid, but if in any thing,
(as in many things I am, and haue beene too prone) I haue
offended my God or my brother, that therefore I should
feare to stand vp (though most vnworthy) in Gods cawses
yea rather am I not so much the more bound (his mercy and
grace not fayling me) to striue to honour God, by how
<pb facs="21"/>
much I haue through supine negligence any way disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
him? But if the heretick haue ought to say, let him
heare <hi>Tertullian: Eximat et de ocule suo trabem Haereticus, tunc
in oculo Christiani, si quam putat stipulam, revincat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But why doe I all this while hold you, in suspense? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
your eyes to the danger before you, threatned by the
Popes <hi>Bull</hi> or <hi>Breeue.</hi> Therein yee may behold the great
Antichrist, arming his <hi>Catholicke sonnes</hi> (as hee calls them)
against their <hi>Souerains Prince.</hi> My hope and prayer is, that
none of them will bee so senselesse, as forgetting themselues
to be not onely Rationall Creatures, but English-men, they
will be led with the voyce of that mysticall Beast (the<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Hiena,</hi> a most subtile Beast, like a Wolfe, with a Mane like a horse, which by nightcommeth to the simple Shepherds Tents, where counterfeiting mans voyce, &amp; by listening learning the Shepherds name calls him forth, &amp; so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoures him <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> A right Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of the Pope. See <hi>Reu.</hi> 9. 8.</note>
      <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>
of <hi>Rome,</hi> which by a counterfet speech, deceiueth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth
those that belieue him) to betray theyr King and
Countrey to the <hi>Romish</hi> and <hi>Spanish</hi> yoakes. Much more am
I assured, that all true Protestant subiects, will now rowse
vp themselues to double the <hi>Fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> of their loyall affection
and fidelity to theyr Prince and Countrey, testified, as in
all due respects, so especially both by <hi>Ministers</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>
in the publicke assemblies in servent prayer, as also by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
private family apart in fasting and humiliation, for the
life and welfare of our gratious King, this Church and state,
and of the Churches of Christ in all Christendome, vntil it
shall please God and the King to appoint a generall <hi>Fast</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the whole land. For great is the confidence of <hi>Antichrist,</hi>
and his Adherents at this present, whatsoever the mischiefe
is, clossely intimated in this Breeue. But we know,
that all the confidence of Antichrist, is but an <hi>Egyptian Reed;</hi>
onely our safety and security is to cleaue fast vnto our God
by faith, to renue our <hi>Covenant</hi> with him by holy vowes of
reformation &amp; better obedience, &amp; to make good the same
by bringing forth the <hi>fruits</hi> therof: that so making our peace
with God▪<note place="margin">Zeph. 2. 1.</note>
      <hi>before the Decree bring forth,</hi> we may not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
the evils which our enemies intend vs, and which our
crying sins threaten to pull vpon vs, but also procure &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
Gods incomparable mercies &amp; blessings vpon vs, &amp; our
Posterity, vntil the comming of Iesus Christ, <hi>Euen so, Come
Lord Iesus.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <signed>Thine in the same
Lord Iesus: H. B.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>