<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Grounds and Reasons of Times Com∣plaint against the Rebellious Scots.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106432_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11385</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21643.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106432</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Grounds and Reasons of Times Com∣plaint against the Rebellious Scots.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The complaint of time against the tumultuous and rebellious Scots : Sharpely inveighing against them (as most justly they deserve) this yeare, 1639. by W.S</title>
                 <author>Saltonstall, Wye</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Grounds and Reasons of <hi>Times</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint against the Rebellious <hi>Scots.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THis Land (God be thanked) is blest in the happy Government of a most gracious King, against whom in despight of Mercy divers aff<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>onts have lately beene offerd by the Rebellions Scots, who under pretence of Religion would ouerthrow the Hierarchy of the Church, pulling downe the house of God, and building Babels of their owne invention, and man'd with this furious zeale, they have raised great forces, and stand ready armed in the Field to resist the head of the Church in his Dominions our most gracious King CHARLES; <hi>Time</hi> therefore hearing how these bold Attempts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Title of Covenanters bad acted many outrages, entrencht vpon the Kings So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne power, and have hitherto neglected and slighted his Royall authority; therefore in this complaint of <hi>Time</hi> some reasons are laid downe. For the Chronicles of this Land due witnesse that Rebels have beene alwayes overthrowne in their designes, and at last met with a deserved Death. Thus <hi>Mortimer</hi> who rebelled against King <hi>Edward</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and violently tooke away his Queene, was afterwards himselfe taken and behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Also those rude mechannicke Rebels that were led under the conduct of <hi>Watt Tiler, Tom Miller,</hi> and <hi>Iack Strae</hi> made a great tumultuous vproare in <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Essex,</hi> untill Sir <hi>William Walworth</hi> than Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> did with his Dagger stabbe <hi>Iacke Straw</hi> in <hi>Smith-field,</hi> whereupon the Dagger was set in the Armes of <hi>London.</hi> The rebellion for <hi>Perkin Warbek</hi> was soone disanimated, and the Imposture discovered, and so likewise <hi>Iack Cade</hi> and his associates were soone confounded and overthrowne, and punished according to their Deserts. And thus Rebellion is like that <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> or that phantastick apparition of fire, which running under hedges doth affright Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people, but having blazed a while, it is soone dissipated and extinguished. The <hi>Scots</hi> therefore cannot promise to themselves any better fortune than their rebellious Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, who were soone scatter'd and confounded, and their leaders received condigne punishment. If therefore any precise Humorist that accounts himselfe a transcendant Protestant, and a <hi>Goliah</hi> in Religion▪ when indeed he is an Hypocriticall Puritane, if any such doe thinke the complaint of <hi>Time</hi> against the <hi>Scots</hi> is too Satyricall▪ I would have him know, that the Rebellion of the <hi>Scots</hi> as it is haynous in its owne nature, and deserves a sharpe vindication and revenge, so it also hath cast an aspersion vpon <hi>Time,</hi> for both the City and Country doe find fault, that it is a very hard, dangerous and doubtfull <hi>Time.</hi> And some in regard of this unnaturall Rebellion say, <hi>Time</hi> declines and growes worse, and that many discentions, Divisions and Rebellions shall happen in the old Age of <hi>Time,</hi> unto all which accusations <hi>Time</hi> doth make answere with one old ancient Verse▪</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <hi>Conscia mens recti famae mendacia ridat.</hi>
      </l>
   </q>
   <q>
      <lg>
         <l>The Conscience that is cleere from spot or stayne,</l>
         <l>Laughs at the false reports of flying Fame.</l>
         <l>Time did not cause the <hi>Scots</hi> rebellious factions,</l>
         <l>Which breaking forth in <hi>Time, Time</hi> blames their Actions.</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>