<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reading Artist.</title>
           <author>P., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106514_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16362</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3279</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reading Artist.</title>
                 <author>P., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chyrurgians closet: or, an antidotarie chyrurgicall : Furnished with varietie and choyce of: apophlegms, balmes, baths, caps, cataplasmes, causticks, cerots, clysters, collyries, decoctions, diets, and wound-drinks, desensatiues, dentifrices, electuaries, embrocations epithemes, errhines, foments, fumes, gargarismes, iniections, liniments, lotions, oyles, pessaries, pils, playsters, potions, powders, quilts, suppositaries, synapismes, trochisces, vnguents, and waters. The greatest part whereof were scatteredly set downe in sundry bookes and papers; by the right worshipfull Mr. Thomas Bonham, Dr. of Physick; and now drawne into method and forme, by Edvvard Poeton of Petworth, (late and long seruant to the foresaid Right Worshipfull Dr.) and published for the benefit of his country, and the helpe and ease, of young practitioners in the ancient, necessarie, and noble science of chyrurgerie</title>
                 <author>Bonham, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 359, 29 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the reading Artist.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, as by former passages you may perceiue the graduall generation of this Worke, so as it being now come to your hands; know that it is more for vse, then delight, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse you delight in what is vsefull: what's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse in it, I pray you pardon; what may serue your turne, vse. The following Table will direct you both to the malladie, and the medicine. The Lord blesse, guide, and prosper you: I onely intreate acceptance of my good-will, with your prayers for me. From my Chamber in <hi>Petworth,</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Sussex.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, E. P.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>