<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
           <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106591_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04374</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14488</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106591</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians apparelling by Christ : Where is shewed in three parts: 1. The happinesse, honour, aud [sic] confortable estate of all true Christians: with the wretched estate of all others. 2. The duetie it selfe, with particular directions. 3. The triall and examination of our selues by distinctiue notes. By R.I. B.D</title>
                 <author>Jenison, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 546 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Christian READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He glory of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is communion with his Maker, and likenesse vnto him; this <hi>Adam,</hi> when hee came newe out of Gods hands, had, and inioyed, vntill by his fall hee, and we,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.23.</note> in him were depriued of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God; wherupon it is said, <hi>they knew themselues naked;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 3.7.</note> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked indeed, not only in body, but in soule, stript of that bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Image, wherby they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented their Creator, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in holines; wherupon God if
<pb facs="9"/>
he had not regarded his owne mercy more then their desert, might haue turned them and their posterity naked into hell. But our gracious God, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the glory of his mercy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other attributes, and willing to bee knowne in his Church by that name of grace mercy, goodnes, &amp;c. aboue all other names, sent his Son clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with our nature, that wee might againe bee partakers of the diuine nature. God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came one with vs, that wee might be made one with him, and hath enriched our nature with all grace, by marrying it to himselfe, that so hee might conforme his mysticall body (his Church) to his owne bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed soule and body in all holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, in that measure hee hath
<pb facs="9"/>
thought fit: only it is necessary for vs to see the beggery wee are borne in, hauing not a rag of sauing goodnes to hang vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs to couer our shame, that so wee might be forced to get into Christ, &amp; out of the rich wardrope of his obedience, be furnished with such Robes, as might not only couer our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, but likewise adorne vs and set vs out to the liking of our Sauiour, that hee may take pleasure in our beautie, and might be armour likewise vnto vs to stand out against all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; outward oppositions: Him God hath made the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like treasury of the Church, in him all fulnesse dwels, that out of it wee might receiue grace answerable to the grace in him; resembling him,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.16.</note> not as an
<pb facs="10"/>
Image doth a man in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward lineaments only, but as a sonne doth his father in nature and disposition:<note place="margin">Esai. 9.6.</note> he is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of eternitie, to whom we must be like in holinesse, as we desire to bee like him in happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and can wee more desire to bee like any, then him by whom we looke to be saued? We see men studie the dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of those they hope to rise by, and carnall men cast themselues into the mould of the times, fashioning their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, language &amp; demeanor to the liking of those they hope to be aduanced by: but a Christian is of a higher and more noble breed, and knowes the worlds fashion to bee the basest fashion, &amp; crosse to the liking of the Father;<note place="margin">Iohn 2.15.</note> he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="10"/>
that hee is predestinate to bee like to Christ, vnto whose image now we are conformed, and not to the image of the first <hi>Adam.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> Hee knoweth that whatsoeuer good is in vs, is first in Christ,<note place="margin">Iohn 17.19</note> who therfore <hi>sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himselfe,</hi> that we might be holy; and therefore he indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoreth neerer vnion and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to put him on First, in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, that so being cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with garments of our ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brother, wee, may finde grace in our Fathers sight, and stand vpright before God in him, who is made of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther righteousnesse vnto vs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. And wee take him as offred of the Father to vs by the hand of a particular faith; for Christ profiteth not, as
<pb facs="11"/>
considered in the broad cloath (if wee may so speake) but as suted &amp; fitted to vs by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying hand of Faith. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause whosoeuer is in Christ, is a new creature; therefore he aymeth in the second place, to put Christ on in Spirit &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation, to bee like minded vnto him in meekenes and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, (as who can be proud, when hee beleeueth God was abased for him?) and to put on the same bowels of loue and mercy, to count it his meat and drinke to doe Gods will, as hee did, going about doing all the good hee could, and oft considers with himselfe what affections and intentions his Sauiour would haue vpon such and such occasions, what hee would doe if hee were on the
<pb facs="11"/>
earth, and what hee did in the dayes of his flesh, and vnto this patterne he fashioneth his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: this accompanieth the former; for none are cloathed with his Righteousnesse, but are likewise cloathed with his Spirit. Therefore our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries wittingly slaunder vs, when they inforce vpon vs such conceits, as if we seuered the imputed righteousnesse of Christ from the inward work of sanctification, and made a iustified man, like the deuill, appearing as an Angel of light; and like a Blackamore couered with a white linnen garment. No, not so, wee know that as Christ saueth his Church, so hee purgeth it, that hee may present it to himself a glorious Church. And as he performed
<pb facs="12"/>
the Law for vs;<note place="margin">Ephes. 5.20</note> so will he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it in vs. By looking with the eie of faith on his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful loue to vs, discouered in the Gospel, we are trāsformed frō glory to glory, frō one degree of grace to another.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.18.</note> It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible that that soule that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer felt peace &amp; ioy, by the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactiō &amp; obedience of <hi>Christ</hi> for vs, but with cōceiuing <hi>Christ</hi> thus louing and grcious in his heart, hee should haue the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of these graces that are in our blessed Sauiour. In what heart soeuer he is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in, he fashioneth it alwaies like to himselfe. Indeed those loose professors that are led with the spirit of the world, &amp; haue little of Christianitie in them but Baptisme, suppose a Sacramentall putting on of
<pb facs="12"/>
Christ (with a powerlesse pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, which they may take vp, and lay aside at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as they do their garmēts) to bee ynough: but the true learning of Christ is a deeper matter then so, there must bee an indeauour to put off our whole selues, &amp; haue nothing in vs of our own, but what we thinke, desire, speake, or doe, should euer sauour of the spirit of Christ; which who wanteth is none of his, &amp; by the which whosoeuer is indued with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from aboue, it will raise his soule aboue it selfe, and make it firme &amp; impregnable against all temptations, either on the right hand or the left, &amp; carry it strongly through all duties. A meer humane spirit can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe or suffer any thing:
<pb facs="13"/>
but hee that is clothed with a more excellent spirit then his owne, is more then a man, and in Christ can <hi>doe all</hi> things that are required in the couenant of grace.<note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> How should this sharpen our desires of being more and more filled with the fulnesse of Christ? especially, considering we must all lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side these garments of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in the dust, and appeare shortly before him; and then he will owne none for his, but such as beare his Image: A fearefull thing it will be to bee found in his case that is not found in Christ; that hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Christ in him: for the pure eyes of God cannot look on him, but as an obiect of his wrath, and fewell of his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, which wil borne to hel.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>As we desire to hold vp our heads with ioy, and not to lye open and naked, exposed to all the stormes of his displeasure, wee must labour to put on whole Christ, and weare him close to our soules. Euery day we gather new staines, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery day wee must wash our garments in his blood, and appeare before God clothed with him, that hee may looke on vs with a forbearing eye.<note place="margin">Iohn 3.29.</note> Those friendes of the Bride therefore deserue well of her, that lay before her her owne nakednes, and the vnsearchable riches of Christ, that shee may bee drawne out of her selfe, to an admiration of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Christ, and shine in his beames,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.</note> and trample whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is glorious in the world
<pb facs="14"/>
vnder her feet, seeing nothing ere long will bee glorious but Christ and his Spouse.</p>
   <p>Hitherto tendeth this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of this godly Minister, whom for his soundnesse in Iudgement, faithfulnesse in friendship, painefulnesse in his calling, &amp; integritie of his life, I haue much esteemed euer since our first acquaintance in the Vniuersitie: I can there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (Christian Reader) with the more confidence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to thy reading, and both thee, and it to Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Richard Sibbs.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>