<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106969_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17306</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4153</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106969</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plea to an appeale : trauersed dialogue wise. By H.B</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 93, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian</hi> Reader, <hi>I present thee here with a</hi> Plea <hi>to an</hi> Appeale. <hi>That</hi> Appeale <hi>I meane styled,</hi> An Appeale to Cesar. <hi>Which is such, as I confesse (sauing for the Titles, wherein I find the Sacred name</hi> of Cesar) <hi>I had filed my feete, rather then my hands with it, if after my long frustrate expectation of seeing it burned, I had not, to my great wonderment, seene the contrary, namely, that it found so many friends and favorites. Besides sundry things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which at first might haue passed onely for errours, as fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from some distemper of hastie passion: being now stoutly and stiffly, in cold blood, defended, they grow to be flat</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, <hi>and so no further to be tollerated, as</hi> S. Augustine <hi>spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. For my owne part, when I perused the booke, my spirit was not a little stirred in me, to see Gods glory defaced, our Salvation vndermined, our Church scandalized, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish</hi> Arminianisme <hi>triumphing, even vpon the open Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Faine would I haue beene dealing with it, but both the consciousnes of my many both naturall disabilities, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall infirmities, as also the hope I had of so many my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and able elder brethren (who I trusted would, and still hope will, vindicate at least their deare Mothers credit, the Church of</hi> England) <hi>held me backe. Notwithstanding at last (though the least of all) I gaue the on-set</hi> (nec tardum oppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens, nec praecedentibus instans) <hi>as, well knowing, that</hi> Hosanna <hi>is accepted of Christ, as well from the mouthes of little children, as of others; Yea, and sometimes, (if those</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
should hold their peace, the very stones would cry. <hi>And where as not only my personall imperfections, but my naturall corruptions also stood vp to disswade me from such a Taske: yet even from them also, did I draw motiues vnto it. First, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I thought my example of shewing willingnesse to my weaknesse, might provoke the more able, to be the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to supply my wants. Secondly, out of the sense and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of my many corruptions, that</hi> Law in my members, leading me <hi>(miserable!)</hi> captiue to the law of sinne; <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving such abundant experience of that</hi> superabundant grace <hi>of God, which hath mightily borne me vp even against the streame of rebellious nature, so that</hi> when my foote slipped, his mercy held me vp: <hi>I have learned hereby how deepely I am bound to expresse my thankfulnes to God, in setting forth to the vttermost of my power,</hi> the praise of the glory of his Grace, sufficient <hi>for me, against those</hi> thornes <hi>in my</hi> flesh, <hi>against those</hi> buffering messengers of Satan, <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to overthrow me, if the Lords never fayling grace had not made me to stand. Yea how many stormes of temptations hath my brittle barke indured, yet blessed be God, it is not wracked. Those Reliques of rebellious</hi> Canaanites <hi>dwelling in me, as</hi> thornes in my side, <hi>and</hi> pricks in myne eyes, <hi>by Gods grace humble me onely, overcome me not. So that God having put in my hand, such a tryed weapon of infallible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of his saving grace: I should be very ingratefull to let it lie rusting in the sheath, and not to use it with my best strength, courage and skill, against the adversary of this grace, who saith, that the Child of God ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> fall away</hi> totally, <hi>and</hi> possibly also finally from grace and justification. <hi>Which one Heresy overthroweth the whole tenure and truth of the Gospell; it turneth vpside downe the very foundation of our salvation, grounded vpon Gods eternall loue, in Electing and
<pb facs="8"/>
Predestinating vs in Christ to Grace and Glory, those</hi> gifts and calling of God without repentance; <hi>it revineth (directly in part, and by consequence, altogether) that wicked heresy of the</hi> Pelagians, <hi>noted by the Reverend Bishop of</hi> Chichester, <hi>and the worshipfull</hi> M. Francis Rovs, <hi>two noble champions of Gods Truth; it comes close vp also to make a league with the Councel of</hi> Trent, <hi>to truck with</hi> Rome, <hi>in all that fard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ll of Apostaticall doctrines, packed vp in the sixt Session of it, as of</hi> Freewill, Iustification, Predestination, Cortaintie of salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Perseverance in grace &amp;c. <hi>In which poynts and many more of that nature, coincident to the doctrine of</hi> Iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>the subiect of that whole Session, I had</hi> (I confesse) <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taken some paynes, in setting downe the true difference betweene vs, and the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>in this mayne funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall. And having the Treatise by me, already finished, and priviledged also, (while the season served) for the Presse, onely prvented by the last visitation: I haue ben the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take this new occasion to borrow at least some Artillery from that greater worke, to encounter these fresh Assaults, made against the Truth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And see, how the same motiue, that put me vpon the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer worke, hath drawne me also to this. Shall I tell the plaine truth? Why not? But I must name Doctor</hi> Francis White <hi>then, and discover something, which passed betweene him and me in private. But this I hope shall not violate the Law of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, sith I shall say no more, but what himselfe, in his</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation <hi>prefixed to the</hi> Appeale, <hi>hath not stuck to make open profession of to the world. It is this, I having about foure yeares agoe, taken a thorow survey of the sixt Session of the Councel of</hi> Trent, <hi>and finding therein</hi> Romes <hi>Apostacy from the faith of Christ cunningly couched: I tooke occasion (simply suspecting nothing, as then) to goe to the said Doctor, wishing
<pb facs="9"/>
he would vndertake so worthy a Taske, as to declare fully the true difference betweene vs and the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>in the doctrine of</hi> Iustification, <hi>according to the Councel of</hi> Trent. <hi>But his answer was, that the difference was but small between vs. I wondring at his answere, No Sir, said I, then let vs shake hands with them, and be good friends. For on this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation stands the maine fabrick of</hi> Romes <hi>Religion, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in humaine satisfactions and merits, all devised to fill vp the vast emptines of their</hi> Iustification, <hi>from which Roote they all, as branches, doe receiue life and growth. Yet to be sure, another time I propounded the same question vnto him; his answere was the same; and so was my reply.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Hereupon, farre aboue my strength, I tooke courage to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that taske my selfe, leuelled against</hi> Pontifician <hi>and</hi> Arminian <hi>Doctrines ioyntly all along: and now againe am I no lesse, if not much more, iustly prouoked, to reuiew and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue something of that former worke, being spurred thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, more (I confesse) by Doctor</hi> Whites Approbation, <hi>then Master</hi> Mountagues Appeale. <hi>Nor, in such a Cause, am I a whit moued with the name and fame of Doctor</hi> White. <hi>He is a learned man, I confesse; but Truth is better learned. Hee is an ancient graue Diuine, crowned with an hoary venerable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; true: but</hi> Salomon <hi>saith,</hi> The hoary head is a crowne of glory, if it be found in the way of righteousnesse. <hi>And howsoeuer the world may value Truth according to personall respects: yet God is no Accepter of persons.</hi> My brethren <hi>(saith Saint</hi> Iames) haue not the faith of our Lord Iesus Christ, the Lord of glory, with respect of persons. <hi>He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes those, that in points of faith, preferres the</hi> Gold-ring, <note place="margin">Tertul de Praescript aduersus hareticos. lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="5 letters">
            <desc>•••••</desc>
         </gap> mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>the soft or white</hi> rayment, <hi>before the</hi> poore man Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>saith,</hi> Quid si Episcopus &amp;c. What if a Bishop, if a Deacon, if a Widdow, if a Virgin, if a Doctor, if also a
<pb facs="9"/>
Martyr, shall fall away from the Rule: therefore shall hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies seen e to obtaine the truth? Ex personis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus fidem, an ex fide personas? Doe we approue the faith by the persons, or the persons by the faith? Nemo sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens &amp;c. No man is wise, but hee that is faithfull; none great, none a Christian. Nemo autē Christianus &amp;c. And no man is a Christian, but hee that shall perseuere vnto the end. Auolent, quantum volent, paleae leuis fidei &amp;c. Let the chaffe of light faith fly away as fast as they will, with euery breath of temptation, the cleaner heape of graine shall be laide vp in the Lords Garner. Nonne &amp;c. Did not some of the Lords Disciples forsake him, being scandalized, and offended with his Doctrine? Yea was not Iudas the Traitor one of the twelue Apostles? <hi>What then, if any great Doctor, yea or Bishop fall away from the faith, they once professed? Is this a sufficient proofe, that Gods saints may fall away totally or finally from sauing grace and iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Will any</hi> Appealer, <hi>or his Approuers make this good by their owne examples of falling away? No, saith Saint</hi> Iohn, <hi>cited by</hi> Tertullian <hi>in the foresaid place,</hi> Phigellus, Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes, Philetus, and Hymeneus forsooke the faith; they went out from vs, but they were not of vs; for if they had beene of vs, they would no doubt haue continued with vs; but they went out, that they might bee made manifest, that they were not all of vs. <hi>And why wēt they out? Saint</hi> Iohn <hi>a little before admonisheth Gods children to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the loue of the world; whereupon he giueth them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Apostates; inferring, that the loue of the world drew them away.</hi> Demas <hi>forsooke</hi> Paul, <hi>and</hi> imbraced this present world. <hi>So easie a thing is it for a louer of the world to fall into all heresy, the God of this world hauing blinded his eyes? Therefore when we see a starre shoote, as the vulgar call
<pb facs="10"/>
it: doe we, as they, thinke it to be a very starre, falling from the firmament? Nothing lesse. We know it to be nothing else, but an earthy slime, falling to the earth, whence it ascended in a vapour. For earth will to earth.</hi> Stella cadens non est stella, cometa suit. <hi>Such acry vapours then, when you see am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiously mounting aloft towards the vpper part of the lowest heauen, well may they shine there for a time like starres, but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile not when you see them fall backe againe; they were no true starres.</hi> Sacerdotium, quod intus cecidit, diu foris stare non potest. <hi>It was</hi> Gregory <hi>the greats saying of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious simoniacks. Was</hi> Iudas <hi>once in the state of grace &amp; iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, because he was an Apostle? Indeede</hi> Andreas Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>one of the champions of the</hi> Trent <hi>Councell, puts him downe f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> an in instance, that the Elect may fall away finally from grace: because Christ said,</hi> Haue not I chosen you twelue? Iudas then <hi>(saith he)</hi> was one of the Elect. <hi>But as</hi> Saint Augustine <hi>answereth well,</hi> it is one thing to be elected to the office of Apostleship, another, to the fellowship of the <note place="margin">Quaest. su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 1. qu. 117. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 4. and in Psal. 55.</note> Saints. <hi>For there is, as a twofold vocation, so a twofold elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion; externall, and internall; temporary, and eternall.</hi> Iudas <hi>was of the externall and temporary, but not of the internall and eternall election. For of this, Christ said elsevvhere,</hi> I speake not of you all; I know whom I haue chosen. <hi>There Christ puts a plaine difference between</hi> Iudas <hi>an elect Apostle, &amp; the rest, who were also elect Saints. But how came</hi> Iudas, <hi>an elect Apostle, to fall away? hee was a theefe, and bare the bagge. Yet he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ught not his Apostleship, he was elected by Christ. He had a faire, and lawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l calling. Yet his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse brought him to Apostacy, and euen to betray the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood of the Lambe of God. Then wonder not at the Church of</hi> England. <hi>The sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e</hi> Rebecca <hi>brought forth as well a rough</hi> Esau, <hi>as a smo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th</hi> Iacob. <hi>And, as</hi> Tertullian
<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>saith to the same purpose,</hi> Of the kernell of the milde, and fat, and vsefull oliue, doth spring the rough wilde oliue: and of the most pleasant, and sweete figges seede, doth grow the windy, and empty wilde figtree. So heresies <hi>(saith hee)</hi> haue fructisied of that, which was ours, but they are not ours, being degenerate from the graine of truth, and by lyes become wilde. They went out from vs, but they were not of vs. <hi>What then, if wee shall see some of the Apostles, or such as would bee accounted Apostolicall, to proue Apostaticall from the faith? shall this stumble Gods Saints? Or shall an impotent admiration of their persons draw beliefe to their heresies? God forbid. For as the same</hi> Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian <note place="margin">Tertul ibid.</note>
      <hi>(for I finde not an acuter authour for this purpose) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring champion-like hereticks to wrastlers, or sword players, which many times ouercome, not by their owne strength, but by the others weaknesse:</hi> no otherwise <hi>(saith he)</hi> doe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies preuaile ouer the infirmities of men, but haue no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at all vpon a sound faith. <hi>Yea, of what qualitie or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty soeuer hereticks be, whether for personall, or politicall res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, the holy Ghost warnes the Saints to auoid, and contemne them.</hi> Auoide an hereticke, <hi>saith the Apostle. And St.</hi> Iohn, <note place="margin">2. Iohn 10.</note> If there come any vnto you, that brings you not this Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, receiue him not to your house, neither bid him God-speede: for hee that biddeth him God-speede, is parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his euill deedes. <hi>And Saint</hi> Paul <hi>doubles his admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> If an Angel from heauen preach vnto you any other <note place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Gospell, then that which we haue preached vnto you, let him be accursed; which is not another Gospell; but there be some that trouble you, and would pervert the Gospell of Christ. <hi>Into this condemnation be the new Pontifician</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian <hi>(shall I say Hereticks? I need not, if they persist; I will not, if they</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">As Master <hi>Mountag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> hath fairly promised, laying, though he may erre, yet he will be no He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Church of <hi>England Appeale c 1. p. 4. &amp; p.</hi> 9.</note>
      <hi>recant, and desist) Approvers of the Councel</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>of</hi> Trent <hi>fallen: the doctrine whereof is a fowle and flat Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy from the Mystery of godlines. They would bring in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gospell, though no Gospell, but they would obtrude it far the true and only Gospell of the Grace of God. And if the</hi> Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians <hi>were said to be fallen from Christ, onely for mingling Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision with the Gospel, as requisite with faith to their iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: how fearefull is that Apostacy from Christ, which quite ouerthroweth the effectuall and free grace of God, excluding, yea, accursing the true sauing faith, in our iustification, as the Doctrine of</hi> Trent <hi>doth; so dangerous it is, to be any way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary by yeelding the least assent vnto it. And what execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heresies will these proue to be, that goe about to pluck vp the tree of life, by the roote, out of the Paradise of Gods Church, and would plant instecde thereof, the forbidden tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, teaching and perswading the eaters, that they are made thereby as Gods, selfe-sufficient, selfe-wise, selfe-able to saue themselues, not onely in their receiuing, but retaining grace, which worke of their owne wills being foreseene of God, was (say they) the first mouing cause of electing and praedestinaring them to saluation? which what is it else, but a meere making voide of Gods vnchangable Decree of Praedestination, and free grace of Election, no farther fixed and certaine, but as mans receiuing and retaining of grace, and perseuering therein is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, which (say they) is vncertaine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pardon my zeale, gentle Reader. Impute it not to any bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse of spleene. I beare it not to any mans person liuing, God is my record, much lesse to the Authours of the</hi> Appeale, <hi>and the</hi> Approbation. <hi>I know none whom I hate more, then my sinfull selfe. But the Lord knowes, it is no small greife to me, that I am thus forced to sharpen my style. Which if it seeme tarter to thy Palate, then may sure with Christian moderation and modesty: examine I pray thee, whether the long custome of
<pb facs="11"/>
Court-smoothing, and eare-pleasing, specially in Diuine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, haue not bred such a delicacy in the soules tast, as that downe right zeale for Gods glory, can hardly finde a slomack to take it downe, or digest it, but is reiected as a bitter pill, or potion, of such Patients, as account the remedy worse then the disease. Zeale will not passe now but for fury, or rude incini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, at the best. But</hi> ab initio non erat sic. <hi>In old time, it was lawfull to</hi> call a spade, a spade. <hi>Saint</hi> Peter <hi>dealt roundly</hi>
      <note place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>with</hi> Simon Magus <hi>for his Simony,</hi> Thy money perish <note place="margin">Acts 13.</note> with thee. <hi>How sharpe was</hi> Paul <hi>with</hi> Elimas <hi>the Sorcerer, for going about to</hi> turne away the Deputy fiō the faith? O full of all subtilty, and all mischiefe, thou child of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, thou enemy of all righteousnesse &amp;c. <hi>And what would he haue said (trow we) to those men, who goe about to</hi> turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, <hi>not a</hi> Deputy, <hi>but a whole</hi> kingdome, <hi>&amp; a well settled flourishing</hi> Church, from the faith? <hi>What if they were graue &amp; learned Diuines? So much the worse.</hi> If an enemy had, done this, <hi>it had ben more tolerable;</hi> but it was euen thou, my guide, and familiar freind. <hi>I will not adde</hi> Dauids <hi>impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but rather aduise them, as</hi> Peter <hi>did</hi> Simon, <hi>to</hi> pray, <hi>that</hi> if it be possible, <hi>the sinne, not of their heart onely, but of their hand, may be forgiuen. How did</hi> Paul, <hi>though but a young Apostle, reproue the prime Apostle</hi> Peter, <hi>onely for a matter of dissimulation in his conuersation, not any default in his preaching? And shall wee not zealously</hi> resist <hi>those</hi> to the face, <hi>that, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> now dissemblingly anymore, but with opē professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, approue, auow, &amp; stafly maintaine grosse and greiuous here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, deuised by the Deuil, to betray Gods glory, and mans sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? That sticke not to call the Doctrinas of Pradestinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, freewill, and the like,</hi> Scholasticall speculations meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, questions of obscurity, not fit for pulpits, and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar eares; but procuring rather discord and troubles in
<pb facs="12"/>
Church and State, then serue to edification, &amp;c. (Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale pag. 42. 78. 80.) <hi>Which speeches, and the like, whether doe they tend, but to suppresse those Doctrines of the Gospell, whereby God is most glorified, and man most humbled? shall we spare such? When</hi> Policarpus <hi>met</hi> Marcion <hi>the hereticke ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Euseb. lib. 4 cap. 14.</note>
      <hi>and neglecting him, was asked of him, Dost thou not know vs? He replyed,</hi> I know thee for the Diuels eldest childe. <hi>Such was the zeale of holy men in times past, against, not onely those that were Hereticks, but hinderers of the truth. The Apostle wished, that those false teachers of legall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, were euen</hi> cut off, <hi>which</hi> troubled <hi>the Church of</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia. <hi>Therefore what cause any faithfull Minister of Christ hath to vse sharpnesse of stile to seditious seducers, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of Church and State, in so famous a Kingdome, in so peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a season too, let any indifferent man iudge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And consider iudicious Reader, if we had not a King, seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from his very cradle with the knowledge of the true faith of Christ, hauing now growne vp therein to a goodly ripenesse, in regard whereof we haue small cause to suspect his constancy herein: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>to what danger were we, and Gods religion brought, when such kind of Ministers are not wanting to helpe forward the reerecting of the Romish</hi> Baal <hi>in our Land, had they but a young</hi> Manasses <hi>to restore the</hi> Altars <hi>and</hi> Groues, <hi>which the good King</hi> Ezechiah <hi>his Father had pulled downe?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But to conclude: sith these two fore named Worthies, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be named againe, the Reuerend Bishop of</hi> Chichester, <hi>Dostor</hi> Carlton, <hi>and the Worshipfull Maister</hi> Francis Rovs, <hi>haue so learnedly and zealously confuted some materiall points in the</hi> Appeale <hi>(which like expert archers, making speciall choyse of for their marke, they haue hit home) although I could haue wished, that they had with no lesse felicity coped with the rest of the materialls in the booke: yet sith they haue ben plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="12"/>
to leaue behind them some liberall gleanings, yea some whole ricks of tares to be cut vp, and carried away from Gods wheat field: I will craue leaue, to shew at least my good will in all, hoping my defects will finde pardon of all them, who though they can, yet forbeare to make their best supply. The</hi> blasphemer <hi>was to be</hi> stoned <hi>of the</hi> whole Congregation, <hi>some hitting one part, some another, till he were beaten downe, and buried vnder the heape.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Yet in this Impression, the</hi> Plea <hi>reacheth no farther, then the</hi> first part of the Appeale. <hi>Which if it finde courteous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, the other part is forth comming, and wants but time, to helpe the slownesse of the Presse to bring it forth. Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
H. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>