<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ These thynges ensuynge are ioyned wt this present vo∣lume of the bible.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1539</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106968_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10392</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106968</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ These thynges ensuynge are ioyned wt this present vo∣lume of the bible.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most sacred Bible : whiche is the holy scripture, conteyning the old and new testament, translated in to English, and newly recognised with great diligence after most faythful exemplars, by Rychard Tauerner</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Byddell, alias Salisbury, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1539</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, ccxxx, lxxxxi, 1, lxxv, 1, liiii, lxi-ci, 3 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="miscellaneous_features">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ These thynges ensuynge are ioyned w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this present vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of the bible.</head>
   <p>An exhortacion to the studye of the holye scripture, gathered out of the Bible.</p>
   <p>The summe &amp; content of all the holy scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> of the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e and new testament.</p>
   <p>The names of all the bokes of the Bible with the content of the chapters.</p>
   <p>Abriefe rehersall declarynge how longe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ndured from the creacion of Adam vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his present yere of our Lord <hi>M.D.XXXIX.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>A table for to fynde manye of the chyefe and principall maters conteyned in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>☞ An exhortacion to the diligent studye of the holy scripture gathered out of the Bible</head>
      <p>
         <label>Christ vnto the people. Iohn̄ .v.</label> Serche the scriptures: for they are they that testifye of me.</p>
      <p>
         <label>Paul to Timothy, ii. Tim .iii.</label> Al scripture gyuen by inspiracion of God is profitable to teache, to improue, to amend and to instruct in ryghtousnesse, that the mā of God maye be perfecte and prepared to al good workes.</p>
      <p>
         <label>The same to the Rom .xv.</label> What thynges so euer are wrytten, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re wrytten for our lernynge: that we thorowe pacience and comfort of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scriptures, might haue hope.</p>
      <p>
         <label>Salomon Prou .xxx.</label> All the worde of God, is pure and cleane it is a shyld vnto them that put their trust in it. Put nothinge vnto his wordes, lest he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the, and thou be found a lyar.</p>
      <p>
         <label>Moses to the people. Deu .xii.</label> Ye shall not doo euerye man what semeth hym good in his owne eyes: But what soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I commaunde you that take hede ye doo, and put nought thervnto, neither take ought therefrom.</p>
      <p>
         <label>The Lord vnto Iosua. Ios .l.</label> Let not the boke of this lawe departe oute of thy mouth: But recorde therin daye and nyghte, that thou mayste be circumspecte to doo accordynge to all that is wrytten ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For then shalte thou make thy waye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous, and then shalte thou haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge. Turne there from neyther to the ryght hande, ne to the lefte: that thou mayst haue vnderstandynge in all that thou takest in hande.</p>
      <p>
         <label>The same to the people. Exo .xiii.</label> And thou shalte shewe thy sonne at that tyme, saying: This is done bycause of that whiche the Lorde dyd vnto mē when I came oute of Egypte. Therfore it shall be a signe vnto the vpon thyne hande. and a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce bytwene thyne eyes, that the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des lawe maye be in thy mouthe. For with a stronge hande the Lorde brought the oute of Egypte.</p>
      <p>
         <label>Moses Deut .xxxi.</label> Se that thou rede this lawe before all Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeli in theyr eares. Gather the people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther: bothe men, women and chyldren, and the straūgers that are in the cities: that they maye heare, lerne, and feare the Lorde youre God, to kepe all the wordes of this lawe.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>