<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE YOVNG LORD, VVILLIAM, LORD HARBERT of Cardiffe, sonne and Heyre apparant to the right Honorable Earle of Pembroke. Robert Barret wisheth increase of all Honour and vertue.</title>
           <author>Barret, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106853_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04863</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1500</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106853</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE YOVNG LORD, VVILLIAM, LORD HARBERT of Cardiffe, sonne and Heyre apparant to the right Honorable Earle of Pembroke. Robert Barret wisheth increase of all Honour and vertue.</title>
                 <author>Barret, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theorike and practike of moderne vvarres : discoursed in dialogue vvise. VVherein is declared the neglect of martiall discipline: the inconuenience thereof: the imperfections of manie training captaines: a redresse by due regard had: the fittest weapons for our modern vvarre: the vse of the same: the parts of a perfect souldier in generall and in particular: the officers in degrees, with their seuerall duties: the imbattailing of men in formes now most in vse: with figures and tables to the same: with sundrie other martiall points. VVritten by Robert Barret. Comprehended in sixe bookes</title>
                 <author>Barret, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 247, 7 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE YOVNG LORD, VVILLIAM, LORD HARBERT of Cardiffe, sonne and Heyre apparant to the right Honorable Earle of Pembroke. Robert Barret wisheth increase of all Honour and vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Noble young Lord, and of honourable expectation, although your yong yeares, haue scarse arriued yet to the bearing of Armes, neuerthelesse on the assured hope conceiued of your honorable parts, as so nobly each way descended, (whose vertue hath alwayes shined to the glorie of your name and house) I haue emboldened my selfe to offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordships view and protection, these Military dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, penned vpon occasion of conference had with sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Gentlemen, and by them wished to be published. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good reasons haue moued me to dedicate them vnto your Lordship, as well in respect of your owne vertues (resembling altogether that Noble Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> your Graund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and that worthie Sir <hi>Phillip Sidney</hi> your Vncle) as also in respect of the great and waightie Commandes which your Right Honourable father doth worthily hold ouer vs, in these our Westerne parts and VVales, vnder our dread Soueraigne. Such as they are, I humbly beseech your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to accept, as from a souldier, who humbly offereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his seruice vnto your selfe, next vnto my good Queene and deare Countrie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships humbly at command ROBERT BARRET.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="4"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>