<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRAGEDY OF DARIVS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106640_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106640</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRAGEDY OF DARIVS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Recreations vvith the Muses : By William Earle of Sterline</title>
                 <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 253, 5, 326, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="37"/>
   <head>THE TRAGEDY OF <hi>DARIVS.</hi>
   </head>
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ARIVS,</hi> the fourteenth from <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> being after the death of <hi>Occhus,</hi> for his singular valour, from the government of <hi>Armenia,</hi> advanc'd to the <hi>Persian</hi> Empire, became so arrogant (a good successe as it were, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to confusion) as he sent to demand tribute of <hi>Philip</hi> then King of <hi>Macedonia</hi> who being of a hauty nature (and inferiour to none of that age in courage, or for melitary discipline) requited this contumelious message, with as disdainefull an answer; threatning that he would come and deliver it in <hi>Persepolis.</hi> But being prevented by death, he left the execution of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe to his sonne <hi>Alexander,</hi> who for the great victories which thereafter he obtained, was surnamed the great: He inher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ting the hatred of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Father to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Darius,</hi> and farre surmounting h m in ambition, past in person to <hi>Asia,</hi> with an army of thirty thousand men onely.</p>
   <p>After his arr vall, <hi>Darius</hi> wrote to him in a proud and contemptible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ascribing to himselfe the title of the King of Kings, and kinsman of the Gods, and nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng <hi>Alexander</hi> his servant; Hee also in vaunting manner, bragged that he would have the mad boy, the sonne of <hi>Philip</hi> (for so in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>armed him) bound, and beat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n with roddes, and after brought to his presence apparelled like a Prince. For performance whereof he directed one of his Minions, with forty thousand men to make impediment to his passage at the River of <hi>Granick,</hi> where by the wonderfull valour of <hi>Alexander,</hi> they were overthrowne.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Darius</hi> being advertised of this, came himselfe in proper person, accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with infinite (but evill ordered) numbers, and encountred <hi>Alexander</hi> beside <hi>Isso,</hi> in the strait of <hi>Cili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>a</hi> where having fought doubtfull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy battell, in end by the invincible valour and never-failing forture of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> his Army was defeated, himselfe put to fight, and his mother, wife, and children made captives. Who were most courteously entertained by <hi>Alexander,</hi> who notwithstanding their exceeding great beauty, yet would not abuse them, nor suffer them to bee abused by others: nor ves<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed he them more then once (and that to comfort them) all the time of their imprisonment.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Darius</hi> notwithstanding of all his losses (his courage being in the full, whilst his fortune was in the waine) wrote very proudly to <hi>Alexander,</hi> taking still the title of a King to himselfe, but not giving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> gold, as <hi>Macecon</hi> could containe, for ransome of the captives. Which being
<pb facs="38"/>very disdainfully refused by <hi>Alexander</hi> he having re enforced his troupes, and comming forward to fight with greater force then before, was informed how his wife had died in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>son, whose death he bewailed with exceeding great sorrow. And understanding what courtesie <hi>Alexander</hi> had used towards her, he sent to use for peace, not for any feare of his force, but allured (as he alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) by his courtesie. This sute being likewise rejected, he fought beside <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> with no better fortune then before.</p>
   <p>Yet for all these misfortunes, being of an invincible courage and despairing of peace, he re-assembled all his forces which were augmented by the comming of the <hi>Bactrians,</hi> and was comming forward, with intention at last either to dye, or prevaile. But in the meane time, two traiterous subjects of his owne, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssus,</hi> whom he had preferred to be governour of <hi>Bactria,</hi> and <hi>Nabarzanes,</hi> one in speciall credit with him, conspired his death. Which danger, though it was revealed to him by <hi>Patron,</hi> Captaine of the Greekes, yet he could not, or rather would not eschew. At length, those two Traitours tooke, and bound him with golden chaines, and cast him in an old Chariot, with purpose to present him to <hi>Alexander.</hi> But they hearing how he would not accept their Present, and how he was comming to invade them, threw their darts at <hi>Darius,</hi> and left him for dead. In this estate he was found by <hi>Polystratus,</hi> and after the delivery of some few words dyed. <hi>Alexander</hi> having exceedingly lamented his miserable and undeserved end, directed his body to his mother <hi>Sisigambis</hi> to be honour ably buried.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>