<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the mercifull Christians inhabiting in or about Banbury.</title>
           <author>L., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106612_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15012</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25316</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the mercifull Christians inhabiting in or about Banbury.</title>
                 <author>L., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The poore mans advocate, or, A treatise of liberality to the needy. Delivered in sermons by William Whately minister of Banbury</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Edwards, George 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 179, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the mercifull Christians inhabiting in or about <hi>Banbury.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmes</hi> in Greek comes from a word that sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> whence the Latine <hi>Eleemosy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> French <hi>Aulmosne.</hi> English <hi>Almes ab</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>misereer.</hi>
      </note> because all our <hi>almes</hi> should proceed from a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and pittifull heart, in the Hebrew<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack tongue it is called <hi>righteousnesse,</hi> as if it were by right due to the poore.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.27.</note>
      <hi>Withhold not they
<pb facs="6"/>good from the owners thereof,</hi> so the orginall runs.<note place="margin">Pro. 11.18.</note>
      <hi>To him that soweth righteousnesse, shall be a sure reward.</hi> Therefore hath the Author of this ensuing Treatise by demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strative arguments proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the necessity of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and fully answered the sophismes and seeming ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections which the wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wit of man will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to invent and urge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst its performance. Hee hath laid downe likewise certaine rules to direct men how rightly to give, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed meanes to inable them, and added motives
<pb facs="7"/>also to quicken them to this laudable worke. And as hee most frequently and earnestly presseth this duty upon the consciences of his hearers, so he shewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to them in this (as in all things,) <hi>a patterne of good works,</hi> Tit. 2.7. His holy life is a true counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane of his doctrine, he hath a purse for the poore as he adviseth others to have, and giveth the tenth as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts others to give. Well knowing, that it is the duty of a Minister that would bee found faithfull both <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 2 Tim. 2.15. &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> Gal. 2.14. to
<pb facs="7"/>teach and to tread the way to Heaven.<note place="margin">Phil. 4.9.</note>
      <hi>Those things</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>which yee have both learned and received, and heard and seene in me, doe.</hi> More might I say with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either falsehood or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, but this will bee thought too much by him who thinkes so meaneby of himselfe, that this very Worke was almost extorted from him with importunate solicitations. The poore hee pleadeth for, are not such as are strong and able to labour for their living, but such as are weake, impotent,<note place="margin">Esay 5 d. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>at. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 5, 36.</note> and unable to take paines, and
<pb facs="8"/>there are three degrees of such needie persons. <hi>1.</hi> Some are utterly destitute of all the meanes of preservation of life, these we are bound (saith a Learned Divine) to relieve out of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to our state, since the life of our neighbour is more to be esteemed then our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward state. Others are in great need having but little to maintaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves or theirs, we are bound to relieve these out of those things which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to the decency of our state. A third sort have something,<note place="margin">Occurere est succur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere.</note> but yet not that which is sufficient or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent,
<pb facs="8"/>wee are bound to relieve them out of those things which are superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the decency of our state. For order of relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>coeteris paribus,</hi> other things being equall, wee must relieve such as are in greater necessity. Secondly, n the like ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity those are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to which we owe most love, as those that are neare to us in blood before those that are far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of, <hi>Mat. 15.5, 6.</hi> the poore of our owne familie,<note place="margin">Deut 15.7</note> towne and countrey before strangers, <hi>1 Tim. 5.8.</hi> the houshold of faith before
<pb facs="9"/>the ungodly, <hi>Gal. 6.10.</hi> This scattering <hi>Prov. 11.24.</hi> is increasing, this is no spending but a <hi>lending,</hi> Pro. 19.17. no laying out, but a <hi>laying up.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luke 12.33.</note> It is a blessed thing thus to give,<note place="margin">Plus pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tibi cansert quam á te accipit. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Acts 20.35.</hi> the gift will prove more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the giver then to the receiver, if thou givest a penny, the poore man gives thee a good prayer and blesseth thee in the name of God, of which <hi>Iob</hi> made great reckoning, <hi>Iob 20.13. &amp; 31.20.<note place="margin">Pro. 22.9</note> And for this thing God will blesse thee in all thy workes,
<pb facs="9"/>and in that thou putst thine hand unto,</hi> Deut. 15.10. and blesse thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, <hi>Psal. 37.26.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 10.5 <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Pro. 11.25. Eccles. 11 1. Mat. 5.7. Heb. 13.16. 2 Cor. 9.6.</note> Our charitable actions ascend up to bee a <hi>memoriall</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, or a standing monument and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, as the word signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, wee shall heare of them at the resurrection, <hi>Luke 14.14.</hi> God hath made many ample sweete and precious promises to the mercifull, to reward them abundantly, <hi>Pro. 11.25. Mat. 10.41, 42. Luke 6.38. Heb. 6.10.</hi> He hath promised Temporall blessings <hi>they shall not
<pb facs="10"/>lacke,</hi> Prov. 28.27. <hi>They shall have comfort in sicknesse, and bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> Psal. 41.1, 2, 3. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, <hi>Breaking off of sinnes</hi> and <hi>pardon,</hi> Dan. 4.27. <hi>Perpetuity of righteousnesse,</hi> Psal. 112.9. Eternall, <hi>A certaine treasure in heaven,</hi> Luke 13.33. <hi>Receiving into everlasting tabernacles,</hi> Luke 16.9. <hi>Possession of eternall life,</hi> Mat. 25.34. Oh let us therefore <hi>doe good, bee rich in good workes, ready to distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, willing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, 1</hi> Tim. 6.17.
<pb facs="10"/>Beneficence to men is there expressed in the variety of foure Epithets, both to shew the vehement intention of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> desire of good workes, and the important ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, this if wee doe,<note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note> wee may <hi>lay hold on eternall life,</hi> as hee there addes, may bee as sure of it as if wee had it. Let us give then that which wee cannot keepe, that wee may gaine that which we cannot loose.<note place="margin">Luke 16.9</note>
      <hi>Let us make to our selves friends of the Mammon of unrighteousnesse, that
<pb facs="11"/>when wee faile, they may receive us into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting habitations.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true Christian friend, <hi>E. L.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>