<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVor: THO: HIGGONS, Doctor of Divinitie, an ear∣nest Favourer of all good and law∣full Intentions: W. BORASTON wisheth all Prosperitie both now and euer here∣after.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106525_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3372</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106525</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVor: THO: HIGGONS, Doctor of Divinitie, an ear∣nest Favourer of all good and law∣full Intentions: W. BORASTON wisheth all Prosperitie both now and euer here∣after.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A necessarie and briefe treatise of the contagious disease of the pestilence : with the causes, signes, and cures of the same. Collected and newly composed for the benefit and comfort of the vulgar sort. By W. Boraston</title>
                 <author>Boraston, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVor: THO: HIGGONS, Doctor of Divinitie, an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Favourer of all good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Intentions:</hi> W. BORASTON wisheth all Prosperitie both now and euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He most Mighty <hi>ELOHIM,</hi> Creator of all things, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our grievous Sinnes, and haynous transgressions against his Precepts and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinances, haue threatned his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to inflict vpon them, the plague of Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and divers other Sicknesses, as Holy and Divine writ testifieth. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the foresaid Afflictions and manifold Diseases wherewith for our sinnes, from
<pb facs="3"/> time, to time wee haue beene often pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished; Wee haue not perceived (by reason of the custome of sinning) how horrible the rust and Canker of Sinne is, vntill GOD out of his wrath powreth againe his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the offenders, and thereupon haue not onely inflicted man which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally haue transgressed, but also all other creatures which were created and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for mans vse, and haue caused the Starres to cast downe there venomous influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vpon his creatures, in regard we would not repent and acknowledge the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse of our corrupt nature, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue farther in the middest of all our inflictions of the Plague of Pestilence ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through want of Charitie or diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hate haue sought to infect others, for which I would wish all so euill disposed, to preuent the punishments ordained for them which are so presumptuous, for as <hi>CRATO</hi> saith, <hi>Qui malitiosè pestifera diffundit, homicida est proximi sui, &amp; paenas non modo aeternas sibi luendas sciat, Sed in
<pb facs="3"/> hoc etiam seculo Magistratus seueritatem experietur.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And euen as this wickednesse and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate blindnesse is of all men to bee abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; So the vnmeasurable Mercy of GOD purchased through Contrition, Penance and Satisfaction is to be imbraced, Seeing that he in the middest of all our abhominations and deseruings of extreame punishments, haue euer remembred them which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite of heart, and sorrowfull for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and losse of GODS fauour, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them hee haue yeelded compassion, and haue infuded blessing vnto Hearbes, Stones, and Metals, for their recouerie and cure of all their Malladies, as well also for nutriment as preseruation.</p>
   <p>So that wee may plainly see that GOD taketh not any delight in punishing his creatures, but rather to make vs know how detestable a thing sinne is, for by it wee often loose his diuine Fauour and Grace, So we ought with all diligence by Humility and Obedience to obtaine the same againe,
<pb facs="4"/> and to frame our course of life thereafter, that we may returne to him as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>thfull and obedient Children.</p>
   <p>Now euen as they which with study and trauaile haue sought out the wonderfull Workes of God in the Firmament, are to be commended; So deserue they not the least praise, which haue indeauoured to find out the properties and vertues of such things which may comfort and succour the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities of their distressed Neighbours, And in regard the Plague of Pestilence is so ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible vnto humaine Nature, that it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times separateth the Father from the Child, the Husband from the Wife yea the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian from his Patient, and one friend from another, for their owne safety, as is suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, I therefore receiuing my Talent at the last houre, would not negligently bury it in a Muckhill.</p>
   <p>But for the reasons aboue-specified, I thought it not amisse (let busie speakers ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then dooers babble what they please) to bestow s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me paines in setting forth som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/> directions and Remedies for them that are subiect to the foresaid contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sicknesse; especially, for them which are not able to fee the Physitians and Chyrurgians. And in regard I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes found loue and receiued friendship, at your Worships hands; I now farther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume vpon your fauor, and right godly iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with desire to accept of this my poore Dedication in good part. And pardon the boldnesse of your poore Neighbour in this attempt, and he shall euer rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your Worships command, W: B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>