<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL the Master, Wardens, Assistants, and Brotherhood of that antient, vsefull, and noble Societie, the medicine Chyrurgians; the principall members of that Societie, or Corporation of the Barber Chyrur∣gians of London, EDVVARD POETON of Petworth wisheth all happinesse in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Poeton, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106514_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16362</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3279</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL the Master, Wardens, Assistants, and Brotherhood of that antient, vsefull, and noble Societie, the medicine Chyrurgians; the principall members of that Societie, or Corporation of the Barber Chyrur∣gians of London, EDVVARD POETON of Petworth wisheth all happinesse in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Poeton, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chyrurgians closet: or, an antidotarie chyrurgicall : Furnished with varietie and choyce of: apophlegms, balmes, baths, caps, cataplasmes, causticks, cerots, clysters, collyries, decoctions, diets, and wound-drinks, desensatiues, dentifrices, electuaries, embrocations epithemes, errhines, foments, fumes, gargarismes, iniections, liniments, lotions, oyles, pessaries, pils, playsters, potions, powders, quilts, suppositaries, synapismes, trochisces, vnguents, and waters. The greatest part whereof were scatteredly set downe in sundry bookes and papers; by the right worshipfull Mr. Thomas Bonham, Dr. of Physick; and now drawne into method and forme, by Edvvard Poeton of Petworth, (late and long seruant to the foresaid Right Worshipfull Dr.) and published for the benefit of his country, and the helpe and ease, of young practitioners in the ancient, necessarie, and noble science of chyrurgerie</title>
                 <author>Bonham, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 359, 29 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL the Master, Wardens, Assistants, and <hi>Brotherhood of that antient, vsefull, and noble Societie,</hi> the medicine Chyrurgians; the principall members of that Societie, or Corporation of the <hi>Barber Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians of London,</hi> EDVVARD POETON of <hi>Petworth</hi> wisheth all happinesse in this life, and eternall felicitie <hi>in the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right worshipfull,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowen vnto the most of you, that I was a long, (and the last) seruant, vnto the Right Worshipfull, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. THOMAS BON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. of Physick; (and one of the Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants of your noble Societie,) who whilest he liued was to me a Master, yea more, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at his death a bountifull Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor; for he gaue and deliuered vnto mee before he dyed, all his Manuscripts, both of Physicke and Chyrurgerie: the which being knowne vnto sundrie of your Societie, they requested the sight, suruey, and copies of them, or of such of them as they should best like; whereunto I yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But being drawne forth of the City, vnto the place where I now reside; the opportunitie of satisfying their request, and performing my promise was cut off. But not forgetting what I had promised, as leysure would permit: I gradually composed this present Worke, and haue procured it to be prest for your seruice. If there be any thing in it that may accommodate but the Iunior sort of your Societie; I shall be glad. If not; I pray you accept my loue therein, and I shall for euer rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in his best Deuotions, EDVVARD POETON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>