<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Hic sequntur Miscellanea. ¶ Here followeth the mixt annotations vppon the preface going before.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106822_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16838</idno>
           <idno type="STC">374</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106822</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Hic sequntur Miscellanea. ¶ Here followeth the mixt annotations vppon the preface going before.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ptōchomuseion [sic] . = The poore mans librarie : Rapsodiæ G.A. Bishop of Exceter vpon the first epistle of saint Peter, red publiquely in the cathedrall church of saint Paule, within the citye of London. 1560. Here are adioyned at the end of euery special treatie, certaine fruitful annotacions which may properly be called miscellanea, bicause they do entreate of diuerse and sundry matters, marked with the nombre and figures of Augrime. 2</title>
                 <author>Alley, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 292, 138, 16 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="annotations_upon_preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>❧ Hic sequntur Miscellanea. ¶ Here followeth the mixt annotations vppon the preface going before.</head>
   <div n="1" type="part">
      <head>Anselmus. 1.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hys Anselmus, was Archbishop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, he was a blacke Monke, and an Abbot of a certayne monasterie in Normandie: he wrote workes almost infinite, and floryshed in the tyme of Henry the first, being King of Englād, which Henry for his learnyng was called Beuclarke. There was a great controuersie betwen him and Anselme, concerning the inuestiture of Bishops, and geuing of benefices. This Anselme condemned the lawful mariage of priestes, and constrayned thē to forsake their wyues. He accused also the King at Rome before Paschalis the second, who was then Byshop of Rome, because the King had made and ordained certaine Byshops and Abbotes in Englād. And one VVilliam VVarluuaste being the Kinges Proctor and Clarke, aunswearing for the Kinges ryght amonge other thinges sayd boldely, that the King woulde not for the losse of his kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, lose the prerogatyue of the inuestiture of hys Byshops. Vnto the whiche Pope Paschalis aunswered full proudlye. If (as thou sayest) thy King will not suffer the donation of Churches to bee alienate from him, for the losse of hys kingdome, know thou (flatlye and playnely, I speake it before God) I would not suffer him quietly to enioy them for the price of his hedde (O proud Sathan.) VVhich talke being finished, Anselmus desyred the Pope, that he hauyng no regard to the King, would depose the sayd Byshoppes, whiche thyng when it came to the Kinges eares, he did confiscate Anselmus goodes, and depriued hym of hys Byshoprike. Notwithstandyng as some write, the King restored Anselmus agayn frō excile and banyshment. This Anselme was Archbyshop of Canterburye after Lanfrancke, Anno Domini. <hi>1100.</hi> or there about.</p>
      <p>There were three Anselmes besydes thys Archbyshop, one was By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Lukes, who was by the craft and falsehode of Hildebrand made Pope, and named Alexander secundus, as Benno writeth.</p>
      <p>But the Lombardes with the consent of Henry the Emperour, set vp an other Bishop agaynst hym, whom they chose at Basile in a greate as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblye. Thys prelates name was Cadolus Byshop of Parma, who with a mighty host of men besieged Rome, but after one or two battailes foughte, he was put to flight. Henry the Emperour to take awaye this scisme, sent thether with his authoritye, one Otho Archbishop of Colyne,
<pb n="4" facs="8"/> who commyng to Rome, made and sayd very muche of the Emperours syde, for the election of the Pope, and dyd greatlye blame and accuse Alexander for that he was elected without the Emperoures consent. Then Hildebrand interruptyng the Archebishoppes oration, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded stoutelye Alexanders parte, and affirmed that the election of the Pope perteyned onelye to the Clergie. Otho easely gaue place to Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander and entreated that there myght bee a Counsell assembled at Mantua for the appeasing of the scisme. In the whiche Counsell Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der decreed that no man should here the Masse of any Priest that kept a concubine. He depriued also all maried Bishops, Priestes, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons of their benefices. Yet he permitted Priestes sonnes to entre into ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly orders, hauing at the least the Popes authoritie. He decreed that the Pope shoulde be chosen onely of the Cardinals, he commaunded Alleluia not to be song or sayd from Septuagesima vnto Easter.</p>
      <p>Benno Cardinalis writeth thus of this Alexander. VVhen Alexander vnderstode at the last that he was elect and intronizate by the subtletie and crafte of Hildebrand and the Emperours enemies, made vpon a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine day a Sermon vnto the people, and said that he would not sit in the see Apostolicke without the Emperous licence, and said openly that he would for the same cause send letters to the Emperour: which whē Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrand hard, grudging and murmuring, could scarse refrayne his hāds before the Masse was ended, but whē all was finished, he led Alexander with a strōg cōpany into his chāber, and before he could vnraye him self of his pontificalibus Hildebrand so fel to buffeting of him, that he made him to beraye the rost (as they say.) And Hildebrād appointed that frō that day forward no more money should be geuen to Alexander, but fiue shillings of the Lucenses coyne. And so casting Alexander into prison, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned all the reuennewes of the Church of Rome to his owne vse. In the end Alexāder in the night departed this world and perchaūce not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poison. And Hildebrand was intronizate of his souldiours without the consent either of the Clergie, or of the people, fearing least an other would preuent him. Vnto whose election not one of the Cardinalles did subscribe. Vnto the whiche place when the Abbot called Abbas Cassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensis came, Hildebrand sayde vnto hym, <hi>Frater nimium tardasti,</hi> the Abbot aunswered. <hi>Et tu Hildebrande nimium festinasti,</hi> for thou (the Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe thy Lorde and master beyng not yet buried) hast vsurped the see Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicke contrary to the Canons and lawes.</p>
      <p>There was also an other Anselme, whiche did expounde the whole course of holy Scriptures with the glose called, glosa interlinearis, and with other notes set in the mergent, whiche he tooke out of the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges
<pb facs="9"/> of certeine fathers.</p>
      <p>An other Anselme also was a blacke Moncke &amp; a Frenchman which wrote the booke named. Itinerarium Leonis Papae.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="part">
      <head>Gethicall. 2.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Etae, were people in Scithia, Appianus doth call thē Dacos. But Strabo in his seuenth booke doth make this differēce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the people called Getas, and the people called Dacos. That is that Getae dwell in the Orient toward the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion Pontus: Daci dwell in the parte opposite towarde Germany, and by the fountaine of the great riuer Ister, which people many in the old time would haue to be called Danos. Among the Athenians the names of the Danes and the Getes were vsually compted and called seruile.</p>
      <p>Aelius Spartianus writteth them to haue bene called Getas who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward were named Gothi. Ouid in his boke de Ponto writeth this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be barbarous, fierce and cruell, his wordes be these.</p>
      <q>
         <l>
            <hi>Nulla Getis toto gens est truculentior orbe.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>No people in the worlde permanent.</l>
         <l>Then the Getes are more fierce or truculent.</l>
      </q>
      <p>Therfore this Epitheton Gethicall is applied to them that be barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, fierce and vnthankefull, whereupon this verse is spoken of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull man.</p>
      <q>Dicitur ingratos exsuperare Getas.</q>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="part">
      <head>Talentum. 3.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vdeus, in his booke de Asse, doth throughly define what Talen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum is, and how many wayes it is taken.</p>
      <p>Concerning the signification of Talentum, when it betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a somme of money, it shalbe sufficient to knowe that <hi>Talentum At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum minus</hi> is most written of, and conteyneth <hi>60</hi> Minas, euery Mina conteining <hi>100</hi> drachmes, or Denaries, and euery Denary being a grot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sterling, so that the value of Mina is. <hi>33.</hi> s. iiij. d. or after Tunstall <hi>40.</hi> s. and Talentum <hi>100.</hi> poundes, or after Tunstall. <hi>120.</hi> poundes sterling, of this Talentum in this signification there be <hi>Tot sensus quot capita.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But Talentum by a Metaphor doth signifie a gift, a dowry, a charge committed to man,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> as in Matthew it is said that vnto one he gaue fiue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, to an other two, and to an other one, to euery man according to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> habilitie. Talentes in this place, are the giftes of God and of grace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and geuen to man to worke and labour, whether it be to teache, to preach, to exhorte the people, or to benefite and profite our neighbours
<pb n="5" facs="9"/> any maner of way, Christ doth not giue these giftes cōcerning the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and scarsenes of them, to one man more, and to an other lesse, but to euery man according as he is able to take and receaue. As the fielde being fertile and plentifull by nature doth bring forth fruite more abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dant, then that fielde whiche holpen by the industrie and labour of man, euen so he that is holpen with the instincte and furtheraunce of nature. To one therfore whiche by nature is of a quicke wit, and of a liuely spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite ar committed fiue talents, vnto an other (according to his capacitie) ar geuen two, to an other one, wherupon saint Paule confesseth that he fedde certaine of the Corinthians with milke,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> whiche (as yet) coulde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest no whole meate. And to the Ephesians he sayth,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.</note> to euery one of vs is geuen grace according to the measure of the gift of Christ.</p>
      <p>Chrisostome sayth, that talentes in this place of Mathew doo signifie that which any mā is able to do, whether it be to defend with authoritie, as Princes and Magistrates may, or to helpe with money, as the rich may the poore, or to admonish by doctrine, as the elders ecclesiasticall may, or by any maner of meanes to furder their neighbour. And no mā cā excuse him selfe from one good exercise or other, nor ought (say I) haue but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one talent. For in distribution of almes who was poorer then that wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe that caste but two mites into the treasurie chest?<note place="margin">
            <hi>Nar.</hi> 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.</note> Yf there he any poorer, he may yet giue a cup of water to them that neede it.</p>
      <div type="caution">
         <head>Cautio.</head>
         <p>BVt we must take heede, that we thincke not to haue of our owne, or of our selues that which we haue,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> for (as Paule sayth) <hi>Quid habes quod non accepisti?</hi> what hast thou that thou hast not receaued? Therfore we must graunt and cōfesse not onely the offices, but the facultie and power to the administration of them, to come of the Lorde. VVe be not (sayth Paule) sufficient of our selues to thincke any good thing,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3</note> but all our suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie is of God. It is farre otherwise in Gods case, then in mans case, for a prince and ruler may conferre and giue an office to any man, but to giue him the gifte and facultie to do his office well, it lyeth not in mans power. But in Gods case our heauenly king can giue vnto man not onely <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is libertie and authoritie to do thinges, but also he can giue him <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <hi>rastonin,</hi> that is power, facultye and strength to do it.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="part">
      <head>Paules Churche. 4.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare of our Lord <hi>.1087.</hi> and the vij day of Iuly the Churche of Paules and all that was in it with a great parte of the Citie were burned, (Maurice then beyng Byshop of London,) and in the <hi>21.</hi> yeare of VVilliam Conquerour. In the yeare also <hi>1132.</hi> the most part of the Citie of London, was burned by
<pb facs="10"/> the fire of Gilbert Becket and in the <hi>.32.</hi> yeare of king Henry the first. Of this kindred came that goodly impe Thomas Becket.</p>
      <p>In the yeare likewise <hi>.1137.</hi> and in the first yeare of king Stephen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan a fire at London Bridge, and burned all the Citie and Churche of Paules vnto saint Clementes Churche without temple barre, which was then called the Danes Churche.</p>
      <p>In the yeare likewise <hi>.1382.</hi> and the <hi>.21.</hi> day of May with a great earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quake through the realme, the Crosse in Paules Churcheyard was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, in the sixt yeare of Richard the second. To the building of that Crosse again VVilliā the Bishop of Canterburie gathered great sommes of money, and enriched him selfe, and because men shoulde be more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and willing to giue, he and the rest of suche holy Bishops, graunted many dayes of pardon, to them that would freely geue money to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that Crosse agayne.</p>
      <p>Furthermore Polichr. telleth that a great piece of London, and Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Church with the principal cities of Englād, were burned,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 4</note> &amp; he saith that a hurlewind threwe downe an hundred houses in London, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches also.</p>
      <p>On Candlemas euen, in midwinter, Paules steple was burned with lightening, in the time of king Henry the sixte.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="part">
      <head>London. 5.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He citie of London was founded and builded of Brutus, in that tyme whē Heli the high Priest was iudge of Israell, whiche was about the yeares before Christ <hi>.1125.</hi> and was first named Troye nouant. This Brute had three sonnes whose names were Locrine, Cāber and Albanact. Vnto Locrine he gaue the middle parte of Britayne, with the superioritie of the Ile: Vnto Cam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber he gaue VVales, vnto Albanact, Scoteland.</p>
      <p>Ebrancke the fith king after Brute, builded the Citie of Yorke, and the Castles of Dunbar and Edenbrough, and one Leyle the seconde kyng after Ebrancke builded the Citie of Carlell, and Lud his sonne builded the Cities of Canterburie, VVinchester, and the Towne of Shastisburie. Bladud the sonne of Lud builded the Citie of Bath, and made therein the hote bathes, and by vayne trust of the Art of Necromancie toke vpō him to flie in the ayre, from whence he fell downe and brake his necke. Leir the sonne of Bladud builded the citie of Leicester.</p>
      <p>At the last after the house of Brute was cruelly destroyed, Mulum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius Dunwallo duke of Cornewall: brought this realme into one Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, and he made the foure notable wayes in Britayne, called the Fosse
<pb n="6" facs="10"/> wayes. In London he builded a great temple, whiche some suppose to be Paules Church, some Blackwel hall. He liued about <hi>.441.</hi> before Christ.</p>
      <p>Bellinus sonne of Mulumsius, did cōstitute thre archeflamins, whose sees were at Lōdon, Yorke &amp; Carlion, he finished the foure great wayes begon by his father, he made Denmarcke tributarie vnto him. In Londō he made the hauen called Billinsegate, and as Leiland writeth, builded the towre of London.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="part">
      <head>Plato. 6.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Plato was called <hi>Diuinus Plato,</hi> for his excellent doctrine, which doctrine cōteyneth many things (as S. Austē saith) which accorde with the holy Scriptures, so that in thē is perceaued the first part of Genesis, vnto this text, <hi>Spiritus dn̄i ferebatur super aquas,</hi> and the mistery of thre persons in diuinitie, is there expressed, his name was first Aristocles, and after called Plato, bycause as some suppose, he was broad in the shoulders, other write bycause he had a broade visage. He was before Christ <hi>.342.</hi> yeares, he liued sole and chaste (as S. Austen saith) and died being of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> age of <hi>.81.</hi> yeares. Plato lieng in his cradle, bees brought honie into his mouth w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out hurting of him, which thing diuerse did interpret, to signifie, that from him should flow eloquēce most sweete and delectable Socrates dreamed the night before y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Plato was brought to him to be instructed in learnyng, that he helde betwene hys knees a white Cygnet, who hauing fethers quickelie growen, flew vp, towarde heauen, and filled the ayre with most pleasaunt tunes. So the day after Plato being brought by his father vnto Socrates, who beholdyng him well, sayd: This is the birde, whose Image I beheld this last might, but his end and death was (as some say) the disease of the lowsy euill, called of the Phisitions Ptyriasis.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="part">
      <head>Countrie. 7.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Omer writeth that Vlisses so loued his countrie, that he desired to see the smoke thereof once appeare before he died, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he should dye fourth with.</p>
      <p>One named Seriphius, when it was obiected against him that his coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie was poore and base, made this aunswere. <hi>Mihi patria dedecus est, tu autem patriae,</hi> my countrie is a dishonor to me, but thou art a dishonor to thy countrie.</p>
      <p>Teucer hearing certaine conferring together of the sweetenes of their countrie, sayd. <hi>Patria est, vbicun{que} est bene.</hi> VVhere a man liueth well, there is his countrie, for it is often tymes seene, that certayne hath bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="11"/> successe, and be of more estimation among straungers, then they be in their owne countrie. And therfore it is a good and a golden saying: <hi>Omne solum forti patria est.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="part">
      <head>Cassiodore. 8.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Cassiodore, was a Moncke of Rauenna, but was firste consul, &amp; thē Senator of Rome, he wrote vpō the Psalter, and many godly and learned Epistles, anno domini. <hi>550.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="part">
      <head>Hierocles. 9.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ierocles, was a Philosopher of Alexādria, whose constācie, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie and eloquence, is of Suidas with maruelous prayses cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mended. This his magnanimitie of minde (sayth he) may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued and vnderstoode by the commentaries whiche he wrote vpon the verses of Pithagoras, called <hi>Aurea Pithagorae carmina.</hi> He wrote also of prudence, and many other bookes, in the whiche his excellent wit and learning do playnly appeare. Of this read more in <hi>Suidas.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="10" type="part">
      <head>Iudas Machabeus. 10.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdas Machabeus was y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sonne of Matathias the Priest. This Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das did with a most godly zeale, withstand the edictes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of Antiochus. VVho cōmaunded the Iewes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the law of God, and to receaue and embrace the Idolatrie of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. He (vanquishing and putting to flight certeine hostes of Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus) at the last repayred to the citie of Ierusalē, &amp; to the temple which he did purifie and clense againe, the .xxv. of Nouember.</p>
      <p>Afterward, when he had made a league with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romanes, he was slaine in the battayle by Demetrius the king, as it is recorded in the first boke of the Machabees, the .ix. chapiter.</p>
      <div type="question">
         <head>Quaestio.</head>
         <p>Some will demaunde what is to be thought of the bookes of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, whether they be Canonicall or no, and whether they be of a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent authoritie to confirme any doctrine?</p>
      </div>
      <div type="response">
         <head>Responsio.</head>
         <p>For that our aduersaries do mixt and mingle vnto bookes auctenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call &amp; Canonicall, other bokes named Ecclesiasticall or Hagiographall (as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bokes of the Machabees &amp; others) they do it for this coūsel &amp; end, to make equall traditions and vnwritten verities, with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy scriptures. But to omit other their doings, they take vpon them to proue and shewe
<pb n="7" facs="11"/> out of the second booke of the Machabees, that it is an holsome thyng to pray and offre for the dead, that they myght be loosed from their sinnes. They bragge also that they can shewe out of those bookes, that the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the saintes beyng in heauen, are offred vnto God, for them whiche lyue in the earth. VVhen notwithstandyng in the primatiue Church, the seconde booke of the Machabees, and other lyke, were neuer rehearsed nor nombred among the bookes canonicall.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="objection">
         <head>Obiectio.</head>
         <p>VVhy syr? saint Austen in his boke <hi>De doctrina Christiana,</hi> doth nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber among the bookes canonicall, not onely other bookes Ecclesiasticall, but also the second booke of the Machabees.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="response">
         <head>Responsio.</head>
         <p>If we looke well vpon the Histories and other monumentes of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, it will appeare that euen thē first, that is in saint Austens time, this boke was receaued into the nomber of the bookes cononicall, in the thirde counsell holden at Carthage, aboute the yeare of our Lorde. <hi>400.</hi> or <hi>.399.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Nor saint Austen doth dissemble or denie the same, for in his booke <hi>De ciuitate dei,</hi> &amp; in his worke <hi>Contra Gaudentii epistolam,</hi> he doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monishe and teach the bokes of the Machabees not to haue bene nombred of the olde fathers in the Canon. Notwithstanding he addeth, that they were not vnprofitably receaued, so that they be redde soberly and with discretion.</p>
         <p>He saith also in an other place, they are taken for canonicall, bycause they conteine the vehement and maruelous passions and death of certein martyrs. Besides this he writeth, that euery thing which is set fourth in that booke, is not to be receaued, except it be well examined and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with other Scriptures. It may be shewed out of the most aunciēt and noble Churches of the Easte, that the bookes of the Machabees were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer receaued for canonicall. Meliton <hi>Sardensis episcopus,</hi> whiche lyued not many yeares after the death of the Apostles, about the yeare of our Lord <hi>.173.</hi> vnder the Emperour <hi>Anthonius verus</hi> (to whom he wrote an Appologie for our faith) doth recite the bookes of the old Testament, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king no mention of any of those bookes called Ecclesiasticall. He sayth that he went into the Easte, where our preaching began, and where all thinges were done, whiche are written, that he might diligently inuesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and searche out all thyngs, whiche doth pertayne to the veritie and certaynetie of the bookes canonicall, and that there he founde out the cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne and true nomber.</p>
         <p>Origine hymselfe doth rehearse no more bookes of the olde Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then <hi>.22.</hi> Lykewyse saint Hierome not onelye in hys Prologue
<pb facs="12"/> named Galeatus, but also in his Epistle vnto Paul, doth know and nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber onely <hi>.22.</hi> bookes, other bookes saith he, must be set out of the Canon.</p>
         <p>In his Prologue also vpon the Prouerbes of Salomon, after he had spoken of the booke of wisedome, whiche is sayde to be Salomons, and of the booke called <hi>Ecclesiasticus,</hi> he addeth this. As the Churche there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth reade the booke of Iudith, of Tobie, and the bookes of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees, but yet doth not receaue them amongest the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, so likewise doth she receaue these two bookes of Machabees to the edifieng of the people, and not to the aucthoritie of any Ecclesiasticall doctrine to be confirmed.</p>
         <p>This Hierome coulde not be ignoraunt of the Decree of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of Carthage, for (as many do write) he dyed aboute the yeare of our Lorde <hi>.422,</hi> and therefore it is to be iudged, that saint Austen ment no otherwise, but as Hierome did, that is, that he nombred the seconde booke of the Machabees among the Canonicall, but yet vnderstoode it to be Ecclesiasticall, that is not of so great aucthoritie, as the bookes, which of olde antiquitie were counpted Canonicall.</p>
         <p>Ruffinus in the exposition of the Apostles Symbole, doth recite no more bokes of the old Testamēt, but so many as are rehearsed before, &amp; amonge other thynges these be his wordes. <hi>Hec sunt veteris Testamenti volumina que secundum maiorum traditionem, per ipsum spiritum san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum inspirata creduntur, &amp; Ecclesiis Christi tradita sunt. Sciendum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men est, quod &amp; alii libri sunt, qui non Canonici, sed Ecclesiastici, a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioribus sunt appellati: vt est sapientia Salomonis, Ecclesiasticus, Tobiae &amp; Iudith, &amp; Machabeorum libri, que omnia in Ecclesiis legi voluerunt, non tamen proferri ad authoritatem fidei ex his confirmandam.</hi> These be the bookes of the olde Testament, whiche after the tradition of the Elders, are beleued to be enspired by the holy Ghost him self, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to the Churches of Christ: Yet we must knowe, that there be other bookes, whiche are not called of the elders canonicall, but Ecclesiastical: as the boke of Sapience, the boke named Ecclesiasticus, the bokes of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie and Iudith, and of the Machabees. VVhiche bookes all they woulde haue truely to be red in the Church, but not to be brought fourth out of them any aucthoritie to confirme our faith.</p>
         <p>Finally, the fact and dede of Rasias, recorded in the secōd boke, is not greatly commended of certeyne learned and godly men, bycause he in a maner killed him selfe, also in the ende of the booke it is written: <hi>Si bene scripsi, est quod volui: Sin exiliter, est quod potui.</hi> If I haue written wel, it is that, that I woulde: If I haue written sclenderly, it is that which I could. These wordes are not to be attributed to the holy ghost, for he is the author onely of wordes and woorkes most perfect and pure.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="11" type="part">
      <pb n="8" facs="12"/>
      <head>Apollo. 11.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertaine Authors write, that Apollo first brought in the vse of Phisicke, and therfore deserued to be called a God. He is called also the Autor and inuētor of Verses and Musicke, wherfore the Poetes coumpte him their chief God.</p>
      <p>In the Yland called the Rhodes, there is an image named Colossus, of such great quātitie and bignes, that it is nōbred among the seuē wonders of the world. Three folde power and authority is geuen vnto him, that is, In heauē he is called <hi>Sol,</hi> the Sunne, in earth he is called <hi>Liber Pater,</hi> the father of Vine and wines, in hell he is called Apollo. Three thinges are painted alwaies w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his image, an Harpe, a Buckler, and Arrowes. There is ascribed vnto him continuall youth, and therefore he is fayned of the Poetes to be alwayes remaining among the florishing herbes and greene grasse. There is a prouerbe whiche sprange of <hi>Apollo. Apollonis oracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> the oracle of Apollo, by the whiche is signified a thing most true, bycause Apollo being cōsulted, gaue euer true answeres. There is also an other prouerbe <hi>Ex tripode dictum,</hi> the originall and meaning wherof ye shall reade at large <hi>in Chiliadibus Erasmi.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="12" type="part">
      <head>Athenae. 12.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Thens was a noble citie where all liberall sciences were taught, it is called the mother of all Philosophers, all Greece had not in it a more beautifull and nobler thing. The situation thereof was very spectable and pleasaunt. It was also as it were a certaine mother ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and refuge, into the which all other cities nere adioygning, (afflicted and prest with terrors of warre or any other calamities) did flie &amp; had recourse. It was a most safe and sure receptacle of all shippes, mariners and Marchauntes. It was the noblest vniuersitie of all the worlde, and none in times past was coumpted learned, which had not geuen diligēce to learning at Athens. Strabo writeth that there was in Athens a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine rocke set in a plaine, which was inhabited rounde about circle wise. In that plaine was the temple of Minerua, and in that temple there was an image, whiche the inhabitantes did beleue to haue fallen from heauē. In the sayd Churche there was a perpetuall fire with a companie of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins. This citie was called also Cecropia, of a certaine kyng named Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crops, and Mopsopia of one Mopsus, as of Ianus the sonne of Iaphet, was named (as some write) Ionia, At the last this citie was called of this word Minerua, Athens, for the Grecians do call Mineruā, Athenā. And Minerua the virgine founde out Clothemakyng, VVeauyng and Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and manye other Artificiall things. And therfore she was taken as a famous goddesse. And bycause all her inuentions did procede out of the
<pb facs="13"/> quicknes of wit and greate wisedome, the Poetes do fable that she was borne of Iupiters brayne.</p>
      <p>As Cecrops was repairing and fortifieng the citie of Athens, water broke fourth sodenly in a certaine place, and in an other place there was founde an Oliue tree, vpon the which wonders, Apollo being demaunded at Delphos, what was ment therby, and what were best to be done, made aunswere: that the Oliue tree did signifie Mineruam, and the water dyd betoken Neptunum, and that they both were sisters children, and both Gods, and that it was in the arbitrement of the citezens, to call the citie after one of their two names. So (al the citizens beyng assembled) the mē did cleue and consent to Neptunus, the women vnto Minerua: who obtei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned that the citie should be called by the name of Minerua. The Poets do say that Neptunus and Minerua did builde the citie of Athens, and whē there was altercation betwen thē for the imposition of the name, (other Gods being present,) they conuented betwene them selues, that whether of them (smityng the ground) should bring fourth the most laudable and worthy effect, should name the citie. Neptunus smiting the ground with his mace, brought fourth an borse, an instrument of war, but Minerua throwing her speare vpon the ground, brought fourth an Oliue tree, of peace &amp; quietnes, which bicause it was coūted more profitable by their iudgemēt, the city was called by her name, Athens. Therfore the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were not straungers, nor a rablement of people gathered together which gaue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> originall of the citie, but they wer borne in the same groūd wher they dwelt. They first taught y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vse of Clothemaking, and of Oyle, they taught the maner to Ploughe and to sowe Corne, vnto them whiche before did eate Acornes. Learning, Eloquence, and al ciuill order of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline did florishe at Athens.</p>
      <p>Cecrops also made .iij. lawes against their womē, to pacifie y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ire of Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunus, whō the womē did set behind Minerua. The first law was that no womā should euer enter into the Senate, the secōd law was, that no child should be called by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mothers name. And the third was, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> no man should call them <hi>Mulieres Athenienses,</hi> but <hi>Atticas.</hi> There be three prouerbes which had their originall of Athens. The firste prouerbe is this: <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ensium inconsulta temeritas:</hi> the vnaduised rashenes of the Athenians, It may be applyed agaynst them whose rash consultation cometh to good successe. For in tymes paste it was commonly imputed to the Athenians, that they would slackelye consulte for their affaires, and had litle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight, or no prouidēce in their doinges. But Minerua Lady President of the citie did accustome to turne their ill purposes to a good end.</p>
      <p>The like prouerbe is at this tyme in euery mans mouth: <hi>Est fortunati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or quam prudentior.</hi> It is better to be happy, then wise. It may be spoken
<pb n="9" facs="13"/> of hym whiche hath good successe and chaunce, not by hys industrie and wisedome, but by commoditie of fortune.</p>
      <div n="2" type="proverb">
         <head>The second prouerbe is this.</head>
         <p>
            <hi>ATticus testis vel Attica fides,</hi> a witnes of Athens, or the fidelitie of Athens, whiche prouerbe may be spoken of a most vncorrupte and vpright testimonie and faith.</p>
         <p>The originall of this prouerbe sprang of this, bycause that at Athens there was a Churche builded vnto the Lady faith. Velleius Paterculus maketh mention of this in these wordes: If any do impute to the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that time of rebelliō, in the whiche Athens was taken of Silla, truly he is ignoraunt of al truth and antiquitie. For the faith of the Atheniās, was so certaine &amp; sure toward the Romanes, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> alwayes and in al things what soeuer was done w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a sincere and vncorrupt fidelitie, the Romanes would pronounce that to be don <hi>Attica fide,</hi> by the faith of the Atheniās.</p>
         <p>Quintilian doth write that the soyle and grounde of Athens, did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rendre more sede then it did receaue.</p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="proverb">
         <head>The third prouerbe is this.</head>
         <p>
            <hi>NOctua volauit.</hi> The owle hath floen: The fleing of the owle was to the aūcient Atheniās, a simbole &amp; presage of victory, bycause this birde was dedicate as an holy thing vnto Minerua, who alwayes as it is sayde before, brought to good successe the slacke consultations of the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. And therfore when any matter cōmeth to a good ende contrarie to our expectation, It may be prouerbially sayd, the owle hath floen, as Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das doth write.</p>
         <p>It shall not be vnaptely applyed, when matters are brought to effect, not by any industrie and strength, but by the mediation of money. The originall wherof, came of this, bycause the coyne of the Athenians had an owle ingraued in it. It may well be obiected agaynst them whiche doo both giue and receaue bribes.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="13" type="part">
      <head>Phileni. 13.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey were two brethren of Carthage of whō it is written, that where they of Carthage and they of Cyren did striue for their boundes, it was agreed that out of eche citie two men shoulde issue, and where as they met shoulde be the boundes, then the sayde brethren beyng sent, went a greate waye into the boundes of the other, eare they did returne, and when they of Cyren did see that they were preuented, they tooke it displeasauntly, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naced the two brethren, that if they woulde not go backe they shoulde be put quicke into the earth, but they notwithstandyng woulde not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte, wherefore they beyng buried alyue, their countrie men made ouer
<pb facs="14"/> them two alters, which at this day be called <hi>Arae Philenorum.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="14" type="part">
      <head>Herodotus. 14.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Herodotus was borne in a citie of Halicarnassus in Asia, and he wrote nyne bookes of Histories, whiche he did entitle by the name of the nine Muses, in the which he wrot the Historie of all the Actes done in Europa, and Asia, by the space of <hi>.240.</hi> yeares. He came of a noble linage, he began hys Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with Cyrus king of the Persians. He was before the incarnation of Christ <hi>.200.</hi> yeares.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="15" type="part">
      <head>Xerxes. 15.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His king was Darius sonne, &amp; he inuaded Grece, with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē hundred thousand straūge souldiours, &amp; yet was vāqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by a few Greekes, and cōstrayned to flie away in great feare in a litle boate vnknowē, and at the last was slaine by Artabanus the greate Capitaine of his armye. On a time whē he saw the whole Sea called Hellespontus couered w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his Nauie, and all the bāckes and plaine fieldes replenished with his armie of men, he boasted hym selfe blessed, and yet straight way fell on weepyng. Artabanus his vncle whiche had disswaded him from that viage, maruelyng at so sodayne a chaunge, demanded the cause. Then Xerxes sayd, <hi>I</hi> nowe recorde in my mynde, howe short the life of man is, when of this great multitude after an hundres yeares not one of these shall remayne alyue. He was before Christ <hi>.485.</hi> yeares.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="16" type="part">
      <head>Religion. 16.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Icero de natura deorum</hi> sayth, that this worde Religio cometh a <hi>Relegendo,</hi> of readyng agayne, or gathering agayne together, and so saint Austen, <hi>Lib. 2. de ciuitate dei</hi> sayth, <hi>Religio dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a relegendo deum, quem amiseramus negligentes,</hi> Religion is sayde of gatheryng God againe, whom we beyng negligent, had lost. Lactātius Li. <hi>4.</hi> affirmeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it cometh a <hi>Religando</hi> of bynding, bycause we be binde bounde to do our duety towarde God. And so Isidorus Lib. <hi>18.</hi> Etimo: writeth saying. <hi>Religio dicta est, quod per eam, vni soli deo religamus animas nostras ad cultum diuinum,</hi> It is called Religion, bicause we be it our soules to one onely God to do him diuine and godly honor. Religio is taken somtime for feare and scruple of conscience, as <hi>Dignus es tua reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione odio.</hi> Thou art worthy to be hated for thy peuishe superstition. Sometime it signifieth wickednes, as <hi>Hoc patrare Religio est.</hi> It is an hai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nous thing to do this.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="17" type="part">
      <pb n="10" facs="14"/>
      <head>Scotiste. 17.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Duns, by sur name called Scotus, whom they call the most subtle doctr and prince of all diuines, did expound the foure bookes made by Petrus Lombardus, called the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the sentēce. He proposed and wrote also. <hi>21.</hi> questiōs, called <hi>quodlibetates,</hi> beside many other subtle workes. Al his scollers &amp; followers were called Scotistae. He was about the yeare of our Lorde <hi>1304.</hi> and died as some write, of the disease named Apoplexia, whych maketh the patiēt to leese his feeling, his speche &amp; mouing, but the most part write, that he was buried quicke and a liue. He was a gray Frier.</p>
      <p>There was an other Scotus, a Benedictine Moncke, a great Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, the hearer and disciple of Bede, and liued in the time of Carolus Magnus, and Bertramus. He translated the bookes of Dionisius the Martir into Latin, and made a booke of the sacrament of the bodye and bloud of Christ. Sabellianus writeth, that some iudge the Vniuersitie of Paris to haue bene institute of this Iohannes Scotus, but it is more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the Vniuersitie was made by the meanes of Carolus Magnus, &amp; furnished with learned men, and expert readers by the same Scotus. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuinus, Claudius, and Rabanus, which came out of Scotland. Vincentius in speculo historiali, sayth: That Elfridus king of England, being raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with the fame of this Scotus name and learning, brought him into England, where (being in a Monasterie called Monasterium Melbrinē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se) taught children, and at the last was digged and persed with writing pensels, with which kind of martirdome he finished his lyfe.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="18" type="part">
      <head>Negry. 18.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Egry quidē, is as much to say as he is able to say litle or nothing to it. For gry doth signifie a very vile or base thing, as the paring of the nayles, or the grunting of a sow, and therfore some thinke that grunire, which is to grunt as a sow, commeth of this word gry.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="19" type="part">
      <head>Furies. 19.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Poetes fayne that there be three furies of hell, whose names are: Alecto, Tisiphone, Megera, and they signifie the worme and painful remorse of conscience, which horriblye tormenteth the mindes of wicked personnes. These three furies betoken the three folde affections of the minde, anger, greedines, and pleasure. Anger desireth reuengement, greedines desireth riches, pleasure desireth wantonnes.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="20" type="part">
      <head>Momish. 20.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Omus the God of reprehension, of whom all curious reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ar called Momi, that is finding fault with euery thing. This
<pb facs="15"/> Momus (as Aristotle writeth) found fault with Nature, bicause she pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced the hornes in the head of the Oxe, and not in the shoulders, whereby he might geue the mightier stroke. Also (as Luciā saith) he blamed Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, for that he had not set eyes in mans brest, that he might see what is within him, and of this riseth a prouerb, <hi>Momo satisfacere,</hi> to satisfie Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus minde, which is very hard to do.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="21" type="part">
      <head>Zoilus. 21.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Z</seg>Oilus was an enuious Poet, and called the rhetorical dog, very busie to write and speake ill, not onely of Homer, Plato, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noble writers, but also contencious and full of enuye and strife against al mē. He being demaūded of a certain learned mā, why he spake so ill of al mē, bicause (saith be) I cānot do il when I would, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the enuious, of al learned mē ar named Zoili Aelia. lib. <hi>11.</hi> de varta historia.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="22" type="part">
      <head>Enuie. 22.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ion beholding a certain enuious man very sad, said: <hi>Nescio vtrū tibi acciderit aliquid mali, an alteri boni quippiam,</hi> I cannot tell whether any ill thing be chaunced vnto thee, or some good thing happened to some other mā. For an enuious man is no les tormented with an other mans felicity, then with his own misfortune. Laertius. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Antisthenes said, that it was very absurde, to purge the wheate, frō cockle and Darnel, and to seperate warre from an vnprofitable soldiour, and not to put away enuious persons, from a cōmon welth, signifieng en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious persons to be more vnprofitable to a City, then cockle or darnell is vnto wheate, and a coward and dastard vnto battaile. Idem. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Socrates being demaunded what thing was greuous to good mē, made answer, <hi>Malorum faelicitas,</hi> the good succes of ill men. And being asked what was greuous to ill men, sayd: <hi>Bonorum prosperitas,</hi> the prosperity of good men. Antonius, in Meliss.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="23" type="part">
      <head>Sainct Austen. 23.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vsten was a famous doctor of Christes church, borne in Affrick, in a towne called Gathensis. His mothers name was Monica, &amp; his father was of the order of Senators. They were verye honest persōs, but yet of no hie nor rich degree, his brothers name was Nauigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. He was of such excellent wit, that in his childhood he learned all the seuen liberal sciences, without any instructor. He was wonderfully lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, specially in the doctrine of Plato. His maisters name was Manlius Theodorus. He hated the Greeke toung, and was in great loue with the Latine toung. In his youth beyng sixtene yeares of age, he was greatlye geuen to fleshly lustes, and by the reason of ill companye cōmitted theft.
<pb n="11" facs="15"/> About the age of .xix. yeares (his father being dead two yeares before) chaunsed vpon the booke of Cicero called Hortensius, and being moued thereby, fel to the study of philosophy. He somwhat applied his minde to the holy scriptures, but for the simplicity of the stile he did lothe them. He being of the age of .xx. yeares, by himselfe did read the Catagories of Aristotle, and vnderstode them, &amp; was expert in al the Mathematical sciences. A litle after he chaunced vpon the Manichies, and did embrace and receiue their opinions.</p>
      <p>And by the space of ix. yeares, that is from .xix. vntil he came to the age of .xxviij. he did persist in the same heresye, and disceaued manye. He vsed the vnlawful companye and bed of one Concubine. At the age of .xxix: he heard one Festus a Manachie reade at Carthage, whom at the first he praysed aboue all other: but when by conference and disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, he perceaued him to be ignorant of the liberal sciences, and to be ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pert in nothing but grammar: he dispeired that he mought be taught by the Manichies of the truth, which to attaine he much desired. At the last he went to Rome, agaynst his mothers wyll, who pitifully lamented the same: wher he professed Rhetorick, hoping that he should find ther more obedient and more thankful disciples. And ther he fel sick of a feuer, &amp; was in great daunger, but he recouered his health, and vsed stil the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Manichies, but did not so much defend their doctrine, bicause after the opinion of the Academickes he iudged all things to be doubted of. And being forsaken of his ingrate disciples, went vnto Millen, where he was fatherly receaued of saint Ambrose, whom he also loued agayne, not for true doctrines sake, but onely for his benificence. He heard Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose diligently, not for the desire of the knowledge of truth, but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he would proue whether Ambrose were of the same eloquence as he was reported to be. At the last he became neither a Manichy nor a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, but doubted how the way of life and saluation mought be found out, his mother came to Millen vnto him, hoping her sonne to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by saynt Ambrose.</p>
      <p>VVhen he was .xxx. yeares of age, he maried a wyfe, and was betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vnto her, but she was not mariageable by twoo yeares, and he was faine to exspect and tary for her so long. VVhen his Concubine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode that he minded to mary a wife, she departed from him into Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica, and left him a sonne, which he had by her, and then he tooke an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Concubine. At the last he came to one Simplicianus, and did vtter and open vnto him al the circumstances of his errours, and desired coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of him, how he might come to a more perfect and fuller knowledge of the truth, who did exhort and counsel him to reade the holy scriptures,
<pb facs="16"/> and to follow the example of Victorinus, who with the diligent reading of them, became a Christian, and professing openly his fayth, was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. Austen being very desirous to follow the same example, his mynde was drawen hether and thether what he might do, and by chaunce one Pontinianus did recite vnto him the history of Antonius, and of other two, which readyng the booke of Antonie (forsaking al their goods &amp; their wiues) embraced the monastical life. VVith the which narration, Austen being greatly moued, lamented his life, and departing into a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with his friend Alippius, fel to pouring out aboundaunce of teares, and desired God to giue him a more pure minde and better life. And ther he heard as it were out of the next house, a voice of children or maidens, singing and saying: <hi>Tolle, lege, Tolle, lege,</hi> take and read, take &amp; reade. But when he saw no person, he thought it to be Gods admonition and warning. And then taking the booke of the new testament, chaunced vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this place of Paule. <hi>Induite dominum nostrū Iesum Christum, et car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis prouidentiam ne feceritis in concupiscentiis.</hi> Put vpon you our Lord Iesus Christ, and make not prouision for the flesh in concupiscence and luste. After he had red these woordes, all darknes and ignorance were shaken from his eyes, so that he saw the truth, and imparting this to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippius, they both purposed to embrace Christes riligion: not without the great comfort and ioy of his mother Monica, who al the time that he was a Manichie, both dayly and most earnestly prayed to God for his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. In the meane time, he was greatly tormented with the tooth ache, but by the praiers of his brethren he was miraculouslye healed. At the last he renounced the profession of Rhetoricke, by the reason that he was short winded, and pained in his stomache, and gaue his minde wholy to the reading of the holy scriptures. He wrote to saint Ambrose, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and confessing vnto him al his errors, and sheweth what he purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to do, and asketh counsell what bokes of the holy bible he ought chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reade. Ambrose perswaded him to read the prophet Esay, but when it seemed somwhat hard vnto him, he deferred the readyng therof vnto an other time. About y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> feast of Easter, he was baptized at Millen, with Alippius his friend, and his natural sonne Adeodatus, which was of the age of .xv yeares. After his conuersion, he led a most godly and vertuous life. He wrote notable and worthy workes, he was very liberal and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the poore. He kept no company with women, for auoiding of suspition. His apparel was neither to costly nor to base, but of an honest and comely sorte. His table was not sumptuous, but frugall and honest, hauing flesh for straungers sakes, and for them which were diseased. At his meales he did more regard reading and disputing, then eating or
<pb n="12" facs="16"/> drinking. He was very harberous, and kept a good house. He most ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nestly hated detractions, and ill reportes of suche as wer absent, and had written vpon his table these two verses.</p>
      <q>
         <lg>
            <l>
               <hi>Quisquis amat dictis absentum rodere vitam,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hanc mensam vetitam nouerit esse sibi.</hi>
            </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>He that delighteth to backebite them that be absent,</l>
            <l>I forbyd hym this table to frequent.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
      <p>Often times, he would very sharply reprehend his fellow Bishops, for deprauing other, and sayd that he would either put out those verses, or els that he would depart from thence himself. Finally, the city Hippona being besieged three monethes of the Vandoles and Gothes (at whych time the state of the Church, and all things was most sorowful) he often prayed vnto God, that either it wold please him of his goodnes to dissolue and breake of that siege, or els to graunt him an happy and blessed ende, and so he fel into a feauer, and kept his bed, and the disease waxing more and more, he by him self did reade certaine psalmes of repentance, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired other also to reade them. And so geuing himself, by the space often daies to reading and prayer, at the last departed out of this miserable life, Possidonius and other of his frendes being present. He liued .lxxvj. yeares, and was Bishop .xl. yeares, and died Anno domini. <hi>437.</hi> Saynct Ambrose and he, being both replenished with the holy Ghost, did sing to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether the psalme <hi>Te deum,</hi> answering mutually one the other.</p>
      <p>This man sainct Austen doth wonderfully set forth to vs by his lyfe, the vnspeakable mercies of God, who made of a fornicator, a chaste Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who made of an hereticke, an Apostolike Doctour, who made of a theefe, a Bishop, who made of a wicked and naughty man, a sound mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and sure piller of his Church. It is he that can make of a Saul a Paul, of a Publicane an Euangelist, of a fisher a Preacher, of a theefe a Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor, and of a wanton Austen, a deepe diuine, and a worthy preacher (O the great mercies of God toward mankinde.)</p>
   </div>
   <div n="24" type="part">
      <head>Cain &amp; Abel. 24.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the gestes of Cain &amp; his brother Abel, are not vnknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en: yet that the secretes and misteries which they contayne may more depely and worthely be pondered and weighed, I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiously set them before your eyes.</p>
      <p>Not long after that our first parents were driuen out of the place of pleasure, they begat a sonne, whō (partly bicause he was the first borne, partly bicause they supposed him to be that strong seede, which shoulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>halenge and deliuer vs from the tiranny of the Serpent) they made not
<pb facs="17"/> onely head and chiefe of their posterity, but also the treasure and posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of all their desire, for the which cause they named him Cainū, which doth discend of this Hebrue word Canah, which signifieth to possesse.</p>
      <p>They begat also an other sonne not long after, of whom they dyd not onelye not depende, and had no regarde, but did compt him as a vayne thing, and made almoste no compt of him, wherupon they named hym Abelum, which doth signify vanity, and as it were but a vapour, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring but a litle time. But how blind and disceauable the iudgement of the flesh is, and how many times he iudgeth darkenes light, and light darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: in this act of Adam it doth euidently appeare.</p>
      <p>The history of these two brethren is set forth at large in the boke of Genesis, but of the mistery of the same, I entend at this present to make some discourse.</p>
      <div type="section">
         <head>¶ The mistery signified by Cain and Abell.</head>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N these two brethrē, two peoples are signified. In the yonger are signified the elect people of God, and especially of the Gentiles. In the elder are signified reprobates, and speciallye of the Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites. Nor yet two peoples onelye are signified by them, but also the chiefe heades of them. VVherefore Abel is the tipe and figure of Christ which is the elect of all electes. And on the other side Cain is the tipe &amp; figure of Antechrist, which is the reprobate of all reprobates. The elect, I say, are noted in Abel, bicause he is counted the first iust man, not by the righteousnes of nature, law, and flesh, but by the righteousnes of grace, faith, and the spirit. He is iust by the righteousnes of Christ, of whom he was partaker through the spirite, no otherwise then as the mēbers are partakers of the influence of the head: and as the riuer is of the exundant flowing of the spring. For Christ is not onely full of grace and righteousnes, but is ful of the original iustice, and capital grace, that al persons may draw therof.</p>
         <p>And wher it was said before that in Abel wer signified the elect peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and specially of the Gentiles: that was spoken partly bicause he is the yonger, and partly bicause his name is Abel.</p>
         <p>For the first it doth playnly appeare that the Gentiles were younger then the Hebrues, for the Hebrues had their original being of Sem, which was Noes eldest sonne, and the Gentiles came of Iaphet, a younger sonne of his. They were younger I saye, not onelye in nature, but also in fayth, for as much as God did first open him selfe vnto the Iewes, and shewed them away how they should worship him.</p>
         <p>For the second, Abel doth signify vayne, which doth well agree vnto the Gentiles, both before they were conuerted, and after they wer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted,
<pb n="13" facs="17"/> but yet in a diuers respect. Before they were conuerted, not onely bicause they were Athei, that is, knowing no God, vncertayne, vayne, swelling in their euil thoughtes, worshipping idols, being without hope, without promise, without testament and couenantes, but also bicause God made none accompt of them, but as one suffring them to folow their own lustes and wayes, yea and regarding them not onelye not to be hys people, but as though they were no people, as the Apostle Paule doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times record.</p>
         <p>Nowe after they were conuerted, they were likewise vaine, but yet in an other sense. For when the most highest began to call those thinges which were not, euen as those thinges which were, and after it pleased him to make a people not his, to be his people: and after he had opened their eyes, and had surrogate them in the place of the Israelites, and made them his members: yet they were compted vayne, partly, bicause such is the peoples iudgement of Gods elect, compting their life madnes, and their end without honour: partly, bicause they which be elect, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly taught by Gods spirite, that there is nothing firme and sure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the sunne, but that all thinges are vanity, and affliction of the spirit, and specially that the life of man is nothing els but a vapour, and that man is nothing els but Bulla, a buble of the water. The elect I say, being thus perswaded, do litle regard thinges temporal: nor greatlye passe for them selues, nor do trust to their own good woorkes, but deny them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, hating their own life, and coumpting all thinges filthynes, which are without Christ, as Paule sayth to the Philippians.</p>
         <p>In Cain (as is sayd before) the reprohates are signified,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> bycause he is coumpted the first wycked man, the reprobate I say, speciallye of the Hebrues, and that partly bicause he was the elder brother, and partlye bicause his name is interpreted possession. The Hebrues did greatlye flatter them selues, and boasted them selues to be the peculiar people of God, they were puft vp with incredible pride, and dyd perswade them selues, that the whole world pertayned to them, bycause they dwelled in the chiefe and best place thereof. They bragged often saying:<note place="margin">Phan. 8.</note>
            <hi>Nos natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Iudaei,</hi> we by nature are Iewes, and not synners of the Gentiles. VVe are not borne in fornication, but we haue God for our father, wyth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other such brags.</p>
         <p>Looke more of this matter, if ye wyll learne the fulnes thereof, in the booke called <hi>Scripturae medulla,</hi> compoed by Iacobus Naclantus.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="25" type="part">
      <pb facs="18"/>
      <head>Rachel &amp; Lia. 25.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y Rachel and Lia, are signified (as the diuines do writ) the two kinde of liues of man. By Lia, the actiue life, by Rachell, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue life.</p>
      <p>Lia is interpreted labour, and therfore it may well be applied to the actiue life of mā, which ought to cōtinue alway in some trauel &amp; labor.</p>
      <p>Lia was bleare eyed, by the which is signified the great cares and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubles, with the which man is pressed, and enforced sometime to weepe and mourne.</p>
      <p>Rachel doth signifie the life speculatiue, which is alwaies occupied in diuine matters, as the sinfull woman did sit at Christes feete, ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and weighing the wordes which she heard of him.</p>
      <p>Rachel is interpreted <hi>Ouis,</hi> a sheepe, by the which is signified, that they which be geuen to the life contemplatiue, shoulde be meeke, geuing place, studieng peace and quietnes, alwaies recording and chewing the cud of Gods law and his holy word.</p>
      <div type="question">
         <head>Questio.</head>
         <p>
            <note place="margin">Genes. 31.</note>VVhy did Rachel steale and conuey away her fathers idols, and what is signified therby?</p>
      </div>
      <div type="response">
         <head>Responsio.</head>
         <p>
            <note place="margin">Ephes. 5. 1. Sam. 15.</note>Couetousnes is the seruing of idols, as saint Paule writeth to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesians, and not to obey God, by the sentence of Samuel it is coumpted also idolatry. Furthermore to obserue supersticiously the letters, the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and the pointes of the law, (as the Cabalistes do) cannot be without the compasse of idolatrie.</p>
         <p>Therfore that Rachel stole her fathers idols, is manifestlye signified that they which do truly know God, and do vewe godlye thinges, do not onely coumpt the thing before recited, to be foolish and vayne, but also wicked and diabolical.</p>
         <p>Also by it is signified, that these twoo thinges, idolatrie and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious obseruation of the law, are taken away by Rachel, that is to say by the faith in Christ, who did manifest and open the secretes of God, &amp; taking away from the Phareseies, the scriptures and oracle of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, which they had corrupted with their false gloses, did restore the true sense and natural meaning vnto the law.</p>
         <p>The whole mistery that is signified by Lia and Rachel, is described at large in the sayd booke of Naclantus before named.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="26" type="part">
      <head>Valerius Maximus. 26.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were two of that name, the one called Valerius Potitus, who after the enuy which rose concerning the office called De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem
<pb n="14" facs="18"/> Viratus, did mitigate and appease with lawes, and certaine conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the people being stirred and moued against the Seniors.</p>
      <p>The office of Decem viratus, was this: Ther were .x. men chosen and appointed, which should make lawes, write, and publish them, and their authority was aboue al other, so that they might not onely make lawes, but also, if nede were, interprete them. And wher before were but .x. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of lawes, they added vnto them two more, and so all these lawes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether were called <hi>Leges duodecem tabularum.</hi> He (beyng the first Consull after the .x. men called <hi>Decem viri,</hi> when he had vanquished the people called Volsci) had a denial of the fathers for his triumph, but yet being the first, did make his triumphe, without the authoritye of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, with his companion and fellow Marcus Horatius, and therefore he got this name to be called Valerius Maximus.</p>
      <p>The other Valerius Maximus wrote worthy and memorable sayings and gestes, vnto Tiberius the Emperour, and did digest them in <hi>.9.</hi> bokes into common places. He was souldiour vnto Sextus Pompeius. He is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Valerius Maximus Historicus.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="27" type="part">
      <head>Alanus. 27.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were many of this name, one an englishe man called Alanus de Lynna, Allin of Lynne, a white Friar. He wrote one booke of diuers senses of the scripture. He wrote also a booke of the morals of the Bible, and also the booke entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Sermones notabiles.</p>
      <p>Maister Baal maketh mention of him in his booke De scriptoribus Angliae.</p>
      <p>An other Alanus was called Alanus Teukesberiensis, he wrote of the exile and life of Thomas Becket, Bishop of Canterbury.</p>
      <p>VVhat shal I speake of other, as of Alanus Restaldus, which wrote the institutions of the Hebrue Grammer?</p>
      <p>But this Alanus, whome I alledge, was a Germane, and wrote ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good workes, as the worke De complanctu naturae, and foure bookes vpon the sentences. Likewise vpon the fiue bookes of Moses, wyth many other. He flourished in the yeare of our Lord. <hi>1300.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="28" type="part">
      <head>Plinius. 28.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Her wer two of that name, who both were notably learned, the one was called Plinius secundus Veronensis. He lyued in the time of Vespatian, in whose affaires he was muche busied. He wrote the most excellent woorke called Naturalis historia, which he wrote by night, and at certayne times by stelth.</p>
      <pb facs="19"/>
      <p>Yet some say, that in that worke be many fables, and therefore he is named <hi>Pater fabularum,</hi> the father of lies. He would leese no time. He perished at the last in a certain hill, called Vesuuius, by fire, while he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to inuestigate and search the cause why the toppe therof should be baren.</p>
      <p>There was an other called Cecilius Plinius, neuew to the first Plinie by his sister, who wrote eloquent Epistles, and one oration to Traian the Emperour, in his commendation, which oration is named Panegeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. In the which he geueth thankes vnto Traian, who made him Consul. He helped the doughter of Quintiliā with a dowry, and also he succou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Martialis the Poet, departing with necessary costage for iourny, as Volateranus writeth. Lib. <hi>18.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="29" type="part">
      <head>Aediles. 29.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Edilis was an officer, whose charge was to see the mayntaining of the Temples and priuate houses, and to make prouision for so<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lemne playes. Of them some were called Ediles curules, of a chair with crooked feete, wherin they did sit, other wer called Aediles plebis, bicause they were chosen out of the people or commons.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="30" type="part">
      <head>Quirites. 30.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Virites was a name, wherby the Romanes wer called by their first king Romulus, called Quirinus, who was so called of thys word Quiris, which signifieth in the Sabin tounge a speare, which weapon Romulus did continually beare. Other write that he was so named of his father Mars, who was called when he was fierce, Gradiuus, when he was peaceable and quiet, Quirinus.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="31" type="part">
      <head>Bias. 31.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ias was one of the seuen wyse mē of Grece (beholding his coūtrye taken by enemies) fled, other men carying with them such goods as they might beare: he was demaunded why he tooke nothyng with him, whereto he answered: Trulye I carye all my goods with me, meaning vertue and doctrine, reputing the goods of Fortune none of his.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="32" type="part">
      <head>Parasites. 32.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Arasitus is properlye he which haunteth other mens tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, which also doth prayse all the wordes and dedes of him, in whose companye he is, doth neuer resist, but suffereth all thinges, and refuseth to do nothing, for his bellies sake, in the which he doth constitute his chiefe pleasure, &amp; of this he tooke his name <hi>quod</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>hoc est, e cibo totus pendeat,</hi> he hangeth altogether of meate. The image and nature of a parasite Terence doth trimly describe
<pb n="15" facs="19"/> in his Comedie called Eunuchus. The name of a Parasite, as Atheneus teacheth. lib. <hi>6.</hi> was once an honest name, for they were geuen to the holy ministery, and Parasites were called in times past the companions and fellowes of Bishops and Magistrates. This word <hi>Parasitus,</hi> hath the last sillable sauing one long. <hi>Horatius, lib. 2. epist. 1. quamuis sit Dorcennus edacibus in parasitis.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="33" type="part">
      <head>Fire in one hand. 33.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He like prouerbe is in Plautus, <hi>Altera manu fert lapidem, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra panem ostentat.</hi> In one hand he beareth a stone, in the other hand he sheweth bread. By this they are signified, which to the face flatter and speake faire, but priuely they do detract and report the wurst. The like prouerbe, hath Gregorius Theologus writing <hi>Ad Euse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium Caesariensem,</hi> saying: <hi>Perindequasi quis eiusdem viri altera manu scabat caput, altera manu feriat,</hi> that is, euen as one would scratch a mans head with one hand, and giue him a blow with the other.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="34" type="part">
      <head>Argi. 34.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Poetes fayne that Argus had an hundred eyes, and that Iuno appointed him to kepe Io, whom she had transformed to a Cow, but Mercurius being sent by Iupiter, wyth hys sweete harmony brought Argus a sleepe, slew him, &amp; toke Io from him, and brought her into Egipt. Then Iuno tooke Argus eyes and set them in the Pecockes tayle. The eyes of Argus do signify wisdom and circumspection, and that a man should vse prouident circumspecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all his doinges.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="35" type="part">
      <head>Fenel. 35.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Linie in his <hi>.20.</hi> booke, cap. <hi>23.</hi> saith that Serpentes hath eno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the herbe Fenel, for in tasting of it, they cast their olde skinne, &amp; refresh the sharpnes of the eye sight with the iuyce of Fenel VVherby it is vnderstand that the dimnes of mans sight, is also with it remedied.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="36" type="part">
      <head>Phisitions. 36.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Alexander the great, had passed ouer the mount Taurus, with a very expedite iourney, and came to Tharsus, being raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with the pleasātnes of the riuer Cydnus, which ran through the middle of the Citye, being in a great sweate, and ful of dust, put of his armour, &amp; went naked into the cold riuer, by reason wherof such a cold stifnes came into his limmes and ioyntes, that it was thought he shoulde rather dye then lyue.</p>
      <pb facs="20"/>
      <p>Then one of the Phisitions, Philip by name, did by himself alone promise recouery of health, but one Parmeniō sent letters vnto Alexander, that he shuld beware of Phillip his Phisitiō, for king Darius (saith he) hath corrupted him with a great sōme of mony, to poison you. Then Alexāder being in a suspēce, thought it a more safe &amp; better way to cōmit himself to the doubtful trust of the Phisition, then there to perishe and dye of that sodaine disease, he tooke the cup at Phillips handes, and deliuered him the letters to reade, and as he dronke, cast his eyes vpon the Phisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons countenance, and when he perceaued Phillip nothing abashed at the letters, cherefully dranke vp the whole potion, and the fourth day after recouered his health. This is a goodlye president for all Phisitions to be true and trusty to their soueraign Lords, and I would vnto God that the saying of Aristotle, with all that do practise phisicke, might be verified, <hi>Vbi definit philosophus, ibi incipit medicus.</hi> For a good Phisitiō ought to be a good Logitian, a Geometrician, a natural Philosopher, and a good Astronomer, of the which sciences how the Phisitions now a daies be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute and voyde, it is euident to al the world.</p>
      <p>Rome was without Phisitions sixe hundred yeares. Philemon was wont to say, <hi>Qum quiuis se habeat bene, tum medicus pessime.</hi>
      </p>
      <q>
         <l>When euery man is in good health,</l>
         <l>Then is the Phisition without his wealth.</l>
         <l>But when men be sicke and diseased,</l>
         <l>Then is the Phisition best pleased.</l>
      </q>
      <p>Pausanias a Lacedemonian, who alwaies hauing his health, without the conference and counsell of Phisitions, being demaunded of a certaine Phisition, how he came to so great an age without any disease, answered verye feately and merely. <hi>Quia non vsus sum te medico,</hi> bicause (saith he) I haue not vsed thee, nor any other for my phisition.</p>
      <p>Adrianus the Emperour, lying in his death bed, sayd: <hi>Turba medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum perdidit Cesarē,</hi> the multitude of phisitiōs hath killed the emperor.</p>
      <p>I write not this to the dispraise of that noble arte of phisicke, or the professors of the same, whom the holy scriptures commaunde to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for necessities sake.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="37" type="part">
      <head>Ouidius. 37.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vid was surnamed Naso, he gaue him selfe most diligently to the making of verses, in so much that he wrote of himselfe this verse. <hi>Quicquid conabar dicere versus erat.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But he was withdrawen from it by his father, and put to learne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricke wherin he much profited, and was in the nomber of the best ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors at that time, he was aduaunced to sondrie aucthorities, and made a
<pb n="16" facs="20"/>
         <hi>Senator,</hi> yet he chiefly gaue him self to Poetrie, wherin by nature he was excellent, both in facilitie, and also in aboundaunce of sentences.</p>
      <p>He was in great fauour with Augustus the Emperour, of whom at the last he was exiled into Pontus, where he spent the rest of his lyfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong people most barbarous, who notwithstandyng lamented his death for his curtesie and gentle maners. The cause why he was exiled, was for the abusing Iulia the Emperours daughter. Some suppose it was for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the booke, <hi>De arte amandi,</hi> wherby young mindes might be stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to wantones. There be whiche affirme .vi. of his bookes called Fasti, to haue bene inuented in this our time.</p>
      <p>He was borne in a towne called <hi>Sulmo,</hi> wherof he wrote these verses.</p>
      <q>
         <l>Sulmo mihi patria est gelidis vberimus vndis,</l>
         <l>Millia qui nouies distat ab vrbe decem.</l>
      </q>
      <p>Plinie maketh mention of this place. Lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>5.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="38" type="part">
      <head>Patience. 38.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertamen patientiae tale est vt qui vincitur ipso victore est me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior. Euripides.</hi>
      </p>
      <q>
         <l>Of patience alwaye suche is the conflicte,</l>
         <l>That better then the victor, is the conuict.</l>
      </q>
      <p>VVhen one had smitten Socrates with his foote, he suffred it patiēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but certeine of his disciples and fellowes taking it in ill part, did coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sell him to smite agayne. VVhat (sayth Socrates) if myne Asse had hit me with her heele, doth it behoue me to kicke agayne, by and by, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge it vpon the domme beast? Sabellicus.</p>
      <p>Philip king of Macedonia said, he was bound to rendre great thākes to the chief gouernours of the weale publicke of Athens, bycause by their slaunderous checkes they had made him better both in talke and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for I now endeuour (saith he) to cōuice them of lyes, both in sayings and doinges. O the noble and Philosophicall minde of the prince, whiche knew to take profit of his enemies, and not to haue onely a regarde (as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmon sorte doth) to punish and rendre euil to the ill sayers, but to care y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he myght be made lesse euill, beyng admonished by their euil sayinges.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="39" type="part">
      <head>Xenophon. 39.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">X</seg>Enophon a Philosopher of Athens, disciple of Socrates, &amp; was also a noble and politique capitaine, who for his most delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble stile in writing, was named the Muse of Athens. He made most excellent workes, replenished with such kind of wisdome and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine that to the instruction of a prince none maye be compared vnto hym. VVherefore it is to be wished, that all noble men woulde reade hys workes studiouslie.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>