<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>▪ To the Honourable Robert Askwith, Lord Mayor of the Citty of Yorke, and the Right Worshipfull his Graue Asso∣ciates and Brethren the Aldermen, all spiri∣tuall Graces, with wordly Prosperity in this life, and eternal happines in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Whitbourne, Richard, Sir</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106092_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10216</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20493</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>▪ To the Honourable Robert Askwith, Lord Mayor of the Citty of Yorke, and the Right Worshipfull his Graue Asso∣ciates and Brethren the Aldermen, all spiri∣tuall Graces, with wordly Prosperity in this life, and eternal happines in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Whitbourne, Richard, Sir</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ieremiahs teares, or A sermon preached in York-minster vpon Trinity Sunday, in the yeare of our Lord, 1604 : when the sicknes was begunne in the cittie. By Thomas Pullein vicar of Pontefract, sometime chaplaine of New Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Pullein, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Knight, Clement</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>▪ To the Honourable Robert Askwith, Lord Mayor of the Citty of Yorke, and the Right Worshipfull his Graue Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates and Brethren the Aldermen, all <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Graces, with wordly Prosperity in this</hi> life, and eternal happines in the life <hi>to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing of long time conceiued a purpose, (my good Lord) to giue some publicke Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of my Loue to your Honourable Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the place of my byrth, J began now in the latter end of your Lordships yeare, to consider, that J could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue a fitter opportunity, for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of my desire. Whereupon, beeing loath to vse any further delay, in letting passe so good an occasion, neere lost already, I was forced in hast, the time so requiring, to looke vp my old Papers, to see if I could finde any thing worthy to present vnto your Lordship. And while I was thus occupied, I bethought my selfe, of that Sermon which heeretofore
<pb facs="3"/>
I made in the City, when it was newly visited with the late contagious sicknes, being drawn thither at the earnest request of a Worshipful friend. And this J thought the fittest, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish at this time, for sundry causes First, to put vs in mind of the manifolde, Gracious, and Fatherly benefites, wherewith God hath bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vs aboue al the Nations of the Earth, and how we haue abused the same. Secondly, to set before vs the horrible sins wee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, with our monstrous vnthankfulnesse against his Maiesty. Thirdly, to renew a fresh the remembrāce of his seuere Chastisements, lately, but most iustly inflicted vpon vs which we seeme to haue vtterly forgotten. And last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to admonish vs, that if neither his blessings nor punishments wil moue vs to repent &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our liues, hee hath yet more fearefull iudgements, to astonish our rebellious harts, &amp; vtterly to make an end of vs, which though we haue escaped the plague, do still threaten our ruine and destruction. All which points, I had rather should be obserued out of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it selfe, then trouble this place with the repetition therof. The reason why I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb facs="3"/>
this vnto the end of your yere, was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I had partly heard by generall report, &amp; partly seene with mine owne eyes, how hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably you haue performed your Office, and passed your yeare with as much credit &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause, as any of your Predecessors, I coulde not but reioyce in your Lordships behalfe, &amp; for a Testimony of my Gratulation, bringe with me this pore present, to the shutting vp of your yeare, not doubting, but your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship will take the same in good part.</p>
   <p>And thus (honorable, and right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) commending this small exercise to your diligent reading, &amp; carefull practise, with my harty Praiers to the Lorde, for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his blessings vpon your Citty, &amp; that it will please him to replenish the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Gouernment with the knowledge of his heauenly truth, and feruent loue of his holy Gospel, framing their harts in obedience thereunto to their eternal Saluation, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue. <hi>Pontefract,</hi> this first of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, 1607.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships and Worships to command in the Lord Thomas Pullein.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="4"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>