<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the moste victorious / and our moste gracious soue∣raigne lorde kynge Henry the .viii. kynge of Englande and of France / Defender of the feyth / and lorde of Irelande. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1532</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106702_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01998</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12143</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106702</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the moste victorious / and our moste gracious soue∣raigne lorde kynge Henry the .viii. kynge of Englande and of France / Defender of the feyth / and lorde of Irelande. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Io. Gower de confessione amantis</title>
                 <author>Gower, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1532</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 191, 1 leave, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶To the moste victorious / and our moste gracious soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne lorde kynge Henry the .viii. kynge of Englande and of France / Defender of the feyth / and lorde of Irelande. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lutarke wryteth / whan Alexander had discō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte Darius the kynge of Perse / amonge other iewels of the sayde kynges there was founde a curyous lyttell cheste of great value / whiche the noble kynge Alexander beholdynge / sayde: This same shall serue for Homere. whiche is noted for the great loue and fauour / that Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander had vnto lernynge. But this I thynke veryly / that his loue and fauour therto / was not so great as your gracis: whiche caused me / moost victorious / and most redoubted souerayne lorde / after I had printed this warke / to deuyse with my selfe / whether I myght be so bolde to presente your hyghnesse with one of them / and so in your gracis name putte them forthe. your moste hygh and most princely maieste abasshed and cleane discouraged me so to do / both bicause the present (as concernynge the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue) was farre to symple / as me thought / and bycause it was none other wyse my acte / but as I toke some peyne to prynte it more correctly than it was before. And though I shulde saye / that it was not moche greatter peyne to that excellent clerke the morall Iohn̄ Gower to compyle the same noble warke / than it was to me to prynt it / no man wyll beleue it / without conferring both the printis / the olde and myn to gether. And as I stode in this basshement / I remembred your incomparable Clemency / the whiche / as I haue my selfe sometyme sene / moste graciously accepteth the sklender gyftes of small value / whiche your hyghnes perceyued were offred with great and louynge affection / and that not onely of the nobuls and great estates / but also of your meane subiectes: the whiche so mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che boldeth me agayne / that though I / of all other / am your mooste humble subiecte and seruaunt / yet my harte gyueth me / that your hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / as ye are accustomed to do / woll of your moste benigne nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider / that I wold with as good wyl / if it were as wel in my power / gyue vnto your grace the most goodlyest and largest cite of all the worlde. And this more ouer I very wel knowe / that both the nobuls and commons of this your most noble royalme / shall the soner accepte this boke / the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer rede it / and be the more diligent to marke and beare awey the morall doctrines of the same / whanne they shall se hit come forthe vnder your gracis name / whom they with all their very hartes so truely loue &amp; drede / whom they knowe so excellently well lerned / whome they euer fynde so good / so iuste / and so gracious a prince. And who so euer in redynge of this warke / dothe consyder it well / shal fynde / that it is plentifully stuffed and fournysshed with manyfolde eloquent reasons / sharpe and quicke ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes / and examples of great auctorite / perswadynge vnto vertue / 
<pb facs="7"/> not onely taken out of the poetes / oratours / historywryters / and philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers / but also out of the holy scripture. There is to my dome / no man / but that he may bi reding of this warke get right great knowlege / as wel for the vnderstandyng of many &amp; diuers autors / whose resons / sayenges / &amp; histories are translated in to this warke / as for the plenty of englysshe wordes and vulgars / besyde the furtheraunce of the lyfe to vertue. whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che olde englysshe wordes and vulgars no wyse man / bycause of theyr antiquite / wyll throwe asyde. For the wryters of later dayes / the whiche beganne to loth and hate these olde bulgars / whan they them selfe wolde wryte in our englysshe tonge / were constrayned to brynge in / in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges / newe termes (as some calle them) whiche they borowed out of latyne frenche / and other langages / whiche caused / that they that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstode not those langages / from whens these newe vulgars are fette / coude not perceyue theyr wrytynges. And though our most allowed olde autors dydde otherwhyle vse to borowe of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her langages / eyther by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of theyr metre / or elles for lacke of a feete englysshe worde / yet that ought not to be a president to vs / to heape them in / where as nedeth not / and where as we haue all redy wordes approued and receyued / of the same effecte and strength. The whiche if any man wante / let hym resorte to this worthy olde wryter Iohn̄ Gower / that shall as a lanterne gyue hym lyghte to wryte counnyngly / and to garnysshe his sentencis in our vulgar tonge. The whiche noble autour / I prostrate at your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis feete / most lowly present / and beseche your hyghnes / that it may go forthe vnder your gracis fauour. And I shal euer pray: God that is almyghtye preserue your royal maieste in mooste longe continuance of all welthe / honour / glorye / and grace infinite. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>