<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106505_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14689</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106505</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A deuoute mans purposes : Being zealous and comfortable meditations, to weane a man from this world, and the vanities thereof</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Mattes, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mattes, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 183, 2 leaves, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this book to any fauorite of this worlde, because it will prooue too vnsauorie for his taste, and to wishe it to one that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiseth the worlde, being ignoraunt of his abode, I know not how to sende it him▪ therefore in so hard a case this wilbe most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for mee, to let it passe along with what suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse shall please God to
<pb facs="6"/> send it, for he will giue his blessing to euery good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour.</p>
   <p>Concerning the title which is giuen to the booke, it may bee carpt at by some, and misconstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by others, as if this poor man did imagine himselfe onely to be deuout, or that none but he were acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the rules of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But thus he answers for himselfe: He tearmes it not the Deuoute mans Purposes, in any respect of his owne singularitie, or that he is, or easily can bee so mortified from this worlde, as these seuerall Meditations doo instruct
<pb facs="6"/> a man to bee: but he that will attaine to true deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion indeed, and frame his life as becommeth a good christian, he must (in his opinion) lay holde vppon these purposes, as also ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely to practise them in his dayly conuersation, whereto God giuing the holy assistance of his spirit, and enabling him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede on in these religious determinations: that then they may iustly be called a deuout mans purposes, &amp; no man can so purpose, but he will bee deuout in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</p>
   <p>And thus yee haue this poore mans plaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb facs="7"/> farre from proude conceite of himselfe, or misdeeming of others. Read first, and then iudge, be as slow in condemning him, as ye would haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to deale with you: If these purposes please ye, looke the sooner for his <hi>Preparation,</hi> and but that they should both benefite, he could wish them buryed in vtter obliuion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>