<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title> ❧ THE PROEME.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106942_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03467</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1359</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106942</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title> ❧ THE PROEME.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of man : sucked from the sappe of the most approued anathomistes, in this present age, compiled in most compendious fourme, and now published in English, for the vtilitie of all godly chirurgians, within this realme, by Iohn Banister, Master in Chirurgerie, and practitioner in phisicke</title>
                 <author>Banister, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 112, 4 leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head> ❧ THE PROEME.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Yme, the generall rust of the world, which weareth eateth, consumeth, and perfora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all thynges, hath denied that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of the deuine parentes and proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours of Phisicke, should for euermore remaine insoluble, or free from all future chaūge: els what should withstand, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the workes of Hipocrates and Galene should not suffice all posterities that come after? For what thyng notable haue they not noted? what secret so daintie, that they haue not vncouered yea what misterie so couert, the doore wherof they haue not opened? And yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, these deuine Oracles haue not taken from posteritie all occasion to write, neither shall the bookes which hitherto are written, do the like to those that come after. But ech age hath his tyme, eche nation his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ech nature his property.</p>
   <p>Albeit, this excellencie we ascribe to Hipocrates and Galen, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any hath bene their equals, and that from their fountaines flow the springyng streames, that nourishe Phisicke for euer. So that what good thing soeuer we haue, or atcheiue, we are to consecrate the same vnto their honor and prayse: and what worke soeuer is published, if the same be worth the reading, we owe it wholly vnto them. What thē (you will say) is the cause, that their workes suffer in these dayes such sundry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, especially in the partes of mans body? It is aunswered a litle before, how that tyme, natures, and nations must be respected.</p>
   <p>For first; that the magnitude of our body is greatly diminished, it is a<note place="margin">Iac. Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. in Isag. Pre.</note> thing in readynes to euery man, not onely by the authoritie of auncient<note place="margin">Ph. Lib. 7. cap. 6.</note> writers, but also that dayly, and (as I suppose) throughout the world, the stature of mā in all pointes decreaseth: especially in those regions: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as matrimonie is ouer liberally, &amp; before the iust age, permitted. Who is so ignoraunt; to whom the Scriptures haue not ere now testified, how much longer then in these dayes, the age of mā hath bene in times past?<note place="margin">Iac. Sil. Ibid.</note> how aboundantly do our bodies testisie, how sondry of the inner partes both in magnitude, number, figure, and situation, do differ from those in others of other regions? neither are the same in all our bodies in these dayes, as, in elder time the auncient Anathomistes most commōly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued: do not their writynges, and our bodies make it manifest to all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing? but towhat end? that it might not seeme to vs incredible, that in men of euery region, like as in beastes, yea in the plantes them selues, is either some thyng peculiar from others, or els some certaine mutation from the sirst nature to haue chaunced.</p>
   <p>As, to come first to the exāples of beastes. In Ciria the sheepe haue<note place="margin">Arist. Lib. 8. hist. ca. 28.</note> tayles a cubite broad, and the goates eares ix. intches in length. What meruaile is it when as the ramme and the ewe, whiche both in Affrica
<pb facs="7"/>
beare hornes, in Pontus a prouince of Scythia, to haue therfore none at all? As other where sheepe, so in Cilicia goates are clipped. The oxen, sheepe, hartes, and such others, are greater in Aegipt then in Greece: but for that the dogges, wolues, foxes, hares, and hawkes, are greater in Greece thē in Aegipt. Oxē in Scythia through cold possesse no hornes. Oxen in Phrygia haue hornes that are mouable. The Isle Ithaca is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute of a hare, like as the field called <hi>Ager Lebadicus</hi> of a moule, and Sardinia of a wolfe.</p>
   <p>If histories be to be beleued, then these are true: if not, what do we with auncient testimonies? why credite we thynges written, or beleue any thyng to be true which our owne eyes haue not witnessed vnto vs? yea let vs reiect the monumentes of our elders, detract their doynges, and wholy obliterate their writynges. And if the bookes of Aristotle, Plinie, and others most famous Historiographers, be worthy to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, thē are beastes in Asia, all more cruell, in Europe more stronger, and in Aphrica more diuersly fourmed. But, to speake more appertinēt to the body of man, these aforesayd varieties, obserued of auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, arguyng onely vnto vs, that, as beastes are bred diuersly in eche na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and accordyng to the nature therof, so to be in men some dissimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; by the same reason, was not denied. Euery one knoweth that the Moores haue onely white teeth, but blacke skinne and nayles. But it is not a thyng so commō that they, and also the inhabitantes of such hoate<note place="margin">Cor. Cels. Li. 8. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> countreys, are without seames in their Sculs, which with vs is a thyng somuch approued.</p>
   <p>But, omittyng those natiōs which differ a litle amōg thē selues, let vs come to those which more manifestly vary in figure. In Asia are a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple named Macrocephali, hauing very long heades, though first of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome<note place="margin">Hipochr. de. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ere.</note>
      <note place="margin">Aquis et lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>is Lib.</note> then after of nature: of custome, because they kept the compres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed heades of their children, swathed so, till some consistence of yeares grew on them, which thyng afterward made their children beget the like, though in tract of tyme, and through their negligence, nature amē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that fault. The people called Phasiani, inhabityng a marish ground and rayny region, are in figure from other men very diuers: as, of mighty stature, and marueilous corpulēt, so that neither veynes, nor ioyntes are in them apparaunt, alway bearing a yellow colour, like persons afflicted with the iaundes, and in voyce most base and terrible.</p>
   <p>It is straūge to vs that womē haue beardes, albeit not so euery where:<note place="margin">Hipp. Lib. 6. Epid.</note> for in Caria it is a thyng familiar: whereas some of them beyng a while frutefull, but after widowes, and for that suppressed of naturall course, put on virilitie, being then bearded, hoarie, and chaūged in voyce. Shall it be counted a fable that toucheth the transformation of one kinde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an other, as the Male into the Female and so contrariwise? surely Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie<note place="margin">Lib. 7. Cap. 4.</note> saith. No: since him selfe to haue sene a woman chaunged into man, in the day of mariage, he playnly auoucheth. And agayne, a child of a yeare old, from a mayden to a boy. There are certaine wild men whose
<pb facs="7"/>
feete are turned backward on the legges, and some of them hauyng viij.<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>i. I: b. 7. cap. 2.</note> toes on a foote. What shall we say of the Cyclopes, whose eyes haue in thē two apples or balles? I omit to speake of those that haue but one eye: of those that are both Male &amp; Female: of such as haue heades like dog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>: of the people which haue no heades: of them who with one legge co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their whole body: of those without mouthes: and so forth of such sortes many, which are in Indie very familiar.</p>
   <p>True it is also that the Scythiās, named Nomades, are very corpulēt,<note place="margin">Hipp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ib. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <note place="margin">Aquis. et. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and fleshy, their inferiour bellyes euer slippery, &amp; their ioyntes through moysture very weake, in somuch as they are euer found to haue applied fier to their shoulders, armes, handes, brestes, hippes, and loynes, for no other cause, then for the naturall moysture and softenes: for thus if they should not do, they would not be able to hold their bowes, or cast their darts, for losenes of their loints, through slippery humors so obnoxious to luxation. And it is no more truly written of the Pygmeiās, then mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous<note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ast. cap. 15.</note> to our vnderstandyng, since they are of so small stature (for they exceede not in height the length of a cubite) that dayly they are prest to put on armour agaynst Cranes.</p>
   <p>These Argumentes, and sundry such others, which Iacobus Siluius<note place="margin">Iac. Sil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> hath gathered together, and therfore I thinke them also most fitte for this place, may not lightly moue vs, to beleue likewise that in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies sometyme sundry mutations do happen.</p>
   <p>In places either very hoate, or very cold, men are in countenaunce<note place="margin">Sec. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>b.</note> and maners fierce and cruell: notwithstanding they that inhabite hoate places are more fearefull, though wiser: and they which dwell in cold, strōger. The Asians are fairer, greater, more gentle, feareful, effoeminate, and vnapt to warre for the temperature of the ayre and lawes.</p>
   <p>The Europ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ans cōtrariwise are in magnitude much different amōg<note place="margin">Hipp. Loc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> them selues, cruell, of hauty courage, bold, vpright or honest, and giuen to warre. They differ (I say) in magnitude, and fourme, through the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the tymes of the yeare, which there are great and often: as strōg heate; vehemēt cold, much rayne, long draught, and strōg windes, whereby euery where, sundry, and many mutations are made. In Asia so the other creatures, and all plantes are more happely produced then in Europe. Many kyndes of men are in Europe, which in magnitude, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, fourme, and stature are much different among them selues. The caus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> of which varietie is somewhat before touched, but Hipocrates<note place="margin">Loc. cit.</note> more clearely doth descriue. As they which inhabite a place or region full of mountaines, rough, high, and watry, and haue with thē many mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tariōs of tymes much differēt, it is requisite that of their own nature be mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> many fourmes os bodyes, and such as are laboursome, exercised, and strong, and such natures also to be fierce and cruell.</p>
   <p>Agayn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>hey which reigne in places more medowy, or groūdes flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng with herbes, and hoate, &amp; their windes more hoate thē cold, &amp; vse hoate, or warme waters, these persons are not high, butrather broad,
<pb facs="8"/>
with blacke heares, and they more of dusky colour or browne, then are bred in other places, and of their owne nature lesse flegmaticke then cholericke. But they that inhabite a high and pleasaūt place, not rough, or windy, and haue good waters, these are large in body, straight, and like vnto them selues, endewed with witte and myndes more milde and gentle: like as they of thinne, barreine, and not watry and naked places, neither haue the mutations of tymes temperate, are hard bodies, not great, rather yellow then blacke, wayward, irefull, bold, and obstinate in opinion. For where often mutations of tymes are, and those also much different, truly there also may you finde their fourmes, maners, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures greatly disagreeyng. The regions wherein tymes and waters are chaunged, or do varie, the bodyes there also do vary: since alway, or for the most part, the maners and fourmes of the people do imitate the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the region.</p>
   <p>If then the varietie of times doth so transmute, and chaunge the state<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ig. de. Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>n. ob.</note> of mans body, as that worthely sayth Virgill (although perhaps he had not altogether this sense.)</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Tempora dispensat usus, &amp; tempora cultus,</l>
      <l>Haec homines, pecudes, haec moderantur aves.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>It is straunge to see how sturdely some striue to deface those, which, full of Naturall pietie, write the truth of their owne tymes. Why, they will haue it that there were neuer Amazones in Scythia, because per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps<note place="margin">Iac. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>l. Loc. cit.</note> there are none now to be founde. Aristotle erred, for saying there were no Asses in Fraūce, Ponte, and Scythia, because now in those coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys they abounde. Hipocrates he is reproued, for affirmyng no kinges to be in Europe, though at this day it possesseth plentie. What is it, that in the tyme of Aesculapius were no distillations nor inflations. Hipocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes<note place="margin">Plat. Dial. 3. de. Repub. Li. de. caus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> saw no rigour without a feuer, though in Galens dayes it chaunced often, but now a dayes most often, especially to womē, through a more intemperate diet.</p>
   <p>If we shall stand vpon disseases purchased by tymes, yea yet dayly, by the immoderation of diet, when should we draw to an end. In the age of Galen Eunuches did incurre the gowte, though long before, and in<note place="margin">Aph. 28. 29. 30. Lib. 2.</note> the tyme of Hipocrates it was notso. Also the gowte, pleurisie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamations<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ib. de. coacis prae not.</note> of the lunges were not wont to chaunce before the age of xiiij. yeares, but where standeth it at that stay now? who hath not sene them all at younger yeares? yeasome of them at x. ix. yea (though the more meruailous) at viij. yeares of age. The which thyng I dare boldly testifie, since, in Not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ingham, in An. 1574. it pleased God to make me the instrumēt of health to diuers childrē, of the ages before recited, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng no present remedy (for to diuers in the beginnyng I assayed other helpes in vayne) but Phlebotomie, notwithstandyng their tēder yeares, the dissease beyng the Plurisie, and the tyme of the yeare the spring.</p>
   <p>What Artist of experience in these dayes knoweth not, that women (for the most part) do beare males aswell on the left side as the right, and
<pb facs="8"/>
their females aswell on the right side as the left? the transuerse processes of the Vertebres of the necke appeare vnto vs alway as if they were clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">Iac. Sil. Loc. ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> though to Galen the last of them was seldome so. Os Sternon Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, with the elders, obserued perpetually to consist of seuen Bones, but we in these dayes neuer inuent the number so large: albeit that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer finde the number certaine.</p>
   <p>What then? shall we finde the number of the Vertebres alway one? he that hath so the happe, let him set it downe. For my part, amongest those very few bodies, which, also in very few yeares, though to my cost, yet for the very zeale I haue had thereto, I haue dissected, I haue found some of Galens Sceletons in sundry pointes. It may fall out to be no new saying, that almost in all bodies, some varietie is to be sene.</p>
   <p>Much meruailous shall it be to him that vseth dissection, to see such sundry and often varieties: yea, settyng aside monstrous shewes, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathomist shall see in his own region, and in few yeares, sundry notes of new shapes in nature, not so straunge now, as worthy the notyng.</p>
   <p>To praetermitte those whiche Vesalius obserued, because they are confused, let vs come to the most notable, by others descriued and set in order.</p>
   <p>Collūbus, that Anathomist of worthy fame, beginning at the head,<note place="margin">Col. Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> runneth through the whole body, notyng what new thyng he hath in any particle obserued. So that first he excuseth not the head, but that he hath sene it sometime without seames, somtime with sundry seames, and those keepyng diuers orders, to haue bene compact together. The teeth in diuers numbers: and the neither iawe growne to the vpper. Of the necke, the first Vertebre inseparably growne to Occiput: the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Vertebres of the necke sometyme sixe, and sometyme eight with the like varietie at sundry tymes of the other Vertebres. Of ribbes xxij. xxv. and xxvj. Os Sternon consistyng of two, three, and iiij, Bones. The thigh to haue ouergrowne the legge into an incredible tumor. But aboue all these it is notable that he reporteth of a Sceleton, whose Bones all, from the head to the toes, were ioyned together, so that the partie in his lyfe tyme, beyng old, could moue no part saue his eyes, toung, brest, bellye, and yard. I passe with silence, the aboundaunce, or want of Muscles whereof he remembreth, and the sundry trases of Veynes, with their want, or extraordinarie diuisions. Of the kidneys he sawe the singular number, although that a greate one, and Splenes so large, as that eche one in waight peised twenty pound, beyng out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ouercouered with a Cartilage. So vlcers, and tumours in the hart. So the hedge that distinguisheth the Ventricles of the hart, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilaginous. It was straunge to behold Pericardium, the enclosure of the hart, wantyng. What then? he obserued stones in the lunges, liuer, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Porta, vrinarie wayes, in the bleddar, Hemorroidall Veynes, and in the nauell of sundry straunge abscesses, in diuers bodies obserued, the same authour also remembreth. But among all thynges that he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="9"/>
this one seemeth most notable, whiche he reporteth of a woman, who had outwardly a perfect shape, &amp; onely the necke of the matrice, but no matrice, seminarie vessels, or Testicles at all: and so oft as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the company of man, (which she did often) she in meruailous sorte moued her selfe.</p>
   <p>But why stand I so long vpon the obseruations of Columbus, an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathomist of such yeared experience? come we to them that scarse dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sected two for his twentie, for it is more rare that they haue inuented such nouelties.<note place="margin">Lib. de. Var. Corp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ec.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Iacobus Siluius in his tyme sawe sundry illusions of Nature, both in men, women, and children: in the liuer, splene, kidneys, ventricle, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreif, intrels, veynes, and matrice. All which, to penne particularly, I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Botall. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ib. de cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>o.</note> together with the straunge, or rather monstrous kidneys which Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallus mentioneth, and hath openly depainted: as also his obseruation of the foure Ossicles or litle Bones in the diuisiō of the brayne: since it hath bene my happe to see much in few dissections.</p>
   <p>And first (touchyng the Sceleton) in the number of Vertebres: as sometyme sixe in the loynes: sometyme foure, sometyme fiue in Os sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum: and sometyme three, sometyme one in Cauda. Among the inner partes, I haue obserued the liuer twise deuided into lobes. To the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side and bottome of the matrice I haue found a certaine mole, or masse, white in colour, and hard, or in substaunce Cartilaginous, in fashion like the Testicles, as yet within their purse enuolued: saue that it wayed almost ij. poūd. This bieng cut, cōteined aboundaunce of slimie matter, which at the first brust forth thinner, though at last, very thicke and sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in deede. Once, in an aged Gentlewoman I searched in vayne for the right vētricle of the hart. And once in the hart of man I foūd a thing notable, and which these before named haue made no mention of, that is, a bone in the hart, situated at the endes of the vessels inserted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, as in the History of Bones I haue more copiously handled. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides in the same old mā (forso he was in deede a man prest to the groūd with dayes) I saw one of the vrinarie vessels, which, for the space of an intche (or more) in length, had wholly possessed a Cartilaginous sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce, which seemed still to encrease.</p>
   <p>But here perhappes some are ready to obiect, and say, why what then? do you intend to reiect those authorities which fo oft you haue here alledged, nay, not alledged, but rather out of whose mynes all this treasure is digged? no, but I could wishe with Siluius that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one might be more zealous to searche the truth, then busie seekers to finde oportunitie agaynst their elders. And those in deede the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes of all Phisicke. For if in any thyng they disagree from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of other regions, surely these rehearsed Argumentes are suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to proue the same farre more worthy to be imputed to the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of regions, and chaunge of tymes, then otherwise, with foule obloquie to spurte our elders, whilest we ourselues in the meane tyme,<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>c, ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <pb facs="9"/>
as maleuolent detractours are publiquely denounced. <hi>Siluius</hi> therfore wisheth him that findeth any thyng otherwise then Galen hath written it, to ascribe the same as a certaine addition to Galens Anathomie, els frendly to admonish the reader therof.</p>
   <p>As for my selfe, I confesse I haue in sundry places cited, and as it were enrolled Galen in sundry errours, yet not by halfe so oft as my au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours haue prouoked me? for <hi>Vesalius</hi> chiefly, and <hi>Collumbus</hi> (as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) haue spared him in no place. Which hath excited me (frēdly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) familiarly thus to warne therof in the begynnyng, that when thou readest them, thou mayest rightly know from whence they come.</p>
   <p>In the meane tyme to come to the matter proposed, I commit to thy diligence in the begynnyng the History of Bones, the frame of the body, wherein (of truth) attentiuenes ought to be vsed, both to carie in mynde, together with thy eye, the direct sense of the present descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed part, or rather (if it may be) to conferre the same with the Scele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton it selfe, as also because it is an introduction to the whole History of Man, and may be called the keye of knowledge to Anathomie: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the perfectiō wherof, the rest is not onely obscure, but almost vayne at all to read. After the Bones, ensue the Cartilages: then the Ligamēts: after those the Muscles: next the Muscles the nutritiue partes: and next the nutritiue the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue partes. Then at length the spirituall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: and finally the animall. To these I haue added a ninth, least (otherwise) the marey, Periosteon, and the heares should haue bene sought in vayne in the History of Man. All these to my power, I haue faythfully, and therewithall sufficient briefly, compiled together. Now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth no more, but read, and enioye.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>