<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull his very good Patrone, Mr. Henry Hall Esquire, one of his Maiesties Iustices of the Peace and Quorum in the County of Kent; and to the truely Pious, and Religious Gentlewoman, Ms. Iane Hall his Wife: All Felicitie, Internall, Externall, Eternall.</title>
           <author>Boughton, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106544_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16497</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3410</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull his very good Patrone, Mr. Henry Hall Esquire, one of his Maiesties Iustices of the Peace and Quorum in the County of Kent; and to the truely Pious, and Religious Gentlewoman, Ms. Iane Hall his Wife: All Felicitie, Internall, Externall, Eternall.</title>
                 <author>Boughton, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>God and man. Or, a treatise catechisticall : wherein the sauing knowledge of God and man is plainely, and breifely declared, whereby such as are ignorant may be helped, to heare sermons with profit, to reade the Bible or other bookes with iudgement, to receiue the Lords Supper with comfort, to discerne betweene truth and error, with vnderstanding, and to giue an answere to their minister, or any other that shall aske them a reason of their faith, with readinesse. Collected out of the sacred Scriptures, and the most orthodoxe and best approued diuines ancient and moderne, for the good of such as desire to be made wise to saluation, and heires of eternall life. By I.B. preacher of the Word</title>
                 <author>Boughton, John, preacher of the word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 185, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull his very good Patrone, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Henry Hall Esquire, one of his Maiesties</hi> Iustices of the Peace and Quorum <hi>in the County of</hi> Kent; <hi>and to the</hi> truely Pious, and Religious <hi>Gentlewoman,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">s</seg>. <hi>Iane Hall</hi> his Wife: All Felicitie, <hi>Internall, Externall, Eternall.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE saying of one (Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) is most true:<note n="a" place="margin">French hist. <hi>1187.</hi>
      </note> Compare vice with vice, and euill with euill: Ingratitude is the most odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and the worst. <hi>Vitium om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Theodoric. dom. <hi>14.</hi> post. trin. p. <hi>2.</hi> d. <hi>3.</hi> Ingratum si dixeris omnia dixeris.</note>
      <hi>teterrimorum teterri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> of all foulest vices the most foule, admitting no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell. And yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it is the common vice of this vicious, and flagitious age of ours: a Gangrene that hath diffused it selfe farre and neere.<note n="c" place="margin">Para. in Gen. <hi>1970.</hi> b.</note>
      <hi>Turpissima ingratitudine pleri{que} omnes obliterare solent beneficia accepta.</hi> It is the guise of the most, with filthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude to obliterate recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fauours. Iniuries are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in brasse, but benefits are written vpon the waters: And<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 40.23.</note>
      <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler hath but too many consorts, who remember not, but forget their <hi>Iosephs,</hi> their benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. My desire is not to
<pb facs="3"/> be found in this list: And therefore I am bold to present you with this poore oblation. A poore present I confesse to gratifie them withall, to whom I am so deepely enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. T'is but a silly mite, I owe you many talents, yea (as<note n="e" place="margin">Hieron. Sophron.</note>
      <hi>Hierom</hi> sometime sayd to one) <hi>&amp; quae possum, &amp; quae non possum,</hi> both what I can, and what I cannot, make tender of. And such are your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits towards mee, that (as<note n="f" place="margin">Effecisti vt viuerem &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerer ingratus. Senec. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de benef. cap. <hi>25.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Furnius</hi> once to <hi>Caesar</hi>) I must liue and die ingrate. Howbeit, whatsoeuer it is, be pleased to vouchsafe it your fauourable acceptation, as a Symboll and Testimony of my gratefull mind, and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="4"/> respect towards you both; for your great vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued fauours. In confidence whereof (not meaning to tire you with a tedious incult Epistle) I humbly take my leaue, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships most obliged, and in the Lord euer to be commanded,</hi> Iohn Boughton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>