<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Brilkley, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106872_Bo1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17145</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4026</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106872</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Brilkley, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie for the religion established in the Church of England : Being an answer to T.W. his 12. Articles of the last edition. In this impression recognized and much inlarged. Also answers to three other writings of three seuerall papists. By Ed: Bulkley Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Bulkley, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 6, 9-270, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, I am to certifie thee of the occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sion of the first wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and now publishing of this my answere to these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions and calumntations. In the yeare 1592. a good vertuous gentlewoman, called M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stris <hi>lane Brograue,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et liuing, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Wapnam in Northampton shire, being in her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Country with her friends, some not so well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffected to the truth as others, pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sed be God, are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>id giue to her these questions, intending thereby (as it seemeth) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert her, and to conuert her from the trueth of God, vnto their false Doctrine &amp; Idolatry. The which she presently deliuered vnto me, and desired mee to write an answere vnto them. This her godly request I thought my selfe bound in conscience for to satisfie, and thereupon I did forthwith in short time write this answere, the which she did send to her deceaued friends, for their better instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and information. Afterwards by wards which a Popish Priest in conference with me did vtter, I did ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the same was sent to Wish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he, there to be ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mered, and examined. But what they did wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h it. I doe not know. I neuer heard that either they, or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uer
<pb facs="112"/> made any reply vnto it. I haue beene moued by some, and namely by M. <hi>Christopher Goodman</hi> (to whom I did send a copie of it, because it did concerne him) to publish it in print. The which although it was allowed to the Presse many yeares past, by one in great place and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie now, yet I haue vntill this time suppressed it, howbeit now I haue yeelded to publish it, partly because the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both obiected and answered is suteable to the former articles, and my answeres: and partly because the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who had intelligence of it, did earnestly desire to haue it. I haue now passed it, as at the first I did write it without addition or alteration. This I confesse that thou good Reader mayst reade these things, namely those of <hi>Aerius, Vigilantius,</hi> &amp;c. obiected to vs, more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly and largely answered by others, especially by that reuerend and learned man M. <hi>D. Abbot</hi> in his learned answere to <hi>D. Bishops</hi> Epistle. Notwithstanding, if this my simple labour herein bestowed, may serue in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to the confirmation of the truth, and confutation of errour: to the instruction and edification of the faithfull that reade and receiue it, and, if not to reclaime the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, yet to be a testimonie and witnesse against them, that will be more ready to reiect it, then to reade and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine it, I know that God shall thereby be glorified, and his Church profited, the which is the onely thing I seeke and desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Aprill 22. 1608.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in Iesus Christ, ED. BRILKLEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>