<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>How to make Bread of Casaua rootes.</title>
           <author>Hughes, Lewes</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106329_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03803</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13920</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>How to make Bread of Casaua rootes.</title>
                 <author>Hughes, Lewes</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and trve relation of the goodnes of God towards the Sommer Ilands : written by way of exhortation, to stirre vp the people there to praise God. VVherevnto are added certaine qvestions and answers concerning the keeping holy of the Saboth day, and publicke exercises of religion, written in the Summer Ilands for the benefit of the people there. By Levves Hvghes minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Hughes, Lewes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <p>striuing to keepe them in thankfull remembrance, and as occasion serueth, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eake of them in all places, to stirre vp as many, as you can to praise God with you; I for my part will helpe what I can.</p>
   <p n="1">1 First, let vs think vpon &amp; consider of the great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God towards those Ilands in their first creation; how God did then inuiron and fortifie them about, with fearefull Rocks and sholes; by meanes whereof, you dwell as safe from forraigne inuasion, as any people in the world, which is a great comfort.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Consider we also, how Almighty God by his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prouidence; in their first creation did fit them with two goodly and large harbours, with such curious &amp; nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row comming in, as few men in the Plat-formes and Forts on both sides the Channels are able (by the helpe of God) to sinke all Ships of Enemies that shall offer to come in.</p>
   <p n="3">3 Note also the goodnesse of God towards you in the matter of artificiall fortification, in that, howsoeuer at the arriuall of Captaine <hi>Nathaniell Butler</hi> your Gouernour, there was by former neglects, a generall decay that way; yet, within the space of one onely yeare, we haue attained to that perfection, that the particulers following men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As first, at the Kings Castle, there are at this present 18. great Peeces excellently mounted, the most of them vpon new Cariages of Caedars; and fiue more are moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Southampton Fort, newly made by Captaine <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> which flankers the Kings Castle so, that there are in all 23. Peeces of Ordinance that play vpon the mouth of that Harbour.</p>
   <p>At <hi>Pembroke</hi> Fort there are two great Peeces; in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets</hi> Fort fiue; and in <hi>Smithes</hi> Fort fiue, the which two last Forts command the mouth of the Harbour of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Georges.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>At <hi>Warwick</hi> Fort are three more to commaund that Harbour: At the Towne before the Gouernors house are eight to commaund the Harbour, and to keepe Shallops from landing; another at the foote of the Mount, to serue for a Warning-Peece; and at S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Katherines</hi> Fort two, to skoure that Bay: In all, you haue at the present 53. Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of great Ordinance very well mounted, whereof 26. are newly mounted by Captaine <hi>Butler,</hi> and most of all the other so repaired, as that now they are become fully ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable.</p>
   <p>The Mount which was blowne downe with a terrible gust of winde, being the Eye of the Iland, and a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, because from the top of it, ships were discouered, is built againe by Captaine <hi>Butler,</hi> so that now these Ilands are well fitted and prepared both within and without, against all forraigne inuasions. Gods holy &amp; great name be therefore praised.</p>
   <p n="4">4 Consider also of the goodnes of God, in reseruing and keeping these Ilands, euer since the beginning of the world, for the English Nation, and in not discouering them to any, to inhabit but to the English.</p>
   <p n="5">5 Consider also of the manner, how they were disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and (by the mercy of God) made as a <hi>Ionas</hi> his Whale, to receiue into safety, men out of hope of life: I meane, when in the yeare of our Lord, 1609. eight sailes of Ships, were sent from England to Virginia; all which continued together from the 15. of May, till the 25. of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when (by reason of a storme, which continued three dayes, wherein they saw neither Sun, Moone, nor Starres) the Admirall, called the <hi>Sea: Aduenture,</hi> a Ship of 300. Tunnes, lost sight of the rest, and was ready to sinke euery houre, being nine foote deepe of water in the hold (the
<pb facs="3"/> storme still encreasing) and all the men out of hope of life, and tired with bailing and pumping: then (by the mercy of God) they discried these Ilands and within two houres after, the Shippe (ready to sinke, if shee had gone but her length further) did strike betweene two Rockes, where she stuck fast; then presently God shewed his mercy, and his power in rebuking the winde, so as it ceased, and the Sea, which before with euery waue, was ready to ouer-rake her, became quiet and calme, on the sodaine, and all with glad hearts went quietly to shore, praising God, who tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the stormy winde into a calme, Psal. 107.29. and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the raging of the Sea, and stilleth the waues thereof when they rise, Psal. 89.10.</p>
   <p>They remayned in ihese Ilands about ten moneths, and builded a couple of Pinnaces, with which they sayled to Virginia, and caried with them good store of powdred Porke and Bacon, made of wilde Hogges, whereof they found in these Ilands great plenty.</p>
   <p>Also they caried liue Tortoyses, salted Birds, and salt Fish which they tooke and salted here, and therewith sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued many of their liues that were in <hi>Virginia,</hi> whom they found there ready to perish through want of food: Before that prouision was spent,<note place="margin">Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>irall of the Fleet.</note> Sir <hi>Geo. Summers</hi> returned hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for more, and here ended his dayes. Sir <hi>Geo. Summers</hi> being dead, his men would not goe againe to <hi>Virginia,</hi> but came for England, &amp; left behind them in these Ilands three men; <hi>Edward Chard, Christofer Carter,</hi> and <hi>Edward Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n?</hi> these three they left here, because they would not goe with them (God did put into their hearts such loue and liking of these Ilands.) These three men found good store of Ambergreece to the value of 9000. pound, which I am perswaded, God brought into their hands of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
<pb facs="3"/> to encourage the Aduenturers to vndertake this Plantation.</p>
   <p>Thus it pleased God to discouer these Ilands, in great mercy for the safety of them that were ready to perish in the Sea, and for the sauing of their liues also, who were ready to perish in <hi>Virginia,</hi> through want of food, though now they be (as I heare) in good estate, thanks be to God.</p>
   <p>I am perswaded that Almighty God, who by his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and gracious prouidence, hath discouered and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed these Ilands vpon our Nation, hath some great worke of wonder, to bring to passe by them, to his great glory: therefore be glad of them, and praise him for them, despise them not for the smalnesse of them, because Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God doth most commonly by small meanes bring great thinges to passe. And take heede that your sinnes doe not prouoke God to cut you off; so as your eyes shall not see, what God will bring to passe. The more to stirre you vp to praise God, consider how many wayes, God hath shewed his loue, and care of you, since your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into these Ilands.</p>
   <p n="1">1 You that were sent in the first Ship called the <hi>Plowe,</hi> with M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Richard Moore</hi> Gouernour, in the yeare of our Lord 1611. you were no sooner within the Harbour, but, for your welcome, God brought plenty of good Fish to the Ship side, which did attend vpon you, and follow the Boat to shore, where some did cast out of the water with their hands, so much as did suffice you all, which did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce you much.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Consider also how (to your further ioy) God brought vnto you, the three men that were left in the Iland, all three in good health, fat and well liking, though out of clothes.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <pb facs="4"/>3 Consider also how God by them had prouided an Acre of good Wheat, ripe and ready to be gathered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the Wheat that you found in their houses, with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Beanes and Pease, and great store of ripe Pompions. Also you found Tortoyses ready taken, and by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, rosted and sod so much, as sufficed you all.</p>
   <p n="4">4 Consider also how bountifully God brought vnto you the Fowles of the ayre in great abundance, which did offer themselues to be taken by you, so as if one did but sit on the ground, &amp; make any mournfull noyse, more came to him, then he was able to kill and carrie away, so as one man in one houre, hath taken aboue thirty dozen.</p>
   <p n="5">5 Consider also of the goodnesse of God, in blessing your first labour, in clearing of ground, and setting of Corne, so as by the blessing of God, you had great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, notwithstanding that the Corne was set late.</p>
   <p>Vpon your second Crop, (partly for the vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of some, and partly for the triall of other some, God denied his blessing, so as you receiued not your seede againe, therefore feare of great want came vpon you: Then, euen then when your hearts began to be troubled with feare of want, Almighty God who neuer faileth nor forsaketh them that are his, did send you a comfortable supply vnlooked for.</p>
   <p>While that was spending, your looking for more sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies out of England, and following Tobacco too gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, did cause you to neglect setting of Corne, whereby you were brought into great want. Then the number of people encreasing, and as they encreased, sin and disorder did also encrease, which brought the correcting hand of God vpon you many wayes, so as diuers did perish very miserably: but, consider I pray you, that most of them
<pb facs="4"/> that so dyed, were vngodly, slothfull, and heartlesse men, which sheweth plainely that God hath not reserued these Ilands from the beginning of the world, to bestow them now vpon such, as shall dishonour and prouoke him eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, as many of them did. I cannot but wonder, when I thinke vpon the nastinesse &amp; loathsome lazinesse, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in too many of them died, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> night and day for meat, notwithstanding they had m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nough, if not too much; for, they did nothing night and day but dresse, and eate, and so greedy, as they would not stay till their meate was sod; but more like dogges then Christians did deuoure it blood rawe.</p>
   <p>The first night that I lay in the Iland, which you call <hi>Coopers Iland</hi> (whither the lazie-staruing-crue were sent, and with them, some honest industrious persons, though then much out of heart, and now liuing, and well, thanks be vnto God) when I saw in euery Cabbin, Pots &amp; Kettles full of birds boyling, and some on Spits rosting, and the silly wilde birds comming in so tame into my Cabbin, and goe so familiarly betweene my feet, and round about the Cabbin, and into the fire, with a strange lamentable noyse, as though they did bemoane vs, and bid vs take, kill, roast, and eate them: I was much amazed, and at length said within my selfe, surely the tamenesse of these wilde birds, and their offring of themselues to be taken, is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest token of the goodnesse of God, euen of his loue, his care, his mercy and power working together, to saue this people from staruing.</p>
   <p>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Moore</hi> then Gouernour, fearing that their ouer eating themselues, would be their destruction, did remoue them from thence to <hi>Port Ryoll,</hi> where they found but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or no want: for, birds they had there also, brought to
<pb facs="5"/> them, euery weeke, from the Ilands adioyning, whither some were sent of purpose to bird for them: Also they had fish brought vnto them, a Boates loading at a time, and Palmetoe Berries, which you know are so wholesome and nourishing, as a man may liue well with them, and be in heart, and strength, though he haue nothing else: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all this, they died miserably, some with meat in their mouthes crying for more. This surely was a great iudgement of God vpon those slothfull and greedy belly-Gods, and a manifest signe and token (as I said euen now) that God hath not reserued these Ilands from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world till now, to bestow them vpon such as shall prouoke him euery day, as many of them did. The correcting hand of God, which then lay heauiest vpon the lazie ones, did stretch out it selfe ouer all, euen the most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious, when their Lines, Hooks and Nets were worne out, so as many of them also died.</p>
   <p n="6">6 You that came in the first Ship with M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Moore,</hi> being about 60. persons, haue great cause to praise God for his goodnes in preseruing you; so as you are now all aliue in health and strength, except one that was killed with shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off a great Peece: it is now almost nine yeares since you came hither.</p>
   <p>God make you all thankfull, the worst (by the grace of God) is past; your hope and common talke is, that (by the helpe of God) you shall neuer see the want, that you haue seene. Now that a constant course is held in planting of Corne, you are sure by the blessing of God to haue two Wheat Haruests euery yeare, with lesse labour then they haue one in <hi>England,</hi> because here is neither plowing nor harrowing.</p>
   <p>You haue plenty of good Fish, if you will take paines
<pb facs="5"/> to goe out to Sea for it.</p>
   <p>In stead of the plenty of wilde Hogges, that you found here at your first arriuall, you haue tame Hogges, and also Turkyes and Powltry, so many as you can keepe.</p>
   <p>The Kine in S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Georges</hi> Iland (you see) doe multiply and prosper well, so as in time, by the blessing of God, they will be a great comfort vnto you; so will the Goates also, if care be had of them.</p>
   <p>Potatoes you haue plenty, as good as any bee in the world, Plantynes, Pynes, and other delicate Indian fruits, you are like to haue plenty, if you will haue a care to plant them.</p>
   <p>Also if (according to the Statute made in the first yeare of Captaine <hi>Butler</hi> his gouernment) you make your Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Figge and Pomgranate Trees, you will haue more Figges and Pomgranates then you will be able to spend: what a comfort will it be vnto you, to haue all your Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Figge Trees &amp; Pomgranate Trees? the like (I think) is not to be found in the world.</p>
   <p>Sugar Canes, though they are not like to proue any marchantable commodity, yet they will be a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to you many wayes.</p>
   <p>The Casaua roote is like to prooue a great blessing of God vnto you, because it makes as fine white bread as can be made of Wheat, and (as I am perswaded) wholsome, because the Indians that liue of it, are tall and strong men.</p>
   <p>The bread will keepe as long as Bisket, and therefore good for the Forts.</p>
   <p>If it yeeld a little, and become soft, doe but lay it out in the Sunne, and it will bee as hard, as when it was first baked.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>The planting of Casaua would not be neglected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is a sure foode: your Corne is subiect to blasting, and to the wormes, so is not the Casaua.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>How to make Bread of Casaua rootes.</head>
      <p>FIrst wash, and scrape cleane; or pare away the out-side. Then grate the root vpon a Grater, as you do bread: get Graters made of purpose, with holes somewhat big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then ordinary.</p>
      <p>If you want a Grater, you may make shift with a rough pumish stone, wherof you may finde some vpon the Bayes by the Sea side, or with nayles broad pointed, driuen thick through a bord.</p>
      <p>Presse out the iuice through a Bagge of haire, as you doe Veriuice; then spread the grated roote vpon a cleane cloath in the Sunne to dry.</p>
      <p>That which will not goe through the Siue, beat in a Morter till it be small like meale, and fift it againe.</p>
      <p>Take the sifted roote, and strew it in a cleane dripping panne, and put it into the Ouen, and it will bake in a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an houre.</p>
      <p>The Ouen must not be too hot.</p>
      <p>You must not knead the roote, as you doe Dowe, nor put water to it, but strew it dry, like Saw-dust, almost an inch thicke.</p>
      <p>If you haue no Ouen, you may bake it on a Triuet or three stones, with a little fire, if you make a great fire, it will not bake, but crumble like Saw-dust: remember to turne it three or foure times, vnlesse you bake it in a Ouen, then it needes no turning.</p>
      <p>Your chiefe and Merchantable commodity for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="6"/> is Tobacco: pray to God to blesse you with some other commodity, which may be more to his glory, and comfort of his people then Tobacco is.</p>
      <p>There is great hope of the Silke-worme, Captaine <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> your Gouernour saith, that the Mulberrie Trees grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Summer Ilands, are as good, if not better, then those, that he hath seene, where silke is made.</p>
      <p>The Spiders doe make perfect Silke; therfore I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded there is no doubt to be made of the Silke-worme, faile not therefore to plant Mulberrie Trees neere your houses, that you may haue meat at hand for the Wormes, when they shall be sent you.</p>
      <p>Forget not the goodnes of God, in manifesting the loue and care that he hath of you, by blessing you with a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein diuers Lawes and Statutes fitting your estate, and agreeing with the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> haue been made: wherein also I obserue the good hand of God, in that (notwithstanding your discontentments and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances were many; and that diuers did purpose (as I did gather by their speeches) to stand stifly or rather obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly to haue things caried according to their owne wills, so as I did feare it would prooue, an vnhappy, long, and troublesome Parliament.) It pleased God so to direct Captaine <hi>Butler</hi> your Gouernour in the ordering of it, and also to change the minde of diuers of the Burgesses, as when they were assembled, there was such reasonablenesse and sweet vnity of mindes euen in all, as the Bils did passe, and were graunted on all sides, readily, and cheerefully, which to me seemeth a great worke of wonder, and a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest signe, that God, who is the God of loue and peace, was in the midst of vs, guiding and assisting vs with his holy spirit; his holy and great name be therefore praised.
<pb facs="7"/> I hope that God will giue the like blessing to the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and in his good time establish a good pollitick ciuill estate amongst you.</p>
      <p>Consider well I pray you of the goodnes of the Lord Iesus, in choosing and taking you out of his Vineyard in <hi>England,</hi> and in bringing you into these Ilands, to plant you here, so as now these Ilands also, which formerly haue beene called the Iland of <hi>Deuils,</hi> are become the Vineyard of the Lord Iesus, and you the plants that his right hand hath planted here.</p>
      <p>Consider I pray you of this, and take heede that you bring not forth the sower Grapes of vnthankfulnesse and disobedience, least God doe to his Vineyard here as he did to his Vineyard in <hi>Iudea;</hi> when it did so, hee tooke away the hedges, brake downe the walles, and laide it waste. Isai. 5.56.</p>
      <p>Consider also of the goodnes of God in preseruing all Shippes belonging to these Ilands, so as none haue beene cast away neither going nor comming: true it is that this last yeare 1619. a Ship was cast away, not going nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but riding at anker in the harbour.</p>
      <p>My heart giueth me, that among other sinnes, the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable sinne of Drunkennesse, that aboundeth among you, euery shipping time, did much further the bringing of that iudgement vpon her, to admonish some to bee no longer Bawds to Drunkennesse, by sending ouer so much <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> and also to admonish you to suppresse Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennesse and all other sinnes, as much as you can, which doe abound too much among you, to the great dishonor of Almighty God, and daily prouoking of him to wrath.</p>
      <p>Forget not the iudgement that God hath shewed on Drunkards among you.</p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <p>In <hi>Summerset,</hi> you know how one died suddainly with drinking himselfe dead drunke.</p>
      <p>Also in the Towne at S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Georges,</hi> a man of <hi>Summerset</hi> drunke himselfe dead drunke, and being by a <hi>Coroners In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest</hi> found guilty of his owne death, was by the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Captaine <hi>Butler</hi> your Gouernour, buried in the high way, with a stake driuen through him, by them in whose company hee dranke himselfe dead, each of them hauing a paper on his backe with this superscription, <hi>These are the Companions of him, which killed himselfe with drinking.</hi> Two of the most notorious of them were punished, the one whipped at the whipping Post, the other (because he was a Souldier) did ride the Cannon, shot off full charged, which did shake him terribly.</p>
      <p>Forget not the Boats of <hi>Summerset</hi> that were ouer-tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the keele vpward, and some of the men drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, because they that should guide them, were troubled in their braines with <hi>Aqua-vitae.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let not the hand of God, which lay heauy vpon you in Captaine <hi>Tuckers</hi> time, be forgotten, when the Rats did abound, and goe by Sea, from Iland to Iland, so as no Iland was free, but all were like so many Coney-Warrens: I say they went by Sea, from Iland to Iland, because fishes haue diuers times been taken three leagues off at Sea, with Rats in their mawes, which sheweth plainly, that the Rats did swim, and were snapt vp of the fishes.</p>
      <p>Consider what a plague of God they were vnto you both within dores, and without: within, they deuoured your Corne, and other prouision of foode, and your cloathes and shooes, (as my selfe hath good cause to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member:) without, they deuoured your Corne by scra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it out of the ground: when it was new set, the Grains
<pb facs="8"/> which were thrust in so deepe, as they could not scrape vp, vntill God in mercy hearing our poore prayers, tooke them away, on the sodaine in three or foure dayes, I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the time, because I tooke good notice of it.</p>
      <p>Assoone as the Rats were destroyed, vvilde Cats, that vvere neither seene nor knowne, to be in any such aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, came marching out of the Woods, to your houses, sixe, seauen, or eight in a company: then it vvas in euery bodies mouth that the Cats had destroyed the Rats, and some said, that the coldnesse of the Winter killed them. I remember indeede, that vve had a very colde time a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before they vvere destroyed, vvhich (I am perswaded) God in mercy did send, for the killing of them: therefore giue the glory to God and not to the Cats, nor (as some doe to the Traps, nor to the ruinating of the Ilands vvith fire; and take heede, that your vnthankfulnes bring them not againe, or some other plague as bad.</p>
      <p>Haue God alwayes in minde, and pray for grace to set forth the praise and glory of his holy and great name, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaning of the first Petition of the Lords Prayer.</p>
      <p>Follow not the sway of your owne corrupt lusts: let them not ouer-rule you, but pray to God to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne you by his word, and holy spirit, according to the meaning of the second Petition.</p>
      <p>Make conscience euen of the least sinne, and take heede of following your owne wills in any thing: but pray to God for grace to doe his will in all things, according to the meaning of the third Petition.</p>
      <p>Abhorre idlenesse, and take paines for your liuing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly in the feare of God: be content with your estate, how meane soeuer it bee; trust to Gods fatherly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb facs="8"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> pray to God continually according to the me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ing of the fourth petition, for such things as you stan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>of.</p>
      <p>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esse your sinnes vnto God euery day, and with grieued hearts desire God, according to the meaning of the fift Petition, for Christ his sake, to forgiue them.</p>
      <p>Pray to God euery day for grace to amend your liues, according to the meaning of the sixt petition, especially when you are tempted to doe any euill: pray heartily that God will deliuer you; that is, not then leaue you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nto your selues, with power and minde to do that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto you are tempted: but rather take that power and minde from you, and cause your hearts to faile you, as he did the heart of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> when being tempted by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse to commit adultery, said, <hi>How can I doe this great wickednesse, and so sinne against God.</hi> Gen. 39.9.</p>
      <p>Forget not, but carefully remember the Sabaoth day, to keepe it holy, the doctrine whereof, which (by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, I preached vnto you, I haue for your sakes) writ by way of question and answer, as plainly as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God to enable me, in hope that God will blesse it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, to his glory, and your comfort through Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus: to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghost, be all honour, thanks, praise, and glory, now and for euer.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>The grace of our Lord Iesus Christ be with you all,</hi> Amen.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Yours, as his owne, LEVVES HVGHES.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>