<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Of the foure generall Synodes or Counsels.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106874_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17183</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4056</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106874</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Of the foure generall Synodes or Counsels.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fiftie godlie and learned sermons : diuided into fiue decades, conteyning the chiefe and principall pointes of Christian religion, written in three seuerall tomes or sections, by Henrie Bullinger minister of the churche of Tigure in Swicerlande. Whereunto is adioyned a triple or three-folde table verie fruitefull and necessarie. Translated out of Latine into English by H.I. student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Bullinger, Heinrich</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 489, 491-781, 2, 812-1142, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>❧ <hi>Of the foure generall Synodes</hi> or Counsels.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE THE TIME OF THE APOSTLES, MANY Counselles haue beene celebrated in sundrye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces. Those (Counsels) then were Synodes or as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies of Bishops and holy men, meeting together to consult for keeping the soundnesse of Faith, the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Doctrine, and the discipline and peace of the Churches. Some of which sorte the Epistles of the blessed martyr Cyprian haue made vs acquainted withall.</p>
   <p>The first generall or vniuersall Synode therefore, is reported to haue <note place="margin">The Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel.</note> bene called by that moste holy Emperour Constantine in the Citie of Nice, the yere of our Lorde 324. against Arius and his parteners, which denied the naturall Deitie of our Lorde Iesus Christ. And thither came there out of all nations vnder heauen 218. Bishops, and excellent learned men, who wrote the Creede commonly called the Nicene Creede.</p>
   <p>Hitherto the Creede of the Apostles sufficed, and had bene sufficient to the church of Christe euen in the time of Constantine. For all men cōfesse that all the churches vsed no other Creede than that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles (which we haue made mention of and expounded in the firste De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade,) wherewith they were content throughout the whole world. But for because in the dayes of Constantine the great, that wicked blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Arius sprange vp, corrupting the purenesse of Christian faith, and peruerting the simple trueth of doctrine taught by the Apostles, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the churches were compelled of very necessitie, to set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues againste that deceiuer, and in publishinge a Creede, to shewe forth and declare out of the Canonical Scriptures, the true and auncient confession of faith, condemning those nouelties brought in of Arius. For in the Creedes set forth by the other three general counsels present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly folowing, neither was any thinge chaunged in the doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, neither was there any new thinge added, which the churches of Christe had not before taken and beleeued out of the holy Scripture: but the auncient truth beeing wisely made manifest by cōfessions made of faith, was profitably and godly set against the new corruptions of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques. Yet were the writings of the Prophets &amp; Apostles the Springe, the Guide, the Rule, and Iudge in all these counsels, neither did the fathers suffer any thing to be done there according to their owne minds. And yet I speake not of euery Constitution and Canon, but namely of those auncient Confessions alone, to which we doe attribute so much as
<pb facs="5"/>
is permitted by the Canonicall Scripture, which we confesse to be the onely rule how to iudge, to speake, and doe.</p>
   <p>The seconde generall counsell was helde in the royal citie Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, vnder Gratian the Emperour, in the yeare of our Lorde 384. <note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> There were assembled in that Synode (as witnesseth Prosperus Aquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus) 180. fathers or Bishops, which condemned Macedonius and Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxius denying the holy ghost to be God.</p>
   <p>And about the yeare of our Lorde 434. in the very same yeare that the blessed father Augustine died, when that godly Prince Theodosius <note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sel of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesus.</note> the great was Emperour, there came together at Ephesus the thirde Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node, of 200. Priestes or thereabout against Nestorius, which tare the mysterie of the Incarnation, and taught that there were two sonnes, the one of God, the other of man: whom this Counsell condemned, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Pelagians helpers of this doctrine as cousin to their owne.</p>
   <p>The fourth generall counsell was assembled at Calcedon, in the yere <note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sel of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon.</note> of our Lorde 454. vnder the Emperour Martian, where 630. fathers were gathered together, who accordinge to the Scriptures condemned Eutyches, which confounded the natures in Christ for the vnitie of the person.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Beda de ratione temporum,</hi> and many other writers doe ioyne with these foure vniuersall counsels, two generall Synodes more, the fifte and the sixte, celebrated at Constantinople. For the fifte was gathered together when Iustinian was Emperour, against Theodorus, and all heretiques, about the yere of our Lorde 552. The sixte came together vnder Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine the sonne of Constantius, in the yere of our Lorde 682. And there were assembled 289. Bishops against the Monothelites. But there was nothing determined in these Synodes, but what is to be founde in the foure first counsels, wherefore I haue noted nothing out of them.</p>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>¶ <hi>The Nicene Creede taken out of the</hi> Ecclesiasticall and tripartite historie.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E beleeue in one God the father almightie, maker of all thinges visible and inuisible. And in one Lord Iesus Christe the sonne of God, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten sonne of the father, that is, of the substaunce of the Father, God of God, light of light, very God of very God, begotten not made, beeing of the same Essence and substance with the Father, by whome all things were made, which are in heauen, and whiche are in earth: Who for vs men, and for our saluation came downe, was incarnate and manned (was made man.) Hee</hi>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <hi>suffered and rose againe the third day, he ascended into Heauen, and shall come to iudge the quicke and the dead. And (we beleeue) in the holie Ghoste. As for those that say, it was sometime when he was not, and before he was borne he was not: and whiche say, because he was made of thinges not beeing (of nothing) or of an other substance, that therefore the sonne of God is either created, or turned, or chaunged, them doeth the holie Catholique and Apostolique Church curse or excommunicate.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>
         <hi>The Creede of the counsell held at Constantinople,</hi> taken out of a certeine copie written in Greeke and Latine.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
         <hi>Beleeue in one God, the Father almightie, maker of heauen and earth, and of all things visible and inuisible. And in one Lord Iesus Christe the onelie begotten sonne of God, borne of his father before all worldes, light of light, very God of very God, begotten not made, beeing of the same substance with the father, by whome all things were made. Who for vs men and for our saluation, came downe from Heauen, and was incarnate by the holie Ghoste and the virgine Marie, and was made man. He was also crucified for vs vnder Pontius Pilate. He suffered and was buried: and he roase the third day, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures. And he ascended into heauen, and sitteth on the right hand of God the father: and he shall come againe with glorie to iudge the quick and the dead, whose kingdome shall haue no end. And (I beleeue) in the holie Ghoste the Lord and giuer of life, who proceeding from the father, is to be worshipped and glorified together with the father and the sonne, who spake by the prophets, in one Catholique and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolique church. I confesse one baptisme for the remission of sinnes. I looke for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the dead: and the life of the worlde to come.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>❧ <hi>The confession of faith, made by the</hi> Synode at Ephesus.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N as much as because heere I note all things briefly, I could not in writing place with these that large Synodall Epistle written by S. Cyrill to Nestorius, wherein is conteined the full consent of the generall Counsell held at Ephesus: I haue therefore rather chosen out of the 28. Epistle of the same Cyrill, a short confession sent to the Synode and alowed by the whole Counsell. Before the confession are set these wordes. <hi>Euen as in the beginning wee haue heard out of the diuine Scriptures and the tradition of the holie fathers: so will we briefely speake, not adding any thing at all to the faith set foorth by the holie fathers in Nice. For that doeth suffice as well to all knowledge of godlines, as also to the vtter</hi>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <hi>forsaking of any hereticall ouerthwartnesse.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And a litle after this, the Confession is sette downe in these wordes. <hi>We acknowledge our Lorde Iesus Christe the onely begotten Sonne of GOD, to be perfect God and perfect man of a reasonable soule and bodie, borne of the father accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Godhead before the worldes, and the verie same according to his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie borne in the latter times of the virgine Marie for vs, and for our saluation. For there was made an vniting of the two natures. Wherfore we confesse bothe one Christe, one Sonne, and one Lorde. And according to this vnderstanding of the vnconfounded vnitie, we acknowledge the holie virgine to be the mother of God, because that GOD the word was incarnate and made man, and by the verie conception gathered to him selfe a bodie taken of her. But for the speaches vttered by the Euangelistes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles touching the Lord, we knowe that the Diuines doe by reason of the two natures diuide them, so yet as that they belong to one person, and that they doe referre them, some because they are more agreeable to the diuinitie, to the Godhead of Christe, and other some (because they are) base to his Humanitie.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>To this confession Cyrill addeth these wordes. <hi>When wee had read these holie wordes of youres (euen in the Synode to whiche the confession was sent) and did perceiue that wee our selues were of the same opinion (for there is one Lorde, one faithe, and one baptisme) wee glorified GOD the sauiour of all (men) reioycing together in our selues, for that the Churches bothe oures and youres do beleeue agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the Scriptures of God and tradition of the holie fathers.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>¶ <hi>A Confession of faith made by the Counsell</hi> of Chalcedon, taken out of the booke of <hi>Isidore.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the rehearsall of the Creeds set foorth by the Synodes of Nice and Constantinople, with a fewe wordes put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, streight way the holie Counsell of Chalcedon doeth prescribe (their Confession) in these words.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>We therfore agreeing with the holie fathers doe with one accorde teache to confesse one &amp; the same sonne, our Lord Iesus Christ, and him (to be) perfect GOD in the deitie, and the same also verie man of a reasonable soule and bodie: touching his Godhead (beeing) of one nature with his Father: and the same as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his manhoode of one nature with vs, like to vs in all thinges excepte sinne. Touchinge his Godhead borne of his Father before the worldes: and the same in the latter dayes made man for vs and for our saluation. (Wee teache) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that hee is the one and the same Christe the sonne (our) Lorde the onely begotten sonne in two natures, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ither confounded, nor chaunged, nor diuided, nor separated, and that the difference of the natures is not to be taken awaye because</hi>
         <pb facs="7"/>
         <hi>of the vnitie, but rather, the propertie of bothe (his) natures remaining whole and mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together in one person and one substance, that he is not parted or diuided in two persons, but is one and the same Sonne the only begotten sonne God the worde (Our) Lord Iesus Christe: euen as the prophets from the beginning (haue witnessed) of him, as he himself hath instructed vs, and the confession of the fathers hath taught vs. These thinges therefore being ordered by vs with all care and diligence, the holy and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Synode doth determine that it should not be lawful for any man to professe any other faith, or else to write, to teache, or speake to the contrarie.</hi>
      </p>
      <div type="defense">
         <head>
            <hi>That the Decree of the Synode of Calcedon is not</hi> contrarie to the doctrine of the blessed bishop Cyrill, taken <hi>out of the fifte Booke of the holy Martyr Vigiluis</hi> against Eutyches.</head>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt nowe let vs consider the last article in the decree of the Synode of Calcedon. <hi>We confesse that Christ our Lord the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne is to be vnderstoode to bee one and the selfe same in (his) two natures neither confounded, nor chaunged, nor diuided, nor separated, not making voide the difference of the two natures because of the vnitie, but keeping sound the propertie of both natures comming together into one person and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, not as beeing diuided or separated, but (as beeing) one and the same onely bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne God the word (our) Lord Iesus.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In this article this displeaseth them, because they saide: <hi>The propertie of bothe natures remaining sound,</hi> Or, <hi>The difference of the natures not beeing made void.</hi> And that they may persuade vs y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> those things (which they mislike) are assuredly so, they vsing their accustomed largenesse of wordes, and vaine assertions doe bring in many testimonies out of the articles of Cyrill, wherein he denyeth not the two natures in Christe, but tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that there is but one person. To the intent therefore that we maye not confute them with our disputation alone, let vs set downe also the wordes of Cyrill, that euen as they leane to the testimonie of Cyrill, so by the testimonie of Cyrill they may be ouercome. In the Synodall epistles of Cyrill to Nestorius, thus it is (writtē.) <hi>For we do not affirme</hi> (saith he) <hi>that the diuine nature is turned or chaunged into flesh, nor yet that it is transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into the whole man, which consisteth of bodie and soule, but wee say rather that the reasonable soule hath coupled to it selfe the substance of liuing flesh, that it is vnspeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie and vnconceiuably made man, and is also called the sonne of man, not of bare will alone, nor by the onely taking on of the person, but because the two natures doe after a certeine maner come together in one, so that there is one Christ, and one Sonne of both (the natures) by ioyning them in one, not in making void or taking away the difference of</hi>
            <pb facs="7"/>
            <hi>the natures, but because they, that is, the Godhead and the manhoode, together by that hidden and vnspeakeable knitting to the vnitie, haue made to vs one Lorde, and (one) Christe, and (one) sonne.</hi> What could be spoken more plainely than this? What could be shewed more cleerely out of the Epistles of Cyrill to agree with the determination of the Counsell of Calcedon? For see, neither are wordes to wordes, nor sentence to sentence any thinge contrarie, but euen as they had one meaning of faithe, so vse they in a manner the selfe same wordes.</p>
         <p>The holie Synode said: <hi>The difference of the two natures beeing no where made voide.</hi> Saint Cyrill sayde: <hi>The difference of the natures not beeing made voyde, or taken away by ioyning them together.</hi> The holie Synode said, <hi>Bothe the natures meeting together in one person.</hi> S. Cyrill saith, <hi>Not of a bare will onelie, nor yet by the onlie taking on of a person, but because the two natures after a sorte doe meete together in one.</hi> The holie Synode said, <hi>Not beeing diuided into two persons: but beeing one and the same Christe.</hi> S. Cyrill said, <hi>So that of two, that is to say (of two) natures is one Christ the sonne.</hi> And again, <hi>Because they, that is, the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and the manhood together haue made to vs one Lorde, (one) Christe, and (one) Sonne &amp;c.</hi>
         </p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>
         <hi>The Creede of the first Counsell held at Toledo,</hi> when Honorius and Arcadius were Emperours, taken <note place="margin">About the yeare of our Lord</note>
         <hi>out of the booke of Isidore.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E beleeue in one verie God the father allmightie, and the sonne, and the holie Ghoste, maker of thinges visible and inuisible, by whome all things were made in heauen and in earth. We beleeue that there is one God and one tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the diuine substance. And that the father himself is not the sonne, but that he hath a Sonne, which is not the father. That the sonne is not the father, but that the sonne of God is of the nature of the father. And also that the holie Ghoste is the comforter, which neither is the father him selfe, nor the sonne, but proceeding frō the father and the sonne. The father therefore is vnbegotten, the sonne begotten, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter not begotten but proceeding from the father and the sonne. The Father is hee from whome this voice was hearde out of Heauen, <hi>This is my beloued sonne, in whome I am well pleased, heare him.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="8"/>
The Sonne is he whiche saide, <hi>I went out from the Father, and came from GOD into this worlde.</hi> The comforter is the holie Ghoste of whom the sonne said, <hi>Vnlesse I go away to the father the cōforter shal not come.</hi> We beleeue in this trinitie differing in persons (but) all one in substance not diuided nor differing in strength, power and maiestie, (and) we beleeue that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side this there is no diuine nature, either of Angel, or of spirit, or any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, which may be beleeued to be God.</p>
      <p>We therefore beleeue, that this sonne of God, beeing God begotten of his father all together before all beginning, did sanctifie the wombe of the virgin Marie, and that of her he toke vpon him verie man, begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten without the seede of man, the two natures onlie, that is of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and manhood comming together into one person onelie, that is, our Lord Iesus Christe. Neither (doe we beleeue) that there was in him an imagined or any phantastical bodie, but a sound &amp; verie (bodie) and that he both hungered, and thirsted, and taught, and wept, and suffered all the damages of the bodie. Last of al, that he was crucified of the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and was buried, and rose againe the third day, &amp; afterwarde was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersant with his disciples, and the fortieth day after his resurrection as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into heauen. This sonne of man and also the sonne of God, wee call bothe the sonne of God and the sonne of man.</p>
      <p>We beleeue verilie that there shall be a resurrection of the fleshe of mankinde: and that the soule of man is not of the diuine substance, or of God the father, but is a creature created by the will of God,</p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>
         <hi>The Creede of the fourth Counsell kept at</hi> Toledo, taken out of the booke of Isidore.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S we haue learned of the holie fathers, that the father, and the sonne, and the holie ghost are of one Godhead and substance, (so) is our confession, beleeuing the trinitie in the difference of persons, and openly professing the vnitie in the Godhead, neither confounde we the persons, nor diuide the substance. Wee say that the father is made or begotten of none: we affirme that the sonne is not made, but begotten of the father: and wee professe that the holie ghoste is neither created nor begotten, but proceeding from the father and the sonne. And (we confesse) that the Lord him selfe Iesus Christe the sonne of God, and the maker of all things, begotten of the substance of his father before all the worldes, came downe from his father in the latter times for the redemption of the worlde, who (neuerthelesse) neuer
<pb facs="8"/>
ceassed to be with the father. For hee was incarnate by the holie ghoste and the glorious virgine Marie the holie mother of God, and of her was borne alone the same Lord Iesus Christ, one in the trinitie, beeing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (man) in soule and bodie, taking on man without sinne, beeing still what he was, taking to him what he was not: touching his godhead e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with the father, (and) inferiour to his father touching his manhood, hauing in one person the propertie of two natures. For (there are) in him two natures, God and man. And yet not two sonnes or two Gods, but the same (God and man) one person in bothe natures, who suffered griefe and death for our saluation, not in the power of his godhead, but in the infirmitie of his manhood. He descēded to them belowe to draw out by force the Saintes which were held there. And he rose againe, the power of death beeing ouercome. He was taken vpp into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, from whence he shall come to iudge the quick and the dead. By whose death and bloud we beeing made cleane haue obteyned forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of (our) sinnes, and shalbe raysed vp againe by him in the last day, in the same flesh wherein now we liue, (and) in that manner wherein the same (our) Lord did rise againe, (and) shall receiue of him, some in rewarde of their well-doing life euerlasting, and some for their sinnes the iudgement of euerlasting punishment. This is the faith of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique church, this confession we keepe and holde, which whosoeuer shall keepe stedfastly, he shall haue euerlasting saluation.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>
         <hi>A declaration of the faith or preaching of the</hi> Euangelicall and apostolicall truethe, by the blessed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Irenaeus, taken out of the 2. Chap. of his first booke <hi>Contra Valent.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He churche dispersed through the whole worlde euen to the endes of the earth, hath of the Apostles and their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <note place="margin">About the yeate of our lorde 185.</note> receiued the beliefe which is in one God the father almightie, which made Heauen, and earth, the Sea, and al that in them is. And in one Iesus Christe the Sonne of God (who was) incarnate for our saluation. And in the holie Ghost, who by the prophets preached▪ the mysterie of the dispensatiō &amp; the cōming of the beloued Iesus Christe our Lord with his natiuitie of the virgine, and his passion, and resurrection from the dead, and his ascension in the flesh into the Heauens, and his comming againe out of the heauens in the glorie of the father to restore all thinges, and to raise vppe againe all flesh of mankinde: so that to Christe Iesus our Lorde, bothe God, and
<pb facs="9"/>
sauiour, and king, according to the wil of the inuisible father, euery knee may bow, of thinges in Heauen, and things in earth, and thinges vnder the earth, and that euerie tongue may praise him, and that he may iudge rightlie in all things, and that hee may cast the spirites of naughtinesse, with the angels which transgressed and became rebells, and wicked, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust, mischiefous, and blasphemous men into eternall fire: and that to the iust and holie ones, and such as haue kept his commaundements and remained in the loue of him, partely from the beginning, and partely by repentaunce, he may graunt life, bestowe immortalitie, and giue glorie euerlasting. The Churche, although it be dispearsed throughout the whole worlde, hauing obteined, as I haue saide, this confession and this faith, doeth as it were dwelling together in one house, diligently keepe them, and likewise beleeue them, euen as if it had one soule and the same hart, and doeth preache, teach, and agreeably deliuer these thinges, euen as if it had al one mouth. For in the world y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tongues are vnlike, but the force of teaching is one and the same. Neither doe the Churches whose foundation is laide in Germanie beleeue otherwise, or teache to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie: neither those in Spaine, nor those in France, nor those in the East, nor those in Aegypte, nor those in Libya, nor those whiche are in the worlde (beside,) but euen as the Sunne (which is) the creature of God is one and the selfe-same in all the worlde, so also the preaching of the trueth shineth euery where, and giueth light to all men, whiche are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come to the knowledge of the truth. And neither shal he, which among the chiefe ouerseers of the Church is able to say muche, speake cōtrarie to this. For no man is aboue his maister. Neither shal he which is able to say litle, diminish this doctrine any whit at al. For seeing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> faith is all one and the same, neither doeth he which is able to say much of it, say more than should be said: neither doeth he whiche saith little, make it euer a whit the lesser. Reade further in the fourth chapter of his third booke <hi>Contra Valent.</hi> and you shall perceiue that by the terme of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall tradition, he meaneth the Creede of the Apostles.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>¶ <hi>A rule of faith after Tertullian taken out</hi>
         <note place="margin">About the yeare of our lorde 210.</note> of his Booke <hi>De praescriptionibus haereticorum.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He rule of faith is, that we out of hande professe openly what our beleefe is, which is that in deed, wherby we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that there is one God onlie, &amp; not any other beside the maker of the worlde, whiche by his worde sent out firste of all brought foorth all thinges of nothing. That
<pb facs="9"/>
worde beeing called his Sonne, beeing seene after sundry sortes of the Patriarches, beeing alwayes hearde in the Prophetes, and lastly by the spirit and power of God the father beeing brought into the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, beeing made fleash in her wombe and borne of her, became Iesus Christ, (which) afterwarde preached the new law and the new promise of the kingdome of Heauen, wrought myracles, sate at the right hande of the Father, was nayled to the crosse, roase againe the thirde day, was taken into the heauēs, sitteth at the right hand of the Father, sent the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the holie Ghost to gouerne the beleeuers in his owne steed, shall come with glorie to take the saintes into the ioy of eternall life and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly promises, and to condemne the wicked to euerlasting fier, when both the parties are raysed vp and haue their fleash restored againe.</p>
      <p>This rule, as it shall be prooued, beeing ordeyned by Christ, hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs no doubtes at all, but those which heresies bring in, and which make men become heretiques.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>The Creede of the blessed Athanasius Bishop <hi>of Alexandria, taken out of his bookes.</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bout the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>are of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
      </head>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hosoeuer will be saued: before all things it is necessarie that he holde the Catholique faith.</l>
      <l>Which faith, exeept euery one do kepe holy &amp; vndefiled: without dout he shall perish euerlastingly.</l>
      <l>And the Catholique faith is this: that we worship one God in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and trinitie in vnitie.</l>
      <l>Neither confounding the persons: nor diuiding the substance.</l>
      <l>For there is one person of the Father, another of the Sonne, and another of the holy Ghost.</l>
      <l>But the godhead of the Father, of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghost, is all one: the glory equall, the maiestie coeternall.</l>
      <l>Such as the Father is, such is the Sonne: and such is the holy Ghost.</l>
      <l>The Father vncreate, the Sonne vncreate: and the holy Ghost vncreate.</l>
      <l>The Father incomprehensible, the Sonne incomprehensible: and the holy Ghoste incomprehensible.</l>
      <l>The Father eternall, the Sonne eternall: and the holie Ghost eternall.</l>
      <l>And yet they are not three eternalls: but one eternall.</l>
      <l>As also there be not three incomprehensibles, nor three vncreated: but one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created, and one incomprehensible.</l>
      <l>So likewise, the Father is almightie, the Sonne almightie: and the holie Ghoste al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</l>
      <l>And yet are they not three almighties: but one almightie.</l>
      <l>So the Father is God, the Sonne is God: and the holie Ghost is God.</l>
      <l>And yet they are not three Gods: but one God.</l>
      <l>So likewise the father is Lord, the Sonne Lord: and the holie Ghost Lord.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>
And yet not three Lordes: but one Lord.</l>
      <l>For like as we be cōpelled by the Christian veritie: to acknowledge euerie person by him selfe to be God and Lorde.</l>
      <l>So are we forbidden by the Catholique religion: to say there be three Gods or three Lordes.</l>
      <l>The father is made of none: neither created, nor begotten.</l>
      <l>The sonne is of the father alone: not made, nor created, but begotten.</l>
      <l>The holie Ghost is of the father and of the sonne: neyther made, nor created, nor begotten, but proceeding.</l>
      <l>So there is one father, not three fathers: one sonne, not three sonnes: one holy ghost, not three holy ghostes.</l>
      <l>And in this Trinitie none is afore or after other: none is greater or lesse than other.</l>
      <l>But the whole three persons be coet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rnall together: and coequall.</l>
      <l>So that in all things, as is aforesaid: the vnitie in trinitie, and the trinitie in vnitie is to be worshipped.</l>
      <l>He therefore that will be saued, must thus thinke of the trinitie.</l>
      <l>Furthermore it is necessarie to euerlasting saluation: that he also beleeue rightly in the incarnation of our Lorde Iesus Christ.</l>
      <l>For the right faith is, that we beleeue and confesse: that our Lorde Iesus Christ the sonne of God, is God and man.</l>
      <l>God of the substance of the father, begotten before the worldes: and man of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of his mother borne in the worlde.</l>
      <l>Perfect God and perfect man: of a reasonable soule, and humane flesh subsisting.</l>
      <l>Equall to the father as touching his godhead: and inferior to the father touching his manhood.</l>
      <l>Who although he be God and man: yet he is not two, but one Christ.</l>
      <l>One, not by the conuersion of the godhead into flesh: but by taking of the manhood into God.</l>
      <l>One altogether, not by confusion of substance: but by vnitie of person.</l>
      <l>For as the reasonable soule and flesh is one man: so God and man is one Christ.</l>
      <l>Who suffered for our saluation, descended into hell, rose againe the thirde day from the deade.</l>
      <l>He ascended into heauen, he sitteth on the right hand of the father, God almightie: from whence he shall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</l>
      <l>At whose comming all men shall rise againe with their bodies: and shall giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for their owne woorkes.</l>
      <l>And they that haue done good, shall goe into life euerlasting: and they that haue done euill, into euerlasting fier.</l>
      <l>This is the Catholique faith: which except a man beleeue faithfully, he can not be saued.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="creed">
      <head>
         <hi>The Creede of the blessed Damasus bishop of Rome,</hi> taken out of the seconde Tome of S. Hierome his woorkes.</head>
      <p>
         <pb facs="10"/>
WE beleeue in one God the father almightie, and in one Iesus Christ our Lorde the sonne of God, and in the holy ghost. We worship <note place="margin">About the yeare of our Lorde 336.</note> and confesse God, not three Gods, but the father, the sonne, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost one God: one God, not so as though he were alone, nor as one which is himselfe father to him selfe, and sonne him selfe also: but him to be the father which begot, &amp; (him) to be the sonne which was begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: but the holy ghost to be neither begotten, nor created, nor created, nor made, but proceeding from the father and the sonne, coeternall, coequal, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king together with the father and the sonne: because it is written, <hi>By the worde of the Lorde the heauens were established,</hi> that is, <hi>by the sonne of God, and by the breath of his mouth all the powers thereof.</hi> And in another place: <hi>Sende forth thy breath and they shall be created, and thou shalt renew the face of the earth.</hi> And therfore vnder the name of the father, of the sonne, &amp; of the holy ghost, we confesse one God, which is the name of the power, and not of the propertie. The proper name of the father, is the father: and the proper name of the sonne, is the sonne: and the proper name of the holy ghost, is the holy ghost. In this trinitie of persons, we worship one god (in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,) because that which is of one father, is of one nature with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of one substance, and one power. The father begat the sonne, not by will or necessitie, but by nature.</p>
      <p>The sonne in the last time came downe from the father to saue vs and to fulfill the scriptures, who (neuerthelesse) neuer ceassed to be with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And he was conceiued by the holy ghost, and borne of the virgin, he tooke vpon him flesh, and soule, and sense: that is, he tooke on him very man, neither lost he what he was, but began to be what he was not, so yet that in respect of his owne properties he is perfect God, and in respect of ours, he is verie man. For he which was God is borne man, and he which is borne man, doth woorke myracles as God, and he that woorketh myracles as God, doeth die as a man, and hee that dieth as man, doeth rise againe as God. Who in the same flesh wherein he was borne and suffered, and died and roase againe, did ascende to the father, and sitteth at his right hande, in the glorie which he alwayes had, and yet stil hath. By whose death and bloud we beleeue that we are clensed: and that at the latter day we shall be raised vp againe by him in this flesh wherein we now liue. And we hope that we shall obteine a reward for our good deedes: or else the paine of euerlastinge punishment for our sinnes. Reade this, beleeue this, holde this, submit thy soule to this faith, and thou shalt obteine life and a rewarde at Christ his hande. S. Peter Bishop of Alexandria taught and beleeued the verie same with the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Athanasius and Damasus, as it may be gathered out of the 37. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the 7. booke, and the 14. chapter of the 8. booke of the Tripartite historie.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="decree">
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <head>
         <hi>The Jmperiall decree for the Catholique faith,</hi> taken out of the Tripartite historie, lib. 9. cap. 7.</head>
      <p>THE noble Emperours Gratian, Valentinian, and Theodosius, to the people of the citie of Constantinople. We will all people whom the royall authoritie of our clemencie doth rule, to be of that religion, which the religion brought in by (Peter) him selfe doeth at this time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that S. Peter the Apostle did teach to the Romanes, and which it is euident that byshop Damasus and Peter the byshop of Alexandria a man of Apostolicall holinesse do followe: that is, that according to the discipline of the Apostles and doctrine of the Euangelistes, in the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the maiestie and in the holy Trinitie, we beleeue that there is (but) one godhead of the father, of the sonne, and of the holy ghoste. Those which keepe this lawe, we commaunde to haue the name of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique <note place="margin">Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</note> Christians: But for the other whom we iudge to be madde &amp; out of their wits, (we wil,) that they susteining the infamie of hereticall doctrine, be punished firste by Gods <note place="margin">Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques.</note> vengeaunce, and after that by punishment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the motion of our mindes, which we by the will of God shall thinke best of.</p>
      <closer>
         <dateline>Giuen <date>the thirde of the Calendes of March</date> at Thessalonica,</dateline> Gratian the fifte,Valentinian, andTheo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius Aug. Coss.</closer>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>