<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Summary]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106061_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02897</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106061</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Summary]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An Æthiopian historie written in Greeke by Heliodorus: very vvittie and pleasaunt, Englished by Thomas Vnderdoune. With the argumente of euery booke, sette before the whole vvoorke</title>
                 <author>Heliodorus, of Emesa</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Coldock (Coldoke), Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 149 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the <hi>firste Booke.</hi>
      </label>
In it is declared the takinge of <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Cariclia,</hi> by <hi>Thiamis</hi> Captaine of the Theeues of <hi>Aegipte,</hi> and how they were brought into their Countrie, whiche is called the Pasture, where, in <hi>Thiamis</hi> his house they fell acquainted with <hi>Cnemon</hi> a Grecian, who telleth an excellent tale of his estate. After this is declared the takinge of <hi>Thyamis</hi> by <hi>Mitranes,</hi> and the burninge of the Ilande, and this did <hi>Nausicles</hi> by a greate summe of monye, procure <hi>Mitranes</hi> Captayne of the watches to doo, because <hi>Thermutes</hi> one of <hi>Thiamis</hi> his men, had taken from him a Louer of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Thisbe,</hi> whiche he brought from <hi>Athens.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the Seconde Booke.</label>
In this seconde Booke is contained the councelles of <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Cariclia,</hi> and the iourney of <hi>Cnemon,</hi> and <hi>Thermutes</hi> to seeke <hi>Thiamis.</hi> And howe by composition <hi>Cnemon</hi> came to <hi>Chemmis,</hi> where he mette with <hi>Calasiris</hi> very sorowfull, who telleth him a notable tale of his owne ill happe, and annexeth thereto the beginninge of the story of the whole Booke, howe <hi>Caricles</hi> came by <hi>Cariclia,</hi> and howe <hi>Theagenes</hi> was sente out of <hi>Thessalia,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme the Funerall of <hi>Pirrhus, Achilles</hi> his Sonne.</p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the Thirde Booke.</label>
In the thirde Booke is contained the maner of the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralles, and howe <hi>Theagenes</hi> fell in Loue with <hi>Cariclia,</hi> and shee with him, and the moane that <hi>Caricles</hi> made for her to <hi>Calasiris.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the Fourthe Booke.</label>
In this fourthe Booke, is contayned the victory of <hi>Theagenes</hi> againste <hi>Ormenes,</hi> and how by councell of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasiris</hi> he tooke <hi>Cariclia</hi> away, and what adoo was therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute in <hi>Delphi.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <label>The Contentes of the fifthe Booke.</label>
In this fifthe Booke is conteined the seperation of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agenes</hi> and <hi>Cariclia,</hi> and howe that <hi>Nausicles</hi> the Merchante gotte her of <hi>Mitranes</hi> in steede of <hi>Thysbe,</hi> and after he had brought her to his house, he desired <hi>Calasiris</hi> to tell him the Story of her and <hi>Theagenes,</hi> who prosequuteth it so farre, vntill he commeth to the great Slaughter, wherof mention is made in the firste Booke.</p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the sixte Booke.</label>
The sixte Booke conteineth the Marriage of <hi>Cnemon</hi> to <hi>Nausiclia, Nausicles</hi> Daughter, and the viage of <hi>Calasiris</hi> and <hi>Cariclia</hi> to seeke <hi>Theagenes</hi> at <hi>Bessa:</hi> where they heare of an olde woman, that the Inhabitantes therof had slaine <hi>Mitranes,</hi> and rescued <hi>Thiamis</hi> and <hi>Theagenes,</hi> and were gonne with them to <hi>Memphis,</hi> to helpe <hi>Thiamis</hi> to recouer againe his Priestehoode. The same olde woman that tolde them this tale, was a VVitche, and shewed before them parte of her cunninge by raisinge againe her owne Sonne: and after, in their sighte, receiued suche ende, as all her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life had deserued.</p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the seuenth Booke.</label>
In the seuenthe Booke is sette foorthe the Battaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the twoo Brethren, <hi>Thiamis</hi> and <hi>Petosiris</hi> for the Priesthoode, and howe the ende was made betweene them by theire Father <hi>Calasiris.</hi> At this Battaile <hi>Cariclia</hi> founde her <hi>Theagenes</hi> againe. <hi>Arsace</hi> falleth in loue with <hi>Theage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and is almoste madde for desire towarde him. <hi>Calasiris</hi> dyeth, and his Sonne <hi>Thiamis</hi> succeedeth him. <hi>Achemenes</hi> is Espoused to <hi>Cariclia:</hi> but he is defeated of the Marriage by <hi>Theagenes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the eighte Booke.</label>
This Booke conteineth the warre, and cause thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Hidaspes</hi> Kinge of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> and <hi>Oroondates</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenante of <hi>Aegypte.</hi> Also the complainte that <hi>Achemenes</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
made to <hi>Oroondates</hi> of <hi>Arsace,</hi> with a commendation of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riclia,</hi> and <hi>Theagenes</hi> to him: who sendeth for them <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goas,</hi> one of his Eunuches. But before he came, <hi>Theagenes</hi> was sore tormented because he would not consent to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saces</hi> vnlawful desire. <hi>Cariclia</hi> also because shee was thought to hinder <hi>Arsaces</hi> pourpose, should haue bene priuily poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned by <hi>Cybele, Arsaces</hi> Bawde: but the mischiefe fell vpon her selfe. Mary <hi>Cariclia</hi> was accused therefore, and should haue benne burned, but is woonderfully deliuered by vertue of a Pretious stoane called <hi>Pantarbe.</hi> Then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Bagoas,</hi> and taketh them away: for sorrowe wherof, <hi>Arsace</hi> hangeth her selfe. After this, <hi>Bagoas,</hi> and they fall into the Foreriders of the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Army, and are taken Prisoners, and carried to <hi>Hidaspes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the ninthe Booke.</label>
This Booke conteineth the siege of <hi>Syene,</hi> in which was <hi>Oroondates,</hi> and the drowninge of the Countrye rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it by <hi>Hydaspes,</hi> and the curtesie shewed to them which were in it when the Towne was geuen vp: then the falshed of <hi>Oroondates</hi> by stealinge suddainely away to <hi>Elyphantina.</hi> After this is described the great Battaile betwene <hi>Hydaspes</hi> and <hi>Oroondates,</hi> in whiche, <hi>Oroondates</hi> was ouercomme, and taken prisoner, and yet in the ende pardoned. After this <hi>Hydaspes</hi> viewethe the Prisoners, and disposeth them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly.</p>
   <p>
      <label>The Contentes of the tenth Booke.</label>
This laste Booke declareth howe <hi>Hydaspes</hi> was receiued into his owne Countrie, and the manner of the Sacrifices whiche he did: then the acknowledginge of <hi>Cariclia</hi> to be his Daughter, and the enterteining of the strange Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadours, with certaine Actiue feates of <hi>Theagenes.</hi> After this is <hi>Theagenes</hi> assured to <hi>Cariclia</hi> by <hi>Hydaspes,</hi> and they are made Priestes, he the <hi>Sunnes,</hi> and shee the <hi>Moones,</hi> and doo Sacrifice. Then goe they to <hi>Meroe,</hi> where the secreter thinges apperteininge to the Marriage are finished.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>