<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Note]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1479</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106511_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5758</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106511</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Note]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Thus endeth the prologue of this book named. Cordʿyal. Whiche treteth of the four last and final thinges that ben to come</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caxton, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Westminster</pubPlace>
                    <date>1479</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>156 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="note">
   <p>THis book is thus <abbr>translated</abbr> out of frenshe into our maternal tongue by the noble and vertuouse <abbr>lord</abbr>
      <hi>Anthoine</hi> Erle Ryuiers / <abbr>Lord</abbr> Scales &amp; of the Isle of wight. Defenseur and directeur of the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses apostolique for our holy fader the Pope in this Roya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of Englonde. Vncle &amp; gouernour to my lorde prince of wales. which book was deliuered to me <hi>william Caxton</hi> by my saide noble lorde Ryuiers on the day of purificacion of our <abbr>blissid</abbr> lady / <abbr>fallyng</abbr> the tewsday the secunde day of the moneth of feuerer. In the yeer of our <abbr>lord</abbr>. M. CCCC lxxvijj for to be <abbr>enprinted</abbr> / <abbr>and</abbr> so <abbr>multiplied</abbr> to goo <abbr>abrood</abbr> emonge the peple / that therby more surely myght be remembred the four last thingis vndoubtably <abbr>co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng</abbr>. <abbr>And</abbr> it is to be <abbr>noted</abbr> that sythen the tyme of the grete tribulacion <abbr>and</abbr> aduersite of my saide <abbr>lord</abbr> / he hath been ful vertuously occupied / as in <abbr>goyng</abbr> of pilgre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>magis to <hi>Seint Iames in Galice.</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi> to <hi>Seint Bartylmew.</hi> to <hi>Seint Andrew.</hi> to <hi>Seint Mathew.</hi> in the <hi>Royalme of Naples.</hi> and to <hi>Seint Nicholas de Bar in Puyle.</hi> and other diuerse holy pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. Also hath procured <abbr>and</abbr> goten of our holy fader the Pope a greet and a large Iudulgence and grace vnto the chapel of our lady of the pielle by <hi>seint stephens</hi> at west mestre for the relief &amp; helpe of cristen sowles passed out of this transitorie world. whiche grace is of like vertue to thindulgence of <hi>Scala celi</hi>▪ And not withstonding the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t labours &amp; charges y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he hath had in the seruice of the
<pb facs="76"/>
kyng &amp; of my said lord prince / as wel in wales as in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>londe. which̄ hath be to him no litle thought &amp; besines bothe in spirite and in body / as the fruit throof experimently she<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth. Yet ouer that tenriche his vertuous disposicion / he hath put him in deuoyr at all tymes when̄ he might haue a leyser. whiche was but startemele to translate diuerse boo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes out of frensh̄ into english̄. <abbr>Emong</abbr> other <abbr>passid</abbr> thurgh myn̄ honde the booke of the wise sayinges or dictes of philosophers. &amp; the wise &amp; holsom̄ {pro}uerbis of xpristime of pyse set in metre. Ouer that hath made diuerse balades ayenst the seuen dedely synnes. Furthermore it semeth that he conceiueth wel the mutabilite and the vnstablenes of this present lyf. <abbr>and</abbr> that he desireth with a greet zele <abbr>and</abbr> spirituell loue our goostly helpe and perpetuel salua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion. <abbr>And</abbr> that we shal abhorre <abbr>and</abbr> vtterely forsake thabhominable and dampnable synnes. whiche comunely be vsed now a dayes / as Pride / periurye / terrible <abbr>swering</abbr> thefte / murdre / and many other. Wherfore he took vpon hym the translating of this present werke named <hi>Cordy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ale</hi> / <abbr>trusting</abbr> that bothe the reders <abbr>and</abbr> the herers therof sholde knowe them self herafter the better / <abbr>and</abbr> amende thair <abbr>lyuyng</abbr> or they departe <abbr>and</abbr> lose this tyme of grace to the recouure of their saluacion. Whiche Translating in my Iugement is a noble &amp; a meritorious dede. Wherfor he is worthy to be greetly <abbr>com̄ended</abbr>. <abbr>and</abbr> also singulerly <abbr>remembred</abbr> with our goode prayers. For certaynely as well the reders as the herers well <abbr>conceyuyng</abbr> in their hertes the forsayd foure last thinges may therby greetly be prouoqued and called from sinne to the greet &amp; plentiuouse
<pb facs="77"/>
mercy of our <abbr>blissid</abbr> saue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur / whiche mercy is aboue all his werkis. <abbr>And</abbr> noman beyng contrite <abbr>and</abbr>
      <abbr>confessed</abbr> nedeth to fere thobteyning therof / as in the preface of my saide lordes booke made by hym more playnly it appereth Then̄e in <abbr>obeying</abbr>
      <abbr>and</abbr>
      <abbr>folowyng</abbr> my <abbr>said</abbr> lordes coman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. In whiche I am bounden so to do. for the manifol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de benefetes and large rewardes of hym <abbr>had</abbr>
      <abbr>and</abbr> receyued of me <abbr>vndeseruid</abbr>. I haue put me in deuoyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ccomplisshe his saide desire and comaūdement / whom I beseche almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty god to kepe <abbr>and</abbr> mayntene in his vertuous <abbr>and</abbr> laud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble actes and wakis. And sende hym thaccomplisshement of his noble and ioyous desire and playsirs in this worlde <abbr>And</abbr> after this short daungerous <abbr>and</abbr> transitory lyf euer <abbr>lasting</abbr> permanence in heuen Amen. Whiche werke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent I began̄ the morn̄ after the saide Purificacion of our blissid Lady. Whiche was the the daye of <hi>Seint Blase</hi> Bisshop and Martir. <abbr>And</abbr>
      <abbr>finisshed</abbr> on the euen of than<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nunciacion of our <abbr>said</abbr>
      <abbr>bilissid</abbr> Lady <abbr>fallyng</abbr> on the wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesday the xxiiij daye of <hi>Marche.</hi> In the xix yeer of <hi>Kyng Edwarde</hi> the fourthe.</p>
   <pb facs="77"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>