<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CVRIOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106804_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16053</idno>
           <idno type="STC">289</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106804</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CVRIOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rogue: or The life of Guzman de Alfarache : VVritten in Spanish by Matheo Aleman, seruant to his Catholike Maiestie, and borne in Sevill</title>
                 <author>Alemán, Mateo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 267, 17, 357, 3 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="148"/>
   <pb facs="148"/>
   <head>TO THE CVRIOVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit I was still afraid to expose this my Second Part to the light, after it had beene some yeares finished and perused, (though more had beene too few, for the presuming to publish it) and that it were better for me to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the good opinion gotten by my first, (which with open armes was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally so kindly embraced by all) then to hazard their good wils by this second; I was in doubt with my selfe, whether I were best to put my reputation vpon so ticklish a pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> either because it should not perhaps be so well accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; or that I might chance to fall short of my desire, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the marke whereat I aymed: For commonly where the greatest care is taken, those that are vnfortunate, are wont to faile most. Yet notwithstanding, it being with me, as with that bad seruant, who with blowes and kicks, is awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of his deepe sleepe; being rouzed vp by so violent a stroake; that hapned to my selfe, which is wont to befall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie and slothfull persons; to doe one thing twice ouer. For hauing beene too prodigall in communicating my papers, and the conceptions of my braine, they caught me when I was vpon my wings. So that seeing my selfe (if I may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vse that phrase) robbed, and defrauded, I was enforced to fall a-fresh to my labour, seeking out some new supply of moneys, wherewithall to pay my debts, and to dis-ingage my word, which I had formerly past. So that by this meanes I was driuen to differ, as much as possibly I could, from that which I had written before. Surely it was <hi>Esaus</hi>
      <pb facs="149"/>
owne ouer-sight, some peculiar slip or fault of his, that being tyred out in the chase, and killing of his game, gaue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to <hi>Iacob</hi> to steale away his blessing from him.</p>
   <p>Truly, I must ingeniously acknowledge in this my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor, Concurrent, or Corriuall (who ere he be) his great learning, his nimble wit, his deepe iudgement, his pleasant conceits, and his generall knowledge in all humane and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine letters, and that his discourses throughout, are of that qualitie and condition, that I doe much enuie them, and should be proud that they were mine. But by the way, let him giue me leaue to tell him (which is no more then what others say) that if vpon any other occasion sauing this, hee would haue beene pleased to make vse of these his good parts, so honourable would his paines haue therein appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the grauest person that is, need not to haue beene ashamed to discouer both his name, and his face; but to deale after this manner, was to foyst into <hi>Castile,</hi> the coyne of <hi>Aragon.</hi> But herein, that succeeded vnto him, which vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (we see) befalleth many women, whose parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, considered seuerally by them-selues and apart, are of that rare and singular perfec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n, that desire cannot wish it more, nor the pensill exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e it better. But afterwards, when all these distinct parts shall be conioyned, made one whole peece, and examined together, they fall short in the making vp of a faire and well-fauour'd face. But he proceeded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in discreetly; taking that course, which they vse to doe, who goe (presuming on the actiuenesse of their person) with their Lance in their wrest, masked and disguised, to encounter their aduersarie. But because these are things of aduenture, and depend much vpon fortune, if they hit right, they make them selues knowne, but if they misse, they goe away asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and you shall neuer see the face of them. Well, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath beene done in this kinde, or howsoeuer carryed by him, he hath enforced me to defend my selfe. For that he argueth; That the great paines that he had taken, and so worthy of excuse, in following the tracke of my steps, and the imitation of my workes, grew first from this, that hee esteemed them to be good. I pay him againe in the same
<pb facs="149"/>
money, by following of him. Onely we differ in this; That he hath made a second part out of my first; and I onely imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated his second. And shall doe the like in the third, if being elder hand, he shall vye vpon me. Whereunto if I be put, I shall not refuse to see it. Assuring my selfe, that I shall not be shut out, but haue a place amongst the rest. For the field being so large, through the pleasantnesse of the subiect, whereunto the sharpnesse of the appetite will likewise giue some helpe, more parts will daily come out of this booke, then Conies out of their Berryes, and more glosses made thereupon, then on the faire <hi>Angelica</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Castilejo.</hi> But I aduise in this case, that they would not be too nimble fingerd in taking pen in hand, till they haue wearyed their eyes with perusing, and inlarged their vnderstanding, that it may bee made capable to receiue whatsoeuer shall bee brought vnto it. Nor would I haue them to write, till they be well read, if they will attaine to hit the white, and not shoot beside the butt. For our <hi>Guzman</hi> hauing purposed to play the good Student in the Latine and Greeke tongues, and in the studie of Rhetoricke, and hauing gone forward in his studies with a full purpose to professe Religion; to take him now out of <hi>Alcala,</hi> thus on the sodaine, so quite alienated from his former inclination, and so bad a Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, were <hi>cortar el hilo alatela,</hi> to cut the thread before the web were wouen; contrary to that which is pretended in this Historie of his Life; which was onely to serue as a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinell, to discouer all sorts of Vices, &amp; to draw treacle out of diuers poysons: That is to say; To describe vnto you a man, perfect in his parts and person, punished with troubles, and afflicted with miseries, and falling afterwards into (of all other) the basest roguerie, is put into the Gallies, where his wings were clipt, that he could not get thence in haste. Let vs slip it ouer, That he could not be called a most famous theefe, for the stealing of three cloakes, howbeit two of them were very faire ones, and of much value, but the other a poore one: Let vs likewise omit, That it is improper to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous Histories, to introduce publike and knowne persons, naming them by their proper names: And let vs come to
<pb facs="150"/>
that obligation, which he had to returne to <hi>Genoa</hi> to reuenge the wrong wherewith he threatned his kindred in the last chapter of the first Part: And many other things, which without giuing satisfaction, hee passeth ouer in diuers diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent fashions, altering, &amp; reiterating not only the accident it selfe, but euen the very words vsed therein. So that vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly I am of opinion, that it is a thing of more difficultie, then euery man is aware of, to vndertake the pursuit of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans discourse. For it leadeth its vndertaker along euen from his purposed, and first intended course, to those things, whose chase he cannot choose but follow. Nay should he come to confer mouth to mouth, with the partie him-selfe, it is impossible but he should goe out of the way: For there are many conceits, that are thrust into by-corners, and there hid; wherewith euen its owne proper Author is much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, vpon a sudden and present occasion, with calling them to minde, time hauing worne them almost out; whereby men may fall into mistakes; quoting <hi>K. Don Fernando</hi> of <hi>Zamora,</hi> in stead of the <hi>Infanta Dona Vrraca,</hi> his daughter. This doth not argue want in the vnderstanding, nor is it a defect, that another should iump vpon my conceit, &amp; think my thoughts. But I say it is rashnes in him, that will offer to run with that man, who must needs out-strip him, through the others slownesse of footmanship, or that he runnes not right vpon the marke. If here the phrase be not so signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, the stile not so loftie, the language not so sweet, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs not so pithie, the stories not so pleasant, nor so cleanly carryed as I could wish; My excuse must be; Many ouer-sights cannot be auoyded in the writing but of a little; which will aske a larger time to correct and amend them. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing finished my third Part, and following <hi>Horace</hi> his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell therein, that I may be the better able to offer it to your view (which shall be shortly) I could not excuse this passage, as being very necessarie for those ends which I pretend. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of my good will, which is to serue thee. For the times are not still alike; nor the starres alwayes fauourable; nor <hi>Calliope</hi> continually set vpon the merry pin.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>