<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE, and much Honored Knight, Sir Humphrey May, Chancelor of his High∣nesse Dutchy of Lancaster G. L. wisheth the confluence of all externall prosperity in this life, and the affluence of eternall Felicity in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Langford, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106794_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05052</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15193a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106794</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE, and much Honored Knight, Sir Humphrey May, Chancelor of his High∣nesse Dutchy of Lancaster G. L. wisheth the confluence of all externall prosperity in this life, and the affluence of eternall Felicity in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Langford, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Manassehs miraculous metamorphosis : representing to euery sinne-loaden (if sinne-loathing) soule, 1 A conduit of consolation. 2 A comfort against desperation. 3 A conduct to deuotion. A sermon preached before the thrice-famous Vniuersity of Cambridge, at Great Saint Maries Septemb. 10. Anno Dom. 1620. By George Langford, Master of Arts, preacher of Gods Word, and chaplaine to the right honourable Thomas earle of Exceter</title>
                 <author>Langford, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE, and much Honored Knight, Sir <hi>Humphrey May,</hi> Chancelor of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse Dutchy of <hi>Lancaster G. L.</hi> wisheth the <hi>confluence</hi> of all externall prosperity in this life, and the <hi>affluence</hi> of eternall Felicity in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honorable Sir:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Bookes and Parchments long since fell into the hands of <hi>Carpus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.13.</note> what may I expect in this curious, this censo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, this criticall, this <hi>carping</hi> age, but to be <hi>scoured</hi> &amp; <hi>scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> with the maleuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tongues of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> &amp; his mates? <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Thucidides, lib. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> saith <hi>Thucidides:</hi> Hearing and Reading haue a prerogatiue not to be liable to account; but Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Printing cast themselues vpon the racke of censure. For are there not in the popular sort
<pb facs="3"/>
as many <hi>heads</hi> as <hi>hearts? Quot capita tot sententiae, quot homines tot humores, quot humores tot mores,</hi> saith <hi>Lipsius:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lipsius.</note> The many headed multitude is so diuided into <hi>faction</hi> and <hi>action,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bellua multorum capitum Seneca.</note> that <hi>Diogenes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, with all his Lanterne and candle-light, can scarce finde two in this noone-tide of the Gospel, <hi>quibus vna vox aut votum, of one minde or mould.</hi> There were diuersities of tastes among <hi>Horaces</hi> guests, so that that which one deemed dainty, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnsauory to another. <hi>Dianaes Temple</hi> was burned by <hi>Herostratus</hi> the same night that <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the great was borne; One more namelesse then <hi>Herostratus</hi> said: It was no maruell, for <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> her selfe, protectresse of that sacred Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was then absent as midwife as so great a child-birth:<note place="margin">Cicero de natura Deorum, lib. <hi>2.</hi> Plutarch in Alexandro.</note>
      <hi>Tully</hi> commends this for a witty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; but <hi>Plutarch</hi> condemnes it at a witlesse ieast. The like vnlike censures I looke for of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: for though the reuerend and learned pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence wherein I preached it, was not like <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> army,<note place="margin">Linius.</note>
      <hi>Collunies omnium gentium,</hi> as <hi>Liuy</hi> cals it, a Miscellany of all Nations; yet was it like S. <hi>Peters</hi> Audience, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. consisting of men of many Countries,<note place="margin">For it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge Faire Sunday.</note> and they (it may be) of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Languages: <hi>Cato,</hi> me thought, called on me to plead for peace, <hi>Pompey</hi> for warre; the Souldiour cried, <hi>Arma virum{que} cane;</hi> the Merchant, <hi>Da pacem Domine:</hi> But I followed <hi>Ciceroes</hi> counsell, <hi>Seruiendum tempori,</hi> though <hi>Lentulus</hi> thought it the voice of fawning flatterie. But how? I dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed of <hi>Praier,</hi> which is not onely <hi>Medicina vulnerum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> stiles it, but is farre
<pb facs="3"/>
more soueraigne then the Physitians <hi>Catholicon,</hi> it is a medicine for all maladies. Were my Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Students in the abstruse mysteries of Arts &amp; Sciences? Behold, Prayer is their <hi>Oedipus</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue, to dissolue their doubts. Were they Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants that traded for the Gold of Ophir? behold, Prayer sanctifies their profits; hence <hi>Constantine</hi> writ a Prayer about his coyne. Were they manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Artificers, or such as liued by retaile, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? behold, Prayer is, <hi>clauis diei, &amp;</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">It is not <hi>dura sera,</hi> as <hi>Tibul.</hi> But <hi>firmasera,</hi> as <hi>Ouid:</hi> Yea, <hi>ferrea sera,</hi> as <hi>Plautus.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>sera no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis,</hi> it is the Key to open, and the Locke to shut vp their shops. In a word, were they<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 28.3.</note> blessed in the City, and blessed in the field? behold, Praier is their Embassador to praise their God, and giue him thankes.</p>
   <p>What then I spoke in the eare,<note place="margin">Quia lucem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam tenui huic &amp; per se obscura scriptioni conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liare conatus sum à luce vestrâ: Lipsius, ad Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Consul. &amp; Senat. Reip. Vltraiectinae.</note> I am bold to put vnder the shelter of your Honours protection, presuming to winne some lustre vnto this poore Paper-present, from your iudicious and learned Patronage. Your fidelitie in Court imploiments, your eminency in Natures endowments, haue moued God and the King to promote you, and all men to congratulate the amplification of your Fortunes. In your Honourable seate of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you are like the Philosopher <hi>Zenocrates,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aelian. lib. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
      </note> into whose bosome the sparrow fled from the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of the Hawke: which doth ascertaine me, that <hi>Manasses,</hi> after the Deluge of his teares, shall not be like <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue,<note place="margin">Gen. 8 9. <hi>Aelian.</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> finding no place to rest in, but that with <hi>Noah</hi> you will put forth your hand, and receiue him into the Arke of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting acceptance. Thus with <hi>Sinaetas</hi> in <hi>Aelian</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
I presume to present you with a fist-full of water, distilled from the Limbecke of <hi>Manasses</hi> his sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull soule:<note place="margin">Seneca de Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
      </note> or rather, with <hi>Aeschines</hi> in <hi>Seneca,</hi> seeing I haue no meet present worthy so great a Person, I will gratifie you with my selfe, who will euer pray that your good <hi>name</hi> and <hi>fame</hi> MAY long <hi>flourish</hi> on earth,<note place="margin">Bonum nomen, bonum omen.</note> fenced and defended from the Theonine consumption of Enuy,<note place="margin">Dente Theonino rodere, Horat.</note> till your consummation in glory.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London</hi>
         <date>this present <hi>Iune</hi> 4. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1621.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>At your Honors seruice I rest euer in all duty deuoted,</hi> GEORGE LANGFORD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>