<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the Christian Reader, The spirit of trueth, and of wis∣dome in sobrietie through Christ Iesu.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106388_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16691</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3599</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106388</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the Christian Reader, The spirit of trueth, and of wis∣dome in sobrietie through Christ Iesu.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rasing of the foundations of Brovvnisme : Wherein, against all the writings of the principall masters of that sect, those chiefe conclusions in the next page, are, (amongst sundry other matters, worthie the readers knowledge) purposely handled, and soundely prooued. Also their contrarie arguments and obiections deliberately examined, and clearly refelled by the word of God</title>
                 <author>Bredwell, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Boyle, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 145, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶To the Christian Reader, The spirit of trueth, and of wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in sobrietie through Christ Iesu.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (Beloued) the iudgement and practise of some men of speciall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt in the Church of God, haue to this day held this impression in me, that I esteeme the captaines and antient bearers of this schisme, vnworthie the honour of any set conflict, and publique confutation: yet is it come to passe (by the prouidence of the onely wise God) that I haue bene, parte after parte, and one occasion pulling on another, drawne (as it were) by head and shoulders through the deepe of this businesse. And the labour nowe accomplished, I am so farre from repenting, that I am in good assurance, through the mercie God, of a two-folde benefite to arise thereby: the one is, of stopping that violent streame of seducing, wherein daily such numbers of the yonger and weaker sorte of Christians are caryed out of our assemblies: principally because the zeale of such, being greater then their knowledge, becommeth an apt pray and bootie, for the instruments of deceit to practise vpon. And this agreeth with the exhortation of the Church,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cantic.</hi> 2.15.</note> when she sayeth: <hi>Take vs the foxes, the litle foxes, corrupting the vines, whilest our vines bring foorth the first grape.</hi> the other benefite is, that hereby those impure mouthes shall be dashed, that hertofore in their malitious defence of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, haue made no conscience, to clothe all those, that haue duetifully vrged the proceeding of our church
<pb facs="5"/>
vnto perfection, in one liuerie, with these schismaticall spirites, that so they might purchase vnto them, both from magistrate and common people equall hatred and auoydance. This booke shal by the grace of God, testifie vnto all that make any conscience to discerne truth from lyes, that there is as much difference betwixt those, whō they in their bitternesse, woulde thus match together, as is betweene that childe, that in tender affection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooueth and laboureth the refourming of his mother, whome hee seeth by her vndiscreete behauiour, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a reproche among women: and him that vnder pretence of the hate of her vncomely behauiour, shoulde plucke out her bowels, and forsake her In this my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, I haue cared, as much as I could, to husbande the time vnto the reader, and therfore haue both cut off ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny idle discourses (which the aduersarie woulde haue drawne mee into) and also haue so sounded the matters that I haue delt with, by al the writings, printed or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, that are probably vouched theirs, as that, I hope, the godly spirit shall find me no trifler, but such a serious and sincere disputer as the weight of the cause hath required. I was (I graunt) in comparison of others, as a woman of too weake a constitution to conceiue and bring forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such child: but the Lord hath had his way &amp; purpose herein. And as (I protest before the Lord &amp; his holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) with much feare and trembling, I haue from the beginning applied my selfe vnto this worke: so yet in the doing thereof (through the mercifulnesse of my God) I haue bin assisted with much cōfort, and great assurance, euen in some things, that seemed at the first, so in wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, by Satan, with so many intricate folds &amp; knittings, as could hardly or neuer by me (for I shame not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my weaknesse herein) bee brought to any cleare triall and expedite dissolution.</p>
   <p>Of mine aduersaries I rather knowe the nature then the number. Although (as it hath beene obserued) sundrie among them, from time to time, haue laboured
<pb facs="5"/>
to be leaders, and so vpon the spurre of emulation haue gallopped as hard as they could: yet without all questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is none among them that can iustly take the garland from <hi>Rob. Browne.</hi>
      <note place="margin">That this schisme may worthily take the name of Browne.</note> His writings doe foreiudge the cause agaynst all his competitors. And albeit newe maisters are risen among them, that nowe, in a fresh hote moode, condemne his coldnesse and colourable dealing, and that worthily: yet they must, euen <hi>Barow</hi> and <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> with the rest, acknowledge him the shop of their store, and the steele of their strength: for arguments, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections and shiftes, to colour, and (if it were possible) to vphold their crasie cause withall. Let them not disdaine (therefore) that he should beare the name, as the father of that familie and brood, which, of late yeares in a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell for the Discipline, haue made that rende in the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies of Englande. But some will obiect, that these that I name, agree not among themselues: and therefore cannot be accounted of one familie. I am not ignorant, that they are at oddes betweene themselues, but yet so, as that neither partie will ioyne member-like with our Churches in the woorde and Sacraments. In doctrine I knowe they differ, but diuersitie of practise was cause thereof. <hi>Barow</hi> and <hi>Greenewood</hi> nakedly discouered their profession, and are prisoners. <hi>Browne</hi> cunningly counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiteth conformitie, &amp; dissembleth with his owne soule, for libertie. They fullie beleeuing, the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to be no Church of God, but vtterly to be auoyded in al things, as his writings haue taught them, made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to separate themselues at all poynts, according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. He, though hee haue contriued that cup, whereby he hath thus transformed them, as into beasts, yet himselfe taking better delite in humane shapes, liketh not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with them into their lot. Hence cōmeth that grudge, quarrell and heartburning among them. They expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with him as a coward, and one that shrinketh in the wetting. He againe nippeth them for their egernesse, in running before their olde maister, and thereby obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="6"/>
his light, as though the truth (forsooth) had first bin reuealed by them. It seemeth, they would not heare a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to gaine their libertie. But it is manifest, that he to redeeme trouble, hath learned to apply himselfe to all times, places, and persons. Nowe in this their iarre, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie strange paradoxes and grosse absurdities haue passed betweene them: arguing both sides to haue trusted in their strength, and therefore to haue beene destitute of the spirit of truth to guide their pennes. <hi>Barow</hi> and <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood denie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">As appeareth in a writing that came from Brownes hand of this matter.</note>
      <hi>that our preachers doe preach the woorde, and that they doe, or can beget fayth.</hi> They say, <hi>The wicked haue no woorde of God, no graces of GOD, no spirituall or sanctifyed graces, that they doe no good, that they may not teach, testifie, preach or counsaile anie woorde of GOD, anie religion or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of religion. That they haue no kinde of promise nor bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: and that there is no Communion to bee had with them in spirituall graces. They denie fayth to come necessarily, by the woorde of GOD:</hi> and say, <hi>It may bee begotten without anie promise of the woorde.</hi> Beeing demaunded, <hi>what faith doeth beleeue</hi>: They aunswere: <hi>God, without anie conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his woorde and promise.</hi> Likewise beeing asked, <hi>howe they came by their fayth,</hi> it seemeth they aunswered, <hi>as it pleased God</hi>: namely, <hi>by his spirite:</hi> but not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the outwarde meanes. Some of them graunt, <hi>our preachers beget fayth or beleefe of the woorde, but not the fayth of Christ.</hi> Hee prooueth it not the fayth of Christ, <hi>because it hath not good woorkes:</hi> And that also he prooueth full wisely (forsooth) <hi>because they haue euill woorkes</hi>; Which hee specifieth to be <hi>Idolatrie, Rebellion and Bondage.</hi> They say, <hi>our ministers bring a newe Gospell.</hi> That <hi>the lawe in their mouthes, and the sacrifices or presumptuous ministerie of Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan and Abiram are alike.</hi> And they make no better account of <hi>our Parish meetings, than of the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings at the groaues and hill altars.</hi> O wofull men, and drunken with the wine of their owne headie conceites. Browne againe, for feare all these reproches shoulde
<pb facs="6"/>
light vppon him, because hee commeth into our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, minseth the matter euerie where,<note place="margin">See further pag. 135.</note> with these ill stampt distinctions, <hi>Of the better, and woorser sort of our preachers</hi>: (wherein hee leaues his meaning doubtfull still,) and of <hi>ioyning with vs in the common graces, both worldly and spirituall, but not as in one bodie, and couenant of the Church.</hi> O mocker: Let the Lorde iudge thy hypocrisie, for no man can sounde it. Concerning the disputation of both parties in this matter if I bee asked my iudgement, this must I say: Browne hath sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerthrowne the maine assertions of his young mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, as hee calleth them, in proouing <hi>our preachers to haue a calling, because they bring the woorde: that they preach the woorde, because they beget fayth:</hi> For examples: <hi>in him and themselues they haue done it, ergo, &amp;c.</hi> And that, <hi>The knowledge of reformation and discouerie of Church cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions came first to them by their preaching, ergo, &amp;c.</hi> And as they number vp all the euils they can finde in the doctrine and practise of our preachers, to prooue <hi>they can doe no good, nor beget faith</hi>: hee contrariwise by a full floud of <hi>their true doctrine, and good fruits</hi> (whereof he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a copious catalogue) woorthily quencheth the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious flame of their slaunderous tongues. Also by the <hi>sitting of the Scribes and Pharisees in Moses chaire, and the commaundement of hearing them,</hi> he verie sufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that wicked men may preach Gods worde, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in such office, charge and calling, ought to be heard. The cauils they make against these things, are such, as shew them wilfully to stoppe their eares, least the sounde of truth shoulde smite their hearts. In these pointes I testifie, that <hi>Browne</hi> hath well confuted their furie. But if one for <hi>Barow</hi> and <hi>Greenwood</hi> shoulde say these wordes vnto <hi>Browne, Though they haue well deserued to bee thus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and conuinced for their follie, yet not at your handes</hi>: I knowe not what he might well replie: for I am sure, if they had beene so well aduised, as to haue pressed him through all their controuersie, with his owne bookes &amp;
<pb facs="7"/>
writings, they must needes haue made him as mute as anie fish. And I doubt not, but the Reader shall bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perswaded hereof, before he come at the ende of this booke. For as for <hi>Browne,</hi> the masterworkeman of all their mad building, notwithstanding that in this place, vpon this present occasion, there want not further matter to decipher him: who maketh his religion alwayes propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to his owne humour and necessitie: and so hath euer vsed, to propound his owne last, to make all his disciples shooes by: yet will I referre the reader to the gathering of the proofe of these thinges, out of other places in this booke: &amp; specially (amongst the rest) where I lay open his honest and well meaning subscription. Onely I will produce a testimonie or two of master <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons,</hi> who in his life time was bewitched by <hi>Browne,</hi> to his euident vndoing, partly, by fleeing with him into the lowe Countreys, and partly, by stretching his purse so wide, to the printing of his booke. In a certaine letter he writeth to one of London thus, concerning the diuision that fell among <hi>Browne</hi> and them beyond the seas. <hi>In deede the Lorde hath made a breache amongest vs, for our sinnes haue made vs vnwoorthie to beare his great and woorthie cause. M. B. hath cast vs off, and that with the open manifesting of so many and so notable treacheries, as I abhorre to tell, and if I should declare them, you could not beleeue me. VVhich because this sheete and many moe woulde not suffice to rehearse, I will meddle with no particular thing, to declare it. Onely this I testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vnto you, I am well able to proue, that Caine dealt not so ill with his brother Abel, as he hath dealt with me.</hi> Againe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ende of that letter, hee writeth thus. <hi>Also I would admonish you to take heede howe you aduenture your selfe to be a meane, to spread abroade any of that parties bookes, except it were more tending to the glorie of God then it is. For in the first booke there is manifolde heresie: and the other vpon the</hi> 23. <hi>of Matthewe, is a patterne of all lewde frantike disorder, whose haue eyes to see it. And I do not doubt but that the Lord will yet driue him on to worse and worse, seeing he hath so notably fallen
<pb facs="7"/>
from him. Giue not your selfe ouer to be abused: the Lorde open your eyes, and giue you grace to take profite by my writing, euen as I do giue it with a well meaning minde to doe you good.</hi> Also in his treatise vpon the 122. Psalme, hee imputeth to <hi>Browne, a leaning to Antichristian pride and bitternesse.</hi> Mee thinke these testimonies from such a man as I haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, should set such a brand of shame vpon his forehed, as that euerie man should abhorre the sight of him, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest he continueth so to be like himself. And here perhaps the most of his sect will answere that they doe indeed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge such thinges in him, and therefore doe also worthily shunne him for a slidebacke. O, but why doe they not withall, forsake the whole course, which God hath so cursed? yea, vpon the which, he hath set from the beginning, so leageable a print of horrible successe? not onely in the outward things thereof, which were indeede (of it selfe) too weake an argument, but also in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ruines and downefall of iudgement, to the dayly corrupting of sound doctrine, euen from worse to worse, as I haue shewed. Which beeing a proper and infallible note, that God signeth the wayes of the wicked withall, to be discerned, argueth all outward misprosperings, which accompanie it, to carie likwise the same stampe of Gods displeasure vpon them. O that you would bee wise therfore in time, and learne vnderstanding, ere it be too late. <hi>Salomon</hi> sayth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.11.</note>
      <hi>The mouth of the righteous is a well spring of life: but violence couereth the mouth of the wicked.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14.15.16.</note> And <hi>Peter</hi> sayth, <hi>If any man suffer as a Christian, let him not bee ashamed, but let him glorifie God in this behalfe.</hi> But withall he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs to looke to it, <hi>that none of vs suffer as a murtherer, or as a thiefe, or an euill dooer, or as a busie bodie in other mens mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> If God haue made it a happie condition, to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted for righteousnesse sake, then foloweth it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, to be a cursed, and desperate condition, to suffer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment, losse of goods, or life, for disordered wayes, such as the worde of God cannot warrant. If any thinke that by applying this to the Brownists, I shall begge the
<pb facs="8"/>
question, to him (I hope) shall the reading of this booke, giue proofe ynough, to free me from all suspect of such vniust presumption. The Lord for his great mercy grant, that all of vs in the Church of England, from the highest, vnto the lowest, to whom the hearing of this controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie shal come, may not onely be directed in iudgement, to the attaining of the truth herein, but withall (likewise) deepely pricked at the hearts (as the rather put in minde by the scourge of this schisme) to search out our sinnes, and humbly powre out our soules for them, before the throne of mercie: if so be, the Lord will yet heare vs, for this, and remoue our iniquities from before his presence; and so the plagues which he hath deuised against vs for the same. For our many and strange sinnes, doe procure many and strange iudgements (whereof this is not the least) to breake in amongst vs. Yea the Lord for his great mercy, grant our Magistrates sincere hearts, still to purge the Church of all offences, our ministers skilfull bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to doe the message of God as becommeth them, euerie priuate man, humilitie, to the diligent attendance of the worde: and the whole body of this Church, a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full growth, and going forwarde to the fulnesse of Christ, that so all enemies mouthes may bee stopped, and the mightie name of Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah be magnified ouer all. Amen. Come Lord Iesu: come quickely.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>