<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Dyke, Jeremiah</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106572_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3733</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106572</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Dyke, Jeremiah</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods treasurie displayed: or, the promises, and threatnings of Scripture, &amp;c : Methodically composed, for the helpe of weake memories: and contrived into question, and answere, for the comfort of Sions mourners, and for the awakening of the Laodicean-like secure</title>
                 <author>Bridges, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Clifton, Fulke</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 550, 2 pages, folding table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the perusall of this Treatise thou shalt find that the Author threof hath taken very great paines, and that which is more, great paines to good purpose. Great paines are but a small Commendation where they proue not beneficiall to a common good. There are not wanting in the world that take paines more than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the Composing, and writing of some Bookes, of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch when they haue done, it may bee truely said as of <hi>IEREMIES</hi> Girdle; That they are <hi>Good for nothing.</hi> (Ier. <hi>13 7.</hi>) The curious trifles of many ill imployed wits want happily for no paines, but
<pb facs="9"/> consider whether such persons may not in another sense take vp <hi>SALOMONS</hi> words: (Eccles <hi>2, 11) I looked on all the workes that mine hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to doe; and behold, all was vanity, and there was no profit.</hi> The<note n="a" place="margin">Non cernis quòd propte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea animalium gloriosissima est ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s, non quia laborat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed quia alijs la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orat. Eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am aranca la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borat &amp; fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur, &amp; tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es per panetes extendit tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur as omnem mulieris sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, sed est ignobile ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, quia opus ejus est nulla ènus v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ales <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> libi laborantes &amp; se defatigantes. <hi>Chrysost. ad Pop. Antioch. Hom.</hi> 12.</note> Spider is industrious in her kind, and takes paines in making of her Web, as well as the Bee in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of her Hony, and Combes. And yet who respects the Spiders web, as the Bees worke? The profit that comes of the labour of the Bee, is it that makes her labour to be in more esteeme than the Spiders. Now in this Treatise thou shalt find the Author to haue beene a diligent Industrious Bee, that hath brought a great deale of profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sweet Hony to this his hiue; it being a Treasurie and Collection out of the Word of <hi>GODS</hi> Promises which are
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>sweeter than the Hony, and the hony Combe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thou shalt in this Authors Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry see how much is to be gotten by the diligent and observant reading of the Scriptures. I wish with all mine heart that his Industry may proue exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and that many may hereby be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to the like religious diligence in acquainting themselues with the word. It was good counsell that a godly old man gaue<note n="b" place="margin">In vita <hi>Musculi</hi> apud <hi>Melch. Ad.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 370.</note>
      <hi>MVSCVLVS</hi> when he first began to Preach. That <hi>Si bonus velit fieri Concionator det operam vt sit bonus Biblicus,</hi> That if ever he would proue a good Preacher, hee must take paines to be well acquainted with the Bible. And it were to be wished that all Preachers would follow that counsell. Preaching would proue the more solid, savourie, and successefull. But I will goe further than that old man; and I say, <hi>Si bonus velis fieri Christianus, des operam v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sis bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Biblicus.</hi> If thou wilt proue a
<pb facs="10"/> good Christian, thou must be well skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Holy Bible. How happy were it if the Scriptures were more carefully read then they are! It is said of<note n="c" place="margin">Nunquam <hi>Cyprianus</hi> abs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que <hi>Tertulliani</hi> lectione vnum diem praeterijt &amp; crebro dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re solirus. Da Magistrum <hi>Tertullianum</hi> significans.</note>
      <hi>CY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRIAN,</hi> that he let no day passe without reading <hi>TERTVLLIAN,</hi> &amp; was wont often to say, <hi>Giue me my Master,</hi> meaning <hi>TERTVLLIAN.</hi> Such diligence in reading the Scriptures would do well; Especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they being <hi>GODS</hi> owne Epistle, and letter from Heaven vnto vs that we should know his mind. And if Princes letters are to be read thrice over, then how much more sayes<note n="d" place="margin">De Princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pum Episto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis prouerbio dicitur, ter eas legendas, sed profecto Dei Epistolae, sic enim Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram appellar <hi>Gregorius,</hi> sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ter, imo septuagies sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, seu vt plus dicam, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties legendae sunt, &amp;c. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.</note>
      <hi>LVTHER,</hi> should the Scriptures bee read seaven times thrice; yea, seaventy times <hi>7.</hi> times thrice, yea infinite times over. We are commanded, (Prov. <hi>2, 4.) To seeke for Knowledge as for Silver, and to search for her as for hid treasures.</hi> If it be asked where we must <hi>seeke,</hi> the Prophet tels vs, (Isa. <hi>35, 16.</hi>) Seeke <hi>in the booke of the Lord, and reade.</hi> If it be asked where we must <hi>search,</hi> our Saviour tels vs: (Ioh. <hi>5.34.</hi>)
<pb facs="10"/> Search <hi>the Scriptures.</hi> Those are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Mines where the veines of this silver, and these hid treasures are to be found. And yet to see how silly men are in wearying themselues by digging in those earths which yeeld little precious treasure, and in the meane while neglect searching these golden Mines. It is our shame and sinne that we bestow more time, and paines in reading any Booke more than Gods. What excellent, and worthy monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments did<note n="e" place="margin">Ego odi me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os libros, &amp; saepe opto eos interire, quòd metuo ne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur lecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; abdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant à scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae ipsius lecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one quae sola omnis sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fons est. <hi>Luth. in Genes.</hi> 19.</note>
      <hi>LVTHER</hi> leaue to the world in his Writings, and how well spent is time spent in reading his workes. And yet out of a Zeale to the reading of the Scriptures, hee stickes not to wish that <hi>his owne bookes might perish, because he feared the reading of them would hinder men from reading the Scriptures.</hi> What would he wish now to a number of vain idle, corrupt, and corrupting writings, if he saw how miserably the Scriptures were neglected for the reading of these?</p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>Now for this present Treatise, I conceiue it such a Worke as needs not the Ivie bush of an Epistle commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie:</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <note n="f" place="margin">
            <hi>Plaut.</hi> in Poen.</note>Invadibili merce oportet emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem vltro adducere</l>
      <l>Proba merx facile emptorem rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit, tametsi in abstruso sita est.</l>
   </q>
   <p>I say no more of this Authors paines then <hi>SALOMON</hi> speakes of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman, <hi>Giue</hi> him <hi>of the fruit of</hi> his <hi>hands, and let</hi> his <hi>owne worke praise</hi> him <hi>in the gates.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his worke will doe it, or no, let all preiudice be layd aside, and doe but as <hi>PHILIP</hi> bids <hi>NATHANAEL,</hi> (Ioh. <hi>1, 46.</hi>) Come and see, And thou shalt soone see, that what I say of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, is much short of what it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue. Thus wishing that thy profit in the reading may bee answerable to his paines in the writing of this worke, I leaue thee to the grace of GOD, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine, in CHRIST IESVS,</hi> Ier: Dyke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>