<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO All faithful and obedient Subiects</title>
           <author>W., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106284_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14606</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24916</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106284</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO All faithful and obedient Subiects</title>
                 <author>W., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arraignement and executon [sic] of the late traytors : with a relation of the other traytors, which were executed at Worcester, the 27. of Ianuary last past</title>
                 <author>T. W.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO All faithful and obedient Subiects</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>the horrible and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable Treason of the Traytours lately ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, with many others, some already executed at Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester, and others their confederates, whome God of his mercie at his good pleasure bring to light, and giue the due punishment of their deserts. This treason J say, so horrible and detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the sight both of God and man, for which their bewitched hearts, not hauing that true repentance, that in
<pb facs="3"/>true Christians may be required: I haue set thee downe a briefe discourse touching the Arraignement of these that were here in London and West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, vpon iust condemnation exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon Thursday and Friday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>30.</hi> and <hi>31.</hi> dayes of Ianuarie last past, to the ioy of all true subiectes, that liuing vnder so blessed and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious a King, may reioyce to see the cutting off, of all such accursed tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as entend the death of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, and subuersion of the whole kingdome: and so beseeching God to roote out all such wicked weedes as may bee hurtfull in so good a ground as this our land, which J hope dooth containe a world of louing Subiectes vnto his Maiestie, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
<pb facs="3"/>which do continually pray to God toblesse his Maiesty, with our gracious Queene, Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> and the rest of his royall Progeny, with long life, a blessed peace, and neuer ending hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, &amp; to continue his holy worde and blessed Peace among vs, and to giue vs all grace with one heart, euer to loue &amp; serue him in all true faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse. J end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing friend, T. VV.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>