<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>Lchfield, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106017_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12906</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lchfield, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trimming of Thomas Nashe Gentleman, by the high-tituled patron Don Richardo de Medico campo, barber chirurgion to Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Scarlet, Philip, pseud.?</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Roface gentle Gē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
I am sorry I haue
no better Cates to presēt
you with: but pardon I
pray you, for this which
I haue heere prouided,
was bred in Lent, and Lent (you know) is
said of <hi>leane,</hi> because it macerates &amp; makes
leane the bodye: if therefore this dish bee
leane and nothing answearable to your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation,
let it suffice twas bred in Lent:
neither had it anye time wherein it might
gather anye thinge vnto it selfe to make it
more fat and delightfull. His Epistle I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
any time these three yeares, but this
mine aunswer <hi>sine fuco loquar,</hi> though it be
<pb facs="3"/>
not worthy to bee called the worke of
one well spent houre) I haue wrought
foorth out of the stolne houres of three
weekes: for although occasion hath been
offered euer since the Epistle hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,
to answere it: yet held in suspence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering
the man and matter, whether I
should take it vpon mee or no: at last con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding
him easily answerable, I haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone
it: therefore howsoeuer you see it
crept abroad Gentles, receiue it well in
worth: Your fauours happily might adde
strength vnto it, and stirre vp the faint cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
steps to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore liuely pace: it by hard
hap being denied of the progresse, keeping
at home hath growne somewhat greater.
To tell you what the man is, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of this book, were but triuiall and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous,
only this, you may call it <hi>The trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
of Thomas Nashe,</hi> wherein hee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed.
In trimming of which description,
though I haue founde out and fetcht from
the mint some few new vvordes to coulor
<pb facs="3"/>
him, grant me pardon, I thinke them fitte
for him who is so limmed and coullored
vvith all nevv found villanie: for if they bee
etimoligisde, they no vvhit disagree from
his properties Slender labour hath suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
to vveaue this thinne superficiall vaile
to couer his crimson Epistle, and shaddovv
it foorth vnto the vvorld. For as a garment
of too bright a color is too euil an obiect for
the eyes (as is the Sun) &amp; is nothing gazed
after, no not of those vvho neuer savv it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
yet nevve things are desired, because
tvvould proue pernicious to their eyes, but
once ore-clovvded and couered vvith a
lavvne vesture, through that it shines &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth
a lesse hurting obiect, and dravvs
the peoples sight after it: so his Epistle in it
ovvne colour beeing too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esplendent and
hurtfull to the readers, is laid apart &amp; is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
in request, for that tvvould proue as a
burning glasse vnto their eyes, but vestured
vvith this Caule &amp; rare-vvrought garmēt, it
loseth part of it hurting vigour, &amp; therefore
is cald to be seene againe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Loathed tediousnes I also eschewed as no
lesse hurtfull than too bright an obiect: the
Booke which he dedicateth to me, is so te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,
that had I read it through, it so loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
would haue vvrought more on mee
both vpvvard &amp; downvvard, then 3. drams
of pilles: his Epistle is not behinde hand, to
that I might say as said <hi>Diogenes</hi> to the men
of <hi>Minda,</hi> (vvhose gates vvere greater in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogicall
proportion then their Citie:) O
yee men of <hi>Minda,</hi> looke to your Citie, that
it flyes not out at your gates: So his booke
might well for the largenesse of the Epistle
haue flowne out at it, and surely I thinke
had his book any wings, that is, any queint
deuise flying abroad to please withall, it
would neuer haue staid till this time: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I thinke it prouidently done of him
(though out of doubt the foole had no such
drift) to make the gates so bigge, that when
vve haue passed through the gates, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
all the Cittie to be sutable to the stateli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
of them: but after we are entred, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="4"/>
our selues meerely guld, and that all the
Cittie is not worth the gates, vvee may the
more readily finde the vvay out of the
Cittie againe, the gates beeing so great:
and this remedye I founde once vvhen
I tooke my iourney into his Cittie. But
to returne, If this bee not so vvell set foorth
as you could vvish it vvere, blame mee not:
for as the Moon being naked &amp; bare, is said
once to haue gone to her mother, and asked
of her a coat to cloath her: but she ansvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
there could bee no coate made fit for
her, for her instabilitie, sometime she being
in the ful, and somtime in the vvane: so hee
being a man of so great reuolution, I could
not fit him, for if I had vndertaken to speak
of one of his properties, another came into
my mind, &amp; another follovved that, vvhich
bred confusion, making it too little for him:
therefore vvere it not too little, it might be
tvvold be fit, but hovvsoeuer, pardon (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen)
my boldnes in presenting to your
fauorable viewes this litle &amp; cōfused coate.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all curtesie, <hi>Richard L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>chfield.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>