<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A necessary Aduertisement, by an vnknown freend, giuen to the modest, and godly Readers: who also carefully desire the prosperous State of the Common wealth, of this BRYTISH KINGDOM, and the Politicall SECVRITIE thereof.</title>
           <author>Waldegrave, Ste. Winton, W. Rochester, Thomas Ely, Io. Bourn, John Baker, &amp; Francis E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106676_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20020</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6459</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106676</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A necessary Aduertisement, by an vnknown freend, giuen to the modest, and godly Readers: who also carefully desire the prosperous State of the Common wealth, of this BRYTISH KINGDOM, and the Politicall SECVRITIE thereof.</title>
                 <author>Waldegrave, Ste. Winton, W. Rochester, Thomas Ely, Io. Bourn, John Baker, &amp; Francis E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>General and rare memorials pertayning to the perfect arte of nauigation : annexed to the paradoxal cumpas, in playne: now first published: 24. yeres, after the first inuention thereof</title>
                 <author>Dee, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 80, 6 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A necessary Aduertisement, by an vnknown freend, giuen to the modest, and godly Readers: who also carefully desire the prosperous State of the Common wealth, of this BRYTISH KINGDOM, and the Politicall SECVRITIE thereof.</head>
   <p>LAmentable and irkesome,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> are these our drery dayes:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Veritas (vt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur) Odium pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm id fit, apud Veritatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: ipsi etiam Omnipotenti ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sos Deo.</hi>
      </note> (my welbeloued Cuntri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) Seeing the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of to to many, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come such, as, to be to to curious of other <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Cur quidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> quae es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n oculo fratris tui, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tem, quae es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> in oculo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>o, non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>tis? Math.</hi> 7</note> Mens dooings: As though, they them selues, were superha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly perfect: or dwelt in Security, of not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng at any tyme, hereafter, either surueyed, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled for their own.</p>
   <p>Nay, seeing the subtilty and impudency of <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Legas &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legas librum Quintum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticorum Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotelis.</hi>
      </note> some,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is such, that they can, and dare, cunningly and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, conuey to them selues (or, to whom they list) the Title and Interest of the thanks and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, due to other Men: who are not of so brasen visages, as to practise such ambitious fatches for them selues, or to procure such malitious Disgraces, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But are of that myldenes of Spirite, as, PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIENTLY TO ATTEND THE END, which shall reueale the VERITY: when, iust gwerdon, shall to euery Man be distributed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
   <p>And thirdly, Seeing, some are so doggedly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and vayngloriously doting, that they can not
<pb facs="4"/>
like, consent, or well suffer any od Man, beside them selues: or, otherwise, then by them selues, to receiue due Salary, either of Credit, Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or liberall Consideration: where, their word or working (directly or indirectly) may hinder the same.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, how pitifull is the Case, that <note place="margin">
         <p>As, <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</p>
         <p>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. &amp;c.</p>
      </note> diuers, of sundry states, haue, (of Late,) become so shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les lyers, and to some priuate mens liues, (thereby) so dangerous, That, if Credit had bin giuen to them, (by other, than the light hedded sort) of such Murders and Treasons, as (most diuell like) they haue imagined, and reported to be: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, (wholy, of their own hellish myndes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any spark or drop of Veritie,) haue fathered the same vpon the very Innocent (yea, so much an Innocent, as for any such thought, in his hart, at any tyme, embracing or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ostering): It had bin greatly to haue bin douted that the mighty wrath of God, would not so long haue forborn the iust re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge (of so haynous abhominacions) taking, vpon, aswell such wicked and principall Forgers, as on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fickle fauourers, or careles sufferers of the same, any whit to preuaile.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Seeing the Prince of Darkenes hath sundry such his Factors: And yet, one <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> other kinde, more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and abhominable, than the rehearsed: which are such, as not onely, they them selues, commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelish horrible facts, but also practise other very fraudulent feats: And all, to their priuate Lucre onely: Chiefly ayding and furnishing vp their own shamefull Credit herein, with the <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Cownterfeting
<pb facs="4"/>
of other honest and learned Men their letters: as, written vnto them, in such their vngodly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull affayres:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Coo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> &amp;c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Or, as falsly, reporting their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences had with them, to the behoof (say they) of such, as are become their miserable and Cosened Clients.</p>
   <p>And Sixthly, how, (almost, without remedy,) hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> the most wily Tyrant, and Insatiable Bludsucker, layd the plat, for a wofull Tragedy contriuing: yf, the power and Iustice diuine, did not bridle his maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rage, and Infernall fury? How, hath he (I pray you) insinuated his Credit with some, so far, and so long since: that diuers vntrue and Infamous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, by their Sinister information, haue bin giuen vp to such, as haue gathered Records, of those Mens Acts, who dyed in the Cause of Veritie? And so, the same hurtfull vntruthes, beyng (yet) the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Credited, by reason of the Dignity of the place, wherin they were enstalled, haue seemed, bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to the foresayd Diuelish Cosener, and also, to the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Cosen (yea, and to very many others,) to haue bin a certain kynde of warrant: To the one, without feare, to Counterfet letters, or Discourses, answerable to the foresayd fowle vntruthes, vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly Recorded. And to the other, without suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, lightly to Credit any such matter, reported. And, so, hath the Feend Infernall, most craftily, and vnduly, gotten the honest <note n="*" place="margin">
         <p>A good Name is more to be desired, than great riches. Prouerb. 22.</p>
         <p>A good Name is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e worth then precious oyntment. Eccles. 7.</p>
      </note> Name and Fame, of one extraordinary Studious Ientleman, of this land, within his Clawes: that, diuers his mere Maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and wilfull Enemies, do verily hope, that it is impossible, that this Ientleman, shall, with this
<pb facs="5"/>
English or Brytish State, either (during his life) be counted a good Subiect, or a Commendable, (nay, scarse a Tolerable) <note place="margin">If you will Read his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geticall, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Euclide (Imprinted A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> 1570.) you may the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand this point of this brief Aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Christian: or, any his Acts or Trauailes, all ready past: or, other his intended ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits, of great Importance, shall be, in this Land, acceptable: or, of the people, of this kingdome, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued: as, by the fauour, light, and Ayde of the Blessed Trinitie vndertaken, inuented, Compassed, and atchieued: but, rather, by wicked and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Arte, to be framed: and, by the help of <hi>Sathan,</hi> or <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> to be finished: vnleast, the wise, or the peculiarly chief Authorized, will vse due Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and Charitable Discretion, From henceforth, to repres, abolish, and vtterly extinguish this very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious Report, (for these xx. yeres last past, and somwhat longer,) Spred &amp; Credited, all this Realm ouer:<note place="margin">Oh, A damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sklaunder: vtterly vntrue, in the whole, &amp; in euery worde and part therof: as (before the King of Kings) will appere at the dreadfull day.</note> it is to wete, That the Forsaid Ientleman, is, or was, Not onely, a <seg rend="sup">1.</seg>
      <hi>Coniurer,</hi> or Caller of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels: but, <seg rend="sup">2.</seg>
      <hi>A Great</hi> doer therin: Yea, <hi>The Great Coniurer:</hi> &amp; so, (as some would say,) <seg rend="sup">3.</seg>
      <hi>The Arche Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurer,</hi> of this whole kingdom.</p>
   <p>Before, that the (mentioned) Diuelish Cosening was vsed: this sklanderous vntruthe was recorded, publis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, and Credited: But, by these new deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Cosening forgeries, the same, may (with some) seeme to be vndoutedly confirmed. Oh Lord, with how tickle and strong Snares, and with how wily Laberinthes, hath the most enuious Traytor, to the honor of our God and Christ, bewrapped and Daunted many a thousand of simple &amp; honest Mens fantazies: inducing them, to Credit this Infamous Report? To Credit it, (I say) in respect of the
<pb facs="5"/>
honorable Seat, wherin, it was, (very vnaduisedly) set downe. In dede, euen he: who, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Esaiae.</hi> 14.</note> sayd, <hi>Ascendam in Coelum, &amp; similis ero Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimo:</hi> euen he, hath setled this intolerable sklan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the vertuous, among the glorious Renown of the Righteous: to so great hurt, and dammage of the Ientleman (who, to all other Men, is harmles) as, neuer to him, by any one Mortall Man, the iust Amends, can duly be made. I would to God, this foresaid sklander, and other Disgracing Reports, to to rashly, and euen then <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Esaiae.</hi> 14.</note> recorded, when this Courteous Ientleman was also a prisoner himself: (&amp; bedfellow, with one Maister Barthelet Greene) had bin, in due tyme espyed, and vtterly cancelled, and razed out of all Records, wherin they were vnduly, and vnaduisedly (first) admitted.</p>
   <p>Nerer to pres this Matter in particular, it is nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. But, by this, and such like foule ouersight of Man, &amp; Cruell despite of the hellish Enemy, it is come to pas (among many other great Inconueniences) that, wheras the said Studious Ientleman, hath at God his most mercifull handes, receyued a great Talent of knowledge and Sciences: (after his long, painfull, and Costly Trauails, susteyned for the same:) and both by God, being warned, and, of his owne dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, desirous, not onely to enlarge and multiply the same, but also to communicate to other: He fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himself, (now, at length), partly forced, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to yelde to the wickednes of these tymes, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not possible to sayl against the windes eye): And partly demeth himself (in Gods Iudgement,) excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable, not to bestow any more of his Talent &amp; Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="6"/>
Trauailes, vpon the Ingratefull and Thankles: Nay, vpon the skorners and Disdainers of such his faythfull enterprises: vndertaken chiefly, for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of the wonderfull Veritie Philosophicall: And also, for the State Publik of this BRYTISH MONARCHIE, to become florishing, in HONOR, WEALTH, and STRENGTH: as much, as any thing in him, mought haue bin therto, (by any means,) found seruisable.</p>
   <p>But, who would haue <note place="margin">
         <hi>Solomon in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesias<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>es cap.</hi> 4. So, I turned me, and considered all the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lent wrong, that is done vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er the Sunne: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the teare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of such as were oppressed: and there was No Man to comfort them: Or, that would deliuer &amp; defend them, from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of their Oppressours.</note> thought, that they, who are (in dede) of the honester sort, and more chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: yea, of the wiser, and (by Office) mightier (&amp; some of them, taken for his especial great freends) would, so many yeres, haue bin so <note place="margin">
         <hi>Solomon in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesias<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>es cap.</hi> 4. So, I turned me, and considered all the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lent wrong, that is done vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er the Sunne: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the teare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of such as were oppressed: and there was No Man to comfort them: Or, that would deliuer &amp; defend them, from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of their Oppressours.</note> Careles, or slack, to Ayde, and procure the Innocent, to be <note place="margin">
         <hi>Solomon in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesias<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>es cap.</hi> 4. So, I turned me, and considered all the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lent wrong, that is done vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er the Sunne: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the teare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of such as were oppressed: and there was No Man to comfort them: Or, that would deliuer &amp; defend them, from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of their Oppressours.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, from the greuous, and most Iniurious spoyle of his good Name and Fame: and all the inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, depending theron? Or, who would haue thought, that so great, &amp; so vncharitable Vntruthes, should so vndiscretely haue bin published: by those Men especially, who, otherwise, in woord and life, were very modest, and Circumspect?</p>
   <p>I thought it good, Therfore (my honest freend and Cuntryman) to aduertise thee,<note place="margin">The chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tisement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> of some parte of the Cause, of the strange maner, of this Treatise com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to thy sight, or reading: As, without the Name, of any certain Author therof: And, without the Name, of the zealous Artificer, who first did sollicite, and collect such matter (by <hi>Dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ata,</hi> as it were) from this Ientleman. And Thirdly, without my own Name: into whose hands, the sayd Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, hath deliuered all the matter, that he could get
<pb facs="6"/>
of this Brytish Ientleman: to the Title of this booke, answerable: yea, and other rare Instructions, also.</p>
   <p>For (vndowtedly) this BRYTISH PHILOSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHER, is not <seg rend="sup">1.</seg> only discouraged to labor, or * pen any more Treatises, or bookes, him self, in ARTIFICI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALL METHOD, for his vnkinde, vnthankful, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull, and sklanderous Cuntrymen, to vse (nay abuse:) but, <seg rend="sup">2.</seg> also, is loth (and hath great reason, so to be) to haue his Name, any more, prefixed, or subscribed, to any Treatises, passing from him, either by writing, or by speech.</p>
   <p>And, both these Inconueniences, are purposely committed: to auoyd, or, somwhat to preuent hens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, the farther grief and offence, that might grow to him, and his true freends: to perceiue the former sundry sorts of Caterpillers, and great hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the prosperous Estate, of any Common-Wealth, to knaw vpon the leaf, or flower, of his Commendable Fame: who, would take very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Occasion (by the forefronts of bookes, garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with his BRYTISH NAME,) to fall to a fresh pang of enuious busiosity, impudent arrogancy, and dogged malicious speeches vsing and vttring against the Ientleman: who (vndoutedly) wisheth euill to none. And (perhaps) though it were very good matter, that should, by him, be contriued and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and vnder his Name, be published: yet, they would (in perusing it), either peruert their own Iudgements of it, through their vnquieted, and mere malicious fantazie, wilfully bent against him: or, rather, in dede, through their own great Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, would verify the Prouerb: <hi>Scientia non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet
<pb facs="7"/>
Inimicum, nisi Ignorantem:</hi> as, they did by his <hi>Monas Hieroglyphica:</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1564.</note> dedicated to the late Emperor Maximilian: wherein, the Queene her most Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiesty, can be a sacred witnes (as I haue heard) of the Strange and vndue speeches, deuised of that Hieroglyphicall writing:</p>
   <p>Or, if they liked the matter: then, they would say, that such a Treatise, (vnder his Name, published) is not, or was not, of his owne compiling and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, as Author therof: but that, some other Man, now liuing, or long since dead, was the only and first Author, of such a good Treatise. And, that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r of malicious Iniury, hath bin very notably d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, for these many yeres past, about his Booke Intituled <hi>Propaed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>umata Aphorislica:</hi> and is, yet, searse ceased in all corners (for, it is backbiting worke, and seeketh Corners.) For, some men, (And they such, who ought to haue bin honest and discreet, as they are, or were accounted learned) haue, very enuious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fathered it, vpon the excellent <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rardus Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Rupelmundanus,</hi> (yet liuing at <hi>Duysburgh,</hi>) as, to be the only and true Author of those <hi>Aphorismes.</hi> But, afterward, when that was found a peui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Then, vpon one <hi>Vrso</hi> (who liued many hundred yeres since) was all the Commendation bestowed, for that <hi>Aphoristicall</hi> worke contriuing. And then, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, after that, vpon one <hi>Alkabitius:</hi> And at length, with shame enough (but more will follow) being driuen from these mere enuious, and spitefull false deuises: yet (most obstinately and impudently) they still auouch to diuers Ientlemen, and certaine Noble Men, that some other, or (in effect) any
<pb facs="7"/>
Man els, was the Author therof: rather, than they would honestly acknowlege the Truthe, of only this Ientleman his peculiar Industry, and no small skill, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the contriuing and framing of that <note n="*" place="margin">A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1558. In Iuly. First printed.</note> Booke: containing the chief Crop and Roote, of Ten yeres his first Outlandish &amp; Homish Studies and exercises Philosophicall: as, partly in the preface therof, to the Reader, is specified: but more habundantly and purposely, hath that point bin <note n="*" place="margin">A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1574. In August. At Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack.</note> proued and testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to some, who were (before) fowly infected, with the sklaunderous Opinion, that one <hi>Vrso,</hi> was the Author of it, and not this honest <hi>Brytish Ientleman:</hi> as, at an other tyme, will be made more euident: When, a ful declaration, in more conuenient place, may be made, of the mere malicious, very rash, and Brutish Censure, of a certain Doctor, (yet liuing.) Who, lately, endeuored him self, to perswade some right worshipfull Ientlemen, that it were good, and behoofull for this Common Wealth, If the sayd Philosopher, were <hi>Banished</hi> this land, for euer.
<q>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, said this Doctor (but most vntruly: as is now very euident, to Thousands of Men, of this Kingdom, and other) That, to no Man of this Realm, he did at any tyme, or yet doth, or will, communicate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part, of his learned Talent, by word or writing: But is wholy addicted, to his priuate commodity on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auancing, by his own Studies and practises very secret.</q>
That Doctor, his name, shall not, here, by me, be disclosed: for that, he hath (vpon honest Repentance, for his so iniurious &amp; dammageable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) receiued his <note n="*" place="margin">A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1575. In March. At Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack.</note> Sentence of free forgiuenes: in the presence of worshipfull witnes, yet aliue.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>And when, likewise, the perfect declaration may more aptly be had, of the most Iudas like pranke, of an other Doctor: who (in the tyme of this Brytan Innocent his Captiuity: and somewhat, before the day of his enlarging, by <note n="*" place="margin">
         <floatingText type="letter">
            <body>
               <head>The true Copy of these Letters sent to D. Boner Bishop of London.</head>
               <p>AFter our harty Commendations to your good L. the King and Queenes Maiesties pleasures is, you shall cause Iohn Dee, committed to your L. Custody, to be brought before some Master of the Chauncery: and there bound to be of good abea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and forth comming, when he shall be called for, betwixt this and Christmas next<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to set him at libertie. Wherof we pray you not to faile. And so we bid the same hartily Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Grenewich, <date>the xxix. of August, 1555.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your L. louing frendes.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ste. Winton, Cancell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>W. Rochester. Thomas Ely. Io. Bourn.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Baker. Francis E. Waldegraue.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Engerfeld.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
      </note>letters, sent to his keper, from the Right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Priuy Counsail, to KING PHILIP and QVEENE MARY) did, very ernestly sollicite with the Lord Chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, (with whom he could do very much) And with the Bishop of London, (whom, also, he could half perswade) that it were requisite, and Iustice, that the sayd Brytan Captiue, were not set at liberty at all: but, should be forthwith committed to PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PETVAL PRISON: And that, vpon such respects, as he, most vnchristianlike and maliciously, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised: and very impudently, vpon his Credit with them (such as it was) would haue forced, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile. But, God would not suffer the sayd Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Captiue, his great freendship and humanity, a few yeres before, vsed toward that Doctor (in <hi>Paris</hi>) so, to be requited, with worse, then Ingratitude. Besides, that the sayd Captiue, could neuer (nor yet can) be duly charged, with any word or deed, vttred or done, contrary to the performance of his duty toward his Soueraigne and the higher Powers.</p>
   <p>And though I here omit many other great Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, done vnto him, about the bereauing him, of
<pb facs="8"/>
the true and due Title and Interest, in and to his own works, writings and Inuentions, in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces recorded (And among that sort, omitting that foule Iniury, done to him by one <hi>Ioannes Franciscus Offhuysius,</hi> whose booke <hi>De Diuina Astrorum facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> was of this Brytan Philosopher, his Inuention, chiefly: As, may be made euident, both by the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therin contayned, being compared to his <hi>Propae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deumata Aphoristica</hi>: And also, by the said <hi>Franciscus</hi> his daily familiar <note n="*" place="margin">
         <p>As may sufficiently appeare by these few pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces taken out of some of his letters.</p>
         <floatingText type="letter">
            <body>
               <opener>Doctissimo probae{que} Indolis Dn<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Ioanni Deeo, suo Intimo.</opener>
               <p>OCcupatiuncula me hactenus domidetinuere, &amp;c. Quas de Aeris mutatione, concepisti causas, ne relinquas, ore. &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Ex Diuersorio, raptim: <date>30. Octob. 1553.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Tuus, si su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: I-F van Offhuysen.</signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
         <p>And agayne.</p>
         <floatingText type="letter">
            <body>
               <opener>Suo charissimo Dn<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Ioanni Deeo.</opener>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is proximis diebus, &amp;c. Hypothesibus ad A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologiam confirmandam, quaso, seriò Des (vt caepists) operam. Syderum sedes, spero te vteun{que} cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas à me accepturum, saltem eorum qua per nos ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruata fuere quando{que}, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>Vale. <dateline>
                     <date>6. Nouemb. 1553.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Tuus Offhuysius.</signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
         <p>And agayne.</p>
         <floatingText type="letter">
            <body>
               <p>DOmine, si non queas incommodè carere Epheme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridibus prasentis anni, obsecro, mitte: Et de tuis intelligamus studijs. Ego diligenter planto sydera. Spero, dum tuae creuerint, quas concepisti Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, aliquid boni seminis nos collecturos. Vale f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elix.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tuus Offhuysius.</signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
      </note> Letters solliciting and requesting those &amp; such like <hi>Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses Astrologicall,</hi> at the said Philosopher his hands: he being, moreouer here conuersant with, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon this our Brytan <hi>Mathematicien,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a whole yere.) Yet I must Note vnto you, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen here, that one of those Iniuries, was aboue all the rest, so Notorious: and withall, so notably well <note n="*" place="margin">M. Steuen and M. William Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowgh, two of the chief Mos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couy Pilots (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable M. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor his death) can be sufficient witnesses, also<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> known, to be an Iniury, that the last yere, a certain Mechanicien, (being bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied about matter of Nauigation), calling to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance the same Iniury: being a fowle and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent <note n="*" place="margin">An Iniurious Brag.</note> brag, that an English Mariner, (now, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, 20. yeres sins, had made, to diuers honest men: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>of the new Sea Instrument, newly also, called
<pb facs="9"/>
the <hi>Paradoxall Cumpas</hi>: As, to haue bin of his Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.) was so inflamed with Indignation against this arrogant Mariner, his abhominable Impudency, (so long tyme, by this Ientleman, very patiently suffred,) that he made very earnest request to this Ientleman (the true Inuentor, of this Instrument Paradoxal) that, although, all the Iniuries receiued at their hands, who were deemed learned, he would not very sharply reproue: and, but at leysure: yet, that it should be an Act, mete and needfull for him to do, (being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so behoofull for the Common Wealth) speedily to detect, such shameles Braggers and Crakers: onely sophistically furnished, to outward shew: and that, with other Mens rare Inuentions: but, of them selues, vtterly vnhable to Inuent any worthy Conclusion, to be profitably practised, on Sea or Land.</p>
   <p>Which Mechanicien his ernest request, (by the foresayd Ientleman) being graunted, was the very chief &amp; first occasion, of these Rare Memorials (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>The perfect Arte of Nauigation</hi>) so comming in Record:<note place="margin">The volumes of Rare Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, by what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten first.</note> after a Mechanicall and vulgar Artificer his blunt maner of penning, and collecting the same. Who, about the Entrance into the matter of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation, finding good <note n="*" place="margin">The brief Argument of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ce, or first booke of the Gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>al &amp; Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e Memorials.</note> Opportunity, to speake First of a PETY-NAVY-ROYALL, continually to be mainteyned, for manifold great Commodities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing to this BRYTISH MONARCHIE: (which, no other way, can be brought to pas:) and among them all,<note place="margin">Perpetuall Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litik Securitie, is to be so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ght for: but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>luggi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>chle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie: which is the ouerthrow of many a noble Kingdom.</note> the PERPETVALL POLITIK SECV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITIE and better preseruation of this famous King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, from all Forrein danger, or Homish disorder, to be the chiefest: and most needfull Publik Benefit:
<pb facs="9"/>
(and vndowtedly, likely, to ensue therof:) he was du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully willing, rather to follow some brief discussing of that very waighty matter,<note place="margin">☜</note> (and especially in these dangerous dayes, and Incredible peeuish practises, ful often deuised against the GOOD PEACE, AND PROSPEROVS TRANQVILLITIE of this IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COMPARABLE ILANDISH MONARCHIE:) then, to fall to the foresayd Generall and Rare Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials recording, of THE PERFECT ARTE OF NAVIGATION: which, he, (therupon) set aside, a while. And wherof, now, only the Second Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume entreateth: vnder this proper Title:<note place="margin">The Title and brief Argument of the Second Volume.</note> THE BRYTISH COMPLEMENT, OF THE PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FECT ARTE OF NAVIGATION. For, no vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar doctrine, or practise, is therin conteyned: But rather the GENERALL COMPLEMENT, and (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in particular,) all that, which hitherto, was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: or, which mought be most needfull to so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent an Arte, and (to this kingdome) most bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall of all other Mechanicall exercises:</p>
   <p>And such is the foresayd Brytish Complement, (as I do right well know) that the Contents therof, are aboue the most part of the best learned mens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, (yea, or hope) of being brought to pas: and all that, in rare, general, and excellent Conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gubernautik, chiefly. And so great, is the Volume therof, that, to haue it fairely and distinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly printed, with all the Appertenances, it would be, (in bulk) greater than the English Bible, of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test volume: And yet, the plat of Inuention, Dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, and recording therof, was finished in les, than 4. monthes space: it is to wete, of September, Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="10"/>
Nouember, and December last. Due Laud and Glory, be, therfore, ascribed to the free geuer of all good and perfect Gifts.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The Third Booke, suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</note>The third Booke, I neither will, or may (as yet) say any thing of. The Ientleman his desire was, that it should be vtterly suppressed, or deliuered to Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can his Custody.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The Fourth Volume.</note>But, the fourth Volume, I may Iudge it, to be as an Earthly Paradise: A Booke, of as great godly pleasure, as worldly profit and delight: A Booke, for the BRYTISH HONOR and WEALTH (And that, in diuers maner) such an one, as neuer, King <hi>Ptolomaeus,</hi> or Prince <hi>Abilfada Ismaël,</hi> or any Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphicall or Hydographicall Discouerer did write, or Collect: as I (for my simple Capacity) do verily Iudge of it. The Title wherof, is, OF FAMOVS, and RICH DISCOVERIES: The Discourse ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, not only conteineth the Generall Suruey Hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphicall, of all the whole world, (and chiefly the rare Euidences for all the partes therof, most Septen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trionall) but also, a particular and ample examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of King Solomon his Ophirian three yeres voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: And also, the lawfull and very honorable Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling of our most gratious and Soueraigne Lady, QVEENE ELIZABETH, (and so, this BRYTISH SCEPTRE ROYALL) to very large Forrein Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: such, as in, and by the same, duly recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and vsed, the Course of the Diuine prouidence generall,<note place="margin">☞</note> in this present Age, will bring to light and life, matter of great Importance and Consequency, both to the Glory of God, and the benefit of all Christendom, and Heathenes. The greatnes of this
<pb facs="10"/>
Volume, is not much les, than of the Second. And one way, it far passeth the Second: For, in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Center therof, is more bestowed, and stored vp, than I may, or (in this place) will expres.</p>
   <p>The same Volume, was, chiefly, of the Ientleman his own very speedy collecting: And (by his wil, and order) hath this Inscription, or Dedication, TO THE MOST VVORTHY: And the same Inscription, to be written, or printed in letters of Gold.</p>
   <p>And had not the Incredible, and manifold Iniuries, and vndue Disturbances bin, which haue happened to him (by sundry parcels of tyme) for the space of three Monthes, and more, (in Totall summe), within the tyme of all these Collections, most speedily and Carefully heaping vp togither, since August last: I am rightwell assured, that, neuer, in so small tyme, so much matter, of so great Importance, with such syncere and dutifull zeale to pleasure his Natiue Cuntry: had by any Subiect (BRYTISH or ENGLISH) bin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from him, by Inuention of his own, or by Circumspect Collection, or discrete Application, out of former or present writers, and Authors.</p>
   <p>What is than (I pray you) in all his life tyme, to be thought likely, or possible, and in tymes more commodious, to haue bin Inuented: Or, conuerted to better Method of Knowledge, or vse of practise: or notably reformed, by the said Ientleman? Especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, for the space of these <note n="*" place="margin">In which space of tyme he hath aduisedly spent aboue Thirty Hundred pounds, for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of worthy Knowledges &amp; Sciences: to the Honor of God aduancing, (far and nere,) and the better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habling of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to pleasure his Natiue Cū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Thirty yeres, last past? In which long tyme of his Tyrocinie, he hath, inces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly, to the vttermost of his power, and hability, followed an extraordinary, and most painfull, and very costly Course of Philosophicall Enquiries ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb facs="11"/>
after the best Verities:<note place="margin">The Fruit, and end of Naturall Philosophy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vsed, as Christen men ought to vse it.</note> which, may yeld, (by due Considerations of the Creatures, their vertues and properties) to their Creator and ours, Glory, Praise, &amp; Honor vnspeakable: for his Infinit Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Wisdom and Power: the euident print, &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrable proof, wherof, the same, (our God), hath bestowed most abundantly, in his own handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, of all his Creatures Creating: all the whole, and vniuersall world ouer, dispersed: nay, rather Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the whole Cosmographicall frame,<note place="margin">☞</note> and Orbe: from the Center therof, to the vttermost Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the same: being, to Mortall mans out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eye, vtterly vnsensible.</p>
   <p>It will appeare, hereafter, in due tyme, that, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, furder, and of longer Continuance, hath bin his doings, and very well liked of, Aduertisements and Instructions, in sundry affayres Philosophicall, and Cosmopoliticall, FOR VERITIE, IVSTICE, AND PEACE FVRDERING, than hath, of any Three, of his neerest freends, and most familiarly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted Cuntrymen, bin (as yet) perceiued.</p>
   <p>And this also, I may say of the same Ientleman (without seeming to flatter him, or any whit to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse thee, my honest freend and Cuntryman:) or, he him self, with great Modesty, and no arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, might (to God his high Glory) say: That, yf in the foresaid whole cours of his tyme, he had found a Constant &amp; Assistant CHRISTIAN ALEXAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER: BRYTAN, should not haue bin, now, desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of a CHRISTIAN ARISTOTLE.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Alexander. Aristotle.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>Any farder, is nedeles, to be disclosed of this Ien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman: whose greuous <note n="*" place="margin">The wordes of a sklander<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r, are very wound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and go through vnto the inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most partes of the Body. Prouerb. 18.</note> wounds, (by dedly sklan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb facs="11"/>
vpon diuelish Enuy, only: and the same, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily slasht, and hewed into his Sydes: and nere vnto his Hart) are not, yet, in the perfect and charitable Chirurgiens, curing. The more Lamentable, will the case be found: and the remedy, to late, thought vpon, I am greatly afraid.</p>
   <p>In the mean space (my louing freend, and vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Reader) I am, to aduertise thee, that, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the publishing of the other two great Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes: though, the Inuentions, and Collections be such, as I sayd, and of great Value: both for the HONOR AND WEALTH OF ENGLAND, and no little furderance of the GLORY OF GOD: yet, (by Order, taken by him, who hath the chief Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest therin:) the same, are not to be printed, VNTIL THE PROOF BE PAST, How, this Mechanicien, his zealous, dutyfull, and humble Aduertisement Politicall, (for the Perpetuall Garde, and furder Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, of a PETY-NAVY-ROYALL,<note place="margin">A PETY NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VY ROYALL continually to be mainteyned without the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, Charges, or any vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Burden to the Commons.</note> to be maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, without any Cost or Charge to the Queene her most excellent Maiestie, or any vnpleasant bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the Commons, and faithfull Subiects, of this BRYTISH MONARCHIE) shall be liked of, and accepted: (for the zeale, and matter, I mean, rather, than for any Rhetoricall polishing bestowed on it.) Seeing, the same, conteineth in it, such Fragments of Instructions, receiued from the foresaid Philosopher: being, hitherto (almost) a <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Exceptis, Excipiendis: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t illis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>cissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</hi>
      </note> Freendles freend. Why say I, <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Exceptis, Excipiendis: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t illis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>cissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</hi>
      </note> freendles? Seeing, a Ientleman, of great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in this world, sayd vnto him, in my he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, within these few dayes:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Tu certè Infoelix, at multos inter Amicos.</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
Wherby, it might seme, that he hath many freends. But, for all that, betwene a cold freend, and a faint harted Enemy, is small diuersity. And vndowtedly, a fayned, hollow harted or Hypocriticall freend, is worse, ten tymes, than an open Enemy: And, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede, is not to be counted a freend. And, so, may the outward repugnancy of these two sayings, aptly be reconciled.</p>
   <p>But, proceding in my former purpose, you may vnderstand this, moreouer: that the Second Booke or Volume, (to this Preface apperteyning) will be of more hundred pounds, Charges, to be prepared for the print (in respect of the Tables, and Figures therto requisite): than you would easily beleue. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though there were no warning, of Attendance to be giuen, to vnderstand the issue of liking or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking the foresaid, (zealously collected, and as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly presented) Politicall Aduertisement: yet, this matter of Charges, so far passeth my slender habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and, withall, is so dreadfull to the Printers, for feare of great los therby susteining (So rare, and few mens Studies, are in such matters employed) that, delay, on my part, is rather, that way, Constrained: And,<note place="margin">☞</note> therfore, no Order is to be thought vpon, by me, for the printing therof: <note n="*" place="margin">Till than,</note> TYLL, A COMFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE AND SVFFICIENT OPPORTVNITY OF SVPPLY, DOTH VERY VVELL SERVE THERTO.</p>
   <p>And before, I bid thee Farewell (my Cuntryman) I may yet aduertise thee, of one point more (whither the sayd Second Volume, be euer printed, or no) That, therin, is one parcell conteined: so, contriued
<pb facs="12"/>
and Dedicated vnto the AEternall, Royall, and Heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Honor, and Renowm of our Incomparable Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious QVEENE ELIZABETH: that, all the whole world ouer,<note place="margin">A strange Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument, Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the AE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Renowm of our Queene her most Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiestie.</note> yea, among the Heathen, as well as Christen: what language so euer they speake, that haue to deale with Hydrography, or Dangerous and long voyages by Sea: euen they, will, most thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and for euer, sing and extoll her marueilous Princely Benefit herein: as, to them, chiefly for her Maiesties sake and Merits, imparted: who, hath bin so constantly fauorable, and so gracious a Soueraign Lady, vnto the Inuentor therof, her most faythfull and obedient Subiect. The richest <hi>Pyramis</hi> at <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis,</hi> did neuer so far, and so durably spred the Fame and Commendation of the Builders therof, as these TABLES GVBERNAVTIKE, will win, and procure the large loue, and good liking of our Elizabeth, all the world ouer, and while the world endureth, to florish. The English Title therof, is,<note place="margin">A Treasor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable for the Arte Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tik: and for very many other Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</note> THE BRYTISH QVEENE ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH, HER TABLES GVBERNAVTIK. And the same, is of many Quires of Paper, conteining.</p>
   <p>Now, haue I sufficiently (for this place &amp; tyme) gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto you (my courteous Cuntryman) Aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: which (I trust) you will take in good part &amp; thankfully: yf, in your own Conscience, you plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that all my zealous speech, herein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed, tendeth to the Aduancement of vertue, and to the great Benefit and Commodity Publik. At an other tyme, I hope to haue Comfort, and conuenient Opportunitie, to impart vnto you, other matter: for your exceeding good Contentation, and great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light also.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>And, in the mean space, I trust that this my syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, blunt, and simple Aduise, shall be some Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, that hensforward, this honest Ientleman, shal be fully restored to the Integrity of his duly deserued honest <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Da operam vt Famatua integra sit. Haec enim du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilior quàm Mille The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauri. Vita quam vis bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ad breue exiguuni{que} tē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus durat: Bonum ver) Nomen, ad perpetuitatem stabile est. Iesus Sir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. cap. 41.</hi>
      </note> Name and Fame: And, also receyue great Publik Thanks, Comfort &amp; Ayde of the Whole Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish State. To the Honor, Welfare, and Preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherof (next vnto his duty doing vnto God) he hath directed all the course of his manifold Studies, great Trauailes, and incredible Costes. As, both, by these his <hi>Hexameron Lessons</hi> (First, here, for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the same) spedily Dictated: and also, by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many other his wordes, workes, and writings els: both, in England, and other where, spoken, done, communicated, and published, will, or may abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly be testified. And, so, Fare you well in Christ, my Courteous, and vnpartiall Cuntryman: And, for a Remembrance, at this our most freendly Farewel, take this heauenly Counsail with thee:<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note>
      <hi>Omnia quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun{que} volueritis vt faciant vobis homines, sic &amp; vos fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite illis: haec enim est Lex &amp; Prophetae.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Which kinde of skantlin, and Measure diuine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before hand, and in due tyme, layd vnto all our thoughts, wordes and dedes, may be as a good and familiar Angell vnto vs: to help vs to shonne, and flie from all sklandrous speeches vsing: all mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, or seditious Libels skattring: and all other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust, &amp; vncharitable dealings: yea, and from consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or suffring of the same, where we can, or ought, to redres the Cause.</p>
   <p>And, Then, the Glory, and Peace of God, will flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish in this BRYTAN MONARCHIE. Ouer which,
<pb facs="13"/>
(so reformed) that our most Gracious and Soueraign QVEENE ELIZABETH, may, very many yeres, most prosperously and Triumphantly Raigne, it is (vndowtedly) our bounden duty, feruently and full oft, by Prayer, to request at his hands, who is the King of Kings, Almighty. To whose Protection, &amp; furderance also, most hartily, and dutifully, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende the very waighty Case, of this Common Wealth: not vtterly vnduly, or, (yet) out of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son (I hope) in this first booke ensuing, somewhat Considered of: as, in a <note n="*" place="margin">The first Book here following, is but (as it were) a Preface: To the Second, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it the Art, to this kingdome most beneficiall, if it might be duely vsed.</note> Preface, very nedefull, to the BRYTISH COMPLEMENT, OF THE PERFECT ARTE OF NAVIGATION. And herewith, (once more), I say, <hi>Adieu</hi>: and well motest thou Fare, my Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Brother, and syncerely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Cuntryman.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Anno, Stellae (Coelo Demissae, recta{que} Reuersae) Quinto: Iulij verò, Die.</hi> 4. <hi>ET Anno Mundi.</hi> 5540.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>