<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND Mighty Prince, IAMES, King of Great-Britaine, France, and Ire∣land, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107111_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16939</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3832</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107111</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND Mighty Prince, IAMES, King of Great-Britaine, France, and Ire∣land, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catalogue and succession of the kings, princes, dukes, marquesses, earles, and viscounts of this realme of England, since the Norman Conquest, to this present yeare, 1619 : Together, vvith their armes, vviues, and children: the times of their deaths and burials, with many their memorable actions. Collected by Raphe Brooke Esquire, Yorke Herauld: discouering, and reforming many errors committed, by men of other profession, and lately published in print; to the great wronging of the nobility, and preiudice of his Maiesties officers of armes, who are onely appointed and sworne to deale faithfully in these causes</title>
                 <author>Brooke, Ralph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 7, 3, 9-20, 2, 21-52, 4, 53-276, 4 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND Mighty Prince, IAMES, King of <hi>Great-Britaine, France, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Gracious Soueraigne:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I thinke not the meane fruite of my Studies worthy so great a Patron as your selfe, and therefore dedicate the same onely to those Honourable Lords your Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners for the Office of Earle Marshall of <hi>England,</hi> vnto whose Censure and Office, all matters of Honour and Armes belongeth, and are committed: (yet after fiftie yeeres labour and experience, Now treating of Nobility, Honour, and Armes, which are deriued from the fountaine of Royall authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Kings and Princes, and being heereunto partly led by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of my Office of Herauld, wherein I haue serued your MAIESTY and the late Queene ELIZABETH of famous memory, these for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeeres) I held it my bounden dutie, thus much at least (by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Praeface) to intimate vnto your HIGHNESSE, that heere I disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and reforme many things heeretofore grossely mistaken, and abused by ignorant persons; who venturing beyond their owne element and skill to write of this subiect, haue shewed themselues more bold and busie, then skilfull in Herauldry, and haue thereby so troubled the cleare fountain of Honorable Titles and Descents, flowing from your MAIESTY and former Princes, that true Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is greatly blemished and obscured thereby. For the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and preuention of these and the like abuses hereafter, I most humbly pray a reformation, and that vpstarts and Mountebankes
<pb facs="4"/>within this our profession, may be prohibited to make their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and credite, vpon the discredite and impouerishing of your MAIESTIES poore seruants the Officers of Armes, who labor dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and spend both their bodies and substance, faithfully to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue and keepe in Register, the Descents and Achiuements of the Nobilitie and Gentrie of this Kingdome, with their Noble and worthie Actes, Marriages, Issues, and Armes, which is no easie thing now to do. And much more harder it will be heereafter, if these busie bodies (catching by chance the imperfect Notes of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds deceased) shall be suffered to publish in print their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, as true and infallible verities, whereby in time to come, it will be hard to distinguish light from darknesse, and truth from falshood, vnlesse your Princely care and feeling heereof, may bee signified vnto the Lords Commissioners to redresse the same.</p>
   <p>So most humbly praying your MAIESTIES pardon, I beseech the King of Kings, long to continue and prosper your happy Reigne ouer vs.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble deuoted Subiect and Seruant, RAPHE BROOKE, Yorke Herauld.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>