<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian reader, Iohn Olde wysheth grace / mercye and peace / from God the father and from his sonne Iesu Christ our Lorde &amp; onely sauiour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107068_Bo1_5_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68942</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2854.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107068</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian reader, Iohn Olde wysheth grace / mercye and peace / from God the father and from his sonne Iesu Christ our Lorde &amp; onely sauiour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seconde tome or volume of the paraphrase of Erasmus vpon the newe testament : conteynyng the Epistles of S. Paul, and other the Apostles. Wherunto is added a paraphrase vpon the Reuelacion of S. Iohn</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, xliiii, xliiii, xliii-lxiiii, xxi, 6, xv, x, x, xi, 1, xxxi, xxxi-xxxiii, xxvii, 3, liiii, 2, xl leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="151"/>
   <pb facs="152"/>
   <pb facs="152"/>
   <head>To the Christian reader, Iohn Olde wysheth grace / mercye and peace / from God the father and from his sonne Iesu Christ our Lorde &amp; onely sauiour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche (moost gentle reader) as euery pryest vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> a certayne degree in scholes is bounden by the kynges Maiesties most gracious iniunctiōs to haue prouided by a daye lymited for his owne study and erudicion y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> whole Paraphrase of D. Erasmus vpon the newe testamente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oth in Latine and Englishe: And where I heard neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles in the begynnyng of this last somer by the Pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tout▪ my very hertie good frend Edwarde Whitchurche, that the Paraphrases vpon seuen of Paules Epistles, that is to saye, to the Ephesians, Philippians, both thepistles to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Thessaloniās, both to Timothee, and thepistle to Philemon were neither translated ready to the Prynte, ne ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> appoynted certaynly to be translated of any man, so as thafore mencioned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction should be lyke in this case to be frustrate of his due execucion, the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt priestes iniunction breakers (as they are in other thynges ynowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besydes that) and the symple vulgare people hungryng and thirstynge after ryghteousnes, by wantyng of these Paraphrases, vnfedde: and not onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedde for lacke of suche liuely playne exposicions of the scriptures, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphrases in most thynges are, but also by reason of the continuaunce of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed vanities (yea rather blasphemies) in the churche, they are broughte throughe the Popishe persuasions of the couetous gredye missal sacryficers, into daylye encreace of errour and ignoraunce more and more. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe it myght be iustely answered vnto me, that it is not the onelye lacke of the translated Paraphrases, wherby the commune people communely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynue still in ignoraunce, but muche rather the lacke aswell of good wyll as habilitie in the priestes and curates, that reade the good Homylies al ready set forth, and the scriptures with cuttyng, hackynge, hummyng, cheopping and mynceyng after such sort, as y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> people are in most Parishes not only broughte into a great tedious wearynes bicause of the vnsauery &amp; imperfite readynge pronoūceing &amp; pointing of those good thinges, but also into a certayne cōtēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous lothsomnes &amp; hatred therof, seing their curates beare so lytell good wyl &amp; so vnto warde to the furtheraūce of gods worde &amp; glory, to their parishene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s erudicion, &amp; so diligent to cōtinue &amp; aduaunce their popyshe pryuate masses &amp; other straunge tounged seruice to passe awaye the tyme &amp; to kepe both thēsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues &amp; the people blynde styll: yet myne vnfeyned hope &amp; trust is, that lyke as y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> almyghtie euerlyuing God the father of our lorde Iesu Christe (&amp; by Christe of al perfite christians) hath of his owne vnspeakeable mercye to this mooste Emperiall Realmewarde, geuen so gracious, so godly, so vertuous, so learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toward and so faythful a Christen Kyng, and most worthy supreme head euē our most soueraine lord king Edward y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> .vi. to rule gouerne, nourishe &amp; defend it: who by thaduise, ministery and trauaile of his victorious &amp; most noble vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle the Lorde Protectours grace, &amp; other of his moste honourable Counsayll,
<pb facs="153"/>
seketh the kyngdome of heauen and the righteousnes therof, aswell in free set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forth of the most holy sacred scriptures by iniunccions and visitoures, as in diligent placeing and sendyng abroade of moste excellently learned readers and preachers to instructe his subiectes in the true knowledge of them selues and of God, and in theyr bounden dueties to theyr superiors, and also in christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an charitie to their neighbours: so he will also of his moste haboundaunte ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of mercye and inscrutable power contynue (wyth daylye encreace) suche forewarde hertynes and hertye forewardenes of earnest godly procedynges in the Kynges moste Roial Maiestie, by the aduise, ministerie, and trauayle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayed, as (the ignoraunt ministers being charitably amoued from their ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall cures hauyng competent in other trades of lyfe to rest vpon, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable necessarie prouision for the honest mayntenaunce of learnyng &amp; good ministers beyng had) that father of mercies and Lorde of glorye, whose waies are vnsearcheable and iudgementes incomprehensyble, by whose wisedome all thynges are swetely disposed and ordred, wyll (in case we be seruent in hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e prayer and not slacke in rendryng thankes vnto him for his excedynge mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde benefites) sende conuenient, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>llyng and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stye forewarde workemen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this his most copious great haruest of Englande, aswel to the extirpacion, banyshement, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yng out of popyshe faythe, false religion, cankred opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, heathnyshe rites, idoiatrous worshyppynges, supersticious deuoucions, disguysed myssall sacrificeinges, aduouterous conuersacion, and other grosse vile iniquities arysyng and growing (to the contempt and dishonour of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng God) as braunches out of the roote of the Romyshe Antichristian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as also to the plantyng, settyng forth, and glorifyeng of the moste vndefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led lawe of the Lorde that conuerteth soules from naughtynes to godlynes: to the syncere teaching of the most sacred religion of Christ, and the true wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp of God: to the reformacion of maners and also to the expressyng of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauiour in outwarde conuersacion both in the ministre and parishene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, to walke in loue as Christ hathe loued vs, in Christen almose dedes, in scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fastyng, in ghospellike prayer, in rendryng thankes, in lifting vp pure han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, in pacience, long suffryng, perfite charitie, temperaunce, sobrietie, chastitie, brotherly compassion and true obedience towardes the Kynges maiestie and all other set in autoritie vnder hym: and in other offices, workes, dedes and vertues, that God requireth and commaundeth by his actes, proclamacions, and decrees most earnestlye and straightely mentioned in his mooste holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite boke the Byble, so as God (I doubt not) shall vouchesafe long to preserue vnto thys Realme y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> most vnspeakable worthy Iewel y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> kynges hyghnes: and defendyng it frō the daungerous plagues &amp; curses due vnto the wicked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of vnbelefe, shall vouchesafe also to powre vpon it the mercies &amp; blessyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in most pleyntuous habundaunce that he hath promised by the same boke to the beleuing chyldren of obedience. Vpon these respectes, hope &amp; consideraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and seing thaforenamed seuen Epistles (whiche in dede are as necessarye &amp; requisite pieces of scripture to the furtheraunce of Christes religion, &amp; christen maners as y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> rest of the newe testamēt is) to be left vntrāslated: I toke in hāde to trāslate thē at such seldome leasures as I possiblie could frō mine other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane trauailes incidēt to my drudging vocaciō spare, &amp; now at last haue fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed thē: not doubting, albeit I cōfesse my self (euē frō y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> botome of mine he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t) as vnmete for this kinde of office as a cartes of husbādry to be a caruer at a noble mans table, yet y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> this my rude trāslaciō is bothe accordyng to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> texte in euerye
<pb facs="153"/>
sentence agreably to the Paraphrastes mynde, and playnlye Englished to the vnderstandyng of the moste vnlearned Englyshe men, for whose erudicion I did take vpon me thys laboure. For althoughe curious soughte termes of Rhetoricall Englishe, in thys translacion woulde better please the delicate eares and fyne wyttes of men fynely broughte vp in trickynge of termes and tounges, yet in asmuche as these translated Paraphrases are set forth for the informacion and playne teaching of the Kynges maiesties playne Englyshe subiectes that vnderstande none other but theyr owne natiue barayne tongue, I thoughte it rather better to seke the edification of the playne vnlearned by playne termyng of wordes, than by tedious circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ocucion to make a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase vpon a Paraphrase, and by that meanes, not onelye to leaue the simple vulgare people vntaught or neuer the better, but also in vayne sekynge after curiositie to be iustly laught to scorne, for bunglyng at the thyng that is ferre aboue my capacitie. Therefore where vnnecessary fynesse wanteth, accept true meanyng playnesse. And (good reader) be not of the nōbre of those men, whiche leade and get an easye and a wealthye lyfe almoste altogether by deprauinge, comptrollyng, querellyng, mysreportyng, and fault fyndyng at other mennes doynges (whose studye is to doe some good) and loyter the tyme them selues and do no good at all. But in case thou chauncest to fynde any notable faulte in this my grosse translacion, whiche hathe escaped me either for lacke of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure or learnynge, I beseche thee correcte it charitably with aduysednes, so as the readers and hearers thereof, maye the better and more expressely perceaue the Paraphrastes mynde▪ considrynge howe profitable doctrine for these oure present daungerous dayes the Paraphrases doe importe, aswell in teachynge Christ sincerely, and in settyng forthe of Christen manners playnlye, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukyng vice &amp; wicked customes sharpely. I ment not by thys my translation to hunt after worldly commendacion or temporall rewardes, God is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but to do good to the best of my poore vnlearned talente, vnto the symple vulgare sort, who I perceiued by most euident experience at y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> kynges highnes visitacion, wherin I vnworthye was a wayting ministre, were glad &amp; confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mablye willyng to heare the pure word of God, &amp; obedient to receyue the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges most godly iniūccions traynyng them to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> same: &amp; so they would contynue, in case theyr ordinaries, Curates, &amp; ministers were not try<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lers and hynderours therof, and if they were not seduced, and taught by sedicious earewhisperours contrary to the worde of God &amp; the Kynges hyghnes mooste godly gracious procedinges, onely for pelfe, belycheare, ease and lucre. But take me not, that I meane all them to be triflers, hynderours, or sinistre resisters, that are ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, curates or ministres. For there are some of the chiefe &amp; Byshoppes, &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries which w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all their possible earnest labour and paynes tendre the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles affaires, god be thanked for them: And sondry other curates &amp; ministres (whō I know) althoughe to fewe, are honest and diligently well wyllynge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the trueth in diuerse shyres, where I wayted vpon the kynges hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes visitours, especyally in Lincolneshyre and in other shires of that Diocese. And I verayly trust in God, that the nombre of the honest sorte shall dayly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creace there aboute more and more, by the industruous ministerie and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme concurrence in holsome doctryne of the Byshoppe and Deane of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, and the rather by the helpynge forewardnes and forewardyng helpe of the deuoute woman of God, the Duchesse of Suffolke. But I meane onely
<pb facs="154"/>
certaine sortes of ministers, whom ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> noble learned Paraphrast Erasmus paynteth notablye out in the person of the Euangelistes and apostles: of whō, one sort are those, that beyng altogether vnlearned had leauer cōtinue styl like Horses and Mules without vnderstanding, than to acknowlege their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunces and blyndenes and laboure for better knowledge to become the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of lyght. These are dogges y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> can not backe, &amp; ouerseers that can not see. These are also the blynde guydes, whom whan the blynde doe folowe, not the blynde guydes onely but the blynde folowers also (as our sauiour Christ him selfe testifieth) doe fall bothe in to the ditche of errour &amp; endles dānacion. The seconde sorte are they, which beyng noseled &amp; roted in worldly pelfe, belycheare &amp; promociō obteined by coūtrefaite crouching, hipocritical lowting, &amp; by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their courtely frēdes wil rather obstinately resyst &amp; murmure agaynst y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> kinges maiesties most godly trauailes &amp; procedinges as much as in thē lyeth, &amp; with slaūderous dissuasions, &amp; perplexe impertinēt interpretaciōs go about to bryng the most pure playne worde of God in to contempte, yea and to incēse the people to tumultes, sedicions, rumours and rebellions, (as practiced ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath of late dayes mooste lamentably taughte vs) than they woulde lose or forgoe any iote of their worldely wicked pompous Mammon, or (for conscience sake) submytte thē selues to the trueth of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> scriptures, or any syncere godly quietnes. These are the cursed shepeherdes of Israell, that eate vp the fatte of the shepe, and clothe them selues with the wolle: that slea the best <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>edde and nourishe not the flocke. These are the damnable hipocrites that shute vp the kyngdome of heauens before men, in forbyddyng, dissuading and discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageing them from readynge or meddlyng with the scriptures, (whiche be the breade of the soule) and wyll nether entre▪ in them selues, ne suffre them that woulde. These are y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> false doctours, that S. Peter prophecied of before hand, which slyghtyly bryng in pernicious sectes amonge the people, denyeng euen y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> lord that bought them, and throughe couetousnes by feyned woordes make marchaundise of men. These are the incarnate angelles of Satan, which with theyr fyne maner of crepe a bosome and outwarde pretence of holynes, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them selues into the angeles of lyght. These are the y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ching eared mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and spirites of errour, that teache doctrines of deuilles and inconuenient thynges for fylthy lucres sake, hauing their consciences marked with an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e yron, and teaching genealogies &amp; endles riedles that engendre questions, more than edifie to Godwarde. These are the Antichristes that against al the whole scripture, &amp; to the vndenyable de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ogation of the merite &amp; dignitie of Christes death &amp; blodsheading done once for all, take vpon thē dayly to sacrifice for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>emyssion of synnes of the quycke and the deade: &amp; teache swete to be sowre, &amp; sowre swete, lyght to be darknes, &amp; darknes light. These are also y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> right sonnes of their right father the deuill, that hath bene a murtherour &amp; alyer frō the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng. Finally these are the whelpes of the roaring Lyon the deuil, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> goeth about sekyng by their ministery, whō he may deuour. A thrid sorte there is, whiche for the sauetie of their pelfe and promocion, employe their studyes and forecastyng pollycies to please all partes, thynkynge in their owne phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasies that to be possible to them, that Christ our most true doctour sayth is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, to serue both god &amp; Māmō. These are they, by whose occasion y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> people halt betwene two opiniōs, not knowyng what is best for thē to folow, wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> God or Baal. These are the messagiers of Laodicia, whose workes are nother
<pb facs="154"/>
colde nor whote, but betwene bothe, smellyng neither to muche of the ghospel, nor to lytell of pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie. And yet they must be called fauourours of the trueth, for they woulde fayne all thynges were well, so it were not long of them. These woulde fayne haue Goddes corne to come vp, but yet they dare sowe none, longer than the worlde (as they saye) maketh faire wether. And notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng the more parte, yea and to muche the more parte, of ecclesiastical par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons be of these three sortes, that is to saye, eyther of blockeheaded asses, plaine professed enemyes, or doublefaced frendes: Yet God of the habundaunt riches of his exceding great mercies, hath reserued vnto him selfe some syncere Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppes and preachers in this Emperiall Realme, to erecte and confirme the towardenes of the true meanyng fauourours, to comforte the weakeharted, &amp; to confounde the stow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e rebelles, (the golden cupped courteours of the prowde whore of Babylon) with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he myghtye swearde of the spirite, whiche is the word of God. And for theuidenter declaracion of his mercies to his Englishe flocke, and for the glorouse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> enhaunceyng of hys own kyngdome and glorie in thys Realme, in forewardyng the godly labours and industruous trauailes of hys faythfull ploughmen the ministres, (in despighte of all hys enemyes) God (in whose hande all kynges heartes are) hathe put in to the hearte of oure mooste Royall worthye kynge, Edwarde the. vi. not onely, lyke a moste Christen Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sias, by the ministerie, trauaile, and studious endeuours of his moste faythfull deare Vncle the lorde Protectours grace &amp; other of his most honorable Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle, to abolyshe idolatrous sacrificeinges, and supersticious customes, and to restore the true worship, religion and gospell of Christe in to his pristine sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, purenes and lybertie agayne, but also lyke a moste prudent yong Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon to buylde vp perfitely the Lordes house, and to walke (after thexample of the olde Salomon) as it were before the porche of the temple, lyke Goddes true minister, to expell and kepe out all false worshyppinges, popishe Goddes seruice, vayne ceremonies, pernicious sectes, sedicious tumultes, fylthye er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and noughtie lurkyng hereticall opinions, from amonge hys Christen Englyshe subiectes, whiche is the lyuing temple of God, and to trayne, ordre and gouerne them with the rule of holsome lawes (to the banishemente of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly licencious libertie, that men are nowe a dayes to muche geuen and bent vnto, and to the nourishement of vertues, whiche God requireth) and also to kepe and defende them from all intestine tumultes, daungers and inuasions, that myght perchaunce be intended by forayne or homedwellyng enemies. Forasmuch than as al the kinges maiesties obedyent true subiectes, are now most straytely debtebounden generally to rendre most humble perpetual than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to God, throughe our lorde Iesus Christ, for his excedyng vnspeakeable mercies and most bounteous liberall benignitie powred in most habundaunt wyse vpon vs, nowe already sene by manifolde proued miraculous experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, in sendyng vs so godly a yong Kyng, in placeing so noble and so religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Protectour, &amp; inprouiding so worthy a prudent Coūsail: And lyke as we may be most vndoubtedly sure, in case we lay fast hold on y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> promisses of god, &amp; stick hard to his gospel w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cōstaūt belefe of our hert, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vnfeined cōfessiō of our mouth, &amp; frame our cōuersaciō w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out grudging agreably to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> same, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> he wyll cōtinue, maintene &amp; increase his trasoures, blessinges, &amp; liberal benefites vpon vs: Euē so it standeth vs in hāde w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al vigilaūt circūspection generally to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> we take not these graces of god so gētly, so frely &amp; so bounteously geuē
<pb facs="155"/>
vnto vs, in vayne, lest for oure neglygente vnthankefulnes, contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous stubburnes, outragious licenciousnes, and dissolute vnthriftines, he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe his blessynges, and take away these most precious Iewelles, treasours, and benefites from vs, and so for our owne wicked desertes iustely leaue vs to our selues, to worke the thynges that are not conuenyent euen with gredy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to receyue therfore the rewarde of errour. Therefore to be playne with the (good reader) seyng that our moste bounteouse mercyfull God almyghtye, doeth aswell in powryng these hys mooste plentcouse proued blessynges vpon vs Engyshe folkes without our deseruynges, as in his longe sufferaunce and wynkyng at our daylye practised naughtines, inuite and most gently prouoke vs vnto repentaunce: I thinke it not best for vs to mocke on styll with God, and to contemne the riches of his goodnes and long suffraunce. For God wyll not be mocked for vs. And yet yf a man any thyng earnestly marke the maners of this roiall rufflynge worlde, it woulde seme, that men thynke that there is no God, either that God is a slepe, or elles that he is not so greuously displeased with the fylthynes of synne and disobedience, as the holy scripture in all places reporteth him to be: or at leaste that the scripture is not the woorde whiche declareth the cōmaundement and trueth of God. For it is a monstrous mater to marke, howe shamelesly the Romyshe ympes, slaunder, depraue, and abuse the moste holy sacred worde of God, the Byble, and the true preachers and expounders of the same, namyng it falsely the newe learnyng, and thē new fangled felowes: and howe hansomly they vpholde, and how stubburnely they continue theyr popyshe baggage of dumme ceremonies, idolatrous worshyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynges, heathnyshe rites, cankred opinions, disguysed deuotion, missall sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeinges, faythles phantasied workynges, and other trades of countrefaycte supersticious religion, estemyng the trueth of God to be a lye, and the lying Prophecies of Methodius and other fonde imaginations to be the trueth. It it is an horrible thyng also to heare the blasphemous swearyng, sturdye diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyeng, traiterous rebellynge, false rumours inuentyng, deuelishe backby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, slaunders caryeng, sedicious murmuring agaynst the trueth and al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly procedynges, and to see the hellyshe workes of palpable darkenes that are exercised nowe a dayes. Whan was there euer more disdayne, and more excesse of costly apparell vsed, and lesse clothyng of the poore than nowe? Whan was there more haftyng and craftyng to scrape money to gether, and lesse succou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of pore wydowes, fatherles children, and poore neady impotent persons, than now? Whan was there at any time more forecast to ioyne house to house, and lande to lande, and lesse hospitalitie, than nowe? Whan were there in anye age īo many gorgious buyldynges set vp, for wealthye mens pleasures, and fewer hospitalles mayntened for poore mennes succours, than nowe? Whan was there more destroying &amp; enclosyng of whole townes, villages and cōmins to some one mannes priuate vse for the nourishynge, rearyng and stoaring of shepe and brute beastes, wherby straunge Realmes, are enryched, and so lytle studie to maynteyne tyllage and to nouryshe tall yomen, to thencrease of the commen strengthe of this theyr owne natyue Realme and to serue to kynges Maiestie in his necessarie affaires, than is nowe? Whan was there euer more pollyng, pylling, theuing, robbyng, extorcionyng &amp; brybyng, &amp; lesse restitucion makyng than nowe: Whan was there at any tyme more holsome lawes made for the commē wealth &amp; good ordre in euery estate, and lesse obserued and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="155"/>
than nowe? Whan was swearyng and takyng of othes vpon the holy euā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes more solemnely vsed, and lesse truth or promysse kept than now? Whā was excessyue riotous bankettyng, pottecompanyonyng, and belychearynge more outragiously vsed, and the pore hungriousnes lesse refreshed, than now? Whan was shameles whoremongyng more licenciously frequented withoute punishement, than nowe? Whan was holowe herted flatterye and craftye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauyng, more practiced, and lesse hertye frendeshyp steryng, than now? Whā were parentes more negligent in vertuous bryngyng vp of their children, and children more disobedient to their parentes, than nowe? Whan were maisters more vnlouyng or strayterlaced to their seruauntes, and seruauntes lesse dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and trustye to their maisters, than nowe? Whan was there more quycke bargaynyng among men, and lesse true dealyng, than nowe? To be short, whā was there mo ghospell talkers, and fewer ghospell walkers, than are nowe? Whan was there so many ghospell bablers, and so fewe ghospell folowers, as nowe? And finally, whan wente Christe in his ministres so diligentlye on prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng and founde lesse faythe vpon earthe, or was lesse entreteyned, than now? These thynges therfore respectiuely weyghed and conferred together, are euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent profes, that lyghte is comen in to the worlde, and men haue rather loued darkenes than lyght. And it is also an aunciente practice of the father of the popes malignaunt churche (that most diligent preachyng prelate doctour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll) whan he can not get him damnable disciples ynowe to sactisfie his gredy lust, throughe his poperye, by reason of the cleare lyght and powre of the ghos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell shynyng forthe, to take vpon him to be a fyne forewarder of the ghospels lybertie: that is to saye, to instigate men, in pretense of the ghospell, to scrape and cloyne in to their handes as muche possession as they can, to thintent that (the godly learned preachers and ministres now lyuing beyng once deade, and no competent prouysion for preaching nor learned men beyng had) there may growe in more blinde popery, barbarousnes and ignoraunce in our posteritie, than was in or before oure tyme. And so the laste errour shalbe worse than the farther. For (as Salomon sayeth) whan preachynge ceaseth, the people shall runne hauocke. And it is that subtill Satans practise also, in pretence of the ghospelles libertie, to cause men to make their belies their Goddes: as we see dayly (alas therfore) euery lyghte headded ydle person, and euerye raungeyng ruffion shamelesly pampre his paunche with fleshe and delicates, regardynge neyther ordre nor cōmune wealth, sparyng nether place nor time, ne yet geuing god any thākes at al ether for fleshe or fishe, meate or drinke, as it may appeare by their impudent abominable lyuinge, &amp; couetous gredynes of worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures: in swearyng, whoring, dyceing, cardyng, braullyng, raylyng, braggyng, querelling, fighting▪ piking, stealing, robbing, bawdy talkyng, &amp; in al kyndes elles of hellishe iniquitie. And so by that reason (ouer their own dānable estate) the poore symple vntaught weake brother, for whom Christe died, seyng thys lybertie and thys iniquitie ioyned together, is by and by offended, and defyeth the worde of God, because of that rashe beastly bellyed mannes wyckednesse, whiche prateth of the worde and lyueth cleane contrarie agaynst it. Thus the deuyll (I saye) purchaseth to him selfe and to the fyre of hell, as many or rather mo slaues by his countrefaite ghospellyng, than he did before with open ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous popery mayntenyng.</p>
   <p>Nowe therfore goe downe in to thy selfe (good reader) and see what case
<pb facs="156"/>
thou standest in, for thou seest by experience that the dayes are euyll. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e not the good oportunytie that God hath lent thee. For all that saye, Lorde, Lorde, shal not entre into the kyngdome of heauen, but he that doeth the fathers wyll whiche is in heauen. Althoughe we are made ryghteous before God throughe onely fayth, yet we muste expresse our fayth by suche charitable workes before men, as God commaundeth, or els our faythe is deade, and become no faythe. And thoughe we are saued throughe grace, yet we may not abide in synne stil, that grace maye abounde. For lyke as whan a synner repenteth, there is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye heauen, the Angelles reioycing for gladnes: euen so whan a man repenteth not, but lyueth styll in infidelitie and synne, he maketh the holy ghost sadde and a sorowfull, heauen. And thoughe we are quyckened together with Christe of his owne fre mercye without our deseruynges, yet we are commaunded by his holy worde, to mortyfie oure carnal membres vpon earth, that lyke as we haue in tymes past made them seruauntes of vngodlynes from one naughtynes to an other, so we shoulde henceforth make them seruauntes of puritie into sant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. For he that gaue vs Christ to be our newe garmente, badde vs (by his Apostle Paule) put of the olde Adam: or elles Christe woulde not stycke cleane on our backes, onlesse olde Adam be stryped cleane of, wyth all his rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged rotten patches of infidelitie and sinfulnes. And he that sayeth: <hi>Let us put on the armour of lyghte,</hi> sayeth fyrste: <hi>Let us cast a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uaye the uuorkes of darknes.</hi> For lyke as God loueth to be wourshypped onelye accordynge to his owne worde and byddyng: so he curfeth all them that inuent or vse other kyndes of worshyppyng or seruyng of him besydes his worde. And lyke as God filleth them with his grace that reuerently and truly vse his holy name: so he fylleth them also full of wikednes, that be swearours: and maketh his plague of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce to hang styll ouer their houses that abuse Goddes name. And lyke as God promyseth reward to them that helpe their pore neyghbours at their nede: so he threateneth punishement to them also, that hurte their neyghbours by worde or by dede. And like as the holy goste alloweth chaste wedlocke for holy and honourable among all men: so doeth he pronounce whoredom and bawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye to be cursed and abominable among all men. Christe that geueth the peny to the diligent workers, byddeth auaunt, I knowe you not, to them that are loyterours. The Prophete Dauid that sayeth: <hi>Prope est dn̄s oībus eum inuocanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> sayeth also: <hi>Longe a peccatoribus salus.</hi> And that ghospell, which is the power of God to saue all that beleue it, shall also be a witnesse at the last daye against all them that shewe them selues in this worlde vnbeleuers by the frutes of their vngodly behauyour. Assure thy selfe of thys, good reader, that lyke as there is God, so is there the deuyll. As there is heauen, so is there hel. As there is lyfe and eternall saluation, so is there death and eternall damnacion. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cast of careles securitie, and be diligent in readynge or hearynge Goddes worde. If Christe be thy sauiour, make no moe mediatours for thee but onely him. For lyke as he wyl not geue away the glory of his passion to any other: so wyl he not geue awaye the glory of his intercession to any other. Cast of feyned custome, and laye holde vpon vnfailyng veritie: Forsake blynde broade bye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes▪ and folowe the streight narowe pathe way: Awaye with fylthy whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monging, and take thee to chaste wedlocke. If thou wilte be chosen, make sure thy vocation. If thou defyest the deuyll, meddle not with false teachers and deuely she lyuyng. If thou louest not the deuylles sauour, dwell not vpon hys
<pb facs="156"/>
donghill of stynkyng ydolatrie and supersticiō. If thou be the sonne of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, doe the workes of Abraham. If thou be iustified throughe onely faythe in Christ, leade the lyfe and doe the dedes of a faythfull iustifyed christen man. If Christe be thy Lorde, be thou his true seruaunt. If thou wylte take vpon the to be Christes disciple, see that thou weare his badge, Christen charitie. If Christe be thy good shepeherde, herken to his voyce and none other. If Christe haue borne the on his owne shoulders into his shepefolde, whan thou wast runne astraye: see thou runne not oute agayne, lest thou droppe into the pitte and be drowned throughe thyne owne folye. If thou wylte take God for thy father, see thou be holy as he is holy. If thou wylte haue the holy spirite of God to be thy comfortoure, make him not sadde with the resisting waiward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy spirite. And than mayest thou be surely bolde to preace vnto the throne of hys grace, and shalte be sure to fynde mercye in conuenient tyme.</p>
   <p>Take hede by tyme, for nowe is the tyme and verye howre for vs to ryse vp from sleape: and therfore, I saye, take tyme of repentaunce, whyle tyme is, for tyme wyll awaye. But and yf thou wylte not aryse and heare the voyce of thy Shepeherde Christ, hauing the lybertie of Goddes woorde (the rather by the ample enterpretyng of these Godly Paraphrases) to teache thee and to be thy warraunt: &amp; thexample of the Kynges Maiestie with hys gracious Vncle the lord Protectour &amp; the test of his most honorable Counsail to encourage, ayde and defende thee: but wylt tomble and walowe styll in wylful ignoraunce, and errour, stickyng to olde heathenyshe idolatrous worshippinges, supersticious deuisinges, masse meritinges, beade droppinges, popyshe customes, disobedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence agaynst superiours and parentes, blasphemous swearyng, aduouterous lyuing, theuyshe stealyng▪ murder and robbynge, couetous cloynynge, bawdye talkyng, holoweharted flateryng, false witnesse bearyng, vntrue dealyng, craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye deceauyng, dronken drinkyng, paunche pampryng, subtyl vnderminynge, and other wyckednesses and vilanies against the wrytten word and commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God: and so differrest repentaunce from daye to daye, and heapyng synne vpon synne, sayest: the mercye of God is greate. Tushe let God sende me a mery lyfe, &amp; ynoughe in this worlde, and than let hym doe with me in an other worlde what he wyll: Be thou assured, that thou enforcest God to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye hys holy spirite, and his good gyftes from thee, and layest vp wrath in stoare for thy selfe agaynste the daye of wrath, whan God shall iudge the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughtes of men, by Iesus Christe. Thou shalt haue the immortall worme of thy conscience to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>awe contynually vpon thee, so as fallynge into desperacyon and grudgeynge agaynste God, thou shalte begynne thyne hell euen in thys worlde, hauynge anguyshe and trouble vpon thy soule for thy wycked lyuynge. And at that greate feaste daye, whan thou shalte appeare wythoute the weddynge garment of a perfyte faythe, garnysshed wyth workes of charitie, and good lyuynge: Christe the kyng shall commaunde thee to be bounden hande and fote, and to be cast into the vtter darkenes, where shalbe weepyng and gnashyng of teethe: &amp; for the rewarde of thyne errour and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, thou shalte be constrayned perforce to pledge the Deuyll of his own cuppe, that is prepared euerlastyngly for hypocrites to drynke vpon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into the Lorde God shall rayne, snares, fyre, brymston<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, storme and tempest. Than it wyll not auayle the to repente. Than it wylbe to late to crye, had
<pb facs="157"/>
I wyste. Remembre thy selfe therefore in tyme: seyng that God of hys curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gentylnes, by hys holy woord geueth thee so curteous warnynge. And take in good parte thys my symple translacyon, intended to none other purpose, but to thy forwardynge helpe, as the Lorde is my wytnesse: God sende thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte vnderstandyng (gentle reader) in hys trueth, and well to fate.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the Prologe.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>