<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND VER∣TVOVS, HIS SINGVLRA GOOD LADIE,
THE LADIE IANE Vicountesse Mountague, all honour and
happinesse.</title>
           <author>Bullokar, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107055_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17230</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4083</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107055</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND VER∣TVOVS, HIS SINGVLRA GOOD LADIE,
THE LADIE IANE Vicountesse Mountague, all honour and
happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Bullokar, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An English expositor : teaching the interpretation of the hardest words vsed in our language. With sundry explications, descriptions, and discourses. By I.B. Doctor of Phisicke</title>
                 <author>J. B. (John Bullokar)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVOVS, HIS SINGVLRA GOOD LADIE,
THE LADIE IANE Vicountesse Mountague, all <hi>honour and
happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing perswaded (Right Noble Ladie) by some friends, for
publike bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to make this Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of words common, which at first was
inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely for priuate vse, (as written in my youth, at the request of
a worthy Gentleman, one whose loue preuailed much with me) I could not finde
in heart to send it forth, no better furnished than with a bare Title;
lest like an vnknowne Infant, it should be exposed to ouer hard vsage,
or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture scornefully reiected, aduenturing abroad without countenance
of any friend or commaunder. Vpon sure knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb facs="3"/>of
your most honourable disposition, and former experience of your
Ladyships fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour toward me, I am emboldned to present this little Pamphlet
vnto your Honour, with hope that by your Patronage it shall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee
protected from iniuries, but also finde fauourable entertainment, and perhaps
grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully admitted among greatest Ladies and studious Gentlewomen, to
whose reading (I am made beleeue) it will not prooue altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vngratefull.
And although I may well be taxed of folly or presumption, that for cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of
a slender trifle, craue the assistance of so eminent a Person, yet
such (I confesse) is my care thereof (since I must not deny it for my
owne) and my duty and deuotion so affected to your Honour, and all yours;
that I haue, (hoping of your Ladishps pardon) wilfullie repelled al reasons
which might disswade me, choosing herein not so much what may seem
most seemly, as what I suppose most behooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me.</p>
   <p>Accept therefore I beseech your Honour, and receiue vnder your
noble tuition this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vocabulary Treatise, which hauing beene many
yeares restrained of libertie, is now glad of enlargement, especially
recommended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to so worthy a Patronesse. The glorious Sun <pb facs="3"/>loseth not the least point of his heighth by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberall lending
downe his light, and quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with his influence the lowest creatures;
neither is any eminency disgraced, that easily condescendeth to others
desired good: which is also confirmed by the Poet, who saieth; 
<q>
         <l>Conspicitur nunquam meliore potentia causa,</l>
         <l>Quàm quoties vanas non sinit esse
preces.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Not thinking needfull therefore to trouble your Honour with many
words of entreatie (vpon assured confidence of your wel known Charitie and
goodnesse) I conclude, sincerely wishing to your Ladiship, the best
that may be wished, and resting my selfe euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours to be commaunded,</hi> IO.
BVLLOKAR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>