<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The argument of the treatise
following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107028_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07826</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18199</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107028</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The argument of the treatise
following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the threefolde state of man : wherein is handled, 1 His created holinesse in his innocencie. 2 His sinfulnesse since the fall of Adam. 3 His renewed holinesse in his regeneration</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas, of Berwick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 426, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>The argument of the treatise
following.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE last and chiefe end why God in
the beginning made the world with
all thinges therein contained▪ was the
setting foorth of his glory: the which before
the creation did shine in and to himselfe onely:
whereas now all the creatures doe praise his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
name. For the effecting whereof, it was
needfull that the creature should be endued with
a kinde of excellencie so great, as that it might
manifest the glory of the power, wisedome, and
goodnesse of God, and yet so meane, that it
should not in any respect be comparable to the
excellency of the creator. Hence it is, that
the state of all thinges in the worlde,
euen of the most excellent creatures, is
kept downe and debased from the state of God,
as in many other respectes, so especially in this,
that the one is momentanie, variable and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse,
the other being eternall, constant, and
the same for euer. So we read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14.
whenas God would euen paint out the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
of his owne nature, and distinguish himselfe
from all other thinges whatsoeuer doe any way
exist, he saith that his name is, <hi>I will be who
I wil be</hi> or <hi>who I am,</hi> that is, I am not a chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
creature, but the Almighty <hi>Iehoua,</hi> in
whome there is no shadowe of chaunge. But it
<pb facs="13"/>
is farre otherwise with the creature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
there is no permanent state to be found. And
to let passe the baser sort of them, which are
made for corruption, and to be consumed in the
vse, let vs consider the state of the most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
creatures, euen those which being endued
with reason, were made according to the image
of God, to wit, Angels and men: of whose e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
the scripture witnesseth, that it is not
onely chaungeable, but also straungely chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.
For it being in the first creation most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie,
glorious, and holy, became afterward most
impure, wretched, and vile. Neither doth it
stay here, but by the mercy of God man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored
to his first excellency. So we read, <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.
18. 19. behold in his seruantes he will not trust,
no not in his Angels wil he put any confidence
how much lesse in men dwelling in howses of clay
whose foundation is in the dust &amp;c? Neither
can it be otherwise, for God hath his being from
himselfe, but the creature dependeth on God,
by whome it was made, and therefore can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
exist nor continue in any estate longer then
the good pleasure of God doth permit. This
mutability of the creature appeareth chiefly in
man, whose diuerse states being three in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
we doe indeuour to lay open in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.
The first is the state of the first creation, of
holinesse, of life, and all happinesse. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="14"/>
is the estate of the fall, of sinne, of
death, and of all miserie. The third is the state
of regeneration, of righteousnesse, of saluation,
and of eternall glory. These three estates, we
desire to declare out of the word of God, which
entreateth plentifully of the two latter, but
more sparingly of the first, for that it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
a verie short time. Yet we may learne the
doctrine of it also out of the scripture, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
by these meanes: first out of the example of
<hi>Adam, Eua,</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> the which three one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of all mankinde liued in this estate. Secondly
out of the state of the Angels which agreeth
with the state of man in many respectes, and
therefore we doe often in the two first estates
speake of the Angels, not of set purpose, but
as by the way and for the further illustration of
the state of man, who in his creation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth
with all the Angels, and in his fall with
the reprobate sort of them. Thirdly we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
the innocency of man in those thinges
which the scripture speaketh of God, to whom
it often giueth the person of man not pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
with sinne but remaining in his first purity:
and lastly we may gather what was the state of
the first creation by the state of regeneration,
the which being nothing else but the renewing
of the first estate, will giue vs great light for
the vnderstanding of it. Further, this is to be
<pb facs="14"/>
marked that by the state of innocency we do not
meane those fewe daies onely wherein <hi>Adam</hi>
did continue innocent, but also the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse
and course of this state, as it would haue
beene if man had not fallen at all, the which
supposed continuance of the state of innocencie
differeth much from that actuall estate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<hi>Adam</hi> was before his fall: for he was not at
the first endued with any such actuall perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of holinesse and happinesse, but that he was
daily to encrease in both these respectes, as God
should reueale himselfe more &amp; more vnto him.
Lastly this treatise is diuided into three parts,
each part into diuers chapters: which in the two
former partes haue each of them three Sections
according to the three diuers states of man,
the which may be considered in the table fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
eyther seuerally by the reader going
downe in the seuerall columnes or in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison
with the other two, in the ouerthwarte
lines.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>