<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Iohn Caluin to all true Christi∣ans, who desire the aduancement of the kingdome of our Lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107288_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17694</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4439</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107288</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Iohn Caluin to all true Christi∣ans, who desire the aduancement of the kingdome of our Lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foure sermons of Maister Iohn Caluin : entreating of matters very profitable for our time, as may bee seene by the preface: with a briefe exposition of the LXXXVII. Psalme. Translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Iohn Fielde</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 59, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ Iohn Caluin to all true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>who desire the aduancement of</hi> the kingdome of our Lorde <hi>Iesus Christe.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you shall vnderstande wherfore and to what ende, I was desirous too publishe these Sermons, and shall bee aduertised of the Argument which they conteine, you shall know the better howe too make your profite of them, and to apply them to suche vse as I haue appointed them. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that I haue written heeretofore two Treatises large enough, to shew that it is not lawful for a Christian, knowing the pure doctrine of the Gospell, when he liueth in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, too dissemble howsoeuer it be, to consent or to cleaue vnto the abuses, superstitions and Idolatries, which raigne there: Notwithstāding there are euery day some people that demaund my coūsel therof a freesh, as if I had neuer spoken therof. I vnderstand also that there are others which neuer cease to alleage their replies, &amp; haue new startīg holes agaīst that which I haue written thereof. Therefore to cut of al oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casiōs, aswel frō those which iniquire of that which ought to be sufficiently knowen &amp; vnderstoode of them, as also from them which thinke to couer themselues vnder this wet sacke from the vengeance of God: I thought that it shoulde be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expedient to reuiew ouer againe and to bring into order a Sermon that I had made as touching this matter, the sūme whereof had beene gathered. Wherefore this first Sermon conteineth an admonition, what a slouthfulnes it is in them too whom God hath geuen to know the trueth of his Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, too defile themselues with the abhominations of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes, the which are altogeather contrary too Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, forasmuche as in so doyng, they deny as muche as lyeth in them, the sonne of GOD who hath redeemed them.</p>
   <p>Nowe because that it is impossible for a Christian man dwelling vnder the tyranny of Antichriste, too make a right
<pb facs="6"/> and pure confession of his faith, but that incontinent hee must bee in daunger to be persecuted, I haue adioyned ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther second Sermon, for to exhort all the faithfull, more too esteeme the honor and seruice of God then theyr owne life, and to fortifie themselues against all temptations. And in deede whereas many thinke it strange that they be not suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to disguise thēselues &amp; to play the coūterfaites, it is not, for that they are not conuinced, that the duetie of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God is too worship him onely in all plainesse and simplicitie, withdrawing themselues from all pollutions and Idolatry: but it is, because they see they cannot doe the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Christians, but they must kindle the rage of the wicked against them. Nowe they woulde flye the crosse as muche as they coulde, I therefore seeing that the doctrine of the pure worshipping God shoulde be altogeather vnprofitable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse that men be setled to despise this brickle &amp; trāsitory life, too seeke the kingdome of God and to follow Iesus Christe to the Crosse, to come vnto the glory of his resurrection: I haue added the second sermon to exhort them which at this day are ouer weake to courage and constancie.</p>
   <p>The thirde Sermon is too declare what a treasure it is to haue libertie not onely to serue God purely and too make publique confession of his faith: but also to be in a well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and gouerned Churche, where the woorde of God is preached and the Sacramēts are administred as they ought: seeing that these are the meanes by which the childrē of god may strengthen themselues in the faith, and bee stirred vp too liue and to die in his obedience. Now it seemed vntoo me that this Argument was very necessary at this day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there are many Christians in immagination, whiche flout at them which take paine to goe into a straunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and farre of to enioy such libertie,</p>
   <p>Now because there are many withholden and hindred from following of this benefite which God so muche estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, for the too great regard that they haue to their ease &amp; commodities: or rather for the feare and doubt which they haue, that any thing shoulde be wanting vnto them: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="7"/> are so delicate that if all fall not out to their desire, they whine and murmure, or rather fall to playne wickednesse: I haue added the fourth Sermon too shew vnto Christians how they ought to be armed against al offences, patiētly too beare al the troubles that may happen vnto thē, so that God geue them this grace to mainteine them in his house. So the summe of the fourth Sermon is, that when we haue this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge to heare the worde of God purely preached, to call vppon his name and too vse the Sacramentes, that this is a benefit recompensing all the vexations, troubles and griefes, that Satan shalbe able to stirre vp against vs.</p>
   <p>I haue set downe in the end a briefe exposition of the 87. Psalme, the which seemeth vnto me to serue fitly for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: for there is handled the restoring of the Churche of God. Now we see many at this day that seeing the Churche so desolate as it is, they discourage themselues, as if shortly it should altogeather perishe. Suche kinde of people, and generally all the faithfull shall finde here wherwith too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themselues, seeing the hope that God giueth of setting vp his Church againe after that for a time it hath beene cast downe: and of making it to prosper and floorish againe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that it shall haue beene miserable in respect of the world. I beseech our good God that my labour be not in vaine, but that you may be edified through my trauaile according as I desire,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Geneua, <date>this 20. of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1552.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>