<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my Honorable and Constant friend, Sir Tho: Walsingham, Knight: and to my much loued from his birth, the right toward and worthy Gentleman his sonne Thomas Walsingham, Esquire.</title>
           <author>Chapman, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107689_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18404</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4968</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107689</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my Honorable and Constant friend, Sir Tho: Walsingham, Knight: and to my much loued from his birth, the right toward and worthy Gentleman his sonne Thomas Walsingham, Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The conspiracie, and tragedie of Charles Duke of Byron, Marshall of France : Acted lately in two playes, at the Black-Friers. Writted by George Chapman</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>132 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my Honorable and Constant friend, Sir <hi>Tho: Walsingham,</hi> Knight: and to my much <hi>loued from his birth, the right toward and worthy</hi> Gentleman his sonne <hi>Thomas Walsingham,</hi> Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, though I know, you euer stood little affected to these vnprofitable rites of Dedication; (which disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in you, hath made me hetherto dispence with your right in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impressions) yet, least the world may repute it a neglect in me, of so ancient and worthy a friend; (hauing heard your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of these in their presentment) I could not but prescribe them with your name; And that my affection may extend to your Posteritie, I haue enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled to it, herein, your hope and comfort in your ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous sonne; whom I doubt not, that most reuerenc'd Mother of <hi>Manly Sciences</hi>; to whose instruction your vertuous care commits him; will so profitably initiate in her learned labours, that they will make him florish in his riper life, ouer the idle liues of our ignorant Gentlemen; and enable him to supply the Honorable places, of your name; extending your yeares, and his right noble Mothers (in the true comforts of his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues) to the sight of much, and most happy Progenie; which most affectionately wishing; and diuiding these poore dismemberd Poems betwixt you, I desire to liue still in your gracefull loues; and euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>The most assured at your commandements</hi>
GEORGE CHAPMAN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>