<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Vernevil, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107505_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17865</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4532</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107505</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Vernevil, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tract of the soueraigne iudge of controuersies in matters of religion. By Iohn Cameron minister of the Word of God, and divinity professour in the Academie of Montauban. Translated into English by Iohn Verneuil. M.A</title>
                 <author>Cameron, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Curteyne, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> present vnto your censure this tract of
<hi>Monsieur Cameron</hi> in English; I know
the skill of many for translating out of
French to bee farre better then mine
owne: but my request is, that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
my desire to do good, and not my imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
I hold it a matter altogether impossible to draw
a picture fully to the life: let Poets tell of painters,
and of birds deceiued by the exactnesse of their
skill; yet an originall ever looseth some lustre and
grace, though the translatours care be never so great.
Howsoever consider I intreate you, the author of
this little tract: for the worke of any man is now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adayes
esteemed, as the workeman is, and men care
most for reading that whose authours they esteeme.
For the Author I will say this little: during his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
life his reputation was great in <hi>France,</hi> and so
great, that all the Iesuites there did seeke, and at last
obtained to haue him banished, nor was there any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
cause thereof then his great learning,<note place="margin">Plantus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite. Act. 3. scena 2. v. 29.</note> the Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites
in their conferences being not able to withstand
him.</p>
   <q>Quoniam aemulare non licet, nunc in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ides.</q>
   <p>He had his refuge here, where by the speciall care of
that great fauourer of learning <hi>K. Iames</hi> (of blessed
memory) he was provided for in <hi>Scotland,</hi> his natiue
coūtry, but so great was his harty loue to <hi>France,</hi> that
by the effectual mediatiō of those honorable Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors
then in <hi>France,</hi> he gat that envious sentence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versed,


<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
which being done he immediately conveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
himselfe to Montauban to bee professour there,
where he ended his dayes, to the great losse of Gods
Church, and that Vniversity. Now seeing the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
loue that hee had in doing good to my owne
natiue Country, I haue endeauoured (as much as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
in mee) to requite his loue, and to make his
French worke speake English. If this tract bee fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
receiued, and that I shall perceiue my English
phrase tollerably to be approued, your kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
shall encourage mee to a greater worke: my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
abhorreth idlenesse, and beeing in such a place,
I loue to be doing, and to imploy my selfe, for feare
to be worse imployed*.<note place="margin">Quem diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus non inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit occupatum ipse occupat.</note> Enjoy this as <hi>a prodromus,</hi>
till by your prayers God of his infinite grace and
mercy enable mee to end my greater worke now in
hand. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord
IOHN VERNEVIL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>