<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, King and Queene of Bohemia, Princes Pa∣latines of the Rhine, &amp;c. AS ALSO To the most Illustrious and victo∣rious, Maurice, Prince of Orenge, Count of Nassau, &amp;c.

Most High
Most Illustrious
Princes,
</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107190_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15717</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22103</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107190</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, King and Queene of Bohemia, Princes Pa∣latines of the Rhine, &amp;c. AS ALSO To the most Illustrious and victo∣rious, Maurice, Prince of Orenge, Count of Nassau, &amp;c.

Most High
Most Illustrious
Princes,
</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of Vox populi, or Gondomar appearing in the likenes of Matchiauell in a Spanish parliament : wherein are discouered his treacherous &amp; subtile practises to the ruine as well of England, as the Netherlandes. Faithfully transtated [sic] out of the Spanish coppie by a well-willer to England and Holland</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Janss, Ashuerus, pseud.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 60, 2 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queene of Bohemia,</hi> Princes <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latines</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>AS ALSO</hi> To the most Illustrious and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, <hi>Maurice,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> Count of <hi>Nassau,</hi> &amp;c.
<list>
         <item>Most High</item>
         <item>Most Illustrious</item>
         <item>Princes,</item>
      </list>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT I haue adventured in these vnfaithfull times, so full of suspition and danger, to passe (without leaue) your guardes, and to presse into your Presence, I most humbly craue pardon, having I confesse no other excuse
<pb facs="2"/> not vnmindfull of a Matchiavillian and<note place="margin">Divide, et Impera.</note> old Maxime; But I trust Almighty God (as hee hath already begun) will open the eyes of all Christian Kinges and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in time not onely to prie into, but ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to oppose, these his immense and ambitious designes, which else in time may fall heauie vpon our children and posteritie, I end; humbly beseeching the King of Kings and Kingdomes, the Almighty Lord of Hoastes: Most High, Most Illustrious Princes, to protect the persons of your selues and children, with his grace to multiplie your Honors and Dignities, foure-fold to restore your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, and after many yeares to crowne you in Heaven, with the Diademes of Glorie and endles happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Who is most devoted vnto your <hi>Highnesses,</hi> in all Loyall affection <hi>T. S.</hi> of <hi>Ʋ.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>