<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶IOHN BROOKE VN∣to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107029_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17797</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107029</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶IOHN BROOKE VN∣to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of two vvoonderful popish monsters : to wyt, of a popish asse which was found at Rome in the riuer of Tyber, and of a moonkish calfe, calued at Friberge in Misne. Which are the very foreshewings and tokens of Gods wrath, against blinde, obstinate, and monstrous Papistes. Witnessed, and declared, the one by Philip Melancthon, the other by Martyn Luther. Translated out of French into English by Iohn Brooke of Assh, next Sandwich</title>
                 <author>Melanchthon, Philipp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 19, that is 18 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶IOHN BROOKE VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the things that are to be seene vnder the heauens (good Christian Reader) there is nothing can stirre vp the minde of man, &amp; which can engender more fere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the creatures then the horrible Monsters, which are brought forth dayly contrary vnto the workes of Nature. The which the most times doe note and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate vnto vs the Ire and wrath of God, against vs for our sinnes and wickednesse, that we haue and doe dayly commit agaynst him. But mans heart is so hardened that those his threatnings and foreshewings are reiected as though they were but fables. Therefore many times the Elements haue bene and be the heraulds and executors of Gods Iustice, as we do read in the viij. chapter of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis,<note place="margin">Genes, 8</note> that the waters ouerflowed the toppe of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est mountaine. xv. cubites, and drowned all the worlde except viij. persons. The fire in lyke manner as we do read in the xix. chapter of Genesis consumed &amp; burned<note place="margin">Genes. 19</note> the Citie of Sodoma and Gomorra. Also the earth as we may read in the xvi. chap. of Numeri opened hir mouth<note place="margin">Num. 16</note> and swallowed vp Chorah, Dathan, and Abiron. Besides an infinite number of examples more, which are to bee seene in the holy Scripture, and all was done for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse &amp; sinnes of the people. Therefore the rather to moue the harts of euery good christian to feare &amp; tremble at the sight of such prodigious monsters, I haue taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to translate out of French into our English tongue these two monsters, the one of a Popish Asle which was found at Rome in the yeare of our Lord. 1496. And the other of a Moonkish Calfe, calued at Friberge in the yeare 1528.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>And the willinglyer for that Philip Melancthon &amp; Martyn Luther two godly and learned men, haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted vpon these two Monsters, who were of such authoritie and credit, that we must not thinke that they be forged and inuented. Signifiyng that these two Monsters may well be compared vnto the Pope and his rablement of Cardinals, Abbottes, Bishops, Priests, Canons, Moonks and Fryers, as Gods messengers, to giue warning vnto them that Gods wrath is redy at hād to destroy both him &amp; his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with his whole rable of Cardinals, Moonks &amp; shauelings, disguising thēselues so against nature, as these two Mōsters were. For Sathā is a wyly Fox see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all the meanes possible thorow his subtile prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises, to seduce and keepe still in ignoraunce &amp; error, all Christendome. Therefore let vs way diligently these his wonderous woorkes, and repent in time from the bottome of our hearts of our sinnes, and desire him to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs, &amp; euer to kepe &amp; defend vs from such horrible Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>