<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY, To the Vnlearned (but vvell-meaning) Puritans.</title>
           <author>C., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107396_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4264</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107396</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY, To the Vnlearned (but vvell-meaning) Puritans.</title>
                 <author>C., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Puritanisme the mother, sinne the daughter. Or a treatise, wherein is demonstrated from twenty seuerall doctrines, and positions of Puritanisme; that the fayth and religion of the Puritans, doth forcibly induce its professours to the perpetrating of sinne, and doth warrant th committing of the same. Written by a Catholic priest, vpon occasion of certaine late most execrable actions of some Puritans, expressed in the page following. Heerunto is added (as an appendix) a funerall discourse touching the late different deathes of two most eminent Protestant deuines; to wit Doctour Price Deane of Hereford, and Doctour Butts Vice-Chancellour of Cambridge. By the same authour</title>
                 <author>B. C., Catholic priest</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 184 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY,</hi> To the Vnlearned (but vvell-meaning) Puritans.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O You onely, vvhose Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stādings, throgh your Grand ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters vvicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doctrinating of you, are corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted; but Wils good &amp; sincere, do I dedicate this smal Worke. My Pen hath heere purposely descended so lovv (not only in <hi>style,</hi> but euen in <hi>Matter</hi>) as to accommodate it selfe to such of you, vvho are vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as indeed most of you are.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>The contēts of this vvorke is of that facility and easines, as that it best may suite to such of you as be illiterate &amp; defectiue in the <hi>Elements,</hi> &amp; mayn Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Learning For though the <hi>matter</hi> here handled, be of such vveight, as that it is able to conuince the iudgment of the most learned Aduersary: yet touching the <hi>Methode</hi> vsed in the deliuery hereof, it is facill; seeing you shall not need here to spend the tyme in searching after the sense of produced pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture; or in reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Ecclesiasticall Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Church; or in pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering &amp; vveighing the places of the Ancient Fathers; all
<pb facs="5"/> vvhich do stand subiect to many difficulties.</p>
   <p>But it vvill suffice, if so you do but read the many <hi>Positions</hi> &amp; <hi>Tenets</hi> of <hi>Puritanisme,</hi> (the Fayth, vvhich I presume your selues professe) and the liues of the first teachers of them, most ansvverable to the said <hi>Posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> In all vvhich you shall fynd (&amp; this from their ovvne expresse Testimonies,) That the very <hi>End,</hi> or as it vvere, the <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ad quem, Puritanisme in Doctrine, doth finally propend, &amp; incline to, is impurity in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and dissolution in life.</hi> And therefore the greater commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seration I haue, that many of you, I presume (vvhose vvills
<pb facs="6"/> and endeauours are vpright &amp; plaine) are infected vvith the said impious doctrines.</p>
   <p>The first inducement, vvhich importuned my penne to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe this labour, is the late discouery in <hi>London,</hi> of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Sodomiticall Persons;</hi> (vvherof some are apprehēded but diuers fled,) in number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fourty, or more; in state competent, and some of very good meanes; in Religion <hi>all Puritanes;</hi> and in entercourse among themselues (a thing vvonderfull to be reported) so linked, as that they made a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar <hi>Society</hi> or <hi>Body,</hi> hauing a common designed place for their publike meetings: So iust
<pb facs="6"/> reason I haue to say a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem.</hi> 18.</note>
      <hi>Interrogate Gentes, quis audiuit talia horribilia?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Novv, seeing these prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Monsters (being so many staines to <hi>Nature;</hi> for <hi>Sodomitae pessimi erāt, &amp; peccatores coram Domino nimis</hi>)<note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> are <hi>all Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> in faith, &amp; hould themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues far more illuminated in the Lord, then the more moderate and learned Protestants; of vvhich nūber of learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, most do vvholy aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done &amp; disclaime from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Puritanicall Doctrines;</hi> And further seeing, that they may make shovv to vvarrant this <hi>their Sodomiticall State</hi> frō their ovvne <hi>Principles,</hi> admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="7"/> them for true: Therfore I haue thought good at this present, to set downe all such <hi>Theoricall Positions of Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme,</hi> vvhich do euen iustify <hi>Sin,</hi> and confidently teach its <hi>Proselytes,</hi> that the greatest <hi>Sin</hi> vvhatsoeuer, cannot become preiudiciall to the saluation of any of the faythfull; of vvhich number, all the foresaid por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentuous Wretches (as being <hi>Puritans</hi>) euen by their ovvne Principles and Doctrines, are taught to be.</p>
   <p>I vvould not haue the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and more <hi>learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> to thinke, that I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulate him in the ranke of the <hi>Puritans</hi> in generall; seeing
<pb facs="7"/> I vvell knovv, that most of those temperate and <hi>sober Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> do disavovv, and reiect diuers <hi>Puritanicall Theses,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted vpon heereafter by me. No It is only the <hi>Hypocriticall Puritan,</hi> vvho can vaunt, and brag of his <hi>Enthusiasmes,</hi> &amp; Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminations from the Lord, vvho depresseth &amp; betramples all Vertue, &amp; exercise of pious Workes, &amp; vvho doth blāch &amp; exalt Vice, against vvhom my Pen is at this time sharpned.</p>
   <p>I vvell knovv, that those, vvho did first stampe most of the doctrins of <hi>Puritanisme,</hi> as <hi>Luther, Svvinglius, Caluin &amp;c.</hi> vvere not vulgarly called <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans;</hi> Because in those firster
<pb facs="8"/> times of <hi>Protestancy,</hi> the name of <hi>Puritan,</hi> vvas scarce heard of; But novv this <hi>denomination</hi> is peculiarly applied to such Protestants, vvho belieuing certaine most damnable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines expressed in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise (&amp; first taught by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eminent Protestants) do differ by such their beliefe, frō the more graue &amp; learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant, vvholy denying them.</p>
   <p>Well, <hi>My simple, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly-meaning Puritan;</hi> for I presume diuers of You to be such; (vvhose Iudgement is vvronged by giuing assent to thy more learned, but vvithall more vvicked Brethren) I vvill remit thee to the perusuall of
<pb facs="8"/> this ensuing discourse; vvhich vvhē thou hast maturely vvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed, &amp; found (and all, by the confessions of the Aduersaries themselues) that the most fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitious Liues of the first tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of <hi>Puritanisme,</hi> vvere in practise most conformable to their ovvne exitiall doctrines therin; their vvicked conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations thus seruing, as a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to paraphraze their vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Positions.</p>
   <p>Then I hope thou vvilt cast off all thy <hi>Puritanicall</hi> doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hitherto imbraced by thee; or at least vvilt haue iust rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to censure vvith greater indifferency, both of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, &amp; of the first Authours
<pb facs="9"/> thereof; and then thou maist cal into thy remembrance our <hi>Sauiours</hi> vvords; vpon vvhich sentence be bold securely to anchour thy Iudgement:<note n="(c)" place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note>
      <hi>Do men gather grapes of thornes, or figs of thistles?</hi> And vvith this I cease.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Christ</hi> IESVS, B. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>