<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107052_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07467</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17854</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107052</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The admirable history of the possession and conversion of a penitent woman : Seduced by a magician that made her to become a witch, and the princesse of sorcerers in the country of Prouince, who was brought to S. Baume to bee exorcised, in the yeare 1610. in the moneth of Nouember, by the authority of the reuerend father, and frier, Sebastian Michaëlis, priour of the couent royall of S. Magdalene at Saint Maximin, and also of the said place of Saint Baume. Who appointed the reuerend father, Frier Francis Domptius, Doctor of Diuinity, in the Vniuersity of Louaine, b birth a Fleming, ... for the exorcismes and recollection of the acts. All faithfully set downe, and fully verified. Wherunto is annexed a pneumology, or discourse of spirits made by the said father Michaëlis, and by him reuewed, corrected and enlarged: together with an explanatory apology ... Translated into English by W.B</title>
                 <author>Michaelis, Sébastien</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 418, 10, 154, 34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendly Reader, When first I made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to put this History in Print, I found two sorts of men, that were of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion. The first had the faire cloak and couerture of Scripture, saying that wee must not beleeue nor giue credence to the Diuell, vpon which (say they) all this History is founded. The second as more eagle-sighted then the former, alleage, that it is vnsitting to put it forth, to auoid thereby the scandall of many (especially of those that are strayed from the Catholicke faith) which they will take at the publishing of this booke, when they shall vnderstand that these things were done by a Priest. To these two points I answere, that as touching the former, Iesus Christ himselfe doth giue vs the resolution thereof, when speaking of the Diuell he saith, that of a certainty there was no truth in him from the beginning of his fall; but hee giueth a restriction and limitation to his Axiome,<note place="margin">Iohn 8.</note> adding immediately these words, <hi>Cum ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prijs loquitur, mendax est,</hi> that is to say, when he speaketh from himselfe, and of his owne accord, it is most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, he is alwaies a liar, euer endeauouring to worke mans preiudice and destruction; but the case is altered, when being inforced and adiured in the efficacy of the name of God, hee speaketh and answereth to exorcis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.<note place="margin">Marc. 5.</note> This wee see verified in the Gospell, when Iesus Christ would vse his authority ouer the Diuels; as when they cried with a loud voice worshipping him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Nemo poterat cum domare, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenas disrumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, &amp; compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des diminuebat &amp; videns le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum à longè cucurrit &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens. Matth.</hi> 8. <hi>Adorauit eum &amp; clamans vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce magna dixit. Quid mihi &amp; tibi Iesu fili Dei altissimi?</hi>
      </note> What haue wee to doe with thee Iesus the Sonne of the high
<pb facs="4"/>
God? I charge thee by the same God (said one of them) that thou doe not torment me; and earnestly besought him not to cast him out of that region, nor into the bottomlesse pit of hell, but to suffer them all to enter into the heard of swine. And Iesus Christ demanding the Diuell that spake and was the chiefe of them what his name was; he answered, my name is <hi>Legion,</hi> for wee are many. In which we may obserue two remarkeable points; first that Christ Iesus being adiured by the name of God, although it was done by a Diuell, yet from the respect and reuerence which hee did beare to God his father, condescended vnto the request of this Diuell and all his companions: as in the like occasion, being semblably charged by <hi>Caiphas</hi> to declare whether hee were the Sonne of God or no, hee then answered more cleerely and amply then at any time before, although hee well knew, that <hi>Caiphas</hi> was vncapable of that my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, and would not make his aduantage of the same? What ought we then to cōceiue of Diuels, being adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the power of the name of God?<note place="margin">Vid, Acta. 16. Decemb. pag. Marc. 5. Luc. 8. Matth. 8.</note> shall they not deliuer the truth, when by the vertue of the same name, they are compelled to relinquish and abandon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of those, whom formerly they did possesse? The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point to be noted is, that vpon the interrogatories of Iesus Christ, they haue spoken and answered truely, and consequently they doe somtimes tell truth, not of their owne accord or motion, but vpon constraint and that of him who is powerfull to constraine them, to wit, Christ Iesus, and his Lieue-tenants that are endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with this power: to whom hee saith; I haue giuen you power to tread on Serpents and Scorpions,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dedivobis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatem calcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di supr a serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c. Luc.</hi> 10. <hi>Et in nomine meo daemonia eijcient. Marc.</hi> 16.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the power of the enemy: And in another place he saith to the successors of the Apostles, that they shall cast out Diuels in his name. If then the answeres of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels are inserted in the Gospell, why may not the like answeres be now written and published to the world? The old Testament doth not stick to say, that the euill
<pb facs="5"/>
Spirit of God hauing possessed <hi>Saul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.</note> besides tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, did prophesie also, that is to say, hee spake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of Prophets, of things absent and hidden from the vnderstanding of men. Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> in the 13. Homily vpon Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> giueth vs his reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this pointe, inueighing against Atheists who deny the paines of bell. They are taught by the Deuils (saith he) who being full of pride will not confesse that they indure any torments, and being replenished with malice, would disswade vs from beleeuing it: yet are they oftentimes compelled (besides the confessions made by them in the Gospell) to say and confesse pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly the great torments which they suffer; and are constrained thereunto by the omnipotency of God, and the excessiuenesse of the torments wherewith they are punished: as a malefactor that is questioned extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, doth by the force of the tortures that are presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him, confesse the truth. If then the Atheists will not beleeue the Scriptures, God maketh the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils themselues to confesse it, and those (saith hee) that will not then beleeue are worse then Deuils.</p>
   <p>For answere vnto the second, wee will make remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance vnto them, that by their reckoning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture should net haue laid before vs the History of the yong Preists that were the sonnes of <hi>Hely</hi>:<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.</note> who did snatch the flesh from the pots that belonged to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and did deflower the deuout women, that came into the Temple to watch there at night. Neither should the narration of the sinnes of <hi>Dauid</hi> who was a Prophet and father of the future Messias be set downe; much lesse should the Euangelists mention the treason of <hi>Iudas:</hi> which are so farre from ministring occasion of scandall vnto the people, that on the contrary, many wholesome doctrines tending much to edification may be drawne from thence. This is declared by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. ad Timoth. 2.</note> when hauing spoken of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> that did scandalize the Church, hee addeth, <hi>The foundation of
<pb facs="5"/>
God remaineth sure, and hath his seale on those that are his.</hi> Notwithstanding (saith he) is it not true, that in the house of a great Lord, there bee vessels of gold and vessels of siluer, vessels of wood and vessels of earth, destinated vnto diuers vses? If therefore any man purge himselfe frō the ordures which are in the contemptible vessels, the same shall be a vessel of honour in the house of God. True it is that the vessels of greatest contempt and dishonour, are the wicked Preists: as for example <hi>Iudas</hi> in the Colledge of Christ Iesus, and <hi>Diacrus Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colaus</hi> in the society of the Apostles; and the reasons thereof are apparent. First because of their great ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> which maketh the grace of God to depart farre from them, and consequently they are the more blinded by the working of the Deuill, <hi>Ingrati, scelesti</hi>; saith S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Another reason is, because they are more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious to Christ Iesus, as appeareth by Magicians. The third reason is, for that the corruption of those things that are excellent, is worse then the corruption of things lesse excellent, as the putrification of the blood is more pernicious then of any of the other humours. And this would <hi>Ieremy</hi> haue said in the vision of the two baskets of figges; the one being full of figges not onely good, but excellently good, and the other full of figges not onely naught, but extreamely naught, <hi>in por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta templi.</hi> And this is amply declared by Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist. 117.</note> in an Epistle which he wrote vpon a suggestion against a Preist of his, who was accused of some soule crime. In the house of <hi>Adam</hi> (saith hee) there was <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi>
      <note place="margin">A thorne in a garden cannot blemish the roses or the garden; but that a man may still say. Behold a faire garden.</note> in the Arke of <hi>Noah</hi> liuing creatures both cleane and vncleane, and in his house one <hi>Cham</hi> with <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Iaphet.</hi> In the house of <hi>Abraham, Ismael</hi> with <hi>Isaac:</hi> in the house of <hi>Isaac, Esau</hi> with <hi>Iacob</hi>; in the house of <hi>Iacob,</hi> incestuous <hi>Rubin</hi> with chaste <hi>Ioseph</hi>: in the house of <hi>Dauid, Absolon</hi> with <hi>Salomon:</hi> And how be it God himselfe had twice talked with <hi>Salomon,</hi> and had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed on him so many indowments of his grace in
<pb facs="6"/>
the house of his father; yea although himselfe was a Prophet and the author of some of the sacred and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall writtes, yet did not the Deuill cease to gaine vpon him, and to cause him to present vnto him the sacrifices that were appointed for God. Finally Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> bringeth in the example of <hi>Iudas,</hi> and concludes, I haue by long experiences learned, that as there are not on the earth better Christians then good Preists, so on the contrary I neuer knew a Christian so euill as a wicked Preist.<note place="margin">Hiero. contra vigil.</note> To the same purpose speaketh Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> no man did euer disesteeme the Colledge of the Apostles, because <hi>Iudas</hi> plaid the villaine among them: no man euer misconceiued of the Quires of Angels, by reason of <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his confederates: but rather by their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy end we should learne to do well, and be strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the more in the Christian faith, when it commeth into our consideration, that the Deuill paineth not himselfe to draw a Minister to make his supper in a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, nor a Rabbin of the Iewes, nor a Musulman of the Turkes; for from hence can redound no ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnto Christ Iesus, neither can he by this gaine in any thing in his pretensions, as he would by the assistance of a wicked Preist that doth consecrate the body of Christ Iesus. Neither doth God suffer such execrable villanies to passe without great and maruellous wonders (as shall be seene in this History) but discouereth all by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary meanes, of his vnbounded power, and doth inforce the Deuils themselues to make discouery and proclaime the same, to their vtter ruine and confusion. And from hence he ministreth matter and occasion vnto Hereticks to make acknowledgement of their Heresies: vnto Magicians to abiure and abandon their abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; vnto Catholicks to implant and establish them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with better assurance in their faith. I haue made some Annotations in the margent vpon the pointes of greatest difficulty, because I would giue contentment vnto euery one. I must intreate the courteous reader of
<pb facs="6"/>
this History to excuse mee, if in the second part heereof I haue bin constrained to make mention o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tentimes of my selfe, and those that were with me; there was a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity for the doing of it, for the more ample verificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the History. Moreouer the courteous reader shall do wel to take heed, that in this History he do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue credit to the Deuill, in that hee speaketh naught that is contrary to the Gospell and doctrine of the Church; but to giue credit to him then, when hee would set on foote some new and contrary doctrine. Besides he may obserue, that this tendeth not any way to the ouerthrow of the company of the Virgines of Saint Vrsula, for there is many times mention and repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition made in this History, that God hath made special election of them to confound and crush in peeces all magicke, and the abhorred villanies thereof, and that for compensation of the same, they shall be extolled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and before men. Furthermore the freindly reader will hold me excused for the rude and vnpollish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed phrase of this booke, I hauing a regard in a businesse of this nature to write rather truely then elegantly: hee may remember that the French Dialects are different, as it was in Greece when it most flourished; and that <hi>Aristotle</hi> with his harsh kind of writing was no lesse profitable, then <hi>Demosthenes</hi> with his Atticke phrase was pleasing: and the stile of the Gospell and of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is more powerfull with vs, then all the oratory of the world. Besides those that are possessed ordinarily spake their mother tongue, so that it was expedient for the more faithfull relation of the whole, to follow their vaine of speaking word for word. Hence it commeth, that the phrases of the natiue French tongue could not be alwayes obserued. The scope of this History is, the feare of God and his iudgements, the detestation of vice whereby the Maiesty of God is prouoked, and the auoiding of the paines of hell; more particularly, to cause in vs a loathing of that abominable sinne of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
<pb facs="7"/>
which is perpetually committed in practising of Magick, and in the Schoole of Satan. In the recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all, there hath beene vsed great faithfulnesse, without any additions whatsoeuer; and the diligence that hath beene employed heerein may bee seene in the page of the actes of the eighth of Ianuary, and in the following page.</p>
   <p>I haue suppressed this History for the space of a yeere and more, and made no account to haue had it publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed; but the zeale of the Catholicke faith hath indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me thereunto, after I had once seene a letter missiue of Monsieur <hi>du Vic,</hi> wherein he aduertised, that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries of our faith did triumph in Rochel, when the depositions of the Magician, now in question, were put forth in print, where it is said, that the said Magician did celebrate Masse in the Synagogue. And thereupon they make an inference, that the Masse is a diabolicall thing, but doe not withall consider, that the Diuels aime is to vsurpe vpon the glory of God, and to inuade (as much as in him lyeth) the honour of his diuinity, that in conclusion hee may cause himselfe to bee adored as a God. For hee shamed not to demand it of Christ Iesus himselfe, saying vnto him, I will giue vnto thee all the kingdomes of the earth,<note place="margin">Matth 4.</note> if thou wilt worship me, that is to say, if thou wilt acknowledge mee to be the onely God and Creator of all things, as Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> doth interpret it: as also hee dared to abuse the sacred Scripture it selfe in the presence of Christ Iesus. To which purpose speaketh Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>: shewing that sacrifice appertaineth to God alone;<note place="margin">August, lib. 20. contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum Manich. c. 21.</note> as in the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament (saith he) the sacrifice of the law, in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament the sacrifice of the true flesh of Christ on the Crosse: and after his ascension, the sacrifice made in the Sacrament, which is in commemoration of his death and passion; hee goeth on and saith. These are things which those proud spirits the Diuell and his Angels do openly chalenge and demand. And in the 4. booke of
<pb facs="7"/>
the Trinity, chapter 13. about the end of the chapter hee saith, <hi>Non intelligunt ne ipsos quidem superbissimos spiritus honoribus sacrificiorum gaudere potuisse, nisi vni vero Deo, pro quo coli volunt, verum sacrificium debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur.</hi> That is, Idolaters doe not vnderstand that these haughty spirits could not be so pleased with the honour of sacrifices, were it not that truesacrifice were due to the only true God, in whose steed they would be serued and honoured. Another inducement wherewith I was much mooued, was a booke in Latine lately printed in Paris, intituled <hi>Mimyca daemonum,</hi> compiled by <hi>Henry de Montaigne</hi> a gentleman of Languedoc L. of S. <hi>Iohn de la Coste,</hi> where in his precursory epistle he giueth to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that the occasion that gaue life and birth vnto this book (which doth intend to shew that in al ages the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel hath bin Gods ape, and vsurpes vpon his glory) is to beat flat that shallow, yet dangerous conclusion which the Ministers of Languedoc held touching the deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the said <hi>Gaufridy</hi>; adding these words, <hi>Nouato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in re tam leui insistunt, &amp; libellum confessionis praedicti Gaufridij à suis curant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mi, &amp; venundari, vt rudi plebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culae, quam decipiunt, quasi horrorem sacerdotum ineuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.</hi> But the truth of this History will cleerely demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, that God was grieuously offended with such im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and that for to bring confusion on the same, hee vsed a maruellous and vnusual meanes, making the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels themselues to be the discouerers of this Magician, who was afterwards burnt. Neither could it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise detected; for the truth of this could not sinke into their apprehensions that knew him, hee being after a strange manner by the aide and conuention of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell growne a couert and close hypocrite, and was after a stranger manner dis-masked and layd open by the omnipotency of God, whom the Diuels themselues are constrained to obey, when it is his good pleasure. The streame of this History runneth mainly on this point, to shew, that al tendeth to ampliate the glory of God vnto
<pb facs="8"/>
vs, and to confirme our holy Catholick faith. Whence the courteous reader may also note, what regard God had of our Priest hood, when to conuert one Priest that had so strangely gone astray, hee did draw it on with such long and admirable solemnities. For matter of fact in this History, there is nothing to bee wondered at, which hath not beene obserued and published vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occurrences by three Inquisitours of Spaine in the yeere 1610.<note place="margin">Printed by Iohn de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gastonat Lon. grond.</note> which was the very yeere that this History was acted; and at the heeles of that followed another booke of the same nature, made by Monsieur <hi>d' Ancre,</hi> one of the Kings Counsell in the Parliament of Borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aux.<note place="margin">The 6. booke and 3. discours pag. 459.</note> But the wonders were done in the person of him, who named himselfe and indeed was the Prince of all the rest in France, Spaine and Turky: and Monsieur <hi>d' Ancre</hi> doth write, that he found by the depositions of the Sorcerers of Biscaye, that one <hi>Lewes</hi> came &amp; taught them to accuse those that were innocent, to excuse the nocent, and to inueagle in as many sonnes and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to Satan as they could. So that the prouidence of God, hath been the true meanes to put to rout al the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Satan in this kinde, in that his Standard is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and the very master of his campe trampled and troden vnder foote. Moreouer hee that will more narrowly consider the History of <hi>Balaam</hi> the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,<note place="margin">Numb. 22.</note> rehearsed in the booke of Numbers, will not think it strange which by assiduall experiments is verified of the Magicians and Witches of our time. For it is there said, that King <hi>Baelac</hi> being conscious to himselfe of his weakenesse to resist the army of Israel, sent to seek out <hi>Balaam</hi> as the greatest Magician of that Countrey, to charme and chaine vp the armes of the Israelits, and so to come to his purpose by this meanes. It is also recited in that History, that to make his charmes and maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions the more potent and effectuall, he caused seauen Altars to be built, and this was to sacrifice and inuocate the seauen Princes of the euill Spirits, which bare sway
<pb facs="8"/>
in the kingdome of <hi>Lucifer:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 1. D. Thom. 1. partic. quest. 113. art 2.</note> wherein he doth by way of limitation endeauour to make himselfe like to God in his Maiesty, who hath seauen principall Angels to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist him. Of whom S. <hi>Thomas</hi> as also S. <hi>Denis</hi> doe say, that the seauen superiour orders do command and send forth, and the two inferiour are commanded and sent; and hence it is that these first are properly stiled Princes. Yet are we not to say, that the superiours doe not come vnto vs when they are sent from God, for S. <hi>Michael</hi> and S. <hi>Gabriel</hi> in the 10. of <hi>Daniel,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tob. 12.</note> and in the 1. of <hi>Luke,</hi> and <hi>Raphael</hi> himselfe who is said to be one of the seauen Assistants before God, were sent by him And in the 10 of <hi>Daniel, Michael who is one of the chiefest is come to aide me.</hi> And in our very History,<note place="margin">The second part pag. 311. act of the 11. of Ian. and the 6. act of the 12. Decem. pag. 39 6. Book 2 dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours pag. 414. after Cardan and Strozzi. Math 12. as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumpsit 7. spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus nequiores se. Marc. 16. De qua eiece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat 7. demonia. See Dr. Maldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat vpon the pastages which he literally ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the seauen Diuels.</note> mention is made of seauen principall commanders amongst the other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, and the same is auerred in the late History of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>d' Ancre</hi> touching the countrey of Biscaye. These Altars were built to sacrifice a Bull and a sheepe vpon euery of them to these seauen Diuels (which was the very manner of sacrificing to God in the Law) and by these meanes to obteine of them that which he desired, <hi>Dabo sicadens adoraueris me.</hi> And because they sought to worke against the honour of God, and the publicke good of the Church by him that was the Prince of all the Magicians of the East, it is said, that God to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and giue stoppage vnto such impiety against his Maiesty, and villany against his Church, did shew great and vnusuall wonders; to wit, that a good Angell did visibly appeare highly displeased, and exceedingly dreadfull, brandishing a sword in his hand, that an asse spake by as great a miracle, that the Sorcerer himselfe became a Prophet, God putting that into his mouth which was not in his heart, and he speaking oppositely vnto that which hee had determined, whereby Magick was by the Magician himselfe defeated and put to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion: to the end (saith S. <hi>Ambrose</hi>) that the perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of those that beleeued not in God, might by
<pb facs="9"/>
their owne South-faier and Sorcerer bee reprehended. We are further to hope, that this History will be no lesse profitable and vsefull vnto France, then that of <hi>Lion</hi> printed in French in the yeere 1566.<note place="margin">Bartholomaeus Fayus praeses. Parisiensis in Energumenico Hadrian. Hof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stadius ser. 52. de Eucharistia. Ioan. Lorinus in acta apost. c. 5. vers. 16.</note> which greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the Catholicke faith, and conuerted many he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, that heard the Diuell which possessed a Virgin to say diuers times in a high voice, that these Hereticks were his friends and confederates; and that the reality of Christs body was in the Sacrament, because in it there was <hi>Hoc.</hi> To this purpose speaketh S. <hi>Augustine</hi> in the 1. booke of the Concordance of the Euangelists chap. 15. that in his time the Paynims durst not blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme Iesus Christ, because their Oracles were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained by the power of God to speake well of him: and thereupon the Paynims began to blaspheme the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles; but (saith hee, speaking to the Paynims) que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion your Oracles touching the sanctity of life of the Apostles, and you shall cleerly see, that they will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to speake well of them also. If they could not haue had a power to speake a truth, S. <hi>Augustine</hi> had made these other more obstinate in their vnbeleese. S. <hi>Thomas</hi> in his <hi>Opusculum</hi> 17. cap. 10. answering to the fourth obiection of those that said, it was vnlawfull to receiue children into the orders of Religion, because that sometimes it proceedeth from the temptation of the Diuell, hee saith, that there is no danger to follow that which perhaps may be a temptation of the Diuell, so that it bee to a good end, with this prouision, that if the Diuell would afterwards wreath and wrest this to an euill purpose, as to scandalize or corrupt others, they doe not consent vnto the euill; otherwise the Diuell by this scruple may diuert vs from all goodnesse. Thus did S. <hi>Anthony</hi> practise who was well versed in this arte,<note place="margin">Anthanas. in vit. Anthonii. Ioan. Lorin in act. Apost, c. 16. vers. 17.</note> as <hi>Athanasius</hi> obserueth. And for resolution of all scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous doubts, a late Doctor of Prouince of the society of Iesus, called father <hi>Iohn Lorin</hi> hath prettily collected, that the Diuell may speake truth foure severall waies:
<pb facs="9"/>
first to beguile those that are vnbeleeuers and faithlesse, because they may say, this is not true, for the Diuell saith it; as S. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> and <hi>Oecumenius</hi> haue noted vpon the 16. chapter of the Acts of the Apostles, where it is said, that <hi>Paul</hi> being with his associats in the city of <hi>Philippi,</hi> a maid hauing an euill Spirit vpon her, cryed after them and said, These men are the seruants of the high God, and doe shew vnto you the way of saluation. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for a while suffered her to say this, thinking that it might bee auaileable vnto some; but when shee still continued on for many daies, hee grew angry, and conceiuing that this might be hurtfull vnto others, hee commanded him to come out of the maiden in the name of Christ Iesus, which he presently did. Secondly to flatter and collogue with the Exorcist, that he would cease to torment him, or to cast him out: which reason is also alleaged by S. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> vpon the same passage saying,<note place="margin">Marc. 5.</note> that hee behaueth himselfe heerein as a guilty person before his Iudge, and a boy before his Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master, holding the rodde with his hands for feare of being scourged.<note place="margin">The discours of the history which is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gathered shall giue you to vnderstand that the Diuell spake after this manner.</note> After this manner did a Diuell flatter Christ Iesus, saying, I pray thee torment me not Iesus, thou Sonne of God; in which hee spake the pure truth. Thirdly, (which is the most ordinary fashion) when they are enforced thereunto in despite of themselues, by the diuine and hidden prouidence of God, or in the vertue of his name by exorcismes; which reason is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged by the sweet and religious Poet <hi>Arator,</hi> in his Poems vpon the Acts of the Apostles, as also by vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Bede,</hi> and many others. Fourthly, hee speaketh truth to gaine thereby an opportunity to accuse and giue attestation against vnbeleeuing and impenitent men, before the throne of Gods iudgement. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon Saint <hi>Anthony</hi> rehearseth the history of a Diuell, that hauing taken on him the shape and habite of a Preacher, made a very good sharpe sermon, and in the end declared before them all, that hee was a wicked
<pb facs="10"/>
Spirit permitted by God to accuse vnbeleeuing and vnrepentent persons before the tribunall of Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The friendly Reader may be pleased to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vnto two things; first that this is a History making a bare declaration of a fact, &amp; is no foundation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to build our faith, though it may serue very fitly to stirre vs vp to ponder vpon the iudgements of God. The other is, that hee take not in ill part the frequent repetition of things, for that it was expedient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse and fashion this History to the truth: although those very repetitions were so varied and expressed with such vehemence, that they were neither vnfruitfull nor superfluous to the standers by, but did raise in them such passions, that they cast forth many sighes and teares, God for his goodnesse touch and make tender all our hearts by those many meanes and remedies, which he hath bestowed vpon vs.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>