<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107057_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4094</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107057</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scepter of Iudah: or, what maner of government it was, that unto the common-wealth or Church of Israel was by the law of God appointed. By Edm. Bunny</title>
                 <author>Bunny, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wight (Wyght, Wayght, Whyte?), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newton, Ninian</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 160, 62 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be, thou wilt looke for (gentle Reader) that in this Treatise following I should have set down not only the ordinances them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves that unto the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were praescribed: but also the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and meaning of them: both for the better understanding therof; and bicause that most of them are altogither abolished to us, but so far as in sense and spirit, we are to take instruction of them. I have therfore to give thee to understand, that it was of purpose by me omitted, partly bicause that many others have written of it, &amp; the book would so have grown to be very great: but cheefly for that it agreeth not with the course that I have taken, meaning first to set down the storie of the church by it selfe: and then, under the doctrine of it, to shew the sense of those constitutions that were given unto it. As for the Table of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that foloweth at the end of the book, I have to this end gathered the same, that so it may more easily be seen, what texts of the law are alreadie gathered hither, and unto what place they are sorted: that so it might more easily appeer, what they are that are omitted; and how aptly those are applied that alreadie are taken. Which I trust shal
<pb facs="4"/>be a readie way for others, both to judge better of this which is done: and to amend the same to their own private use as need shal require. Of other things I trust I shal not need to admonish thee: neither yet, if thou find any use of this, to take it unto thee. So fare thou wel, and give glorie to God: and, to thy power, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy thy selfe to the use of thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>