<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface, or Jntroduction, containing 1 a briefe descrip∣tion of the parties conferring in this Dialogue. 2 The purpose and profit of the conference touched: 3 The manner of it intended, in all humility and meekenesse of spirit: 4 the matter, solidity of Arguments and alle∣gations out of the best Authors of both sides.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107369_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17513</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4327</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107369</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface, or Jntroduction, containing 1 a briefe descrip∣tion of the parties conferring in this Dialogue. 2 The purpose and profit of the conference touched: 3 The manner of it intended, in all humility and meekenesse of spirit: 4 the matter, solidity of Arguments and alle∣gations out of the best Authors of both sides.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iustification of the Church of England : Demonstrating it to be a true Church of God, affording all sufficient meanes to saluation. Or, a countercharme against the Romish enchantments, that labour to bewitch the people, with opinion of necessity to be subiect to the Pop of Rome. Wherein is briefly shewed the pith and marrow of the principall bookes written by both sides, touching this matter: with marginall reference to the chapters and sections, where the points are handled more at large to the great ease and satisfaction of the reader. By Anthony Cade, Bachelou of Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Cade, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 315, 1, 112, 28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>The Preface, or Jntroduction, containing <hi>1</hi> a briefe descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the parties conferring in this Dialogue. <hi>2</hi> The purpose and profit of the conference touched: <hi>3</hi> The manner of it intended, in all humility and meekenesse of spirit: <hi>4</hi> the matter, solidity of Arguments and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations out of the best Authors of both sides.</head>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Roman-Catholicke.</speaker>
      <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough in mine owne iudgement, I am sufficiently resolued of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and sanctity of the <hi>Roman-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke-Religion;</hi> and am loath to be either vnsettled or disquieted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by any further conference: yet to giue satisfaction to my tryed honest and good friends,<note place="margin">Such should be the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a good Minister as may win the loue of the Aduersarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note> who vrge me once againe to conferre with a graue learned Minister hereby; I am content to goe to the man. And the rather, because (besides his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) I know him to be very honest, iust, louing, and of a meeke spirit; And here he comes. Saue ye Sir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Protestant Minister.</speaker>
      <p>Master <hi>Candidus,</hi> I haue much longed to meet you. The Lord now giue a blessing to our meeting. I haue heard, with no small griefe of heart, by some of your good friends, that you are fallen into mislike of our Church of <hi>England,</hi> and into liking of the present Religion of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now in tender care of your saluation, I desire to confer with you thereabout, to try if by Gods gracious blessing I may be a meanes to resolue and settle you in the truth.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
      <p>Sir, I would haue you to thinke, that I haue a great care of my saluation, and in simplicity of my heart, and tendernesse of conscience, and not for any other by respect, I haue sought the true way to saluation, and doubt not but I haue found it. And therein I am so well settled, that you may spare your labour.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>I doubt not, but in the simplicity of your heart, and desire of the truth, you haue laboured in this
<pb facs="22"/> waighty matter. For I haue obserued you alwayes to be of an honest disposition, sober, temperate, aduised &amp; of discreet conuersation: for which faire carriage of life you haue gained the surname of <hi>Candidus.</hi>
         <note place="margin">Good natures mis-led are much to bee pittied.</note> And I haue also found you zealous of Gods honour. So farre as your knowledge did lead you. The more it grieueth me, that so honest a nature should be abused &amp; mis-led <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by bad Teachers. But I pray you consider that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himselfe was blamelesse in life, deuout and zealous in his Religion, when it was erronious (as you are now) and thought his courses maruellous godly, and much tending to Gods glory. He was instructed by <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Act. 2.3. Phil. 3.6.</note> a learned Doctor, according to the perfect manner of the Law of the Fathers (as was then thought) &amp; was zealous towards God, and touching the righteousnesse of the Law, blamelesse: and of very zeale persecuted the true Church of God: and thought he was bound in conscience to doe many things contrary to the name of Iesus.<note place="margin">A &amp; s 26.9.</note> So that men may thinke, they are in the holy way of truth, and may be deuout and zealous there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and yet be farre wrong. As we hold those of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish</hi> Religion to be at this day, who persecute the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches of Christ which professe to hold the doctrine of the holy Scripture entire, without admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any other grounds of Religion. Remember what our blessed Sauiour foretold,<note place="margin">Iohn 16.2.</note>
         <hi>John</hi> 16.2. <hi>Ʋenit hora, vt omnis qui interficit vos, arbitretur obsequium se praestare Deo.</hi> The time commeth that whosoeuer killeth you, will thinke he doth God seruice. This was fulfilled in part, quickly. As in <hi>Acts</hi> 13.50. The <hi>Iewes</hi> stirred vp deuout and honourable-women,<note place="margin">Acts 13.50.</note> and the chiefe men of the City, and raised persecution against <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> and expelled them out of their coasts. So that people that are deuout and zealous in their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yet may be in the wrong: and had need well to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their groundes.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Rom</speaker>
      <p>These examples may as well be applied to the Protestants, as to the Catholiks.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <pb facs="22"/>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>You apply them to the Protestants: wee to your new Catholiks. Let the vnpartiall world Iudge, who are the persecutors, and who are the persecuted. But hereby you may see, mortall men must not be too hasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly resolued, but first thorowly examine the truth of their groundes, wherevpon they build their Faith. Lest they run amisse, as <hi>Saul</hi> did, though taught by <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel;</hi> and as the deuout honorable-women, and chiefe men of the City did, being stirred vp by the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
      <p>But when a man is well resolued vpon good grounds: why should hee disquiet himselfe, and call his Faith into question againe?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>The question is whether his grounds be good or no. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> before his conuersion, and these honourable-women thought as well of their grounds, as you doe of yours: and yet were deceiued in them. But beside this, there is another reason, why you should thorowly know the strength of your grounds, to wit for the winning, satisfying, &amp; confirming of others. To which end S. <hi>Peter</hi> saith (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.) Be alwayes ready to giue satisfaction to euery one that asketh you a rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son of the hope that is in you with meeknes and feare. So then both for your own fuller resolutiō in the truth, and for the satisfaction of me or any other, I pray you let vs seriously conferre of these waighty matters.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
      <p>With all my heart. So it be done in that manner <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> there prescribeth: with meeknesse, feare, and a good conscience. For rough, rude, biting, and railing speaches, argue rather a blinded heart, or a proud, scornfull, and vnmortified man, then one endued with Gods grace, loue and patience, such as is fit to winne others with all long suffring and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24.25. and 4.2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1.2. and 3.3.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>Sir wee pray with vnderstanding in our <hi>English Letany,</hi> from all blindnesse of heart, from pride, vainglory, and hipocrisie, from enuy, hatred, and malice, and all vncharitablenes: good Lord deliuer vs.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <pb facs="23"/>
      <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
      <p>It is a good prayer. I would it were well liked and practised of you all.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>You shall finde me not onely patient, but exceeding pitifull, and full of commiseration to you, and to all other well-minded men that are seduced, that be <hi>Errones</hi> onely, and not <hi>Turbones</hi> (as <hi>Lipsius</hi> distinguisheth them) not wilfull but ready to yeeld to sound reason,<note place="margin">Iustus Lipsius. Politic.</note> and to the truth when it manifestly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares: such as be <hi>vere Candidi,</hi> as I hope you bee. But against those wicked seducers, that wilfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist to blindfould themselues and you by Pious fraudes (as they call them) and keepe you on their side for by-respects, contrary to the truth laied open to their eies; you must giue me leaue to vse iust indignation, As we see the Prophets, our Sauiour and his Apostles did.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
      <p>Whomsoeuer you shall proue to be such I will ioyne with you in your lust indignation, and abhorre them. I account no <hi>fraud pious:</hi> nor lawfull to doe euill that good may come of. But by forgery and deceit to mis-lead simple soules from the truth in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, I account most detestable.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>If it please you then to alleadge your best and most solid reasons whereby you are moued to forsake our Church and embrace the now <hi>Roman</hi> Religion: I will be willing to answer you,</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
         <hi>Rom.</hi>
      </speaker>
      <p>I will doe it not of mine owne head, but out of the best and learnedest Authors of our side.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
      <p>And I will endeuour to answere out of the learnedest and most iudicious Authors of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and most especially out of our latest, pithiest, and substantiallest <hi>English</hi> writers, referring you to the bookes themselues, with notes of their Chapters, Sections, and Pages for your more thorow satisfaction and setling of your Iudgement: with like allegations also of your owne best Authors, when they doe (as they doe often) yeeld vs the truth.</p>
   </sp>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>