<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Ayre</title>
           <author>Coprario, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107252_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19264</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5679</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Ayre</title>
                 <author>Coprario, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Funeral teares : For the death of the Right Honorable the Earle of Deuonshire. Figured in seauen songes, whereof sixe are so set forth that the wordes may be exprest by a treble voice alone to the lute and base viole, or else that the meane part may bee added, if any shall affect more fulnesse of parts. The seauenth is made in forme of a dialogue, and can not be sung without two voyces. Inuented by Iohn Coprario</title>
                 <author>Coperario, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Barley, William, Assignee(s etc.) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Ayre</head>
   <lg>
      <l>EV'n to thy sweetnesse pure benigne, kind Ayre</l>
      <l>That first embrac't these teares, these I present.</l>
      <l>Know them, though now transform'd from Christall faire</l>
      <l>Th' appeare to thee in Musicall ornament:</l>
      <l>Free passage to melodious pearcing sounds</l>
      <l>Thine open bosome yeelds: greefe owes to thee</l>
      <l>Her groanes, and sighes: through thy swift-healed wounds</l>
      <l>Her shrikes are shot, and thine her clamours be.</l>
      <l>Receiue then chearefull Ayre these sad laments,</l>
      <l>Though thou art but one Element, and she</l>
      <l>That owes them, of all foure the quintessence,</l>
      <l>The Starre of honor, and the sphere of beautie.</l>
      <l>Goe, heare her sing these farewels, thou wilt weepe,</l>
      <l>And mouelesse euer in thy regions sleepe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Sing Lady, sing thy Deu'nshires funerals,</l>
      <l>And charme the Ayre with thy delightfull voyce,</l>
      <l>Let lighter spirits grace their Madrigals,</l>
      <l>Sorrow doth in the saddest notes reioyce.</l>
      <l>Fairest of Ladies since these Songs are thine,</l>
      <l>Now make them as thou art thy selfe, deuine.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>The deuoted seruant of</hi> true noblenesse. <hi>Iohn Coprario.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>