<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE PHILIP, EARLE OF MOVNTGOMERIE &amp;c. Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, and Steward of the famous Vniuersity of Oxford.</title>
           <author>Carpenter, Nathanael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107604_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18028</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4677</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107604</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE PHILIP, EARLE OF MOVNTGOMERIE &amp;c. Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, and Steward of the famous Vniuersity of Oxford.</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, Nathanael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Geographie delineated forth in two bookes : Containing the sphericall and topicall parts thereof, by Nathanael Carpenter, Fellow of Exceter Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, Nathanael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Cripps, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Curteyne, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 272, 16, 286, 2 pages, 4 folded tables, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="151"/>
   <pb facs="151"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE PHILIP, EARLE OF MOVNTGOMERIE &amp;c. Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, and Steward of the famous Vniuersity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Geographicall</hi> Treatise consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting of two parts, was in the very birth in such sort consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your inestimable <hi>Brother,</hi> as notwithstanding it so farre reserued it selfe to awaite your <hi>Honours</hi> fauour, that <hi>Both</hi> may seeme, as to share a <hi>part,</hi> so to
<pb facs="152"/>
challenge the <hi>whole</hi> in my poore <hi>Industrie.</hi> The <hi>Soule</hi> of <hi>man</hi> which some Philosophers imagine, to be <hi>all</hi> in <hi>all,</hi> &amp; <hi>all</hi> in euery <hi>part,</hi> seemes to me no where better resembled then in your Generous <hi>Fraternity</hi>; wherein the <hi>Soule</hi> of <hi>Heroicall Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence,</hi> though <hi>Indiuided</hi> in it selfe, so <hi>entirely</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates herselfe to either, that both may seeme at once to <hi>enioy</hi> her presence while neither <hi>want.</hi> If this my bold attempt in presenting to your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> hands these vnworthy labours, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny former reference, might be interpreted intrusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it were enough for <hi>Ingenuity</hi> to pretend, that your generous loue vnto our poore <hi>Colledge</hi> and the respectiue duty wherein the <hi>Colledge</hi> alwayes stands obliged vnto your <hi>Honour,</hi> commands my pen beyond <hi>manners</hi> or <hi>ability.</hi> Your affection to our <hi>house,</hi> could no way expresse it selfe ampler then by trusting our custody, with the charge of your choicest Iewell:<note place="margin">
         <hi>R. L<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. D.</hi>
      </note> A <hi>Gentleman</hi> of that tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly <hi>wit</hi> and sweet <hi>disposition,</hi> that <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Morality</hi> commonly reputed the daughters of <hi>time,</hi> seeme in him scarce beholding to <hi>yeeres,</hi> and to challenge a precedency before <hi>experience</hi>; in so much that our ancient <hi>Mother</hi> markt out with all the Characters of <hi>age</hi> and declining <hi>weakenesse,</hi>
      <pb facs="152"/>
cherishing in her bosome this young darling, seemes to resume her <hi>youthfull</hi> habit, and triumph ouer <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Ruines.</hi> This happines amongst diuerse others vouchsafed by your Honour to the place, for whose good opinion the best part of mine endeuours stand engaged, hath encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my <hi>hopes</hi> to promise me your indulgent Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of this slender piece, long since inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deuoted, as my selfe, vnto your seruice: In which confidence, fearing any longer to tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe on your serious and high imployments <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted</hi> to your King and Countrey, I humbly rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all duty and seruice to bee commanded <hi>NATHANAEL CARPENTER.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>