<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Light in the Porch for him that enters.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107870_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11070</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107870</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Light in the Porch for him that enters.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diseases of the time, attended by their remedies. By Francis Rous</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 526, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A Light in the Porch for him that enters.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Confesse the World is very tedious in the Multiplicity of his corruptions, and it would make a worke of the like te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diousnesse, if all the particulars of the one should become the contents of the other. But I haue by diuers winnowings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated the Heap; desiring to set some shape, if not on the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (for Vice cannot bee made handsome) yet on the manner of handling it. Ordinary Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which haue ordinary (if iust) Cures, I mostly omit, &amp;
<pb facs="6"/>
leaue the World to practise on themselues, that which they know already. Other euils there are, which for their insolent growth, scorne to bee slaine by a Pen, but like the Princes of <hi>Midian</hi> they call for <hi>Gideon</hi> himselfe, euen the power of the Magistrate to fall on them. These being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally referred to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cure, yet if some bee tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched (for I haue heard of a Gyant slayne by a Sling and a stone) they are incountred with the kindly Weapons of this Warfare, euen Spirituall and not Carnall. Another sort of Euils like the Plague, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming abroad infect farther &amp; become Documents of Vice and not Reproofes. And I wish there were not another sort of Diseases like the same
<pb facs="6"/>
Sicknesse, which taking the Ayre in a Worke of reproofe, may strike backe to the heart of the same Worke, and make it to dye like <hi>Ieremies</hi> Roll, if it meete with that kind of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour which vseth to cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all, if any one thing differ from it. In such a Case, Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may bring forth Substra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and a little more in the writing, may cause a great deale lesse in the reading. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there are other Vices, which heretofore in some Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I haue discouered, for which the labour of Repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be saued.</p>
   <p>But what sayth the Man of Exception? Are not these the Times of Light and Purity, and therefore how can there be many faults where there is so much Light? Surely I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb facs="7"/>
and thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the purity of our Doctrine, and am assured that in many it hath brought forth the purity of Heart and Life. But I say, euen because the Light is so cleere, therefore doth sinne the more appeare, and appearing, is the more to be blamed. For the more light, the more Direction; and the more Direction, the more shame, and sharper reproofe belongs to the strayer. Againe, the more light, the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation, and the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation, the more sinnes appeare; yea, sinnes appeare the more sinfull. So, in some sense, Light may be said to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease sinnes, but that is not in their number, but in the knowledge of the numberer. Therefore must our Light dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer
<pb facs="7"/>
those to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, which ancient Ignorance accounted to be none; and the Manhood of a Christian m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e vp to that height of Vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, which his child-hood could not reach vnto; yea perchance did think it vnpossible or vncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Againe, where the Deuill hath lost much, there hee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours much for the recouery of his losses, and the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men not being stil awake (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie often inticing to se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) the Enemy finds times to sow his tares: so that the good dayes of <hi>Iosiah</hi> had matter of reproofe for the Prophet <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaniah,</hi> and the flourishing Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> was taxed for a mixture of the Seruants of <hi>Iezabel.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, it is an obseruation of secular Policie, That all
<pb facs="8"/>
States, with time gather rust, and therfore by often reuiews, they are to bee reduced to the first grounds of Vertue and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, which setled their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. This is no lesse true in the Church, and if any doubt of it, let the Church of <hi>Ephesus</hi> resolue him. There was no long time betweene the planting of that Church, and the receiuing of the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Of their first Estate Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a Master-workman in that Plantation, testifieth, that their Faith in Christ and Loue to the Saints made him incessantly to giue thankes to God for them. And of their second Estate at the time of the Reuelation, Christ restifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that this Church was fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from her first Loue and her first Workes. Therefore
<pb facs="8"/>
the Church, and euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church out of the experience of humane frailty, by contiunall turnes should suspect and examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, to see what the Flesh hath gotten vpon the Spirit, and so with <hi>Ephesus,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring from whence they are fallen, returne and amend, and doe the first Workes.</p>
   <p>Thus it appeares that there is matter of reproofe, euen in the purest Churches, and if where there is matter, there reproofe should bee denyed, this were to encourage Disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and to forbid Physicke. Surely there is at this day a libertie, yea a necessitie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouing, and it dyed not wholly when <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the House of God in all Ages hath it, and hath need
<pb facs="9"/>
of it. But I confesse, there is a wisdome of reproouing, as well as a libertie, and I wish that they who haue this wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, did especially, if not only, make vse of this liberty; and I wish, that they who take the liberty, tooke also the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with it. The occasion and maner of reproouing oft-times makes the reproofe effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, and an especiall part of the manner is this. That it proceed from a visible Chari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie. Splenaticke and eager re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes harden those affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which they pretend to soft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, because these reproofs looke like a quarrell or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> like the inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of Loue, which hurt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they may heale. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ayme and end of all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions should be, the good
<pb facs="9"/>
of the admonished; and those are most commendable which are most effectuall to this end, and not those which fit most with the humour of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouer. Now if such meanes of aduantage bee sought and practised, a shame and a curse must needs light on that Man, who being sought by Loue to be amended, returnes hatred for the best office of Loue. Most commonly to such a one belongs the speech of the Prophet to <hi>Amaziah; I know that the Lord will destroy thee, because thou refusest my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for <hi>Babylon,</hi> let her not think, because of such reproofs that her deeds are better then those of <hi>Sion.</hi> For euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of such reproofes, the deeds of <hi>Sion</hi> are better then
<pb facs="10"/>
those of <hi>Babilon.</hi> For <hi>Sion</hi> growes more beautifull and glorious, by seeing her spots, by acknowledging them, and by washing them away. But a speciall marke and brand it is of the sonne of perdition, to hide sinnes as <hi>Adam,</hi> yea to bind them fast with the cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes of Iniquity. And this hath the Church of Rome done; for by Canons and Councels they haue bound their errours fast to them, and by a kind of perpetuity, haue intayled Errour to them and their heires for euer. Now it is a certaine Rule, when there is no Remedie by perswasion, then God vseth the Remedie of Destruction. This did God with his owne People, 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 36.16. This did hee with the first <hi>Babilon, Ierem.</hi> 51.9. And
<pb facs="10"/>
this will hee doe with the last, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18.5, 7, 8. Secondly, here is not one corne of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine pulled vp, but only the tares that haue beene mingled among it, by humane errour and infirmity, or by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious diligence of Satan. Thirdly, among these Tares, shall they find their owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, so that part of this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse is to shew, that the mayne Body of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is a Body of Sores, that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the knowledge of <hi>Babilons</hi> vnholsomnesse, <hi>Sion</hi> may flye from her infection.</p>
   <p>It is now time, that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bee admitted into the house, but I thinke he will be content to stay till hee know what I haue done, as at first I told him what I haue not done. I haue aymed to the
<pb facs="11"/>
Vices, not vsually discouered, not rightly cured, or not thus cured. Vices I call them, that are found in the Vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as well as the Will; for error and ignorance are faults, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s wel as outward, visible, and bodily disorders. But when all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his is done toward the cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f Man, there is nothing done, vntill the same God, who giues the word to the mouth, speake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the same word to the heart. Therefore with the Centurian, let vs intreat the Lord, that hee will but speake the word, and wee his seruants shall be whole.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>
         <hi>HIERON,</hi> ad Demetriadem de virgin. seruanda.</bibl>
      <q>Sermo offendit plurimos, dum vnus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisque in se intelligens quod dicitur; non quasi monitorem libenter audit, sed quasi criminatorem sui operis auersatur.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>