<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Admonition to the gentle Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107559_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18015</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4664</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107559</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Admonition to the gentle Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preparatiue to contentation : conteining a display of the wonderfull distractions of men in opinions and straunge conceits: and of the seuerall discontentations which are incident to euerie particular vocation and condition of men in this life, with the causes and inconueniences of the same: also how they may be either salued or qualified, pacified or eased. Consected applicatorie, especially to this people and time, as an argument most necessary and profitable to be vrged. By Iohn Carpenter</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 344, 30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_note">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>An Admonition to the gentle Readers.</head>
   <p>WHereas it is said in the 6. Chapter, that the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Beast is conteined in certaine Hebrew and Greeke words and voices &amp;c. ye shall vnderstand, that the saide Number, is to be gathered and made of the letters and characters of the same wordes after the manner of the Hebrewes and Greekes, which vse their Alphabeticall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and characters for Arithmeticall figures.</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>Faults escaped.</head>
      <p>Moreouer, because it was not my good lot to be present at the printing of this Booke, there bee therein too many faults escaped, for the which I am sory, and do beseeche you gentle Readers either to constre all in the best sence, or else to reade or correct them thus.</p>
      <p>In pag. 6. lin. 2. reade thus <hi>Clh. mlc. ail.</hi> or thus, <hi>Calah. Melech. ael.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>In pag. 64. lin. 1. supply these words omitted <hi>H Aitalih. cschr. chuh.</hi> which ye may thus reade <hi>ha Italy ceschar: chehu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</hi> 1. <hi>lo: Italy</hi> is like a Prince of the priesthood. Lin. 7. read <hi>ha. anosch cijhovah.</hi> Lin. 23. read <hi>Royh quohel ha Romah.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>In pag. 59. lin. 3.4.5. read it thus, yeares 666. expired: but chiefly from the time that the Diuel was let at libertie after the thousand yeeres: that is sithence the yeare of our Lord 1000.</p>
      <p>In pag. 113. lin. 1. supply (No, thus haue I said) &amp;c.</p>
      <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>