<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A CATALOGVE OF the severall Treatises heretofore published by the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107480_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04168</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107480</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A CATALOGVE OF the severall Treatises heretofore published by the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The humiliation of the Sonne of God : by his becomming the Son of man, by taking the forme of a servant, and by his sufferings under Pontius Pilat, &amp;c. Or The eighth book of commentaries vpon the Apostles Creed: continued by Thomas Jackson Dr. in Divinitie, chaplaine to his Majestie in ordinarie, and president of Corpus Christi Colledge in Oxford. Divided into foure sections</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 398, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="by_the_same_author">
   <pb facs="203"/>
   <head>A CATALOGVE OF the severall Treatises heretofore published by the Author.</head>
   <p>THe Eternall Truth of Scriptures and Christian beliefe, in two Books of Commentaries upon the Apostles Creed.</p>
   <p>The third Book of Commentaries upon the Apostles Creed, containing the blasphemous positions of Iesuits and other later Romanists, concerning the authoritie of their Church.</p>
   <p>Iustifying Faith, or the faith whereby the just doe live, being the fourth Book upon the Creed.</p>
   <p>A Treatise containing the originall of unbeliefe, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, or misperswasions concerning the Verity, Vnity, and Attributes of the Deity: with directions for rectifying our beliefe or knowledge in the forementioned points, being the fifth Book upon the Creed.</p>
   <p>A Treatise of the Divine Essence and Attributes the first and second parts, being the sixth Book upon the Creed.</p>
   <p>The knowledge of Christ Iesus, or the seaventh
<pb n="398" facs="204"/>
booke of Commentaries upon the Apostles Creed, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the first and generall principles of Christian Theologie, with the more immediate principles concerning the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Christ: divided into foure Sections.</p>
   <p>The humiliation of the Sonne of God: or the eighth Book of Commentaries upon the Apostles Creed.</p>
   <p>A Treatise of the holy Catholick Faith and Church.</p>
   <p>Christs answer to <hi>Iohns</hi> question: or an Introduction to the knowledge of Iesus Christ, and him crucified: delivered in certaine Sermons.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Nazareth</hi> and <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> or <hi>Israels</hi> portion in the sonne of <hi>Jesse,</hi> And mankinds comfort from the weaker sex, in two Sermons preached at S. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="204"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>