<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, the Lord Archbishop of Canter∣bury his Grace, Primate and Metropo∣litane of all England, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Latham, Simon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107556_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17985</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4644</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107556</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, the Lord Archbishop of Canter∣bury his Grace, Primate and Metropo∣litane of all England, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Latham, Simon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tithes examined and proued to bee due to the clergie by a diuine right : VVhereby the contentious and prophane atheists, as also the dissembling hypocrites of this age, may learne to honour the ministers and not to defraude them, and to rob the Church. The contents heereof is set downe in the page next following. Written by George Carleton Batchelour in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Carleton, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 39, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, the Lord Archbishop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury his Grace, Primate and Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane of all England, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch hath beene the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the times (most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered Father in God) not in this age onely, but in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages of the world heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore: that many truthes haue lien either neglected, as couered in the dust, or oppressed by the countenance and multitude of such as commonly are ready to condemne the thing, which they will not vouchsafe to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. The feare of which censures hath moued me to suppresse for a long time, that which I had written of this question. In which purpose I should still haue continued, if the reasons of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had not more preuailed with me then mine owne opinion. Being therefore perswaded of your graces fauourable acceptance, I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to offer this as a pledge of my dutie, which as it was intended for the seruice of the Church, so to whom may it more worthily bee
<pb facs="3"/>
offered then to him, who as in place, so in care and resolution sitteth to aduance the good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of the Church.</p>
   <p>In offering heereof my case is strange and singular, for I must do it with protestation, that I am far off from thinking that the thing for which I plead will or can be effected, onely the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which many haue conceiued of your Graces wisedome and courage, for the aduancement of the Churches oppressed estate, doth incourage mee also to thinke that by your Graces care the oppressions of the Church may be mollified, if not remooued: that the malice of iniurious cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes and prescriptions against the Church may be abated: that the vse of impropriating may now at least be staied from proceeding to any further greauance of the Church. In which seruice of the Church, as you shall heereafter leaue a memorable name to your selfe: so in the meane time you shall stir vp the prayers of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for your preseruation and continuance for the good of the Church of God, who with his plentifull graces blesse and direct your wayes to his glory and the comfort of his Church, through Iesus Christ.</p>
   <p>Your Graces in duetie and in the seruice of the Church to be commaunded.</p>
   <p>George Carleton.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>