<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶An exhortacion to prayer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107833_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16109</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107833</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶An exhortacion to prayer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deuout psalmes and colletes : gathered and set in suche order, as may be vsed for dayly meditacions</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="exhortation">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶An exhortacion to prayer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Monges all other exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, (good Christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that god hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs, that we may exercise oure selues in: there is none better, none more excellent, then is true prayer, cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a cleane hert, and an vnfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conscience. For in the day of temta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion when the olde serpent by his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl suggestions shal go about our helth to subuert, we shal easely by prayer (as a present remedy) all hys malicyouse &amp; sondry dartes extynguishe. Also in the day of external affliccion (which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times chaunseth for our sinnes &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes) by prayer we shall eyther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne helpe that it may be mitigated, or elles all together taken away. Fyrst of all, this is to be noted y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we must make our prayers and commen peticions vnto god, and to hym onely: For he is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of euery good and perfecte gifte. It is one chefe operacion and working be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto his diuinitie, to graūt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs suche thinges as we doe aske and craue of hym. They therfore that dooe aske of other besydes hym, (somuche as is in them) dooe rob god of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="2"/> and diuinitie. It is written in the epistle of saynt Iames: If any of you want wisdom, let him aske of him that geueth it, that is of god. And god also by hys prophet Dauid exhorteth vs to make our prayers vnto him, his wordes be these: Cal vpon me in the day of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion, and I will delyuer the. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to thys saynt Paule sayeth: How shall they call vppon him, in whom they beleue not. Therfore we cannot call on hym for help but in whome we dooe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue: we cannot beleue that oure peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions shalbe graunted, excepte we be steyed vpon some promise made vnto vs in the scripture. The promyse in scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as concernyng our peticions to be graunted, is made by the father only, &amp; that in the name of Christ: wherfore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him only oure prayers is to be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Furthermore this is to be noted in prayer, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we must pray with our hartes and mindes, not onely with our lippes, &amp; our toung. For yf we do: we may well be compared vnto the Iewes, vnto whō our sauiour Christ sayde: o ye hipocrites Esaie the prophet hath prophecied well of you, saying: This peopell draweth nere vnto me w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there mouth, &amp; they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="3"/> me with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyppes, but theyr heart is far from me. Let vs call to our remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce the example of Anna mother of Samuel, whiche prayed vehemently vnto god, and her peticion was heard &amp; graunted, &amp; yet she spake not one word with her toung: But powred furth the whole sorow &amp; anguyshe of her mynde afore god. And god sayde vnto Moises, wherfore doest thou crye vnto me whē Moyses spake nothing with his toung, but w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his hart. Therfore in our praiers let vs lift vp our heartes vnto God, earnestly desyring those thinges, that we haue most nede of: se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating our mindes frō all cares and desyres of the worlde, &amp; the fleshe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>