<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE
TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107577_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4747</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107577</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE
TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The originall of idolatries: or, The birth of heresies : a true, sincere, and exact description of all such sacred signes, sacrifices, and sacraments as haue been instituted and ordained of God since Adam; with the true source and liuely anatomy of the sacrifice of the Masse. First faithfully gathered out of sundry Greeke and Latine authors, as also out of diuers learned fathers; by that famous and learned Isaac Casaubon, and by him published in French, for the good of Gods Church: and now translated into English for the benefit of this monarchy; by Abraham Darcie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE
TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most courteous Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering the Controuersies and bloudy hatred grown
betwixt those (who professe themselues Christians)
about Religion, for they aspiring to retaine these vaine
superstitions proceeding from their predecessors: and
many also not contented, do inuent new Sects, Schismes
and Heresies: Others (least in number) diuinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired,
and of God elocted, desire to extirpate the Darknesse of Ignorance,
thereby to cause resplendently to shine, the Light, and claritie of Truth:
But it seemes, that the most dangerous Poyson that Satan vseth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicate
men with the Venym of sedition, and cruell contention and hatred,
deriues chiefly from the Masse, desguised with some good meaning, mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
and couered (peraduenture) with a good intention. And although
that many heretofore haue by sundry faithfull descriptions endeueured
to discouer to the world the deceitfulnes, error, and blindnesse thereof,
yet could they not preuailc, nor giue light to their duskish and heauy
sight.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Therefore now, without any passion, I haue faithfully extracted, and
liuely drawne out, from the Volumes of</hi> ELASOPOLITAN'S
COMMENT ARIES: (It is a large &amp; faithfull description;
whereof the second Volume treates of the Constitutions of great
Pontiss, Soueraigne Priests, and Sacrificers, as haue been ordained
since the beginning of the World, and their true Number Power,
Riches and Authority; (all for thy only benefit) <hi>this sincere Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of the</hi> Sacrifice, <hi>called</hi> The Masse.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
In this Treatise (though little in appearance) are designed and set
downe all such <hi>Sacred Signes, Sacrifices, and Sacraments</hi> ordained of
<hi>GOD</hi> from time to time: As also the <hi>Corruptions</hi> that haue grown
successiuely in the <hi>Church of GOD:</hi> whereby I doe euidently shew
the birth of all <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Idolatries,</hi> and especially the true Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
of the <hi>Masse;</hi> for the which the world is in great strifes, bloudy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,
cruell Diuisions, Hatred, and lamentable Ciuile Warres: for
some do <hi>Inuectiuate &amp; Inueigh</hi> against it, alleaging that it is newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised
and inueuted; others defend it by prescription, and long possession; and
thus by such like altercations the Christian Church is sore afflicted with
the yoke and <hi>Terror</hi> of <hi>Sedition.</hi> But if thou art a <hi>Christian</hi> (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
Reader) of what Sect soeuer, <hi>Papist,</hi> or <hi>Euangelicall;</hi> I pray thee
heartily, for thy owne good, to haue patience to reade this Worke; for by
it thou mayest euidently know, and plainely discouer the very trueth of
what soeuer thou standest in doubt of, what Sacrifices, Sacraments, and
Sacred Signes haue beene instituted of <hi>GOD</hi> since <hi>Adam;</hi> what is the
Masse and Originall thereof; who were her Founders, Augmenters,
and Inuenters; and to the end thou mayest firmely beleeue with assurance,
all the Contents herein mentioned, haue recourse to those Authors out of
whose Bookes and Workes I haue drawne and deriued it: their Names
and Bookes are quoted in the Margent. So ayming at <hi>GODS</hi>
glory and thy owne Benefit, I rest with my prayers to <hi>GOD.</hi>
to inspire thee with his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> by the intercession
of our onely <hi>Sauiour, Redeemer,</hi> and <hi>Mediatour</hi>
IESVS CHRIST. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>