<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ADVISE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107544_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17889</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4554</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ADVISE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The spirituall director disinteressed : According to the spirit of B. Francis of Sales, Bishop and Prince of Geneua, Institutor of the Order of the Visitation of our Bl. Lady. By the most Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus, Bishope of Belley. Translated out of French by A.B</title>
                 <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Blageart, Francoise</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 660 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>ADVISE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>OTH in the begining, and in the end of this booke, I render à reason, ample enough, of the subiect which gaue it birth; And I satisfie (me thinkes) the obiectiōs which may be made against many points therin by me handled, which might haue serued for matter, and ornament to à preface. I touch here many nice and delicate strings, the euent wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will proue as it shall please the diuine Prouidence. I cannot war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it, I may onely here assure in words of veritie, and Charitie, not fayned; that my intention was
<pb facs="5"/> sincere, and without passion, in composing this worke, and that I rather thought therby to serue God in my neigbour, then to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice any. This is onely as it were à Commentary vpon the third Chap: of the first part of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lothea of my B. Father Francis of Sales, Bishop of Geneua; and though I giue à Carreere large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough vnto my spirit, suffering it to runne into the Christian libertie of its thoughts, I beleeue neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, not to haue swarued from the <hi>conceipts</hi> of this holie Prelat, from whose mouth, I haue her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore heard things which had euen as much quicknes, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, (not to saie rigour) as those which I here produce, albeit he had milke, and honny vnder the tongue, and that his words, no lesse then his manners were steeped
<pb facs="5"/> in an incomparable sweetnes. If I mingle here wine with oyle in imitation of the good Samatitan, it is to heale the wounds which haue neede of this dressing, and where suauitie ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaigned with à wholsome bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes. My principall intention in this litle worke is, to furnish deuout soules with à touchstone to discerne the true from the false Directour, by the marke of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, of his Dis-interessed Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. I here set downe artes to know the pure alloie, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish it from the sophisticall, to the end we may become good <hi>coyners</hi> according to the counsell which some auntient Fathers saie to haue flowed from the mouth of our lord. To giue assistance to this choise, I framed this addresse; Choise of so much importance, as
<pb facs="6"/> there are few practises in the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life which in necessity sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe it. I present vnto thee here, READER, neere sighted spectacles to see things at à small distance, which thou peraduēture hast neuer well perceaued by reason of their remotenes, there being question of many acts, for the most part hidden, and diuerted from the knowledge of the vulgar. Reade this without other Interest, then the glorie of God, and thy salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and without respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons by à preocupate opinion; and when thou shalt haue mett, in à Directour, with the qualities which I note vnto thee in this booke, feare not to commit thy barke, to the guidance of such à Pilot; For doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse vnder the winde of heauenly grace, he will cause it to arriue at the hauen of saluation, &amp; immortality.
<pb facs="6"/> To conclude, I submit with all my hart, both this treatise, and all those which haue, or may issue, by the assistance of God, from my spirit, and from my pen, vnto the iudgement, and to the correction, not onely of the holie Church▪ and of her visible Head, the chiefe Bishop, but also of her Doctours▪ whom I reuerence as my Maisters.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>