<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107365_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4318</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107365</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Dutch suruay : VVherein are related and truly discoursed, the chiefest losses and acquirements, which haue past betweene the Dutch and the Spaniards, in these last foure yeares warres of the Netherlands, with a comparatiue ballancing and estimation of that which the Spaniards haue got in the Dutchies of Cleeue and Iuliers, with that which they haue lost vnto the Dutch and Persians, in Brasilia, Lima, and Ormus. VVhereunto are annext the Mansfeldian motiues, directed vnto all colonels, lieuzanant-colonels, sergeant majors, priuate captaines, inferiour officers and souldiers, whose seruice is engag'd in this present expedition, vnder the conduct and commaund of the most illustrious Prince Ernestus, Earle of Mansfield</title>
                 <author>W. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, thou maist behold
in this discourse a true Suruay of
those more remarkable losses and
acquirements which haue past be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
the Dutch and the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,
since the expiration of the
last truce, which ended with the
beginning of the yeare 1621. Thou maist behold also a
true counterpoise or comparatiue ballancing of the same,
wherein it doth most plainely appeare, that the Dutch
haue not onely not beene loosers in these latter and time
neerer warres of the Netherlands, but for diuers ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantageous
respects, haue beene victorious against their
potent and most redoubted Enemies, who vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable
pretence of the Burgonian Title, sought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe
the liberties of these Countries, contrarie to the
auncient customes, freedomes, and priuiledges of the
same. To this relation is annexed a briefe encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
vnto all those, who either as voluntaries or by way
of Imprest, are ingage in this expedition of Count
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Mansfield.</hi> In the censure of both these, let thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
be milde and fauourable, and not according to the
common Current of the disaffected and Spaniolized
English, whose reports are so farre from truth &amp; equity
in these and other traditions, that they wholy encline to
partiality and detraction: For my part I know the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
and integritie of my owne thoughts, and how free
they are from any bending inclination or report, being
vnwilling that any knowne truth, though it were in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
the Diuell his due, should be wronged by any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous
or counterfeit adumbrations. The conscience of
this, armes me against the danger of their malicious aia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations,
and makes me hopefull of the impartiall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
best construction, which if I may obtaine, I
shall for euer rest happy for this their
good estimation.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>