<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           <author>Darcie, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107577_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4747</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107577</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 <author>Darcie, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The originall of idolatries: or, The birth of heresies : a true, sincere, and exact description of all such sacred signes, sacrifices, and sacraments as haue been instituted and ordained of God since Adam; with the true source and liuely anatomy of the sacrifice of the Masse. First faithfully gathered out of sundry Greeke and Latine authors, as also out of diuers learned fathers; by that famous and learned Isaac Casaubon, and by him published in French, for the good of Gods Church: and now translated into English for the benefit of this monarchy; by Abraham Darcie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>MOST ILLVSTRIOVS,
RIGHT HONORABLE,
RIGHT WORTHY,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O HONORS can bee comparable to those,
which GOD most graciously returnes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, who constantly in this WORLD,
aduance the true HONOR of his NAME,
and confidently maintaine, against all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions,
his sacred Verity and Truth. This fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
MONARCHY hath alwayes, as vpon so many firme and
Noble Pillars, committed the earthly foundation of GODS
Church and flocke, to the Religious care and Honourable
supportations of her Noble Peeres, out of which number,
you are such Patrons, as haue euer manifested a rare and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
protection of GODS vnspotted Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship:
but in your late HONOVRABLE employments in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
parts, vnder our Illustrious PRINCE, they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
a more apparent testimony of your true HEARTS
RELIGION and ZEALE, when soiourning for a time, (as one
may say) in the very Tents of KEDAR, and beholding with
your bodily eyes, many superstitious Idolatries, you yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb facs="7"/>
firme and vnshaken, the treasure of a sincere faith, and
inuiolable conscience, hauing conueniently
<q>—L'OEVIL AV GVET,</q>
the eye at his sight-hole, (as our French Prouerbe termes
it) the better to discerne of all obiects, and with the surer
ayme, to leuell all your Honourable Actions, and worthy
designes.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt but your Noble selues mette with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Oppositions and Encounters, by way of discussion and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument:
But the Scripture being a Test &amp; quadrant, by which
they are not willing to trie, or square their proceedings, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
CASAVBON hath made a diligent search &amp; Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
of their owne Registers, and Records, and chiefly out
of the Volumes of the Commentaries of ELASOPOLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAN,
whereas by the direction of a Diuine hand, may bee
found out the Birth and Originall of all adulterous and
strange Adoration, from the first ADAM, to these our later
times, but especially the Sacrifice of the ROMANE MASSE,
is here most learnedly delineated to true life, from the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
and infancie thereof, till now that it hath made so great
and perillous a progression.</p>
   <p>The AVTHORS are nominated the seuerall parcels set
downe, as they were in seuerall AGES annexed, the perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous
difference betwixt it, and the infallible forme of the
Apostolicall, and Primitiue CHRISTIAN worship is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained,
with whatsoeuer else that meere HVMANE TRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DITION
&amp; INVENTION hath vniustly vsurped, ouer Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall,
and vnspoated true seruice in the CHVRCH OF
GOD. So as clearely discerning the Scandals, the Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizers
likewise are as plainely reuealed, and this Christian
<hi>Domus deuisa in se:</hi> Out of my humble and dutifull affection,
<pb facs="8"/>
I could not but commend this excellent Treatise, to your
Honourable viewes, and learned censure, the which I haue
studiously expressed in the English Tongue, principally to
manifest vnto all your Lorships, my seruiceable and grateful
heart, both to euery one of your Honours in particular, as
also to this happy Kingdome in generall, to whose boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and protection I stand deepely oblieged; and as he,
whose thoughts haue no higher scopes nor
ayme, then iustly to bee reputed.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>YOVR GRACE,
YOVR HONORS,
and YOVR WORTHINES,
Most faithfull, and humbly deuoted,
ABRAHAM DARCIE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>