<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107411_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4537</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107411</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true reporte of the death &amp; martyrdome of M. Campion Iesuite and preiste, &amp; M. Sherwin, &amp; M. Bryan preistes, at Tiborne the first of December 1581 Observid and written by a Catholike preist, which was present therat Wheruuto [sic] is annexid certayne verses made by sundri persons</title>
                 <author>Alfield, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Verstegan (Rowlands), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>AMongst the diuers reportes of the behavior of M Campion, M. Sherwin, &amp; M Bryā at their death (passing among freindes from hand to hand) I hapned vpon one ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven out as it seemeth by a Catholike priest, who as it apereth pressed to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serue &amp; marke those dealings: which report I have here published, cōside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the divers &amp; many slaunders rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed since by some maliciously blinded to satisfie &amp; content all such as do desire to vnderstand the manner of the same: I hope that consideration which hath movid me hereto, wil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so perswade that priest to the wel li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this my doing? &amp; I dout not but that the relation it self will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the reader throughly touching their words, and behaviour at the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of execution, Notwithstanding those slaunders which were since sp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to diminish the honour of their refolute departure &amp; Martirdome, as that M Campion was timerous and fearfull, &amp; that M Sherwin died a
<pb facs="3"/>
protestant, with other such false re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes, as thov shalt see in pervsing this short relation here exhibitid for thy satisfaction: wherin is a lively I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of resolute martirs, constantly professing their faith &amp; belief, resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly disclaming from all treasons and treacheryes falslie intendid againste them: and loyaly behaving them se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues towards our queene &amp; country. Who as they were in their lives lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of piety &amp; vertue, so in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athes made themselves paternes and examples for all good christian sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes to follow.</p>
   <p>And here by the way I might point out M. Elmers folly, as not one of the least, who notwithstanding the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen lerning of M. Campion (he him selfe a man of knowen wisedome, &amp; iudgement,) was not ashamed, at a Sessions at Newgate, vpon the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Cutler of Holborne, to say openly, that M Campion was vnlern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, and that a Note booke or two of his felowes being taken from him, he had nothing in him, as it was manifest in his disputations in the
<pb facs="3"/>
Tower. Further that al the Papistes in the worlde coulde not answere Whitakers booke against the saide M Campion. Which his censure, I referre vnto the iudgement of the lerned discret and wise, who I know do condemne the babbling of that barren declaymer, as voyde of witte, discretion, lerning, modestie, &amp; truth. But howe friuolous and vayne these slaunders are, although the whole world (filled nowe with the fame of his lerning) doth know, yet it shal be made more manifest and apparant euen vnto him selfe by those Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations had in the Tower, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of M Campion and furthering of his cause, at suche time as by the grace of God they shal be published. This rehearsal (good Reader) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse is impertinent to the purposse of that Preist who gaue out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port folowing, and yet I thought it not altogether amisse to touch those slaunders so false and malicious, as many good Gentlemen can not but confesse. Muche more M Elmer spake that day, as he thought, to the
<pb facs="4"/>
discredite of M. Campion, but I pray God giue him better consideration both of this and of further iustice, and so shall the poore Poulter at his nexte complaynt be heard, euen of himself, beeing as he himself said, a Bishop, a Lorde, and of some credite Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>