<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107449_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14174</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14308</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107449</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eternall truth of scriptures, and Christian beleefe, thereon vvholly depending, manifested by it owne light : Deliuered in two bookes of commentaries vpon the Apostles creede: the former, containing the positiue grounds of Christian religion in generall, cleared from all exceptions of atheists or infidels. The later, manifesting the grounds of reformed religion to be so firme and sure, that the Romanist cannot oppugne them, but with the vtter ouerthrow of the Romish Church, religion, and faith. By Thomas Iackson, Bachellar of Diuinitie, and fellow of Corpus-Christi Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 479, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Gnorant altogether I am not of the disposition, though not much acquainted with the practises of this present age: wherein, to haue meditated vpon so many seuerall matters as I heere present vnto thy Christian view, will vnto some (I know) seeme but an effect of melancholie, as to haue taken the paines to pen them, will argue my want of other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, or forlorne hopes of worldly thriuing. Vnto others (and those more to be regarded) so soone in print to publish what had beene not so well concocted, and more rawly penned, will be censured as a spice of that vanitie which vsually haunts smatterers in good learning, but wherewith iudicious Clearks are seldome infected. To the former, I only wish mindes more setled, or lesse conscience of their owne extrauagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and carelesse mispence of choicest time, faults apt to breed a mislike of others industrie in such courses as will approue themselues in his sight that sits as Iudge and trier of all our waies, howsoeuer such as desire to be meere by-standers as well in Church as Common-wealthes affaires, may vpon sinister respects, mutually misinforme themselues. For many of the later, I am afraid, least, being partly such and so esteemed, they prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterously affect not to be takē for more iudicious scholers then indeed they are: for the fostering of which conceit in others, their vnwillingnesse to publish what they haue conceiued aright, may well be apprehended as a meanes not improbable. Not to expose their meditations to publike censure, is and hath beene (as the Christian world too well can witnesse) a resolution incident to men of greatest iudgement: though no such es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiall propertie, as necessarily argues, eyther all so minded to be, or all otherwise minded, not to be, alike iudicious. Certaine it is, the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent the internall feature of mens minds is, the greater disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them will an ordinarie representation of it bee, and to adorne their choice conceits with such outward attire as best beseemes them,
<pb facs="4"/> would require too great costes and charges. Thus from perfection oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times springs defect: whilest iudgement, too much ouergrowing fancie, and drying vp that kinde affection, whereby the fruit and vertue of one soule is diffused vnto another, makes men more iealous of diminishing the high estimate of their foreprized worth, then zealous of their infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours good, which many times might be reaped in greatest abundance from such labours as yeeld least contentment to their Authors. In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect alone can I gratulate my imperfections: hoping that as my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can neither please the delicate, for their forme, nor informe the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious for their matter: so they may proue neither offensiue for the one, nor vnfruitfull for the other, vnto many of a middle and inseriour ranke.</p>
   <p>At the least (I trust) they will occasion some others, whom God hath bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with better abilitie and opportunitie, to hunt that out which in this long range I may chance to start, or make full conquest of that goodly field wherein that inestimable pearle lies hid, for whose discouerie these my trauels may happily yeeld some obseruations not impertinent. To this end haue I purposely trained my wits to vntroden pathes, to aduenture on new passages, vnto that true treasure which all of vs trafficke for, oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one to anothers hindrance, the more because wee beate one place too much, when as many others might affoord vs the same or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter commodities better cheape. Though the truth be one: yet it is not alwaies of one shape, whiles we looke vpon it diuers waies. The mine wherein it lies, is inexhaustible; oft times more full of drosse and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidge, where most haue digged: and, though the inward substance of it be the same, yet the refining of it admits varietie of inuentions. Doe not preiudice me (charitable Reader) so much as in thy secret censure, as if these premises might seeme to argue my dissent in any conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which our Church professeth: the euent (I trust) shall acquit mee, and condemne all my accusers, if any I haue; and how I stand affected in points of spirituall obedience to my superiours, thou mayest be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, if it please thee but to peruse some few sheetes of these my first fruites, which I presume thou wilt, surely thou oughtest, ere thy censure passe vpon me. If in the explication of some points I ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accord not with some well esteemed domesticke writers: I trust <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> free borne children may enioy that priuiledge amongst themselues, which is permitted the sonnes of <hi>Hagar,</hi> in respect of their brethren, though all absolute bondmen to their mother. Yet that I doe not thus
<pb facs="4"/> farre dissent from any of my mothers children, vpon emulation or humour of contradiction, thou wilt rest satisfied vpon my sincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious protestation, That the whole fabricke of this intended worke was set, and euery maine conclusion resolued vpon, before I read any English writer vpon the arguments which I handle. From some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed which had written before me, I haue since perceiued a direct dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in one or two points of moment; but wherein they had (in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) contradicted the most iudicious writers of our Church and all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie I am acquainted with, more rashly, then I would doe the meanest this day liuing. Yet shall they, or whosoeuer of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, finde the manner of my disputing with them, such as shall not (I trust) exasperate, howsoeuer the dissonance of matter may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like them. For outlandish or forraine Latine writers, I must inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niously confesse, when I first laboured to bee instructed in the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall principles of faith and manners, some points which I much wished, I found they had not handled, in others, wherein I misliked no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as vnsound, I could not alwaies finde that full satisfaction, which (me thought) a more accurate Artist (for a meane one I was then my selfe) would require. The greater since hath beene my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire eyther of giuing, or by my attempt, of procuring satisfaction. But will not others, when I haue done my best, so thinke and say of mine, as I haue done of these much better indeauours? It were great arrogance to expect any lesse. Notwithstanding, if what they shall finde defectiue in my labours, moue them to no worse patience, then what I thought (at least) was so in theirs that euery way goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee, hath done mee: nor I, nor they, nor the Church of Christ, (by this meanes paitaker, and free to dislike or approue of both our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours) shall (I trust) haue any great cause to repent vs of our paines. For thy better satisfaction, I will acquaint thee with the particulars which moued mee to write.</p>
   <p>First, in vnfolding the nature and properties of Christian faith, to omit the errours of the Romish church, (wherein it is impossible it should euer come to full grouth,) many in reformed, too much fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in particular Sermons, did striue to ripen it too fast. I haue heard complaints immediately from the mouthes of some yet liuing, of others deceased, that they had beene set too farre in their first Lessons: that the hopes they had out of hand directly built vpon GODS generall promises applied to them by their instructours,
<pb facs="5"/> were too waightie, vnlesse the foundations of their faith had first beene more deepely and surely planted. That certainty of iustification and full perswasion of inherent sanctifying grace, whereat these worthies (whose footsteps I precisely tracke not) ayme, is (I protest) the marke which I propose vnto my selfe, but cannot hope at the first shoote to hit; if at the second, third, or fourth (as shall please God,) it must content me. In the meane time (I hope) I shall neither offend him, nor any of his, as long as I gather ground of what I prosecute, and still come nearer &amp; nearer the proposed end. The first step, me thought, that tended most directly to this certaine apprehension of sauing faith, was our vndoubted assent vnto the diuine truth of Scriptures in generall: and for the working of this assurance, meanes subordinate I could conceiue none better for the kinde (particulars others happily may finde more forcible,) then such as I haue prosecuted at large in the first booke: not ignorant, that such as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me more, might moue others lesse, those euery man most, that were of his owne gathering, wherein the disposition of the diuine prouidence (alwaies concurrent to this search, so men would marke it) is most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous. For this purpose I haue proposed such varietie of obseruations, as almost euery one able to read the Scriptures or other authors, of what sort or profession soeuer, students especially, may bee occasioned to make the like themselues, well hoping to finde a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>thode as facile and easie for establishing the assent of the simple, and altogether illiterate, vnto those articles, whose distinct explicit knowledge is most necessary to saluation. But many (I know) will deeme the broken traditions, or imperfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of heathen men (for these I vse,) but weake supporters for so great an edifice: nor did I intend them for such seruice. Their ignorance notwithstanding, and darkned minds, doe much commend the light of diuine truth so may the experience of their vanitie dispose our minds to embrace the stabilitie of Gods word with greater stedfastnesse. We know the vertue and benefit of the Sunne, not so much by looking vpon it selfe continually or directly, as by the varietie of other obiects or colours, all pleasant with it to the eye, but altogether inuisible or indistinguishable without it: so for mine owne part, I must professe, that such historicall narrations, poeticall fictions, or other conceits of Heathens as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues knew little vse of, nor should I haue done had I beene as they were, being compared with this heauenly light of Gods word, did much affect me euen in my best and most retired meditations of sacred mysteries, their obseruation, as it were, tied my soule by a new knot, or fest, more surely
<pb facs="5"/> vnto that truth, which I knew before to be in it selfe most sure, most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. Yea euen in points wherein my heart, vnto my seeming, was best established, it much did nourish, augment, and strengthen beleefe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die planted, to obserue the perfect consonancie of profane, with sacred writers, or the occasions of their dissonancy, to be euidently such, as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures specifie: that of many euents wondred at by their heathenish rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, no tolerable reason could be giuen, but such as are subordinate to the neuer-failing rules of Scripture. And whosoeuer will, may (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume) obserue by experiment, the truth of what I say. There is no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto beleefe so weake or feeble, but may be very auailable for quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling temptations of some kinde or other, eyther in speculation or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, oft-times such as are absolutely more weake or feeble, more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for expelling some peculiar distrust or presumption, then others farre more forcible and strong for vanquishing temptations of another kinde, in nature most grieuous. Many, halfe students, halfe gallants, are often tempted eyther to distrust the commendatiōs of this Eden which we are set to dresse, or distast the food of life that grows within it, from delights sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested by profane bookes, wherewith commonly they are first acquainted, and hence much affect the knowledge their Authors profer, as likely to deifie them in the worlds eyes. Our pronenesse to be thus perswaded, is a witnesse of our first parents transgression, and these suggestions as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of Sathans baites, whereby he wrought their bane. But what is the remedie? not to tread in any heathenish soile, least these serpents sting vs? rather the best medicine for this maladie would be a confection of that very flesh wherein such deadly poyson lodged. Other arguments may more perswade the iudicious, or such as in some measure haue tasted the fruits of the spirit: But none the curious artist better, then such as are gathered from his esteemed Authors Euen such as are in faith most strong, of zeale most ardent, should not much mispend their time, in comparing the degenerate fictions or historicall relations of times anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent or moderne, with the euerlasting truth. For, though this methode could not adde much increase, eyther to their faith, or zeale: yet would it doubtlesse much auaile for working placide and milde affections. The very penmen of sacred writ themselues were taught patience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in the waies of Gods prouidence, by their experience of such euents as the course of time is neuer barren of, not alwaies related by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Authors, nor immediately testified by the spirit, but oft-times beleeued vpon a morall certaintie, or such a resolution of circumstances
<pb facs="6"/> concurrent into the first cause or disposer of all affaires, as wee might make of moderne accidents, were we otherwise partakers of the Spirit, or would we minde heauenly matters as much as earthly.</p>
   <p>Generally two points I haue obserued, not much for ought I know, if handled at all by any writer: albeit their fruite and vse would fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence the best paines of any one mans life-time, though wholly spent in their discussion, whose want in my mind hath beene the bane of true deuotion in most ages. The first is an equiualencie of means in the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God so proportioned to the diuersity of times, as no age could haue better then the present, howsoeuer they may affect the extraordinarie signes and wonders of former generations. Of this argument here and there, as occasion shall serue in this worke; elswhere at large, if God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. The second is an equiualencie of errours, hypocrisie, infidelitie, and idolatry, all which varie rather their shape then substance, in most men, through ages, nations, and professions, the ignorance of God remaining for the most part the same, his attributes as much (though in another kinde) transformed by many in outward profession ioyned with the true Church, as in times past by the heathen. The truth of which assertion, with the originall causes of the error, &amp; means to preuent it, are discus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at large in the article of the Godhead. Many likewise for ought their consciēce (because not rightly examined) wil witnesse to the contrary, are strongly perswaded they loue Christ with heart &amp; soule, and so detest as well the open blasphemy or professed hatred, which the Iew; as the secret enmity the Iesuit or other infamous heretiks, beare against him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen as oft-times the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y ground of their loue to him, is their spite to some or all of these, as they are deciphered to thē in odious shape, the only originall of their despite to these, the very dregs of Iewish, Popish, or other hereticall humors in thēselues, by some light tincture of that truth which they out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly professe, exasperated to more bitter enmity against them with whose internall tēper they best agree, then otherwise they could conceiue; as admission to place of credit or authoritie makes b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se minds, conscious of their own forepast villanies, more rigid censurers of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hers misdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, or cruell persecutors of such malefactors as thēselues in action haue beene, &amp; in heart yet are (were all occasions and opportunities the same) then any moderate or syncere man in life &amp; action could be. Of the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of this disease, with the crises &amp; remedy, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> also the triall of faith inherent, in the articles concerning Christ and remission of sinnes.</p>
   <p>From the manner of Ierusalēs progresse to her first destruction, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of the Iews naturall temper (the principal subiect of my subcisiue
<pb facs="6"/> or vacant houres from these meditations &amp; other necessary imployments of my calling) I haue obserued the originall as well of most states as mens miscarriages professing true religion, to haue bin from presumption of Gods fauour before dangers approch, &amp; distrust of his mercy after cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities seaze vpon thē: the root of both these misperswasions to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or error in the doctrine of Gods prouidence, whose true knowledge (if I may so speak) is the fertile womb of all sacred moral truths, the only rule of rectifying mens wils, perswasions &amp; affections, in all consultatiōs or practises priuat or publik. Vnto this purpose much would it auaile to be resolued, whether all things fal out by fatal necessity, or some contingētly; how fate &amp; contingency (if cōpatible each with other) stand mutually af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, how both subordinate to the absolute immutability of that one euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting decree. Want of resolutiō in these points (as far as my obseruation serues me) hath continually bred an vniuersal threefold want: of care &amp; vigilancy for preuenting dangers in thēselues auoidable: of alacrious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauors to redeeme time in part surprised by them; of patience, of hearty submissiō to Gods will, &amp; constant expectation of his prouidence, after all hope of redēption from tēporal plagues long threatned by his messengers, is past. For here we suppose (what out of the fundamētal principles of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian religiō shal in good time be made euidēt) that in all ruinated states or forepast alterations of religiō from better to worse, there was a time wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in the possibility of misfortunes which afterwards befell thē, might haue bin preuēted, a time wherin they might haue bin recouered frō eminent dangers, wherewith they were encompast, a time after which there was no possibility left them of auoiding the day of visitation, neuer brought forth but by the precedent fulnesse of iniquity, but alwaies necessarily by it. In the discussion of these &amp; other points of like nature (because more depending vpon strict examination of consequences deduced from the vndoubted rules of Scripture, then vpon authorities of antiquity, skil in the tongues, or any other learning that required long experience or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation) I laboured most, whilst those arts and sciences which are most conducible to this search, were freshest in my memory. And could I hope to satisfie others in all or most of these, as fully as I haue long since done my selfe, I should take greatest pleasure in my pains addressed to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. But would it please the Lord in mercy to raise vp some English writer, that could in such sort handle these points, as their vse and consequence, or necessitie of present times requires: succeeding ages (I am perswaded) should haue more cause to blesse the day of his natiuitie, then of the greatest States-mens or stoutest warriours this land hath
<pb facs="7"/> yeelded since the birth of our Fathers this day liuing. It shall suffice me to beginne the offering with my mite, in hope some learned Academicks (for vnto them belongs the conquest of this golden fleece) will imploy their talents to like publike vse. What I conceiue, shall be (by Gods assistance) vnfolded in as plaine and vnoffensiue termes, as the nature of the subiect will beare, or my faculties reach vnto, partly in the Article of Gods prouidence, partly in other discourses directly subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate vnto it.</p>
   <p>Lastly, for the full and perfect grouth, at least for the sweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant flourishing of liuely faith, one of the most effectuall meanes our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie that can but plant or water, attaines vnto, would bee to vnfold the harmonie betwixt propheticall predictions and historicall euents concerning the kingdome of Christ, and time of the Gospell: a point, for ought I know, not purposely handled by any moderne writer, except those whose successe cannot be great, vntill their delight in contention and contradiction be lesse. Notwithstanding, whatsoeuer I shall finde good in them or any other, without all respect of persons, much more without all desire of opposition, or occasion of contention (a matter alwaies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent in a Christian, but most odious and loathsome in a Subiect so me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious and pleasant,) I will not be afraid to follow, intending a full Trea-tise of the diuers kindes of prophecies, with the manner of their interpretations, before the Articles of Christs Incarnation, Passion, and Ascension.</p>
   <p>These are the especiall points, which for the better confirmation of true Christian faith, and rectifying perswasions in matters of manners or good life, are principally aymed at in these meditations. The maine obstacle the Atheist stumbles at, is the Article of the bodies resurrection. Whose passiue possibilitie shall by (Gods assistance) be euidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated against him by the vndoubted rules of nature, whose Priest or Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nister he professeth himselfe to be. That <hi>de facto</hi> it shall be, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whose truth ere then will appeare diuine, must assure vs; Nature cannot, though thus much were in some sort knowne and beleeued by many naturall men from traditions of the ancient, or suspected from some notions of the law of nature not quite obliterated in all sorts of the heathen, as shall in that Article (God willing) be obserued. But why our assent vnto this and all other Articles in this Creed, being in good measure established, the momentarie hopes or transitorie pleasures of this world, should with most in their whole course of life, with all of vs
<pb facs="7"/> in many particular actions in priuate and secret temptations, more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, then that exceeding waight of glorie, which Christian hope would fasten on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> soules, to keepe vnrulie affections vnder, hath often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced mee to wonder, and wonderment hereat first moued me to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake these labours, if by any meanes I may attaine vnto the causes of this so grieuous an infirmitie, or finde out some part of a remedie for it. Doubtlesse, had the heathen Philosophers but knowne or suspected such ioyes as we professe we beleeue and hope for, or such a death, or more then deadly torments, as after this life ended we might feare; their liues and manners would as farre haue surpassed the best Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now liuing, as their knowledge in supernaturall mysteries came short of the most learned that are or haue beene in that profession: and yet whatsoeuer helpes any Christian or heathen had for increasing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or bettering manners, are more plentifull in this then any precedent age, so that the fault is wholly in our selues, that will not apply medicines alreadie prepared, as shall (God prospering these procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings) be declared in the last Article of this Creed.</p>
   <p>For controuersies betwixt vs and the Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh Church, beside such as are directly opposite to the end and methode proposed, I purposely meddle with none: of that ranke, some (as that of the Churches infallibilitie) vndermine the verie foundation, others (as the doctrine of merite and iustification, the propitiation of the Masse) vnroofe the edifice, &amp; deface the walls of Christian faith, leauing nothing therof, but altar-stones for their Idolatrous sacrifices. For this reasō haue I built with one hand, &amp; vsed my weapon with the other: laying the positiue or generall grounds of faith against the Infidell or Atheist in the first booke, and guarding them in the second by the sword of the spirit, against all attempts of Romish <hi>Sanballets</hi> or <hi>Tobiahs,</hi> who stil labour to perswade our people, the walles of Christs Church heere erected since our fore fathers redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from captiuitie, vnlesse supported by their supposed infallibilitie, are so weake,<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>That if a Foxe should goe vpon them, he should breake them downe.</hi> In the third (which was at this time inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but must stay a while to bring forth a fourth) I batter those painted walles, whose shallow foundations are discouered in the second. The other controuersies about the propitiatorie sacrifices of the Masse, Merits, and Iustification, I prosecute in the Articles of Christs passion and of finall iudgement.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>By this (beloued Reader) thou maist perceiue my iourney is long, and may well plead my excuse for setting forth so soone: but from that course which I haue chosen, or rather God hath set me, I trust nor hopes of preferment, nor any desires of worldly wealth, nor affectation of popularitie, by handling more plausible or time-seruing arguments, shall euer draw me away. So farre I am from ayming at any such sinister end, that since I begun to comment vpon the nature of Christian faith, I neuer could, nor euer shall perswade my selfe it possibly cand finde quiet lodging, much lesse safe harbour, but in an heart alike affected to death and honour; alwaies retaining the desires, and feare of both (eyther se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally considered, or mutually compared) in equall ballance. Both are good when God in mercie sends them, both euill, and hard to determine whether worse, to vnprepared minds, or whilst procured by our sollici <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us or importuna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e suite, or bestowed vpon vs in their Donours anger. Only this diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rence I finde; death is mankinds ineuitable doome, but wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>y preferment neither so common to all, nor so certaine to any. the less<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in reason) should be our indeauours eyther for prouiding it, or preparing our selues to salute it decently, though comming of it owne accord to meete vs. But what meditations can be too long, or what indeauours too laborious for gaining of an happie end, or giuing a messenger of so importunate &amp; waightie consequence as death one way or other brings, correspondent entertainment? This Christian modestie I haue learned long since of the heathen <hi>Socrates,</hi> to beseech my God he would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe me such a portion of wealth, or whatsoeuer this world esteemes, as none but an honest, vpright, religious minde can beare: or, to vse the words of a better teacher, that of all my labours vnder the sunne, I may reape the fruit in holinesse, and in the end, the end of these my present medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, <hi>euerlasting life.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Christ,</hi> Thomas Iackson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>