<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Answere to the
PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107216_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18610</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5138</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107216</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Answere to the
PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The religion of protestants a safe vvay to salvation : Or An ansvver to a booke entitled Mercy and truth, or, charity maintain'd by Catholiques, which pretends to prove the contrary. By William Chillingworth Master of Arts of the University of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Chillingworth, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 413, 3 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="answer">
   <pb n="6" facs="20"/>
   <head>The Answere to the
PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the First, and Second.</hi> If beginings be omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
(as they say they are,) <hi>D. Potter</hi> hath cause
to look for great store of uningenuous dealing
from you; the very first words you speak of him
<hi>vz. That he hath not so much as once truly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
fallen upon the point in question,</hi> being a most
unjust and immodest imputation.</p>
   <p>2 For first, the point in question, was not, that
which you pretend, <hi>Whether both Papists and Protestants can be saved
in their severall Professions?</hi> But, <hi>Whether you may without uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
affirme that Protestancy unrepented destroyes Salvation?</hi> And
that this is the very question is most apparent and unquestionable,
both from the title of <hi>Charity Mistaken,</hi> and from the Arguments of
the three first Chapters of it, and from the title of your own Reply.
And therefore if <hi>D. Potter</hi> had joyned issue with his Adversary only
thus farre, and not medling at all with <hi>Papists,</hi> but leaving them to
<hi>stand or fall to their own master,</hi> had prou'd <hi>Protestants</hi> living and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
so <hi>capable of Salvation,</hi> I cannot see how it could justly be charged
upon him, that he <hi>had not once truly and really fallen upon the point in
Question.</hi> Neither may it be said that your Question here and mine,
are in effect the same, seeing it is very possible that the true Answere
to the one might have been Affirmative, and to the other Negative.
For there is no incongruity but it may be true <hi>That You and We cannot
both be saved:</hi> And yet as true, <hi>That without uncharitablenesse you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
pronounce us damned.</hi> For all ungrounded and unwarrantable sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencing
mento damnation, is either in a propriety of speech unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
or else (which for my purpose is all one,) it is that which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants
mean, when they say, Papists for damning them are uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
And therefore though the <hi>Author of C. M.</hi> had prov'd as strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
as he hath done weakly, <hi>that one Heaven could not receive Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
and Papists both,</hi> yet certainly, it was very hastily and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably,
&amp; therefore uncharitably concluded, that Protestants were
the part that was to be excluded. As, though Iewes and Christians can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
both be saved, yet a Iew cannot justly, and therefore not chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
pronounce a Christian damned.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="7" facs="20"/>
3 But then secondly, to shew your dealing with him very injurious;
I say he doth speak to this very Question very largely, and very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually;
as by confronting his worke and <hi>Charity Mist.</hi> together, will
presently appear. <hi>Charity M.</hi> proves you say in generall, <hi>That there
is but one Church. D. Potter</hi> tels him, <hi>His labour is lost in proving the
unity of the Catholique Church, whereof there is no doubt or controversy:</hi>
&amp; herein I hope you will grant he answeres right &amp; to the purpose. <hi>C.
M.</hi> proves (you say) secondly, <hi>That all Christians are obliged to harken
to the Church. D. Potter</hi> answeres, <hi>It is true: yet not absolutely in all
things, but only when she commands those things which God doth not
countermand.</hi> And this also I hope is to his purpose, though not to
yours. <hi>C. M.</hi> proves, you say thirdly, <hi>That the Church must be ever
visible and infallible.</hi> For her <hi>Visibility, D. Potter</hi> denyes it not; and as
for her <hi>Infallibility,</hi> he grants it in <hi>Fundamentalls</hi> but <hi>not in Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structures.</hi>
C. M. proves you say fourthly, <hi>That to separate ones selfe
from the Churches Communion, is schisme. D. Potter</hi> grants it, with this
exception, <hi>unlesse there be necessary cause to doe so;</hi> unlesse the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of her Communion be apparently unlawfull. C. M. proves, you
say lastly, <hi>That to dissent from her doctrine is heresy, though it be in
points never so few, and never so small, and therefore that the distinction
of points fundamentall and unfundamentall, as it is applyed by Protestants
is wholy vaine.</hi> This D. <hi>Potter</hi> denyes, shewes the Reasons, brought
for it, weak and unconcluding; proves the contrary by reasons unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable:
and therefore that <hi>The distinction of points into fundamentall
and not fundamentall, as it is applied by Protestants, is very good.</hi> Vpon
these grounds you say, C. M. cleerely evinces <hi>That any least difference
in faith cannot stand with salvation, and therefore seeing Catholiques
and Protestants disagree in very many points of faith, they both cannot
hope to be saved without Repentance,</hi> you must mean, without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit
and particular repentance, and dereliction of their errors; for so
C. M. hath declared himselfe p. 14. where he hath these words, <hi>We
may safely say that a man who lives in Protestancy, and who is so farre
from Repenting it, as that he will not so much as acknowledge it to be a
sinne, though he be sufficiently enform'd thereof, &amp;c.</hi> From whence it is
evident, that in his judgement there can be no repentance of an errour,
without acknowledging it to be a sinne: And to this <hi>D. Potter</hi> justly
opposes: <hi>That both sides, by the confession of both sides, agree in more
points then are simply and indispensably necessary to Salvation, and differ
only in such as are not precisely necessary: That it is very possible, a man
may dye in errour, and yet dye with Repentance, as for all his sinnes of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance▪
so in that number, for the errours in which he dies: with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
though not explicite and particular which is not simply requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
yet implicite and generall which is sufficient: so that he cannot but
hope considering the goodnesse of God, that the truth's retained on both
sides, especially those of the necessity of repentance from dead workes and
faith in Iesus Christ, if they be put in practise, may be an antidote against
the errors held on either side; to such he meanes, &amp; saies, as being diligent
in seeking truth, and desirous to find it, yet misse of it through humane
<pb n="8" facs="21"/>
frailty and dye in errour.</hi> If you will but attentively consider &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
the undertaking of C. M. and D. <hi>Potters</hi> performance in all these
points, I hope you will be so ingenuous as to acknowledge, that you
have injurd him much in imputing tergiversation to him, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
that <hi>through his whole book he hath not once truly and really fallen
upon the point in Question.</hi> Neither may you or C. M. conclude him
from hence (as covertly you doe,) <hi>An enemy to soules by deceiving them
with ungrounded false hopes of Salvation;</hi> seeing the hope of salvation
cannot be ungrounded, which requires and supposes beliefe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
of all things absolutely necessary unto salvation, and repentance
of those sinnes and errours which we fall into by humane frailty: Nor
a <hi>friend to indifferency in Religions,</hi> seeing he gives them only hope
of pardon of Errors who are desirous, and according to the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of their opportunities and abilities industrious to find the truth, or
at least truly repentant, that they have not been so. Which doctrine
is very fit to excite men to a constant and impartiall search of truth,
and very farre from teaching them that it is indifferent what Religion
they are of, and without all controversy very honourable to the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of God, with which how it can consist, not to be satisfied with
his servants true endeavours to know his will and doe it, without full
and exact performance, I leave it to you and all good men to judge.</p>
   <p>4 As little Iustice me thinkes you shew, in quarrelling with him for
descending to the particular disputes here mentioned by you. For to
say nothing that many of these Questions are immediatly and directly
pertinent to the businesse in hand, as the 1. 2. 3. 5. 6. and all of them
fall in of themselves into the stream of his discourse, and are not
drawn in by him, and besides are touched for the most part, rather
then handled; to say nothing of all this, you know right well, if he
conclude you erroneous in any one of all these, be it but in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
in one kind,</hi> or the <hi>Language of your service;</hi> the infallibility of
your Church is evidently overthrown: And this being done, I hope
there will be <hi>no such necessity of hearkning to her in all things: It will be
very possible to seperate from her communion in some things, without
schisme, and from her doctrine so farre as it is erroneous without here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy:
Then all that she proposes will not be, eo ipso, fundamentall, because
shee proposes it:</hi> and so presently all <hi>Charity Mistaken</hi> will vanish into
smoak, and clouds and nothing.</p>
   <p>5 You say <hi>he was loath to affirme plainly, that generally both Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques
&amp; Protestants may be saved:</hi> which yet is manifest he doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
plainly, of Protestants throughout his book; &amp; of erring Papists
that have <hi>syncerely sought the Truth and failed of it, and dye with a
generall repentance:</hi> p. 77. 78. And yet you deceive your selfe if you
conceive he had any other necessity to doe so, but only that he thought
it true. For we may and doe pretend that before <hi>Luther there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
true Churches, besides the Roman,</hi> which agreed not with her: in
particular, <hi>The greek Church.</hi> So that what you say is evidently true,
is indeed evidently false. Besides if he had had any necessity to make
use of you in this matter, he needed not for this end to say that now
<pb n="9" facs="21"/>
in your Church Salvation may be had; but onely that before <hi>Luthers</hi>
time it might be: Then when your meanes of knowing the Truth were
not so great, and when your ignorance might be more invincible, and
therefore more excusable. So that you may see if you please, it is not
for ends, but for the loue of truth, that we are thus charitable to you.</p>
   <p>6 Neither is it materiall that these particulars he speakes against, are
not <hi>fundamentall errours;</hi> for though they be not <hi>destructiue of salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
yet the convincing of them, may be, and is <hi>destructiue enough of his
Adversaries assertion:</hi> and if you be the man I take you for, you will
not deny they are so. For certainly no Consequence can be more pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
then this; The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth erre in this or that, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it is not infallible. And this perhaps you perceiu'd your selfe; &amp;
therefore demanded not, <hi>Since they be not fundamentall, what imports
it whether we hold them or no, simply:</hi> But, <hi>for as much as concernes our
possibility to be saved.</hi> As if we were not bound by the loue of God &amp;
the loue of truth to be zealous in the defence of all Truths, that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
way profitable, though not simply necessary to salvation. Or as if
any good man could satisfie his conscience without being so affected
and resolv'd. Our Saviour himselfe having assur'd us,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5. 19.</note> That <hi>hee that
shall breake one of his least Commandements</hi> (some whereof you
pretend are concerning veniall sinnes, and consequently the keeping of
them not necessary to salvation) <hi>and shall so teach men, shall be called the
least in the kingdome of Heaven.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>7 But then it imports very much, though not for the <hi>possibilitie that
you may be saved,</hi> yet for the <hi>probabilitie that you will be so:</hi> because the
holding of these errours, though it did not <hi>merit,</hi> might yet <hi>occasion</hi>
damnation. As the doctrine of Indulgences may take away the feare
of Purgatory, and the doctrine of Purgatorie the feare of Hell; as you
well knowe it does too frequently. So that though a godly man might
be saved <hi>with these</hi> errours, yet <hi>by meanes of them,</hi> many are made vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and so damn'd. <hi>By them</hi> I say, though <hi>not for them.</hi> No godly Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
who is verily perswaded that there is neither impietie nor super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition
in the use of your Latine service, shall be damn'd, I hope, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
present at it; yet the want of that devotion which the frequent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the Offices understood, might happily beget in them, the want of
that instruction and edification which it might afford them, may very
probably hinder the salvation of many which otherwise might haue
been saved. Besides, though the matter of an Errour may bee onely
something profitable, not necessary, yet the neglect of it may be a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
sinne. As not to regard veniall sinnes is in the doctrine of your
Schooles, mortall. Lastly, as veniall sinnes, you say, dispose men to
mortall; so the erring from some profitable, though lesser truth, may
dispose a man to errour in greater matters. As for example: The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife
of the Popes infallibility is, I hope, not unpardonably damnable
to every one that holds it; yet if it be a falsehood (as most certainely
it is) it puts a man into a very congruous disposition to beleiue <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi>
if he should chance to get into that See.</p>
   <p>8 To the Third. <hi>In his distinctions of points fundamentall and not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall,
<pb n="10" facs="22"/>
he may seeme, you say, to haue touched the point, but does not so
indeed. Because though he saies there are some points so fundamentall, as
that all are oblig'd to belieue them explicitely, yet he tells you not, whether
a man may disbeleiue any other points of faith, which are sufficiently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
to his understanding, as Truths revealed by Almighty God.</hi> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
which matter of <hi>Sufficient Proposall,</hi> I beseech you to come out
of the Clouds, and tell us roundly and plainely, what you meane by
<hi>Points of faith sufficiently propounded to a mans understanding, as Truths
revealed by God.</hi> Perhaps you meane such, as the person to whom they
are propos'd, understands sufficiently to be truths revealed by God.
But how then can he possibly choose but belieue them? Or how is it
not an apparent contradiction, that a man should disbelieue what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
understands to be a Truth; or any Christian what he understands
or but belieues to be testified by God? D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Potter</hi> might well thinke it
superfluous to tell you <hi>This is damnable;</hi> because indeed it is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
And yet one may very well think, by your saying, as you doe
hereafter, <hi>That the impietie of heresie consists in calling Gods truth in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion,</hi>
that this should be your meaning. Or doe you esteeme all those
things <hi>sufficiently presented to his understanding as Divine truths,</hi> which
by you, or any other man, or any company of men whatsoever, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
to him to be so? I hope you will not say so: For this were to
oblige a man to belieue all the Churches, and all the men in the world,
whensoever they pretend to propose divine Revelations. <hi>D. Potter,</hi> I
assure you from him, would never haue told you this neither. Or doe
you meane by <hi>sufficiently propounded as Divine Truths,</hi> all that your
Church propounds for such? That you may not neither; For the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion
betweene us is this; <hi>Whether your Churches Proposition be a
sufficient Proposition?</hi> And therefore to suppose this, is to suppose the
question; which you knowe in Reasoning is alwaies a fault. Or Lastly,
doe you mean (for I knowe not else what possibly you can meane,) by
<hi>sufficiently presented to his vnderstanding as revealed by God;</hi> that which
all things considered, is so propos'd to him, that he might and should
and would belieue it to be true and revealed by God, were it not for
some voluntary and avoidable fault of his owne that interposeth it
selfe betweene his understanding and the truth presented to it? This is
the best construction that I can make of your words; and if you speake
of truths thus propos'd, and rejected, let it be as damnable, as you
please, to deny or disbelieue them. But then I cannot but be amaz'd
to heare you say, That <hi>D. Potter never tells you whether there be any
other points of faith, besides those which we are bound to belieue explicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
which a man may deny or disbelieue, though they be sufficiently presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to his understanding as truths revealed or testified by Almighty God;</hi>
seeing the light it selfe is not more cleare then <hi>D. Potters</hi> Declaration
of himselfe for the Negatiue in this Question. p. 245. 246. 247. 248.
249. 250. of his Book. Where he entreats at large of this very Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
beginning his discourse thus. <q>It seemes fundamentall to the
faith, and for the salvation of every member of the Church, that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
and belieue all such points of faith, as whereof he may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
<pb n="11" facs="22"/>
that they belong to the doctrine of Iesus Christ.</q>
   </p>
   <p>To this conviction he requires three things. <q>Cleare Revelation; Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Proposition, and Capacity &amp; understanding in the hearer. For want
of cleare Revelation, he frees the Church before Christ &amp; the Disciples of
Christ from any damnable errour, though they believed not those things
which he that should now deny were no Christian. To sufficient Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition,
he requires two things. 1. That the points be perspicuously laid open
in themselues. 2. So forcibly, as may serue to remoue reasonable doubts to
the contrary, and to satisfie a teachable minde concerning it, against the
principles in which he hath been bred to the contrary. This Proposition
he saies is not limited to the Pope or Church, but extended to all meanes
whatsoever, by which a man may be convinced in conscience, that the
matter proposed is divine Revelation; which he professes to be done suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently,
not only when his conscience doth expresly beare witnesse to the
truth; but when it would doe so, if it were not choaked, and blinded by
some unruly and unmortified lust in the will. The difference being not
great between him that is wilfully blind, &amp; him that knowingly gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saieth
the Truth. The third thing he requires is Capacity and Abilitie
to apprehend the Proposall, and the Reasons of it: the want whereof ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuseth
fooles and madmen, &amp;c. But where there is no such impediment,
and the will of God is sufficiently propounded, there <hi>(saith hee)</hi> hee that
opposeth is convinced of errour; and he who is thus convinced is an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique:
and heresie is a work of the Flesh which excludeth from salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<hi>(he meanes without Repentance,)</hi> And hence it followeth, that it
is fundamentall to a Christians faith, and necessary for his salvation,
that he belieue all revealed truths of God, whereof he may be convinced
that they are from God.</q> This is the Conclusion of D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Potters</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course;
many passages whereof you take notice of in your subsequent
disputations, and make your advantage of them. And therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but say againe, that it amazeth me to heare you say, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines
this Question and never tells you <hi>whether or no there bee any
other points of faith, which being sufficiently propounded as divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations
may be denied and disbelieved.</hi> Hee tells you plainely there are
none such: and therefore you cannot say, that he tels you not whether
there be any such. Againe, it is almost as strange to mee, why you
should say, this was the only thing in question, <hi>Whether a man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
or disbelieue any point of faith, sufficiently presented to his understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
as a truth revealed by God.</hi> For to say that any thing is a thing in
question, me thinks at the first hearing of the words, imports, that it is
by some affirm'd, and deni'd by others. Now you affirme I grant, but
what Protestant ever denied, that it was a sinne to giue God the lye?
Which is the first and most obvious sense of these words. Or which
of them ever doubted, that to disbelieue is then a fault, when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
is so proposed to a man, that he might and should, and were it not
for his owne fault, would beleiue it? Certainly he that questions either
of these, justly deserues to haue his wits call'd in question. Produce
any one Protestant that ever did so, and I will giue you leaue to say it
is the only thing in question. But then I must tell you, that your ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="23"/>
Argument, viz: <hi>To deny a truth witnessed by God is damnable, But
of two that disagree one must of necessity deny some such truth, Therefore
one only can be saved;</hi> is built upon a ground cleane different from this
postulate. For though it be alwaies a fault to deny what either I doe
know, or should knowe to be testified by God; yet that which by a
cleanly conveyance you put in the place hereof, <hi>To deny a truth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed
by God</hi> simply, without the circumstance of <hi>being knowne or suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
proposed,</hi> is so farre from being certainely damnable, that it
may be many times done without any the least fault at all. As if God
should testifie something to a man in the <hi>Indies,</hi> I that had no assurance
of this testification should not be oblig'd to beleiue it. For in such ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
the Rule of the Law has place, <hi>Idem est non esse &amp; non apparere:</hi>
not to be at all and not to appeare to me, is to me all one. <hi>If I had not
come and spoken unto you</hi> (saith our Saviour) <hi>you had had no sinne?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>10 As little necessitie is there for that which followes: <hi>That of two dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing
in a matter of faith one must deny some such truth.</hi> Whether by
[such] you understand, <hi>Testified at all by God;</hi> or <hi>testified and sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
propounded.</hi> For it is very possible the matter in controversie may be
such a thing wherein God hath not at all declare himselfe, or not so
fully and clearely as to oblige all men to hold one way; and yet be so
overvalued by the parties in variance, as to bee esteemed a matter <hi>of
faith,</hi> and one of those things of which our Saviour saies; <hi>He that belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
not shall be damn'd.</hi> Who sees not that it is possible two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
may excommunicate and damne each other for keeping Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masse
tenne daies sooner or later; as well as <hi>Victor</hi> excommunicated
the Churches of <hi>Asia,</hi> for differing from him about Easter day? And
yet I beleiue you will confesse, that God had not then declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
about Easter; nor hath now about Christmasse. Anciently some
good Catholique Bishops excommunicated and damned others for
<hi>holding there were Antipodes:</hi> and in this question I would faine know
on which side was the sufficient proposall. <hi>The contra-Remonstrants</hi>
differ from the <hi>Remonstrants</hi> about the point of predetermination as a
matter of faith: I would knowe in this thing also, which way God
hath declar'd himselfe; whether for Predetermination or against it.
<hi>Stephen Bishop of Rome</hi> held it as a matter of faith &amp; Apostolique tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<hi>That Heretiques gaue true Baptisme:</hi> Others there were, and they
as good Catholiques as hee, that held that this was neither matter of
<hi>Faith</hi> nor matter of <hi>Truth. Iustin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> held the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of the <hi>Millenaries</hi> as a matter of <hi>faith:</hi> and though <hi>Iustin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi>
deny it, yet you, I hope, will affirme, that some good Christians
held the contrary. S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Augustine,</hi> I am sure, held <hi>the communicating of
Infants</hi> as much Apostolique tradition, as the Baptising of them: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the Bishop and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> of his time, held so too, or
held otherwise, I desire you to determine. But, sure I am, the Church
of <hi>Rome</hi> at this present holds the contrary. The same S. <hi>Austin</hi> held it
no matter of faith that the <hi>Bishops of Rome were Iudges of Appeales</hi>
from all parts of the Church Catholique, no not in <hi>Major causes and
Major Persons:</hi> whether the Bishop or Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did then hold
<pb n="13" facs="23"/>
the contrary doe you resolve me; but now I am resolv'd they doe so.
In all these differences, the point in question is esteem'd and propos'd
by one side at least as a matter of <hi>faith,</hi> and by the other rejected as not
so: and either this is to disagree in matters of faith, or you will have
no meanes to shew that we doe disagree. Now then to shew you how
weak and sandy the foundation is, on which the whole fabrick both
of your Book and Church depends, answer mee briefly to this <hi>Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi>
Eyther in these oppositions one of the opposite Parts err'd dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably,
and denyed Gods truth sufficiently propounded, or they did
not. If they did, then they which doe deny Gods truth sufficiently
propounded may goe to heaven; and then you are rash and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
in excluding us, though we were guilty of this fault. If not, then
there is no such necessity, that of two disagreeing about a matter of
faith, one should deny Gods truth sufficiently propounded. And so
the Major and Minor of your Argument, are prov'd false. Yet, though
they were as true as Gospell, and as evident as Mathematicall Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
the conclusion (so impertinent is it to the Premises) might still
be false. For that which naturally issues from these propositions is not.
<hi>Therefore one only can be saved:</hi> But, <hi>Therefore one of them does some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
that is damnable.</hi> But with what Logick or what Charity you
can inferre either as the immediat production of the former premises,
or as a Corollary from this conclusion, Therefore <hi>one only can be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi>
I doe not understand; unlesse you will pretend that this conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
is good, such a one doth something damnable, therefore he
shall certainly be damned: which whether it be not to overthrow the
Article of our Faith, which promises remission of sinnes upon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
and consequently to ruine the Gospell of Christ, I leave it to
the Pope and the Cardinalls to determine. For if against this it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged,
that no man can repent of the sinne wherein he dies: This
muche I have already stopped, by shewing that if it be a sinne of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
this is no way incongruous.</p>
   <p>11 <hi>To the fourth.</hi> You proceed in sleighting and disgracing your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary,
<hi>Pretending his objections are mean and vulgar, and such as have
been answered a thousand times.</hi> But if your cause were good, these Arts
would be needlesse. For though some of his objections have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
shifted by men<note n="*" place="margin">I mean the Divines of Doway: whose profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion we have in your Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick <hi>Expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorius</hi> p. 12. <hi>in censura Bertrami,</hi> in these words. Seeing in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ancient Catholiques, we tolerate extenuate &amp; excuse very many errors, and devising some shift of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deny thē, and put upon them a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient sense when they are objected to us in dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and conflicts with our adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; we see no reason why <hi>Bertram</hi> may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the same equity.</note> that make a profession of devising shifts and evasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to save themselves and their Religion from the pressure of truth,
by men that are resolv'd they will say something, though they can say
nothing to purpose; yet I doubt not to make it appear, that neither by
others have they beene truly and really satisfied; and that the best An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere
you give them, is to call them <hi>Mean and vulgar objections.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>12 <hi>To the Fift. But this paines might have been spared: For the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of his discourse is in a Sermon of D. Vshers, and confuted four
yeares agoe by Paulus Veridicus.</hi> It seemes then the substance of your
Reply is in <hi>Paulus Veridicus,</hi> and so your paines also might well have
been spared. But had there been no necessity to help and peece out
your confuting his Arguments with disgracing his person, (which yet
you cannot doe) you would have considered, that to them who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="14" facs="24"/>
D. <hi>Potters</hi> Book, &amp; the Arch-Bishops Sermon, this aspersion will
presently appear a poore detraction, not to be answered but scorn'd.
To say nothing that in D. <hi>Potter,</hi> being to answere a book by expresse
Command from Royall Authority, to leave any thing materiall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,
because it had been said before, especially being spoken at large,
and without any relation to the Discourse which he was to Answere,
had been a ridiculous vanity and foule prevarication.</p>
   <p>13 <hi>To the sixt.</hi> In your sixt <hi>parag.</hi> I let all passe saving only this, <hi>That
a perswasion that men of different Religions</hi> (you must mean, or else you
speak not to the point, Christians of divers Opinions and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
<hi>may be saved, is a most pernitious heresy, and even a ground of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme.</hi>
What strange extractions Chymistry can make I know not;
but sure I am, he that by reason would inferre this conclusion, <hi>That
there is no God;</hi> from this ground, <hi>That God will save men in different
Religions,</hi> must have a higher strain in Logick, then you or I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
made shew of. In my apprehension, the other part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,
<hi>That there is a God,</hi> should much rather follow from it. And
whether contradictions will flow from the same fountaine, let the
Learned judge. Perhaps you will say you intended not to deliver here
a positive and measur'd truth, and which you expected to be call'd to
account for; but only a high and tragicall expression of your just de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation
of the wicked doctrine against which you write. If you mean
so, I shall let it passe: only I am to advertize the lesse-wary Reader,
that passionate expressions, and vehement asseverations are no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
unlesse it be, of the weaknesse of the cause that is defended by
them, or the man that defends it. And to remember you of what <hi>Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi>
saies of some such things as these, <hi>—Nubila mens est haec ubi
regnant.</hi> For my part I am not now in Passion; neither will I speak
one word which I think I cannot justify to the full: and I say and will
maintaine, that to say, <hi>That Christians of different Opinions and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions
(such I mean, who hold all those things that are simply necessary
to Salvation) may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> obtain pardon for the Errours wherein they dye ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly,
by a generall Repentance; is so farre from being a ground of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme,
that to say the contrary, is to crosse in Diameter a main Article
of our Creed, and to overthrow the Gospell of Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>14 <hi>To the Seaventh and Eight.</hi> To the two next Paragraphes, I have
but two words to say. The one is, that I know no Protestants that <hi>hold
it necessary to be able to prove a Perpetuall Visible Church distinct from
Yours.</hi> Some perhaps undertake to doe so, as a matter of curtesy; but
I believe you will be much to seeke for any one that holds it necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
For though you say that Christ hath promised there shall be a
Perpetuall Visible Church; yet you yourselves doe not pretend that
he hath promised there shall be Histories and Records alwaies extant
of the Professors of it in all ages: nor that he hath any where enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
us to read those Histories that we may be able to shew them.</p>
   <p>14 The other is. That <hi>Breerelie's</hi> great exactnesse, which you mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify
so and amplify, is no very certaine demonstration of his fidelity.
A Romance may be told with as much variety of circumstances, as a
true Story.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="15" facs="24"/>
16 <hi>To the Ninth and Tenth.</hi> Your desires that I would in this rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
<hi>Avoid impertinencies. Not impose doctrines upon you which you dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme:
Set down the substance of your Reasons faithfully and entirely: Not
weary the reader with unnecessary quotations: Object nothing to you
which I can answere my selfe, or which may be return'd upon my selfe: and
lastly, (which you repeat again in the end of your Preface) speak as cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and distinctly and univocally as possibly I can,</hi> are all very reasonable,
and shall be by me most punctually and fully satisfied. Only I have
Reason to complain, that you give us rules only and not good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
in keeping them. For in some of these things I shall have frequent
occasion to shew, that <hi>Medice curateipsum,</hi> may very justly be said un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you; especially for objecting what might very easily have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered
by you, and may be very justly returned upon you.</p>
   <p>17 To your ensuing demands, though some of them be very cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
and ensnaring; yet I will give you as clear and plain and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Answers as possibly I can.</p>
   <p>18 <hi>To the Eleventh.</hi> To the first then, about <hi>the Perpetuity of the visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Church,</hi> my Answer is: That I believe our Saviour, ever since his
Ascention, hath had in some place or other a Visible true Church on
earth: I mean a company of men, that professed at least so much truth
as was absolutely necessary for their Salvation. And I believe that
there will be somewhere or other such a Church to the Worlds end.
But the contrary doctrine I doe at no hand believe to be a damnable
heresy.</p>
   <p>19 <hi>To the twelfth.</hi> To the second, what <hi>Visible Church there was before
Luther disagreeing from the Roman?</hi> I answere, that before <hi>Luther</hi> there
were many Visible Churches in many things disagreeing from the
Roman: But not that the whole Catholique Church disagreed from
her, because she her selfe was a Part of the Whole, though much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.
And to undertake to name a Catholique Church disagreeing
from her, is to make her no Part of it, which we doe not, nor need not
pretend. And <hi>for men agreeing with Protestants in all points,</hi> wee will
then produce them, when you shall either prove it necessary to be
done, which you know we absolutely deny; or when you shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
a perpetuall succession of Professors, which in all points have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
with you, and disagreed from you in nothing. But this my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise,
to deal plainly with you, I conceive, &amp; so intended it to be very
like his, who undertook to drink up the Sea, upon condition, that he,
to whom the promise was made, should first stop the Rivers from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in. For this unreasonable request which you make to us is to your
selves so impossible, that in the very next Age after the Apostles, you
will never be able to name a man, whom you can prove to have agreed
with you in all things, nay (if you speak of such, whose Works are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
and unquestioned) whom we cannot prove to have disagreed
from you in many things. Which I am so certain of, that I will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
my credit, and my life upon it.</p>
   <p>20 <hi>To the Thirteenth.</hi> To the third, <hi>Whether, seeing there cannot be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd
any visible true Church distinct from the Roman, it followes not
<pb n="16" facs="25"/>
that she err'd not fundamentally.</hi> I say in our sence of the word <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall,</hi>
it does follow. For if it be true, that there was then no
Church distinct from the Roman, then it must be, either because
there was no Church at all, which we deny: Or because the Roman
Church was the whole Church, which we also deny: or because she
was a Part of the Whole, which we grant. And if she were a true part of
the Church, then she retained those truths which were simply neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary
to Salvation, and held no errours which were inevitably and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonably
destructive of it. For this is precisely necessary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute
any man or any Church a member of the Church Catholique.
In our sence therefore of the word <hi>Fundamentall,</hi> I hope shee erred
not fundamentally: but in your sence of the word, I fear she did. That
is, she held something to be Divine Revelation, which was not; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
not to be which was.</p>
   <p>21 <hi>To the fourteenth.</hi> To the fourth. <hi>How it could be damnable to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
her errors, if they were not fundamentall?</hi> I answere. 1. Though
it were not damnable, yet if it were a fault, it was not to be done. For
a veniall sinne, with you is not damnable; yet you say, it is not to be
committed for the procuring any good. <hi>Non est faciendum malum
vel minimum, ut eveniat bonum vel maximum.</hi> 2. It is damnable to
mantaine an error against conscience, though the errour in it selfe, and
to him that believes it, be not damnable. Nay the profession not only
of an errour, but even of a truth, if not believ'd, when you think on it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
I believe you will confesse to be a mortall sinne; unlesse you will
say, Hypocrisie and Simulation in Religion is not so. 3. Though we
say the errors of the Roman Church were not destructive of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but pardonable even to them that dyed in them, upon a generall
repentance: yet we deny not but in <hi>themselves they were damnable.</hi>
Nay, the very saying they were pardonable, implies they needed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
and therefore in themselves were damnable: damnable <hi>meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously,</hi>
though not <hi>effectually.</hi> As a poyson may be deadly in it selfe, and
yet not kill him, that together with the poyson takes an antidote: or
as felony may deserve death and yet not bring it on him that obtaines
the Kings pardon.</p>
   <p>22 <hi>To the fifteenth.</hi> To the fift. <hi>How they can be excus'd from Schisme,
who forsook her Communion upon pretence of errours which were not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable!</hi>
I answere. All that we forfake in you, is only the beliefe, and
practice, and profession of your Errors. Hereupon, you cast us out of
your Communion. And then with a strange, and contradictious, and
ridiculous hypocrisy, complain that we forsake it. As if a man should
thrust his friend out of doores, and then be offended at his departure▪
But for us not to forsake the beliefe of your Errors, having discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
them to be Errors, was impossible; and therefore to doe so could
not be damnable, believing them to be Errors. Not to forsake the
practice and profession of them, had been damnable hypocrisie; sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing
that (which you vainly runne away with, and take for graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
those errors in themselves were not damnable. Now to doe so,
and as matters now stand, not to forsake your Communion, is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
<pb n="17" facs="25"/>
contradictious: seeing the condition of your Communion is,
that we must professe to believe all your doctrines not only not to be
damnable errors (which will not content you,) but also to be certain
and necessary and revealed truths. So that to demand why we forsake
your Communion upon pretence of Errors which were not damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
is in effect to demand why we forsooke it upon our forsaking it!
For to pretend that there are Errors in your Church though not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
is <hi>ipso facto</hi> to forsake your Communion, and to doe that which
both in your account, and as you think in Gods account, puts him
as does so, out of your Communion. So that either you must free your
Church, from requiring the belief of any errour whatsoever, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and not damnable, or whether you will or no you must free us
from Schisme. For schisme there cannot be in leaving your commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
unlesse we were obliged to continue in it. Man cannot be obliged
by Man, but to what either formally or virtually he is obliged by God,
for all just power is from God. God the eternall truth neither can nor
will obliege us to believe any the least and the most innocent falshood
to be a divine truth, that is, to erre; nor, to professe a known errour,
which is to lye. So that if you require the belief of any errour among
the conditions of your Communion, our obligation to communicate
with you ceaseth, and so the imputation of schisme to us, vanisheth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
nothing: but lies heavy upon you for making our seperation from
you just and necessary, by requiring unnecessary and unlawfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
of your Communion. Hereafter therefore, I intreat you, let
not your demand be, how could we forsake your Communion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Schisme, seeing you err'd not damnably? But how we could doe
so without Schisme, seeing you err'd not at all? which if either you
doe prove, or we cannot disprove it, we will (I at least will for my
part) returne to your Communion, or subscribe my selfe Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.
In the mean time, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>23 Yet notwitstanding all your Errors we doe not renounce your
Communion <hi>totally</hi> and absolutely, but only leave Communicating
with you in the practise and profession of your Errors. The tryall
whereof will be to propose some forme of worshipping God, taken
wholly out of Scripture; and herein if we refuse to joyn with you,
then, and not till then, may you justly say we have utterly and abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
abandoned your Communion.</p>
   <p>24 <hi>To the sixteenth.</hi> Your sixt demand I have already satisfied in my
answeres to the <hi>Second</hi> and the <hi>Fourth:</hi> and in my reply, <hi>Ad</hi> § 2. to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
the end. And though you say <hi>your repeating must be excused,</hi>
yet I dare not be so confident, and therefore forbear it.</p>
   <p>25 <hi>To the seaventeenth.</hi> To the seaventh, <hi>Whether errour against any
one truth sufficiently propounded as testified by God, destroy not the
Nature and Vnity of Faith, or at least, is not a grievous offence exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
salvation!</hi> I answere, if you suppose, as you seem to doe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
so sufficient, that the party to whom it is made is convinc'd
that it is from God, so that the denyall of it involves also with it the
denyall of Gods veracity; any such errour destroyes both faith and
<pb n="18" facs="26"/>
salvation. But if the Proposall be only so sufficient, not, that the party
to whom it is made is convinc'd, but only that he should, and but for
his own fault would have been convinc'd of the divine verity of the
doctrine proposed: The crime then is not so great, for the beliefe
of Gods veracity may well consist with such an Errour. Yet a fault I
confesse it is (and without Repentance) damnable, if all circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
considered the proposall be sufficient. But then I must tell you
that the proposall of the present Roman Church is only pretended to
be sufficient for this purpose, but is not so: especially all the Rayes of
the Divinity, which they pretend to shine so conspicuously in her
proposalls, being so darkned and even extinguished with a cloud of
contradiction, from Scripture, Reason, and the Ancient Church.</p>
   <p>26 <hi>To the Eighteenth.</hi> To the eight. <hi>How of disagreeing Protestants, both
parts may hope for salvation, seeing some of them must needs erre against
some Truth testified by God?</hi> I answere, 1. The most disagreeing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants
that are, yet thus farre agree, that these books of Scripture
which were never doubted of in the Church, are the undoubted word
of God, and a perfect rule of faith. 2. That the sense of them, which
God intended, whatsoever it is, is certainly true. So that they believe
implicitely even those very truths against which they erre; and why
an implicit faith in Christ and his Word, should not suffice as well as
an implicit faith in your Church, I have desired to be resolved by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of your Side, but never could. 3. That they are to use their best
endeavours to beleive the Scripture in the true sense and to live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to it. This if they performe (as I hope many on all Sides doe)
truly and syncerely, it is impossible but that they should believe aright
in all things necessary to salvation; that is, in all those things which
appertain to the Covenant between God and man in Christ, for so
much, is not only plainly but frequently contained in Scripture. And
believing aright touching the Covenant, if they for their parts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
the condition required of them, which is syncere obedience, why
should they not expect that God will performe his promise and give
them salvation? For, as for other things which lye without the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
and are therefore lesse necessary, if by reason of the seeming
conflict which is oftentimes between Scripture and Reason, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
on the one side, and Scripture, Reason, and Authority on the
other; if by reason of the variety of tempers, abilities, educations,
&amp; unavoidable prejudices, whereby mens understandings are various<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
form'd and fashion'd, they doe embrace severall Opinions, whereof
some must be erroneous; to say that God will damne them for such
errors, who are lovers of him, and lovers of truth, is to rob man of
his comfort, and God of his goodnesse; it is to make Man desperate
and God a Tyrant. <hi>But they deny Truths testified by God, and therefore
shall be damn'd.</hi> Yes, if they knew them to be thus testified by him, and
yet would deny them, that were to give God the lye, and question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
damnable. But if you should deny a truth which God had testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
but only to a man in the <hi>Indies,</hi> (as I said before) and this testifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
you had never heard of, or at least had no sufficient reason to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="19" facs="26"/>
that God had so testified, would not you think it a hard case to
be damned for such a denyall? Yet consider I pray a little more at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively
the difference between them, and you will presently acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
the question between them is not at any time, or in any thing,
Whether God saies true or no? or whether he saies this or no? But
supposing he saies this, and saies true, whether he meanes this or no? As
for example, between <hi>Lutherans, Calvinists,</hi> and <hi>Zwinglians,</hi> it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
that Christ spake these words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
he meant in saying so is true: But what he meant and how he
is to be understood, that's the question. So that though some of
them deny a truth by God intended, yet you can with no reason or
justice accuse them of denying the truth of Gods Testimony, unlesse
you can plainly shew that God hath declared, and that plainly and
clearly, what was his meaning in these words. I say <hi>plainly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
For he that speaks obscurely and ambiguously, and no where de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares
himselfe plainly, sure he hath no reason to be much offended
if he be mistaken. When therefore you can shew, that in this and all
other their Controversies, God hath interposed his Testimony on one
side or other; so that either they doe see it, and will not; or were it not
for their own voluntary and avoidable fault, might and should see it
and doe not; let all such Errors be as damnable as you please to make
them. In the mean while, if they suffer themselves neither to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traid
into their errors, nor kept in them by any sin of their will; if they
doe their best endeavour to free themselves from all errors, and yet
faile of it through humane frailty; so well am I perswaded of the
goodnesse of God, that if in me alone, should meet a confluence of all
such errors of all the Protestants in the World, that were thus qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
I should not be so much afraid of them all, as I should be to ask
pardon for them. For, whereas that which you affright us with of
calling Gods Veracitie in Question, is but a Panicke feare, a fault that
no man thus qualified, is, or can be guilty of; to ask pardon of simple
and purely involuntary errors is tacitely to imply that God is angry
with us for them, and that were to impute to him the strange tyranny
of <hi>requiring brick, when he gives no straw; of expecting to gather, where
he strew'd not; to reap where he sowed not:</hi> of being offended with us for
not doing what he knowes we cannot doe. This I say upon a supposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
that they doe their best endeavours to know Gods will and doe
it; which he that denyes to be possible knowes not what he saies; for
he saies in effect, That men cannot doe, what they can doe; for to doe
what a man can doe, is to doe his best endeavour. But because this
supposition, though certainly possible, is very rare, and admirable, I
say secondly, that I am verily perswaded, that God will not impute er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
to them, as sinnes, who use such a measure of industry, in finding
truth, as humane <hi>prudence</hi> and ordinary <hi>discretion</hi> (their abilities
and oportunities, their distractions and hindrances, and all other
things considered) shall advise them unto, in a matter of such conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.
But if herein also we faile, then our errors begin to be malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
and justly imputable, as offences against God, and that love of
<pb n="20" facs="27"/>
his truth which he requires in us. You will say then, that for those
erring <hi>Protestants,</hi> which are in this case, which evidently are farre
the greater part, they sinne damnably in erring, and therefore there is
little hope of their Salvation. To which I answer, that the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
of this Reason, is somewhat strong against a <hi>Protestant;</hi> but
much weakned by coming out of the mouth of a <hi>Papist.</hi> For all sinnes
with you are not damnable; and therefore Protestants errors might be
sinnes, and yet not damnable. But yet out of courtesy to you, we
will remove this rubbe out of your way; and for the present suppose
them <hi>mortall sinnes;</hi> and is there then no hope of Salvation, for him
that commits them? Not, you will say, if he dye in them without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;
and such Protestants you speak of, <hi>who without repentance
dye in their errors.</hi> Yea but what if they dye in their errors with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?
then I hope you will have Charity enough to think they
may be saved. <hi>Charity Mist.</hi> takes it indeed for granted, that this
supposition is destructive of it selfe;<note place="margin">In the place above quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and that it is impossible, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous
that a man should repent of those errors wherein he dies; or
dye in those whereof he repents. But it was wisely done of Him to
take it for granted; for most certainly He could not have spoken one
word of sense for the confirmation of it. For seeing <hi>Protestants</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
as well as you, Gods infinite and most admirable perfections in
himselfe, more then most worthy of all possible love: seeing they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
as well as you, his infinite goodnesse to them, in creating them
of nothing; in creating them according to his own image; in creating
all things for their use and benefit; in streaming down his favours on
them every moment of their lives; in designing them, if they serve
him, to infinite and eternall happinesse; in redeeming them, not with
corruptible things, but the pretious blood of his beloved sonne: seing
they believe, as well as you, his infinite goodnesse, and patience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
them, in expecting their conversion; in wooing, alluring, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and by all meanes, which his wisdome can suggest unto him, and
mans nature is capable of, drawing them to Repentance &amp; Salvation:
Seeing they believe these things as well as you, and for ought you
know, consider them as much as you, (and if they doe not, it is not
their Religion, but They that are too blame,) what can hinder, but that
the consideration of Gods most infinite goodnesse to them, and their
own almost infinite wickednesse against him, Gods spirit cooperating
with them, may raise them to a true and syncere and a cordiall love of
God? And seeing sorrow for having injur'd or offended the person be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,
or when we fear we may have offended him, is the most natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
effect of true love; what can hinder, but that love which hath
oftimes constrained them, to lay down their lives for God (which
our Saviour assures us is the noblest sacrifice we can offer,) may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
in them an universall sorrow for all their sinnes, both which they
know they have committed, and which they fear they may haue? In
which number, their being negligent, or not dispassionate, or not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudicate
enough in seeking the truth, and, the effect thereof, their
errors, if they be sinnes, cannot but be compriz'd. In a word, what
<pb n="21" facs="27"/>
should hinder, but that, that Prayer<hi>—Delicta sua quis intelligit? who
can understand his faults? Lord cleanse thou me from my secret sinnes,</hi>
may be heard and accepted by God, as well from a <hi>Protestant</hi> that dies
in some errours, as from a <hi>Papist</hi> that dies in some other sins of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
which perhaps he might more easily haue discovered to bee
sinnes, then a Protestant could his errours to be errours? As well from
a Protestant, that held some errour, which (as he conceived) Gods
word, and his reason, (which is also in some sort Gods word) led him
unto; as from a <hi>Dominican,</hi> who perhaps took up his opinion upon
trust, not because he had reason to beleiue it true, but because it was
the opinion of his <hi>Order;</hi> for the same man if hee had light upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Order, would in all probabilitie, haue beene of the other opinion.
For what else is the cause, that generally <hi>all the Dominicans are of one
opinion, and all the Iesuits of the other?</hi> I say, from a <hi>Dominican</hi> who
took up his opinion upon trust; and that such an opinion (if we beleiue
the writers of your Order) as if it be granted true, it were not a point
matter, what opinions any man held, or what actions any man did, for
the best would be as bad as the worst, &amp; the worst as good as the best.
And yet such is the partialitie of your Hypocrisie, that of disagreeing
Papists, neither shall deny the truth testified by God, but both may
hope for salvation: but of disagreeing Protestants (though they differ
in the same thing,) one side must deny Gods Testimony and bee inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of salvation. That a <hi>Dominican</hi> through culpable negligence, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
and dying in his errour, may repent of it, though hee knowes it
not; or be saued though he doe not: But if a Protestant doe the very
same thing, in the very same point, and die in his errour, his case is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate.
The summe of all that hath been said to this Demand is this.
1. That no erring Protestant denies any truth testified by God, under
this formalitie, <hi>as testified by him;</hi> nor which they know or beleiue to
be testified by him. And therefore it is a horrible calumnie in you to
say, <hi>They call Gods Veracitie in question.</hi> For Gods undoubted and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>question'd
Veracitie, is to them the ground why they hold all they
doe hold: neither doe they hold any opiniō so stifly, but they will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe
it rather then this one, <hi>That all which God saies is true.</hi> 2. God
hath not so clearely and plainly declared himselfe in most of these
things which are in controversie between Protestants, but that an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
man, whose heart is right to God, and one that is a true louer of
God, and of his truth, may by reason of the conflict of contrary Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
on both sides, very easily, and therefore excusably mistake, and
embrace errour for truth, and reject truth for errour. 3, If any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant
or Papist be betrayed into, or kept in any Errour, by any sinne
of his will (as it is to be fear'd many millions are) such Errour is, as the
cause of it, sinfull and damnable: yet not exclusiue of all hope of salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
but pardonable if discover'd, upon a particular explicite repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;
if not discover'd, upon a generall and implicite repentance for all
Sinnes knowne and unknowne: in which number all sinfull Errours
must of necessity be contained.</p>
   <p>17 <hi>To the 9. To the nineteenth,</hi> Wherein you are so urgent for a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="22" facs="28"/>
Catalogue of Fundamentalls:</hi> I answer almost in your owne words,
that we also constantly urge and require to haue a particular Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
of your Fundamentals, whether they be written Verities, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written
Traditions, or Church Definitions? all which, you say, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate
the materiall Object of your Faith: In a word of all such points
as are defin'd and sufficiently proposed; so that whosoever denies, or
doubts of any of them, is certainly in the state of damnation. A Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
I say in particular of the Proposals: and not only some gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
definition, or description, under which you lurke deceitfully, of
what and what only is sufficiently proposed: wherein yet you doe not
very well agree.<note place="margin">This great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions among you, touching this matter, if any mā doubt of it, let him read <hi>Francis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Picus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randula in l. Theorem. in Exposit. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. quarti,</hi> and <hi>T h. Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis. Tom. 3. De Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus. doct. 3. fol.</hi> 5. andhee shall bee fully satisfied that I haue done you no injury.</note> For many of you hold the Popes proposall <hi>Ex Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedra,</hi>
to be sufficient and obligeing: Some a Councel without a Pope:
Some, of neither of them severally, but only both together: Some not
this neither in matter of manners, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> acknowledges, &amp;
tells us it is all one in effect, as if they denied it sufficient in matter of
faith: Some not in matter of faith, neither think this proposall infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
without the acceptation of the Church universall: Some deny the
infallibility of the Present Church, and only make the Tradition of all
ages the <hi>infallible Propounder.</hi> Yet if you were agreed <hi>what and what
only is the Infallible Propounder,</hi> this would not satisfie us; nor yet to
say <hi>that All is fundamentall which is propounded sufficiently by him.</hi> For
though agreeing in this, yet you might still disagree <hi>whether such or
such a Doctrine were propounded or not: or if propounded, whether suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently,
or only unsufficiently.</hi> And it is so knowne a thing, that in many
points you doe so, that I assure my selfe you will not deny it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
we constantly urge and require a particular and perfect Inventory
of all these Divine Revelations, which you say <hi>are sufficiently propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
&amp; that such a one to which all of your Church will subscribe as neither
redundant, nor deficient;</hi> which when you giue in with one hand, you
shall receiue a particular Catalogue of such Points as I call <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall,</hi>
with the other. Neither may you think mee unreasonable in
this demand, seeing upon such a particular Catalogue of your suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Proposalls as much depends, as upon a particular Catalogue of
our Fundamentalls. As for example. Whether or no a man doe not
erre in some point defined and sufficiently proposed: and whether or
no those that differ among you, differ in Fundamentalls; which if they
doe <hi>One Heaven</hi> (by your owne Rule) <hi>cannot receiue them All.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
you will here complaine, that this is not to satisfie your demand,
but to avoid it, and to put you off as the <hi>Areopagites</hi> did hard causes
<hi>ad diem longissimum,</hi> and bid you come againe a hundred yeares hence:
To deale truly, I did so intend it should be. Nether can you say my
dealing with you is injurious, seeing I require nothing of you, but that,
what you require of others, you should shew it possible to be done, and
just and necessary to be required. For, for my part, I haue great reason
to suspect, it is neither the one nor the other. For whereas the Verities
which are delivered in Scripture, may be very fitly divided into <hi>such
as were written because they were necessary to be beleived,</hi> Of which
ranke are those only which constitute and make up the Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="23" facs="28"/>
God and Man in Christ: and then <hi>such as are necessary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived
not in themselues but only by accident, because they were written.</hi>
Of which rank are many matters of History, of Prophecy, of mystery,
of Policy, of Oeconomie, &amp; such like, which are evidently not <hi>intrinse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi>
to the Covenant. Now to sever exactly &amp; punctually these Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
one trom the other: what is <hi>necessary in it selfe</hi> &amp; antecedently to
the writing, from what is but only profitable in it selfe, and <hi>necessary
only because written,</hi> is a businesse of extreame great difficultie, and
extreame little necessitie. For first he that will goe about to distinguish
especially in the Story of our Saviour, what was written because it was
<hi>profitable,</hi> from what was written because <hi>necessary,</hi> shall find an intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
peece of businesse of it, &amp; almost impossible that he should be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
he hath done it, when he hath done it. And then it is apparently
unnecessary to goe about it, seeing he that beleiues all, certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues
all that is necessary. And he that doth not beleiue all (I meane
all the undoubted parts of the undoubted Books of Scripture) can
hardly belieue any, neither haue we reason to beleiue he doth so. So
that, that Protestants giue you not a Catalogue of Fundamentalls, it is
not from Tergiversation (as you suspect, who for want of Charitie to
them alwaies suspect the worst,) but from Wisdome and Necessity.
For they may very easily erre in doing it; because though all which is
necessary be plaine in Scripture, yet all which is plaine is not therefore
written because it was necessary. For what greater necessity was there
that I should know S. <hi>Paul left his Cloak at Troas,</hi> then those <hi>Worlds of
Miracles,</hi> which our Saviour did, which were never written. And
when they had done it, it had been to no purpose; There being, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
now stand, as great necessitie, of believing those truths of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
which are not Fundamentall, as those that are. You see then what
reason we haue to decline this hard labour, which you a rigid Taske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master
haue here put upon us. Yet insteed of giving you a Catalogue
of Fundamentalls, with which I dare say you are resolu'd before it
come, never to be satisfied, I will say that to you, which if you please
may doe you as much service; and this it is. That it is sufficient for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
mans salvation that he belieue the Scripture: That he endeavour to
beleiue it in the true sense of it, as farre as concernes his dutie: And that
he conforme his life unto it either by Obedience or Repentance. Hee
that does so (and all Protestants according to the <hi>Dictamen</hi> of their
Religion should doe so,) may be secure that he cannot erre fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally.
And they that doe so cannot differ in Fundamentals. So that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
their differences, &amp; your presumption, <hi>the same Heaven
may receiue them All.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>28 <hi>To the twentieth.</hi> Your tenth &amp; last request is, <hi>to know distinctly
what is the doctrine of the Protestant English Church, in these points; and
what my private opinion.</hi> Which shall be satisfied when the Church of
England hath expressed her selfe in them; or when you haue told us
what is the doctrine of your Church, in the Question of <hi>Predetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi>
or the <hi>Immaculate Conception.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>29 <hi>To the 21 &amp;</hi> 22. These answers I hope in the judgement of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="24" facs="29"/>
men are satisfactory to your Questions, though not to you,
For I haue either answer'd them, or given you a reason why I haue not.
Neither, for ought I can see, <hi>haue I flitted from things considered in
their owne nature, to accidentall or rare Circumstances,</hi> But told you my
opinion plainely what I thought of your Errours in themselues: and
what as they were qualified or malignified with good or bad circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances.
Though I must tell you truly, that I see no reason, the Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
being of the damnablenesse of Errour, <hi>why you should esteeme igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
incapacitie, want of meanes to be instructed, accidentall</hi> and rare
<hi>Circumstances:</hi> As if knowledge, capacitie, having meanes of Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
concerning the truth of your Religion or ours, were not as rare &amp;
unusuall in the adverse part of either, as Ignorance, Incapacitie, and
want of meanes of instruction. Especially how erroneous Conscience
can be a rare thing in those that erre, or how unerring Conscience is
not much more rare, I am not able to apprehend. So that to consider
men of different Religions (the subject of this Contoversie) in their
owne nature and <hi>without circumstances,</hi> must be to consider them,
neither as ignorant, nor as knowing: neither as having, nor as wanting
meanes of Instruction: neither as with Capacity, nor without it: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with erroneous, nor yet with unerring conscience. And then what
judgement can you pronounce of them, all the goodnesse and badnesse
of an Action depending on the Circumstances. Ought not a Iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to giue sentence of an Action, to consider all the Circumstances of
it, or is it possible he should judge rightly that does not so? Neither is
it to purpose, <hi>That Circumstances being various, cannot be well compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
under any generall rule:</hi> For though under any generall rule
they cannot, yet under many generall rules they may be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
The Question here is, you say, <hi>whether men of different Religions
may be saved?</hi> Now the subject of this Question is an ambiguous
terme and may be determined and invested with diverse and contrary
Circumstances: and accordingly contrary judgements are to be given
of it. And who then can be offended with D. <hi>Potter</hi> for distinguishing
before he defines, (the want whereof is the cheife thing that makes
defining dangerous?) Who can finde fault with him for saying, <hi>If,
through want of meanes of instruction, incapacitie, invincible or probable
ignorance a man dye in errour, he may be saved. But if he be negligent in
seeking Truth, unwilling to find it, either doth see it and will not, or might
see it and will not, that his case is dangerous, &amp; without repentance despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</hi>
This is all that D. <hi>Potter</hi> saies: neither rashly damning all that are
of a different opinion from him, not securing any that are in matter of
Religion sinfully, that is, willingly erroneous. The Author of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
(I will abide by it) saies the very same thing, neither can I see
what adversary he hath in the maine Question but his owne shaddow;
and yet I know not out of what frowardnesse findes fault with D. <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
for affirming that which himselfe affirmes: and to cloude the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
whereas the Question is, <hi>whether men by ignorance, dying in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
may be saved,</hi> would haue them considered <hi>neither as erring, nor
ignorant.</hi> And when the question is, whether <hi>The errors of Papists bee
<pb n="25" facs="29"/>
damnable:</hi> to which we answer. That to them that doe or might knowe
them to be errours, they are damnable, to them that doe not, they are
not. <hi>He tels us that this is to change the state of the Question,</hi> whereas
indeed it is to state the Question, and free it from ambiguity before
you answer it: <hi>and to haue recourse to Accidentall Circumstances;</hi> as if
Ignorance were accidentall to error, or as if a man could be considered
as in errour, and not be considered as in ignorance of the Truth from
which he erres! Certainly Errour against a Truth, must needs presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
a nescience of it: unlesse you will say, that a man may at once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue
for a Truth and resolue against it, assent to it, and dissent from
it, knowe it to be true, and beleiue it not to be true. Whether Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
&amp; Opinion touching the same thing, may stand together, is made
a Question in the Schooles: But hee that would question, whether
knowing a thing and doubting of it, much more, whether knowing it
to be true &amp; believing it to be false, may stand together, deserues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
question no other Answer but laughter. Now if Errour &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
connot consist, then Errour and Ignorance must be inseparable.
He then that professeth your errours may well be considered either as
knowing or as Ignorant. But him that does erre indeed, you can no
more conceiue without ignorance, then Long without Quantity, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
without Qualitie, a Man, and not a living Creature, to haue gone
ten miles, and not to haue gone fiue, to speak sense, and not to speake.
For as the latter in all these is implied in the former, so is Ignorance of
a Truth, supposed in errour against it. Yet such a man, though not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueable
without Ignorance simply, may be very well considered ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
as with, or without voluntary and sinfull Ignorance. And he that
will giue a wise answer to this Question, Whether a Papist dying a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist
may be saved, according to Gods ordinary proceeding; must di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish
him according to these severall considerations, and say, Hee
may be saved, If his ignorance were either invincible, or at least unaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
and probable: if otherwise, without repentance he cannot.</p>
   <p>To the rest of this Preface, I haue nothing to say; saving what hath
been said, but this, That it is no just exception to an argument to call it
vulgar and thredbare. Truth can neither be too common nor super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuated,
nor Reason ever worne out. Let your Answers be solid &amp;
pertinent, and we will never finde fault with them for being old or
common.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>