<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Noble and Vertu∣ous Theophilus Howard, Lorde of Walden, sonne and Heire to the right Hono∣rable the Earle of Suffolke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107412_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17871</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4538</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Noble and Vertu∣ous Theophilus Howard, Lorde of Walden, sonne and Heire to the right Hono∣rable the Earle of Suffolke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The discription of a maske, presented before the Kinges Maiestie at White-Hall, on Twelfth Night last : in honour of the Lord Hayes, and his bride, daughter and heire to the Honourable the Lord Dennye, their marriage hauing been the same day at court solemnized. To this by occasion other small poemes are adioyned. Inuented and set forth by Thomas Campion doctor of phisicke</title>
                 <author>Campion, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, illustrations, letterpress music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Games and recreations</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Right Noble and Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Theophilus Howard,</hi> Lorde of Walden, sonne and Heire to the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Earle of Suffolke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF to be sprong of high and princely blood,</l>
      <l>If to inherite vertue, honour, grace,</l>
      <l>If to be great in all things, and yet good,</l>
      <l>If to be facill, yet t'haue power and place,</l>
      <l>If to be iust, and bountifull may get</l>
      <l>The loue of men, your right may chalenge it.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The course of forraine manners far and wide,</l>
      <l>The courts, the countries, Citties, townes and state,</l>
      <l>The blossome of your springing youth hath tried,</l>
      <l>Honourd in eu'ry place and fortunate,</l>
      <l>Which now grown fairer doth adorne our Court</l>
      <l>With princelie reuelling, and timely sport.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But if th'admired vertues of your youth</l>
      <l>Breede such despairing to my daunted muse,</l>
      <l>That it can scarsely vtter naked truth,</l>
      <l>How shall it mount as rauisht spirits vse</l>
      <l>Vnder the burden of your riper dayes,</l>
      <l>Or hope to reach the so far distant bayes?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>My slender Muse shall yet my loue expresse,</l>
      <l>And by the faire Thames side of you sheele sing,</l>
      <l>The double streames shall beare her willing verse</l>
      <l>Far hence with murmur of their ebbe and spring.</l>
      <l>Bnt if you fauour her light tunes, ere long</l>
      <l>Sheele striue to raise you with a loftier song.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>