<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>C., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107081_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17473</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4293.4</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diatelesma. Nu. 3 : The moderne history of the vvorld, expressing the principall passages of the Christian countries in these last six moneths, whether politicall, or polemicall brought downe from Aprill last to this present. VVherein is comprised much varietie. The content whereof you shall finde in the ensuing table</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 136, that is 134, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ISTORY is but a narration of things done, and needs no Orator to plead for it, either by word or writing; Truth is able to justifie it selfe, and feares not the face of any <hi>Aristarchus,</hi> which will snap at her words, though hee cannot blemish her actions. Her Picture was thus drawne by the pencill of <hi>Apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;</hi> Calumnie, attended with Ignorance, Suspition, Anger, Envie, Fraud, Treachery, and Feare, were placed in a Table, casting filth and dirt upon the white garment, the glorious robe of a more glorious Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin; which shee did but shake, and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againe as illustrious as it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. And what needs an Epistle then,
<pb facs="3"/>to be prefixed before this Discourse? it is not to make the Relation more authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but the expression more passable.
<q>Sint bona, sint quaedam mediocria, sint mala plura.</q> It is the fate of Writers, who must stand to your censures; onely I would informe you, that if any thing seeme
<q>
         <l>Aut obscura nimis, Anglica sive parum</l>
         <l>Non meus est Error, nocuit librarius illis.</l>
      </q> An ingenious Reader can amend, an Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous will pardon it; to whom alone, I dedicate this Discourse. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>N. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>