<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous and frendly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107994_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04794</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107994</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous and frendly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Flovvers of epigrammes, out of sundrie the moste singular authours selected, as well auncient as late writers. Pleasant and profitable to the expert readers of quicke capacitie: by Timothe Kendall, late of the Vniuersitie of Oxford: now student of Staple Inne in London</title>
                 <author>Kendall, Timothy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Shepperd, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 112, 30, 2 leaves, 8째</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the courteous and frendly Reader.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Quo semel est imbuta recens seruabit odorem testa diu.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Verse of <hi>Horace</hi> the Poet (right courteous reader) which I my selfe, by my selfe, haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued true: for hauyng enured my selfe in my greene and growyng yeares, to readyng of Poetrie (an arte in my mynd and censure both princely and pleasant) in riper yeares I could neither by faire meanes bee allured, nor foule mines procured, from embracyng thereof, so greatly therewith was I linked in loue. Wel might I beare and forbeare, refraine and abstaine for a season, but by and by in the turnyng of an hand, with the tracyng ape should I breake the daunce, and fall a scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyng for Nuts. <hi>Naturam expellas furca licet vsque recurrit.</hi> And surely farre discrepant al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue I beene from the opinion of those that deeme Poetrie to bryng nought else, but onely a certaine naked and vaine delectation to the life of man: whiche vnworthy and false accusation is well and wisely confuted of <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo</hi> inueighyng against <hi>Eratosthenes,</hi> who see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="5"/>
to apply hymselfe to be a maintainer and defender of that false and impudent sclaunder: wherefore of mee thereof needeth no refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now (courteous reader) if I should take in hand to pen and paynt foorth the praise of Poetrie, and Poets inuentions, I feare mee too long my labour would laste: onely thus muche I dare boldly affirme, that no where shalt thou finde profite and pleasure better linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than in the worthy woorkes of prudent Poets. For <hi>Flaccus</hi> sayeth.
<q>
         <l>Omne tulit punctum qui miscuit vtile dulci.</l>
         <l>The price and the praise he gaineth alone,</l>
         <l>Who profit &amp; pleasure both knitteth in one.</l>
      </q>
Wherfore sundrie the most learned of all ages, of all landes and languages, haue bestowed no small labour in the moste laudable practise of Poetrie. For example: amonge the Italians, <hi>Bembus, Pontanus, Flaminius</hi>: Among the French men, <hi>Borbonius, Salmonius, Muretus:</hi> Among the Germans, <hi>Eob훮nus, Stigilius, Sabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>: Among the Scots, <hi>Bucchananus:</hi> whom <hi>Carolus Vtenhouius</hi> prettily praiseth in his <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stichon,</hi> writyng thus (in <hi>I Sanna. H Francast. A Flam. H Vid. A Nauger. P Bemb. Italos: Mich Hosp. Adr Torneb. Io Aurat. Gallos: &amp; Georg. Buchan. Scotum.</hi>)
<pb facs="5"/>
      <q>
         <l>Tres Italos Galli senos vicere, sed vnum</l>
         <l>Vincere Scotigenam non valuere nouem.</l>
         <l>Three Frenchmen did Italians six</l>
         <l>for learnyng great excell:</l>
         <l>But from them all one Scot alone</l>
         <l>doth heare away the bell.</l>
      </q>
Now (courteous reader) of all sorts of Poems, &amp; Poesies, none (mee thinketh) are more pithie and pleasant, than pretty, shorte, witty, quicke and quippyng Epigrammes: in the which kind of writyng <hi>Marcus Valerius Martialis</hi> is counted cheefly to excell. Wherfore out of him (as sundrie other most singular authors) haue I translated and taken sundrie short, propper, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie &amp; pleasant verses, and Epigrammes, for thy no little profite, and great delectation: marrie this I must let thee vnderstand, that as well out of <hi>Martial</hi> as the rest, I haue left the lewde, I haue chosen the chaste: I haue weeded away all wanton and woorthlesse woordes: I haue pared away all pernicious patches: I haue chipt &amp; chopt of all beastly boughes and br훮ches, all filthy and fulsom phrases: Which I thinke none will mutter at and mislike, but suche as delight more to drawe of the dregs, than drinke of the delicate liquour. I do giue them vnto thee by the name of <hi>Flowers of Epigr훮mes, out of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
<pb facs="6"/>
the most singular authours selected.</hi> For the whiche, if thou shalt thinke well of mee, and thanke mee, I shall (God willyng) shortly as conuenient leisure shall serue, either augment these, or publish more for thy delight and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. In the meane tyme take these in good part (I beseche thee) whiche were made of mee.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Cum mihi vernarent dubia lanugine malae.</l>
   </q>
   <closer>VALE.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>