<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           <author>Braham, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107244_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19169</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5580</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107244</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 <author>Braham, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The auncient historie and onely trewe and syncere cronicle of the warres betwixte the Grecians and the Troyans : and subsequently of the fyrst euercyon of the auncient and famouse cytye of Troye vnder Lamedon the king, and of the laste and fynall destruction of the same vnder Pryam, wrytten by Daretus a Troyan and Dictus a Grecian both souldiours and present in all the sayde warres and digested in Latyn by the lerned Guydo de Columpnis and sythes translated in to englyshe verse by Iohn Lydgate moncke of Burye</title>
                 <author>Lydgate, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>320 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the battayles betwixte the Grecyans and the Troyans before the laste and fynall euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cyty of Troy (as an his<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storye worthye of eterne memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye hath passed through the pennes of sundry famouse Poetes and great clerkes, Grekes, and Latynes, as Homer, Vergyle, Ouyde, and others, whych for that theyr workes ther of came to the handes of most men, haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hytherto ben holden as chiefest reporters of that hystorye. Of whom neuerthelesse part lye by affection towardes theyr countreythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as Homer fauourynge the Grecyans, and Virgyle and Ouyde the Troyans, and partelye breakynge out (as who sayth) into theyr poetycall fictions, the historye was so peruerted: that the verye trouthe therof is not to be had in theyr dygestes. What we maye then hope to fynde of the trouthe, in theyr do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges that haue onely laboured as transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Virgyle &amp; Homer into theyr peculyer and vulgare languages, as it is easelye to be consydered. Of whome, although some I do confesse haue learnedlye and that ryghte well perfourmed theyr enterpryse therin. Yet hath there ben other some, so beastly bolde to vndertake w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out eyther wyt or any learning, to translate the same history namelye the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedes of Virgyle into englyshe, not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge searse any word what Virgile mēt in all that worke. As by example, if a man stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyouse of that historye, shoulde seke to fynde the same in the doynges of Wyllyam Caxton in his leawde recueil of Troye: what shoulde he then fynde thyncke you? assuredlye none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge, but a longe tedious and brayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les bablyng, tendyng to no end▪ nor hauyng any certayne begynnynge: but proceadynge therin as an ydyot in his follye, that can not make an ende tyll he be bydden. Muche lyke the foolyshe and vnsauerye doynges of Ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, whom Iuuinall remembreth, that after he had wryt his booke to the iuste volume, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led then the mergentes and outwarde sydes with his madnes, whych after both that with in and wythout consydered tended to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose at all. whych Caxtons recueil, who so lyst wyth iudgement peruse, shall rather thyncke his doynges worthye to be nūbred amongest the trifelinge tales and barrayne luerdries of Robyn Hode, &amp; Beuys of Hampton, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as a monumēt of so worthy an history. Yet hath there not wanted the faythful &amp; trew reporters of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> historye, as Daretus the Phri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyan, and Dytus the Grecyan, who both cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryouse of the worthy dedes of theyr countrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, &amp; both lykewyse presēt in al the sayd war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res haue dyligently regestred the same, whose bokes although by iniurye of the tyme, were not of long extant, yet at the last beyng founde at Athenes, haue sins by dewe conference ben founde hooly to agre, in all the dyscourse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd warres, which the labores aswel of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rete as Dyte, at the laste came to the syght &amp; handes of the lerned and dylygent Guydo of Columpna, who hath syncerelye and pythely digested the same in one latyne volume. And so by these degrees, hath bene at the laste by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diligence of Iohn Lydgate a moncke of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, brought into our englyshe tonge: and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested as maye appere, in verse who estra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nayle as well in other his doynges as in this hathe wythout doubte so muche preuayled in this our vulgare language, that hauynge his prayse dewe to his deseruynges, may worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be numbred amongest those that haue chefe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye deserued of our tunge. As the verye perfect disciple and imitator of the great Chaucer, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> onelye glorye and beauty of the same. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theles, lykewyse as it hapned y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Chaucer to lease y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prayse of that tyme wherin he wrote beyng then when in dede al good letters were almost aslepe, so farre was the grosenesse and barbarousnesse of that age from the vnderstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of so deuyne a wryter. That if it had not bene in this our time, wherin all kindes of learnyng (thancked be god) haue as much flo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryshed as euer they did by anye former dayes within this realme, and namelye by the dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of one willyam Thime a gentilmā who laudably studyouse to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> polyshing of so great a Iewell, with ryghte good iudgement tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail, &amp; great paynes causing the same to be {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and stamped as it is nowe read, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayde Chaucers workes had vtterly peryshed, or at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lest bin so depraued by corrupcion of copies,
<pb facs="3"/>
that at the laste, there shoulde no parte of hys meaning haue ben founde in any of them. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the same iniurye almost hathe happened to this wryter in this his Pamphlite of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerciō of Troye: being printed about .xlii. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res agoe, euen then in the tayle (as it hapned) of the dercke and vnlearned times, suche was then the ignoraunce of bothe the prynter and correctour, neyther of them as it shoulde seme eyther learned or dnderstandynge englishe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same worke is so falsed in his verse by either lacke, folishe surplus, or displasinge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that thereby y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sentence and cōsequētlye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> historye is so confused and obscured, that in most places, there can be almost nothing ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered therof. I therfore muche meruaylinge how it hath happened, whether for lack of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, (as in dede they be but few) or otherwise y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this boke being thouly trew &amp; sincere english Cronicle, of that so worthye an historye wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon so many great clerkes in other langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges haue voutsafed theyr trauayles, hath not before this tyme (whiche in deede lacketh not that haue already by their doynges shewed them selfes to haue ryght good iudgement in our language) bin purged of his falsyties, &amp; redused as nere as mgiht be with conueniēce to the auctours translation. Haue therfore ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken vpon me as one studyous of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> language of my countreyth although I must confesse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> least able of a great nūbre, to, bring again this historian into lyght somewhat I truste more perfecte &amp; polished then before, not inuertyng therin eyther matter or sentence, but leauyng that to the auctour his commendacyon, as of right apperteineth. Natheles if I would haue ben withdrawen from this myne attempte, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> that which I myght iustly haue recompted w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> my selfe, that is, to consyder how great an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise he vndertaketh, that goeth aboute to brynge perfected into the handes of men y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted labours of former wryters, and howe lyttle thanke is gained therby I shulde neuer then haue dared, to haue bestowed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one penful of yncke. Consideryng that who so trauaylethe in other mennes doynges is thought to do nothinge of him selfe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in some mens iudgmentes hath before hād the thancke that he deserueth. But if any such be that shal so discerne hereof. I may accompt his iudgement like indifferent as is that mās that should iudge, that he whych hath purged an ouergrowē felde of thornes, &amp; stones, hath also sowed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same wyth corne, &amp; shuld in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> end be no partaker of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fruytes or increase therof. And surelye who so euer shall take vpon hym thus to trauayle in others mens labores, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ye lyst to waye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> difficultie of the thing or the commoditye &amp; pleasure that shall ensewe to theym that be desirous to vnderstande the pryueties of our englishe tonge, me thincketh such one worthy of his praise. And that I may say my iudgemēt his trauayle ought not to be thought muche lesse then is his that wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of his owne inuēcyō. For if the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> quickenes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> witt, thother declareth the ripenes of iudgement. He hauyng a large fielde to discourse in, thother cōpelled withī y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> straight boūdes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> writer. The one may vse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> frugalitye of inuencion &amp; wytt, thother must so moderate the same, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> when he hath greatest neade therof, yet may he not passe the lmittes. Not one onely copye must be perused, but ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny exāplars loked ouer, &amp; therin he maye not chose such as lyketh his fantasye, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which shal seme to come more nere to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> auctours me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge, and maye most please and pleasure the readers. So that therin, he shall be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to put on (as it were) theyr fantasye, and yet that so sparinglye, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he maye neither adde nor take awaye, but where he shalbe thereto ledd by certaine &amp; sure iudgmentes. Al which thinges how easie they be, who so list practise the same maye sone discerne. Thus muche I haue thought good to set in wrytynge before this worke. To thend the readers maye be ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monyshed, that this without other is the very trewe and sincere englishe historyan of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable battels, destinye, and vtter euersion of the auncient and famouse Cytye of Troye and also to preuent the malice of suche, as shal happlye accompte my trauayle herein, rather rashe presumpcyon, then anye vertuouse imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion of wel doynge.</p>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>Robert Braham.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>