<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Iohn Caluine to all the true worship∣pers of God, which desire the kyngdome of Christ to be rightly restored in Fraunce, Saluation.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107376_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4397</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107376</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Iohn Caluine to all the true worship∣pers of God, which desire the kyngdome of Christ to be rightly restored in Fraunce, Saluation.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Commentaries of that diuine Iohn Caluine, vpon the prophet Daniell, translated into Englishe, especially for the vse of the family of the ryght honorable Earle of Huntingdon, to set forth as in a glasse, how one may profitably read the Scriptures, by consideryng the text, meditatyng the sense therof, and by prayer</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 120 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ Iohn Caluine to all the true worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God, which desire the kyngdome of Christ to be rightly restored in Fraunce, Saluation.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough these sixe and twēty yeares wholly I haue not vnwillyngly wāted that our natiue countrey, whose beauty doth entice so many straūgers from farre to come vnto it, because I had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite nor desire to dwell in that land whence Gods truth, pure Religion, and the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of eternall saluatiō was banished, forth of the which Christs kyngdome was vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently driuen, neither yet at this day do I greatly desyre the same: yet to forget the people and nation of whom I was borne, it were neither any poynt of humanity, neither lawful so to do. And I do suppose that I haue with playne proofes declared how carefully and earnestly I haue desired to profit our countreymen: vnto whom it may be that myne absence hath bene profitable whiles that by my study and trauayle they haue receiued more fruite. The cōsideration of the which commodity hath not onely wyped away all grief, but hath made myne exile swete and comfortable. Wherefore seyng all this long tyme I haue laboured publikely to profite my coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymē of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and haue not ceassed priuatly also to styrre vp the slouthful, to pricke forward the sluggish, to encourage the fearefull, to exhorte the doubtfull weakelynges vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seueraunce: I thought it now my duety in this daungerous tyme, not to slake my diligence towardes thē, especially God geuing me so good occasion to do it. For when my Lectures wherin I dyd interpretate Daniels Prophecies should come abroad, nothyng could haue come to hand more aptly, then hereby to shew vnto you deare brethren in this glasse, how y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> God willing to proue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fayth of his at this time with diuerse exercises, hath prouided by his maruelous wisedome, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and establish their myndes with old examples, lest they
<pb facs="4"/> should at any tyme faynt, beyng shaken with most greuous stormes and tempestes, or at least if they should at sometyme come into any doubtfull distresse, that they should not fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the ende. For though there be appoynted to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of God a course or race beset with many daungers and impedimentes: yet who soeuer shall diligently read and consider this booke, he shall finde therin conteyned, what so euer is apte and meete to direct and guyde hym that is not slouthfull but forward, from the begynnyng to the end of hys race: and the good and stoute champions shall know by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that they are sufficiently armed to the combate.</p>
   <p>First of all an history, though lamentable, yet very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table doth offer it selfe, that Daniel and hys companiōs were caryed into captiuity whiles the Kyngdome and Priesthode continued: as though God had giuen vp to extreme calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and misery the chief floure of the chosen people. And what at the first vew can be thought more vnmete, then that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren endued as it were with Angelical vertues, should be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as a spoyle, and made slaues to a proude Conquerer, whē as the most wicked men and proude contemners of God dyd remaine at home safe and sound? Is this the reward of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes and of an innocent lyfe, whiles that the wicked flatter them selues because they escape vnpunished, that the Saintes &amp; Godly should suffer the punishment which they had deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Howbeit here do we see as in a lyuely image, that God when hee spareth and pardoneth the most wicked for a space, doth try hys seruauntes lyke gold and siluer, lest it should greue vs to be cast into the fornace of triall or fynyng fyre, whiles that prophane persons do lyue in rest at pleasure.</p>
   <p>Secondly there foloweth an example of more then mans wisedome, and of a singular continency, with an heroicall stoutnes of mynde, whiles that those godly young mē beyng tempted in that tēder age with courtly delicates, do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly passe ouer without regarde, the daynties that were offered them, through their temperancy: but because they perceiued them selues to be craftely assaulted that they might fal by litle and litle from the pure worship of God: to the entēt that they might rid them selues from these snares of Sathan, they do boldly and constantly despise, not without great daunger of death, the honor embrued with poyson.</p>
   <p>There doth folow a cruell and more fearefull cōbate, with a notable example of an incredible and meruelous constancy, whiles that the companions of Daniell are not moued with
<pb facs="4"/> cruell threatnynges to pollute them selues with the worshyp of the image, &amp; at the length are ready to defēd the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp of GOD, not onely by their owne bloud, but also by the sufferyng of most horrible tormentes. As for the goodnes of God that shyneth forth in the end of this tragedy, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable to arme vs with an inuincible fayth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy.</p>
   <p>After this there doth folow the lyke battaile and victory of Daniel hym selfe, whiles that he had rather to be cast to the ragyng Lyons, then to absteine but three dayes from an open profession of hys fayth, lest by deceitfull dissimulation he might prostitute the holy name of God, to the derision of the wicked: and he beyng deliuered forth of the denne, as it were drawen forth of the graue most miraculously, triūpheth ouer Sathan and his cōfederates. Heare come not forth any Philosophers, which can dispute subtily and cunnyngly of vertues in their studyes when they are quyet: but here haue we the infatigable constācy of holy men in the exercise of true holynes, to styrre vs vp with open cry to folow them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnles we be altogether vncapable of doctrine, we must learne of those Scholemasters, diligently to take hede, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Sathan lay hys baytes of flattery, that we be not snared therewith: or if that he assayle vs with violence, that we may repulse and breake hys assaultes with a bold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of death and all daungers. If any man will make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, that the exāples of both these deliueraūces that we haue named, are rare: I do graunt that God doth not alwayes stretch forth his hand from the heauens, to saue hys in lyke sort, but (which is sufficient for vs) he hath hereby testified that he will be the faithfull guerdon and keper of our lyfe so oft as it shall be in any daunger, and that we are not exposed to the lustes of the wicked, but that God can assuage their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and outragious enterprises when he seeth it good. But we may not onely looke vpon the end and successe, but we must behold how boldly &amp; courageously these holy men haue offered them selues to death for the defence of Gods glory, neither doth their prompt and ready myndes in offeryng them selues as sacrifices, deserue lesse prayse because they were deliuered.</p>
   <p>Now, amongest how many styrres and stormes was the Prophet tossed those <hi>70.</hi> yeares that he lyued in Captiuity, it will be good to consider. He was so well treated of no kyng as he was of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> whom he yet found a ragyng
<pb facs="5"/> beast. The other were more cruell, whiles by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sodaine death of <hi>Balsazar</hi> and the wynnyng of the Citie, he was brought vnder new Lordes, the <hi>Persians</hi> and the <hi>Medes.</hi> Who fiercely breakyng in like cruell enemyes, as they made all afrayde, so is there no doubt but that they wounded his heart. And though he were wel vsed of <hi>Darius,</hi> so that that seruitude was tolerable: yet through the enuy and cursed conspiracy of the noble mē, he was then in most daunger. Howbeit as he was more carefull for the commune safety of the Church then for his owne quietnes, in what sorow was it like that he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and with how great grief was he troubled, when that present state dyd shew none end of the cruell oppression of that miserable people? He did depend assuredly vpō the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Ieremy. But this was an incomparable paciēce and constancy, that his hope dyd not languish nor decay beyng so long differed, yea that it was not vtterly drowned beyng drawen through so many ragyng floudes and tempestes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter such sondry sortes.</p>
   <p>Now come I to the Prophecies, wherof the former were sent vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Babilonians,</hi> partly because God would adourne his seruaūt with certaine speciall markes which should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell that most proude nation, though now in conquest, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and honour hym, partly because it was conuenient that his name should be had in reuerēce amongest those pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane persons, that beyng in authoritie he might exercise the office of a Prophet more freely towardes hys owne nation. And after that his name was famous amongst the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> God committed vnto hym Prophecies of great importance, which should peculiarly belong to the elect people: but God dyd so apply them to the vse and commoditie of the auncient people, that they should both mitigate the sorowes with cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable remedyes, and comfirme the waueryng myndes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the commyng of Christ, and also he had no lesse regarde of our tymes. For that which he dyd speake before of the transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and vanishyng shew of the Monarchies and of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastyng stability of Christes kyngdome, is no lesse profitable to be knowne of vs this day then of old. For God declareth that earthly power which is not founded in Christ, is transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and he threatneth a sodeine ruine to all kyngdomes which set them selues vp in pride, to obscure or hynder the glory of Christ.</p>
   <p>The Kynges that now reigne in so great kyngdomes (vnles they willyngly come vnder Christes dominion) shall
<pb facs="5"/> feele in the end by dolefull experiēce, that this horrible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth also apperteine vnto them. For what is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable then to robbe hym of his right and authoritie, by whose protection their dignitie is preserued? yet do we see how few of that number do receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Sonne of God offering hym selfe vnto them, yea how they busie them selues, how they seeke all shiftes and try all extremities, rather then they will suffer hym to enter into their borders: and many of their Counsellours diligently apply their whole industry, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and study to shut vp all passages. And yet in the meane season, that they pretende the name of Christianity, and do boast them selues the chief defenders of the Catholicke faith, it may easely bee confuted as a vayne bablyng, if it be once knowne what the kyngdome of Christ is by a true and right definition. For the scepter of his kyngdome or hys throne is nothyng els but the doctrine of the Gospell, neither doth hys Maiesty shyne any where els, neither doth he otherwayes atteine his empire, then where all, both high and low, with quyte myndes to learne lyke shepe, do heare his voyce and folow whether so euer he calleth. But they do not onely eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywhere reiect this doctrine, wherin true Religion and the lawfull worship of God is conteined, wherin the euerlastyng saluation of man and the true felicitie consisteth, but they ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe it and driue it farre from them with manaces and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, with fire and with sword, and leaue no force vnattemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to driue it forth of their borders. And what a blindnes is this and how monstruous, that they whom the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne of God doth call most louyngly vnto him selfe, cā not abide to receaue him and to imbrace him? But many (such is their pride) thinke their authoritie nothyng if they submit their scepters to the hye Kyng. Others will not suffer theyr lustes to be brideled: and as hypocrisy doth blinde the wittes of them all, they desire darknes and are afrayd to be drawen forth into the light. Yet is there no more wicked pestilēce thē the feare which <hi>Herode</hi> had: as though he would take away earthly dominions from the Monarches, which offereth the heauenly kyngdome to euery one of the least and poorest of the people. The next is, that whiles one doth looke at the doynges of an other, their mutuall league doth reteine them all fast bound vnder the yoke of impiety with a deadly knot. For if they would earnestly apply their mynde to enquire what is truth and right, yea though they would but onely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their eyes, the knowledge therof were euident. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="6"/> this is perceiued vsually for the most part, when Christ springeth forth with his Gospell, that also great styrres do aryse: vnder an honest pretence they cast away the heauenly doctrine, to prouide for publike tranquillity.</p>
   <p>I must graunt in deede, that such alterations &amp; chaunges as do engender publicke disturbance may be iudged odious: but God hath great iniury offered vnles we attribute thus much to his power, that he can establish the kyngdome of his sonne, and assuage all tumultes that boyle forth agaynst him. Although heauen and earth should rolle together, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp of God is farre more precious, then that the least dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing therof can be recompensed with any ransome. How be it they do burden the Gospell with a false sclander, which do imagine that it is the matter &amp; cause of tumultes and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roares. It is true in dede that God doth therein thunder with the vehemency of his word, wherby he shaketh the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and the earth: but whiles the Prophet bryngeth in this sentence to commend the word and to bryng credit therunto, that shakyng is blessed and much to be wished. And assuredly vnles Gods glory be set aloft in his due place, whiles all flesh be humbled and brought downe, the pride of men which doth lift vp it selfe agaynst it, will neuer giue place but forced and throwne downe by the strong and mighty hand of God. And if so be that the earth trembled at the publishyng of the law,<note place="margin">Exo. 19.18</note> it is no maruaile if the power and office of the Gospell appeare more glisteryng and glorious. Wherfore we ought more louyngly to embrace the Gospell, which whiles it ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the dead from the helles, and openeth the heauēs to them that were vnworthy to lyue vpon the earth, it sheweth a straunge power and vertue, as though all the elementes dyd agree to our saluation.</p>
   <p>But loe, the tumultes and tempestes do spryng forth of an other fountaine: because that some tymes the nobility and such as are in hygh honor in the world, do not willyngly suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the yoke of Christ: sometymes the foolish multitude spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth what soeuer is for saluation, before they haue any taste what it is: and part like porkes delite them selues in their filthynes. And others, as though they were enraged with infernal furies, are outragious in slaughters. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil doth pricke forth those that he hath, wholly to be his slaues with most excessiue fury and outrage, to bryng all to hurly burly. Hereof commeth the soundyng of the trumpets, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of come battailes and warres, whiles that <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> that
<pb facs="6"/> Prelate of <hi>Rome,</hi> with hys red and bloudy route and horned beastes, rageth so fiercely agaynst Christ and seketh for helpe on euery side of his filthy Clergy, the which altogether al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not fedde in like daynty sort, yet doth it eate browys and collaps out of the same pot, and many hungry companiōs flye vnto thē to offer their seruice. A great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the iudges which were wōt to stuffe their bellyes with Idolatrous feastes, do fight for their kitchyns &amp; bellycheare: but chiefly the deuill sendeth raylers out of the cloysters of Monkes and Friers and forth of the dennes of dimsicall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, who are like bellowes to kindle the fire.</p>
   <p>I do passe ouer the priuy craftes and wicked conspiracies, wherof they can be the best witnesses vnto me, that are the greatest enemies to Religion. I name no man: it is enough to haue pointed them with the finger, who are but ouer well knowne. It is no maruaile though they which depend of the chaungeable state and the diuerse ishue of thynges, continue doubtfull in this confused inuasion of so many beastes. But they reiect the blame of their infidelity iniustly and wickedly vpon the holy Gospell of Christ. Let vs graunt that all hell with the infernall furies do enter into battayle: will God sit idle in the heauēs to forsake and betray his owne cause? And when he shall stand vp agaynst them, can the craftes of men be they neuer so subtill, or yet their forces be they neuer so great, let God to haue the victory? The Pope, they say, will bryng with hym a long trayne of confederates. It is a iust reward of incredulity, to tremble at the sounde of the fall of the leafe. And what say you, vnwise and vnprouident coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saylers? let Christ go that no new straungenes do trouble vs. Therfore shall you perceaue shortly after this, how much better it had bene to haue God mercyfull, and despisyng all vayne terrours, to rest vpon his protection, then to prouoke hym to open warre, lest they should offend and displease the euill and wicked spirites. Surely when all thynges are exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to the vttermost by the Popes defenders, the supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which hetherto hath reigned, is none other but an euill thyng well and cunnyngly layd vp and placed, which they thinke ought not to be styrred, because it semeth that it can not be touched without some losse and detriment. But vnto them which desire Gods glory, and which are setled in true Religion, there must be a farre contrary purpose, that is, that they do so offer their labours vnto God, that they commit all the ishues therof to his prouidence, who if he had promised
<pb facs="7"/> nothyng vnto vs, peraduenture there might be some iust cause to feare and continually to doubt: but seing that he hath so oft testified that hys assistance shall neuer fayle in the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forth of the kyngdome of his Christ, it is the onely way to do well to settle our selues in this confidence.</p>
   <p>Now it is your partes good brethren, as farre as euery mans power and office shall lead hym, to be carefull with all his harte, that true Religion may recouer hys pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect state. I nede not to rehearse how diligently hetherto I haue endeuored my selfe to cut of all occasions of tumultes: so that I haue the aungels and you all my witnesses before the hye iudge, that the faulte was not in me that the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Christ hath not had a peaceable procedyng without any hinderance: and I suppose that my diligence hath some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng profited, that priuate men should not passe theyr boundes. Now, although God by his merueilous power hath spread the restoryng of the Church farther then I durst hope for it,<note place="margin">Luc. 21.19</note> yet is it mete to remember what Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth his scholers, euen to possesse their soules in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. Vnto the which purpose also the vision of Daniel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayneth: that the stone wherby all the kyngdomes which fought agaynst God were broken, was not formed nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioned by mans hand: and though it were rude and vnpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, yet dyd it grow into a great mountaine. Of the which thyng I thought good to admonish you, that amongest the thondryng threatnyngs, you should quietly wayte that these empty cloudes may be driuen away by the heauenly power, and so vanish. Yet am I not ignoraunt (to passe ouer the fires of thirty yeares) what vnworthy troubles ye haue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer these last sixe monethes: how ofte in sundry places the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous people haue broken into your assemblyes: how oft you haue bene assaulted with stones and with swordes: how your enemyes haue layne in wayte for you, that they might oppresse your peaceable congregations with suddayn force at vnwares: how some haue bene slayne in their owne houses, some in the hye wayes: how the bodyes of the dead haue bene trailed in derision, the womē rauished, many men wounded, one woman great with child and her child also thrust through, the houses broken and pulled downe.</p>
   <p>But although more cruell thynges were yet at hand, that you may declare your selues the Disciples of Christ rightly instructed in his schole, you must indeuour your selues that no rage of the wicked which deale so outragiously, do driue
<pb facs="7"/> you from that moderation whereby hetherto onely they haue bene ouercome and disapoynted. And if so be that the length of tyme do make you weary, remember oftentymes that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Prophecy, in the which the condition of the Church was liuely expressed. God declared then vnto his Prophet what battayles, what troubles, what griefes and perils the <hi>Iewes</hi> should suffer from the end of their captiuity and ioyfull returning into their countrey, vntill the commyng of Christ. Now y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> likenes of times causeth the same thyngs to be agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto vs, and therfore may be applyed to our vse. <hi>Daniel</hi> reioyced for the miserable Church which had ben long drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a depe floude of miseries, when he collected by the count of the yeares, that the day of deliueraunce spoken of by <hi>Ieremy</hi> the Prophet was at hand.<note place="margin">Iere. 25. c. 12. &amp;. 29.10.</note> Howbeit he had an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere that the state of the people should be more greuous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that liberty were restored, so that they should scantly haue any breathyng tyme from their continuall miseries. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> continued hys hope seuenty yeares not without great and bitter sorow and many griefes: but now God increasing the tyme seuenfold, doth strike hym to the heart, as it were with a deadly wound. Neither doth he yet onely pronounce that the people should be subiect to new troubles, when after long tyme they beyng restored had gathered strength, had built their Citie and Temple: but in the first begynnyng of their mirth, when they had scarce tasted the swetenes of the comfort, he doth appointe them vnto misery. Now, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the calamities which folowed soone after (wherof there is a long rehearsall) seyng we tremble at the hearyng onely of them, how dolefull and bitter do we thinke they were to the rude people, how horrible and fearefull a spectacle was it to see the temple prophaned by the bold malice of a cursed ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, the sacrifices mixed with filthy pollutiōs in despite, and all the bookes of the law to be burned to destroy all Religiō, and all those to be drawen to the same fire, who soeuer dyd confesse playnly and constātly that they would perseuere and continue in the worshyp of God? How could the tender and weake behold this without great feare of heart? And this was the purpose of the tyraunt, that cruelty should driue the weakelynges to fall from their Religion. Vnder the <hi>Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees</hi> there semed some release to be offered, the which yet was straight after deformed with most cruel slaughters, and neuer wanted sorrow and grief. For where as their enemy did farre excell them both in multitude and warlike munition, they all
<pb facs="8"/> thought nothyng better which had taken weapons for the defence of the Church, then to hide them selues in the dennes of wild beastes, or to wāder in wildernes with great pouerty and scarcity of all thynges.</p>
   <p>There was also an other kynde of temptation, that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hipocrites, vnder a false pretēce of zeale (as <hi>Daniel</hi> sayth) did ioyne them selues to <hi>Iudas</hi> and his brethren. By the which subtilty Sathā spotted the garisons that <hi>Iudas</hi> had collected, with great infamy, as though they had ben a bande of theues and robbers. But nothyng was more lamentable vnto good men, then to see the Priestes them selues, as euery man was caried with hys ambition, to betray the Church and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of God with wicked packyngs and practises. Neither was that holy office onely sold and made a marchandise, but it was bought with mutuall slaughter and parricides. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of came it that all states of men, all though Circumcision and sacrifices were in vse, were polluted in the ende through the manifold corruptions which spred euery where without punishment: that it was a straunge wonder to wayte for the kyngdome of God when Christ came into the world, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few are therfore named with this commendation. If now in that miserable deformity of the Church, in the manifold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations, amongst those great terrours, the spoylyng of their countreys, the robbyng of houses, and amongest the daūgers of death the Prophecy of <hi>Daniel</hi> hath susteined godly mindes, when as Religion was yet wrapped in darke shadowes, and the doctrine almost extinguished, and the Priests themselues beyng degenerate dyd tread all holy thynges vnder foote: how shamefull shall our tender weakenes be, vnles this cleare light of the Gospell, in the which God hath shewed his fatherly face towardes vs, lift vs vp aboue all impediments, and stablish vs with a constancy that can not bee wearied? For as there is no doubt but that the seruauntes of God then dyd apply vnto their age, to mitigate the sorowes of their present miseryes, all such things as were spoken by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes of the Babilonicall captiuity: so is it our part to haue our eyes bent vpon the miseries of our fathers, that we refuse not to be gathered vnto that Church, vnto whom it is spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken:<note place="margin">Isa. 54.11. Psa. 129.1 2.3.4.</note>
      <hi>O thou poore one, affiicted and tossed with tempestes, that hast no comfort, behold I will receaue thee:</hi> and the which in an other place, after she hath cōplained that the plowers haue plowed theyr backe, and the wicked haue made long forrowes as it were in a field, yet doth she glory straightwayes that their cordes
<pb facs="8"/> were cut by the iust God, that they could not preuaile. And the Prophet hath not onely encouraged vs by the examples of those tymes to hope and to patience, but he hath ioyned an exhortation taught by the holy spirite, which is extended to the whole kyngdome of Christ, and is peculiar vnto vs.</p>
   <p>Wherfore let it not be greuous vnto vs to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongest the number of them, who as <hi>Daniel</hi> sayth: <hi>Must be tryed by fyre that they may be made white:</hi> seyng that the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable felicity and glory which springeth therof, doth more then sufficiently recompence all the griefes of the crosse. And though many can feele no taste in this doctrine, but thinke it vnsauery, yet may not their dulnes or sluggishnes make vs the more slouthfull: and therfore must we print deepely in our hartes that which the Prophet straight way pronounceth: that the wicked shall do wickedly, because they will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand nothyng: but the children of God shall be endued with the knowledge of God, that they may kepe the right course of their godly vocation. And it is necessary to consider the fountaine of that brutish blindnes, that the heauenly doctrine may be sauery vnto vs. For there is none other cause why the most part doth despise Christ and his Gospell, but for that they carelesly flatter them selues in sinne, and are neither wakened with any feare, neither with the sense of their mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, neither with the terrour of Gods wrath, to desire ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly and feruently the redemption which onely doth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from the bottomles depth of eternall destruction: and in the meane tyme beyng snared with pleasures and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allurementes, or rather betwitched thereby, they are all together careles of the blessed eternity of the other lyfe. And though there be many and sondry sectes of them that contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteously despise the doctrine of the Gospell, and in some of them pride is more euidēt, in some others tender weakenes, in others a certaine dronkennes of the mynde, in others a sleapy dulnes: yet shall we finde that this contempt commeth of a prophane careles security: because that no man doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into him selfe, to examine his owne miseries to finde a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for them.</p>
   <p>This is a monstrous madnes, when Gods wrath and curse lyeth vpon vs, and his iust vengeance doth presse vs, that we should cast of all care, and stand in our owne conceit, as though nothyng were to be feared. How be it this vice is to much commune: that those that are gilty a thousand tymes and are worthy a thousand tymes of eternall death, whē they
<pb facs="9"/> haue sleighty done a few foolishe ceremonies vnto God, they bryng them selues into a slepe, or rather a deadly and senseles traunce. But seyng that <hi>Paul</hi> doth pronounce that the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Gospell is deadly vnto all those whose myndes the deuill bewitcheth: it is necessary for vs that will taste the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour therof vnto lyfe, to set our selues before Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment seat, and often thether to sommon our consciences, the which beyng wounded with an vnfeined feare, the reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation which Christ hath purchased for vs with his bloud so precious, may be estemed of vs accordyng to the price and worthynes. Wherfore the aungell preacheth of the eternall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice which Christ hath sealed with the sacrifice of his death, to cause men to reuerence Christes doctrine, &amp; to wynne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vnto it: and he expresseth also the maner and meane to obteine iustice: because (sayth he) iniquity is done away and purged. Therfore whiles the world doth run mad after theyr lustes and wantonnes let the consideration of the cōdemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which we haue deserued make vs afrayde and hūble vs before God. And whiles carnall men do glutte them selues with earthly pleasures &amp; delites, let vs embrace with feruent desire, this vncomparable treasure, in the which an assured fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity and blessednes is layd vp for vs. Let our enemies prate as they please, that they also care how to haue God mercifull vnto thē: seing they are of this opiniō, that men must doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call vpō God in prayer, it is plaine that they ouerthrow the chief foundation of our saluation. Let them taunt &amp; scoffe at our fayth as long as they list, so that we feele assuredly that no man can attaine to this prerogatiue but by the benefite of fayth, with a free and quiet conscience, trustyng to the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christ, to call God father.</p>
   <p>But the study of Religion and care of godlines will neuer take force in vs as it ought to do, vntil we do learne to lift vp our myndes (which are alwayes ouer prone to the earth) and exercise them in a continuall meditation of the heauenly lyfe. In the which point the meruelous vanity of mankynd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth it selfe, that whereas al men can speake plausibly, as they were Philosophers, of the shortnes of this life, yet no man aspireth to that eternall and euerlastyng life. Wherfore it was not without cause that <hi>Paul</hi> when he cōmēdeth the faith &amp; charity of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Collossians,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Col. 1.2.5.</note> sayth that they are encouraged by y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hope which was layd vp in the heauēs. And speakyng in an other place of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> end of the grace which is reueled vnto vs in Christ,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.12.13</note> he sayth that we are taught therby to deny all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes
<pb facs="9"/> and worldly desires, and to lyue soberly and iustly and godly in this world, waityng for that blessed hope &amp; glorious commyng of the great God euen our Sauiour Iesus Christ. Let this hope then &amp; waityng for his cōmyng rauish vs vnto it, and lose vs from all worldly impedimentes: and the more that the world is infected and farced with the careles lyfe of the Epicures, it becommeth vs to labour so much the more earnestly, that this infection creepe not into vs also, vntil we come to the marke appointed. And although it is to be lamē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that such a multitude doth willyngly perish, yet lest the wicked madnes of them which thus cast them selues downe purposely to their owne destruction should trouble vs, let an other lesson of <hi>Daniel</hi> comforte vs, that there is a sure salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion layd vp for all them that are found written in the booke. And although our election be hyd in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> secrete coūsell of God, which is the first cause of our saluation, yet seyng that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption of all that are grafted into the body of Christ by faith in the Gospell is nothing doubtfull: be you content with this testimony, &amp; go forward courageously in this that you haue blessedly begon. And though you must yet fight a longer bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile (as I pronounce vnto you that there are yet behynd so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer skyrmishes then you do looke for) with what rage so euer the madnes of the wicked shall boyle forth, and though they bryng all the deuils of hell to helpe them, remember you that your full course is appointed by the heauenly moderator and ruler of the field, whose lawes and orders you must obey the more willyngly because that he doth minister strength vnto his souldiours vnto the end. Now because it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to forsake the state, place, and office wherein God will haue me to remaine, this my labour dedicate vnto you, shalbe a pledge of my carefull desire to helpe you, whiles that my pilgrimage beyng en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the heauenly father of great mercy shall gather me together with you into his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styng heritage. The Lord gouerne you with his holy spirite, my deare beloued brethren, and defend you with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection agaynst all the enterprises of the enemyes, and strengthen you with an inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible power.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At Geneua</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>14. Calend of September. 1561.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>