<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107177_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4374</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107177</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Aphorismes of Christian religion: or, a verie compendious abridgement of M. I. Calvins Institutions : set forth in short sentences methodically by M. I. Piscator: and now Englished according to the authors third and last edition, by H. Holland</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Dexter, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 197, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <argument>
      <p>THis copie past from my ragged hand after the first writing to the presse immediatly: for the whole worke had not aboue six whole dayes. The worke-men were wearied with the hand, and the hast might haue caused many errours. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I must desire thee, good Reader, friendly to correct these few saults which haue escaped.</p>
   </argument>
   <head>Errata.</head>
   <p>Pag. 1. marginall note or, for, as. pag. 1. Aphoris. 3. of yeares and iudgement. pag. 22. Aphoris. 3. commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for commandeth. pag. 39. Aphoris. 2. supply as if they had read. pag. 42. Aphoris. 11. put out stirring. pag. 48. Aphoris. 17. which came of, for which came not of Abrah. pag. 56. first line, the last, for and at the last. pag. 69. Aphoris. 9. reade by faith imputed vnto vs. pag. 115. Aphoris. 5.7.8. in for into. pag. 125. Aphoris. 6. of for and. pag. 144. Aphoris. 16. were for we. pag. 172. se &amp; 8. panem Domini and panem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum transposed. pag. 181. Aphor. 14. put out that.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>