<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader, encrease of all
spirituall vnderstanding and euer∣lasting
peace.</title>
           <author>M., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107028_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07826</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18199</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107028</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader, encrease of all
spirituall vnderstanding and euer∣lasting
peace.</title>
                 <author>M., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the threefolde state of man : wherein is handled, 1 His created holinesse in his innocencie. 2 His sinfulnesse since the fall of Adam. 3 His renewed holinesse in his regeneration</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas, of Berwick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 426, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the reader, encrease of all
spirituall vnderstanding and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E doe here offer, to thy chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
consideration and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
entertainment (gentle
reader) a rude description
of the spirituall state of man.
The which if perhaps thou desire to haue
for shortnesse, plainnesse, memory, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shions
sake comprised in some one memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
worde, may not vnfitly be tearmed
<hi>Adam</hi> in whome onely all these three e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states
did concurre and may be seene, or an
anatomie of the soule. A matter of all other
most needefull to be knowen and learned:
yea most worthy to be handled, explaned,
dilated, and illustrated with all care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,
it being that wherein the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of man doth wholly consist. For
this is eternall saluation to knowe God, to
wit, the father creating vs according to
his owne image in perfect puritie: the sonne
redeeming vs by his pretious bloud from
sinne and miserie: the holy spirite sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and renewing vs by his grace to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
glory. In the which respect we haue
<pb facs="8"/>
thought that our time and laboure, the
which it hath pleased God in mercy to ty to
the study of his holy word, coulde not be
better bestowed then in commending this
sauing knowledge vnto others: and that by
this meanes which nowe we vse, being
thereunto moued by some vrgent reasons,
wherewith it is not needefull that either
we shoulde trouble you, or you your selfe.
Our purpose, or rather our desire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour
is, to make an anatomie of the soule
of man, to lay open before thy eyes the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
partes and faculties of it, together with
the naturall and supernaturall holinesse and
sinfulnesse of them.</p>
   <p>Wherein we haue endeuored to vse as
great breuitie and plainnesse as we coulde,
and as the greate varietie and difficultie of
the matter, which often is verie intricate,
woulde permit: auoyding both loathsome
tediousnesse and vnprofitable obscuritie, as
thinkeing it much better not to speake
then not to be vnderstoode, and to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
darke matter in rude and homelie
tearmes, then with enigmaticall parables
to amaze and mocke the reader. We haue
rather applied our stile to the capacitie of
the simple, and the good of all, by insisting
most in those thinges whereby we may be
<pb facs="8"/>
edified in the knowledge and obedience of
Christ, then affected the curious scanning
of subtile questions, seruing rather for
the whetting of the witt, then the sauing
of the soule. And yet as they haue their vse,
which is not to be neglected, so we do
breifely touch them as occasion is offered.
Desiring the readers, especially those who
doe not professe learning, to picke out of
this treatise some matter of edification ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then of contention, and with me to
leaue needlesse controuersies to scholasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
exercises, and men of nimble wites.</p>
   <p>But what needeth all this, will some man
say: this laboure might verie well haue bene
spared, and much better bestowed: consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
the abundance of knowledge, the
daily and continual preaching, the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie
of bookes written of all argumentes
both diuine and prophane, in such swarmes
and huge multitudes, that men haue no
leasure to looke on the faire inscriptions,
much lesse to peruse the tedious and irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
bodyes of them. Yea men are so cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and deceaued with vaine repetition of
olde matter glosed ouer with new wordes,
and so amazed with straunge doctrines late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
deuised, that they haue in a manner
giuen ouer the buying and reading of
<pb facs="9"/>
bookes, esteeming it a fruitelesse and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishe
mispending of mony and time, both
which ought to be reserued for necessary
vses, and a needlesse disquieting of their
mindes being already sufficiently groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
and settled in the trueth. Howe iust and
true this complainte is in some respect we
are not nowe to discusse: but for this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
whereof we speake, it were to be wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
if so it pleased God, that it were true
indeede, and that we had as great plenty
of the true knowledge of God and of
sounde teachers of the trueth, as of the
stones in the streetes, and in one worde,
that all the people of God did prophecy.</p>
   <p>But is it so indeed? doth knowledge,
religion, godlinesse, and all the meanes
thereof, or not rather palpable ignoraunce,
atheisme, and superstition abounde in most
places? Yea surely, the complainte of the
Prophet <hi>Hos.</hi> 4. 1. is more true, There is no
knowledge or feare of God in the land.</p>
   <p>But what of this? is this to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
to the want of bookes and other
meanes of knowledge? Surely there is
no cause why either some places shoulde
complaine of want, or any loath their
plenty in this behalfe. We haue moe
bookes learnedly and godlely written, then
<pb facs="9"/>
we doe vse well, and yet we might vse
moe well then we haue. There is and
will be as long as the church remaineth here
on earth a needfull vse of newe tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates,
comments, sermons, catechismes,
and determinations, as newe reasons, illust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
and methodes are inuented: as
newe doubtes, controuersies, errours, and
hereses doe arise: as this or that vice doth
raigne: and as men giue themselues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly
to the studying of particular heades
of doctrine, and partes of the worde of
God. All is not to be expected at any
one hand: where one sleepeth, another
waketh: one is concise and darke, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
large and plaine: one drie and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,
an other full and pithy. Yea in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
writers thou shalt see the admirable
variety of spirituall giftes, and so be stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
vp to praise the greate bounty of God
towardes his church, The doctrine accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge
to godlinesse (as th' apostle defineth
diuinitie) is a large feilde, wherein ten
thousand may laboure continually, and all
haue elbow roome: yea each one differ
from the rest, not onely in manner but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
in matter and argument, howsoeuer all
doe handle the same doctrine in generall.
As for diuersitie of opinions in some cases,
<pb facs="10"/>
it ought not any way to trouble or offend
any man, seing that it is the will of God,
that while we remaine here on earth, we
shoulde both knowe and prophecie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by speaking or by writing, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
but onely in part. A fewe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions
doe not, as it may seeme, either
impaire the credit of the teachers, or shake
the faith of the hearers of Gods worde,
but rather strengthen and vpholde both.
For hereby it appeareth, that men doe not
(as the prophete compalineth. <hi>Iere.</hi> 23.
30.) steale the worde of God one from
an other, deliuering for sounde doctrine,
whatsoeuer the most doe holde and
teach, rather then what they themselues
doe thinke: and so conspiring together in
a compact forme of doctrine, are not many
but onely one witnesse: but are in their
consciences before God perswaded of the
trueth of the gospell of Christ, which they
professe and teach. It is but folly to looke
for in mortall and earthly men, a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
and angelicall harmonie void of all
iarring. It is rather our partes to labour in
repressing that pride and selfel-oue of our
corrupt natures, whereby men carnally
minded and affected, are made to swell in
anger and hatred against those who doe
<pb facs="10"/>
not in euerie respect daunce after their pipe:
being more alienated from their brethren
for some fewe contradictions, then ioyned
together in Christian loue, by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sente
in all the points of religion beside.
Milde and modest dissenting worketh out
the trueth, as the striking of flintes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
doth sparkes of fier: and that often
commeth to passe <hi>errando via reperta:</hi> Try
all and keepe the best.</p>
   <p>But we trust that no man will make
these obiections which we imagine, or
thinke, much lesse speake euil of that which
is intended for his good. That which one
misliketh, another perhaps will approue:
and if studentes waste their inke and we are
their pens, and printers venture their paines
and paper, they for their owne exercise,
or in any other good intente, these in hope
of some honest aduantage, and both of
them in a Christian desire of profiting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
let not that trouble thee. The losse
is their owne, and it is lawfull for them to
doe with their owne what they list (we
speake of priuat censures not of publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint)
vse mennes writings and giftes, if
thou thinke them for thy purpose: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,
take their good meaning (and ours
among the rest, not the worst of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="11"/>
in good part, and so leaue them to
their likers or to their losse.</p>
   <p>Lastly we desire the friendly reader to
put to his helping hand to this worke which
we haue taken in hande to amend what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
is any way amisse, to adde to this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect
and light delineation of mans soule,
not onely the essentiall partes which are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
but also the sinnewes of strong proofes
and argumentes, yea the cleare colours
of examples and other illustrations: and
Lastly to further our endeauours if he think
them any way profitable for the Church
of Christ by harty good will and earnest
prayer.</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt especially I do intend,
and commend this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise
vnto you (my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
countrimen, and kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke,
the inhabitauntes
of the towne of <hi>Barwicke,</hi>
euen to all that in the saide towne doe call
on the name of the Lorde Iesus, being there
vnto moued by nature it selfe, which would
wringe euen out of a flinty hearte speciall
affection and harty loue to the natiue soyle.
Yea what is more meete or more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
in all reason and equity then that we
<pb facs="11"/>
shoulde retourne the first fruites of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure
thither from whence we came, and
where we had our first being and beginning.
Accept I pray you at my handes this poore
mite in steade of some riche pledge of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained
loue. Who knoweth, but that by
the blessinge of God, this small graine of
mustardseed, the simplest of a thousand
bookes euery where extant, being careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
receaued by you into your mindes and
heartes, as into good ground, may sende
foorth plentifull fruite of spirituall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
and vnfained obedience vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
life: and may growe to that bignesse,
that the birdes of the ayer, may builde their
nestes in the braunches of it? for so I hope,
that you acknowledging this simple and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned
peece of worke, to be the fruite
of your owne feilde, will euen in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
the more willingly eate of it, and
perhaps the more happily digest it, to the
encrease of that stature, and strength
whereunto you haue already attained in
Christ. In whome I doe earnestly desire
that you may growe from grace to grace,
labouring to glorifie him by a holy and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable
life, as he hath shewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
most mercifull and bountifull vnto
you.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
He hath powred foorth his blessings both
temporall and spirituall vpon you with a full
hand: he hath giuen vnto you greater plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of thinges needfull for the preseruation
of the body, then to any other place in the
land beside: he hath freed you from the
dregges and reliques of poperie, wherewith
the whole country farre and neare euen a
hundred miles from you, is infected as with
a common plague: you haue godly &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
preachers of the worde of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
not many, yet moe then some scores
of miles in the countrey will afforde: and
lastly you haue leasure and opportunitie of
seruing God, and vsing all the meanes of
your saluation greater then any other hath, as
all men knowe. What wanteth then, but
onely this, that you be not wanting to
your selues, but carefull in vsing these sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
blessings to your owne edification
and eternall saluation? That so your Church
may be renowmed in all places, as florish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in the multitude, not of verball pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours
mocking God and deceauing
themselues with an outwarde shew of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
but of sincere and sounde Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
seruing God in spirite and trueth, and
labouring to kepe a good conscience in
the wholl course of their liues, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="12"/>
God and towardes their brethren.
Thus crauing pardon of you for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
in this behalfe, I commend you to
God, and to the worde of his grace which
is able to builde you further and to giue
you an inheritaunce among those that are
sanctified. The lorde be with you all now
and euermore. Amen. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Written <date>this first of Aprill. 1596</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>your harty well-willer and countriman T. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>