<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>F., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107708_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16897</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107708</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>F., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The beginning, continuance, and decay of estates : vvherein are handled many notable questions concerning the establishment of empires and monarchies. Written in French by R. de Lusing, L. of Alymes: and translated into English by I.F</title>
                 <author>Lucinge, René de, sieur des Alymes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 163, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He world had neuer more Bookes,
Bookes neuer lesse woorthy matter:
learned, vnlearned, all will be writing,
and of these the most affecting the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
names of Authors, become the
authors of their inglorious names.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Pro captu lectoris habent sua fata libelli.</l>
   </q>
   <q>
      <l>The Readers skill,</l>
      <l>Makes Bookes thriue well or ill.</l>
   </q>
   <p>But the true life of a worke, and sound discretion of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
appeere not more in the well handling, then wise choice of a
subiect. I know diuers courses may meete with one end, as
many waies leade to one citie, so may one theame entertaine a
world of inuentions; but of these (like the same meate serued in
in seuerall fashions) some few onely shall carry the true pleasing
relish and temper; the rest (as knots in names) stand rather for
ornaments or flourishing differences, then matters regardable or
of consequence: well may the will or appetite for a time transport
vs, but reason as soueraigne must in the end controle and checke
vs. In the compasse of my obseruations, I haue seene discourses
and stiles, otherwise hollow and vnsound, sway euen the best
iudgements, not alone to allowance, but imitation. Whether this
were the infection of ignorance, that seasing the most might
spread to the best; or the tyrannie of fashion, which must, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
monstrous, (if our selues will not seeme monstrous) be
followed, I know not: one thing I am sure of; time hath discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
their weaknesse, and trueth his concealed daughter is come
to light, when such light owles liue (or to say better) die con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
<pb facs="6"/>
to perpetuall obscuritie. This worke seemes to haue passed
the pikes of such dangers; it hath for a sufficient time vndergone
the view and censure of the best discerning nations of Europe: it
hath beene taught to speake both their and the old Roman lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage:
if England should not now affoord it kind entertainment,
I should thinke it in an error (not to say of iudgement) of custom,
as being not yet cleere of the imputation it carries of harshnesse
towards euen woorthy strangers; but since I finde (as doe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
that suffer) that this discourteous fault is laid vpon the
common sort, and the contrary extolled in the gentrie &amp; persons
of more eminent quality, <hi>Vilia miretur vulgus:</hi> We will appeale
from their ignorance, to the more generous and better bredde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings.
And to awake these, let me tell them, they shall
finde it a discourse not faint or languishing, but such as like a wel
breathed runner, gathers more strength towards the end of the
race, then was bewraied in the beginning. Now to others which
shal perhaps obiect, that the scope hereof lying out of our distance,
asketh as small heede, as it smally concerneth vs; I answere, that
then the gout or gangrene is not to be regarded because the great
toe onely hath it. Time and sinne may one day (which God turne
from vs) make vs more sensible, and this subiects debating more
necessary: such as it now is, or may prooue (Reader) I heere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
it to thy view and censure. I know some acquainted with me
and my courses, will expect rather matter of mine owne, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
inuention. They haue reason in this, howsoeuer I haue abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie:
but I cannot yet forget an honest learned Physician I once
obserued, who (it seemes) to spare others, so spent his owne spirits
in the personall practise of his medicinall conclusions, as his bodie
yet suffers the iniuries of such selfe-offered violence. I am not so
charitable; neither hold I him the vnwisest, that out of others
triall frameth his owne confirming. It is time that begets iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and assurance. And to this purpose I will close with a saying
of that euer most reuerenced Master of moralitie <hi>Seneca, Non
ignoro etiam quae in speciem laborant, dignitatem dico
&amp; eloquentiae famam, &amp; quicquid ad alienum suffragium
venit, mora conualescere.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>