<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Maister Doctour Hunton, D. of Physicke, and his most reuerend and worthily respec∣ted friend, I. B. wisheth all true happinesse in Christ both now and euermore.</title>
           <author>Brinsley, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107968_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18817</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5288</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107968</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Maister Doctour Hunton, D. of Physicke, and his most reuerend and worthily respec∣ted friend, I. B. wisheth all true happinesse in Christ both now and euermore.</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first book of Tullies Offices translated grammatically, and also according to the propriety of our English tongue; for the more speedy and certain attaining of the singular learning contained in the same, to further to a pure Latin stile, and to expresse the mind more easily, both in English &amp; Latine. Done chiefly for the good of schools; to be vsed according to the directions in the admonition to the reader, and more fully in ludus lit. or grammar-schoole</title>
                 <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 320 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Maister Doctour Hunton, <hi>D. of Physicke, and his</hi> most reuerend and worthily <hi>respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted friend,</hi> I. B. <hi>wisheth all true</hi> happinesse in Christ both now and euermore.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering with my selfe (right worshipfull) to whō I should dedicate this small part of my schoole indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, I could bethink me of none to whom it might be more iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly due, then to you; sith I owe vnto you euen mine owne selfe and all my later trauels: for I must needes acknowledge your vnfained loue and tender care for mee, to the glorie and praise of our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God, and to bind my selfe still more



<pb facs="3"/>
vnto his heauenly Maiestie, and euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your owne selfe to testifie my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, all my daies. Because, besides all your regarde which you haue euer had of my health, when as through long affliction by sundrie most heauie trials, and by ouer-toyling both minde and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (in lacke of all meet helps and means, to performe that seruice which I had entered into, and so much desired for the good both of Church and common weale) my life was become most mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and a burden vnto me, by chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the best humors of my bodie into lumpish melancholy, it pleased him, to make you his principall instrument for my recouerie and restoring. Whereby in stead of that heauie dumpishnesse, by which I was made vnfit for my calling, and almost vtterly ouerwhelmed, as you well knowe; that our holy and most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious God, to bee praised for euermore, hath caused me to finde euen heauen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth, so that I can againe reioice



<pb facs="3"/>
in all my labours, and especially in my calling: by which, my ioy in him, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee indeed a continuall feast, yea my strength and health, and such a portion, as in regard whereof I can account base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all earthly things. And secondly, for that loue and fauour, which you haue continually shewed to all my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, so incouraging me therein. And moreouer also, for that you are able to iudge of the hope of this Worke, for the perpetuall benefit of Schooles, by the more speedie and certaine attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both of the singular matter and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine contained in that booke of <hi>Offices,</hi> which I haue thus farre proceeded in. For the book it self I cannot but admire, according to the high commendations giuen vnto it, by the most learned: who preferre it before all others of this kind, which haue beene written by the light of nature alone; for that it doth so diuinely point out the true pathway to all vertue, and guide vnto a right course of life, as if



<pb facs="4"/>
it had receiued direction from the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures themselues. So that it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> graced, as a mirror of wisedome, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse of Iustice, the teacher of valour, a schoole of temperance, the iewell of cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, containing in so fewe leaues, so many excellent instructions, as no other the like. Whence, <hi>Erasmus</hi> wonders tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> a heathen man should write so much to heathens; admireth the equitie in it, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, veritie, sinceritie, agreement of euerie part with right nature &amp; amongst themselues, as also the conscience he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth especially in gouernours, the amiable beautie of vertue which he set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before the faces of all. Yea, he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it strange, that he should write so reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously and so like a Diuine, of helping and rele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uing one another, of procuring and maintaining friendship, of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of those vanities which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sort of Christians doe so doate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And finally iudgeth it most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and meet for schoole-masters to



<pb facs="4"/>
teach, and scholars to learne; and not onely for all young men, but euen olde men themselues againe and againe both to vse and peruse. Inregard of all which, so many learned men haue not disdained to beare it in their bosome, lay it vnder their pillows, make it their companion, which way soeuer they haue gone. Now what I haue done heerein, that all who are truely studious of good learning, though children in yeares, may more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silie beholde and bee more fully parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of these rich treasures, for which the Learned haue had this Worke in so high estimation, I referre to all who are truely learned to iudge, and chiefly to your selfe who are better acquainted with my indeuours in it. For my self, my hope is, that whereas it hath formerly seemed to sundrie so obscure, as that they haue read with very little fruit or delight, because they haue not vnderstood it; that they may now at the first viewe, liuelilie beholde the true lustre thereof,



<pb facs="5"/>
and receiue most sweete content, to cause them euer to delight therein. Which if the Lord shall vouchsafe, as I vndoubtedly trust, I shall receiue the end of my desires, and bee incouraged to proceede to the accomplishing of the rest of it, and euer to be imployed for the common good, vntill I haue spent my last breath for the same. In which vnfained desire, I rest &amp; euer shall</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord most beholden, Iohn Brinsley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>