<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107677_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18071</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107677</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The preachers trauels : Wherein is set downe a true iournall to the confines of the East Indies, through the great countreyes of Syria, Mesopotamia, Armenia, Media, Hircania and Parthia. With the authors returne by the way of Persia, Susiana, Assiria, Chaldæa, and Arabia. Containing a full suruew of the knigdom [sic] of Persia: and in what termes the Persian stands with the Great Turke at this day: also a true relation of Sir Anthonie Sherleys entertainment there: and the estate that his brother, M. Robert Sherley liued in after his departure for Christendome. With the description of a port in the Persian gulf, commodious for our East Indian merchants; and a briefe rehearsall of some grosse absudities [sic] in the Turkish Alcoran. Penned by I.C. sometimes student in Magdalen Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Cartwright, John, of Magdalen College, Oxford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 107, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>OMPEY the Great being put to flight in the battell at <hi>Pharsalia,</hi> by <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> was desirou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to know of <hi>Cratippus</hi> the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, what should be the euent of the warres betweene <hi>Caesar</hi> and himselfe, demanding of him, <hi>an sit Prouidentia?</hi> whether the purpose &amp; decree of God were vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able without alteration? To whom <hi>Cratippus</hi> answered,
<pb n="2" facs="5"/>
not as a Philosopher, but as a true Diuine, saying, <hi>Fatales esse Imperiorum periodos,</hi> the prouidence of God is most sure and certaine; which <hi>Pompey</hi> found most true, in a small time after, when <hi>Caesar</hi> was created the first Emperour of the Roman Monarchy; and which also shall be verified (God willing) in the discourse of this Iournall: wherein is principally shewed, how all humane affaires, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Cities of renowme haue had their Periods in their greatest perfections; to which though they haue ascended <hi>gradatim,</hi> yet they haue forthwith fallen into a retrograde of declination, till they haue beene brought to the lowest degree which misery can allot: So true is that of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
      <q>
         <lg>
            <l>Nulla sors longa, dolor &amp; voluptas</l>
            <l>Inuicem cedunt: breuior voluptas,</l>
            <l>Ima permut at breuis hora summis:</l>
            <l>Nemo confidat nimium secundis.</l>
            <l>Nemo desperet meliora lapsis.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>No chance is long, for griefe and eke delight,</l>
            <l>By course giue place, pleasure hath shorter flight,</l>
            <l>An houre but shor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that presently doth end,</l>
            <l>Doth make the lowest things aloft asc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd:</l>
            <l>Let none too much trust in a prosperous state.</l>
            <l>Let none despaire, but hope for better f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
For in this small discourse wee shall see how vnauoidable destruction doth alwaies attend on the succession of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and aduancement on the posterity of misery: as also the sacking of many Cities, the depopulating of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Countries, the deposing of Princes, and high descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded families of their liues, together with their Crownes and Kingdomes, and that in so short a time, as neuer the like was executed in the antique world. Two reasons haue moued me to set downe this Iournall:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he causes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> moued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Authour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> write this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>urnall.</note> The one for that I haue not yet seene any that hath made a full description of these parts, as they are at this day, which I hope shall be performed by my selfe, who spent much time in those Countries, being familiarly conuersant (to helpe my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="3" facs="5"/>
herein) with many <hi>Sultanes,</hi> and principall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders in the Kingdome of <hi>Persia,</hi> as also diuers Ianiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who serued in the warres betweene the great <hi>Turke</hi> and the <hi>Persian.</hi> The other is for that I doe verily perswade my selfe, that this discourse will breede much delight vnto any indifferent Reader, when hee shall vnderstand how mighty the forces are of the Persian King, a capitall enemy of the name of Christ, as also in what termes he standeth at this day with the great Turke, what Kingdomes he posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, what Prouinces are subiect vnto him, his worship, his religion, his kinde of gouernment, their weapons, their manner of fight, their forme of battell, the reuennues and expences of that Crowne, and in a word whatsoeuer else is necessary to be knowen.</p>
   <p>Finally, you haue here described the seueral Nations, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuations, Cities, Riuers, Mountaines, and Prouinces, which I haue seene and passed by. It is not my purpose to write any thing of the Ilands in the <hi>Mediterranean-Sea,</hi> which we sailed by, and are so much renowmed in old writers, viz. <hi>Maiorica,</hi> and <hi>Minorica, Corsica, Sicilia, Malta, Cephalonia, Zant, Candia, Rhodes,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> howsoeuer many excellent things might be spoken of them; yet see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are so well knowen to most of our nation, I omit to write, binding my selfe to a true relation of what mine eyes haue seene in more remote parts of the world, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting the iudgement of the vulgars, but contenting my selfe with the conscience of truth, beside which (I protest) I purpose to write nothing.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>