<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF Henry Bullinger vpō the Apocalips of Iesu Christ setforth by the Apostle and Euangelist s. Iohn, vn∣to all thexiles for the name of Christ in Germany and Swyserland, of Fraunce, England, Italy and of other Realmes or nations, and generally to all the faithfull where soeuer they be, abiding and lokyng for the cōmyng of Christe oure Lorde and Iudge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1561</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107053_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11837</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4061</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107053</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF Henry Bullinger vpō the Apocalips of Iesu Christ setforth by the Apostle and Euangelist s. Iohn, vn∣to all thexiles for the name of Christ in Germany and Swyserland, of Fraunce, England, Italy and of other Realmes or nations, and generally to all the faithfull where soeuer they be, abiding and lokyng for the cōmyng of Christe oure Lorde and Iudge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A hundred sermons vpo [n] the Apocalips of Iesu Christe : reueiled in dede by thangell of the Lorde: but seen or receyued and written by thapostle and Eua [n] gelist. S. Iohn: compiled by the famous and godly learned man, Henry Bullinger, chief pastor of the congregation of Zuryk. Newly set forth and allowed, according to the order appoynted in the Quenes maiesties, iniuntions. Thargument, wurthines, commoditie, and vse of this worke, thou shalt fynd in the preface: after which thou hast a most exact table to leade thee into all the princypall matters conteyned therin</title>
                 <author>Bullinger, Heinrich</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1561</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56, 699, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE OF Henry Bullinger vpō the Apocalips of Iesu Christ</hi> setforth by the Apostle and Euangelist s. Iohn, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thexiles for the name of Christ in Germany and Swyserland, of Fraunce, England, Italy and of other Realmes or nations, and generally to all the faithfull where soeuer they be, abiding and lokyng for the cōmyng of Christe oure Lorde and Iudge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat this Apocalips was reueled of Iesus christ king of kinges and high Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, our lord from the right hand of the Father, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth by thapostolical spirite, for the saluatiō of al faithfull chieflye of those that shall be in the latter dayes, before the last iudgment, both the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it selfe, whiche is treated, right necessary to be knowē, holsom and excellēt, proueth: And also the simple maner &amp; meane, wherby it is handled being euident and plaine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth. I will speake of ether briefly, Collectyng those thinges only, which seme to be more profitable and more necessary.<note place="margin">Iohn .xvi.</note> The Lorde had sayd in the Gospell, how he wold ascende into heauen, and frō thence wold send to his Apostles the holy Gost, the comforter, which shulde leade them into all truth, and shew them the thinges that ar to come. And that which he sayd he wolde do in wordes, the same verely hath he also perfourmed in dede aboundantly. The holy Gost beyng sent to his Apostles, which induced them into all truthe, and opened to them the thinges that were to come, especially to the Apostle and Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyst. S. Iohn, who receiued this Reuelatiō, exibited to him of Christ, from the ryght hand of the Father, by the mistery of an Aūgel, in the holy Gost, who also by Chryste his commaundement, committed the same to wryting. The summe and ende of the which wryting is this:<note place="margin">The summe &amp; ende of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalipse.</note> That Christ Iesus our Lord, wil neuer fayle hys churche in earth, but will gouerne it with his spirite and worde, through thecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ministery. But that the church it self, whilest it remaineth in this worlde shall suffer many thinges, and that for Chryst and the truthe
<pb facs="7"/> of his Gospell professed. And it openeth al and singular euils in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the church shal suffer, shewing how it must be exercised with common Calamities, as warre, plage famyne and suche other lyke, What it shall priuately suffer of the false bretherne through heresies, schismes and greuous and continuall stryfes, contentions &amp; corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the matter of religion: Finally how terribly it shulde be vexed by the most cruell persecutions of tholde Romane Empire, And laste by the wicked crafts &amp; extreme Tyranny of Antichrist. Al the which thinges apperteyne to this ende, that all the chosen being sufficiently warned before, and prouided, in all ages whilest this worlde shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, may with true faith alone, cleaue vnto Christ our redemer, king and high prieste, only and eternall, and may purely and syncerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse hym, call vpon him, in the innocencie of lyfe, serue him, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently attend after him, commyng to Iudgemente, and to delyuer and saue the godly: But contrarywise, that they dispise all superstitions and the worlde it selfe with those his sondrye religions, felicities and pleasures: and bewar of al vngodlines. And chiefly that they flee An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist which shall com in thende of the worlde, vsurping to himselfe most vniustly the kingdom and Priesthod of Chryst, and greuouslye persecuting the churche of Christ, euen to the laste Iudgemente. In the whiche at the laste he with all his adherentes, shall be throwen downe hedlonge into Hell.</p>
   <p>And. S. Iohn beginneth this holsome matter of Chryste hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,<note place="margin">The fyrste Chapter of the Apocalips.</note> Lorde, king and high Bishop, whose wonderful and most good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly description, after the Apostolicke maner, he placeth in the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng, as the foundation of the whole worke. The same descriptiō dooeth so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ately setfoorthe the Lorde, that all the churche may easely know,<note place="margin">What thinges are treated in this boke, &amp; in what order.</note> dispersed throughout the whole worlde, in Chryst oure Lorde all thinges to be accomplished, what so euer he had sayd before shulde be fulfilled in him, namely that he shulde be exalted, one to the ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of his father, into all celestiall glory, power and maiestie &amp; there to be kinge of kinges, of all other most mightye, and the true and only hygh Byshop. Sauiour gouernour, Lorde and generall defendour of the Catholycke churche. For blessed. S. Iohn not only saw him such him selfe, but also exhibiteth him such, to be sene of vs all in thys hys wryting so godly, by a most bryght and goodly vision. And moreouer to thintent it myght be knowne to vs all, in what sorte our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Chryst, king and priest sitting or working in Heauen on the right hande of his Father, is neuerthelesse in the middes of the catholycke church, wherof he hath a faithfull care, how louingly and fully he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth it, &amp; in best order gouerneth it. S. Iohn sheweth in this his vision, that Christ walketh amonge the seuen golden candlestickes, &amp; holdeth in his right hande, seuen starres. And streyghtway declareth what thing he vnderstandeth by the candelstickes and starres, calling the candelstickes churches, and the starres, Aungels of the churches. That is to witte,<note place="margin">Seuen chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> Messagers, ministers and pastours. For the Lord chose vnto him selfe seuen famouse churches in Asia, with whom he treateth nowe generally and compendiously, vsing S. Iohn for hys
<pb facs="7"/> interpretour: which he doth perpetually in all churches throughoute the world, and will neuer cease to do tyll the worldes ende. For the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth number, whiche is most vsed in this boke,<note place="margin">Chap. 2, and .3</note> and is the numbre of fulnes, comprehendeth in it all churches. Wherfore S. Iohn doeth so propounde, moderate, and temper all thynges that he treateth with these seuen churches, that they may be applied vnto all the Churches that shalbe in the worlde, vntyl the worldes ende, for theyr learnynge and edifiyng. And for the same cause, these seuē churches may be exā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all other churches. For loke what thing then, did please or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please the Lord in those seuen churches, what tyme these thyngs wer reuealed: the selfe same in all other churches, shall please or displease him, so long as the worlde shall laste. And as he wolde haue those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed and taught: so wyl he that all and singular be instructed at all seasons. Therefore in these seuen churches we haue examples of churches moste excellent in dede, and of God derely beloued: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne of moste corrupte, meane also, and finally mixed. And in these al is shewed, what is, or shall be, the disposition, maners and vertues of all the churches in the whole world, and of al tymes and seasons, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the vices of them and remedies of the same. Therfore the Lorde in these instructeth, reproueth, chideth, threatneth, exhorteth, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, promiseth. Wherfore in these we shall see, as it were in a table set before vs, what the true and ryght doctrine of the churche is. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, which is the false and the corrupt doctrine. We shall heare and learne, that the churche beloued of God, must stande styll in the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng of the Gospell, once receyued of the Apostles of oure Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Chryst: and muste loke for no new, nor other mo doctrines, and to haue no nede of other Reuelations: For the churche ys already in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed with a most complete doctrine. There is it taught also, what we ought to do with corrupte doctrines, and teachers. And where it is easy to fall into vices, this boke doth dilligently and plentifully mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister medicines, teaching, how the churche falling downe maie be set vp and repared againe: And here it treateth much of true repentaūce, of the fruites of repentaunce, of the duties of Saincts or of very good workes. Moreouer, it exhorteth the afflicted to patience and constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to the confession of Christes name, withoute feare, and to all godlynes: many times settyng forth the most ample rewardes of god, And also affirming that tourmentes are prepared for the disobedient and reuoltes. By this waie &amp; meane. S. Iohn sheweth to the church how our Lorde Iesus Chryst being in heauen, on the righthande of his father, in the meane tyme, &amp; neuerthelesse worketh in the middes of the congregation of his faithful, inspiring, quickenyng, kepyng and gouernyng it. And agayne, how the church liuing in this world, may l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue notwithstanding in Christ, and be quickened of him, of whom it dependeth wholye, whom only it regardeth and in whom it is preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And who wyll not acknowledge this handlyng of the matter, to be all together Apostolicke, and right well grounded in the doctryne of Chryst? But in the worke it selfe, all and euery thynge, shall to vs be muche more euidently declared.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>But where as Christ in the Gospel hath said, that the church his welbeloued spouse, shulde be exercised with sondry afflictions, in the whiche notwithstanding,<note place="margin">The church is subiect to tēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions.</note> he wolde neuer faile her: Nowe in dede frō the right hand of his Father, he recompteth moste plentifully and in a most goodly order of all the dollefull destenies of the churche, to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that whilest the churche is subiecte to sundry euilles, she may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member these thinges, and coumfort her selfe, lest she beyng discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with aduersitie, she begin to doubte of the good wyll of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, and fall againe to Idolatrye forsaken, into the errours of theyr Fathers, and into the slippery pleasures of this worlde: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that she go forewarde in the Religion of Chryste once receyued, that she holde on throughe constante patience to professe Chryste, to cleaue vnto him vnseparably, that at the length we maye also be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the same, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heauēly countrey. Which is verely the marke and ende of our lyfe, &amp; the course of all faithful in this miserable world. Howebeit,<note place="margin">Chapter .iiii.</note> wheras in the calamities and persecutions of the faithful, and in the felicitie &amp; triumphing of the infidels, the minde euen of the holyest seruaunt of God, is sore moued, and greuously tempted, before he come to declare the heauy and miserable destenies of the church, he setteth foorth vnto them, a moste beautifull type or figure of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende, holy▪ and euermore blessed Trinitie, wherin is setforthe, to be sene of theyes of all men, the vnspeakeable wisdome of God, power &amp; maiestie, the iuste gouernement of the same, and holy iudgement in all thinges: And is also declared, that almightie God the father, by that Lambe, that is, by hys sun, our onely redemer, in the vertu of the holy Gost, doth gouern well althinges, what soeuer they be eyther in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or in earth. And also the very destenies of the churche, which are written in the boke of his eternal prouidence, closed with seuē seales. There appereth the Lamb of God,<note place="margin">The seuen hornes of the Lambe. <hi>Chap. v.</hi>
      </note> setforth with seuen hornes: That is furnished with most ful power aswel princely as priestly, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test of al, and in all the most absolute. The Lamb receyueth, that boke of the ryght hand of hym that sitteth in the Throne, and vndoeth and openeth in order those seuen seales. For he receyueth of hys father all power, bothe in heauen and in earth. And that the Lambe alone ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth those seuen seales, it conteyneth a swete mistery, and ministreth a singular comfort to the faithfull. For where we beleue, that the Lābe of God, our redemer Iesus Christ doth loue mankind so excedyngly, that neyther in heauen nor in earthe, maye any thyng be founde, that loueth vs more intierly: And now see the very same, and none other to open the seuen seales,<note place="margin">Seuen seales.</note> which opened, sondry calamities issew out by and by, into the worlde: Who wold double, the same to be sent to him for his health, since they are sent not without his prouidence and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, who directeth al thinges for the saluation of his chosen? vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the which thinges, that notable matter is added, that al the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites Angelicall, thelders also, and all heauenlye creatures, worshyp God and the Lambe, prayse and commende his righteousnes, and for his excedyng good gouernement, geue him immortall thankes. For therof we miserable mortall men, inuironed with synful fleshe, ought
<pb facs="8"/> to learne, that we shuld acknowledg also, the iustice of God in all hys workes and not mumer at his gouernement and most rightfull iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: but rather to worship God, to submit vs vnto him, to prayse his righteousnes, and geue thankes for his moste holy gouernmente, and to crye with the prophet, thou art iust O Lorde, in all thy wayes,<note place="margin">Chap. vi.</note> and holy in all thy workes. These thinges, being on this wise promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and the mindes of the faithfull, thus instructed and prepared, in the opening of the seuen seales, seuerally is accompted and rekned vp, what and how greate euils shuld inuade men, from the which not so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faithful liuing in this world, shuld be free. Wares, slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, famine, pestilences are recyted, and suche other lyke plages: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne persecutions, seditions,<note place="margin">Gospel or Consolation.</note> and a great deale worse then al these the seducyng, and distroying of men through corrupt doctryne.</p>
   <p>But because this boke of the Apocalippes, is most euangelicall &amp; apostolical, it mingleth doubtles in all that declaration, often tymes ioyfull thinges with sorrowful, and comforteth the faithfull exceding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in moste and greatest daungers. And therefore in the calamities,<note place="margin">Chap. vii.</note> troubles, euils and corruptions declared hitherto, the Aungel of God is brought in, who marketh the elect of God, in theyr foreheades: and all they in dede, throughe the goodnes and custodye of God, are saued from perdition. And of these are accompted innumerable thousandes. Wherby we learne that the mercy of God is moste ample in sauing of men: and that we ought to hope well, of the saluation of oure elders,<note place="margin">We must hope wel of the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of oure forefathers.</note> wherof though the most part lyued vnder the corrupt tyme of Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie, yet followeth not thereof, theyr saluation to be doubtfull, at the least euen for this cause, that we see, that God had, &amp; hath his church at all tymes, euen when they be most daungerous: To haue hys sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to haue suche as worship hym, whiche like as in times paste, haue not bowed theyr knees to Baall. Al the which through his vnspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able goodnes and mercy he hath saued from perdition, and mercyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clensed, from all corruption.</p>
   <p>And out of the seuenth seale,<note place="margin">Seuen trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets. <hi>Chap. viii.</hi>
      </note> are brought consequently seuen trō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, by the which are denounced greuous conflicts of the faithful and infidels. Yet before that these things are expounded, Chryst is shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Throne of God, making intercession for vs. And to him are the faithful sent, in their perils, to craue helpe of him, succour, and deliueraunce. And the Deuil, master of lyes, bloweth the one, sente to his men: Againe the holy spitite of God, soundeth the trompet to the Sainctes. They ioyne together in battell here, the godly and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the disciples of the pure, and of the corrupt doctrine, the soldiours of Chryst, and of the Deuil. Here are great daungers, and the minds of the godly ar more greuously afflicted and tempted with peruerse doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynes in the churche, then with the cruel sworde of tyrantes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maner of calamities. Here are sondry heresies resited, which impugne and corrupt the euangelical veritie. And as by the seuen seales he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstode al maner of calamities, by the iust iudgement of God powred out vpon the worlde: so vnder the seuen trompets, he comprehendeth al heresies in the world, and pernitious opinions against thapostolical
<pb facs="9"/> doctryne. And sheweth that amonges those corrupte deprauations, Mahometrie and Papistrie, did moste excell. He describeth the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and tedious clergie of the Pope,<note place="margin">Chap. ix.</note> whiche to men is euen intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, vnder the kynde of grassehoppers. And Lawrence Valla, a man excellently learned, though he was a Romane borne, and that of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble house. Where the libertie mete for Christe, was of him more este<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then so hard and monstrouse a bondage, coulde not refrayne, but inueyghed against the Popish clergie, and said: I verely yf I haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fayth at all, beleue nothing to be more hatefull, neyther to God, nor to other men, then so greate a licentiousnes of the Clergie in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall matters. And no lesse euidently expresseth, the Turkishe crueltie, vnder the kind of terrible horses breathing out smoke and fyres. By all the which thinges, he setteth forth the church to be moste miserab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicted and tormented, vtterly after the same sorte, that we see thē vexed at this day, vnder the moste vnhappie papistrie, &amp; mahometrie.</p>
   <p>Againe yet lest any man shuld be in so great euils discouraged, and shuld thinke that God,<note place="margin">The Gospel, or consolation.</note> his promesses touching the endes of good and euill men, were vayne, &amp; also concerning the deliueraunce of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, by the last iudgment. Agayne after the disposition and maner A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall, he annexeth and setteth against all these perilles and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,<note place="margin">Chap. x.</note> a most strong consolation. For he bringeth forthe, the Lorde Chryst hym selfe confirming by a solemne othe, that doubtlesse an end of all these thynges shulde come: And that God of hys iustice wyll as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly render rewardes to the godly, and punishment to the wicked. Where he dissembleth not, that Iohn himselfe, shall prophecy again, to write in thapostolicall spirite and doctryne, to kynges, nations, and many people. Moreouer, he affirmeth manifestly that he wyll send in to the worlde,<note place="margin">Chap. xi.</note> teachers of the veritie, and of certayne saluation, which also most sharply, shal rebuke the wickednes, and wicked men, of the moste corrupt last age, shall preache Christ, sincerly, and accuse Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ most greuously. These he shaddoweth by a figure of two excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent doctours. Whom he saith, for the libertie of preachinge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie of fayth, shuld be most cruelly slayne of Antichrist. But he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that these shall receyue of God, most ample rewardes: And that Antichrist shall laboure in vayne to suppresse by fyre and sworde, the preaching of the Gospell: for so muche as the Lorde shall oftentymes stire vp new preachers, which shal lighten the truth obscured. He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth furthermore, that many shal daily reuolt from Antichrists king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that the same finally by the coming of the Iudge, shalbe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly brought to nought, and he maketh no conclusion, at this present in this place of the last iudgement of Christ, but differreth thexpositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or treatyng of that matter, to an other place more cōuenient, which he treateth in the .xix. and .xx. Chapters. And these thinges hitherto hath he spoken generally of the perils, calamities, contentions, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, sectes, and persecutions of the churche of Chryst, whiche shal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise it from the time of Chryst and his Apostles, to the worlds end. He annexeth consequently, a singular or priuate, and that a plentifull treatise of the most greuous conflictes and persecutions of the church.
<pb facs="9"/> For it behoueth chieflye the sainctes, to haue knowne these thynges, that in the veri perilles and afflictions, they may remember this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admonition, and beare in minde, that the Lorde hathe tolde before,<note place="margin">Chap. xii.</note> of the things that they now suffer, who ruleth &amp; gouerneth al things, finally who can and wil delyuer them from al these euyls, when, how, and asmuche as he of his good wyll shall see it good. Firste therfore he propoundeth agayne, generally the partes of this conflicte or strife, a woman clothed with the sunne, crowned, traueling, which is a figure of the faithfull churche: he setteth against her a most fierse and cruel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, I say the great dragon, Red, with seuen heades, &amp;c. A figure doubtles of that olde serpente, the Deuill. After are setforth theyr at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, nature, force and conflictes or fyght.<note place="margin">Seuen heads of the Dragon</note> And here again for a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte it is expressed the victory of Chryst the head, and of the churche, and members of the same. Afterward the Lord by Iohn, rehearseth, seuerally in the vision, the special instruments or members of the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, by the which he assaulteth, and moste cruelly vexeth,<note place="margin">Chap. xiii.</note> and werieth the church. And these instrumentes are, the beaste with seuen heades and ten hornes, and the beast with two hornes, that is, thempire and false prophet, and the image of thempire.<note place="margin">Seuen heads of the beast.</note> These thynges he painteth out after the Imutation of Daniell so liuely, and (as it is sayd) with theyr owne colors, in the .xiii. and .xvii. Chap, that no man can chouse but fele, and muche more perceyue, of whom he speaketh: verely of the olde Romane Empire, and of Papistrie. He calleth beastes after the imitation of Daniell, cruell kyngdomes or empires. And the thyng it selfe declareth, that our very Lorde Iesus Chryst, the head and king of all Sainctes, suffered and was crucified vnder Ponce Pilate, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of Iuri, but sent thither frō Rome, and gouerning althinges in the name of Themperour Tiberius. Agayne, euery man knoweth that the first persecutiō against the Christians, was styred vp by Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Emperour of Rome. The seconde by Flauius Domitian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Rome, which intrapped also the Authour of this worke. And after this we reade of eyght other persecutions or mo styred vp by the residew of Romane Emperours, against the faithful spouse of Christ by the whiche she was cruelly rent in peaces and troden vnder foote. And that for no other cause, then for that she woulde not worship the beaste: that is, that she wold not receyue the superstions and heathen rites of the Romane Empire. I meane the false Gods, and idolatrie of the Heathen. And for that she worshipped one God, alone through Chryst, and cleaued to him &amp; seruid him, after his Gospell. Here ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are excepted Constance, Constantine, Gracian, Theodose, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly and christen princes or Emperours, which be not rekened vnder the deuelish beast. For an Empire or kingdom of it selfe, as. S Paule sayeth, is of God: wherfore yf good men rule, and geue not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer themselues to be ruled of the Deuill, they shall verely appertaine to the body of holy church, and not to the abominable bodi of the beast. In the meane time, whilest that olde Rome wold not seriously repēt, and tourne to Chryst, forsaking theyr false gods and superstitions, at the last it was condemned of Chryst, by the law of like penaltie. For
<pb facs="10"/> with the same measure, that the Romanes met to other nations, with the selfe same, did other nations measure agayne to Rome. Wherfore the Persians, Hunnes, Frenchemē, Alemans, west Gothians, Vā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalles, and East Gothians, invaded thempire, &amp; rent the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in pieces. And at the last, beseged Rome it self, brake in to it, toke it, spoyled, sacked, burnt &amp; destroyed it. And so at the length, the Lord Iesus by iust iudgement, reuenged the bloud of his seruauntes. And Rome lay, and yet lyeth in ruine, and shall neuer be repared to the aū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient beautie. And it behoueth the ruine of it, to remayne in token of the veritie, and reuengment of Christ Iesus: that euen therof al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may gather, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> God wyll be most true in thother promeses of Christ also as yet not fulfilled. Moreouer the Romane Empire westward, laye neglecte without an Emperoure, aboue thre hundreth and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares, from Augustulus, whom Odacer a Germane oppressed, til Charles the great king of Fraunce. And in these times of desolation, that is, of thempire oppressed and extinguished in the west. The Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome, began by little and little to gather to him no smal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and possessions, by the authorytie which he toke vpō him vnder the pretence of Chryst and the Apostles Peter and Paule, tyll such time as he began to reygne also.<note place="margin">The falle of tholde Empire is the rysyng of a new.</note> But tholde Popes, his predecessours, wer not Princes in the Churche, ruling vnder pretence of Religion: but were ministers of the churche, simple pastours and poore. And Saint Paule prophecied, that of the ruine of the Empire, and destruction of the citie, Antichrist shulde spryng vp. For he sayd, only this holdyng now (or, only thys let that now deteyneth) tyll it come to passe that it be taken a waye, and then shall that wicked be reuayled. He signifye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> therfore that Antichrist shuld not reygne, com, nor appere, before tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> olde Romane empire were taken away. For this being ouerthrowē, that the same See of Rome shulde be erected. For Tertullian, who lyued a thousand and three huddreth yeres past, in hys boke of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the fleshe: Who, sayeth he, shall be taken out of the way, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> state of Rome? whose departing, being dispersed in to ten kings, shall bryng in Antichrist. And. S. Hierom in the .xi. question to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gasia. The Romane Empire, sayth he, which now possesseth al naty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, depart and shalbe taken away: and then shal Antichrist come, the welspryng of iniquitie. The same authours, by Babylon in this boke of. S. Iohn,<note place="margin">The two hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beast.</note> vnderstand Roome. And Iohn hym selfe in this boke sheweth, that the seuen headed and mighty olde empire of Rome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, an other beaste shal aryse, and that with two hornes: that is to witte suche a Prynce, whyche shall chalenge to hymselfe, a double rule or kingdome, fulnes, I say, of power, aswell in thynges spirituall as temporall. And this same doth the whole worlde at thys daye acknowledge to be the Byshop of Rome, decked with his triple crowne (vndoubtedly of the three hornes, which accordyng to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of Daniell,<note place="margin">Daniel .vii.</note> eyther brought lowe, or toke away this base &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned horne and Armed with two keyes, signifieng hym to be king and Byshop, the most myghty Monarke, in matters spiritual &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, Christes vicar in earthe, hauyng full power in Heauen and in
<pb facs="10"/> earth. He hym selfe in tymes past, caused men to set vp the Image of the beast: that is, to set vp a new empire, after the Image and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of the olde Romane Empire. Whych thing after it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon in Charles the great, a right noble prince, and furthermore auaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and commen from the kings of Fraunce, to the Germans, which in dede were stoute, Godly, and worthye Prynces. The Byshop of Rome was not ashamed in straunge wise to vexe, trouble, excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, depose, and to substitute others in theyr place, &amp; to styre vp wars in many Realmes at ones, and set them together by the eares, so long till those kynges did frame themselues after hys wyll and appetyte, and wolde fall downe to kisse hys fete: And he hym selfe at the length toke vpō him thempire, &amp; publishing his decrees to the whole world, boasted hymselfe to be the Monarche, or soule ruler of the world, who myght at hys pleasure bothe depose kinges, and set them vp in kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: Finally, that he was supreme iudg in earth, whych may iudg al men, but he hym selfe, may in nowyse be iudged of any man. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lyke as in tholde empire, we sequestred from the cōmunion of the beastes all good men, which were, or liued vnder thempire: so in this new also we do alwayes except the graue and witty, the good &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, and al religious people, which mixed among them, not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde styll in Chryst, but also eyther abhorre and comtemne the beast, or to theyr power fight against him:<note place="margin">The Characte of the beaste.</note> Wherby they come not in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the beast. And this two horned beast, marketh his worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers with a Characte: And those that refuse thys characte, he excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth out of al mens company, so that it is lawful for them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to by nor sel: Yea more he condemneth them for hereticks &amp; schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, for damned and lost creatures. If thou confesse thy self now to be a Christian, and professe with a syncere and loyall hart the belefe or crede of the Apostles, &amp; one holy church of Christ and of al saincts, and dost not aboue all thinges confesse the Pope to be Chrystes vicar in earth, with the fulnes of power, and the Romish churche, which is the mother of all churches, and can not erre: thou shalte seme as yet to haue confessed nothyng, but shalt be sayed rather to be suspected of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy, and therfore to be more straytely examined. This thing can not be dissembled, for it is knowen to all men in the whole world. But to thintent, we shuld not erre in a matter so nedefull to be knowen, and that we might more easely flee Antichrist once knowne.<note place="margin">The nombre of the name of the beaste.</note> S. Iohn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so addeth the nomber of the name of the beast, 666: by the whiche we verely come to the name, or knowledg of Antichrist. For if we accōpt from the settyng forth of the Apocalips, syxe hundreth threscore &amp; syxe yeres, we shal come to the yeare of our Lord .763. To the same time, I say wherin the Bishop of Rome, forgettyng his humilitie, simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, pouertie and also his office and ministerie, set his mynd to beare rule, and receyued exceading great rewards of king Pipine and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, and prepared him selfe away, wherby afterward he cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the high dignitie of thempire. Which thynge in the worke it selfe shall appere more playnely out of historyes.</p>
   <p>And as he did once or twise before, so now also. S. Iohn after the
<pb facs="11"/> Apostolicke maner comforteth the afflicted and faithfull Churche, least haply in this distresse and continuall persecutions of Antichriste it shoulde falle,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Comforte.</hi> Chap. xiiij.</note> and shoulde thinke that religion and the church were cleane forsaken. He sheweth therfore, howe cruelly so euer bothe the ten horned beaste and the two horned beaste do rage, yet stondeth the lambe neuerthelesse in mounte Sion, not as the Dragon in the sāde: And that Christ, hath in this wicked worlde polluted of Antichrist, his chosen churche, which he will moste faithfully preserue euermore and mainteyne, he addeth, that howe muche so euer the beast coueteth to haue the sacred and holye preachinge of the Gospell oppressed, the Gospell shal neuerthelesse be preached, and that clerely, and that Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon shall certenly falle, and the churche of Christe be established. He addeth moreouer for a comforte, that the soules of Saints that at in daunger or suffer for Christe, do assuredly and streightwaye flitte from this corporall death to eternall lyfe. Agayne, that the Lorde is ready to take vengeaunce of all his enemies, &amp; to requyte them aboū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, which he sheweth trymly by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parables of vintage &amp; haruest.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Of the rewards &amp;, punishments of good &amp; euyll.</note>And these things handled on this wyse, he procedeth to declare dilligently, not the laste place of thys booke, of thendes of good and euyll, men, of moste ample rewardes to be geuen to the worshyppers of Christe, and of moste greuouse paines and tormentes to be inflicted to the adherentes of Antichrist. Men of no smalle estimation sticke in these things doubtefull, and the common people herin erre more than shamefully: whilest for the present felicitie of the wicked and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall miserie of the Godly they doubte whether paynes be appoynted for the wycked, or so greate rewardes for the godly. For euen for thys cause fewe kepe theyr standynge, and more laugh at Chryste and hys woorde, and imbrace the presente pleasures of thys present woorlde, followynge the more happie and victoriouse parte.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Chap. xv.</hi> Seuen vials.</note>Therfore blessed Saint Iohn, not wythout cause (the Lorde commaundinge him) bestoweth very muche diligence in declaringe these thyngs exactely. And firste after hys maner he bringeth foorthe seuen Aungels, hauynge cuppes of the plages of God, and thaungels come out of the temple: signifienge the iudgements of God in punis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shynge the wycked to be most ryghtuouse. And the seuenth nombre comprehendeth agayne all maner, and the most ful plages of God. The Aungels powre out these vialles vpon the Antichristianes,<note place="margin">Chap. xvi.</note> the enemies of Gods woorde, and the hard harted that can not repente. For God moste rightuouse plageth the impenitēt woorlde with son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry tormentes: reseruinge yet more greuouse then these, to punishe them in the woorld to come.<note place="margin">Chap. xvij.</note> But especially he exhibiteth the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is to witte, the punishement of the harlot in pourple, I meane of the Pope and the beaste, to be sene. Firste he brought foorth an honeste and noble matrone, to witte, the very spouse of Chryste: Nowe as it wer by opposition he setteth against her a proude whore, that false newe start vp Romishe Churche, who extollinge her selfe braggeth more of her outwarde apparell then of inwarde furniture. And he affirmeth that she shall perish for her greate offences, lyke as
<pb facs="11"/> it is euident that tholde beaste was torne in pieces and burnt. And that strompet that is called the whore of Babilō, sitteth on the beaste. For Rome is the seate of the same church that is called both the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and most holy church. Wherby all men maye see that S. Iohn hath spoken so skylfully, that he hath as it were pointed with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garre (as they comonly saye) whom he meaneth, and of whō he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, doubtles thauncient wryters, as I tolde you a little before, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode by Babylon Rome it selfe. But afterwarde he discourseth at length the destruction of Babylon wyth a maruelouse plentye of playne woordes, as it were powringe out a certen fludde of eloquēce:<note place="margin">Chap. xviij.</note> and compendiously collectynge all amplifications and figures that beautifie the speache, which are any where to be founde amonges the Prophets. But by the way he placeth among these, certen most plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant thyngs of the mariage of the lambe,<note place="margin">Chap. xix.</note> and of the bryde preparynge her selfe to the mariage, and of the certenty of the saluation of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godly and what maner a thinge that blessed felicity is. Whiche finished, he descendeth immediately to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same laste iudgement, whiche I suppose is no where els in the whole scripture, as it is here not only so descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, but also painted out with liuely couloures. For here is described the persone of the Iudge comynge to Iudgement with his saints &amp; with greate power and gloryes. There stonde against him the ranks of his enemies breathing most cruell thinges againste the Saints of God. By and by succedeth the most terrible iudgement, but yet most iuste. For the false prophet is throwen downe into hell, downe is the beaste throwen, and down are cast all wycked and impenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. There is shewed here moreouer the iustice and equitie of thys vniuersall Iudgement in thende of the worlde,<note place="margin">Chap. xx.</note> wherin is punishmēt taken of all persones of what nation, religion degree or state &amp; sexe so euer they be, that are sequestred and alienated from the true religion of Christe. Where both the resurrection of the dead is touched, and the processe of the whole iudgement, is figured. Herunto he annexeth a most ioyfull disputation of the blessed lyfe, shewyng firste generally, what it is, and that it shall most certenlye be geuen to the faithfull, by the which treatise most strongely is beaten downe the distruste or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that is naturally greffed in vs. After pryuatly and plentifully vnder the Type or Image of a most beautifull Citie,<note place="margin">Chap. xxi. xxij.</note> he shadoweth after a sorte, the place &amp; palace of the blessed, omitting vtterly nothing at all, that is either ioyouse, cōfortable, delectable, or preciouse, which he affirmeth not to be in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> court celestiall most aboundantly &amp; worlde without ende. Notwithstāding we know well inough that touching the ioy to come albeit s. Iohn hath hitherto spokē neuer so largely, yet hath there nothīg be sayd worthy so greate a matter, wher both y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical &amp; Apostolicalscrip. saith, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which the eye hath not sene, nor y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eare hath hard, nor yet hath ascended into the harte of man; the same hath God prepared for those that loue him. But those things whiche I haue hitherto drawen into an abridgement (the title and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of the woorke omitted, the order of the booke shewed also by the way). S. Iohn in his Apocalypse deliuered by Christe (as ofte I
<pb facs="12"/> haue said, through the ministery of a most excellent Aungel, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the vniuersall Churche of Chryst, and chiefly to vs, in whom thende of the world hathe chaunced: wherin he hath taught nothyng at all contrary to that, which he hath taught in his euangelicall story, and his epistles.<note place="margin">The doctrin of the Apocalypse is the apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call doctrine. <hi>Iohn .v.</hi>
      </note> In his story he resiteth certen thinges, concernynge the persecutions of the church, by the wordes of our Sauiour Christ Of Antechrist nothing, vnlesse he sayd this only, which many vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stode to be spoken of Antechrist: I came in my fathers name, and you receyue me not. If an other shall come in hys owne name, hym ye wil receyue. In thepistle, he touched by the way Antechristes matter, &amp; sayde:<note place="margin">1, Ioan.ij.</note> dere children, the last tyme is at hand, and as you haue hearde, that Antechrist shall come, euen now many Antechristes haue begon to be. But in this last boke of his. S. Iohn toke vpō hym to declare peculiarly, and in dew order and plentifully, such things as oure lord Iesus Chryste, had distinctly and playnly reuealed to hym of that great Antechrist, and of the perills and persecutiōs of the church. And for that cause he appereth to haue vsed more plētiful copie, and a kind of speach, better furnished, more painted, variable and polished: so that it is no maruell, though the phrase of this boke vary somewhat from the style of his other bokes. Wherof we shal touche somewhat also, in this that followeth. In the meane time you wil say, there wanteth nothing in this boke, if you way euery thing more dilligently, whiche you shulde require of a boke moste euangelicall and apostolicall. We haue in the same, not only expressed, but also well expounded the chief articles of our belefe. Moreouer, innumerable places of the prophets are expounded in this boke. For the whiche cause this. S. Iohn was called of Iohn Decolampadius,<note place="margin">The apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lypse is the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphrasis of the Prophets.</note> not without cause thexpositour of the prophets. And as the Apostles had this peculiar to themselues, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme such thinges as they taught, by the wrytinges of the prophets: So in thexposition, of the boke it shall appere, that this holy wryter. S, Iohn, hathe either borrowed all his thinges of the scriptures, or to beautifie and confirme his writhinges by the scripture.<note place="margin">What excellent and profitable things ar trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this boke</note> Bat chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this boke of. S. Iohn setteth forth the kingdom and priesthode of oure Lord and sauioure Iesus Christ, the power, glory, and maiestie, of his deitie and humanitie, the mistery and veritie of his redemptiō. And I doubt, whether after the Gospel there, may be founde in anye other boke of the scripture more goodly and more godly &amp; fit descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chryste. Neither do I desire, that credit shulde be geuen to these my wordes, let the triall be made of the thinge it selfe. Yea the church also, the chosen spouse of Christ is painted out most beautiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and she with her vertues and vices is touched, also the fall of her, and likewise, the reparation and reformation, and the conflict or fight of the same: here be moreouer described the perils, ayde, and victories: that you may seme to haue herein, an abridgemente of the story of the church. Moreouer, it appereth by this boke what is the true and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere doctrine in the church of God, &amp; which is false &amp; corrupted. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore it sheweth vs also sondry descriptions &amp; figuratiōs of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters most weyghtie, but first and chiefly of that honorable Trinitie, of
<pb facs="12"/> Chryst also (as I said before) our sauiour and iudge. Finally protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and president, gouerning all thinges most iustely &amp; in most good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order for the saluation of his chosen, watching ouer his worde, and ouer his church, and ministers of the same: Iustifieng also, sanctifieng and preseruing all the faithfull, in the felowship of the churche: Puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyng lykewyse all the wicked, with all superstition and vngodlynes. Briefly no where neglecting the chosē, no where sparyng thenemies. Besides this it setteth forth to vs, the description also of the Deuil, &amp; of al his mallice and warre: And setteth before oure eyes also, the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible torments, and paynes that they suffer in hell. It setteth open to vs heauen it selfe, and sheweth what may be the hope of the faithfull: And affirmeth the true resurrectiō of al flesh. In this boke is taught, how great is the grace and mercy of almighty God, howe rightuous he is &amp; true. Here is taught, what is the true repētaunce of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, here are taught the true good workes of the true faythe, what be the duties of true pietie, and what be the holy exercises, dew &amp; to God acceptable of Sainctes in earth. Here are shewed also most diligently those wicked dedes, whiche are to God most hatefull. Here is shewed most plenteously, what shal at the length be thend of good men and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, what shal be the souerayne felicitie, and what the extreme misery and infelicitie. In somuche that this boke maye euen by the thinge it selfe or matter, that it treateth and setteth forthe, commende it selfe to all godly people, and may shew and proue in dede, that it was writtē by the spirite of thapostle.</p>
   <p>Now all these matters are setforth and handled after the Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke maner, and accustomed facion of holy scripture,<note place="margin">By what meane and in what sort these are setforth.</note> playne and ful of perspicuitie. At the beginning God propounded diuine matters, and the which concerned our saluation, as it were vnder a veale, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der figures, not to thintente to darken or obscure them: but rather to vnfolde them and set them foorth. For this maner of declaryng inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible thyngs, by visible, is more fit to teache, more mete to moue, more apt for perspicuitie, and most conuenient and sitting, that things may be more depely imprinted in minde, and the lesse fall out of the same. And therfore we rede that sondry visions, were exhibited to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, as to Abraham, Israell, Ioseph, Moses and others. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes yf you take frō the bokes of the Prophetes, the visions, parables, and sundry figures of speache, how much, I pray you, shall you leaue of theyr doctryne? emongs these, be more notable in visions, Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, Daniel, and Zacharie. Neyther is thys maner of teachyng by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, parables, and sundry figures, takē away in the new testament, lyke as I haue shewed els where. The very story of the Gospel doth figurate and teache most thinges by parables. And. S. Iohn himself in his Gospel, is veri much in the mention of light, darknes, of bread, water, of a Sheperd, and shepe, and suche other lyke. In the meane while I am not ignorant, howe great a difference, there is betwene parables, Metaphores or Allegories, and visions: But who agayne knoweth not, that in teaching, and setting forth of matters the maner of either to be after a sort al one, and of the same effect? For they serue
<pb facs="13"/> for plainnes and perspicuitie. But let suche as think not a misse, that Parables taken of earthly things, differ very muche from heauenlye visions. Consider, how these celestial visions ar exhibited to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle. S Iohn, by Christ now remayning in heauē, and requiring that his seruauntes, hauing theyr mindes lifted vp to heauenly thinges, shuld learne to sauour spirituall matters. Where he yet neuerthelesse hath obserued plaines and perspicuitie.<note place="margin">The boke is plaine and may be vnderstand.</note> I suppose verely this boke to be simple and playne to the faithful, that wil read it attētiuely &amp; with deuotion. I graūt that thold expositours of this boke haue sticked ful oft in expounding the same, &amp; could not alwayes wind thēselues out: but in the meane season it is euident, that the same men haue said oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thē once, that hardely shuld this boke be vnderstand before it wer fulfilled. And in dede to those auncient fathers, the vision of Daniell semed vtterly most obscure. But whē such things wer accomplished, as he had hid vnder figures, there wanted not that sayde, how he had wrytten a story of things don, and not a prophecie of things to be don. And our lord him self also in the Gospel of S. Matthew. When you shall see, sayth he thabomination of desolation, which was spokē of by Daniel the Prophet, stāding in the holy place, he that readeth let him vnderstand. Doth not Esay also in a maner in all his prophecies, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the comming of Christ, and most of the misteryes of the kyngdom of God accomplished, seme likewise to haue compiled a most playn hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story? And doubtles, if we reade with diligence this same boke of the Apocalips, &amp; confer those things which he speaketh vnder a shadow, with the same that stories testifie to be done: We shall say also, that he telleth plaine histories. I haue verely loued this boke from my youth vpward, I haue gladly red in it, &amp; bestowed much labour, ther vpon, obseruing what things it had out of the bokes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prophets, &amp; howe the prophecies herof did agree with thother prophesies of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prophets, &amp; doctrins of the Apostls. I haue searched finally, after the capacitie of my sklēder wit, diuers stories, which I thought to make for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the sence of this prophecie. I haue searched also thopinions of other expositours: And haue diligentli compared domestical matters, which ar don now in our tyme, with this narration of Iohn: of al the which things, and chiefly being ayded by the helpe of God, whiche I called for, I haue gathered such things as I now do cōmunicate here to the godly readers. Hereunto came also the singular learnyng &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and aptnes in expounding the holy scriptures of the most god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man. D. Theodore Bibliander doctour of Diuinitie in the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of Zurick,<note place="margin">Doctour The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odore Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</note> who thirtine yeres past, red openly, and to his greate praise, this boke of reuelation: of whō, vnlesse I wold confesse my self to be very much holpē, I were excedingly vnthankful. There remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth as yet a faithful relation of the same, imprinted at Basyl the yere of our Lord .1545. Wherin he disposeth this boke of. S. Iohn, &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a light to it with his scoles. And bothe of thold and new that I could get, I haue red ouer Aretas, the successor of Andreas bishop of Casaria,<note place="margin">Who haue written vpon the Apocalips.</note> whose expositions vpō this boke, he allegeth oftner thē once, S. Austen also, bishop of Hippon, and Primasius Bishop of Vtica. Neither haue I contemned Thomas of Aquine, nor dispised the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb facs="13"/> glose, as they terme it, of the newer sort. s. Sebastian Meter-minister of the church of Bernes .xx. yeres since, a man of great vertu and learnyng, hath faithfully, and not without great fruite traueled in expowndyng this boke, whose commentaries vpō the Apocalips wer imprinted many yeres since at Zurick, by my frend Froschouer. And D. Fraunces Lambart of Auenion, a most godly and excellent lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man hath laboured in expoundyng the same boke, who had fyrste red it at Marsepurge, the noble vniuersitie of Hessia: And after in the same citie he caused to be printed and setforth, seuen bokes of thexposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof, the yere of our Lord .1528, Moreouer, there was impryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Wittēberg. in Saxony a commentary vpon thapocalipse, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an hundreth yeres past, and sent to D. Luther out of the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most parts of Germany, namely out of Sarmatia and tartaria, which I red also: as likewise certen thyngs of D. Leuthers vpon this boke of Reuelation. And here I may not forget the most excellent learned men, and the which haue right wel deserued of learnyng, Erasmus of Roterdame, and Laurence Valla, who haue also lefte theyr annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon thys boke. By all whose labours I confesse my selfe to be very much holpen: whiche I recite franckly for this pourpos, that I would dissemble nothyng, nor seme toffend against ciuilitie, or defraud any man wrongfully of his deserued praise: And therfore wold admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the godly, that if I seme to any man to haue don any thing in this work prayse worthy, he may know that I haue don nothyng without coadiutours: And that he refer thys whole benefite to God thauthor and fountain of all goodnes, &amp; geue hym thanks therfore. And al these thinges of myne I propound to be iudged of the godly readers &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours, that they may take that shall seme good herin: and where I seme to haue erred frō the right rule, they may eschew the same. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil I contend with any man, neither will I enuy better learned, or better exercised, wherof som haue promised already commentaryes vpō this boke if they shal bring forth better thīgs: yea, I am alwaies ready my self, not only to receiue better thynges, but also to geue them thanks that offer the same. In the meane season I put out my talent, which I haue receyued of the Lord, that I may win som lucre with it for my Lord. And I beseche the Lord that he wold prosper it wel, and blesse thys my simple trafficke.</p>
   <p>Here moreouer I take God to witnes, that I haue takē this pain, for no priuat hatred towards any man, for no desire of raylyng,<note place="margin">That these cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions are frēd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wretten.</note> nor for any intent to procure any mās displeasure: but simply to expound this excellent and right profitable boke of the new Testament which haue lately with my commentaries setforth al the residue of the boks of the new Testament. And besides all this, many godly &amp; learned men out of sondry places, in their letters writtē to me, haue required my expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitiō vpō the Apocalips. To whose iudgmēt sins I gaue very much, I did in dede more easely consent to this editiō. And wherin y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane time the hatfull cause of Antichriste (as many men cal it) came in the beginnyng of the worke to be handled, I neyther ought, nor myghte dissemble it.</p>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <p>Moreouer, this is playne, that I haue brought forth nothing in this matter, that is new, straung, or hath not ben heard of: nor that I role this stone alone. Now al the world crieth out, that no other antichrist shall come into the world, then he that is commen already in the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Rome: Who shal in the meane time be slaine with the sword of God, his word in the harts of the faithful, and shortly shalbe who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abolished, by the glorious comming of Christe vnto iudgement. If I shall suppresse and conceale this thing, the stones wyl cry out. For now is the time fulfilled, and the kingdom of God is cōm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n. Blessed, and for euer blessed be those,<note place="margin">Theldest and most common doctrine is that the Pope is Antichrist. Gregory the first Pope.</note> that watche and loke for Christ vnto sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Ireney an holy Bishop sayde, a thousand and foure hundred yeres sins: Antichrist where he is but a seruaunt, will be worshipped as God. Tertullian and. S, Hierom, (as I haue said now oftner thē once) haue expounded this prophecie of. S. Iohn touching Babilon of Rome plainly. Gregory the first of that name, who was also Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome, was not affrayd to pronounce openly, that he was the vauntcurour of Antichrist, that wolde suffer him selfe to be called the vniuersal and high Bishop. But then did the bishop of Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vsurpe to himselfe this title, who ran before the latter bishops of Rome. And in the, xxxv. epistle to Iohn Bishop of Constantinople. Al thinges, saieth he, that are spoken before are don. The king of prid, to wit antichrist, is at hand: And the which is not lawfull to be spokē, An army of priestes is prepared for him. For they serue in the bande of prid,<note place="margin">Arnulphus bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce.</note> which wer placed to be guides of humilitie. And these things wrote Gregory, nine hundreth &amp; fiftie yeres synce. Arnulphus a mā very godly &amp; lerned, Bishop of Orleance .550. yeres since in the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of Reins, speaking openly of the Bishop of Rome, brake out at the last into these wordes. What thinke you him to be that sitteth in the high seat, in the pourple garment, glistering with gold, whom, I say, think you him to be? Vereli, if he be destitute of Charitie, and be puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp, &amp; extolled with only knowledg, he is Antichrist, sitting in the Temple of God, and boasting himselfe, as though he were God. But if he be neyther grounded vpon charitie, nor yet exalted with knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, he is in the Tēple of God as an Idoll. Thus far he: who semeth by these his wordes, to haue alluded to the places of holy scripture. Apocalips .xix.ii. Thessa. ii. Zacha. xi. S. Barnard. Albeit that by reason of the infelicitie of his time, he agreeth not with him selfe in all thinges: Yet inueyhed so against the Pope, bishops, and clergie of his time, that if any shuld at this day, omitting his name, vse his words, he shuld be called the greatest heriticke that lyueth. Where notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing al things ar now more corrupted, thē they wer in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of s. Barnard. His sermon which he had to the clergie in the counsell of Reines, remayneth. In his bokes of consideration he is moste vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, especially in the .ii. and fourth boke. He liued about the yeare of our Lord .1150. In the yere of our Lord 1240. was sūmoned a coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of Princes and Bishops at Regenspurge,<note place="margin">Eberhard bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge.</note> and that for the Tirā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of bishops of Rome, most greuously oppressinge the godly Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Friderick the second of that name. In the whiche Eberharde
<pb facs="14"/> Archebishop of Salisburg standing dp. Vnder the Title, fayth he, of the greatest Bishop, we perceiue in a Sheperds clothynge, a moste cruell wolfe, vnlesse we be blind. Bishops of Rome haue war against al Christians, by attempting, disceyuing, &amp; makyng war vpon war, waxing great, they kil and murther the pore shepe: peace and concord they dryue out of the earth, Ciuile warres, &amp; domestical vprores, they coniure out of hell: dayly more and more, they weaken the forces of al men, that they may treade them all vnder foote, may deuoure all, and bring all into bondage. Hildebrād an hundreth and threscore and ten yeres past, first vnder the pretence of religion, layed the foundation of Antichristes kingdom: He first began this wicked war, which by his successours, hath ben continued hitherto. And by and by: The bishops of Babilon, couet to reigne alone, they can not abide theyre pere, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue me for my experience, they wil not cease, til hauyng brought thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure vnder, and the dignitie of the Romane empire dissolued, &amp; the true pastours oppressed, they may on this wise extinguish all thinges, tread al thinges vnder theyr fete, and sit in the Temple of God, and be exalted aboue al that is worshipped. He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is seruaunt of seruaunts, seketh to be Lord of Lordes, in like case as if he were God. He hathe new deuises in his hart, that he may establish thempire for him selfe: He chaungeth the lawes, &amp; setteth forth his owne lawes: That loste man, whom they are wont to cal Antichrist, polluteth, Robbeth, spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, defraudeth, sleyeth, in whose forhead is written the name of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche: I am God, I can not erre: he sitteth in the temple of god, and ruleth far &amp; nere. And a little after, the maiestie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people of Rome, wherwith in times past the world was gouerned, is takin out of the earthe. The kingdome is multiplyed, the gouernment dispersed into many, cut of, lessened, I wyl not say, rent in pieces. Themperoure, is a vayne calling, &amp; is only a shadow. There be ten kings atones, which haue parted the world, which in times, was the Romaine empire, not to gouerne it, but to consume it. The ten hornes (which thing to. S Austē semed incredible) Turks, Greks, Egiptians, affricans, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, Frence men, Englishmen, Germās, Sicilians, Italians do posesse the Romane prouinces, &amp; in them haue distroyed the Roman inhabiters: And a little horne hath growen vp vnder these, that hath eyes and a mouth speaking great things. It hath brought in subiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on especially three kingdoms of Sicilie, Italy, and Germany, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled them to serue him, with intollerable tyranny, it vexeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Christ, and the saincts of God, it confoundeth all thinges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God and man, and attempteth deuelish things. And the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew which is to be red in the .685. leafe in the seuenth boke of Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines cronicles, which in the yere of our Lord .1554. were printed at Ingolstad, by themperours priuilege, out of the which I wrot word for word al that I haue hitherto recited in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of Eberhard Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of Salisburge. About the same time,<note place="margin">Abbot Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim. Fraūces Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch.</note> liued Abbot Ioachim of Calabria, who likewise calleth the Pope, Antichriste, and setforthe thapocalips with prophetical pictures, &amp; scolies in Italiā. Fraūces Petrark, a man excellently learned, &amp; most worthy mortall fame flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished
<pb facs="15"/> about the yeare of our Lorde .1350. Who also least suche wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngs behynd hym agaynst the See of Rome, against the court there, and agaynst the Pope, that yf they wer comparde with these things, whych in our tyme .D. Luther wrote most bitterly against Rome, he may seme to be vtterly vāquished of him. In the .xx. epistle, he calleth the Popes court, both Babilon, and also the whore of Babilon, syt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng vpon the waters, the mother of all Idolatry and fornicatyon. There is moreouer a learned boke of Marsilyus Patauinus,<note place="margin">Marsilius Patauinus.</note> writtē for Lewis the .4, Emperour, agaynst the Pope, wherin he inueyeth sharply against the bishop of Rome, and his tirannicall lawes. In the same age, to wyt two hundreth yeres past, flourished also Micael Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senas,<note place="margin">Michell Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senas.</note> general of the Minories, who openly accused the Pope as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichryste, and the church and See of Rome as the whore of Babylon dronken with the blod of saincts. An hundreth yeres since liued Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Valla, a gentleman of Rome of a noble house, who also obiected him self to the Pope and the Romish See,<note place="margin">Laurence Valla. Hieronimus Sauonarola.</note> for the which cause he was dryuen into exile: but of the kyng of Naples, he was honorably recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Moreouer, Hieronymus Sauonarola of Farrare. an excellente diuine and Philosopher in hys time, a man in holynes of lyfe (as he is sayde of many) notable, preached openly in Italy, that the Pope was Antychist: for the whych cause he was most cruelly burnt at Florēce by Pope Alexander the sixt. Thys is had yet in the Fresh memorye of men, where it was don about the yere of our lord .1499. Yet Iohn Fraunces Picus, Counte of Mirandula calleth the same Sauona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola, an holy prophet. Albeit that Nawclerus signyfieth in hys story that he did many thyngs for ambition sake and for vayne glyrye. And Marsilyus Ficinus attributeth to the same Sauonarola the spiryte of prophecye, in a certeyn epistle, Furthermore. Philippus Cōmines an Historiographer witnesseth that he was an holy man, and to haue had the spiryte of Prophecye. For they say how he prophecied of the sackyng of Florence and Rome, and the restauratyon or reformatyon of the church, and of many other thynges that shuld chaunce vnto I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, whych came to passe there in the meane season. I remembre, whē I was yonge and followed my study in sondry vniuersityes, to haue hearde certen blacke Freers say, that Sauonarola prouoked the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dygnatyon of Alexander the sixt, the courte of Rome agaynst hym by nothing more, then for that he preached against them in Italy the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalips of S. Iohn. What shuld I say, that the Waldensians foure hundreth yeres past in Fraunce, Itali, Germany, Boheme, Poland, and in other parts of the world, professing the gospel of Iesus Christ, accused the bishop of Rome with diuers wrytings, and continual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings as the verey Antichrist, prophecied by. S. Iohn thapostle and therfore to be abhorred. They themselues beyng put to most greuous torments, haue constantly testifyed theyr fayth by gloryous martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and stil do at this day. For they could neuer be roted out, which thing notwithstanding hathe ben full oft attempted by most myghtye kings and princes, inspired by the bishop of Rome, the wyl of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>g otherwise. But why rehearse I these thynges, synce thys yeare
<pb facs="15"/> 1556. was printed at Basill, a register of the witnesses of the veritie,<note place="margin">All good men at all times haue spoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the pope</note> which before our time, haue spoke against the Pope, wherof the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in dede is great, and the more parte of them called the Byshop of Rome, with out any prouerbe, that Antichrist, which shuld come into the world? Therfore it is manyfest, that I in this my worke brynge forthe no vnwonted thing, or that hathe not ben heard of before, wher now we do plainly vnderstand that this song hath in so many ages b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> songen, written, painted, printed, and beaten in of the best, holyest, and most excellently learned men, yea and confirmed to, with the vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surable bloud of martirs. Furthermore, yf any remayne that be desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of good thinges emongs the bishops or prelates of the churche, &amp; in the clergie it selfe, let thē not be offended with me, in case any where in expounding the Apocalips, I bryng foorth theyr sayings &amp; doings, and compare thē with the Apostls words: Let them rather be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with theyr owne wordes and dedes spoken and done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esydes and against Gods word, Let them leaue doing that they do: Yea,<note place="margin">Daniel .xii.</note> let them do penaunce, so shall they haue prayse in the churche of Saincts. But yf they hold on euen against their conscience to defend and maintayne their kinde of lyfe, theyr pleasures, theyr riches, theyr honours &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and to accuse, persecute and murther the preachers yf the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as enemies of the church: let them take hede, it chaunce not to thē sodenly, that the Gospel resiteth, of the dronkē seruaunt,<note place="margin">Math. xxiiii.</note> who did vexe and beate his fellow seruaunts: but was of the chief Lord him self op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, when he thought least of it, and hewen al to pieces.</p>
   <p>But yf there were euer any tyme heretofore,<note place="margin">Thapocalips in oure tyme is not only profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table but neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary.</note> wherin it behoued to setforth, to vrge, and beate in this doctryne to al the people. This is chiefly necessary to be don in this our tyme. For this age of ours hath in the Popes kingdom, sharpe and quick wittes, which cōmend with maruelous prayses, both the Pope and the popish church, &amp; perswade and dryue into the heads of the sort vnlearned, cleane contrary things to theuangelical and Apostolicall doctryne. Moreouer they haue wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull crafts, wherwith the wittier number are also disceaued. They haue welth and riches, authoritie, armure, munitiō, threatnings, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>messes and torments, wherby some strong also are made wery, and ar hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d away to the popish parte. There be many without experience, whych esteme not this thing as it ought to be estemed, suche care not, nor passe not what religion be preached, whether it be euangelicall or popish, or what thynge be of eyther beleued, or not beleued. For they suppose all these things to concerne them nothyng. In the meane sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son many perish and are in daunger, not a few fall away, diuerse stick in perplexitie, and the kingdom of Christ is abbreuiated. For the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes omit nothing, which may make for reparing of theyr kingdom, and pullyng downe of the kingdome of Christ. Therfore where these fellowes spare in this case, nether paines nor cost, that they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte all thynges to oppresse the faythe of the Gospell, and to dryue the sympler sorte to forsake it: We oughte not to suffer that the Churche, and the symple people afflycted and tempted in the same,
<pb facs="16"/> shulde want that comfort, admonition, and doctryne, which in tymes past the lord Iesus him self by S. Iohn, hath prepared for these hard things &amp; times, by reuealing this Apocalips. And in dede these things here haue a singular grace and vertu, which ar reuealed to vs of God. Neyther shal the aduersary and enemy of Christ be ouerthrowē with any corporal weapons, saue only with the sword of Gods word. For now it is nedeful that antichrist shuld waxe vile, &amp; perish in the minds of men, that Christ alone might liue again, and be glorified for euer.</p>
   <p>And thys my exposition I haue diuided into sermones, bothe for that I haue nowe,<note place="margin">Conefonsor sermones.</note> these yeares of a .1555. and .1556. expounded thys boke to the faithful church of Christ, which I serue, making in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner these same sermons to the people: and also that being requested, I wold deliuer som copy, to such as wil read and expound the same boke to the churches committed to their credit also. Where not withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I admonish the readers, that they loke not for all thines of thys my work: or think that these things are to be rehearsed word for word to theyr auditours. For certen thinges, which I propounded to the people for the consideration of the time and place, I haue not setforth in these my sermons, studieng much, for breuitie: And other thynges, namely such as concerne the conferring of tongs, and the kind &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of speakyng, and such other lyke, I rehersed not to the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but haue written them here in my sermons, to the profit of those that wyl confer these things together more dilligētly. It shal be the part of the preacher to haue a respect chiefly to such thynges as make both for the plaines of speache, that he may be vnderstand, euen of the grossest sort: and also for the edifyeng of the audience, that he brynge nothyng, that shuld little profit. Let euery man therfore applye these things to the edifieng of the church where he is, hauing consideratiō of the place, time, and persons: Yet alwayes obseruing the true sence of the boke or of Gods words. For violēt wrestings, and long digres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions far from the pourpos, deserue no prayse in preachynge: or what tyme swaruing ouer muche from the playne sence of the scripture, we boult out I wot not what mysteryes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the worke.</note>And all this work compiled not without my great labour &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, but chiefly by the grace of God, to the glory of Iesu Chryste, and written to the saluation and confirmation of his afflicted churche, I dedicate to you banished men, as many of you as comyng or driuē out of Fraunce, England, Italy, &amp; other realmes and nations for Iesus Christ and the gospels sake, dwel in Germany, Swisserland, &amp; other places, where God hath permitted you: And also I dedicate this my worke to all you, which dispersed in sondry realmes and nations, are consecrated only to Christ our Lorde, loking for his coming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, In the which we shall vndoubtedly be delyuered at the last frō all euils, and then shall be made that long loked for, and in al ages and most fortunate restitution, most expressely &amp; constantly promised, both of the prophets and Apostles.<note place="margin">Actes .iii.</note> And surely your Godly zeale, banished brethern, which had rather forsake your countrey, then the Gospell, &amp; to want your temporal cōmodities, then to be polluted with a religiō
<pb facs="16"/> estraunged from Christe, deserueth no small prayse.<note place="margin">Iames .i. Math. xxiiij</note> But you haue nede of constancie, and wonderfull patience, that after you haue ben tried, you may receyue the crowne of lyfe, which the Lorde hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to them which perseuer vnto thende. The heauenly regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doeth not so chaunge vs, but that some doubtefull &amp; trouble some dregges of olde Adam remayne. Therfore alwayes the regenerated fele sundry temptations, and harde conflicts: then especiallye, when suche things chaunce as they had leaste looked for. The godly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had euermore nede of consolation. But this booke of the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lypse doeth minister the same with greate plentie: whiche if you wyll reade ouer diligently, you shall finde all things that happen to you, &amp; that vexe you nowe with painefulnes, to haue ben already so prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied in this boke, as they nowe come to passe. Whereunto are added oftentymes most comfortable and swete consolations. Moreouer ye are not ignoraunte right honorable and dere bretherne, what chaūced to oure fathers the holyeste of all others. Howe they wandered in mansions vncerten, and howe they demeaned them selues in those most paynefull flittings, you vnderstande me to speake of Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, and Ioseph: whose peregrinations out of Chaldey into Palestine, from thence into Egypt, and agayne into Palestine, &amp; from thence againe into Syria, and agayn into Palestine &amp; Egypte, are well knowen to the whole worlde. Nowe what bannishements and perills abode that woorthie seruaūt of God and most excellēt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Moses, is not vnknowen so much as to those that be ignoraunte in matters of antiquitie. Whose faith the vessell of election S. Paule commendynge: By faith (saith he) Moses when he was greate,<note place="margin">Heb. xij</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to be called the sonne of Pharaos daughter: And chose rather to suffer aduersitie with the people of God, then to in ioye the pleasures of sinne for a season: And estemed the rebuke of Christe greater ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesse, then the treasures of Egypte, for he had respecte vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. What shall we saye that our Lorde Iesus Christe hym selfe was constreyned in his infancie to flee into Egypte, euen from hys swaddlynge cloutes teachinge his to suffer exile: who is red also in the Gospell to haue sayed: Foxes haue holes, and the byrdes thayre haue nestes. But the sonne of man hath not wher on to reste his head.<note place="margin">Dan. xi.</note> Of Antechriste we reade in dede that Daniel prophecied: whom who so will acknowledge, he will promote him to greate honours and make him the lorde of many, and shall distribute the earth for mony. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywise we shall heare in the .xii. chapter of this Booke, that both Christe and the Churche his spouse, suffer greuouse persecutiō of the dragō: That Christ is takē vp into heauē, a blessed hath opened hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē also for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fartheful: And there sheweth a place permanēt countrey, to them that haue in maner no habitation in earth. From thence he will come to Iudge the quicke and dead, and to assumpte vnto hym the faithfull into ioye euerlastynge, and to geue them what thyngs so euer he him selfe in the Gospell and the Prrphets and Apostles haue promysed. Of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mple hope this boke of Apocalypse most plentifully and goodly discourseth, instructyng all that desyre to heare
<pb facs="17"/> certayne things and most full of comforte vnto all you therfore exiles and godly throughout the whole worlde, desyringe the comynge of Christe our Lorde and iudge of all, I offer and cōmende and dedicate this my labour. Receyue it with louing minds: which I setfoorthe to non other ende but that (fleenge Antichriste) you shoulde cleaue to Christe alone, fixinge all your truste in him alone, where we loke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready from heauen for the selfe same Lorde,<note place="margin">Philip. iij.</note> whiche shall chaunge our vile bodye, that it maye be lyke fashioned vnto his gloryouse bodye, accordynge to the woorkynge, whereby he is able to subdew all thinges to hym selfe, he blesse vs all, and brynge vs in that daye, into the sight of hys father: that we maye see hys glorye, whych he had before thys woorlde was made, to him alone be glorye.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Zurick, <date>the moneth of Ianuarie, in the yere of our Lorde. 1557.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>