<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107018_Bo1_34_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06151</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16641.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107018</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exercise of a christian life. Written in Italian by the Reuerend Father Gaspar Loarte D. of Diuinitie, of the Societie of Iesus. And newly translated into Englishe. by I.S</title>
                 <author>Loarte, Gaspare</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Carter, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 224 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="213"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>I HAVE thought good (gentle Reader) folowing herein the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise of certaine vertucus and learned men, to annexe in the ende of the former most excellent Treatise these few praiers that folow; moued therto, chiefly with this reason, that such as haue not ben erst exercised in the maner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prescribed by the Authour, might here see some practise of his preceptes touching gouernment on morninges and euenings, (the two especial times wheron depend the whole course of a wel-ordered life) as also touching the disposition requisite both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after confessiō; with some such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prayers, as I demed most necessary here to present vnto thee. I hope, if thou beest a Nouice, and delighted with the former worke; this my smale paine shal not seeme vnprofitable vnto thee: which I beseech thee to vse to thine auaile, whiles thou wantest better meanes. And this must I say for the better credite of that which foloweth; how it is not I that am the authour thereof, but other famous men of the same liuery that the former is; God requite al our benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; spiritual especially, and geue thee, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, such good by this whole worke, as the Authours thereof doo wish thee, and my poore hart affordeth thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>