<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, SIR STEPHEN SOME KNIGHT, LORD MAYOR OF THE CITTY OF LONDON AND TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL THE Aldermen of the same,
Thomas Morley Gent. of her Maiesties Chap∣pell, wisheth long health and felicitie.</title>
           <author>Morley, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107517_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18131</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107517</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, SIR STEPHEN SOME KNIGHT, LORD MAYOR OF THE CITTY OF LONDON AND TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL THE Aldermen of the same,
Thomas Morley Gent. of her Maiesties Chap∣pell, wisheth long health and felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Morley, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of consort lessons, made by diuers exquisite authors, for six instruments to play together, the treble lute, the pandora, the cittern, the base-violl, the flute &amp; treble-violl. Newly set forth at the coast &amp; charges of a gentle-man, for his priuate pleasure, and for diuers others his frendes which delight in musicke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Barley (Barlow), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Ballard, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Morley, Thomas, Assignee (with assent, etc.) of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24+ pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, SIR STEPHEN SOME KNIGHT, LORD MAYOR OF THE CITTY OF LONDON AND TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL THE Aldermen of the same,
<hi>Thomas Morley</hi> Gent. of her Maiesties Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, wisheth long health and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am bolde to present vnto your good Lordship, with the right worshipfull Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men your assistants in the gouernment of this noble Citty, some few fruites of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the most perfect men in their quality, that in the censure of many which can well iudge in Musicke, haue beene, and are at this day held very rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, both for their skill and practise: whose works that I might not abase in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noting them to a meane patron, nor abuse the workers in ioyning them discordes for their true descant, I chose your Lordships vertue with the rest, to grace their deserts with your gracious fauours: and not to disgrace my care and trauaile, which at the instant request of my very good friend haue beene very carefull truly to set them out. The songs are not many, least too great plenty should breede a scarcenes of liking: they be not all of one kinde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause mens fansies seeke after variety: they bee not curious, for that men may by diligence make vse of them: and the exquisite Musitian may adde in the handling of them to his greater commendation. They be set for diuers Instruments: to the ende that whose skill or liking regardeth not the one, may attempt some other. This pain is past, in hope to procure your Lordships pleasure and recreation: and your Honorable acceptance shall be a sufficient warrant that my time is well spent: for I desire not to satisfie bablers, which are baser then brute beasts in reprouing excellencie, neuer attaine to the first degree of any commendable Science or misterie. But as the ancient custome is of this most honorable and renowned Cittie hath beene euer, to retaine and maintane excellent and expert Musitians, to adorne your Honors fauors, Feasts and solemne meetings: to those your Lordships Waits. after the commending these my labors to your Honorable patronage: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend the same to your seruants carefull and skilfull handling: that the wants of exquisite harmony ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent being left vnsupplied, for breuitie of Proportions, may be excused by their melodious additions, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing hereafter to giue them more testimonie of my loue towards them. Thus as with my protested dutiful endeuor and obsequie I begun to your Honor and the right worshipfull Brethren: so with my humble peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Almightie for your prosperous preseruations, I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all duty and humility <hi>THOMAS MORLEY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>