<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, and my very good Lord, JAMES, by divine providence Lord Bishop of Winchester T. J. wisheth all Grace and Happinesse. RIGHT REVEREND And HONOVRABLE,</title>
           <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107487_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04190</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107487</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, and my very good Lord, JAMES, by divine providence Lord Bishop of Winchester T. J. wisheth all Grace and Happinesse. RIGHT REVEREND And HONOVRABLE,</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nazareth and Bethlehem, or, Israels portion in the sonne of Iesse. And, mankinds comfort from the weaker sexe : Tvvo sermons preached in St Maryes Church in Oxford. By Thomas Iackson, Bachelour of Divinitie, and fellow of Corpus Christi College in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wrench, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 75, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, and my very good Lord, JAMES, by divine providence Lord Bishop of <hi>Winchester</hi> T. J. wisheth all Grace and Happinesse. RIGHT REVEREND And HONOVRABLE,</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince it hath pleased such as haue hitherto beene spectators, as well of my weaknesse, as of my industry in the Ministery, to pardon the one for the others sake; it is, and ever shall be my care, to haue your <hi>Lordship,</hi> (vnder whose patronage, as <hi>Honourable Successor</hi> to my worthie <hi>Founder,</hi> I now enioy the continuance of former opportunities) no witnesse of my sloth, or idlenesse. Yet these papers I produce not, either in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie of my paines, which in so little a worke can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be great; or as a proofe of my diligence in polish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what hereafter I meane to set forth. Rather out of indulgence to my bodily indisposition, &amp; diligent fore cast how long my iourny is like to bee, I haue begunne after such a manner, as by Gods assistance, and your <hi>Lordships</hi> wonted coūtenance, I may hope to cōtinue. To leaue some fuller explication, then I haue found,
<pb facs="3"/>
of the admirable consonancie betweene ancient <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>significations,</hi> whether <hi>propheticall, typicall,</hi> or <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall,</hi> and <hi>Evangelicall</hi> relations, concerning our <hi>Saviours</hi> conception, his birth, his baptisme, passion, resurrection, and ascension (or other like parts of his humiliation, and exaltation) is the point, whereto my studies haue beene consecrated, and my observations principally directed, since I vndertooke the ministery. And in this respect, I may truly call my meditations in this kind, the first fruits of all my labours. Now of this crop, which, with reference to my poore harvest, is like to be very great, as much at least as all the rest, and as I trust most acceptable to my God; I haue brought this little Sheafe vnto your <hi>Lordship,</hi> humbly desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that you would vouchsafe to offer it vp vnto Him, by whose only blessing all the rest must bee sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Thus omitting longer preface, vntill I may fit it with a larger worke, I humbly commend your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> to the gratious protection of our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and this slender pledge of my most intire obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to your benigne acceptance. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my study in <hi>CORPVS CHRISTI COLLEGE in Oxford:</hi>
         <date>Septemb. 6. 1617.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours,</hi> in all duty and service to be commanded, <hi>THOMAS JACKSON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>