<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR WILLIAM St. IOHN Knight, Co∣uernour of the Countries of Ginney, and Binney: Sr. Allen Apsley Knight, Liuetenant of the Tower of London, and Deputy Gouernour as a foresayd: Sr. Thomas Button Knight, and other the Noble Knights, and Gentlemen, aduenturers for the sayd Countries of Ginney and Binney.</title>
           <author>Jobson, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107773_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04494</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14623</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107773</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR WILLIAM St. IOHN Knight, Co∣uernour of the Countries of Ginney, and Binney: Sr. Allen Apsley Knight, Liuetenant of the Tower of London, and Deputy Gouernour as a foresayd: Sr. Thomas Button Knight, and other the Noble Knights, and Gentlemen, aduenturers for the sayd Countries of Ginney and Binney.</title>
                 <author>Jobson, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden trade: or, A discouery of the riuer Gambra, and the golden trade of the Aethiopians : Also, the commerce with a great blacke merchant, called Buckor Sano, and his report of the houses couered with gold, and other strange obseruations for the good of our owne countrey; set downe as they were collected in trauelling, part of the yeares, 1620. and 1621. By Richard Iobson, gentleman</title>
                 <author>Jobson, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 143, 152-166, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR WILLIAM St. IOHN Knight, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the Countries of <hi>Ginney,</hi> and Binney: S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Allen Apsley</hi> Knight, <hi>Liuetenant of the Tower of London, and</hi> Deputy Gouernour as a foresayd: Sr. <hi>Thomas Button</hi> Knight, <hi>and other the Noble Knights, and Gentlemen, aduenturers for</hi> the sayd Countries of Ginney <hi>and</hi> Binney.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honorable Gentlemen:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>IF it may please you to take into consideration, the cause of publishing this ensuing treatise, it may some-way satisfie for my presumption, in offering to bring to the publike presse, that which to you hath bin so chargeable in discouering, and therefore by all reason to you belongs the benefit of what is discouered, or at the least free will to dispose of your owne
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <pb facs="4"/>
priuiledges as to your wisedome should be most approueable; But such are the turbulent spirits of some men, that no curtesies can win faire correspondency, but as profest enemies to the ingenious search of worthy minded Gentlemen, proclaime warres against their indeuors, if they tend to merchandizing, thereby intermedling (as they terme it) to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer their secret mistery, although in their perticulars to begin such an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, they can no wayes paralell the meanest of your true experience and well grounded desigments, but it might have bin hop'd, that there would haue beene some better respect towards you, in regard of your persons, and not to deale in that nature as to euery ordinary Gentleman, or other by them imployed, by whose industry after the way is opened to any profitable businesse, and that hee hath made plaine the discouery, then
<pb facs="4"/>
they doe find occasion to cauill and turne them off, and presently imploy seruants of their owne, many times very vnfitting, in regard they will not requite deserts, nor allow of any society in an apparant way of gaine: All which is indeuored towards you, for whilst you haue bin suffered to disburse your monies in the first discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and as it were beating and laying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the way, where and how this Golden Trade should rise, you haue quietly past one, but now there can be no more euasions, but that the profit plainly appeares; what complaints have bin framd? what combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and plotting together? Wherein to auoyd suspition, the face of simplicity, the honest Country-man hath bin made the instrument to bring about the incroaching gaine they aymed at: That it may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appeare, how the first grounds of this hopefull businesse by you were layd, and how you haue seconded one losse by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="5"/>
and how needfull and necessary it is, that you should now proceede to follow what is begun, and make vse of what you so deare haue payd for; I haue written this Discourse out of my owne carefull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation, in the time of my imployment for you, that you might (if you please) see what you haue done, and what (if it please God to blesse the courses) you are like to do, which may not onely incourage you, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite other Gentlemen of your Ranke, to associate with you, to follow and proceede vpon this hopefull enterprize, wherein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending faithfully, in demonstrating the truth, to manifest the zeale and seruice I must euer owe you, humbly crauing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Your deuoted Seruant,</salute>
      <signed>RICHARD IOBSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>