<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>CATHOLICKE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107544_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17889</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4554</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>CATHOLICKE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The spirituall director disinteressed : According to the spirit of B. Francis of Sales, Bishop and Prince of Geneua, Institutor of the Order of the Visitation of our Bl. Lady. By the most Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus, Bishope of Belley. Translated out of French by A.B</title>
                 <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Blageart, Francoise</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 660 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>CATHOLICKE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS SPIRITVALL DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RECTOR DIS-INTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RESSED, hauing out of his charitie towards vs passed the seas, deserues enterteinmēt. And because his language is vnknowen to many, I will be his Interpretour, to the end his zeale of soules may shine to all, and such fruite be reaped of his wholsome and charitable counsells, as is desired. These lines of mine wanting autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="3"/> to moue thee to relish the sweetnes of the Auctour: heare the eloquence of rare Causin of the society of IESVS who hath giuē him, and his workes, this Elogie, in the end of the second part of his holy Court, which flowing from so Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and learned à pen, will be inuitation enough to peruse this worke. His words are these.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>I may well saie, I were stupide and vngratfull, if I should not confesse to haue bene much excited, to prosecute this labour by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Inuitations, which my lord Bishop of Belley hath vsed towards me in his workes. I cānot
<pb facs="3"/> set too high à price vpon his recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation in such à subiect. For he is verily one of the most able, and flourishing spirits, that euer handled pen. To see the number of his bookes, one might saie, he began to write, so soone as to liue; and to consider their worth, it is à wonder how so many graces, and beauties, which others attaine not but with much labour, increased with him, as in à soile naturall for eloquence. If there be any slight discoursers, who amuse thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to argue vpon some words of his writings, it is not à matter vnusuall, seeing we are now in an age, where there are some who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue the example of those cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb facs="4"/> Grecians, that preferred à sauce made by the Cooke Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecus, before the diuine workes of Phidias.</hi> More need not be said, read and followe the Direction of this DISIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERESSED, purely, without any other, then thy spirituall, INTEREST.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farwell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>