<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Ballard, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107472_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17583</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4360</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107472</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Ballard, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Perth assembly : Containing 1 The proceedings thereof. 2 The proofe of the nullitie thereof. 2 [sic] Reasons presented thereto against the receiving the fiue new articles imposed. 4 The oppositenesse of it to the proceedings and oath of the whole state of the land. An. 1581 5 Proofes of the unlawfulnesse of the said fiue articles, viz. 1. Kneeling in the act of receiving the Lords Supper. 2. Holy daies. 3. Bishopping. 4. Private baptisme. 5. Private Communion</title>
                 <author>Calderwood, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Brewster, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Leiden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 101, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE externall worship of God, and the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church (Gentle and indicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) are like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> twins: they are sick together, in health together: they liue together, they die and dwine together. As long as the government of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> stood in integritie, as it was established by lawes, civill and ecclesiasticall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods word, so long was the worship of God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in puritie. Since the former government was altered, and the insolent domination of Prelates hath entered in by unlawfull meanes amongst us; popish rites and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious Ceremonies have followed, and are like to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile universally. They haue verified in their persons their common tenent, <hi>No Ceremony, no Bishop.</hi> The libertie graunted to our Church, to indict and hold generall assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies from yeare to yeare and oftner <hi>pro re nata,</hi> was the cheife bulwarke of our discipline. This bulwarke was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down to the end a more patent way might be made for their exaltation. When vote in Parliament (the needle to draw in the threede of Episcopall authoritie) was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to the great griefe of the sincerer sort, many protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were made, that no alteration in discipline, or divine service was intended: many cautions and limitations were made to bound the power of the minister voter in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They were ordayned to be countable to the generall
<pb facs="3"/>
Assemblies, for the manner of their entrie and behaviour in this new office: But like bankrupts, not being able to render accompt, they laboured that no accompt should bee made at all: that is, that there should be no ordinary gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall assemblie to take accompt. Some few extraordinary Assemblies haue been convocated of late yeeres at their pleasures, for their purposes, and according to their device, constituted as they thought good: wherein they procured, or rather extorted with terror and authoritie, a sort of prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence aboue their bretheren. They were Lords in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Councell, Session, Checker, Lords of Regalities, Lords of temporall lands, Presenters to benefices, modifiers of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters stipends, grand-Commissioners in the high Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. Was it wonder then if so great Commanders comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Assemblies constituted, as is said, and carved to themselues a spirituall Lordship, when their worthy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were banished, imprisoned, confined, or deteyned at Court, that they might the more easily effectuate their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. They haue broken the caveats made with their owne consent, violated their promises, and haue sought prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence both in Church and Common- wealth, with the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of others, and the renting of their mothers belly. Wee haue notwithstanding been so silent hitherto, that the world hath iudged our silence, rather slumbring and slothfulnesse then true patience. They are not satisfied with the wrongs already committed, but do still provoke us with new irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant occasions: and specially by obtruding upon us supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious will-worships, and polluted inventions of men. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooveth us therefore to set pen to paper, and say somewhat for the surer stay and better information of professors, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly affected to the sincerity of religion, lest they bee delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the glorious name of a pretended and null-Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie,
<pb facs="3"/>
or seduced with temporizers, swallowing up all abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations or corruptions whatsoever. The meanes of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and publishing are to us very difficill: wee wish therefore every good Christian to take in good part our meane travels, and not impute unto us want of good will, but of meanes, if they be not served hereafter continually after this manner. Wee shall bee ready God willing for our owne part, as need shall require, and opportunitie will serue, to defend the cause we maintaine against any of our opposites their answers, or replies whatsoever, worthy of answer. Wee haue seene of late some Pamphlets, which haue rather exposed their authors to laughter and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, then deserved any serious Confutation. In the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle before <hi>Basilicon Doron</hi> his Maiestie protesteth upon his honour, that hee misliketh not generally all Preachers, or others, who like better of the single forme of Policie in our Church, then of the many Ceremonies in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and are perswaded that their Bishops smell of a <hi>papall Supremacie,</hi> that the <hi>surplesse,</hi> the <hi>corner cap,</hi> and such like, are the outward badges of <hi>popish errours.</hi> And that he doth equally loue and honour the learned and graue men of either of these opinions. His Maiestie useth this Provision, that where the Law is otherwise, they presse by Patience and well grounded reasons, either to perswade all the rest to like of their iudgement, or where they see better grounds on the other part, not to be ashamed peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to incline therunto, laying aside all preoccupied opinions. Wee are able to proue that no Ecclesiasticall law hath been made in any free and formall Assemblie for the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by-past, or presently intended, either in Government or Ceremonies. The ratification of civill Lawes already made, or to be made, cannot rectifie the <hi>Ecclesiasticall,</hi> as long as
<pb facs="4"/>
wee are able by good reason to impugne their authority, and evince the vicious constitution, the informall and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proceedings of these Assemblies, where the said Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall Lawes are said to haue been made. Put the case that no exception might be made against the Law, his Maiesties provision permitteth us to perswade others with well grounded reasons. The verity of our relations, and validity of our reasons, we refer to the tryall of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iudicious Reader, making conscience of his oath, promise, subscription, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his profession.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>