<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVR∣TEOVS REA∣DER.</title>
           <author>Whately, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107622_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14992</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25299</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107622</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVR∣TEOVS REA∣DER.</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A care-cloth: or a treatise of the cumbers and troubles of marriage : intended to aduise them that may, to shun them; that may not, well and patiently to beare them. By William Whately, preacher of the word of God in Banbury, in Oxfordshire</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 262 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE COVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEOVS REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader: Most graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth our Communion Booke admonish such as come to be married, that they ought to enter into this estate, not <hi>rashly, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnaduisedly, to satisfie their carnall lusts and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, like bruit beasts, that haue no vnderstanding; but discreetly, aduisedly, soberly, and in the feare of God.</hi> Needful it is, that this counsel be sounded often in the eares of the vnmarried, and not alone in that instant, whē they are now about to consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate marriage. For want of heeding this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, how common is it, and withall how mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous? For men to offend in an ouer-sudden and ouer-hastie vndertaking of Marriage, without the due meditation of two special things (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what be the duties of Marriage, and what the difficulties,) it is as impossible to be well prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for that estate, as to flye without wings, to goe without legs, or to see without an eye: yet
<pb facs="3"/>scarce one man or woman of a number will put themselues to the paines of informing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues beforehand, of either of these two things. Thus hauing blindly and headlongly cast them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues into marriage, either not at all (or with no firme and settled knowledge) knowing, what belongs vnto it, what seruices they are called to performe, what burdens to sustaine in it: it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes (as needs it must) that with much hazzard to their owne soules, and much vnquietnesse to themselues, families and neighbours, they proue vtterly carelesse of their duties, and extremely impatient vnder their crosses. Hence it comes to passe, that marriage prooueth to many, iust as the stocks vnto the drunkard; into which, when his head was warme with Wine or Ale, hee put his foot laughingly, and with merriment: but a little after (hauing slept out his Wine, and coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his head with a nap,) hee longs as much to get it out againe. Hence it is, that diuers houses are none other, but euen very Fencing-Schooles, wherein the two sexes seeme to haue met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for nothing, but to play their prizes, and to trie masteries. Hence it is, that many husbands and wiues doe fare almost alwayes, as <hi>Iob</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when the Deuill had smitten his body with boyles and vlcers, cursing their Wedding-day, as much as he did his Birth-day, and thirst<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after diuorce as much, as euer hee did after death. Hence it is, that many wedded people brooke their wedlocke in none other fashion, then a dog doth his Chaine, at which he neuer
<pb facs="3"/>ceaseth snarling and gnawing, that he may break it asunder, and set himselfe at libertie. Hence it is, that the little child is no more wearie of his fine new guilded book, now a little ouer-worne &amp; sullyed (yea, that the prisoner is no more wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his gyues, nor the Gally-slaue of his oares) then many an husband of his wife, and shee of him, within an yeere or two, and sometimes within a moneth or two, after their wedding. In a word, from this fountaine, such a streame of bitter waters doe issue, as make the liues of a number in marriage, like the soiourning of Israel in Marah, where almost nothing could be heard, but murmuring and complaining. To redresse or preuent, if it might be, at least, some of these many mischiefes, I haue been bold (as once <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> did cast a piece of wood into the waters of Marah to sweeten them, so) to publish already to the World, some few directions about the duties of the married, and doe now aduenture againe, to put forth some other aduertisements, about the troubles of Marriage. Neither let it seeme superfluous to giue men tidings of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles before they come, seeing they are alwayes so much the better borne, by how much they are more expected. Men are indeed desirous to please thēselues rather, with the sweet thoughts of comfort, then to imbitter their minds with fore-fearefull conceits of miserie. Also, to a mind fully bent vpon a course, disswasions proue tedious; and hee that foretelleth inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may seeme to disswade. But let it be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="4"/>withall, that likely none doe meete with more crosses in marriage, or beare their crosses more vntowardly, then those that most dreame of finding it a very Paradise: For they strange aboue measure at the cumbers they neuer fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of, and are put out of all patience, by being so farre disappointed, as to find thick mire and dirt there, where they would tell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of nothing, but faire and pleasant way. And indeed none shew themselues lesse resolute in vnder-going miserie, then those that make themselues most resolute to rush vpon it. The same vices that breed stiffenesse in ones course, will breed impatiency vnder the crosses that he meetes with in his course. Wilfulnesse and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, grow like two euill branches, out of one roote of folly. But warinesse of mind, in foreseeing, and forefearing euill, brings quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of mind, in bearing and sustaining euill: and the expectation of miserie makes it, at least, seeme lighter, because the mind is somewhat acquainted with it by contemplation. When Israel would needs haue a King to rule ouer them, as other Nations, the Lord commandeth <hi>Samuel</hi> to testifie vnto them, what should bee the manner of their King, and so hee tels them, what heauy burdens their much-desired Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch should lade them withall. No doubt it is as needfull for marrying persons, to know what burdens their wedded condition is like to bring vpon them. Wherefore I will make bold to foretel those that will enter into Marriage, that
<pb facs="4"/>they must make account in changing their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, to change for the lesse easefull; and will aduise him that will follow mine aduice (if not, let him follow his owne mind, and say ten yeres after, whether was the better counsell) To goe vnto Matrimonie with feare of the worst, and to know before-hand, that there grow Briers and Thornes in this way, wheron he must needs tread, that will trauaile in it. Yet is not this writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by me, to make any man forbeare marriage, whom God calleth vnto it; nor to make men hazard themselues to wickednesse, for feare of the cumbers of Matrimony: but alone to make those willing to want marriage, that may want it without sinne, or hazard of sinne; and to make men careful not to marry, before God cals them to it; and withall, being called, to fit themselues for it; lest if they marry sooner, or with lesse warines, they discredit Marriage after a while, as most do that are married, by wishing themselues single againe. Some man, perhaps, vpon occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of these words, may desire to haue this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand satisfied, When doth God call a man to Marriage? I answere: First, when he sets him in such a condition, that he may marry, without wronging any other person, that is, when hee is now become his owne man, not bound by coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to continue another mans seruant: for God neuer crosseth himselfe: whom he hath called for a certaine time to bee seruant vnto a Master, him he doth not call, during that time, to breake from that seruice, without his Masters liking;
<pb facs="5"/>and to thinke of making himselfe a Master, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he haue fulfilled the dutie of a seruant. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, when God furnisheth a man with some conuenient meanes to maintaine a Wife and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and not before: for God calleth no man to any place, vntill hee haue granted him some meanes of discharging the duties of that place; and it is one part of an housholders duty to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for them of his houshold. The Lord sends not souldiers into the field to fight, without some weapons, nor men to house-keeping, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some meanes to keepe house. Lastly, when a man, after diligent labour, conuenient watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, due abstinence, earnest prayers, and a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full shunning of all times, places, companies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, that may prouoke ill affections, doth yet still find his heart so restlesly possessed with these desires, that he cannot with-hold his will, at least, from often consenting vnto them; and so is disabled from seruing God in duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and his calling, with comfort and cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse: to whom God, after all these meanes vsed, vouchsafeth not the power of containing, him he cals, to enter into Matrimony. But hee that is so tyed in other respects, that he cannot marry without wronging another, or wants all fit meanes to maintaine a wife, or in regard of any other let, cannot attaine a wife, shall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faile attaine the gift of continency, if hee be carefull to vse the forenamed meanes, and the like, that God hath appointed to subdue lust. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if men force themselues to an vnmarried
<pb facs="5"/>life, either by superstitious vowes, or incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous feares, or the like, the Lord will likely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish their presumption or diffidence, by not yeelding his powerfull helpe, and so will make them find their owne folly and weakenesse. But such is the wisdome of God to proportion his owne actions to his owne ends, and cause, that all his deeds shall hold agreement each with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and such is his truth and goodnesse to them, that faithfully call vpon him that whom himselfe debarreth from Matrimony, him he will inable to liue chastly and purely out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, vpon condition of his vpright and carefull endeuours to get this abilitie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whosoeuer is yet a seruant to another, or is wholly destitute of all meanes, to prouide for a wife and children, or is otherwise so hindred, that he cannot haue a wife, must say to himselfe thus; God hath made me a single man, &amp; would haue me so to continue as yet; I will not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to my selfe in striuing for continency, and Gods blessing shall not be wanting to mine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, in giuing continency. And hee that is at his owne disposing otherwayes, and enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth conuenient meanes of prouiding for a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, shall, for all that, doe best to forbeare Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, as I suppose, if hee perceiue no need of marriage for the preuenting of sinne, or other important consideration. For albeit in such case the Lord hath left a mans conscience at libertie (so that hee sinnes not either by abiding in his present estate, or altering it, which he likes best)
<pb facs="6"/>yet it may seeme the wisest way to make choice of that part, which the Scripture rather of the twaine doth seeme to commend, saying, 1. Cor. 7.1. <hi>It is good for a man not to touch a woman.</hi> 7. <hi>I would that all men were euen as I my selfe.</hi> 8. <hi>I say to the vnmarried and widdows, it is good for them, if they abide, euen as I,</hi> that is, single. 27. <hi>Art thou loosed from a wife? Seeke not a wife.</hi> 38. <hi>He that giueth her in marriage, doth well; but hee that giueth her not, doth better.</hi> 40. The Widdow is <hi>happier, if she abide so,</hi> that is vnmarried, <hi>after my iudgement, and I thinke that I also haue the Spirit of God.</hi> But yet if God leade any man to marriage, let him follow him, yet so, that hee follow him with prudence and discretion. Hee whom God shall will to fight with an enemy, must furnish himselfe with fit weapons. <hi>Dauid</hi> gate himself a sling, and smooth pibbles out of the valley, when he went to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter <hi>Goliah.</hi> So men must arme and furnish themselues for marriage, that they may not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour this honourable estate, by turning backe from it, in their minds and wishes. Specially, he that will bee married, must arme himselfe with patience against the troubles of that kind of life, and resoluing, that hee shall meete with them, must determine, that hee will behaue himselfe, not alone quietly, but euen chearefully, though they come apace about him. Digest in the seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous consideration of thy mind, the cause of trouble, sinne; the vse of trouble, the healing of sin; the Sender and Moderator of trouble, God; the end and issue of trouble, glorie; that thine
<pb facs="6"/>heart may neither faint nor fret, because of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yea, tho some heauy and more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie calamitie should betide thee; much lesse, if thou meete alone with those vsuall matters, which (like spirtlings in a dirty way) will surely come to the lot of euery man, in euery Family. For to see a man so foolish and absurd, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made himselfe the Gouernour of an hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he can beare no disorder of wife, children, seruants; no disaster in goods, cattell, dealings; without chasing, and fuming, and stormes, and without those pangs of a base and feeble mind, vaine wishes of hauing neuer knowne this wife, or so forth, is a spectacle of that nature, as may iustly mooue disdaine, as well as pitie in the wise beholder. What was he, trow you, a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable man, or a bruit creature, that rushed so foresightlesly into marriage, as neuer to say to himselfe, that some of these things must needs befal al that are wedded: And if a man do know, that such things must needs happen to all that will marrie, is it not a strange indiscretion to take on, that they haue happened to himselfe, who would needs marrie? Make reckoning therefore of crosses in thy matrimoniall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then bee carefull to preuent them so much as may be. For which end, let mee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto thy consideration, these two things following: When thou art married, if it may be, liue of thy selfe with thy wife, in a family of thine owne, and not with another, in one family, as it were, betwixt you both. And in all thy
<pb facs="7"/>worldly dealings, trust no more then thou must needs; nor otherwise, then vpō due security. The mixing of gouernors in an houshold, or subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating or vniting of two Masters, or two Dames vnder one roofe, doth fall out most times, to be a matter of much vnquietnes to all parties: Youth and Age are so far distant in their constitutions, that they wil hardly accord in their conditions; and how to make the young folks so wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe themselues vnto the elder, as not to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented with their proceedings; or to make the elder so much to deny themselues, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descend vnto the wils of the younger; or to make both so moderate themselues, as to meete in the mid-way (without one of which three things, there is no maintaining of concord) is a matter in the best natures, &amp; most discreet persons, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding difficult; and in the common sort of people altogether impossible. Wherefore, as the young Bees do seek vnto thēselues another Hiue; so let the young couple another house, that they may learne to liue of a little, to know what is their owne, and how it becomes their owne, and to vse their owne to their owne best aduantage, that whatsoeuer come, they may neuer fall into that vnhappiest of all vnhappinesses, of either being tormentors of their Parents, or tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them. And for ones worldly affaires, let him trust as little as is possible, and then also vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods assurance. It is most certaine, that the most of those with whom a man shall deale, will alwayes bee vngodly, and vnrighteous, seruing
<pb facs="7"/>themselues altogether, and ready to aduantage themselues by deceite. It were an vncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to say before trial, Such a man wil deceiue me, therefore I will not trust him: but it is wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to thinke before triall, This man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me, therefore, if I may, I will forbeare to trust him; if not, I will trust him on such termes, as he may not be able, if he should be willing to beguile me. Boldnesse to borrow, boldnesse to lend, boldnesse to trust, and to be trusted (which likely come from this originall, that men would ouer-faine, either to be rich, or seeme so,) haue plunged many families into great misery, which else might haue sailed through the World with a constant tenour of prosperitie. Let a man ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee willing to lay his foundation low, to content himselfe with the imployment of his owne portion, not delighting to make himselfe a seruant, by making himselfe a borrower, nor to hazzard himselfe (more then hee must needes) vpon the doubtfull honesty of such slipperie seruants, as most times borrowers prooue to bee. But forbearing to giue further counsell, I commit the booke following to thy censure, praying thee to reade it with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and fauour, and to be the same to the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of another, that thou wouldest another should be to thine. So with my best wishes to God, to make the troubles of thy marriage (if thou beest, or shalt be married) as easie as is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible (and the more easie, by meanes of that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice which this Treatise will giue thee, if thou
<pb facs="8"/>wilt vouchsafe to reade and consider it) I leaue thee to the guidance of him, that giueth his gifts to euery man as seemeth best to himselfe, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Banbury,</hi>
         <date>Feb. 19. 1622.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>A wel-willer to the peace of thine heart and house, <hi>William Whately.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>