<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTY OF HENRIETTA MARIA, Queene of Great Britaine.</title>
           <author>Verer, S. du</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107416_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17883</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4549</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTY OF HENRIETTA MARIA, Queene of Great Britaine.</title>
                 <author>Verer, S. du</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Admirable events : selected out of foure bookes, vvritten in French by the Right Reverend, Iohn Peter Camus, Bishop of Belley. Together with morall Relations, written by the same author. And translated into English by S. Du Verger</title>
                 <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Brooks (Brooke), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 357, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTY OF <hi>HENRIETTA MARIA,</hi> Queene of <hi>Great Britaine.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ancient and moderne custome which all Authors have, and doe yet hold, in dedicating their workes to the hand of eminency and greatnesse, is grounded ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their upon desire to see them powerfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, or by them to proclaim some testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of devoted affection, or to appeare grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for benefits received, if I shall call to this support of my thrice humble dedication to
<pb facs="3"/> your Highnesse, the aforesaid motives either severall or joyned together, I doubt not but their weight will begge pardon for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, and incline your Grace to its fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, since whether I make my addresse in the humble supplication of the first, or in a revering sence of the second: or lastly, in the generall obligation of the third respect. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse no more then what the least and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest in the ranke of subjects is owing to the source of Majesty, whose influence quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, gives motion and being to all civill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustries, sending their lives to equall center.</p>
   <p>In point of subject, since nothing from mine own conceptions was fit to adventure upon so high a theater. I assign my part to the onely choise and conveyance of an Authour, with language intelligible to the English shore, who in the variety and multitude of his writings, both Theologicall, morall, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall, hath as with a Cristall streame wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered a continent of the greatest extent in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> and although in himselfe like good wine he needeth no bush to recommend him to the readers gust, yet in this presentment to your
<pb facs="3"/> gratious Majesty. I will serve him in by the hand of a curious taster. Rare <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssin,</hi> who in a noble translation of the <hi>Holy Court,</hi> towards the end of the second part, hath these words, as well of proper gratitude to his person, as of a full Elogie of the graces and beauties of his minde.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>I may well say (saith he) that I were stupid and ungratefull, if I shonld not confesse to have been much excited to prosecute this labour by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable invitations which my Lord Bishop of</hi> Belley <hi>hath used towards me in his works, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not set too high a price upon his recommendation in such a subject, for hee is verily one of the most able and flourishing wits that ever handled penne: to see the number of his Books, one might say, he began to write, so soone as to live, and to consider their worth, it is a wonder how so many graces and beauties which others attaine not but with much labour, increased in him, as in a soyle natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for eloquence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Character flowing from so learned a pen, may of it self be a fair invitation to your Highnesse, to peruse the work which I have here drawne up to a translation: it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb facs="4"/> of severall Histories culled out of two Treatises intituled <hi>Singular Events,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Relations,</hi> an argument not improper for a vertuous minde, whether profit or pleasure be aymed at, for Histories are the store-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, where vertues are faithfully conserved to posterities veneration, and vices detestation: it is an armory where armour of proofe for all degrees is fitted to the hand; it is a glasse wherein to behold, adorne, and fashion out the life to what is worthy imitation, and to have in hortour and avoydance what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the beginning, or foule in the end: in fine, they are the only monuments of truth, which they purely deliver, no way flattering or concealing any thing</p>
   <p>Give leave then, most gracious Princesse, where I began, there to determine my thrice humble Dedication, with homage and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding oblation of these first fruits of my small industry to your all-atracting goodnesse, which let it deigne to assume unto favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptance, herein imitating the precious amber, that commands the ascent of small, and worthlesse substances, not for their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb facs="4"/> sake, but for the honour of its force, and vertue to attract. Thus my presumption I hope, may be excused, your Highnesse all commanding vertue being graciously incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>To the humblest and lowest of all your Majesties most devoted servants, S. Du VER<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>