<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Mascall, Leonard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107520_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07781</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18159</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107520</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Mascall, Leonard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A notable treatise of the chvrch : in vvhich are handled all the principall questions, that haue bene moued in our time concerning that matter. By Philip of Mornay, Lord of Plessis Marlyn, gentleman of Fraunce. And translated out of French into English by Io. Feilde</title>
                 <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>384 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Pray thee (gentle Reader) to reade this treatise, not as hauing alreadie founde the trueth, but seeking for it likewise, and I pray thee to read it out before thou iudge of it. And if it accord as the doctrine of the trueth, I adiure thee in the name of God, &amp; by thine owne saluation, that thou openly declare it. For it behoueth that we waite no longer to speake, seeing once, that wincking at the kingdome of Antichrist, our kingdome falleth to ruine, in the ruine whereof is the danger of vs all. If yet there be founde any doubt, they shewing it by writing, we shall by the grace of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoure to make it cleare. But if there be any, which will improue the whole, I praye them that they wil answere point by point, and reason by reason, in the spirite of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie and gentlenes, seeking in steade of the prise of victorie, the saluation of the people, and not the glorie of this world. For I protest before God, that in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, I haue aimed at no thing else but their saluation.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>