<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLE AND VVEL-DISPOSED READER, indued with either of these rare Vertues, Iustice, Valour, Honour, Temperance, Magnanimity, Clemency, Truth, Liberality, Ciuility, and Courtesie; Health and happinesse in IESVS CHRIST.</title>
           <author>Darcie, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107372_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17808</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4497</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107372</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLE AND VVEL-DISPOSED READER, indued with either of these rare Vertues, Iustice, Valour, Honour, Temperance, Magnanimity, Clemency, Truth, Liberality, Ciuility, and Courtesie; Health and happinesse in IESVS CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>Darcie, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Annales : the true and royall history of the famous empresse Elizabeth Queene of England France and Ireland &amp;c. True faith's defendresse of diuine renowne and happy memory. Wherein all such memorable things as happened during hir blessed raigne, with such acts and treaties a past betwixt hir Matie. and Scotland, France, Spaine, Italy, Germany, Poland, Sweden, Denmark, Russia, and the Netherlands, are exactly described</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96, 435, 5, 232, 251-292, 2 pages, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLE AND VVEL-DISPOSED READER, indued with either of these rare <hi>Vertues,</hi> Iustice, Valour, Honour, Temperance, Magnanimity, Clemency, Truth, Liberality, Ciuility, and <hi>Courtesie</hi>; Health and happinesse in IESVS CHRIST.</head>
   <argument>
      <list>
         <label>Of Iustice.</label>
         <item>IVSTICE is a constant and perpetuall will, to giue impartially euery one their iust due: the one is generall, diuided in politicke and oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micke: the other speciall, diuided in distributiue and commutatiue; her subiectiue parts are to doe good acts, and fly from bad ones. It stands therefore much in need of Religion, Piety, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruance, Obedience, Thanksgiuing, of expulsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of iniuries, also of Truth, Affability, Amity, and Liberality.</item>
         <pb facs="14"/>
         <label>Of Ʋalour.</label>
         <item>VALOVR, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates feare, and Hardinesse, is a Vertue which encourages one to blame or defend things iustly: her mediocrity is betwixt cowardnesse and temerity. To her belong Magnanimity, Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, Patience, and Perseuerance.</item>
         <label>Of True Honour.</label>
         <item>TRue HONOVR, which belongeth to Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Iustice, is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Vertue, subiect nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fortune nor force: it is that which all good and vertuous men aime at, &amp; leuell their actions.</item>
         <label>Of Temperance.</label>
         <item>TEMPERANCE is a morall Vertue, which moderates sensuall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuousnesse, and the couetousnesse thereof, and the dolour or griefe which is still, as it were, linked with couetousnes: shee mediates, or is a meane betweene Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancy and Stupidity: shee is perfected &amp; made whole by Bashfulnesse &amp; Honesty: shee keepes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her, Abstinēcy, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, Sobriety, and Chastity: To her do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, Gentlenesse, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, Humility, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and Moderation.</item>
         <label>Of Magnanimity.</label>
         <item>MAGNANIMITY belonges to Force
<pb facs="15"/>
and Courage: it is a carefull vertue, and as it were a spur to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase supreme honours; her mediocrity or mean is betweene <hi>Saperba</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
               <desc>••••</desc>
            </gap>animity.</item>
         <label>Of Clemency.</label>
         <item>CLEMENCY is a morall vertue, which moderating anger, quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth in vs fre or choler, to produce pious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: she mediates, or is a meane betweene Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, and too great Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency.</item>
         <label>Of Truth.</label>
         <item>TRVTH, by which, in all our actions &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane society, we should make things as they be: her meane or moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is betweene Simulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and dissimulation.</item>
         <label>Of Liberality.</label>
         <item>LIBERALITY is a Vertue truely, Noble, and most Diuine, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to Iustice? This excellent Vertue mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the desire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in riches, rules the purchasing of goods, and orders expences, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in vs, and bring forth to the world rare actions: it is a meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Auarice and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality.</item>
         <label>Of Ciuility.</label>
         <item>CIVILITY is also a morall vertue, which consisteth in vttering gracefully a speech or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course in Company: by this Vertue, both praise and a good opinion is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: it is a meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Mirth and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</item>
         <label>Of Courtesie.</label>
         <item>COVRTESIE is a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue truely morall, by which we purchase loue, in shewing our selues gracious and officious to those who stand in need of vs: it is a meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene submission and rudenesse or harsh dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position.</item>
      </list>
   </argument>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll-Vertuous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall Reader, </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>here is presented to thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious view, the Translation of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-piece of History, in its owne origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Language truely most rare; which I (for the worthinesse of the Subiect) wish with my soule, I could haue Englished accordingly: But though
<pb facs="14"/>
my poore straine &amp; weake capacity would not permit mee to equalize the eloquence and elegancie thereof, yet I can assure you, I haue had a speciall care, to doe it faithfully: And truely I must confesse ingenuously, doubting of my weaknesse in so important and laborious a Worke, (because I am a Stranger borne) I haue sought the best helpe I could, from those that are holden good Schollers, for the perfecting of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish phrase and stile, but it hath beene amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded so contrary to my expectation, that I haue beene forced to peruse it againe, best I was able, and as the time &amp; Presse would giue me leaue. I beseech you therefore to beare with it, not doubting, but (as I haue obserued the inuention and meaning of my Author) it will affoord you sufficient content: and if I may bee so happy, as to drawe gently the gracious aspect of your eyes vpon these my worthlesse Lines, I will euer be bound to your Noble fauour, for a milde and courteous Censure, in respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the affection and desire I haue, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy my time about that which may tend to immortalize the Honour and Glory of <hi>Englands</hi> dreaded, and vndaunted Nation; in striuing to make vulgar the heroicke
<pb facs="15"/>
Acts, and Diuine Vertues of <hi>Albions</hi> best Queen, and the most Religious, learned and prudent Empresse that euer liued on earth: and Soueraigne Head, or supreme Ruler, next God, ouer this flourishing Kingdome, ayming thereby more at the conseruation of her glorious memory, then at any thing else. I therefore doubt not but this worke will soone purchase your kind fauour, and louing commendation: and so I commit you to the Almighty, wishing you his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, and the perfection of happines, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>A true deuoted to your Vertues,</hi> ABRAHAM DARCIE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>