<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Whately, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107622_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14992</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25299</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107622</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A care-cloth: or a treatise of the cumbers and troubles of marriage : intended to aduise them that may, to shun them; that may not, well and patiently to beare them. By William Whately, preacher of the word of God in Banbury, in Oxfordshire</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 262 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="105"/>
   <pb facs="105"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reliques of good nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in man since the fall, (by the worke of a common Grace preseruing them) haue taught Heathen men to know, and inabled them to practise many worthy duties. Among the rest, some of them haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in a most affectionate loue to their Countrie, the welfare of which, they haue preferred before their owne liues; and the ruine whereof, they haue been care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to preuent, euen with their owne ruine. Many worthy sayings haue they writte to this purpose, but scarce any more diuine, and more deseruing admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue I met withall, then that one of <hi>Tully,</hi> in his booke of <hi>Scipioes</hi> Dreame, where he brings in a dead father (now in Heauen, as he supposed) encouraging his sonne to doe seruice to his Countrie, (wherein himselfe had giuen him a most noble and notable example) with this most worthy sentence: <hi>There is a most sure and certaine place in Heauen for euery man, that shall procure the weale of his Countrie, either by freeing it from perill, or increasing the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse of it any way.</hi> To heare a Gentile tell of Heauen, as of a thing certaine; to heare him tell of certaine places prouided there for those, that should doe
<pb facs="106"/>vertuously; to haue the seruice of ones Countrie pressed on his soule with so celestiall an argument; sure it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, that sometimes the light of Nature doth reach further, then many which liue in the bosome of the Church, do attaine. But the purpose for which I thought of this sentence, is, to let it appeare, how great a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning reason doth tell euery man, that he ought to make of his Countries welfaere, how carefull he should be to preserue it from dangers, to adorene it with all benefits, and to continue, and augment the flourishing estate thereof. It must needs be an happie paines, from which a multitude doe reape commoditie; and that one man deserueth very well of all men, for whose cares or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, all doe fare the better. Now if Nature and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy can giue so good instructions to those that will attend them, how much more perfectly should wee bee able both to learne, and follow the same lessons? It is a great reproch to him that goes by day-light, if another trauelling alone with a candle, or a torch, shall see the way better then himselfe: and without doubt, that eye is very dim, which discerneth lesse by the helpe of the Sun-beames, then another may doe by the helpe of a Lampe or Taper. O, then how iust both blame and shame must be cast vpon vs, that are nothing so regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of our Countries welfare (the most of vs) as were some Inhabitants of Heathen Rome and Athens! I would to God therefore, that I could inflame the soules of those, that shall reade these few lines, with a farre more feruents zeale to the prosperitie of this our Church and Nation, then that they had before. If the fire of loue did burne warmer and lighter in our hearts; it would not drie up the fountaine of teares, to which the
<pb facs="106"/>booke following perswadeth, but would euen melt and dissolue our now-frozen hearts into teares. Those that stand in places of eminency, may performe many good seruices for their Countrie: we shrubs that sit in the shade below, can doe nothing worth the naming, but earnestly to pray for the barke, in which we sayle, and to lament the things that we see, to threaten a miserable shipwracke thereof. He that will iudge of things by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance (and make carnall wisdome his onely Loade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>starre in iudging) can hardly mistrust so much euill, as those, that make faith in Gods threatnings a counsellour to their forecast, must needs most euidently foresee now ready to come against vs. The huge encrease of vices amongst vs, the noysome swarmes of wicked men, and wicked deeds, doe assure euery one that beleeueth, there is a righteous Iudge in Heauen (who thence beholdeth all the sonnes of men) that hee will not long forbeare to scourge vs soundly, for our vnthankfulnesse to him, and rebellion against him. Lay all things together, and I thinke, there neither is, nor euer was a Nation more beholding to the Diuine Maiestie. What peace? What plentie? What deliuerances? What brightnesse of heauenly light haue we enioyed now for the space of more then threescore yceres? Againe, lay all things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and, I think, there neither is, nor euer was a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more wicked and vngratefull, and that did worse requite the louing kindnesse of God. What profanenes? What blasphemy? What contempt of God &amp; his Word? What sinnes of all sorts doe abound and reigne amongst vs? We seeme to haue entred into a contention with the Almightie, whether he shall be more mercifull, or we more sinfull; whether he shall be more constant in
<pb facs="107"/>doing vs good, or we more obstineate in sinning against him. I doubt not but that the same faults are found in other Nations, that are in ours, and in places further off from the light, perhaps also grosser faults: but a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple so long and happily enioying the Gospell, and so poorely answering the seede that hath been sowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, I cannot thinke there is any. What shall we doe then? and what will be the issue of our not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth fruite worthy the paines and cost that God hath bestowed vpon vs? We may flatter our selues, as it is vsuall for men to doe, and promise to our selues as much good, as our hearts can wish: but it is sure, Gods threatnings shall bee fulfilled, and publike sinnes shall bring in iudgements after them, answerable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in greatnesse, and inpublikenesse. Mine inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore, in setting abroad this Sermon, is, to doe the best good that I can to my poore Country, in stirring vp those that are not starke dead in sinnes, to set their endeauours on worke, for the preuenting of her woes. There is no way left for vs to defend our selues against Gods hand, but prayers and teares. Mans wisdome is folly with God: It hurts it selfe often, in seeking to helpe it selfe, and lyes snared in its owne subtiltie, as in a grin. Mans power is weakenesse with God, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten casts it selfe downe, by seeking to establish it self, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with its owne weight. No, my brethren, no: Not our wisdome, not our power, but our prayers and teares; I say, our prayers and teares; these are the best fences against the calamities, to which our Country stands ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed. These will pacifie God, these will make him say, as once he did to the Prophet;<note place="margin">Amos 7.3, 6.</note>
      <hi>It shall not be, saith the Lord.</hi> To the end that I might prouoke some to
<pb facs="107"/>apply themselues to this so needfull a seruice for their Countrie, I haue held vp the example of a most worthy man of God, whose example, if we would imitate, no doubt but we should procure as much prosperitie to our Nation, as Israel inioyed in his time. Set about it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O yee Christian soules: You Countrie hath inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest into you: It callengeth at your hands, all the good you can affoord it: It iustly claimeth the vtumost im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preouement of all your abilities. It stands in danger of Gods hand, by reason of the sinnes wherewith it is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Not your blood (which would you denie?) but your teares are now called for, to wash away those staines. Heathen men haue fought for their Countrie, shall not we sight for it? They haue giuen their whole bodies, shall not wee giue our teares? They haue laid downe their liues, shall not wee lay downe our mirth? They haue encountred all perils, shall not we endure the labour of mourning and lamentation? I call vpon you in <hi>Ieremies</hi> words:<note place="margin">Lam. 3.18, 19.</note>
      <hi>Let your teares runne downe like a Riuer day and night: giue your selues no rest, let not the apple of your eyes cease. Arise, crie out in the night, in the beginning of the night watches, powre out your hearts like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before the face of the Lord, lift your hands towards him.</hi> If miserie come, you will surely crie, when crying will auaile but little; crie before it come with such a crying, as may preuent it. O, deferre not to afford this Iland another sea of teares for its safe-gard, and that a better too, then this wherewith it stands sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded. The multitude are so metamorphosed into stones, that all words are cast away, which may be spent in calling them to sorrow, But if there be (as sure there
<pb facs="108"/>is) in our Nation, any small remnant left, of those that haue hearts of flesh, now let them witnesse their loues to their Countrey, in taking vp a bitter lamentation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst those crimes, that make a clamor in heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it. Crie aloude (I pray you) and out-crie the crying sinnes of England. God from Heauen hath spoken aloud by diuers corrections; He, as a Father loth to strike, hath giuen vs many a faire warning. Let vs not shew our selues to be wanton children, that will take no warning, that will not beleeue their parents threats, that will needs continue their vntowardnes, till the rod be held vp ouer them, yea, till their skin begin to smart with stripes. There are many that mourne for crosses, penurie drawes teares from the eyes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. We weepe to no purpose, in weeping for such things. Let our hearts be filled with ruth, for the faults that fill this Kingdome: Let the Lord see, that some are fit to be spared, if for their sakes, perhaps, he may spare all. I pray thee, Reader, be a true friend vnto thy natiue soile. Helpe her with thy humble requests and earnest lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Intercede to God for her with a beneded knee, and a broken heart, and moystned eyes. Not thy money, not thy toyle, not thy fighting, not thine hazard, but thy sorrowes are called for. These vouchsafe to thy selfe, and to thy Countrie, and we shall all be safe. All ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies here or elsewhere, all Papists at home or abroad cannot hurt vs, if our sinnes hurt vs not; they shall not hurt vs, so long as they bee pursued with cryes and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations. God is our King, sinne is treason against him: if many commit it, and none bewaile it, he must and will auenge it: but if we spare not to grieue for sin, he will surely spare to punish it. Happy griefe, blessed
<pb facs="108"/>teares, ioyfull sorrow. The heart of fooles is in the house of laughter, the heart of wise men in the house of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Follow the worthy Prophet into this house, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him in it, doe as he hath done, and thy Countrie shall enioy thy teares, more then it could doe thy labour, thine hazard, thy substance. But I must not forestall the following Discourse. I hope it will cause the good amongstvs, to pitie their Mother, and to mourne for her, that they themselues may reioyce with her in the fruite of their mourning. Now I commit thee to the following leaues, and them to thee. I would thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest reade them; I would thou wouldest consider them; I would thou wouldest practise them: and so wishing thee a much good sorrow, as in other cases thou couldst wish thy selfe ioy, I leaue thee to his blessing, who will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thy sorrow, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A desirer of thy teares, <hi>William Whately.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>
         <date>Feb. <hi>19. 1622.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>