<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107002_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01004</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11110.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>God and the king. Or a dialogue wherein is treated of allegiance due to our most gracious Lord, King Iames, within his dominions : Which (by remouing all controuersies, and causes of dissentions and suspitions) bindeth subiects, by an inuiolable band of loue &amp; duty, to thei soueraigne. Translated out of Latin into English</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>140, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb n="137" facs="69"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THIS Treatise (gentle Reader) may seeme written by some English Protestant, agaynst some Puritans, enemies of Kingly Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity; which by them in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times openly impugned, they now seeke to ouerthrow, by groū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the same vpon odious, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aungerous Positiōs touching the immunity of Tyrants. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour disputeth the questiō of this weighty subiect, in such mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate stile and manner, bringing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ns both solide, and not reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ing with Catholike doctrine, that he may be thought to be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion Catholike, though for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desties sake, &amp; to the end that this truth might be more pleasingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of Protestants; in this worke
<pb n="138" facs="70"/>
he discourseth as if he were Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. And for this reason, some Catholike arguments he doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit; others he doth not vrge to the vttermost, partly for breuityes sake, but cheefly because his intēt is no more then to shew that the new Protestants principles from which they deduce R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yall Authority be at the least doubtfull and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne. And this he doth cleerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate, and thence concludes. that it is against the rules euen of humane policy, to forsake the most sure grounds of Soueraigne Power in Kinges, whereon Christian Kingdomes relying, haue hitherto stood firme and florished vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> Catholike discipline &amp; iust l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> and to build the sacred authority of Princes, whereon their peoples safety dependes, vpon the new vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Doctrines, &amp; Paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gismes of Scriptures, which seemes
<pb n="139" facs="70"/>
to haue byn the drift of the former Dialogue.</p>
   <p>For this cause, I thought it would not be amisse, nor lost la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to put the same in print, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed before hand &amp; corrected.</p>
   <p>The title, <hi>God and the King,</hi> I would not alter, because i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> two wordes, it doth fully put down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the Catholike opinion concerning Princes Authority, &amp; their subiects Allegiance. For (as this trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ise doth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sinuate) three opinions in this poynt now are in <hi>Englād.</hi> The first of Puritās, who wil haue <hi>God</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>King,</hi> or else such a King that must depend on the peoples beck, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> their Consistoriā Preachers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ose perfidious audacity, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>esty hath had sufficient experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The second is of Politicians, who haue no more Christianity, then Parlamentary decrees breath into them: These will haue <hi>King</hi>
      <pb n="140" facs="71"/>
without <hi>God,</hi> or at least <hi>King</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> that is, <hi>God</hi> so longe, and no longer then the <hi>King</hi> shall please, whome they will haue still obeyed, though he go openly about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish the light of Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. The third opinion is of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ote is, <hi>God and the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in the first place they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God; in the second the King, to whome they giue all Allegiance and subiection as farre as Religion and conscience will permit. And this is to giue, what is <hi>Caesars to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar,</hi> and <hi>what is Gods to God.</hi> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="71"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>