<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the preiudicate and peremptory Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107688_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18401</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4964</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107688</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the preiudicate and peremptory Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Andromeda liberata. Or the nuptials of Perseus and Andromeda. By George Chapman</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the preiudicate and peremptory Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am still in your hands; but was first in his,
that (being our great sustainer of Sincerity,
and Innocence) will, I hope, defend mee
from falling. I thinke you know not him I
intend, more then you know me, nor can you know mee,
since your knowledge is imagined so much aboue mine,
that it must needes ouersee. He that lies on the ground
can fall no lower. By such as backebite the highest, the
lowest must looke to be de uor'd, Forth with your curious
Scrutinie, and finde my Rush as knotty as you lust, and
your owne Crab-tree, as smooth. Twillbe most ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous▪
and pleasing, to sit in a corner, and spend your teeth
to the stumps, in mumbling an ould Sparrow, till your
lips bleed, and your eyes water: when all the faults you
can finde are first in your selues, t' is no <hi>Herculean</hi> labor
to cracke what you breed. Ah las who knowes not your
vttermost dimensions? Or loues not the best things you
<pb facs="9"/>
would seeme to loue, in deed, and better? <hi>Truth</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
the Fount of <hi>Faction.</hi> In whose Sphere since your
purest thoughts moue, their motion must of force be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
and angulare. But whatsoeuer your disease bee, I
know it incurable, because your vrine will neuer shew it.
At aduenture, at no hand be let blood for it, but rather
sooth your ranke bloods and rub one another.</p>
   <p>You yet, ingenuous and iudicious Reader: that (as
you are your selfe) retaine in a sound bodie, as sounde a
soule: if your gentle tractability, haue vnwares let the
common surfet surprize you: abstaine, take Phisique
heere, and recouer. Since you reade to learne, teach:
Since you desire to bee reform'd, reforme freely. Such
strokes shall bee so farre from breaking my head; they
shall be rich Balmes to it, comfort, and streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
the braine it beares, and make it
healthfully neese out, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
anoies it.</p>
   <closer>Vale.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>