<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOSTE HYGHE AND moste excellent prince, our most gracious, and most redouted Souerayn lord and kyng HENRY the .VIII. by the grace of god kyng of Englande and of Fraunce, defendour of the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and supreme heed in erthe immediately vnder Christ of the Churche of Englande, Thomas arch∣bysshop of Canturbury, Edwarde archebysshoppe of Yorke, and all other the bysshoppes, prelates, and Archedeacons of this your realme, wysshe all grace, peace, and felicitie from almighty god the father our lorde Iesu Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1537</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107820_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73731</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5164</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107820</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOSTE HYGHE AND moste excellent prince, our most gracious, and most redouted Souerayn lord and kyng HENRY the .VIII. by the grace of god kyng of Englande and of Fraunce, defendour of the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and supreme heed in erthe immediately vnder Christ of the Churche of Englande, Thomas arch∣bysshop of Canturbury, Edwarde archebysshoppe of Yorke, and all other the bysshoppes, prelates, and Archedeacons of this your realme, wysshe all grace, peace, and felicitie from almighty god the father our lorde Iesu Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The institution of a Christen man : conteynynge the exposytion or interpretation of the commune Crede, of the seuen Sacramentes, of the .x. commandementes, and of the Pater noster, and the Aue Maria, iustyfication [and] purgatory</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1537</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 97 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MOSTE HYGHE AND</hi> moste excellent prince, our most gracious, and most redouted Souerayn lord and kyng <hi>HENRY</hi> the <hi>.VIII.</hi> by the grace of god kyng of Englande and of Fraunce, defendour of the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and supreme heed in erthe immediately vnder Christ of the Churche of Englande, Thomas arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bysshop of Canturbury, Edwarde archebysshoppe of Yorke, and all other the bysshoppes, prelates, and Archedeacons of this your realme, wysshe all grace, peace, and felicitie from almighty god the father our lorde Iesu Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>LEASETH IT YOVR</hi> moste royall maiestie to vnderstande, that where as of your most godly disposition and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der zeale, whyche is impressed in your most noble harte, towardes thaduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of goddis glorie, and the ryghte institution and education of your people, in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Christis true religyon, your hyghnes cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs nowe of late, to assemble oure selfes togyther, and vpon the diligent serche and pervsing of holy scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to sette forth a playne and syncere doctrine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the hole summe of al those thynges, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayne vnto the profession of a christen man, that by the same al errours, doutes, superstitions, and abuses, might be suppressed, remoued, and vtterly taken away, to the honour of almighty god, and to the perfyte esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyshing of your said subiectes in good vnitie and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde, and perfite quyetenes bothe in their sowles and bodies. We consydering the godly effecte and intent of
<pb facs="3"/> this your highnes moste vertuous and gracious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, do not only reioyse and giue thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to almyghty god with al our hartes, that it hath plesed him to send such a kinge to reigne ouer vs, which so er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly mindeth to set forth amōg his subiectes the light of holy scripture, whiche alone sheweth men the righte pathe to come to god, to se hym, to knowe hym, to loue hym, to serue hym, and so to serue hym, as he most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syreth: but haue also accordyng to our moste bounden dueties, endeuoured our selfes, with all our witte, ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and power, to satisfie your highnes sayd desired moste godly purpose. And thervpon callyng to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance howe the hole pithe and summe of all those thinges, which be at great length conteyned in the hole canon of the Bible, and be of necessitie required to the attayning of euerlasting life: was sufficiently, exactly, and therwith shortly and compendiously comprehēded in the .xii. Articles of the cōmune Crede, called thapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stels Crede, in the .vii. sacramentes of the churche, in the tenne commandementes, and in the prayer of oure lorde, called the <hi>Pater noster.</hi> And considerynge therfore, that if your highnes people were perfitely instructed &amp; lerned in the right knowlege and vnderstanding of the same, they shuld not only be hable easily to perceiue and vnderstande, and also to lerne by hart and beare away the hole effecte and substance of al those thinges, which do appertayne and be necessarie for a chrysten man ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to beleue, or to do, but also that al occasions might therby be remouid, which by any colour or visage haue caused any of them to fal or to be offended: we haue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter longe and mature consultation, had amonges vs,
<pb facs="3"/> compiled a certaine treatise, wherin we haue employed our hole study, and haue therin truely and purely sette forth and declared in our mother tongue, the very sense and meanynge, and the veray righte vse vertue and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of all the said foure partes. And forasmoche as Faythe, is that syngular gifte of god, wherby our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that is to say, our naturall reason &amp; iugement (ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scured and almoste extincted by originall &amp; actuall syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) is lyghtened, purified, and made hable to knowe &amp; discerne, what thinges be in dede acceptable, and what be displeasant in the sight of god. and for bycause also that faith is the very fountayne and chiefe grounde of our religion, and of all goodnes and vertues exercysed in the same, and is the firste gate, wherby we entre, and be receyued and admytted, not onely into the familye or householde of our lord god, but also into the knowlege of his maiestie and deitie, and of his inestimable po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, wysedome, rightuousenes, mercy, and goodnes: We haue fyrste of all begonne with the Crede, &amp; haue declared by way of a paraphrasis, that is a kynd, mere, and true exposition of the right vnderstanding of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry article of the same. And afterwarde we haue intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the institution, the vertue, and ryghte vse of the seuen sacramentes. And thirdly we haue declared the tenne commandementes, and what is conteined in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them. And fourthly we haue shewed the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the <hi>Pater noster,</hi> whervnto we haue also ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the declaration of the <hi>Aue Maria.</hi> And to thintent we wold omytte nothynge, conteyned in the boke of Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, deuised and sette forth this last yere, by your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes like cōmandement: We haue also added in the ende
<pb facs="4"/> of this tretise, the article of <hi>Iustification,</hi> and the article of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> as they be in the said boke expressid. And thus hauing determyned our sentence in all thinges contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the said treatise, according to the very true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of scripture, we do offre the same here with vnto your moste excellent maiestie, most humbly besechinge the same to permytte and suffre it, in case it shall be soo thought mete to your most excellent wisdom to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and so with your supreme power set forthe: &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be by vs and all other your subiectes of the clergie of this your mooste noble realme, as well rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as other, taughte to your highnes people, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute the whiche power and lycence of youre maiestie, we knoweledge and confesse, that we haue none au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorytie eyther to assemble our selfes togyther for anye pretence or pourpose, or to publysshe any thinge, that might be by vs agreed on &amp; compiled. And albeit most drade and benigne souerain lorde, we do affirme by our lerninges, with one assent, that the said treatise is in all pointes so concordāt and agreable to holy scripture, as we truste your maiestie shal receiue the same, as a thing most sincerely and purely handled to the glorie of god, your graces honor, the vnitie of your people, the which thinges your highnes we may well se &amp; perceyue, doth chiefly in the same desire: Yet we do moste humbly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt it to the most excellent wysedome &amp; exact iugement of your maiestie, to be recognised, ouersene, and correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if your grace shal finde any worde or sentence in it mete to be changed, qualified, or further expounded, for the playn setting forth of your highnes most vertuous desyre and purpose in that behalfe. Whervnto we shall
<pb facs="4"/> in that case conforme our selfes, as to our most boūden dueties to god and to your highnes apperteineth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your hyghnes most humble subiectes and dayly bedesmen.</hi>
         <list>
            <item>
               <hi>Thomas Cantuarien.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ioannes London.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Stephanus winton.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ioannes Exon.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ioannes Lincoln.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ioannes Bathonien.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Rolandus Couen. et Lich.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Thomas Elien.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Nicolaus Sa{rum}.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ioannes Bangor.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Edouardus Hereforden.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Hugo wigornien.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ioannes Roffen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ricardus Cicestren.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Guilielmus Norwicen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Guilielmus Meneuen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Robertus Assauen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Robertus Landauen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Edouardus Ebo{rum}.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Cuthbertus Dunelmen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Robertus Carliolen.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>Ricardus wolman Archidiaconus Sudbur. Gulielmus knyght Arch. Richemond. Ioannes Bell Arch. Gloucestr. Edmundus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er Arch. Laicestr. Gulielmus Skippe Arch. Dorsett. Nicolaus Heeth Arch. Stafford. Cuthbertus Marshal Arch. Notingham. Ricardus Curren Arch. Oxon. Gulielmus Cliffe, Galfridus Downes, Robertus O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, Radulphus Bradford, Ricardus Smith, Symon Mathew, Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Pryn, Gulielmus Buckmaster, Gulielmus May, Nicolaus wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Ricardus Coxe, Ioannes Edmundes, Thomas Robertson, Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Baker, Thomas Baret, Ioannes Hase, Ioannes Tyson Sacrae theologiae, iuris ecclesiastici et Ciuilis professores.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>