<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Linche, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107896_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18047</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4691</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107896</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Linche, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fountaine of ancient fiction : Wherein is liuely depictured the images and statues of the gods of the ancients, with their proper and perticular expositions. Done out of Italian into English, by Richard Linche Gent</title>
                 <author>Linche, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>208 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that beleeueth, that in his writings he pleaseth all mens humors, too much crediteth his owne opinion, and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his owne iudgement: for men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that haue attained to the true maturitie of knowledge, &amp; arts perfection, it is good to agree with, as for lame, and yet snarling censurers, it is matterlesse to satisfie: for so much as the prodigality of such their lauish opinions, hath his first conception of old father Ignorance, and is brought vp and educated by an infectious nurse, called Selfeglorie. This matter now handled, was vndertaken suddainly, and dispatched hastily, for which he craueth milder constructions, &amp; in very deed had it not by an extraordinary accident hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened into the hands of a stranger, it had not now (poore father forsaken child) endured the insuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table tyranie of lawlesse censure. But when I found that it was so far gone, and as it were irreuocably escaped from out my hands, and euen ready to be thrust out naked &amp; clothlesse into the world, I chose rather to father it, and re-entertaine such my wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring traueller, and bestow some few lines in his behalfe vnto the reader, than that so bare a subiect should passe in his imperfections vnepistled, or not
<pb facs="4"/>
befriended with the authors name in such his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatenesse and obscuritie. Such as it is therefore, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther culpable in words too much affected, or in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion being not methodically composed, or in shallownesse in the not proper vnderstanding of the first authors meaning, it must now passe, as for me it is too late to recall it, and too needlesse to repent it, for howsoeuer it is, it once neuer imagined to haue been now subiest to the error-searching sight of a generall eye, being only pend &amp; translated for mine owne exercises and priuate recreations. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am something too tedious, for as it is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd part in an architector to frame a long &amp; vast entry for a little house and of small receit, so for me to vse many words in this place, whose substance (you will say) challengeth no worthines, they should be friuolously bestowed, and time purpose-lesse en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained. For the indifferent Readers I cannot but promise equal allowance: for any venom-lipt rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censuring Satires, I keepe sorrow for their wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne inciuility and rustike imperfections, and do arme my selfe with steele-mettald patience to abide the shocke of their iniurious toung-oppressions. And so in hast I leaue you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Rich. Linche.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>