<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND
Father in God, RICHARD, Lord
Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace,
Primate and Metropolitane of all
England, and one of his Maiesties
most Honorable Priuie
Councell, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Finet, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107708_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16897</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107708</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND
Father in God, RICHARD, Lord
Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace,
Primate and Metropolitane of all
England, and one of his Maiesties
most Honorable Priuie
Councell, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Finet, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The beginning, continuance, and decay of estates : vvherein are handled many notable questions concerning the establishment of empires and monarchies. Written in French by R. de Lusing, L. of Alymes: and translated into English by I.F</title>
                 <author>Lucinge, René de, sieur des Alymes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 163, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND
Father in God, RICHARD, Lord
Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace,
Primate and Metropolitane of all
England, and one of his Maiesties
most Honorable Priuie
Councell, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost reuerend Father, it pleased
your Graces right woorthy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessor,
to vouchsafe my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthy
letters sent him in
my trauailes, a gracious accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
The greatest trouble they
put him to, was to peruse them;
so were the proofes he gaue of
his vertue, and the signes of his
loue towards me, the onely end
and vse I euer had or made of them. Your Grace hath had the
happines, with the merit, to succeed him in his dignities: his
vertues were already yours in proprietie. Of his loue I may
say, as of your Graces; that I then did, as I now doe, rather
desire to deserue it, then deseruing it, desire to make bold vse
of it. Loue that descends on vs from men of vertue and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie,
is it selfe both hope and reward, hire and paiment.
That to-boote which we call doing good, or a benefit, as it is
<pb facs="3"/>
an effect that true loue matched with ability, will euen striue
to produce, so is it then most welcome when it cōmeth sooner
imparted then expected. With this freedome of minde, and
dutie of respect, I present to your Grace this new apparelled
discourse: It hath alreadie put on the habit of three seuerall
languages, and if my iudgement erre not, our English fashion
will not ill become it. I met with it in my wandrings, and
brought it along with me, with an intent, for my priuate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise
of that tongue it first spake in, to translate it: that performed,
my determination to recommend it to your Graces
patronage, fell to be at this late dangerous time, when the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
(arch-enemie of trueth) and his execrable ministers held
their generall counsaile how they might make but one fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke
of our whole estate: but the consideration of your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
most iust imployments in so weightie a businesse, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
me with a reuerend feare of their disturbance, till I
weighed that euen this subiects handling might perhaps doe
good to some bad that had a head, if not a hand (for so great a
clock could not strike without many wheeles) in so damnable a
proiect: since if they will needs out-strip former ages, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine
countries in strange plots of ruining kingdomes and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
wealths, they may by this discourse be drawen to practise
them vpon the common enemie of Christendome, and not
vpon vs that acknowledge with them one Iesus, one Bible,
one Baptisme. Your Grace seeth the reasons and scope of these
my well intended endeuours, which subiect their allowance or
disallowance to your Graces most graue censure, so doth my
vnworthy seruice with my selfe, to your much desired im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,
as</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most seruiceably deuoted,
IOHN FINET.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>