<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107818_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5155</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An harmony of the confessions of the faith of the Christian and Reformed Churches : which purelie professe the holy doctrine of the Gospell in all the chiefe kingdomes, nations, and prouinces of Europe: the catologue and order whereof the pages following will declare. There are added in the ende verie shorte notes: in which both the obscure thinges are made plaine, &amp; those thinges which maie in shew seeme to be contrarie each to other, are plainelie and verie modestlie reconciled, and if anie points doe as yet hang in doubt, they are sincerelie pointed at. All which things, in the name of the Churches of Fraunce and Belgia, are submitted to the free and discrete iudgement of all other Churches. Newlie translated out of Latine into English. Also in the end is added the confession of the Church of Scotland. Alowed by publique authoritie</title>
                 <author>Salnar</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thomas, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 111, 202-593, that is 609, 41, 24, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>I</hi> am to desire the Godlie and Christian Reader, for whose sake onelie this worke was taken in hand, as to accept friendlie and brotherlie of these laboures, and to beare with some light faults which might easily escape in the translating; so to pardon me a great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight, committed especiallie and onelie in the obseruations, wherein is was verie requisite to haue vsed greater diligence. This ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rsight is of two s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, one in certain obseru▪ set downe in the margent, but ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in latine: the other in such as should haue bin placed in the margent, and are cleane left out. These things because they be of some great weight and moment, I thought it good to admonish thee thereof, and to desire thee before thou readest the booke, either to place euerie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation in it proper page, or in reading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o haue recourse to this place, lest otherwise thou maist think hardly of some parts of doctrine, or other matter, set downe in this Booke.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>