<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable Lord Henry Cary Baron of Hunsdon, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter: William Bulleyn wisheth all health, and perfect felici∣ty in Chryste.</title>
           <author>Bullein, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107134_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17156</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4034</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107134</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable Lord Henry Cary Baron of Hunsdon, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter: William Bulleyn wisheth all health, and perfect felici∣ty in Chryste.</title>
                 <author>Bullein, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bulleins bulwarke of defence : against all sicknesse, soarenesse, and vvoundes that doe dayly assaulte mankinde: which bulwarke is kept with Hilarius the gardener, &amp; Health the phisicion, with the chirurgian, to helpe the wounded souldiours. Gathered and practised from the most worthy learned, both olde and new: to the great comfort of mankinde: by VVilliam Bullein, Doctor of Phisicke. 1562</title>
                 <author>Bullein, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 85, 9, 46, 2, 43, 9, 33, 2 leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord Henry Cary Baron of Hunsdon, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter: <hi>William Bulleyn</hi> wisheth all health, and perfect felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Chryste.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ankynde, whych is called of the Phylosopher, <hi>Microcosmos, Orbiculus,</hi> or a little World, hauing in it selfe, eyther Misery, Felicity, or a Meane: although it bee of the most beautifull Forme, and fayrest Shape, excelling all other lyuing Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vpon Earth: And also is rightly indued with goodly giftes of Nature, in whose Braine is fixed the Iewell called Reason, the Mother of Arte, and Science, by whom bee wrought, &amp; Inuented marueylous thynges, whereby our eternall GOD is perceyued in vs his Creatures, more aboundantly, than in the hygh Lyghtes mooueable, and fixed in the Fyrmament of Heauen: whose naturall influences bee knowen vnto Mankynde. Euen so bee the vertues of euery Creature heere in Earth: as Beaste, Foule, Fyshe, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, Trees, Plantes, Fruictes, Flower, Hearbe, Grasse, Gumme, Stone, and Metall. There is nothing so secret hidden, wythin the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of the Earth, or lurking so lowe vnder the Floudes of the Sea: but by meanes, and pollicy, they are brought to vse. Theyr Names, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and Natures are knowen vnto the witty Heade of Mankynde: to thys ende, to help Mankynde in the tyme of hys bodily infirmity. These hath GOD ordayned by his dyuine prouidence, that euery Creature sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, and insensible, should serue hys best Creature, Mankynde.<note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> To thys ende, that he should serue GOD in righteousnes, &amp; holynesse, al the daies of hys lyfe, for these hys Gyftes. And the Philosopher sayth, <hi>in libro de Coelo, &amp; Mundo: Deus, &amp; Natura nihil frustra agunt: GOD,</hi> and Nature doth nothyng in vayne, but are euer working, and doing: he the prynci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall cause, and they hys effect. Yet for all these syngular Uertues, gieuen to Man: through the continuaunce of tyme, Calamities of thys World, Woundes in the Body, corruption of the Ayre, aboundaunce of Humours. &amp;c. the same Mankynde doth decay, dye, and returne vnto the Dust, and become as though hee had neuer bin: although hee bee neuer so honorable, yea or poore, death doth make equality betwene them. Euery mans course is appoynted, they cannot prolong theyr tyme: notwythstanding,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> GOD hath ordayned sundry Meanes, by hys Mynisters, to help Mankynde in the tyme of Sycknesse, to ease theyr paynes, and heale theyr Woundes. And I being a Chylde of the Common wealth, am bounde vnto my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is, the Lande in whych I am borne: to pleasure it, wyth any
<pb facs="3"/>
good gyft, that it hath pleased GOD to bestow vpon mee: not fo thys ende, to instruct the learned, but to helpe the ignoraunt, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort to thys little <hi>Bulwarcke,</hi> whych I doe Dedicate vnto your honorable Lordship. Where they shall not onely be defended in the same, from sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and Woundes: but also being wounded, through cruell Assaulters of thys <hi>Bulwarke,</hi> or Sicke, heere eftsoones they shall haue at hand, all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Cordials,</hi> and wholesome Salues. Whereby they shalbe the abler, to keepe thys Holde agaynst all bodyly euils: whych I doe call Soare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and Sicknesse: for whose sakes, I haue builded this little Fort cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it my <hi>Bulwarke.</hi> Not being able to builde any bigger worke of defence agaynst Sicknesse, or euill Dyet: as that Man of worthy memory, Syr Thomas Eliot Knyght dyd, when he builded hys <hi>Castle of Health,</hi> a Booke very profitable. Would GOD, that all Men of Worshyp in theyr calling, were lykewyse disposed to theyr Countrey, as hee was, and many moe, whose names I doe commend vnto the Reader, wythin thys little <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke.</hi> And although there wyll bee many peraduenture, both malicious, spightfull, and cankred of Mynde, that both wyth slaunder and disdayne, will lay theyr Battry, agaynst thys Fort: I shall be able euer to repulse them, through your Lordshippes good ayde. For I haue builded it very lowe, wanting neyther the strength of Ordynaunce, prouysion of Uictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alles, nor the Pollycie of most worthy Captaynes, &amp; good Souldeours: as <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Dioscorides. &amp;c.</hi> Nowe finally, I shall most humbly desyre your good Lordshyp, to take thys simple Booke, as an Argument of my good Zeale and Loue, that I bare vnto you, for your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse towarde mee. For if I were otherwyse able, to gratify your Honor, according to my bounden Duety: I would not leaue it vndone, as knoweth GOD, who euer geue your Lordship continuaunce of Honour, and prosperous Health.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London. <date>In Marche. <hi>1562.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordshippes euer to commaunde: VVilliam Bulleyn.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>