<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>C., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107291_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17728</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4466</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107291</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>C., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo and tvventy lectvres vpon the five first chapters of Ieremiah : With prayers annexed, at the end of euery lecture: by Master Iohn Calvin. Which being faithfully collected from him as hee vttered them in Latine, in the schooles of Geneua, were afterwards translated int French: and now newly turned out of French, into English, with a table at the end, containing the summe and scope of euery lecture</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 45, 48-315, 19 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Christian Reader, if (as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith) thou wouldest bee truly wise for thy selfe,<note place="margin">Prou. 9.12.</note>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 11.17.</note> or hast a purpose to shew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to thine owne soule, in any thing; then manifest it in this one thing (absolutely needfull for thee,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> if hitherto thou haue neglected it) <hi>viz.</hi> Be sure, before thou leaue this thy naturall life; that God (by the ministery of his holy word) hath breathed into thy dead soule,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.25. Eccles. 9.10.</note> a supernaturall and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life. For in the graue whither thou goest, there will be neither time, nor place for thee, to haue this worke of workes effected, Ioh. <hi>12.35.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 39.5.</note> Thy life is in length but like a span; and euery step thou steppest, for ought thou knowest;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 20.3.</note> there is but a step betweene thee and death.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27. Gen. 27.2.</note> Seeing therefore by Gods especiall appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thou art once to step out of this world (how soone thou knowest not) it being also thy last step: it stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee vpon, whilest life and liberty lasteth, wisely to foresee, that then thou steppest surely, <hi>2.</hi> Pet. <hi>1.10.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 22.3.</note> For if thou diest, and after descendest into the graue,<note place="margin">Prou. 11.7.</note> a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man; so thou risest at the last day, and then wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full will thy condition be:<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> for thou shalt neuer see the face of God to thy comfort. His wrath is now reuealed from heauen, against all vngodlinesse,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.18.</note> and vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of men: Alas! How much more then? Psa. <hi>77.7</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> Needfull therefore it is for thee now;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.2.</note> euen now whilest the day of saluation lasteth, to lift vp thy heart with thine hands,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.41.</note> with loud and strong cryes, vnto God in the heauens, that for the passion and death of Christ, he will be pleased to grant thee grace, that his word may now so sinke into thine eares,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.44. Isa. 55.10.11. Ioel 1.23.</note> that thence it may soake as the raine of righteousnesse, into the furrowes of thine heart; to<note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 19.8.</note> illuminate, to<note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> regenerate, to<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 13.33.</note> season, and<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 17.17.</note> sanctifie, thy whole man, soule and body, <hi>1.</hi> Thess. <hi>5.23.</hi> that thereby (as by the Spirit of the Lord) thou being cast as into a<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note> new mold, and<note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.18.</note> transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the same image, from glory to glory; thou mayest with patience,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.13. 1. Cor. 2.8.</note> comfort, and good conscience, wait till the last day; for the appearance of the Lord of glory, thy Lord and thy God, the man Christ Iesus. For it is not sufficient for thee onely to know the word, to bee the word of Gods grace;<note place="margin">Act. 14.3. and 20.32.</note> vnlesse by sound euidences, thou also discernest, that it hath been a word of grace vnto thee:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> nor barely affirme it to be the word of faith: but by good proofe to find, that it hath been the meanes to breed a sauing faith in thee. Nor yet onely to say, that it is able to saue soules:<note place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> but that it hath been Gods powerfull instrument to saue thee. For the truth is, the word of God was not<note n="g" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> inspired from God, nor written by<note n="h" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.21.</note> holy men of God, to<note n="i" place="margin">Hos. 8.12.</note> vs, and<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> for vs, to the end it should stand<note n="l" place="margin">Hos. 8.12.</note> stranger-like, aloofe off from vs; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by admitting it to dwell and inhabite richly, and plenteously in vs, Colos. <hi>3.16.</hi> it might at length impart of that heauenly vertue that is in it,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> vnto vs. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly esteeme men so farre foorth good,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.7.</note> as they haue extended of their good things vnto vs: and those things good,<note place="margin">Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.10.</note> that haue communicated of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="5"/> vnto vs.<note place="margin">Isa. 39.8. Rom. 6.17. Heb. 6.5.</note> Now if there be any thing vnder heauen good, which also is able to make vs good, it is the good word of God. But we shall but coldly, and faintly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it for good; vnlesse we know by good experience, that it hath communicated of its goodnesse vnto vs; what good (I pray you) doth that meat or drinke doe vs, which we receiue not into vs? But where the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke craueth, and receiueth these; the effects will soone be discerned.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 14.27.29. Iudg. 15.19.</note> I tasted a little honey (saith <hi>Ionathan</hi>) and mine eyes haue been enlightened. <hi>Sampson</hi> drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (in his excessiue thirst) of the water of Lehi; his spirit reuiued.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 30.11.12.</note> The like befell the poore affamished E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian. Oh that we could come to the good word of God, but with the one halfe of that hungry and thirsty appetite, wherewith (for the most part) wee come to these good creatures of God: we come to these indeed; we take these; we receiue these;<note place="margin">Psal. 104.15.</note> and the goodnesse that is in these, we make it our owne. And if through any defect in nature, we feele them any way defectiue in their nature and properties to vs; we are ready by and by to say, all is not as it should be with vs. Doe wee so strongly and mainly presse toward these, whose vertue at the best, being perishable,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.27. 1. Cor. 6.13.</note> can but sustaine a perish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life: and can we not be at quiet with our selues, vnlesse we feele in our selues, that our natures are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cheered and refreshed?<note place="margin">Luk. 5.1. and 12.1. Matth. 11.12. 1. Pet. 2.2.</note> And shall we not much more presse forwards, to take, and receiue into vs, as with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, the good word of God, which is fitted and framed by God himselfe, to sustaine vs spiritually? Let vs draw neere vnto it then, with knowledge, desire, and faith,<note place="margin">Heb 4.2.</note> as the poore woman in the Gospell, drew nigh to Christ. So shall we sensibly feele the sauing and sanctifying<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15.16.</note>
      <pb facs="6"/> vertue thereof to be infused into vs to our euerlasting consolation and comfort. And then shall our hearts and mouthes be enlarged to speake all the good,<note place="margin">Psal. 138.2. Psal. 19.7.8.9.10.</note> of this good word of God, that can be deuised. Yea, we shall not only praise it, but also with <hi>Dauid,</hi> the man of God, wee shall highly prize it; farre aboue all earthly profits, or delights, Psal. <hi>119.72.103.</hi> Then we shall be able with him againe and againe, to professe how entirely we loue it, vers. <hi>97.</hi> yea, how greatly we delight in it, vers. <hi>174.</hi> yea, what ioy and felicity we take in it, vers. <hi>14.162.</hi> yea, how incessantly our thoughts and meditations are taken vp about it: namely, before break of day, ver. <hi>147</hi> throughout the day, vers. <hi>97.</hi> in the night. vers. <hi>55.</hi> yea, at midnight, vers. <hi>62.</hi> Let vs not then (as the manner of some is) permit the word of God, barely to harbour in our houses: but let vs endeauour rather, to harbour it within the closet of our hearts.<note place="margin">Psal. 119.11. Luk. 11.28.</note> And oh happy wee! that euer it was our hap, to lodge within vs so honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gracious a guest; that will euery way be so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall vnto vs,<note place="margin">Psal 119.24. Vers. 50.</note> as in our greatest distractions, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell vs; in our deepest distresses, to comfort vs: and when we are to seeke of our way; to direct vs, directly to that hauen of happinesse,<note place="margin">105.</note> where there shall bee mirth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mourning; fellowship with God, and all his saints, without parting; where we shall be euer prest to doe his will without fainting; and that, time without ending. As for those that<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 2.3.</note> neglecte so great saluation, that haue the word,<note n="b" place="margin">2. Thes 2.10.</note> but loue it not: that reade it, but will not be<note n="c" place="margin">Psa. 50.16.17</note> reformed by it: that<note n="d" place="margin">Prou. 13.13.</note> despise it,<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 6.10.</note> reiect, and scorne it: To say no more, their damnation sleepeth not: God cannot, nor wil not put vp, such indignities at the hands of sinners, Isa. <hi>5.24.</hi> Ier. <hi>5.13.14.</hi> and <hi>6.10.11</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> vnlesse they meet him, and that speedily,<note place="margin">Amos 4.12.</note> by true and vnfained repentance. And if thou say, Oh that I could! I wish thee often to read these holy Sermons of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, penned by the holy Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> for that purpose. For if repentance be a wounding of the heart, proceeding of faith, which seeketh vnto God for mercy: then hath <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> like a skilfull master-builder in these present Chapters, and those that follow, laid the ground-worke of such a repentance out for thee. And if thou say, how shal I vnderstand, vnlesse I haue a guide?<note place="margin">Act. 8.31.</note> Accept (I pray thee, for the present) of this, which God of his goodnesse hath heere sent vnto thee, by giuing him accesse into thy Chariot, closet, or other retired places: and if thou entreat him friendly, and makest thy gaine by him of this little; the Lord peraduenture may hereafter trust thee with more.</p>
   <p>But before I take my leaue of thee, as the summe of all: let me entreat thee (as thou tenderest thine owne welfare) to lay vp in thy heart, these sixe lessons, which the word of God teacheth thee, according as I find them laid downe by a learned Diuine.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1</hi> The word of God teacheth thee, that thou being by creation made righteous, art by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and by thine owne transgression, become sinfull, Eccles. <hi>7, 31.</hi> Gen. <hi>6.5.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> The word of God teacheth thee, that thou art by nature the child of Gods wrath, and a fire-brand of hell, Ephes. <hi>2.3.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3</hi> The word of God teacheth thee, that thou haste cause to bee troubled for this, more than for all worldly crosses, and to be humbled and cast downe in thy selfe before God for it, Act. <hi>16.50.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>4</hi> The word of God teacheth thee, that thou being laden with thy sinnes, and weary of them, art not to sinke downe in despaire of Gods goodnesse; but to relie vpon his mercy in Christ Iesus, Ezra. <hi>10.2.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5</hi> The word of God teacheth thee, that thus relying vpon God in Christ, he hath mercy in store for thee, Psalm. <hi>130.7.</hi> Ioh. <hi>3.16.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6</hi> The word of God teacheth thee, that all true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers haue a constant care and endeauour, both to learne and know the will of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note> and to obey it in all things, Luk. <hi>1.74.75.</hi> Tit. <hi>2.11.12.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These poynts the word of God teacheth: and these if we learne and beleeue, as the word teacheth them; wee shall in the end be saued. And thus with my humble prayers to God that it may be so,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I bid thee in Christ heartily farwell. C. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>