<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GODLIE AND Faithfull Ministers of the Church of Christ, throughout the Low-countries, my brethren beloued in the Lord.</title>
           <author>Sarauia, Hadrian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107871_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11498</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21749</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107871</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GODLIE AND Faithfull Ministers of the Church of Christ, throughout the Low-countries, my brethren beloued in the Lord.</title>
                 <author>Sarauia, Hadrian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>D. Sarauia. 1. Of the diuerse degrees of the ministers of the gospell. 2. Of the honor vvhich is due vnto the priestes and prelates of the church. 3. Of sacrilege, and the punishment thereof. The particular contents of the afore saide Treatises to be seene in the next pages</title>
                 <author>Saravia, Adrien</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Perrin (Perin), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 240 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Ministers">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE GODLIE AND Faithfull Ministers of the Church of Christ, <hi>throughout the Low-countries, my brethren</hi> beloued in the Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time I liued at Leiden (worshipfull and beloued) I many times, with many of you, bewailed the state of the Church there: In the which, the deuill, (the deuill it is) spreadeth his net, as many other waies, so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speciallie nowe with a certaine newe slight after another fashion: In the which he hath his gins and engins, nothing like vnto those of olde, when hee went a hirding with gainefull hipocrisie, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled the soules of Christian people with a kind of costlie supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: then did the Cleargie, and the Layitie ambitiouslie contend, (as yet they continue vnder the Papacie) whether should exceed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: they in their pompous sanctimonie, or these in their superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous munificencie: So they, sold (and sell) at a deare reckoning: these, bought (and buy) at the hucsters handes: The one deceiuing, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiued; both in an error, neuer a better. And is it not strange to see (a thing that is not strange,) how superstition and hypocrisie is of more force and preuaileth more, to conquere and lead captiue the minds of men, then true and sincere religion, which is pure and plaine, without wealt or gard? But such is either the negligence of men, or the nature of man, it will be deceiued, and will deceiue. Who is able to recompt (and keepe reckoning,) the quircks and the tricks, the gybing and the iugling of the Romaine Alcaron, by the whiche they hold play with the simple, and play noddie with the peoples sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie? The paines of Purgatorie, the Popes pardons, Images, false miracles, pilgrimage to statues, shrines and crosses, reliques of saints, bones, teeth, and ashes, vestments, belts, and sandals, and a thousand such like trumperies? These are the martes and the marchandise which they make ouer to the peple for hid treasure, while they sel the people for olde shooes, What should I more say? They say themselues, (and the more shame) they are not ashamed to say: <hi>That these and such like, are the Religious illusions of the Religious.</hi> VVhat
<pb facs="9"/> a commodious craft auricular confession is, the Iesuits (besides other the Romish Prelates minions) doe feele, and find. But now adaies, because the true Ministers of Christ, and the faithfull stewards of his house are not trained vppe in these trades, nor guiltie of these traines, they are set at naught of naughtie men.</p>
   <p>And yet of olde, when the people doted ouer their false Gods, and spared for no cost, so they might satisfie their soules with neuer-satisfied superstition, they were notwithstanding nothing so ranke in seking to satisfie the rauine of that vnkind lust towards their false God and his worship, as they were slowe and slacke to inquire after the true God his seruice, and his true seruants: and why then should it seeme a thing rare or insolent among vs, if the like kinde of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindnes be reuolued vpon vs in this age? For man to man, and age to age is as like, as is the water to the water, day to day, to day and heareafter.</p>
   <p>In what honour and estimation the Ministers of the Church are among the Romanists, is well knowen to such as either now liue, or at anie time haue liued amongst them. But now, amongst vs the professors of the Gospell, they which sincerely teach the true religion, and truly teach what way leadeth to heauen, and by what means we are reconciled to God, ar ether nothing at al acounted, or as nothing. Is any thing (for honour sake?) for pittie sake yeelded vnto them? it is by and by thought much of, and thought too much, bee it neuer so little. For which sinne, not onely the vnkindnes of the people is to bee condemned, as principallie guiltie, but our owne foolishnes also may be conuicted, as accessorie faultie. And howe? Forsooth a toy hath taken vs in the head, and we haue taken a toy in hand, by sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prising the Popes tyrannie, to suppresse our owne liberty: As if indeede, the excessiue riot, and not expleable auarice of the Popish Cleargie could by no possible meanes be rebated, vnlesse wee thrust downe the reformed Ministerie beneath the Bell-ferie, and hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer head lay wast all the possessions of the Cleargie. A passing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice indeede, to bring this to passe (as it hath alreadie brought it within come to passe) that the Church wanteth wherewith to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish the sacred Muses, and is faine to honour the painefull Minister with monethly menstruous fees.</p>
   <p>From hence is foisted into the Church, a kinde of temporall
<pb facs="10"/> biter, after a new fashion &amp; an euil example: who chiefly attending, vpon their own drudgerie, by the way ioyne hand with the Pastor in his prouince, and that for a yeare or two at the most (that they may be good in their office.) And by this meanes, (that which I account worse then all the rest) the beautie of the Church is vanished, and that vnited force of the brethren which in placed in one Bishop, who dare with confidence, and may with authoritie controule the wicked in their enterprises, is vtterlie lost and languished. For whilest eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one is dispised, all are contemned and likewise, whilest euerie one taketh care of his owne Curch onelie, they altogeather neglect the good of the whole Church generallie. I spare to exemplifie this: your selues suppose, what, and where vpon I speake it. But doe you not see, or can you not conceiue, how that many things may daily chance in the Church, which concerne all Churches in common, and for the which, a present remedie must be had? In this case no priuate man dare vndertake the cause: and why? he seeth and considereth that the matter pertaineth not to him, or to anie one, or to a few, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the rest of that whole Prouince in common. But whilest hee which could find in his heart to put himselfe vpon the action for the common good, yet findeth many doubts in his hart, and is stil affeard least either himselfe should not be allowed, or that he should perform not confirmed, by the rest; of necessitie the time is deferred in this necessitie, and needs must a further time be expected, vntil the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren may bee assembled. That a Synode should bee called for euerie such matter, it is both costly and inconuenient: and many times also before either they could be called, or come togeather, either the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that was feared would be receiued, or the occasion that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered would be ouer-passed, whereby the euil might ether altogether, or more easily haue bene remoued.</p>
   <p>Amongst you, the Church-goods are rifled and ruined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie reuerend regard of sacred or prophane: as if (forsooth) it were religion for the Church of Christ to bee woorth one dodkin in a christian Common-wealth: or as if indeed it were the onely errour of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they are rich. Doth anie thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine yet vnransackt in any of your Churches? the better for those Burgreeues and Burgomaisters in whose handes it is. As for your selues, there is not so much as one mite left to bee at your disposing:
<pb facs="10"/> you that stand so much in your ownlight, and haue put out two lights with your too much lightnes, can you put out mine with an half pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie? alas good souls: if you were euerie one pore, yet might you be all rich. But now it is the cōmon opinion, that Pastors ought of congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be poore and needie: and that is so deeplie infixed in the harts of the simple peple, that they can hardly be perswaded to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Is it possible, but by such meanes it shuld one day come to passe (if they thus proceed) that the whole Ministery of the Church shuld fal ether into vtter decay, or wretched contēpt? I was purposed (if I had staied with you) to haue conferred about this matter with the States themselues. And verely I would haue exhorted and intreated thē, that they would take some better course in this cause: I would haue taught them, that they had no right at all vnto the church-goods: I would haue prooued and protested vnto them, that whatsoeuer ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities haue befallen the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> they are al but the iust vengeance of God for their sacrilege: that the goods of Cathedrall and Collegiat churches, and also of many Monasteries, were desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and consecrated to the vse of sacred studies: And last of all, I would haue informed them, and confirmed to them, that whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath varied from the first institution therof, ought not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, but restored by the christian Magistrate. But this my good purpose was hindered, first by the vntimely death of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and then also for the Earle of <hi>Leycester</hi> his sake: Least I might seeme to haue attempted the same, either at a bad time, (in the greatest tumult of the countrey) or els by bad means (presuming vpon the fauour and furtherance of my L. the Earle.</p>
   <p>In the meane while, I might greatly wonder at the error of many, and they not meanely conceited towards the Gospel: neither should I cease to wonder, were it not that I knowe the Ministers themselues, whome the matter doth more neerly concerne, to bee the authours of that error. But when I consider with my selfe the iniquitie of these euill daies, and the bad meaning of euil men, I cannot wel tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I might rather lament or reioyce in that their foule ouersight. For albeit to haue the churches spoyled &amp; left desolat of such helps with the which it ought to be releued, may bring vpon both Church and State a greater misery then many can suspect, or any can auoyd: notwithstanding, that in the beginnings of reformation, there was
<pb facs="11"/> nor mention nor motion made for the Church-goods, it greeueth me the lesse; for that by this meanes the aduersarie cannot well say, that we rather sought the treasure of the Church, then the glorie of God. For had they made anie question of the Church-goods, these cauils and quarrels might haue taken some aduantage of them. But now, when as they esteemed of whatsoeuer the Papists possessed, as of things nothing pertaining vnto them, and referred all the whole matter to the moderation of the Magistrate; by this meanes, Suspicion it selfe could not but cleare them of suspicion. <hi>So God sometimes doth vse the verie ignorance of his seruants, to some good end:</hi> namelie, <hi>when as a truth taught out of time, would doe more hurt then good.</hi> Notwithstanding, that which sometimes hath beene obiected, can neither be denied nor defended; that there were some which tooke our part in hope of the pray onely. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit these things were not altogether vnknowen vnto the godlie at that time, (as their writings doe witnesse) yet in wisdome they chose rather to suffer and say little to that iniurie, then that in hast they should goe about to offend any. And in this they did imitate Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> who in the rich Cittie of <hi>Corinth,</hi> had rather labour with his hands, and so get his maintenaunce, then otherwise to giue anie occasion of suspect to a nouice people, not seene into the dignitie of his right Apostolique. And shall I tell you? that onely conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was not the least cause, why my selfe dared not bewray vnto euery one the silence of my thoughts: And yet (such was my natiue weakenes, or my foole-hardie forwardnes) I could not hide my selfe from my brethren and companions, and some also of the Magistrats of <hi>Gaunt.</hi> But I spake not then so freely, as I meane to doe in this discourse: For I alwaies feared, as I ought to do, least such as were but newly wonne to the faith of Christ, might be haplie lost by my indiscreet libertie, and my selfe brought into a needlesse gealosie of auarice and ambition.</p>
   <p>But now, seeing I am in that place and condition, in the which no man can iustly accuse me, as if I sought any especiall commoditie for my selfe, or desired any other thing, then that which is commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and necessary for the Church: I thought it my duty to speake plainely, what I thinke of the goods and possessions of the Church. Neither is it enough for mee, that I am heere well prouided for my
<pb facs="11"/> selfe: I wish the like vnto my brethren. And although I may iustlie complain my self, to be iniuriouslie forsaken of you, whom I ought to haue found the chief Patrons of mine innocency: yet notwithstāding, my loue and my Zeale, both towards the Church, and also vnto you-wards, is not therefore either altered, or alienated. And how then shuld I be lesse carefull for yours &amp; your Churches good, then when my selfe was in the same ship with you? VVherefore, seeing we haue now sufficientlie wincked at this errour, as well of the people, as the Magistrate, which (if it be suffered) will bring to the Church, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a deadly ruine, or a desperate mischiefe: we may no longer dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the matter; the Church it selfe must be taught hir duetie towards hir Ministerie. It is a perilous &amp; pernitious thing, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath an euill president vnto our posteritie: who shall take all for reformation, whatsoeuer they receaued in the name of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (for what cause so euer it was done.) Men (as you know) for the most part, vse rather to regard the deed, then to respect the cause: what is doone euerie man can tell, but for what cause it was doone, there are few which can conceiue, or well consider.</p>
   <p>I must needes confesse, I haue proceeded some-what farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this matter, then my purpose was, when I came first hither: For that I see heere in <hi>England,</hi> by the euill presidents of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, most men are carried away with the same errors. Some streine their consciences so farre, and open their mouthes so wide, that like dronken men they stretch and yawne after the Church-liuings, and doe euen gourmandize them already in their hopes mercilesse, and bottomeles conceits. And some againe while they grutch the Pastors their fields, and enuie the Euangelique Bishops the riches of Romish Prelates, (as if it were not lawefull for vs to succeed them, and not exceed them) would seme to eat their hearts in garlike (as they say) while they eat and spit their owne gall in malice. A strange opinion they hold, that the place, power, and authoritie, it hath pleased her Maiestie and the rest of the states, the Bishops should reteine in this kingdome, is a grant vtterly auerse vnto the reformation of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. VVherefore now, what honour is due in a Christian Common-wealth to the Ministers of the Church, and how forforth the same may extend, is to be examined more at large.</p>
   <p>But it is to be feared, least some will be scarcely well pleased,
<pb facs="12"/> especially such as be ignorant of the auncient Church gouernment) with this my treatise <hi>of the diuers degrees of the Ministers of the Gospell:</hi> and the rather, for that I haue noted in their newe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reformation two things not to be liked of: namely, that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentique order of Bishops is abrogated, and a nouell kinde of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters intruded. The which I haue the rather noted, for that the common sort of people are of opinion, that not the least part of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation consisteth in the dilapidation of Church-goods, in the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Prouinciall Bishops, and in the creation of Demi-laicall, and mongrell Presbyters. The which opinion of the people, I doe therefore reprehend, not that I dissallow, that certaine graue seni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours and godlie men should consort with the Pastors, (that is, the true Presbyters of the Church:) but that they may know, (as they shall be taught) not to mistake them for those Elders, of the which, in the Actes of the Apostles, and in <hi>Paules</hi> Epistles there is often mention, and is it not needful also, to point at an error betimes, least it beeing by time confirmed, should not afterwardes be easilie correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
   <p>If any man shall thinke my selfe in the error, or that I haue gone further then he liketh well of: let him teach me that which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I will presently alter my iudgement, and giue ouer the bucklers vnto him that can do best. The which I speake not as if I doubted, or were not thorowlie resolued, that those things of the which I affirme in this book, were not assumed out of gods book. (For I do verely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that I haue not swarued frō that rule which God hath giuen me to follow.) But yet, if any man presume he can teach the contrary out of the word, (and make not the word contrarie) I am more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to attend and be taught, then to teach, and had rather bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, then ouercome: condition, that that onely truth may preuaile, which in truth ought to preuaile. In the meane while, as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies borne, and beare with such as dissent in opinion from me, (so long as they holde intire the Lorde Iesus:) so likewise in the same charity may they beare with me, if I dissent from them, I hartelie wish, and intreat earnestly. If it shall please God, by the counsel of christian Princes, that there may be a generall and a free councell ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated, that (as it becommeth me) I refuse not to bee iudge of my iudgement: but if otherwise, neither I can bee perswaded by others,
<pb facs="12"/> nor perswade others: let vs expect with one accord the iudgement of Almightie God, when euery one shal render according to the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his talent, a reason of his Ministerie. For me to contend with my brethren after a bitter manner? it is no part of my meaning. If in any place my stile shall seeme more sharpe: beleeue me, (I will not fable with you) the greatnes of the mischiefe, not any priuat griefe, hath set an edge on it. And to speake reason, what reason haue I to be violent, or virulent in this question? Seeing whatsoeuer is helde amisse, I impute it to the error and ignorance of art, not to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or euill meaning of men.</p>
   <p>The horrible sacrilege of men is not so manifest to the world, as the execrable authors thereof are vnknown vnto me: (and it gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me not that they are vnknowen.) Of whome then should I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime? Against whome should I declaime? But whereas certaine vngodly men are craftely crept in amongst vs, who make a shewe of religion, and would seem to fauor the Gospell, and that not so much of any deuotion towards God, as in detestation of all godlines: I am constrained many times, more earnestly to inueigh against the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie and impietie of such: (let them be of what estate they may be, if they be of that condition) For neither are our owne colours cleare of such staines: against whome can there bee anie worme-wood too bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</p>
   <p>This I note, that if at any time I name the Hollonders, I note not the whole nation: (God forbid) but onely those that degenerate from the naturall integrity of their owne nation. But are not they so much the more worthy greater ignominy, by how much the more fondly they abuse their owne authority, and the peoples simplicitie? such therefore I must necessarilie, and may worthelie accuse of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme and irreligion, the rest, I cannot excuse of errour and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance onely. Indeed error and ignorance doe sometime mitigate the guilt of the offender, but neuer can it obliterate the staine of the offence.</p>
   <p>It will seeme a hard matter I know vnto some, that sacrilege should be openly reprehended, and vnto some an absurd thing, that in the policy of the Church, Bishoppes should be required. For there are here in <hi>England</hi> a certaine number of wicked men, (and I am very sorie for them) who are so farre out of order with that
<pb facs="13"/> order, as if no Ecclesiasticall Discipline were to be had vnder them. Amongst whome, the quarrell is growen so farre, that nowe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce themselues from the communion of the <hi>English</hi> church, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisticall and Antichristian, and so betake themselues to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and not permitted conuenticles. VVhome I could doe no lesse then lightly note in this place, because they seem to patronage their odious scisme, and mutinous huggor-muggar by the precedent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents of our foraine Churches. O God thou knowest, and themselues cannot bee ignoraunt, that the first peregrine churches which were heere in <hi>England,</hi> had their Lord Bishop <hi>Alasco,</hi> and these which at this day are vnder the protection of the most gracious <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> doe acknowledge the Bishops of those Diocesses in the which they are, and to them they supply. But (thankes be vnto God) there are others, who being somewhat more milde and moderate in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, doe not altogeather estraunge themselues from the assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of their churches: but yet, they haue the Bishops in emulation also, and promise vnto themselues a golden worlde, could they but once bring to passe, that by a preposterous Alchymy of earthly pollicy they could turne gold into drosse, that is, Bishops into Presbiters, &amp; their reuenues into annuities. But to them I dare say, and can fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shew, that they shal bring, themselues? The whole state Ecclesiastik into deepe disdaine, disdaine worse then themselues deserue. And whereas (the Lord be praised for it) we haue now some good Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, it will come to passe that then they shall haue none at all, but voluntary, which as soone as it is begone, will be gone. I omit the tumults and contentions with the which they shall first trouble and turmoyle both heauen and earth. But this is plaine, and I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise them, that they which were the first authors thereof, will proue their first enemies, so sone as vnder these colours they shal haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their desires.</p>
   <p>The calamities of your present churches your selues see, and suffer: but from whence they arise, or what is the true remedy (pardon me, I beseech you, if I speake as I thinke) you seeme not to see or conceiue at all.</p>
   <p>Doe you not heare of the turbulent state of other Churches? and you know what they were from the beginning. Where, if they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained for a popish Prelat, a true BB. &amp; for Romish masmongers
<pb facs="13"/> Euangelique Ministers, contented and contenting themselues, with the rites and reuenues of their owne Churches: no doubt all thinges amongst them, had continued more peaceable and prosperous, aswell in Church as, Common-wealth.</p>
   <p>The like I affirme of other prouinces, from whence is exiled the tyrant of Churches. But what can be done, where the mindes of men are foreseasoned with preiudice, and alreadie resolued, That to bee ruled by bishops, and to be releeued by Tythes (and other oblations of the people,) is a point of Poperie.</p>
   <p>But may I not be so bolde to tell them, (and I will tell them but the truth) that these, and such like medicines as they go about to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minister vnto the Church maladies, are like to prooue but prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto further mischiefes? Admit the drugs they concoct be not simplie offensiue, yet is it to be considered, (and wise men wil consider) whether the faintnes and infirmitie of the whole body of the common-wealth, may abide the same. Here there is need of great wisedome, &amp; no lesse moderation: the which as it may be in many, so must it be in one, which may execute the same: and this is he, which is not to looke ouer one part, but to watch ouer all, not of the whole worlde, (which neuer any mortall thing, or could, or can,) but of one Cittie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, so farre forth as the power of man may extend it self. And may wee not also more saflie walke in the steppes of the auncient fathers, then rashlie to step aside into tracts of our owne treading?</p>
   <p>Now, how you will accept of this my libertie, I cannot well tell, but I hope well of you, and commit the whole cause vnto God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. This I am perswaded, and this haue I learned, that in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stayed estate, it is not the part of a good Cittizen, to suspend his censure of the Common-wealth, nor of a faithfull Christian, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse his opinion of the Church of Christ. For mine owne part, if in this daungerous enterprise, I shall obtaine that onelie, which I haue propounded vnto my selfe, I shall haue iust occasion to giue thankes vnto my GOD: but if it fall out otherwise, yet shall I haue discharged my duetie vnto my Brethren, and performed my vowe to the Church of GOD. Vnto the whiche, I haue hitherto thought my selfe indebted as muche as this comes vnto, That a knowen errour ought not to bee ouer-slipped in the silence of mee.
<pb facs="14"/> But put case, I doe smale good vpon those, for whose sakes especially I haue traueiled in this duetie; yet shall their remaine a perpetuall note of that notorious errour vnto all posteritie, that they yet at the length may amend that, in the which they haue found their Fathers to haue bene faultie.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London</hi>
         <date>the <hi>fourth of the Kal. of Aprill.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Desirous of your welfare. <hi>Hadrian Sarauia.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>