<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Earle of Salisbury.</title>
           <author>C., A. B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107637_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18302</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4895</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107637</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Earle of Salisbury.</title>
                 <author>C., A. B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answere to certaine scandalous papers, scattered abroad vnder colour of a Catholicke admonition</title>
                 <author>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 1 coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ To the Earle of Salisbury.</head>
   <p>MY Lord, Whereas the late vnapprouable &amp; most wicked deseigne, for the destroying of his Maiestie, the Prince, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, with many others of worth and qualitie, (attempted through the vndertaking spirits of some more fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; turbulent, then zealous &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spassionate Catholicks) hath made the generall state of our Catholicke cause so scandalous in the eye of such, whose corrupted iudgements are not able to fanne away and seuer the fault of the professor from the profession it selfe; as that who now is found to be that Religion, is perswaded, at least in minde, to allow (though God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="6"/>as much abhorring as any <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane</hi> whatsoeuer) the said former most inhumane, and barbarous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: And whereas some of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Councill, but especially your L. as being knowen to bee, (as the <hi>Philosopher</hi> termeth it) a <hi>primus motor</hi> in such vncharitable procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, are determined (as it is fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) by taking aduantage of so fowle a scandall, to roote out all memory of <hi>Catholicke</hi> Religion, either by sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den banishment, Massacre, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment, or some such vnsupportable vexations, and pressures; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by decreeing in this next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, some more cruell and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Lawes against Catholicks, then already are made: In regard of these premisses, there are some good men,
<pb facs="7"/>who through their earnest desire for continuing the <hi>Catholicke</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and for sauing of many soules, both of this present, and of all future posteritie; are resolued to preuent so great a mischiefe, though with a full assurance aforehand of the losse of their dearest liues. You are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hereby to be admonished, that at this present there are fiue, which haue seuerally vndertaken your death, and haue vowed the performance thereof, by taking already the blessed <hi>Sacrament,</hi> if you continue your dayly plotting of so tragicall Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems against Recusants. It is so ordered, that no one of these fiue knoweth who the other foure be, for the better preuenting the discouery of the rest, if so any one by attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="7"/>and not performing, should be apprehended. It is also already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, who shall first attempt it by shotte, and so who in order shall follow. In accomplishing of it, there is expected no other then assurance of death; Yet it will willingly bee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced for the preuenting of those generall Calamities, which by this your transcendent Authoritie, and grace with his Maiestie, are threatned vnto vs all. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the difficulties herein are more easily to bee disgested, since two of the intended Attemptors, are in that weake state of body, that they cannot liue aboue three or foure monethes. The other three are so distressed in themselues and their friends; as that their present griefes
<pb facs="8"/>(for being onely Recusants) doe much dull all apprehension of death. None is to bee blamed (in the true censuring of matters) for the vndertaking hereof: For we protest before GOD, wee knowe no other meanes left vs in the world since it is manifest that you serue but as a watch, to giue fire vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie; (to whome the worst that wee wish, is, that hee may be as great a Saint in Heauen, as hee is a King on Earth,) for intending all mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs against the poore distressed <hi>Catholickes.</hi> Thus giuing your Lordship this charitable admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the which may perhaps bee necessary hereafter, for some others your Inferiours (at least in grace and fauour) if so they runne on their
<pb facs="8"/>former inhumane and vnchristian rage against vs, I cease, putting you in minde, that where once true and spirituall Resolution is, there, notwithstanding all dangers what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, the weake may take sufficient reuenge of the great.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your L. well admonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing friends, &amp;c.</hi> A. B. C. &amp;c.</signed>
   </closer>
   <postscript>
      <head>Postscript.</head>
      <p>It may be your Lordship will take this but as some forged Letter of some Puritanes, thereby to
<pb facs="9"/>incense you more against Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants. But wee protest vpon our saluation it is not so, neither can any thing in humane likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood preuent the effecting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but the change of your course towards Recusants.</p>
   </postscript>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>