<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107136_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17242</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4093</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107136</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the head-corner-stone: by builders still ouer-much omitted : that is; a forme of teaching Iesus Christ, out of all the Holy Scriptures, both of the Old Testament (that are canonicall) and of the New; ... The whole worke being digested into two seuerall tomes: eyther of which tomes, hauing two bookes therevnto appertaining: as more at large is to be seene in the next leafe. Togither with certaine tables of diuers sorts, for the better vnderstanding, and vse of these bookes; ... By Edm: Bunny, Batcheler of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Bunny, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 577, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touching these Books, that now (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) I offer vnto thee, I haue thoght it needful to acquaint thee with some fewe things first, concerning the same: most of them cōcerning the substance or matter of them; but some few likewise, of the maner wherin it now procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. As touching the substance or matter of them, I was at the first in such a course or kind of life, as the yonger sort (vnder the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Parents) of like condition, are wont to be sorted vnto, and spent a few yeares therein: not meaning, nor knowing then, but in it to haue proceeded, as in that function or kind of life, wherunto it had pleased God to ordaine me. But those few yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so spent, it pleased God then to call me to the labour of the Ministery: &amp; soone to set me on worke therin. In it I was occupied, after the vsual or common maner, a few years more. Than, hauing a dore of farther imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment opened vnto me, &amp; accordingly (in some measure) both aduising my selfe, and seeking farther, as in such a case it behoueth, what course I were best to take therin, it pleased God to lay me forth such a course as was not so vsuall: both for those among whom I was to bestow my labour; &amp; for the forme or manner of that, which I was to deliuer vnto them. Of the parties it is not needfull to speake, in the case that now we are in: but for the forme or manner of that which I was to deliuer, it was the very same that here I do now offer vnto thee. I haue bin therin occupied long; euen for the most part of my time, since I began it: &amp; both my selfe haue found that benefit by it, and many others too (as of their owne accord them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues haue deliuered) that I could not, but in dutie, both set it downe, and impart it to others. No new thing at all, in the substance of it; but such as soundeth (and that in great measure too, God be thanked in these blessed daies of the Gospell) all Christendome ouer, especially in these Churches of ours: but for the forme or manner of it, though handled by me, but after my plaine and simple endeauour; yet such in it selfe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, as to my knowledge (and as before I haue said, is neither yet vsed by any, nor by our Writers (Old, or New) deliuered vnto vs.</p>
   <p>In which kinde of labour as I was occupied, occasion was offered, to giue forth some part of it before: by which occasion long since I gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and soone after published, a forme or manner of the Lawes of God, such as he gaue to the children of Israel: terming it the Scepter of <hi>Iudah;</hi> and publishing it, 1584. In it I acknowledged, that then already I had a greater worke in hand, which but in much longer time, I could not get ready: and in truth it prooued much longer, than I conceiued. Yet now at the length, God hath vouchsafed that mercy vnto me, that in some sort, or according to my measure, I haue gotten it ready, and now at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent salute thee with it.</p>
   <p>The effect of it is, the whole body of those Scriptures that are Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, generally: but for orders sake, I haue thought best to distribute the
<pb facs="6"/> same into a couple of Tomes; and each of them into a couple of Bookes. The former of these two Tomes likewis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of the Olde Testament: the latter, of the New, and somewhat farther. In that which is of the Olde Testament, the former of those two Bookes, is of Historie: the later, of Doctrine. In that which is of History my endeauour hath been, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact or knit all the seuerall parts together, so to make one body of it: and withall, to draw it forth in equall proportion, as a thred that is euen spun; not lesse not bigger in one place then another, but alike, so neare as I could. But to the ende, that of the History better vse may be made, there is euer now and then Doctrine deliuered, as the History it selfe doth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, and as it pleased God to vouchsafe me to espie. In that which is of Doctrine, my endeauour hath not beene to gather all into one Body (which notwithstanding I had in election, and my selfe was much incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto it) but haue resolued on the better course, as I do take it: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to take all those whole Bookes that are of that sort, as they lie; and but onely to lay forth a Method of them. But whereas in those Bookes that are most of History, we haue diuers parcels that doe rather appertaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Doctrine, especially in those that are accounted the Books of the Law, those parcels haue I gathered to that Booke which is of Doctrine: and those Lawes of God, not onely in parcels as they lie, but haue gathered them all besides, as it were into one entire Bodie. In that which is of the New Testament, the former of those two Bookes is of the estate of the Church or people of God, during the time of Christ, and of his Apostles: the latter of them, a compendious, or briefe recitall of the Story of the Church among vs Gentiles, from the time of the Apostles vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Age wherein we liue.</p>
   <p>The vse of these as I doe conceiue, and as I hope that God will blesse them, will be of good and speciall moment: and to his blessing I do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it. But one thing there is, that my selfe might in some sort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto such, as shall be disposed so to take it. The Saboathes we all doe graunt, the most of vs the Holy-daies also in a second degree) were best to be spent in some godly exercise or other. The Scriptures we haue and other good Bookes, in great plenty, which to such end we may vse to the glory of God, and to the edyfying of our selues and others: and euery one is at his liberty to vse any such at his owne discretion, in all lawful and orderly manner.</p>
   <p>In this worke of mine, there be two chiefe and principall matters: one of History; the other of Doctrine. The knowledge of the History that herein is deliuered (euen frō the beginning vnto this present Age of ours) I am very sure, is to speciall good vse, to such as would profit themselues by the word of God, whether by reading or hearing the same. Some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable measure of this knowledge doe I conceiue might soone be had, by all such as can be content to take some reasonable paines about it. On this perswasion of mine, and on the hope I haue thereof, I haue thought good to put such in mind as shall in themselues be so disposed (otherwise leauing it free to euery one to exercise themselues in those times, with whatsoeuer other good exercise themselues thinke best) of a way that I haue thought, to such a purpose might well be vsed. In those Bookes that are most of Historie, there are (as I take it) three hundred and nine Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb facs="6"/> in the former Booke of the former Tome, two hundred and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene; of the Story of Christ in the first foure Chapters of the former Booke of the latter Tome, thirtie and one; and in the latter Booke of the latter Tome (a briefe History of the Church) threescore and fiue; and so consequently, three hundred and nine in all. And these, in such odde times of our Sabaothes and Holy-daies, as betwixt, before, or after Diuine-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or publique-Prayer, we haue to spare, might wee easily in such sort bestow, as that in the yeare we should goe through the whole. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baothes, we know, are euery yeare fiftie and two: our seuerall Hollidaies, (the Circumcision, twelfe day, Purification, <hi>Matthy,</hi> the Annunciation, <hi>Marke, Philip</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> Ascension day, <hi>Iohn Baptist, Peter, Iames, Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew, Matthew, Michael, Luke, Simon</hi> and <hi>Iude, All-Saints, Andrew, Thomas,</hi> and the <hi>Natiuitie</hi> of <hi>Christ)</hi> twenty likewise. But whereas we haue three principal Feasts, which haue mo Holy-dayes to them appertaining, thogh it may be wel conceiued, that to this purpose it wil not be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>df<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> to take in all such times in them (that so the people, such as are so disposed, may haue some part thereof to any honest recreation): yet, because those Feasts are all of speciall note, if therefore we shall thinke good, to take out to this purpose, that which is the next, or second day of euery of them; so we shal haue three and twenty in al. Againe, in euery of these we lightly haue three seuerall portions of time, besides those that both morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are appointed for publique Prayer: the first in the morning, before the time of morning-Prayer; the next, after dinner, before euening-Prayer; the third after. The Sabaoth likewise we all doe graunt, would bee on all hands more carefully obserued: and so it shall not be amisse, if any of it allot two of those three portions of time that before we noted, to this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise that now we speake of. The Holi-daies also would not be so much neglected as (vnder pretence of zeale sometimes, and then for that cause so much the worse) now by many of vs they are: and so might we obserue them so much the better, to take one of those three portions of time that before we noted, out of them to this purpose also. So will it fal out, that if we take order with our selues, to read fiue of those Sections euery Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth (three in the former of those times that we take, and two in the later) that in the yeare we shall so haue read, two hundred and threescore of them. On those our other Holi-daies likewise if we shall read, on euery one a couple of those Sections, those Holi-daies being twenty and three, so shal we dispatch sixe and forty moe of those Sections. Then wil there remaine but onely three: and those may we well allot to three of those o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Holi-daies that we have in those our three principall Feastes, to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of those three, but one. And all these are none other but of the history: and these may serue for the first yeare that any shall betake himselfe to the exercise that now we speake of.</p>
   <p>In those parts of the whole worke that are for the most part of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (which are, all the latter Booke of the former Tome, and the sixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene last Chapters of the former Booke of the latter Tome; the former of the Olde Testament, these latter Chapters of the New) first I note no more but this, that both those whole Books of Scripture, and those other seuerall portions besides, whereof they consist, are laide, I trust, a great deale more open vnto the Reader, then otherwise they would haue been;
<pb facs="7"/> and yet the same very briefly too: and that, whosoeuer would haue some Method, either for any whole Booke of the Canonicall Scripture, or for any Chapter or lesse portion thereof, there may he haue it, some or other, such as it is.</p>
   <p>But then as touching such vse of these parts also, as before wee haue spoken of in the other, if any be disposed to set in hand with a second year also, they may soone (I trust) find, that the Sections of these parts are, of the second Booke of the former Tome, two hundred thirty and sixe, and the residue of the first Booke of the later Tome, one hundred &amp; twelue in all, three hundred forty eight, &amp; so thirty mine more then the others. For the Sabaothes therefore and for those Holi-daies of the second yeare, we may take of these, as before of the others: and so haue but those thirty and nine remaining; which may fitly bee bestowed on a second portion of time on those Holidaies which first we named, two a peece on euery one. For those (excepting Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> his day before the Natiuitie) are but nineteene, and so take vp but thirty and eyght; and that day of Saint <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> because of the businesse that commonly it hath (because of those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydaies that follow soone after) may well bee allowed, to bee charged no farther, for that second portion of time that it hath, but onely with one: and so haue we al placed for the second yeare also.</p>
   <p>But then, wherof diuers times Sundaies and Holidaies meete together in one, and then (in Diuine-Seruice, and set Sermons) the most vsuall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is, that the one drowneth the other, in this case it might bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (by such as may haue conuenient leisure) in some time of the weeke ensuing: and the same course might be likewise obserued, so often as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise the exercise wee speake of, were by any occasion omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It may be likewise, that some would conceiue, it were much better, if in some Table it were set downe, what Sections would so fall out to be for euery day, and for the seuerall portions thereof: but neither could that so well be done, because so many of those Sundayes and Holidaies are so mooueable; and in this course that now we haue noted, may euery one at all times beginne, whensoeuer himselfe shall be disposed so to do. As also because some Sections are much longer, and some other but short euery one may vse his owne discretion and freedome therein, both in the one, and in the other, as himselfe is disposed.</p>
   <p>As touching the benefite, that in thine estate towards God, both in this present life heere, and in that which is to come, is like (by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and grace of God) to redound vnto thee, if truly thou employ thy selfe therein, and seekest withall thy successe from aboue, so often haue I seene the good hand of God on many therin, that I cannot but hope, but that it will be gracious and comfortable to thee likewise: and the more it shall please God to extend his goodnesse to thee therein, the more be his name glorified therefore; and be thou more carefull, both safely to keepe, and still to encrease that gracious Talent, that so it shall please him, in trust to commend vnto thee.</p>
   <p>Of all the whole together, yet, by thy pacience, one thing more; this manner of teaching by the whole Body of holy Scriptures, doe I take to be of such importance, to the ouerthrowing of the power of darkenesse, and both to let in, and to settle in the hearts of the faithful the loue of the
<pb facs="7"/> Truth, that if it should be taken in hand by any that should be rightly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished to such a purpose, and accordingly disposed withall, as in former ages there were many and diuers Engines of great force in Warres; but none like to the inuention of Gunnes since both great and smal: so in this spirituall warfare of ours, it might well fall out, that although wee haue many and diuers waies to impugne that power of darkenesse that of late did so ouerwhelme vs, and those very forcible; yet such vnfoulding and laying open of the word of God, being rightly and kindly handled in deed would bee the most forcible Engine (to batter downe Popery, and the whole power of Satan too) that yet we haue vsed.</p>
   <p>And for thy better furtherance heerin, before thou shalt enter into the Books themselues, thou hast some farther helpes besides: some, that may be to the vse of all; one other such, as for many of the common sort will be needfull also. Those which may be to the vse of all, are concerning the matter it selfe: and they are, in that the effect of the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the seueral Bookes by themselues is laide forth, first to the Learned, in the Tables of Method prefixed; then, to the residue, in the Contents of the Chapters, after the vsuall manner, besides. That other, that for many of the common sort will bee needfull also, is about the quotations of the Scriptures that therein are vsed: to which end I haue likewise set down (for the readier going to all the places that there are noted) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the names of the Bookes themselues, as in our Bibles they are wont to be noted; but for some farther, and the more easie getting of them a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod likewise, in what sort they may be well taken.</p>
   <p>Those few moe that concerne the manner wherein it now proceedeth or commeth forth, are, one of them before intended: others, comming in at the Window since. That which was before intended, is, that the Tables are framed to the Capitall Letters in the inner Margent, as other books for the most part are vnto the Pages. The reason is, for that the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles were made before, while the Booke was but in writing, and so could not bee knowne then, of what number the Pages would be when they should be printed: but then those Letters do note in effect, but Pages al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, for that they all in euery Section (the first and the last, which must euer take their place as it falleth, only excepted) had the space of a writtē page.</p>
   <p>At the Window (that I speake of) are other two come in since: one, in certaine of the Sections; the other, in the quotations onely. In the Sections no more but this, that a few of the first of them, are into diuers parcels, by Breakes (as they tearme them) diuided: which for a while on supposall was done, as thinking thereby to ease the Readers labor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. That which is in the quotation, is, that therein for a time they haue followed their wonted order: whereas the manner of these quotations, are to distinguish the number that noteth the Chapter with a Colon, or Middle-distinction from the verses that follow; and some-times to sort the verses also (as the case doth sometimes require) by some other distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions besides.</p>
   <p>These are the things that thus I do commend vnto thee: and that they may prooue to thy greater good, the successe thereof, together with thy selfe and thine, I commend to the good blessing of God.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>