<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107654_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18368</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4941</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise against iudicial astrologie : Dedicated to the right Honorable Sir Thomas Egerton Knight, Lord Keeper of the great Seale, and one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Councell. VVritten by Iohn Chamber, one of the prebendaries of her Maiesties free Chappell o VVindsor, and fellow of Eaton College</title>
                 <author>Chamber, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harrison, John 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 96, 99-114, 117-126, 115-132, that is 134, 4, 2, 41, 1 page, plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="81"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>Among other scapes, gentle Reader, there are two of more importance: the one committed in a place of <hi>Philo,</hi> pag. 8. lin. 24. which you may helpe, if in steede of, <hi>The logicall part to the fence and hedges, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to defend the plants, and the plants to beare fruit, so say they, &amp;c.</hi> you reade, <hi>The logicall part to the fence and hedges, but the morall part to the fruit, affirming that the hedges and fences round about, are made onely for the safetie of the fruit, but the plants to beare fruit, so say they, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The other scape is pag. 107. lin. 26. Where the whole sentence, beginning at, <hi>But wheras the Mandrag, &amp;c.</hi> to the end of the first line vpon the page follow-must be transposed to the 22. line of the 108. pag. to come in before that, <hi>Now that which most aggrauateth, &amp;c.</hi> The rest correct thus.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>