<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worthy and my truely honorable Friend, Sir Beniamin Rudyerd, Knight.</title>
           <author>Rous, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107870_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11070</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107870</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worthy and my truely honorable Friend, Sir Beniamin Rudyerd, Knight.</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diseases of the time, attended by their remedies. By Francis Rous</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 526, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worthy and my truely honorable Friend, Sir Beniamin Rudyerd, Knight.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not but diuers doe direct the Dedications of their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Labours, according to earthly respects. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous and vntunable Dedications, haue euer been harsh to my Iudgement, and it hath grieued mee much,
<pb facs="3"/>
when I haue seen a heauenly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arle offred to the hand, but trodden on by the foot of an earthy and sensuall Patron, To auoyd this Incongruity, I thought it best <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o dedicate a Worke that concernes the prosperity of the Church of Christ Iesus, to a louer of the same Iesus, of the same Church, and the same Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity For such a one beares the face and presence of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hosaphat,</hi> which being seene incourageth a Prophet to speake, and not seene, dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> make him speechle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se. And surely I doe but testifie the Truth, when I say, that by ancient and inward know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="3"/>
I haue beene assured of your loue vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o <hi>Sion,</hi> and your w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l-wish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>g to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity of <hi>Ierusalem.</hi> And euen from this Root of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Loue, doe I beleeue that our particular Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship hath suck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> most part of its nourishment; which I thinke the rather, because it hath beene hitherto durable, whereas worldly Friendships do vsually alter with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Changes. Wherefore as to a louer of Gods House, I present vnto you these par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Purple and blue Silk, which I haue consecrated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the reparation of the Tabernacle. And I desire
<pb facs="4"/>
that when you receiue these words from mee, I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Prayers from you; that God will daily adde to the Beauty of his Church, and that hee will prosper these and the like Workes, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to increase it. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall your Prayers be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnrequited, for I will offer vp my hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>res, for your inward and outward Aduancement, and that as you grow outwardly in the World, you may grow inwardly in Christ Iesus. For growth in Christ, is the growth of a holy happinesse that shall flourish for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>But growth out of Christ is the growth of Fuell, euen of an euer-burning but a neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying Miserie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in the best, that is in Christian af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> Francis Rous.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>