<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MAIESTIE OF HENRIETTA MARIA OF BO-VRBON QVEENE OF GREAT BRITTAINE</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107359_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6385</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107359</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MAIESTIE OF HENRIETTA MARIA OF BO-VRBON QVEENE OF GREAT BRITTAINE</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The reply of the most illustrious Cardinall of Perron, to the ansvveare of the most excellent King of Great Britaine the first tome. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Du Perron, Jacques Davy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bogard, Martin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 262, 261-295, 294-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MAIESTIE OF HENRIETTA MARIA OF BO-VRBON QVEENE OF GREAT BRITTAINE</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>YOVR MA<seg rend="sup">IESTIE</seg>,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>MAY please to be informed, that I haue in this dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation deliuered you that right, that I durst not with-hold from you: your challenge hath so manie iust titles, as had I giuen it to anie others protection, I had done your Maiestie a palpable iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. You are a daughter of France, and therefore fittest to owne his worke who was in his time, an Ornament of your countrie. You are the Queene of England, and therefore fittest to patronize the making him an English man, that, was before so famous a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. You are Kinge Iames his Sonns wife, and therefore, since the misfortune of our times, hath made it a presumption, to giue the Inheritance of this worke (that was sent to the Father in Frēch) to the Sonne in English, whose proper right it is, you are fittest to receiue it for him, who are such a parte of him, as none can make you two, other then one. And for the honor of my Sexe, let me saie it, you are a woeman, though farr aboue other women, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore fittest to protect a womans worke, if a plaine translation wherein there is nothing aimed at, but rightlie to expresse the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors intention may be called a worke. And last (to crowne your other additions) you are a Catholicke, and a zealous one, and therefore fittest to receiue the dedication of a Catholicke-worke. And besides all this which doth appropriate it to you for my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, your Maiestie is she, to whom I professe my selfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A most faithfull subiect, and a most humble seruant.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>