<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT OF the epistle of S, Paule written vnto the Philippians.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107378_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17647</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4402</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107378</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT OF the epistle of S, Paule written vnto the Philippians.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine vppon the Epistle to the Philippians : wherein is set out the necessitie and profite of affliction vnto the faithfull, the benefite of God his word, the fruits, of vnitie and humilitie, free iustification by faith in Iesus Christ without our owne merites, the assurance, ioy, and contented mindes of the godlie, and their perseueraunce in godlinesse vnto the end. With many other comfortable and profitable pointes of religion. Translated out of Latine by W.B</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 95, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb n="1" facs="3"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT OF the epistle of S, Paule written <hi>vnto the Philippians.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is manifest, that <hi>Philippos</hi> is a citie of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> situate in the borders of <hi>Thracia:</hi> in whose fieldes <hi>Pompeius</hi> was vanquished by <hi>Caesar,</hi> &amp; afterward <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Cassius</hi> ouercome by <hi>Antonius</hi> and <hi>Octauius.</hi> Thus the dissention of the Romanes, by two notable battells, made the place famous. When <hi>Paule</hi> by a vision was come into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> he layd the foundation of the Church first in that citie, as <hi>Luke</hi> recordeth in the 16. of the Acts, and 12. verse: the which, how it did not onely continue constantly in the faith, but also by continuance of time, numbers of men, and going forward in vertue, it was encreased, this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle doth testifie. Furthermore this was the cause, why <hi>Paule</hi> did write vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> when they by <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> their Pastor, had sent vnto him those thinges that were needefull for him in bonds, to preserue life, and for other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary charges: it is no doubt but <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> as well opened vnto him the estate of the Church, as was a perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to supply those things, whereof they were to be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished. For it appeareth that they were tempted of false prophets, which at that time wandered all abroad to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt sound doctrine: but because they persisted in the truth, <hi>Paule</hi> commendeth their constancie, yet being mindfull of the frailtie that is in men, and admonished perhaps by <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus,</hi> that they were speedily to be confirmed: lest they should againe fall, he ioyneth such admonitions, as he knew
<pb n="2" facs="4"/> were conuenient for them. And first of all hauing testified the kinde affection of his mind toward them, whereby he might procure credite: he speaketh of him selfe, and of his owne bondes, that they should not faint, because they sawe him taken prisoner, and in daunger of his life. Therefore he sheweth that it is so far of, that thereby the glorie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell should be diminished, that it was rather an argument to confirme it: and together with his owne example, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth them to be readye to endure all things: at length with an exhortation vnto vnitie and patience, he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the first chapter. But because ambition is for the most part a continuall mother of dissention, whereof it commeth to passe, that there is a doore open to newe and strange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines: in the beginning of the second chapter, he earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beseecheth them, that they would preferre nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humilitie and modestie: and vnto that he vseth many arguments. And that he might the better keepe them in their dutie, he promiseth that he will send <hi>Timotheus</hi> vnto them shortly: yea he putteth them also in hope of his owne comming: afterward he excuseth the tarying of <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> In the third chapter, he inueigheth against the false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and refuteth as well their vaine boastings, as the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of circumcision, which they vrged: against all their inuentions, he opposeth onely Christ: against their arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, he opposeth as well his owne former life, as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent purpose, wherein did shine the image of Christian god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines. And this he aduertiseth vs to be the scope of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, (whether thorough out all our life we must striue to come) to communicate with Christ in his death, and in his resurrection: and he proueth it by his owne example. The fourth chapter he beginneth with particular admonitions, and forthwith descendeth into generall. And he concludeth the epistle with a testimonie of his thankefulnes toward the <hi>Philippians,</hi> lest they should thinke that ill bestowed, which they had employed to the releeuing of his necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>