<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE FRENCH TRANS∣LATOR TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107143_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4396</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107143</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE FRENCH TRANS∣LATOR TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary vpon the prophecie of Isaiah. By Mr. Iohn Caluin. Whereunto are added foure tables: the first touching places of scripture alleaged: the second, of the principall matters handled: the third, of authors and diuers names mentioned: the fourth, of certaine texts cited out of Isaiah in the new Testament, which by the author in the commentarie are compared and reconciled. Translated out of French into English: by C.C</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Cotton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 674, 40 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE FRENCH TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATOR TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is twentie yeeres since and more, good Reader, that the lessons of M. <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> vpon the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> (which being col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by M. <hi>Nicolas Gallars</hi>) were printed vnder the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of a Commentarie; and dedicated to that noble Prince of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed memorie, <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth, King of England. A long time after, the Author himselfe reuiewing this collection, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed both in Latin, and in French: satisfied not himselfe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reuiew it, thereby to explane that, which otherwise seemed obscure, by reason of the breuitie of it; and to set that in order, which was somewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused: but he laboured therein with such diligence and good successe, that he augmented it in Latin with excellent and necessarie matters for the vnderstanding of the text; more then the third part: bringing all things into so exact a forme, that if any bee pleased to take so much paines, as to conferre the first Commentarie or collection of those lessons, with this second; he shall find that which we haue said to be very true. Neither was this gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the schooles the second time, as at the first; but was written in the house, euen word for word by the Authors owne direction: who hath so aptly disposed and couched the whole together, that in perusing of it, you shall perceiue in this booke, as well as in others which haue alreadie passed his hands, that he hath done great seruice to the Church of God, and hath also faithfully chalked out the way vnto such as desire to profit in diuine studies. But especially by these his Commentaries, which being carefully read, will serue no lesse to the explaning of many texts that are contained in other bookes of the holy Scripture, as they will also be most helpefull to giue the true sense of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah;</hi> which hath mooued mee (good Reader) to bestow my paines in translating the whole anew into French: lest such among you as vnderstand not the Latin tongue, should be depriued of so great a benefit. Reade, and profit thereby in the feare of God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>