<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>☞ The argument or mater con∣tained in Daniel the Prophete by Philip Melanchton.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1545</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107905_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04696</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14823</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>☞ The argument or mater con∣tained in Daniel the Prophete by Philip Melanchton.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exposicion of Daniel the prophete gathered oute of Philip Melanchton, Iohan Ecolampadius, Chonrade Pellicane [and] out of Iohan Draconite [et] c. By George Ioye. A prophecye diligently to be noted of al emprowrs [and] kinges in these laste dayes</title>
                 <author>Joye, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1545</date>
                 <publisher>Goinus, Antonius.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Joye, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>244 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>☞ The argument or mater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Daniel the Prophete by Philip Melanchton.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any myghty and profitable thigis wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be depely repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed into good myndis Daniel comprehēdeth whyche all to peruse and expresse / owr to skantlitle witts be not able. Netheles let euery diligent reder knowe hymselfe miche to haue profited / if he but the cheif prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ipalls vnderstand / although it be but meanly: and vse the same vnto hys own godly exercise: Considering which part techeth him the trewe inuocation and worship of god and which cōfirmeth his faith / which rēiecteth and refuteth the iewes, and vs castinge away god and his gospel as thei did: which parte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to vs repentance / and which euen nowe monissheth and warneth vs in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, of these laste perellous dayes &amp; blody ende of this worlde. For these causes shall I recite breifly / as it wer the titles herein contained, whiche shal shew you what vtilite shall come to you by reding
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
thys holy boke and diuyne Prophete.</p>
   <p>Firste think you thus of the hole boke. That the story of Daniel is a testimony of the preseruacion of the chirche beuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> with great glory / euen then when it semeth almost extincte and destroid. It techeth vs therfor the chirche bothe to be chastised and skourged / ād anon aftir hir crosse / to be restored to glori. It testifieth also the chirche / not by manis counsel / powre / strength / ordināces / noractis / but by the sin helpe of god / euen from the begining to this daye / to be defended, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued and encreaced. It putteth vs also in mynd of the promises of god to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to hys chirche / although it be done aftir a nother waye then we can conceiue. As when it was promised to the tribe of Iuda, The scepter nor tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to be taken awaye from it vntil that sauiour Sylo come: wher of the kinges of Iuda were so bolde / that they so oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling / moste proudly and cruelly they resisted and dampned the prechinge of Ieremye concerninge the destruccion of their cite temple / and kingdom. As wold nowe men resiste and destroye him that shuld preache to emprours and to kinges saing. Excepte ye repent and receiue the gospell nowe offred you / the turke shall
<pb facs="7"/>
destroye all cristēdom. But Ieremy knew full w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll these thinges bothe to come to passe / that the peple of god shuld be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stised by an haithen king / and yet at that tyme / nether the regale famylie nor the stok of Iuda to be extincted nor the trwe prophets to fayle &amp; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wanted. And euen so it came to passe beyond al menis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectaciō / when fewe or non knew therof. For the kingly stok euē in the babylon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> captiuite had their honor / where god stered vp prophets and orned his chirche with great glory, yea and euen the hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then gentiles did he adioyne vnto the felowship of his owne chirche / so that there was then a gloriouse conuersion of the haithen vnto God / as I praye God there may be of the turkes and iewes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vnto owr trewe cristen religion.</p>
   <p>Secondarily ye shal obserue the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis of Messias owr king Cryste. For <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as the other prophets were cheifly stered vp that by them the promises of Cryste shuld be spred the wyder / euen so it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houed Daniel to do the same office: and that bi many wais / and in many visions. For he prohecyed of his birth telling the yere and tyme therof / and of his passion a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> certenly and iustely the very tyme, as did Iohan Baptist poynt himforth withe
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
his finger / euen whyles yet the comon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale of the iews shuld en, Cryste shuld be borne and suffer / and also when their ceremoniall shawdews &amp; sacrifices all shuld ceasse.</p>
   <p>Thirdely ye shal note the order / of the.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 4. Monarchies / which order is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed / that the very tyme wherin god wold haue cryste borne shuld be knowne / and the tyme of the general resureccion of the dead / and the iugement shulde be signifyed and foresene. So that Daniel prophecieth certainly of these troublouse laste blodye dayes and persecucion nowe of late begunne; which all / Cryste with his laste coming now at hād, shall of.</p>
   <p>Fowerthly ye shal note the places of repentance / of faithe / and of the iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> by faith onely.</p>
   <p>Fyftely / ye shall note the examples of good and euil kingis.</p>
   <p>Sixtely consydere the testimonie of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the resurreccion.</p>
   <p>Seuenthly there is geuē v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> of the vngodly kingdoms / which aboute the ende of the worlde shall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> enforce and contēde to quenche and put away the gospel of god. And here is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed the sorowful lamētable cruel sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teringe of the pore prechers and profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours
<pb facs="8"/>
of Crystes verite / and the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the chirche dispersed ād vanished into sondry strange londis, porely there liuing, vnder kinges em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and rulers, which, wyth cruelty defende idollatry, supersticion and false religion. And in so great confusion emong sondry nacions / sondry sectis shall aryse bolstred vp by manis witte &amp; reason, concerninge gods worship, inuented by man and the iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacion by workis &amp;c. Agenst which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane fantasies and idle imaginacions we must lern in the gospel / god to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shiped in spirit / and faith onely in cryst to iustifye. Ayenst the epicures that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye the resurreccion / and soules to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal / here we haue a cleare testimonye of the resuscitation of the dead to come, where the vngodly shalbe punysshed with payns perpetuall / and the godly endewed with ioye eternall. The profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours of this doctryne shal aryse ayen vnto lyfe. By the doctrine of cryste / of the prophets / and apostles, professed and receyued / the trwe chirche is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> from the Synagog of anticryst. Here it is taught also the chirche not to be the most multitude / but often to be but a litle miserable sorte afflic with pouerty, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, and persecucion with many other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
/ and the wyked enimies of god for the more parte to bere rule / to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prours and kinges, popes, cardinals, bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops &amp;c. And to haue the wealthy vayn glorye of this worlde. But when these vtwarde apperances offende manis rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son / which being ignorant of the wrathe of God ayenst synne / yet cleauing in the nature of man / dreameth these rulers ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be beloued of God to whom he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth victory / impery, riches, &amp; rule: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is necessarye to note this premoni cion, teaching vs how we shulde knowe the chirche of God / where we shuld seke it / euen onely in that cōgregacion which receiueth &amp; enbraceth with perel of their lyues the doctryne delyuered by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets / by Cryste &amp; his apostles. And let not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> / kinges / rulers nor ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches nor their gloriouse titles / nor the multitude / nor longe customs / nor the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly names of their holy mother the chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che moue the to esteme them for the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of god, whiche ether castaway / negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> the vniuersal doctrine of the prophets and apostles / orels openly and pertinatly defende imagis, superstici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vaine ryts / idle ceremonies, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistrye. Here also thou seeste the anticry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis bothe seculare and spirituall prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied
<pb facs="9"/>
to come in the second &amp; third but es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in this last Monarchie / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in thei shall moste cruelly towerds the ende of the worlde greuously persecute &amp; resiste the gospell / here (I say) ar these aduersaries to crist lyuely setforth ī their own colors and as it were with Daniels finger pointed forthe: &amp; also / howe / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewithe / and when thei shalbe destroid. Men must be prudent in diuiding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the prophets documents. Thei must loke whiche parte containeth the laws / whiche preche the promises &amp; the gospell. For vnto these principalls allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things muste be referred. Note also whiche parte declareth the documents. As what can be said clerelyer and euidēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier ayenst the iews / then that Daniel af firmeth cryste to must haue had ben bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne during yet the comō weal of Moses? Wherfore that horrible destrucciō of hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem and ruyne of the hole londe of Iuda nowe paste. 1474. yeres / do testify cryste to be borne / &amp; it refuteth their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and cursed pertinacye. Here must we note the lessons of the trwe inuocacion &amp; worship of God. As whē Daniel prayeth / he aknowlegeth to God onely his owne and their synnes for whom he prayeth / &amp; asketh of God onely delyuerance in the
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
faith and confidence of his mercye / ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by expresse name, For the lorde cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste his sake / that is for Messias his sake promised. This forme of prayer with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the mercy of God promised for crystes sake / we ought to vse in these last and perlous days: now be we taught who be the chirche and therwith monisshed to flye and ▪ that false coloured cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that contende to blot out the name and glory of cryste / defende their images supersticiouse rites, cere. and papistry ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enst the gospel / vnder the name of the chirche or of any other begged glitering gay titles.</p>
   <p>Nether ought this thing to be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted / that to confirme our myndis / God<note place="margin">the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is Gods worde.</note> hathe geuen vs prophecies of all sortes concerning the externe kingdōs / so that by the iust fulfilling of euery thing / as it was prophecied / we haue trwe testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys that owr scripture is Gods worde / &amp; no nother but this owr faithe, to be the trwe faithe also. And that we shuld be warned and tolde when cryste shal come and whē we must loke for the ende of the worlde. And when we see althingis to haue had come to passe / and be fulfilled whiche were prophecied / then we shuld beleue euen these same also to be lykewy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se
<pb facs="10"/>
fulfilled whiche yet this daye the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures testifie to come orels we se them presente. Whiche prophecies the cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syer to be vnderstandē / it is necessary we know the ages of the worlde and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the. 4. Monarchies / and the nowm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the tymes howlong thei stode.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>