<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Preface generall to
Catholickes.</title>
           <author>C., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107159_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17505</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4321</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Preface generall to
Catholickes.</title>
                 <author>C., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A replie vnto a certaine libell, latelie set foorth by Fa: Parsons, in the name of vnited priests : intituled, A manifestation of the great folly and bad spirit, of certaine in England, calling themselues seculer priestes. VVith an addition of a table of such vncharitable words and phrases, as by him are vttered in the said treatise, aswell against our parsons, as our bookes, actions, and proceedings</title>
                 <author>Clark, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 106, 6 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ The Preface generall to
Catholickes.</head>
   <p>COurteous, and beneuolent Catholicks, I present here
vnto you a <hi>reply</hi> vnto a certaine Libell, intituled, <hi>A
manifestation of the great folly, and bad spirit of certaine in
England, calling themselues seculer Priests:</hi> which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening
into my hands, I diligently red ouer, &amp; hauing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
passion perused it, and with indifferencie (as to my selfe
seemed) poysing and considering as well the matter deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
with the forme and manner of the deliuery, as also the
verity thereof, I could not but a little wonder, to see a man so
mightily inueigh against passion, and bitter writing in others,
shewing so much choler, passion, yea and impatience, as hee
doth here. And did I not descry the Author thereof to be
one particuler <hi>Parson,</hi> not many priests, (vnder whose names
falsly, yea and vncharitably it is published, thereby to bring
them into obloquy with their Prince, and state, vnto whom
the Iesuits practises in state matters, heere defended, are odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous)
I should much admire to see so palpable vntruths defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
so manifest vniust actions maintained, and such appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
verities with such boldnes denied: but the worke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
frō the party it doth, hammered in the forge it was, I
could expect no other, then I found; &amp; therefore my won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
was the lesse, and my admiration sooner at an end. For
why, the man is well knowne to be of such a naturall disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
as that if he once enter into any course, he will with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
violence prosecute the same. Vpon which headstrong
cariage, &amp; irremouable wilfulnes, many straines (you know)
and ouerstrainings, must needs follow, and many fained in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions,
with concealements of truthes, yea and in the end,
open impugnations of verities, the better to iustifie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
proceedings, least happily otherwise, the fault might
seeme too light, where it may in no case be indured. Pardon
mee deere Catholickes, in deliuering the truth with such
<pb facs="4"/>
plainenes: let not your antecedent conceits of Fa: <hi>Parsons</hi>
worthines, preiudicate your cens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es in matters so apparant,
and such, as will admit no refuge, for that were to blind your
selues wilfully with affection beyond reason. I remit the
iudgement of this my discourse wholy vnto your discreet &amp;
indifferent censure; if you find not iust cause to condemne
the aforesaid Libell, and author thereof, for the faults aboue
cited, then blame me iustly of wrong done, and I will yeeld
to satisfie at your discretions: if you do find true, this which
I haue said, giue not ouer your selues heereafter to be abused
with too much credulitie in father <hi>Parsons</hi> proceedings. And
heere I must a little craue pardon, if in this my discourse you
find me more plaine, and bold with the said Father, then you
would wish, imputing the same to the extremity of matters
falsely, and vniustly by him deliuered; and to the desert of
his actions, as beeing in very deede, the Arch-plotter of all
such disgustfull affaires, as haue caused all these troubles,
and garboyles from time to time amongst vs: which thing
enforced me a little to presume to display and discouer him
plainly vnto himselfe, and the world, if happily thereby ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hee may reduce himselfe vnto better courses, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
remaine loathed, &amp; reiected of all good English Catho:
(as he deserueth) whereby he shall be no more able hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
to deceiue (through vndeserued opinion) the best mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
minds: nor plot heereafter against our Prince &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
with the conuivence of any. If herein my desires may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
way take effect, I shall rest satisfied, and thinke these my
first labours happily bestowed.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your affectionate seruaunt in Christ
to the shedding of his blood.
W. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>