<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the louynge Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1558</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107419_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10878.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107419</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the louynge Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rules and righte ample documentes, touchinge the vse and practise of the common almanackes, which are named ephemerides : A briefe and shorte introduction vpon the iudiciall astrologie, for to prognosticate of thinges to come, by the helpe of the sayde ephemerides. With a treatise added hereunto, touchinge the coniunction of the planets, in euery one of the. 12. signes, and of their prognostications and reuolutions of yeres. The hole faithfully, and clerely translated into Englyshe by Humfrey Baker</title>
                 <author>Fine, Oronce</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1558</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the louynge Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Osephus,</hi> the true Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographe <hi>(gentle reader)</hi> hathe wrytten in his first boke of the Judaical hystories y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> the fyrst inuēters of <hi>Astronomy,</hi> and the inquisitours of the course and celestiall mouementes haue bene the sonnes of <hi>Seth</hi> who wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to leaue some memory ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto their chyldren and poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye, dyd ordayne and make two great pillers, the one of earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng harde dried, and the other of Copper, in the whyche they dyd graue the prynciples of the seuen Artes liberall, and especially that of <hi>Astrologie.</hi> And they wrote the same in the sayd pillers, to thende that if the worlde shoulde perishe by fier, or by water, (as they dyd
<pb facs="3"/>
vnderstande of their good father <hi>Seth:</hi> who had learned the same of <hi>Adam</hi>) that then one of the sayde pillers shoulde abyde whole, and that the Scyence of <hi>Astronomie</hi> shoulde not perishe. Some do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that <hi>Abraham</hi> dyd first find it, other saye that it was <hi>Moyses, Dyodore Sicilian</hi> sayeth, that the Egiptyans were the firste Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and <hi>Herodote</hi> wryteth that the <hi>Phenicians</hi> wer the inuenters, but who so euer they were, it lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle forceth, let vs therefore leaue the inquisition vnto the curious and praise we God the creatoure of his diuine grace, who hath wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led to illuminate the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them whiche haue left vs in writing the art of <hi>Astronomie,</hi> to our great commoditie and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyt. And seinge that the people at thys presente are dayly more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, &amp; enclined also to reade &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
to haue vnderstandynge in artes and sciences, as some which do fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe polletycke and cyuell mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, do applie them selues to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstād the lawes of Cities, and Regions, and of such thynges as apperteyne vnto the feates of war. Other there be whiche gyue thē selues to read the holly scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures according to the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of holy Church, to thende that thereby they maye be stirred and brought to lyue more vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously: and if ther be any which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wise do, we ought to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to God that he wold in suche wise amende theim, that they take not his holy word in vaine: other ther bee whyche are desirous to reade <hi>Histories</hi> &amp; <hi>Poesies,</hi> and some haue affection to read <hi>bookes</hi> of <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logye,</hi> &amp; to haue knowledge of the celestiall constellacions, &amp; moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, vnto whom thys presente
<pb facs="4"/>
treatise of the rules &amp; documents of the comon <hi>Almanackes</hi> named <hi>Ephemerides</hi> (translated into eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lishe) shal be right expedient &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, seing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these rules are the pathe &amp; way vnto the knowledge of the said <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> for by thē are foūd the course, &amp; mouemēts of the lightes and planets, wyth other necessary thinges of <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> wherby to iudge &amp; <hi>Prognosti</hi> eate of the whether, and of things to come, as by the table folowing more plainly doth appere. Take therefore in good worthe <hi>(louing Reader)</hi> these few rules, being my first traduction, &amp; loke shortely if God spare me life for other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes apperteining vnto this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye Arte.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ And this gentle Reader,</l>
      <l>I most hartely the require</l>
      <l>To examine well these Rules,</l>
      <l>And thou shalt haue thie desire.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>