<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧TO THE MOST Noble Theophilos, the friend, and welbeloued of God: I. C. wisheth the right happie increase and continuance of the Grace, loue, and peace of God, and the high∣est felicitie in Iesu Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107559_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18015</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4664</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107559</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧TO THE MOST Noble Theophilos, the friend, and welbeloued of God: I. C. wisheth the right happie increase and continuance of the Grace, loue, and peace of God, and the high∣est felicitie in Iesu Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preparatiue to contentation : conteining a display of the wonderfull distractions of men in opinions and straunge conceits: and of the seuerall discontentations which are incident to euerie particular vocation and condition of men in this life, with the causes and inconueniences of the same: also how they may be either salued or qualified, pacified or eased. Consected applicatorie, especially to this people and time, as an argument most necessary and profitable to be vrged. By Iohn Carpenter</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 344, 30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧TO THE MOST Noble <hi>Theophilos,</hi> the friend, and welbeloued of God: <hi>I. C.</hi> wisheth the right happie increase and continuance of the Grace, <hi>loue, and peace of God, and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est felicitie in Iesu Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S he which regardeth the wind, shall not sow: and he that respecteth the cloudes, shall not reape, (as saith Salomon) so,<note place="margin">Eccle: 11.4</note> if euery wel-willing mind that would gladly benefit the Church and common wealth, should bee discouraged by the partiall censures of straunge concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heades, and the stinging obloquie of vncharmed tongs (wherewith the ingratefull worlde is replenished) many things which bee both profitable and necessarie for either state, would bee couched in thriftlesse obscuritie: and, as a thousand learned wits haue bin thereby the sooner occasioned to fling from their fingers, both the pen and the paper, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring most vnhappily their Lords Talent: there would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently be seene too to many of those negligent fooles, which perceiuing that all trauaile, and the perfection of workes do purchase emulation and enuie of one man towards an other, doo folde their handes with this sorie resolution: <hi>Yet one morsell with quietnesse, is better,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 4.5.6</note>
      <hi>then both the hands-full with labour and vexation of spirit.</hi> And as for mine owne parte (most Noble <hi>Theophilos)</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="3"/>
I speake of peace, and prepare for <hi>Contentation</hi>: yet haue I no lesse cause of care and discouragement proffered me therein, when I assure my selfe to meete with them which are <hi>Enemies to peace, and</hi> (in their Discontented hearts) <hi>prepare themselues to warre</hi>: for as the most vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall maladies and venemous humours do most strongly wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle and striue against the soueraigne salues, and wholsome medicines which are discreetly prepared and applied to expel and purge them, &amp; to restore health vnto the patient: so is it the nature of the vaine men of this world (especially of such as are <hi>Moriones Diaboli,</hi> I meane the diriders of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to striue and struggle against thē which prepare to purge and heale such passionate persons: Neither will they like well of any medicine, how good and soueraigne soeuer it bee, that shall be applied vnto their maladies. Howbeit, because <hi>The Truth is strong and preuaileth,</hi> and the Author of <hi>Truth</hi> hath taught, that whosoeuer he bee which hath receiued either one Talent, or two Talents, or fiue Talents, after his abilitie, hee is to imploy and occupie the same accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: and hath also willed all them who minde to bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie partakers of the Supper of the great King, to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe all excuses and delaies: I haue thereon presumed and aduentured in this sort to <hi>cast fourth my bread as on the face of the waters:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 11.1</note> yet in this good hope, that <hi>in the length of dayes it shall bee recouered,</hi> and that <hi>my labours in the Lorde shall not bee in vaine.</hi> Next, for asmuch as it is the bounden dutie of euery leige Subiect,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58</note> so to tender and regard the safetie of his Prince, and the welfare of his Countrey, that when he perceiueth either the forreigne enemie to prepare his forces and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to inuade: or the vnnaturall Subiectes to withdrawe their obedience and incline to rebellion: hee withstande the one and suppresse the other to his power: defending
<pb facs="3"/>
and preseruing both his Prince and Countrey, I thought it no lesse my dutie to do the like. Therefore, when I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered how <hi>Nimrod that mightie Hunter before the Lorde,</hi> on the one side had called togither and mustred his forces and assistants towardes the reedifying of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused Tower of <hi>Babel;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 137</note> and that the dissembling <hi>Edomites</hi> on the other side, had assayed to raise and pull downe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred walles of <hi>Hierusalem:</hi> and had taken vnto them in that Action, the Ismalites, the Moabites, the Hagarenes, <hi>Gebal</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Amalek,</hi> the Philistines, and them that dwell at <hi>Tyre,</hi> with <hi>Assur,</hi> who haue cast their heads togither, and are confederate against the Lord and his holy Annointed: yea, and that some other, pretending to new build with <hi>Zorobabel</hi> and the principall fathers of <hi>Israel,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Isra. 4.23.</note> haue rather hindred, then any way furthered the Lords worke, and haue practized without ceasing to reduce our State, and so well ordered Common-wealth into an heedelesse <hi>Anarchie,</hi> and lawlesse libertie,<note place="margin">VVant of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</note> which ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nought else, but a monstrous <hi>Ataxie</hi> and wofull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicitie (from the which,<note place="margin">A confusion or disorder.</note> I beseeche God in his mercie to keepe and defend vs): I was thereuppon vehemently prouoked and stirred vp to stand foorth and to acquite my selfe (though as the meanest of others yet) <hi>Zorobabel, Nehemiah,</hi> and other the principall Builders vnder our most redoubted Lord Iesus, to set hand to the Lords worke, the which being begun, he would should be vrged: beeing in hande, hee willeth to bee furthered: and beeing accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, he commaundeth the same to be maintained according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. To, and for the which purpose, I haue taken in the one hand an Instrument to build for and with, <hi>Israel</hi>: &amp; in the other hand a Sworde to fight against the foes of <hi>Israel</hi>: bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right well assured, that the wisedome of God (the which Ireuerence and highly esteeme) is better then the weapons
<pb facs="4"/>
of warre: and that the valour of his Grace is preferred far aboue al the power, prudence, and pollicie of man. And seeing that it is that naughtie humor of <hi>Discontentation.</hi> (engendred in Ambitious heads, and in distracted mindes) that so much enflameth &amp; agonizeth the state of our church and Common-wealth, the which it laboureth to loade with such inconueniences, as are not onely dreadfull and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, but most miserable and remedilesse. I thought it good in this time, and vpon this occasion, to display on the one side, the horriblenesse of that humour, and to disswade men from the same: on the other side, to shewe the vnspeakable good of <hi>Contentation</hi>) the which springeth vp of the feare of God, and combineth with true obedience to the Prince and brotherly loue) and to perswade all men to imbrace it, as that which is not onely commaunded and commended in the word of God, but also esteemed, honoured and obserued of them that be the Lords. For this cause I haue both framed and intituled this discourse, <hi>A Preparatiue to Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> This hauing finished, and perpending to whome I might chiefely dedicate the same, I happily thought on thee (<hi>Most Noble Theophilos</hi>) to whose Nobilitie before all others, I both present and commend it, mooued to this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> choise by no meane causes. For first I consider of thy <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse</hi> beeing (indeede) the friende and welbeloued of God, and therein preferred to all others, as is the soule to the body and things caelestiall, to the things terrestriall.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> Next, I am not ignorant that these and such like things <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which concerne the kingdome of God, doo properly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto such as being of God beloued, doo also loue and feare him; the which Saint <hi>Luke</hi> well considered, and therefore hauing composed two learned Volumes of the Euangelicall History, he dedicated them both vnto his deare <hi>Theophilos. Luke 1.3. Acts 1.1.</hi> Thirdly, it is certaine
<pb facs="4"/>
that the most reuerend <hi>Name</hi> and note of thy <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> doth adde such an Admirable Grace to the things, which to the same commended thy worthinesse, vouchsaueth to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, that in regard thereof, they are the sooner admitted and imbraced, as those, which were sometimes offred in the Temples, and consecrated to holy vses, haue beene esteemed for pretious Iewelles, as <hi>Plynie</hi> said, writing to <hi>Vespasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the Emperour.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4</hi> Thy right willing and gratefull heart, in the ready <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> acceptation and right estimation of those things (though slender and by meane persons) of good will dedicated to thy Nobilitie, is apparant and commended: the which (beeing well weighed (coulde not but mooue me at this time, to cast into thy Treasure-house this my good-wil offring, though so slender, as the two mytes of the pore wydow mentioned in the Gospell.</p>
   <p n="5">5 Being the faithfull of the Lord, and of him so wel-beloued,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> thou wilt not admit, that either those which slide of ignorance, infirmitie or feare, should bee made publique examples of disgrace: or that whatsoeuer is eyther sayd, written, or wrought (especially by them that thereby ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to benefit the church and common-wealth) shoulde bee wrested and vrged with hard censures and like constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but rather, that the multitude of sinnes should be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably couered, and all things taken in the better sence, and fauourably construed. Therefore I haue beene most willing to submit my selfe and my labours in this parte vnto thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Iudgment, and right charitable constructions.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6</hi> As it hath pleased god in his loue &amp; mercie, both to grace <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and protect thee, so hath he also giuen thee a will &amp; abilitie to fauour and defend both his inestimable truth, &amp; the true professours thereof: that so, howsoeuer the worldlings rage and raue against the one and the other, VVisedome may bee
<pb facs="5"/>
yet iustified of her Children: the Truth and her louers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued and defended of them that loue and feare the Lord.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7</hi> Finally: I haue been most willing (most worthie <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philos</hi>) in this sort to signifie my heartie affection and good will towards thee: for whose happie increase and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seueraunce in the loue and grace of God, with all prosperitie I pray daylit vnto his Diuine Maiestie, and that by thine happie Ministerie he would vouchsafe yet to helpe, sustaine and edifie his Church, and promote and further that true, auncient, liuelie and Catholique faith and holy Religion within this realm and Church of <hi>England:</hi> the which hath these many yeares of our peace bin worthily defended in the same, by our right Christian and most Soueraigne Princesse Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whose most excellent Maiestie, the most mightie God long prosper and preserue to reigne ouer, vs, for the comfort of his Church, and his high Glorie. And thus I commend this <hi>Preparatiue</hi> vnto thee (most Noble <hi>Theopilos)</hi> and thy self vnto him who hath both loued, graced, and blessed thee in his Sonne Iesu Christ: to whome be praised and glory for euer more, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>