<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDWARD LORD RVSSELL, Earle of Bedford, and the Ladie LVCIE Countesse of Bedford, Grace and Peace be multiplied, with increase of all honor and happinesse for euer.</title>
           <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107140_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A89915</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4217</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107140</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDWARD LORD RVSSELL, Earle of Bedford, and the Ladie LVCIE Countesse of Bedford, Grace and Peace be multiplied, with increase of all honor and happinesse for euer.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition vpon the Epistle to the Colossians : Wherein, not onely the text is methodically analysed, and the sence of the words, by the help of writers, both ancient and moderne is explayned: but also, by doctrine and vse, the intent of the holy Ghost is in euery plac more fully vnfolded and vrged. And besides, the very marrow of most common-places is aptly diffused through-out the body of this exposition, as the nature of this kinde of teaching would beare. And further, many chiefe cases of conscience are here resolued. All with conuenient varietie and breuitie. Being, the substance of neare seuen yeeres weeke-dayes sermons, of N. Byfield, late one of the preachers for the citie of Chester</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 173, that is 179, 9, 90, 10, 116, 119-137, 9, 157-202 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDWARD LORD RVSSELL, Earle of Bedford, and the Ladie LVCIE Countesse of <hi>Bedford,</hi> Grace and Peace be multiplied, with increase of all honor and happinesse for euer.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most noble Lord, and my very honourable good Ladie,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Epistle to the Colossians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines an excellent Epitome of the doctrine expressed in the rest of the bookes of the old and new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament: as will appeare by a briefe <hi>delineation</hi> or adumbration of the proportion and parts of that sacred <hi>body of truth,</hi> paralelled with the seuerall parts of this Epistle, vsing the benefit of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie vpon it.</p>
   <p>The whole word of God may be diuided into two parts: the first concernes <hi>faith,</hi> or what we must beleeue;<note place="margin">The sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of all Theologie exprest briefly in this Epistle: as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</note> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Loue,</hi> or what we must doe. So the Apostles diuided it, as may appeare by the <hi>patterne</hi> vsed in their times, which stood of two parts, <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>loue,</hi> 2. Tim. 1.13. And so is this Epistle deuided; for in the two first Chapters he tells them what they must beleeue, and in the two last, what they must doe.</p>
   <p>Now faith lookes either vpon <hi>God,</hi> or vpon the <hi>world.</hi> In
<pb facs="26"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="26"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="27"/>
      <hi>God</hi> two things are to be beleeued: 1. the <hi>attributes</hi> of the essence. 2. the <hi>trinitie</hi> of the persons. The attributes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold the nature and proprieties of God; such as are, his <hi>power, glory, knowledge,</hi> and the like; of the power of God, yee may read, Chap. 1.11. &amp; 2.12. of the glory of God, Chap. 1.11. &amp; 3.17. of the knowledge of God Chap. 3.10.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Persons</hi> are three, the <hi>Father, Sonne,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghost;</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> chap: 1.2.12. &amp; 3.17. of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> chap. 1.2.13.15. &amp;c. of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> chap. 2.19. Thus of God.</p>
   <p>In the consideration of the <hi>world,</hi> faith is taken vp espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially about the <hi>creation</hi> of it, and the <hi>gouernment</hi> of it. In the <hi>creation</hi> it viewes the mightie workemanship of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all things of nothing, euen the very Angels, as well as men and other creatures. Of the creation, chap. 1.16. of Angells also chap. 1.16. both good, chap. 2.9. and euill, chap. 2.15.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The gouernment of the world,</hi> is two waies to be considered: First, in the generall disposing and preseruation of all things. Secondly, and principally, faith is taken vp about the consideration of the gouernment of <hi>Men</hi> in the world: of the <hi>generall prouidence,</hi> chap. 1.16.17.</p>
   <p>The prouidence of God ouer man, may be considered according to his fourefold estate: 1. of <hi>Innocencie.</hi> 2. of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi> 3. of <hi>Grace.</hi> 4. of <hi>Glorie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the estate of <hi>Innocencie,</hi> faith chiefly beholds and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at the glorious <hi>Image of God,</hi> in which man was created; of this Image you may read, chap. 3.10. by analogie.</p>
   <p>In the state of <hi>Corruption,</hi> two things do offer themselues to our dolefull contemplation: 1. <hi>sinne,</hi> 2. the <hi>punishment of sin. Sinne</hi> is both <hi>originall</hi> and <hi>actuall:</hi> of originall sinne, chap. 2.13. of actuall sinnes, chap. 2.11.13.3.5.6. of the punishment of sinne, chap. 3.25. &amp; 2.13. &amp; 3.6.</p>
   <p>In the state of <hi>Grace,</hi> faith viewes three things: 1. the <hi>meanes of grace.</hi> 2. the <hi>subiect.</hi> 3. the <hi>degrees.</hi> The meanes is either <hi>before time,</hi> or <hi>in time:</hi> before time, tis the <hi>election of God;</hi> of which, chap. 3.12. in time, the meanes chiefly is
<pb facs="27"/>
      <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>couenant</hi> in him. <hi>In Christ,</hi> two things are to be considered, his <hi>person,</hi> and his <hi>office.</hi> The <hi>theorie</hi> concerning Christs <hi>person,</hi> is twofold: 1. concerning his <hi>two natures.</hi> 2. concerning his <hi>twofold estate</hi> in those natures. The <hi>natures</hi> of Christ are two, <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>diuine,</hi> ioyned in the bond of <hi>personall vnion;</hi> of the humane nature, chap. 1.22. of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, chap. 1.15.16, &amp;c. of the <hi>vnion</hi> of both, chap. 2.9. The <hi>state</hi> of the person of Christ is twofold: 1. of <hi>humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 2. of <hi>exaltation.</hi> His <hi>humiliation</hi> comprehends, 1. his <hi>incarnation,</hi> as the antecedent. 2. his <hi>obedience</hi> to the law of Moses. 3. his <hi>passion:</hi> of his incarnation and obedience impliedly in diuers places; of his passion, chap. 1.14.20.22, 14, 15. His <hi>exaltation</hi> comprehends his <hi>resurrection, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cension,</hi> and <hi>session at the right hand of God:</hi> of his resurrection, chap: 2.12: of his sitting at Gods right hand, chap. 3.1.</p>
   <p>Thus of the <hi>person</hi> of Christ.</p>
   <p>The <hi>office</hi> of Christ is to mediate between God and man. The parts are 1. his <hi>propheticall office.</hi> 2. His <hi>priestly office.</hi> 3. his <hi>regall office.</hi> His <hi>propheticall office</hi> stands in propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of doctrine, and in making it effectuall by his spirit. His <hi>priestly office</hi> standeth in two things: 1. <hi>Expiation of sin.</hi> 2. <hi>Intercession for vs to God.</hi> His <hi>regall office</hi> is partly in the gouernment of the Church, as <hi>the head thereof:</hi> and partly in the subduing of the enemies of God and the Church; of the treasures of wisdom in Christ as a Prophet, chap. 2.3. of the sacrifice of Christ as a Priest, chap. 2.14. of the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Christ ouer the Church, chap. 1.18. &amp; 2.19.</p>
   <p>Thus of Christ.</p>
   <p>The <hi>couenant</hi> followeth, which is considered both in it selfe, and in the <hi>seales</hi> of it. Though the <hi>couenant of workes</hi> be accidentally a meanes to driue vs to Christ, yet the proper effectuall meanes is the <hi>couenant of grace,</hi> which God hath made with the elect in Christ: this being recorded in the word of the Gospell both in the old and new Testament, is the ordinarie meanes, by the power of Christ, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert soules to God, by the preaching of it in the ministery of his seruants; of this chap. 1.6.</p>
   <pb facs="28"/>
   <p>The <hi>seales</hi> of this <hi>couenant</hi> are the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> both of the old and new Testament: of the old testament, was <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision,</hi> and the rest; of which chap. 2.11. of the new testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are <hi>baptisme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> of baptisme, ch. 2.12</p>
   <p>Thus of the <hi>meanes</hi> of grace. The <hi>subiect</hi> of true grace is the <hi>Church,</hi> the body of Christ vnited to him by mysticall vnion. The Church consists of two sorts of men, <hi>Ministers</hi> and <hi>people;</hi> of the Church in generall with her vnion with Christ, chap. 1.18, 19, 20. &amp; 2.19. of Ministers and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with their duties, chap. 1.25.28. &amp; 2.1. and in diuers other places.</p>
   <p>Thus of the <hi>subiect</hi> also. The degrees of grace in the third estate, are 1. <hi>vocation.</hi> 2. <hi>faith.</hi> 3. <hi>remission of sinnes</hi> 4. <hi>sanctification.</hi> of vocation, chap. 3.15. of faith, chap 1.4.23. &amp; 2.12. of remission of sinnes, chap. 1.14. &amp; 2.13. of sanctification, in both parts, both mortification, chap. 3.5.8. and viuification, chap. 2.13. &amp; 3.10.</p>
   <p>Thus of the estate of grace.</p>
   <p>The fourth and last estate of man, is the <hi>estate of glorie;</hi> which stands of three degrees. 1. <hi>resurrection.</hi> 2. <hi>the last iudgement.</hi> and 3. <hi>life eternall.</hi> of resurrection, chap. 1.18. of the last iudgement and eternall glory, chap. 3.4. And thus of the first part of the <hi>patterne of wholesome words,</hi> and that is <hi>faith:</hi> now followeth the second, and that is <hi>loue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Loue</hi> comprehends all the duties we owe to God or men, as being <hi>the bond of perfection,</hi> which ties together all holy seruices. Loue must bee considered both in the <hi>adiuncts,</hi> and in the <hi>sorts</hi> of it.</p>
   <p>The <hi>adiuncts</hi> are <hi>constancie, wisedom, zeale, care to auoide offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and the like of loue in generall, chap. 1.4. &amp; 2.2. &amp; 3.14. of constancie, ch. 2.6. of zeale, chap. 4.13. of wisdome and care to auoide offences, chap. 4.5. thus of the adiuncts.</p>
   <p>The sorts of works comprehended vnder loue, are two chiefly: 1. <hi>works of worship.</hi> 2. <hi>workes of virtue.</hi> The works of worship are either <hi>internall</hi> onely, or <hi>externall</hi> and <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> also. The <hi>internall</hi> are, the <hi>acknowledging of God, the loue of God, the feare of God, the trust or hope in God,</hi> and which
<pb facs="28"/> floweth from thence, <hi>patience.</hi> of the acknowledgement of God, chap. 1.9, 10. of the loue of God, chap. 1.8. of the feare of God, chap. 3.22. of the hope in God, chap. 1.5. of patience, chap. 1.11. The workes of worship that are both <hi>externall</hi> and <hi>internall,</hi> are <hi>praier</hi> and <hi>thankesgiuing.</hi> of prayer, chap. 4.2, 3. of thankesgiuing, chap. 3.17.</p>
   <p>Thus of workes of worship. <hi>Workes of virtue</hi> either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our selues or others: the workes that concerne our selues, are chiefly two: the <hi>studie of heauenly things,</hi> and <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance.</hi> Temperance containes <hi>chastitie</hi> and <hi>sobriety</hi> in the vse of all sorts of earthly things. of the studie of heauenly things, chap. 3.1, 2. of chastitie, ch. 3.5. of sobriety, ch. 3.2.</p>
   <p>Thus of vertue that concernes our selues.</p>
   <p>Works of virtue towards others, are chiefly nine. <hi>Mercy, curtesie, humilitie, meekenesse, long-suffering, clemencic, peaceablenes, thankfulnes and iustice:</hi> of the first eight of these, chap. 3.12. to 16. Now <hi>Iustice</hi> is either publike or priuate: <hi>publike Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> is in Magistrates, of which, chap. 2.5. <hi>priuate Iustice,</hi> is either <hi>commutatiue,</hi> in bargaining, or <hi>distributiue,</hi> in giuing that which is right to euery one according to his degree, and so distributiue Iustice is either ciuill or oeconomicall. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Iustice in ciuill conuersation with men abroad, is either to Magistrates, of which, chap. 1.5. or to all men, and so consists of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>faithfulnes</hi> with <hi>sincerity</hi> and <hi>obseruance.</hi> oeconomical Iustice is that which concernes the houshold; and so containes the duties of husbands and wiues, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and parents, seruants and masters; of which chap. 3.18. to the end, with the first verse of chap. 4.</p>
   <p>Thus also of <hi>Loue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus I haue shewed the excellent compleatnes of this worthy scripture: it remaines that I declare some of the reasons that haue emboldned me to make choice of your <hi>Honors</hi> names for the dedication of my exposition vpon this scripture. Three things swaying Godly men in like case, haue compelled mee, <hi>protection, obseruance,</hi> and <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes.</hi> the preaching of this doctrine, as by the mercy of
<pb facs="29"/> God it wrought abundant consolation and comfortable reformation in many hearers, so did it seldom rest from the assaults and calumnies, which one while <hi>prophanenesse,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while <hi>enuie</hi> powred out vpon it. Great cause there is therfore that it comming out now to a more publike view, should seeke shelter: and of whom should I seeke it or hope for it sooner then of your Honors, who are pleased by your daily countenance to assure me a iust patronage? For the second, to omit the high reputation which the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious eminencie of both your ancestors hath set your <hi>Honors</hi> in, and the praises of many singular endowments and gifts, in which you doe worthily excell: there are two things wherein your <hi>Honors</hi> daily winne a great increase of obseruance; the one is <hi>pietie</hi> towards God, the other <hi>mercie</hi> towards the poore. The loynes of the poore daily blesse your <hi>Honors,</hi> and their mouthes daily pray for you. Your piety is many waies exprest: to omit many vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed proofes of it, your <hi>Lordship</hi> hath much confirmed the perswasion of your religious disposition by your daily and affectionate respect of the word of God and praier in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, since the Lord hath made you lesse able to resort more frequently to the publike assemblies. And <hi>Madam,</hi> what thanks can wee euer sufficiently giue vnto God for that rare and worthy example, with which your <hi>Ladishippe</hi> doth comfort and incourage the hearts of many, in your care of Gods sabaoths, &amp; in your neuer-failing attendance vpon the ordinances of God, with the congregation, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, not only in your owne person, but with your whole familie. For the third, I doe ingenuously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse before God and men, that I hold my obligation vnto your <hi>Honors</hi> in the iust debt of seruice and gratitude to be so great, as the labour here imployed is no way answerable to a meete discharge, no though it had bin taken only for your <hi>Honors</hi> vse; for to omit the debt which I am in for a great part of my maintenance, and that singular incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I reape daily in your Honors respect of my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie; what thankes can euer be sufficient, or what seruice
<pb facs="29"/> can euer be enough for that incomparable benefit (which I haue and shall euer esteeme the greatest ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> bless<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>g did euer befall mee; and which <hi>(Madam)</hi> by your <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> singular care and furtherance, after an admiral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>r I obteined) I meane the cleaning of my reputation from the vniust aspersions of my aduersaries, and that by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> mouth and pen of the <hi>Lords annointed,</hi> my most dread <hi>Seueraigne,</hi> whom the <hi>God of heauen</hi> with all abundance of royall and diuine blessings recompence in all earthly felicitie and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory. And the same <hi>God of Peace</hi> and <hi>Father of mercies,</hi> sanctifie your <hi>Honors</hi> wholy, that your whole spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and soules and bodies may be preserued blamelesse vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ: faithfull is hee that hath called you, who also will doe it. And I doubt not but God that hath inriched your <hi>Honors</hi> with the <hi>true grace</hi> that is in Iesus Christ, will daily winne vnto you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of honor from your perseuerance in well-doing: so as thanksgiuing for your sakes shall bee abundantly giuen vnto God by many. Thus in most humble manner crauing your <hi>Honors</hi> acceptance and patronage of this worke, I end, and shall reioyce to remaine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors Chaplaine to be commanded in all seruice, <hi>NI. BYFIELD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>