<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Illustrious and right Excellent,
my most honoured Lord and Patron,
The Lord Duke of
RICHMOND and LENOX,
Earle of
DARNLEY, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Biondi, Francesco</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107086_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3075</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Illustrious and right Excellent,
my most honoured Lord and Patron,
The Lord Duke of
RICHMOND and LENOX,
Earle of
DARNLEY, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Biondi, Francesco</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eromena, or, Love and revenge. Written originally in the Thoscan tongue, by Cavalier Gio. Francesco Biondi, Gentleman extraordinary of his Majesties Privie Chamber. Divided into six books. And now faithfully Englished, by Ia. Hayvvard, of Graies-Inne Gent</title>
                 <author>Biondi, Giovanni Francesco, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 195, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the most Illustrious and right Excellent,
my most honoured Lord and Patron,
The Lord Duke of
RICHMOND and LENOX,
Earle of
DARNLEY, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Illustrious and right Excellent Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have brought forth to breathe the common
aire this <hi>Eromena,</hi> at the commandment of a
Lady, who (pretending to have over mee
the soveraignety of an absolute Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse)
straightly requires at my hands, a devoutly-obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,
strict, and sudden performance of her imperious
and not to be questioned commands. If she prove imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
she is the more excusable for being no naturall birth,
but an abortive of a few moneths time, accidentally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
without any hope ever to have breath'd. And now
I am constrained to dedicate her (thus unpolish't) unto
your <hi>Excellencie,</hi> before whom shee ought (indeed) to
have appeared as richly endowed with ornaments, as you
are with vertues. Vouchsafe (I beseech you) to accept, in
excuse of my boldnesse, the necessity of my obedience,
by receiving this <hi>Princesse</hi> into your courteous protection,
that you may behold in her the conformity she hath with
your <hi>Excellencie</hi> in nobility and valour, but (above all)
in an eternall constancie, whereby as shee grew to bee
peerlesse among all the Ladies of her time, so makes it
also your <hi>Excellencie</hi> become singular among all the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers
of this our age. The Lord God grant your <hi>Excellencie</hi>
all increase of felicitie, whilst I, with reverend affection,
humbly kisse your hand.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Excellencies most humble
and most devoted Servant,
Gio. Francesco Biondi.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>