<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The argument vpon the Actes of the Apostles.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107377_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17642</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4398</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107377</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The argument vpon the Actes of the Apostles.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The commentaries of M. Iohn Caluin vpon the Actes of the Apostles : faithfully translated out of Latine into English for the great profite of our countrie-men, by Christopher Fetherstone student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 298, that is 598, 34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The argument vpon the Actes of the Apostles.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the intent that all godly men may with more diligence reade this historie, and also be more desirous thereof: it shall not be without profite, briefly to note what commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie they shall reape thereby. This is the chiefest praise that a prophane historie hath, namely, that it is the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stres of life. If that narration of famous deeds which onely teacheth men what they ought to followe, or what they ought to eschewe in their common actions, deserue such a title: of how great praise are the diuine histories worthie, which do not onely frame the outward life of man that he may winne praise by vertue; but also (which it more) which declare vnto vs, that God from the beginning hath had a speciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard alwayes of his Church, and faithfull congregation: that he hath bene alwaies a most iust reuenger of all wrongs done vnto those, that haue betaken themselues vnto his tuition, and haue committed themselues vnto his custodie: that he hath shewed himselfe fauourable and mercifull vnto most miserable and wretched sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: and lastly by teaching vs faith, hoised vs high aboue the heauens? I say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this, that they do euerie where set forth the prouidence of God, that they distingush the true worship of God from the false, they neuer erre in the difference of vice and vertue. Although I omit nowe also those worthie praises which vse most commonly to bee attributed vnto the sacred histories, intending onely short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to touch those, which are proper to this booke, which wee haue taken in hande. Those things which Luke setteth before vs in this place to be learned, are not only great, but also of rare profite: For first in that he sheweth that the spirite of God was sent vnto the Apostles, he doth not only proue that Christ was faithful &amp; true in keeping his promise, made vnto his Apostles: but also he certifieth vs, that he is alwayes mindfull of his, and a perpetuall gouernour of his Church: because the holy spirite did discende from heauen to this ende, whereby we learne that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of place doeth no whit hinder Christ from being present with those that be his, at all times. Nowe heere is most liuely painted out, the beginning of Christs kingdome, and as it were the renuing of the worlde. For although the sonne of God had gathered togither by his preaching, a certaine Church, before such time as he departed out of the world yet neuerthelesse, that was the best forme of the Church which began then, when as the Apostles hauing new power giuen them from aboue, began to preach, that that onely sheapherd did both die and also rise againe, that through his conduct all those which were dispersed farre and wide, vpon the face of the whole earth, might bee gathered vnto one sheepefolde. Heere is therefore set downe both the beginning, and also the increasing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Church of Christ, after his ascension, whereby he was declared to be king both of heauen and earth. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore therein appeareth as well the merueilous power of Christ, as the great force and efficacie of the Gospel it selfe: for in that Christ by a sort of simple soules and of no reputation amongst men, being endued also with no eloquence at al, hath subdued the whole world so easily by the only voice of the Gospel, whereas notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb facs="8"/> Satan did resist him with so manie lets: he hath shewed a most manifest token of his diuine power and might therein. And also we see in the same, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible force of the Gospel, that it did not only come forth &amp; shew it self, although the whole world did say nay, but also with great glorie and maiestie, make all that which did seeme stubborn, to be obedient vnto Christ. Therfore these few &amp; simple creatures, did more preuaile against the troublesome tumults of the world, with the base &amp; simple sound of their mouth, than if God should openly haue thrown down lightnings from heauen. And on the other side, the spirit of God teacheth vs, that the kingdome of Christ beginneth neuer sooner to florish, but by and by Sathan op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth himselfe most furiously against the same, and vseth all his engines either vtterly to ouerthrow, or sore to shake the same. Neither are we onely taught, that Sathan doth resist Christ as an enimie, but also that the whole world doth furious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rage togither against him, that he may not reigne ouer them. Yea, furthermore that is to be set downe as a thing most certaine, that wicked men whiles they doe so rage against the Gospell, doe both fight vnder Sathans banner, and are pricked forward by him into so blind furie. Hereupon doe arise so many vprores, so manie plaguie conspiracies, so many diuellish indeuours of the reprobate, to ouerthrow the Gospel, and to hinder the free passage of the same, which Luke setteth downe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in euery place. Lastly, like as the Apostles haue indeede tried, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Gospel is a fire and a sword, so may we learne by their experience that it will alwaies come to passe, not onely by the obstinate malice of Satan, but also by the fatall stubbornnes of men, that the Gospel shal suffer many conflicts, and that thereby many tumultes shalbe raised. But on the other side he declareth that the Apostles with a stout stomacke, with a liuely courage, and inuincible valiantnesse of minde, did notwithstanding execute the office which they knewe was inioyned them by God: &amp; also what innumerable troubles they suffered with great perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, what werisomnes they passed ouer, how patiently they susteined most cruel persecution; and lastly how meekely they suffered reproch, sorow, and calamitie of all sortes. And we must learne patience by such examples, seeing the sonne of God hath pronounced that the crosse and tribulation shall alwaies accompanie his Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: we must not pamper and cherish our selues with a vaine hope, as though the state and condition of the Church should be quiet, prosperous, and florishing heere vpon earth. Let vs therefore addresse our selues to suffer the like things. And that is added as no small comfort for vs, that as God hath merueilously deliuered his Church in times past, being afflicted, and oppressed so many waies: so he will at this day be present with vs also: For surely seeing that in this booke is declared howe that God by his mightie hand &amp; outstretched arme alone, doth continually defend his Church, being amidst continuall deathes: God himselfe by this meanes setteth before our eies his continuall prouidence in procuring the safetie thereof. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more here are set downe certaine sermons of the Apostles, which intreate in such sort of the great mercies of God, of the grace of Christ, of the hope of blessed immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, of the calling vpon God, of repentance and the feare of God, and also of other principall pointes of Christian doctrine, that we neede not seeke the whole sum of godlinesse any where else. But that I may nowe omit the declaration of sound and pure doctrine: If that be a thing most needfull to be knowne, namely: to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand how the Church of Christ first began: how the Apostles began to preach the Gospel; what successe they had in the same, what cruel combats they suffered, how
<pb facs="9"/> manfully they passed through so many lets, and impediments, how couragiously they triumphed ouer all the pride of the world, vnder the reproch of the crosse, how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully God was present with them: then must wee highly esteeme of this Booke, which vnles it were extant, the knowledge of so great things should either be quite buried, or greatly obscured, or wrapped in diuers doubtes. For we see that Sathan vsed all his engins that he might, to bring to passe, that neuer any of the acts of the Apostles might come to light, but such onely as were mixed with lies; to the end he might bring into suspition what thing soeuer was spoken of them, and so by that meanes might plucke out of the mindes of the godly, all the remembrance of that age. For hee alwaies raised vp, either doting fooles, or craftie flowters, that they might spread abroade a sort of filthie fables, vnder the names of other men; the blockishnes whereof did much discredite euen the true histories. So in those bookes of Peter and Paul which are faigned to be of Linus his doing, are conteined such a sort of stinking trifles, that they cause the wicked to laugh at them, and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to loath them. So that feigned disputation of Peter with Symon Magus, is so ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, that it doeth discredite the name of a Christian. The same opinion must we haue of all that mingle mangle which is set before the recognitions and councels of Clement, and recited of Gratianus in his fragments, they beguile the vnskilful vnder colour of ancient names, the wicked boast of those as of oracles, no lesse boldly than impudently, when as in deede they are filthie toies. Sathan did vse such liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to lie, that we might haue no certaine thing left vs, after Christs ascension. So that vnlesse this work of Luke were extant, it might seeme that Christ being taken vp into heauen, left no fruit of his death or resurrection vpon earth. For all should haue vanished away with his bodie. We should not know that Christ was so recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into his celestiall glorie, that neuertheles hee beareth rule in all the world: we should not know that the Gospel was published by the Apostles, and so came from them vnto vs, though by the meanes of others: we should not know that they were inspired by the holy Ghost, least they should teach any thing but that which was diuine, to the end our faith might be grounded onely vpon the vnfallible veritie of God. Last of all we shoulde not knowe that that Prophesie of Esaias was fulfilled, wherein he foretold that the law should come out of Sion, and the word of the Lord out of Ierusalem. Seeing this booke proceeding no doubt from the spirite of God, taketh from vs all doubting of these thinges, wee must count the same as a great treasure, as I haue said before not without cause, and nowe againe confirme the same.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>