<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT vvorshipfull sir Antony Denny knight his daily oratour Thomas Langley vvisheth prospe∣ritee and long continu∣ance of vvor∣shippe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107600_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14341</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24656</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107600</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT vvorshipfull sir Antony Denny knight his daily oratour Thomas Langley vvisheth prospe∣ritee and long continu∣ance of vvor∣shippe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An abridgement of the notable woorke of Polidore Vergile conteignyng the deuisers and firste finders out as well of artes, ministeries, feactes &amp; ciuill ordinaunces, as of rites, and ceremonies, commo [n] ly vsed in the churche: and the originall beginnyng of the same. Co [m] pendiously gathered by Thomas Langley</title>
                 <author>Vergil, Polydore</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 156, 12 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT vvorshipfull sir Antony Denny knight his daily oratour Thomas Langley vvisheth prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritee and long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ACTANTIVS</hi> writeth that certain philosophers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures feet did sore bewayle the estate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, as weke and far vnder the degre of beastes, bicause thei wer by nature fensed as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rō all displeasures &amp; grefes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable ayre, as armed aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inste the assautes and inuasions of their enemies, and onely man destitute &amp; voide of all suche and
<pb facs="3"/>
other like succours &amp; purueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunces: For bothe beastes &amp; bir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue euery one accordyng to their kynde skynnes, hides, or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to sustein the sharpenes of the cold, and to bere of the stormi raynes and tēpestes, &amp; also wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pōs as hornes, tuskes, and other like munimentes too resist their foes, or at the least thei haue agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litee and swiftnes, to escape and preserue them selfes frō daunger Cōtrarywise mankynd is of his nature so delicate and tēder that he can abyde no heate, no colde, no raynes, nor tempestuous we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: so feble also he is that his membres be not able to helpe his owne wekenesse, muche lesse too vnderstād or auoide the power of his enemies. But if these grosse and carnal Philosophiers hadde
<pb facs="3"/>
withdrawē their heartes frō ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng the behauour of the body, and applied their mynde to the contemplacion of the worthines of the solle, they should haue wel perceiued their owne erroure, the base and vile cōdicion of beastes the high dignite of the solle, &amp; the excellent noblenes of man. For albeit this frayle and yearthly body of oures is not so strong as the brutishe carkeses of beastes be, yet by reason of their grosnes they be vnfit to receiue the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual solle of man, or to be mete instrumentes of the same, where as the imperfection of mannes bodye is abled by the inuentiue and politike reason of the solle whiche deuiseth all necessaries, for the vse of the sayd body by all endeuoure and industrye. And
<pb facs="4"/>
that manne, whiche can shifte for himself, decline frō thynges hurt full, forsee also thynges to come, is iudged &amp; reputed worthye the title and name of a manne, so he likewise farre excelleth al kinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of liuyng creatures, whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe thei bee better armed with the giftes of nature▪ yet for defaute of reason to gouerne the same, thei be far inferiours to the noblenes of manne, whiche kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth through the dotes &amp; quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the solle too deuise all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries fit for his affaires and businesse.</p>
   <p>Wherefore me thynke them worthy of high commendacion, that haue bent them selues wholy to adorne and garnishe this life mortal, with their inuencions, &amp; to accomplishe the feble indigēce
<pb facs="4"/>
of our condicion, by the diligence of their prouision: as thei y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue excogitated &amp; imagined any arte wherby the commen welth of the worlde is preserued, or any other handy craftes or ministeries too the maintenaunce ayde and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of the body. Howbeeit thei be worthy to haue greatest laude and praise, that by their deuises haue found out the sciences libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, wherewith the diuine and imperiall parte called the solle of manne is bewtified: yet maie we not therefore forgette writers of meaner thynges, but be of deutie bound to make some worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of their benefites decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng our kindnes toward thē: to the intente other might bee inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to enterprise the acheuyng of like endeuoures to the great
<pb facs="5"/>
ayd and preferment of the whole common wealth, considryng that their suche deuises shalbee rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered to their perpetuall fame &amp; renoune. And seeyng that the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and craftes, with other like feates, whose inuentours be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this booke, are in this realme of Englande occupied &amp; put in daily exercise to the profet of many and ease of all menne, it were in myne opinion bothe a poynt of detestable vnkyndnes, and a parte of extreme inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite too defraude theim of their praise and perpetuall memorie, that wer autours of so great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites to the vniuersall worlde. For as a beneficiall gift confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a man that hath nede ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is of the owne propre nature commēdable, so if the receiuer of
<pb facs="5"/>
that so liberall benignitee, shewe hymself in mynde inwardly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuious and forgetfull, or in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des outwardly vnthankefull, it is naturally hated, and as an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naturall vice abhorred.</p>
   <p>In consideracion whereof I was moued to take in hande too compile out so well as my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng would serue me, in a brefe some suche thynges, as <hi>Polidore Vergile</hi> hath copiousli gathred to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gither by muche readyng, by lōg study, &amp; hath written with greate lernyng, consernyng the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of thynges, to thentent the autours of suche necessary artes might not be forgottē, &amp; <hi>Polidore</hi> for his great payne and trauaile in collectyng and celebratyng the said artes and sciences might receyue thankes accordyng to
<pb facs="6"/>
his desertes. And althoughe the booke translated might haue been for the diuersitee of matter profitable: and for the authours high lernyng laudable, &amp; finally to a good translatoure commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, yet in so muche, as for the greatnes, it should haue been to the berers greuouse, &amp; for length to the reders tediouse, I thought it best to omit some parte, not by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause any thyng was superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or otherwise written thē wel But for as muche as many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges mighte bee taken diuersly, and other wise then thei wer mēt. Therefore I haue not admitted any thyng in too this abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, whereby the reader maie bee iustely offended, nor haue on the other syde omitted any suche sentence, that either cōcerned the
<pb facs="6"/>
title, or that mighte in any parte please or profit the readers. And as <hi>Polidore</hi> in his booke written in latin dooth pretende to reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe &amp; enriche latin menne with delectaciō and knowlage of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges delectable &amp; worthie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, not myndyng to derogate either any laudable ceremonies, or to define vpō any matter, now or then beeyng in controuersie: euen so I muche desirouse, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the litle talent that God hath giuen me, to dooe all menne good, haue translated the saied booke of <hi>Polidore</hi> into oure En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe toungue, to the ende, that also artificers and other persons not expert in latin, might gather knowlage and take pleasure by the readyng therof.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>ALTHOVGH</hi> this booke be
<pb facs="7"/>
but simple &amp; vnfitte to be presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your good mastership, ye it semed of verye right due to bee offered to you bicause you haue bene alwaies, as the moost parte of men reporte, and many by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience can testifie, not onely en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flamed with desire of knowledge of antiquites, but also a fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble supporter of al good lernyng and a verie <hi>Mecenas</hi> of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde wittes. Wherfore I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this boke to your Maister<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship for the conformitie of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument beyng to your foresaied desire correspōdent: In somuche as it conteigneth the original of all ciuill artes and handecraftes and also the inuentoures of all suche ceremonies as bee vsed in the churche. And here playnely maie bee perceiued what the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb facs="7"/>
of GOD commaundeth, what thynges mennes pollycye haue diuised for the setting furth of good order, and what hath crepte in to the congregacion to the peruertyng of our faithe and seducyng simple people with su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persticion: as these manyfolde swarmes of popish religiōs, that here emōg vs were not long ago vsed, with other papisticall bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage. And I tooke it to bee my bonde dewtie to bestowe the first frutes of my labours (albeit thei bee verie slender and rude) after suche sorte, that thei might be, not onely a continuall monument of the speciall loue and mynde that you haue too further the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of the trueth and abholishe ignoraunce, hipocrisie, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like peinted holines: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb facs="8"/>
too bee a testimonie of my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and louyng herte toward all fauorers of good learnyng and most specialli toward your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stershipe, whose worthie fame mē of pure liuyng and high know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage doo so extoll, bothe for your alacritee and redinesse in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the blessed woorde of God and the sincere setters furthe of thesame, that you nede nothyng the testimonie of my commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Notwithstandyng when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitee shalbee giuen me, I shall not apere slacke in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, desiryng you in the meane tyme to take this litle booke into your tuicion, so dooyng you shal bolden and encorage me hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to employe more earnest la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure in doyng some thyng that maie redownd to your perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="8"/>
memorie and renoune: Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in the meane tyme for the long continuaunce of your Maistershipe in health felicitee &amp; encrease of knowledge in our lorde to whom be onely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>