<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Trussell, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107345_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13983</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24297</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107345</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Trussell, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A continuation of The collection of the history of England : beginning where Samuel Daniell Esquire ended, with the raigne of Edvvard the third, and ending where the honourable Vicount Saint Albones began, with the life of Henry the seventh, being a compleat history of the beginning and end of the dissention betwixt the two houses of Yorke and Lancaster. With the matches and issue of all the kings, princes, dukes, marquesses, earles, and vicounts of this nation, deceased, during those times. By I.T</title>
                 <author>Trussell, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Ephraim.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Pakeman, Daniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 242, 245-260, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y naturall propension to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of History, was the occasion that I left no Chronicle of this land, that purse, or prayer could pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase or procure, unperused: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I found that verified, that Prince <hi>Henry</hi> (now with God) complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of, which was, that of all Nations the English were most blame-worthy; That being inferiour to none for praise-worthy atchievements, yet were surpassed by all, and leaving the memory of those their praise worthy actions to posteritie. This I tooke to heart, but every way unable to remedy it, I rested silent, untill of late it came into my mind; That that part of the History of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> which was most intricate and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, which was the beginning of that Story was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily begun, and as ingeniously followed (by that every way well) deserving Gentleman <hi>Samuel Daniel:</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all those rubbes and blancks, which the deluge of time, had raised and left on the plat-forme, were made smooth or taken away, and that Vicount Saint <hi>Albones</hi> had so sufficiently perfected, that of all other the most doubtfull (if not dangerous peece) of Pater times to bee undertaken, the happy Conjunction of the so long seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Houses of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and that many others, reverend and judicious men, had by way of Annuals pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued the History unto the blessed Vniting of the two
<pb facs="4"/>
neighbour, but long before divided Kingdomes, of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> so that now there wanted nothing to make the History compleat, for so much as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite untill that time, but only the passages from <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the second, to the period of <hi>Richard</hi> the third, a great part whereof was-likewise accurately done, by Sir <hi>Iohn Heywood</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> so that now with little la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that gap might easily be filled up, and the History made; Whereupon I have adventured to adde my peece of ordinary valure, to those rich remnants of three pild Velvet, by enterviewing the times of <hi>Richard</hi> the second, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, <hi>Henry</hi> the sixt; <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, <hi>Edward</hi> the fift, and the Vsurper <hi>Richard</hi> the third, <hi>Wherein though I prove but a botcher, yet as the old saying is, better a course clout then a hole out.</hi> And to cleere my selfe though not <hi>à toto,</hi> yet <hi>à tanto,</hi> from that aspersion that happily might bee cast upon my endevours, that howsoever not ignorant of my owne manifold imperfections, yet like blind bayard, I should over-boldly venture, to tread in that Maze, which ought not to have beene underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but by a more able body, and a more active braine, and thereby have forgetfully brought my selfe within the number of those over-forward Writers, which Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Heywood</hi> in his Epistle Dedicatorie to his first three Norman Kings affirmeth, hath sullied the beautie of the English History.</p>
   <p>Give mee leave gentle Reader, (I beseech thee) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have yeelded the reason, that incited mee to the undertaking of this worke, so to give thee an account of my proceeding therein.</p>
   <p>First, I have forborne to assume unto my selfe the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of an Historian, to obtrude upon thee any thing of my owne invention, <hi>quia malui aliena imprudenter dicere quàm propria impudenter ingerere:</hi> And for that History is or ought to bee <hi>a perfect register of things formerly done truely:</hi> ot at least warrantable by probabilitie, I have <hi>pro posse meo</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
examined, though not all, (yet without touch of <hi>Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance,</hi> I may speake it) the most and best, that have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of those times, and culling out the truth as neere as I could gather it, like an Eccho, <hi>Voces quas accepi fidelissimè reddidi.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, I have pared off these superfluous exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, which like Wennes upon a beautifull face, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the otherwise gracefull comlinesse of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, I meane,</p>
   <p n="1">1. Matters of Ceremony, as Coronations, Christe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Marriages, Funeralls, solemne Feasts, and such like.</p>
   <p n="2">2. Matters of Triumph, as Tiltings, Maskings, Barri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Pageants, Gallefoists, and the like.</p>
   <p n="3">3. Matters of Noveltie, as great inundations, sudden rising and falling of prizes of Corne, strange Monsters, Iustice done on petty offenders, and such like executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with which the <hi>Cacoethes</hi> of the Writers of those times have mingled matters of state.</p>
   <p>And lastly, I have inserted the matches and issue, of all above the degree of a Baron, that have ended their dayes during those times, with the number of slaine, during the division of the two Roses, which how farre it may conduce to the better understanding of the History, I leave to thy capacitie, and my selfe to thy courtesie, and expecting a favourable censure rest thine;</p>
   <signed>IOHN TRVSSELL.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>