<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107947_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04700</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14828.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107947</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The refutation of the byshop of Winchesters derke declaratio [n] of his false articles, once before confuted by George Ioye : Be not deceiued by this bysshops false bokes. Heare novve the tother parte, and iudge truely of the trueth. For the veritie vvyll haue the victorye</title>
                 <author>Joye, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Herford (Hereford, Hertford), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, c xcii leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou shalt vnderstād (good reader) that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the yere. M. D. xivi at easter or pash time I receiued this bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops boke called his Declaration writen agenst me, what tyme, for such trouble and vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as I sustained in flying &amp; fliting from place to place, it was witsontide folowīg ere I could peruse his boke &amp; gather out these principals and (as thou seest) refute them. And yet then because there went forth a straighte commandement fro the emperour (by whose procurement I know not) but wel I weet, the byshop was in those partis ambassiador not longe before that no englysh bokes be no more prī<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted at Anwerpe ne in any other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his nether partes of Germany, I coulde not get this my answer thē printed without troublous tyme for
<pb facs="3"/>
that the popes frendes so fiercelye hunted for vs &amp; our bokes and resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted oure laboures with so greuous nihibicions cōdempnacions, banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and burninges. If this boke therfore seme to sharpe tothed, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in howe sharpe a tyme it was wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten and by whose counsel and labour then most tirannously and vngodlye so many good bokes, holy bybles▪ &amp; testamentes, yea &amp; the innocent chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten holy members of christ were bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned. Beholde howe mercilessely and most cruelly and vniustelye with all spede, good men were then vexed, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, presoned, and condempned for heretiques. No maruell then if anye christen hert moued with pietie and zele to Christ to his holy worde and his poore chirche beholdinge this cruell persecuciō could ether cōtaine teares, refraine speach or penne. And I namely whom this byshoppe that yeare at Anwerpe diligentelie hunted for, and in this his declaration nowe
<pb facs="3"/>
claundereth with heresye. vntruely reporteth my wordes, and gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wordes he violently wresteth vnto his false doctryne. In this tyme ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore very sorowfull also I was to see so many simple vnlearned, hauinge no iugement to decerne his false doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ro the true, hitherto so perel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousely deceiued and seduced into so many dāpnable errours by his false bokes and falser preachinge. For so longe as no aunswer was made, ne his false doctrine confuted, his fyrste tale so craftelye handled and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, myght appere to manye to seme trwe, and the popes false doctrine to be the gospel, especially to such as be more redy to beleue lyes then the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and to them whiche yet more fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour the romish religion then christs and so highly yet depend of &amp; esteme this byshoppes lerning, that thei be addict &amp; sworne into it, as into anye oracle oute of gods mouth. Ryghte heuey I was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rfore that this my
<pb facs="4"/>
answere cold not be printed so sone as it was writen, that the diligent indifferent readers seinge and heringe bothe the parties might haue iuged which of vs standeth vpon the trwe parte, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che iugement he geuethe, the that by his spirit geueth the discrecion to decerne al mens spiritis and doctryne thorow Iesus Christe. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>