<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1537</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107067_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18849</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107067</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The original [and] sprynge of all sectes [and] orders : by whome, wh⁻a or were they beganne. Translated out of hye Dutch in Englysh</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nicholson (Nicolson, Nicolai, Nycolson), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gough (Gowghe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Southwark</pubPlace>
                    <date>1537</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 64 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as ther is in the worlde great disputacyon &amp; reasonynge of sectes, and so many also of the same sectes and religions both contrarye to Christes moost holy religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and also among themselues. To induce them therfore vnto thyne vnderstandynge (moost gentle reader) and to describe them vnto thy knowlege, we haue here gathered together the names, fashions and maner of lyuynges of all suche sectes and orders as are not onely vnder the B. of Rome but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so both amonge the Christen and amonge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iewes, how and whan they came vp, with the maner also of theyr garmentes and sun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drye clothynges.</p>
   <p>Which treatise yf thou reade diligently, thou shalte thynke it no maruayll, that ther is now suche contencyon and diuision in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde, in as much as ther was no tyme, no age, no generacyon sence the begynnynge, but alwaye ther hath ben some sectes, some diuersite of opinion, and some sundrye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of belefe in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. The Iewes lacked not theyr Pharisees, theyr Saduces, theyr Effeies. &amp;c. The communite also of Christē
<pb facs="2"/>
dome hath this lōge tyme not ben without innumerable sectes and dyuerse religions, stablyshed by the B. of Rome. Yee euery lande nacyon and contrye, hath in a maner a sundry fasshion of lyuynge, a sundry fashi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of doctrine, a sundry fasshiō of clothyng, &amp;c. and hath had (I saye) this longe season. And though some of them which be called seetes, are not farre frō Christ nor his fayth yet the moost parte (specyally of them that be brought in by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> B. of Rome) are no lesse contrary vnto Christ, then were y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes in tymes past, then were the phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and then were the heretikes that haue ben sens Christes incarnacyon. For in as much as they wyll not onely be called other wyse then Christen, but denye also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> power lyfe, fayth and merites of Christe, who can then be more contrary to hym: who are thē more worthy to be called brethren of sectes and diuision, then such are?</p>
   <p>As thou seyst therfore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> theyr doctrine is contrary to Christes, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they preach lyes and dreames, that they deceaue the hartes of innocentes thorow fayre and flatterynge wordes. Rom. xvi. that they come to the but in shepes clothynge Math. vii. that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye
<pb facs="3"/>
the power of godlynesse. ii. Timo. iii. that they deuoure wydowes houses vnder the pretence of longe prayers. Math. xxiii. So be thou ware of them, of theyr false doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trin, of theyr lyes &amp; dreames, of theyr fayre and flattryng wordes, of theyr fayned holy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse. For all is not golde that shyneth, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they all of Christes couent, that weare brode crownes, wide coules, and syde coates. And forget not that S. Paul sayeth. The deuell can chaunge hymselfe in to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of lyght.</p>
   <p>Shute not thou thē at a wronge marke but holde the vnto Christ, and to the vnite of his doctrine, of his fayth and of his reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion, that thou mayest here be fre from all false hypocrisy, and not only knyt vnto him herein this world, but inheritour also of his ioye in heauen.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>