<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE CHRISTIAN REA∣der touching the Scope, Argument and ma∣nifold Vse of this ensuing Treatise.</title>
           <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107275_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19554</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5984</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107275</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE CHRISTIAN REA∣der touching the Scope, Argument and ma∣nifold Vse of this ensuing Treatise.</title>
                 <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the Fift General Councel held at Constantinople, anno 553. under Iustinian the Emperor, in the time of Pope Vigilius : The occasion being those tria capitula, which for many yeares troubled the whole Church. VVherein is proved that the Popes apostolicall constitution and definitive sentence, in matter of faith, was condemned as hereticall by the Synod. And the exceeding frauds of Cardinall Baronius and Binius are clearely discovered. By Rich: Crakanthorp Dr. in Divinity, and chapleine in ordinary to his late Majesty King Iames. Opus posthumum. Published and set forth by his brother Geo: Crakanthorp, according to a perfect copy found written under the authours owne hand</title>
                 <author>Crakanthorpe, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Minsheu, John, Children of</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 506, 10 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE CHRISTIAN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der touching the Scope, Argument and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Vse of this ensuing Treatise.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not ambition to live in other mens writings, but desire, if I could, to breath some life into them, which hath drawn me of late rather to preface other mens works, than to perfit mine owne. It grieved me much to see such evidences lie in the darke, which being produced to publike view, would give singular light to the truth: And if <hi>Socrates,</hi> the mirrour of modesty in a Philosopher, held it no disparagement to professe, that he performed the office of a <hi>Midwife</hi> to other mens <hi>wits,</hi> by helping them in the <hi>deliverie</hi> of those conceptions wherein himselfe had no part: why should I either feare or regard any detraction from the living, for a charitable office in this kinde to the dead? doubtlesse if the office of a <hi>Midwife</hi> be at any time needfull, it is then most necessarie, when the living Child is to be takē out of the dead wombe of the parent: Such was this <hi>Posthumus,</hi> in whom I hope the observation of<note n="a" place="margin">Plin. Nat. Hist. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicactùs enecta Parente nascun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, sicut Scipio Africanus pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>musque Caesarum à Caeso matris utero dictus: simili modo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus et Manlius qui Carthaginem cum exercitu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travit.</note>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> concerning children thus borne will bee verified: <hi>For the most part</hi> (saith hee) <hi>those Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren prove most lively and fortunate, of whom the Parents dye in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell;</hi> never seeing them live, who cost them their lives. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances are many &amp; very illustrious, <hi>Fabius</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Tert. lib. de resur. carnis. Possumus illos recogitare qui execto matris utero vivi aerem hauserunt, Labe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij aliquiet Scipiones et Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Caeso ter Consul.</note>
      <hi>Caeso</hi> thrice Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sul, <hi>Scipio</hi> surnamed the Africane, <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> the first &amp; most renowned of all the Romane Emperours, and our peerlesse K. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. Howbeit I confesse, it is an hard thing to <hi>calculate the nativity</hi> of a Book, and certainly foretell what hazzard the
<pb facs="6"/> impression of a Treatise of this subject may runne, or guesse what argument will please the <hi>divers tasts</hi> of this <hi>distempered</hi> age; yet this I am confident of, that all who exactly view this worke in all parts, and compare it with others, drawne with <hi>the same Pencill,</hi> will esteeme it like the<note n="c" place="margin">Cic. Orator.</note>
      <hi>Minerva</hi> of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias his Masterpeece:</hi> It cost him neare as many yeares labour as <hi>Isocrates Panegyrique,</hi> the Prime rose of his flowry Garden, did him. This Author perfected this worke in his life time, and commanded it, after a sort, to the Presse in the last<note n="d" place="margin">Def. Eccles. Angl. cap. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>19</hi> De quo loto Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio conscriptum scias à me li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum integrum, in quo innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiles Baronij fraudes, menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, etiam et hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reses palam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectae, &amp;c.</note> booke hee published by command from supreme authority in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Church of <hi>England</hi> against the calumnies of the revolted Archbishop of <hi>Spalata,</hi> (in these words:) <q>The Church had beene undone if Vigilius his decree had taken place; But the most holy Emperour Iustinian, and the fift Councell then happily shewed themselves Pillars of the Catholike faith; concerning which whole Councell I desire you to take notice of an intire booke written by mee, wherein the innumerable frauds, lies and heresies of <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> are manifestly detected; out of that booke, if it see light and come to your hands, you shall understand and plainly perceive how fraile and reedy your Romane Pillar is.</q>
   </p>
   <p>In which passage he insinuates, that the argument of it is, <hi>non de stillicidiis, aut aquis pluviis,</hi> not of <hi>Eves droppings</hi> or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter passages, but of the <hi>Roofe</hi> of the house and <hi>Arch</hi> it selfe, the authority of <hi>Councels,</hi> and the infallibilitie of the Papall <hi>Chaire.</hi> The <hi>Title</hi> carried through the whole booke, carrieth not the greatest part of it, <hi>plus</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Quintil. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. Orat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>in recessu est, quam à fronte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit;</hi> his warehouse within is fraught with more variety of rich stuffs thā is set out on his shop. An entire Treatise of the <hi>fift generall Councell,</hi> hee professedly undertaketh; but <hi>currente rota,</hi> in the prosecution of this argument, hee taketh tardy <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi> and <hi>Binius,</hi> and other Romish <hi>falsaries;</hi> hee runneth through all the later generall Councels; he substantially hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the maine Controversies concerning the power of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and authority ratifying Ecclesiasticall Synods, and so cleareth all Antiquity on the Reformed side in points of great moment, that I perswade my selfe, the wiser sort of our learned adversaries, who will by stealth get a sight thereof, will take good counsell, and utterly derelinquish their most glorious, but most vaine and false claime to <hi>generall Councels;</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> for if wee devide the Councels, that beare the still of <hi>Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> and <hi>Generall,</hi> according to the different times in which they were held into <hi>pure, mixt,</hi> and <hi>wholly corrupt;</hi> the first of undoubted, the second of doubtful, the third undoubtedly of no authority at all; the first are wholly ours, the last are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs in the middle sort we part stakes w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> them: 4. of the first ranke have beene heretofore wrested perforce out of the Romanists hands by Bishop <hi>Iewell,</hi> Bishop <hi>Bilson,</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Renols,</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Whitaker</hi> and others. The fift, this accomplisht Antiquary vindicates also from them, and declareth how in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of the second ranke we share with them; and in fine hee leaveth them nothing intirely, but the <hi>lees</hi> and <hi>dregs</hi> of all <hi>Councels,</hi> the <hi>Laterane</hi> and <hi>Trent. Habeant quod sunt,</hi> let them have these <hi>lees</hi> to themselves, who themselves, <hi>Moab</hi>-like, for these many ages are <hi>setled upon the lees</hi> of their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
   <p>Had this judicious and industrious Writer bent all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces against the Romanists false pretended <hi>right</hi> to generall <hi>Councels,</hi> and forcibly beat them out of that Hold onely, hee had deserved that Eulogiū which the<note n="f" place="margin">Panlus Fagius Epist. ad Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est magna religio apud Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos non subiice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nomen eius qui boni aliquid dixit, docuit aut scripsit.</note>
      <hi>Iewes</hi> give any <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> to whom they are indebted for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y wise saying or apt note upon any Scripture text,<note n="g" place="margin">Vid. comment. Rabb. passim.</note> ZICRONO LIBRACHA, <hi>sit memoria ejus in benedictione, blessed be is memorie:</hi> How much more when he assaulteth the maine <hi>fort</hi> of the <hi>Romish faith,</hi> and by impregnable authorities and infallible reasons over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the <hi>Popes</hi> supposed <hi>infallibility,</hi> when hee <hi>sits in his Chaire,</hi> and with his <hi>Romane Synod,</hi> determineth out of it que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, and defineth Articles of faith. This is indeed to <hi>let</hi> Rome <hi>bleed,</hi> in her <hi>Master-veine,</hi> to <hi>strike</hi> heresie at the <hi>roote,</hi> to <hi>crush</hi> the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> in the <hi>head,</hi> not to batter and breake downe the mudd-wals, but utterly to ruinate the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Tower of Babell.</hi> For howsoever Scriptures, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, and the Catholike Church, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, are pompously brought in into their Polemike writings against us; yet the last resolution of their faith is upon the Pope, who gives credit to Fathers, validity to Councels, and authority, at least <hi>quoad nos,</hi> to the Scriptures themselves. This their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <hi>Skulkenius</hi> his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond confidently undertakes to maintaine against all oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="7"/> of the Popes transcendent power, and uncontrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable <hi>verdict</hi> in a matters <hi>of eternall life and death.</hi> The<note n="h" place="margin">Bell. de Rom. Pontif. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>1</hi> in disputatione de verbo Dei. Iam ostendimus iudicem contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversiarum nō esse scripturam, nec seculares Principes, &amp;c. ac proinde ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum iudicium summi Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis esse.</note> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall thus flourisheth, <q>In our disputations about the word of God we have already shewed, that the Scripture is not the Iudge of Controversies, nor are secular Princes, nor private persons, though learned and honest, but Ecclesiasticall Prelates; in our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of the Councels it shall bee demonstrated, that Councels generall and particular may judge of Controversies in religion, but that judgement of theirs is then of force and validity when the Pope shall confirme it, and therfore that the last judgement of all is the Popes, <hi>to which all good Catholikes owe such absolute obedience,</hi> that<note n="i" place="margin">Bell. de Rom. Pontif. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>5</hi> in fine. Si Papa erraret praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo vitia, vel prohibendo vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, teneretur Ecclesia credere vitia esse bona, et virtutes malas, nisi vellet contra conscientium peccar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note> if the Pope should erre by commanding vices and prohibiting vertues, the Church is bound to beleeve, that vices are good, and vertues bad, unlesse she wil sinne against Conscience.</q> What, sinne against Conscience in not sinning, and not sinne against Conscience in committing sinnes knowne by the light of nature, if the <hi>Man of sin</hi> command the one and forbid the other? <hi>Woe bee to them,</hi> saith the Prophet, <hi>that call evill good, and good evill, put darknesse for light, and light for darknesse, bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter,</hi> Esay. 5.20. If <hi>Bellarmines</hi> divinity be currant, Pope <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> the fourth needed not to have coyned twelve new Articles<note n="k" place="margin">Bulla Pij <hi>4.</hi> super forma ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramenti professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis fidei, anno Dom. <hi>1564.</hi>
      </note> of faith, affixt to the Canons of the Councell of <hi>Trent:</hi> it had beene sufficient to have added this one, <hi>I beleeve in the Pope his soveraigne infallibility,</hi> for this is <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> and <hi>puppis,</hi> the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstratio</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of a Papists beliefe. <hi>The Popes power</hi> (saith <hi>Skul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenius</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Skulkē. Apolog. pro Bell. ca. <hi>6.</hi> Pontisicia pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stas est vel ut cardo fundamē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tū, et ut uno ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo dicam, suma fidei Christianae.</note>) <hi>is the hinge and foundation, and,</hi> to speake in a word, <hi>the summe of Christian faith:</hi> A short summe and soone cast up. What then serves <hi>Fathers, Councels, Church-Traditions,</hi> and <hi>Scripture it selfe</hi> for with them? for little better than Ciphers, which being added to the Popes authority in their Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike makes something, but without it nothing. To begin with Scriptures, they beleeve them to bee divine, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Scripture saith, <hi>that all Scripture</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note>
      <hi>is given by divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration: For so</hi> (saith<note n="n" place="margin">Bell. de verbo Dei non scripto lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>4.</hi> Etiamsi scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra dicat libros Prophetarum, et Apostolorum esse divinos, tamen non certo id cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, nisi prius credidero, scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam qua hoc dicit esse divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, nam etiam in Alchorano Mahometi pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sim legimus ipsum Alcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranum de Caelo à Deo missū, &amp;c</note>
      <hi>Bellarmine) wee read every where in the Alcoran of Mahomet, that the Alcoran was sent from God, yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it not;</hi> why then doe they beleeve them to bee the word of God? hee answers readily, <hi>propter traditionem Ecclesiae, for the Churches tradition.</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">Quicun{que}, non innititur do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae Romanae Ecclesiae, ac Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani Pontificis tanquā regulae fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei infallibili, à quâ etiam sacra Scriptura robur trahit et authoritatē; haereticus est: cōtra Lutherū.</note>
      <hi>Silvester Pierius</hi> outvies the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb facs="7"/> affirming, <hi>that the holy Scripture taketh force and authority from the Romane Church and Pope.</hi> Vpon which promise of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erius, Gretzer</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Gretz. defens. Bell. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de verbo Dei, id se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pro verbo Dei veneramur ac suscipimus, quod nobis Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices ex Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra Petri tradūt.</note> inferres this peremptory conclusion, <hi>We doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and reverence that alone for the word of God which the Pope in Peters Chaire doth determine to be so.</hi> Strange divinity to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that the Scriptures receive their authority from the Church, that is, that God receives this authority from man. May we not justly upbraid the present Romanists, as <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Tertul. Apol. adversus gentes Ca. <hi>5.</hi>
      </note> doth the ancient heathen, <hi>apud vos de humano arbitratu divinitas pensitatur, nisi homini Deus placuerit, Deus non erit; Homo jam Deo propitius esse debebit; With you Deity is estimated by mans valuation, unlesse God please man, he shall not be God; now man must bee propitious to God;</hi> for if the Pope be not propitious to the Scripture to allow it for Gods word, it shall not passe for such in Rome.</p>
   <p>As for the Fathers; they deale with their writings as <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus Manicheus</hi> did with the writings of the Apostles, <hi>in</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">August. lib. <hi>11.</hi> contra Faustum Manicheum, ca. <hi>2.</hi> inde probo inquiebat Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus, hoc illius esse, illud non esse, quia hoc pro me so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, illud contra me.</note>
      <hi>which hee takes it for a good proofe, that such passages are the Apostles true writings, because they made for him;</hi> others <hi>were spurious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they made against him: Fathers,</hi> saith<note n="s" place="margin">Dureus adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Whitakerum, fol. <hi>140.</hi> Ne{que} eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> patres censentur, cum suum aliquid quod ab ecclesia non acceperunt, velscribunt vel dicunt.</note>
      <hi>Dureus, are not to bee accounted Fathers, when they teach or write any thing of their owne, which they have not received from the Church,</hi> meaning the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane; and <hi>Gretzer</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">Gretz. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de iure &amp; more prohibendi libres noxios. ca. <hi>10.</hi> Nam Ecclesiae pater ille dicitur, qui Ecclesiam sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutari doctrinae pabulo alit et pascit, iam ergo si pro salutari doctrinae pabulo admetiaur Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium et Zizania non Pater est sed Vitricus.</note> backs this assertion with a reason drawn from the formall definition of a Father: <hi>for,</hi> saith he, <hi>he is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church, who feeds and nourisheth the Church with whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some doctrine, who being set over the Lords houshold, gives them their measure of Corne in due season; now if in stead of wholesome food and good Corne hee give them Cockle and Tares, he becomes no father but a stepfather, no Doctor but a seducer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To instance in some particular; <hi>Eusebius Caesariensis</hi> when hee seemes to favour Popery, hee is highly extolled by <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">Lindan. Pano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plia lib. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>17.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>Senensis</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">Senensis Bib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. titulo Eusebius.</note>, and <hi>Possevine</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">Possevinus in apparatu sacro.</note> hee is then <hi>a most famous wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Church, most learned, worthy to bee a Bishop, not of one Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty onely, but of the whole world;</hi> but when the same <hi>Eusebius</hi> lookes awry upon Rome, then hee is branded by <hi>Canus</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">Canus locorum Theol. lib. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>3</hi>
      </note>, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterus</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Coster. in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. contra Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinc. ca. <hi>8.</hi>
      </note>, and <hi>Baronius</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Baron. ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>340.</hi> Lindan. panoplia lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>for a stickler for Arrius, an Arrian here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, a ringleader of the Arrian faction, whose memory is accursed in the second Synod of Nice. Tertullian</hi> likewise is guilded by <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus</hi>
      <seg rend="sup">c</seg> and <hi>Rehing</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Rehing. in muris Civitatis sanctae. fund. <hi>2.</hi> et <hi>12.</hi>
      </note>, with the glorious titles of <hi>a very noble
<pb facs="8"/> author, the chiefe of all the Latine Fathers, the great light of Africa, a most ancient Writer and Doctour, most learned, most skilfull, most acute;</hi> where hee hath some passages which may bee detor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to give countenance to some Romish superstitions: But elsewhere when in expresse words he oppugneth some do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines defined now for Articles of faith in the Church of Rome, he is as much besmeared with foule imputations by <hi>Azorius</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Azorius moral. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>Maldonate</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Maldon. in Math. cap. <hi>16.</hi> vers. <hi>19.</hi> p. <hi>340.</hi>
      </note>, and <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Bell. de sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum beat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>1938.</hi> Bell. de Sacram. Euchar. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>698.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>An hereticall author, an Arch-heretike, an enemy to the Catholike, and like to the Calvinists, a mā whose authority is not much to be set by, because he was no man of the Church:</hi> and as <hi>Euseb.</hi> &amp; <hi>Tertull.</hi> so also <hi>Origen</hi> hath had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>testimonials</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when he pleaseth them hee is<note n="h" place="margin">Lind. Panopl. el. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> et <hi>26</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>a famous light of the Church of Alexandria, whom S.</hi> Hier. <hi>cals another M</hi>
      <seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>of the Churches after the Apostles, a</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Dumus contra Whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> fol. <hi>109.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse beyond all exception;</hi> But when hee fits not their humour, then <hi>he is a Schismatike</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Canus loc. The. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. in Ioan. cap. <hi>1.</hi> vers. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>399.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>a father of the Arrians and Eunomians, a bold</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Ribera in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach. Prophet. proemium.</note>
      <hi>and rash man, an obstinate lover of his owne errours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In <hi>Councels</hi> the case is yet clearer, for the Cardinall sticks not in most plaine termes to hang all them upon the <hi>Popes sleeve: The</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Bell. de Rom. Pont. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>3</hi> Tota firmitas le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimorum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliorum est à Pontifice Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, et cap. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>whole strength &amp; authority</hi> (saith he) <hi>of lawfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels is from the Pope, their</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Conciliorum iudicium tum demū sirmum est cum accesserit, Rom. Pontificis confirmatio.</note>
      <hi>judgment then begins to be of force after the Pope shall ratifie them.</hi> And what Councels will he ratifie? you may bee sure not the Councell in <hi>Trulio,</hi> for that taxeth the Romane Church by name for inforcing single life upon the Clergy: not the Councell at<note n="o" place="margin">An. Do. <hi>681.</hi>
      </note> Constantinople, under <hi>Constantine Pogonate,</hi> for that he accurseth <hi>Honorius</hi> the Pope for an heretike: not the Councell held at <hi>Frankfort</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">An. Do. <hi>794.</hi>
      </note> in the time of Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> for that condemneth their Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: not the Synod of <hi>Pisa</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">An. Do. <hi>1409.</hi>
      </note>, for in that <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> Popes, were deposed: not the Synod<note n="r" place="margin">An. Do. <hi>1430.</hi>
      </note> of <hi>Basil,</hi> wherein <hi>Engenius</hi> was unpoped; nor the Councell of Constance<note n="s" place="margin">An. Do. <hi>1414.</hi>
      </note>, for in it a generall Councel is set aboue the Pope, and three Popes were cashiered by their Authority, (I except the later Sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the same condemned Councell, which are Gospell with them, because they Anathematize the Wicliffists and Hussites:) But the<note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>An.</hi> 787.</note> second Synod of <hi>Nice</hi> shall be held for a generall Councell, because it defendeth and commandeth the worship of Images; though it be full of blasphemous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdities and was called by an insolent woman domineering<note place="margin">Irene.</note>
      <pb facs="8"/> over her husband, and devoted wholly to superstition. The Councell<note n="u" place="margin">An. Do. <hi>1517.</hi>
      </note> of Laterane, though consisting of none in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but the Popes creatures, shall, in despight of the Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Councels of <hi>Pisa, Constance</hi> and <hi>Basil,</hi> bee held a holy and generall Councell, because it defines, that the Pope is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove generall Councels; and for greater reason will the Pope advance the small Conventicle of <hi>Trent</hi> to the honour of a sacred Oecumenicall Councell, because it is throughly for them in all points; though, as a learned Bishop, present at that Councell, truely affirmes, <q>that matters in it came to that passe through the wickednesse of those hungry<note n="x" place="margin">Dudithius quinque Eccles. Epist. ad Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milianum secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Caesar.</note> Bishops, that hung upon the Popes sleeve, and were created on the sudden by the Pope for the purpose, that that Councell seemed to bee an assembly, not of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, but of Hobgoblins, not of men, but of Images moved like the statues of <hi>Daedalus,</hi> by the sinewes of others.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, for their pretended title of Catholike Church, it may be said of it as it was of <hi>Pompeius</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">Lucan de bello <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iu. l. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> Sirname in his decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning age and fame, <hi>Stat magni nominis umbra, 'tis but the shadow of a great name;</hi> for by it they meane nothing but their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Pope himselfe: Thus <hi>Bellarmine</hi> glosseth upon the words of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. the Pope, <hi>Peters</hi> successor, is bid to<note n="z" place="margin">Bell de Concil. author. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> Dicere Ecclesiae, id est, sibi ipsi ut praesidi. et Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae, cui ipse prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est.</note>
      <hi>tell the Church,</hi> that is, <hi>to tell himselfe as Governour, and the Church which hee governs. Gretzer</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Gretz. desen. Bell. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de verbo Dei: Ais tertiò interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur Ecclesiam Patam, non ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo, quid tum?</note> comes off more roundly; <hi>Thou wilt say, they interpret the Church the Pope: I grant it; what then?</hi> And<note n="b" place="margin">2<seg rend="sup">a</seg>. 2<seg rend="sup">a</seg>e. <hi>disput.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Greg de Valent. By the name of the Church wee understand the Head of the Church, the Pope:</hi> and <hi>Bozius</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Boz lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de signis Eccl. ca.</hi> 21. See farther in this Treatise, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 174.</note> declares this mysterie more explicitely, <hi>The Pope su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staineth the person of all Bishops, of all Councels, of the whole Church.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The learned Author then of this ensuing Tractate foyling the Pope, consequently foyleth the whole Romane Church, though he take onely <hi>Vigilius</hi> to taske, yet in overturning his Chaire hee overthroweth, as hath beene shewed, all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane religion, which is <hi>fundamentally</hi> in the Popes Decree, and the whole Romane Church, which is <hi>vertually,</hi> as they teach, in his person. For if Pope <hi>Vigilius,</hi> not as a private man, but as Pope <hi>in Cathedra,</hi> not sitting alone, but with his Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, may erre, not onely in matter of fact, but in matter of faith, judicially and doctrinally determining heresie, and
<pb facs="9"/> commanding it to bee received for Catholike truth: and if this decision and determination of his bee reversed, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and accursed in a lawfully called, sacred and Oecumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Synod, approved by the Christian world, all which are in the following Treatise punctually and uncontroulably proved against all cavils of moderne Papists,
<q>—Ecquis posthac Paparum numen adoret?</q> Will any man hereafter, not wholly given over to be infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with <hi>strong delusions,</hi> adore the <hi>Popes Chaire?</hi> or <hi>kisse his foote?</hi> or pawne his salvation upon his <hi>Cathedrall determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>By all this discourse thou maist see, Christian Reader, the maine scope of the Author; I shall not need to inlarge upon other questions of lesser moment, though now more in <hi>vogue,</hi> which upon the by and occasionally this learned Writer accutely handleth both in this worke and others, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in that imposed upon him by our late Soveraigne of blessed memory, in defence of our Church, <hi>Chap.</hi> 35, 36, 37, 38, &amp; 78.</p>
   <p>Wherfore sith the Composer of this Treatise is most ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall, the argument of great importance, the manner of handling very exact and accurate, I doubt not but thou wilt give it such entertainment, as that thereby others may bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to tread in his steps, and to guide thee in the right way. What though the worke be of some bulke and waight? who ever found fault with gold for that it was too massie and heavy? When <hi>Tully</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Plut. in vit. Cicer.</note> was asked which Oration of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosthenes</hi> he liked best, hee answered, the longest; and questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onlesse in bookes of this nature, <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> the largest which meete with all possible, or at least probable objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and solidly refutes them, give the best satisfaction. Is it not a shame to see in many mens studies idle Poems, <hi>Astreas, Guzmans,</hi> and play-books in folio, but divinity books in <hi>deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo sexto,</hi> or slender pāphlets, stitcht up in blew coats, without any cognizāce, glancing at Church or State, or trēching upon Controversies better buried alive, than to bee revived after they are dead; which are cryed up by the common adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of purpose to foment discords betweene the professors of the Gospell, that whilst, <hi>Pastores odia exercent, Lupus intret Ovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,
<pb facs="9"/> the shepheards are at strife, the Wolfe may make havocke of the flocke;</hi> which I speake not for a <hi>justitium</hi> to any errour, or that I wish any way should bee given to those plausible tenents to corrupt reason, which one of late fitly compared to <hi>flat bottom'd Boates sent from our neighbouring Countries to land Popery in England.</hi> But first my desire is, that all that agree in the love of the same truth, may seeke that truth in love, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally<note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 122.</note>
      <hi>pray for the peace of Ierusalem;</hi> next I pray, that<note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9.</note>
      <hi>our love may abound yet more and more in knowledge, and in all judgment, that wee may discerne things that differ,</hi> and so seeke by all good and lawfull meanes to destroy the <hi>wrigling tayle of the Adder,</hi> whose head was smitten off 1200. yeares agoe in a Synod at <hi>Palestine,</hi> that yet our principall care bee to drive out the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Basiliske,</hi> or rather <hi>the</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.11.</note>
      <hi>King of the Locusts,</hi> against whose poyson I commend the ensuing Discourse as a soveraigne antidote.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Lambeth,</hi>
         <date>April 26. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1631.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord Iesus</hi> DANIEL FEATLEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>