<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface. To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107942_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04779</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14911</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107942</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface. To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The right and iurisdiction of the prelate, and the prince. Or, A treatise of ecclesiasticall, and regall authoritie : Compyled by I.E. student in diuinitie for the ful instruction and appeaceme [n] t of the consciences of English Catholikes, co [n] cerning the late oath of pretended allegeance. Togeather with a cleare &amp; ample declaratio [n], of euery clause thereof, newlie reuewed and augmented by the authoure</title>
                 <author>Kellison, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>412, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="30" facs="16"/>
   <head>A Preface. To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I did not thinke to haue set out this little booke the second tyme, much lesse did I intēd to adde any thing vnto it. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Widdrington in his <hi>New-yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res gifte,</hi> hath of late here and there glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced against some words and speeches of myne, where he imagined most aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, yet I thought (as I see other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writers haue done) to haue quite giuen him ouer, and not to haue made the least replye, as not being desirous to contend with such, as are resolued not to yeelde, hauing other businesses to many where with to occupie my self. But the Printer who first tooke this booke in hād, and other friends also īpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuning me, to let it come forth againe, and alleadging that the copies of the first Edition were all spent, and yet moe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded; I was cōtent <hi>volens, nolens,</hi> yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding herein, more to importunitie then to myne owne inclination, to publishe it once more, and vpon this occasion of this new edition, to adde here and there something, either for a more ample
<pb n="31" facs="16"/>explication, or for answer to Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons obiections. I was willing, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, and forward ynough the first tyme to write of this subiect. For although, as by an accident, I was one of the last, who wrote in the defence, of this the chiefe visible Pastours Authoritie now in Englād impugned, so I counted my selfe amongst the least; yet as when an house is set on fire, some carrie water, others ladders, and euerie one repayreth the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to shew at least his good will to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish it: So in this Cōbustion in which not onlie Heretiques, but also some of them who make profession of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique name, doe endeuoure to put fire, euen to the secundarie foundation of God his Church to wit, the chiefe vifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pastours Authoritie; I thought it the part of euerie zealous Catholicke to runne to the extinguishing of this fire, for though all haue not the like dexteritie, yet all may shew the like good will. Which I hauing performed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Editiō of this little booke according to my abilitie, I thought to haue surcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, had not importunitie of friendes ouercome mee. And therfore after this, as I meane not to dispute any more of this point with thē, with whōe (as I gather by the repulse which greater men then my selfe haue receaued) there is little hope to preuaile; so I wish all Catholiques, seing
<pb n="32" facs="17"/>that they haue hearde their chiefe visible Pastours sentence, to leaue of all Disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching this his Authoritie, and simplie and humblie to obey his commā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and consequentlie to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the sayd Authoritie, to refuse the Oath by him cōdemned, and yet to obey the King our Soueraigne and Liege Lord in all ciuil and temporall causes, to be faithfull to him and his Royall posteritie, and to pray day lie for his maiesties longe and prosperous life, that he may liue lōge to vs, alwayes to God, and so raigne longe in the Kingdome of England, as he may raigne for euer in the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>