<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR IOHN SWINERTON KNIGHT, LORD MAIOR OF THE MOST HONORABLE CITTY OF London; and to the right Worshipfull the Al∣dermen and Shrieues of the same Citty; the aboundant increase of Spirituall Grace in this Life, and in the World to come euerlasting Life, through Iesus Christ our onely Sa∣uiour.</title>
           <author>Cheaste, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107789_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18575</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5105</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR IOHN SWINERTON KNIGHT, LORD MAIOR OF THE MOST HONORABLE CITTY OF London; and to the right Worshipfull the Al∣dermen and Shrieues of the same Citty; the aboundant increase of Spirituall Grace in this Life, and in the World to come euerlasting Life, through Iesus Christ our onely Sa∣uiour.</title>
                 <author>Cheaste, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian path-vvay : Deliuered in a sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the last of Iune 1611. By Thomas Cheaste, minister and preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Cheaste, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR IOHN SWINERTON KNIGHT, LORD MAIOR OF THE MOST HONORABLE CITTY OF <hi>London;</hi> and to the right Worshipfull the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Shrieues of the same Citty; the aboundant increase of Spirituall Grace in this Life, and in the World <hi>to come euerlasting Life, through Iesus Christ</hi> our onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the time now approcheth wherein euery gratefull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son will not onely in word, but also in deed with their presents and giftes shew some signe and token of their louing and kind affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: So (preuenting the time neere at hand) I, as a poore labourer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="3"/> gleaned &amp; gathered these two handsful of corne, two houres labour in the Lords Haruest, I dedicate it (as the best present that I haue) vnto your fauourable acceptation. It may be thought great boldnesse in mee (right Honourable and right Worshipfull) thus presuming to seeke the patronizing of this my poore endeuours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of your Honourable and Worshipfull countenances. But if the name and nature of this my little booke bee rightly considered, and your dignity of place and Office therewith iustly weighed: this bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse I hope will bee thought in mee but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest duty, and your kinde acceptance heereof the true testimony of religious deuotion. I must confesse your serious and zealous atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in hearing this plaine Sermon when it was Preached in your presence; and the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of your religious deuotion, not onely in frequenting the seruice of God, but also in protecting and Patronizing the Preachers and Professours of Gods Word, encouraged mee to preferre this my new borne Orphant, this little booke, to your graue protection, wherein I seeke not, as a Temporizer, to finde out matter to fit and feede Humorists, but in the care of a Christian to make proofe of a better minde: Knowing, that your graue and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious mindes doe contemne idle and friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous flying Pamphlets: What this Booke is, your Iudgements can discerne, and what I am, your kindnesse shall command: so leauing it, with my continuall prayers to Almighty God,
<pb facs="3"/> that hee may direct you in the right path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through the vale of misery into eternall felicity.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours, and Worships in all duty. <hi>THOMAS CHEASTE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>