<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107852_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14274</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14721.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The conquest of the saints: or A short treatise of concord and peace : vvherein is shewed the necessity of unity and peace, without which neither church nor common-wealth can stand. Preached by John Jones Master of Arts, late minister at St. Michael Bashenshaw in London: and now published for the common good</title>
                 <author>Jones, John, minister at St. Michael Bashenshaw, London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 46, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apostle in all his Epistles to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Gentiles, begins with <hi>Grace and Peace,</hi> so in his Epistle to the Saints in <hi>Rome, Grace be with you and Peace.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> being the Apostle of the Gentiles, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes Christs rule in preaching the glad tidings of the Gospell of Peace, and because hee foresaw there would bee many resisters of this Doctrine, hee is therefore more diligent in giving war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to all the Churches to beware of false teachers, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>ver.</hi> 29, 30. hee tells them, <hi>That after his departure
<pb facs="3"/>from them, there should arise men speaking perverse things, to draw disciples after them, yea greedy wolves.</hi> At this time the divisions and contentions betwixt the beleeving Gentiles, and unbeleeving Jewes at <hi>Rome</hi> were so great, that <hi>Claudius</hi> the Emperour commanded all the Jewes to depart from <hi>Rome, Acts</hi> 18. this moved the Apostle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to write this Epistle to the <hi>Romanes</hi> after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priscilla</hi> to <hi>Corinth.</hi> O how carefull was he to give them charge to marke those that caused tents, divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and schismes in the Church, and to avoid them. In like manner, the Author of this short Treatise seeing so many Schismes, and divisions in the Church, and publique State, that both of them as it were lay a bleeding, with the like care, and compassion, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the miserable condition of both, and to that end that these so dangerous evills may bee remooved, hee gives Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veats to avoid all Conventicles of Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratists, Anabaptists, Familists, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as also
<pb facs="3"/>the seducing of Priests and Iesuites, which swarme too much among us, who crie up themselves to bee the onely Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and members of the true Church, who brag and boast so much of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to bee their Founder, yet denie to give to <hi>Caesar,</hi> (who is Christs Lieftenant) his supremacy over the Churches of his owne Kingdomes; briefely the Authors drift and scope in this ensuing Discourse, is to discover all such as cause any divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or disturbance in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale, and so consequently are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Peace of both, that so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing discovered, they may more easily be avoided. Therefore whosoever desireth to follow <hi>the God of Peace,</hi> let mee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire him to reade this short yet sweet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, to perswade all Christians to Unity and Peace, which doubtlesse wee will more eagerly pursue, and more hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily embrace, when from hence wee shall learne what confusions have fallen upon Churches and Common wealths by Schismes, and divisions wrought by Satan
<pb facs="4"/>and his instruments in all ages. Now <hi>the God of Peace</hi> engrave this desire of Peace in all our hearts, and that <hi>Prince of Peace, who hath washed us from our sinnes, and made our Peace with his Father, guide us by the Spirit of Peace to that heavenly Ierusalem, the land of Peace.</hi> To the Sacred Trinity, the Authors of our Peace be given all Glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>