<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE REVEREND, AND RIGHT Worshipfull, Sir IOHN BRAMSTON Knight, Lord chiefe Iustice of his Maiesties Bench, Sir WILLIAM IONES, Sir GEORGE CROOKE, Sir ROBERT BARCKLEY Knights, the Learned Iudges of that Court.</title>
           <author>Trussell, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107345_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13983</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24297</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107345</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE REVEREND, AND RIGHT Worshipfull, Sir IOHN BRAMSTON Knight, Lord chiefe Iustice of his Maiesties Bench, Sir WILLIAM IONES, Sir GEORGE CROOKE, Sir ROBERT BARCKLEY Knights, the Learned Iudges of that Court.</title>
                 <author>Trussell, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A continuation of The collection of the history of England : beginning where Samuel Daniell Esquire ended, with the raigne of Edvvard the third, and ending where the honourable Vicount Saint Albones began, with the life of Henry the seventh, being a compleat history of the beginning and end of the dissention betwixt the two houses of Yorke and Lancaster. With the matches and issue of all the kings, princes, dukes, marquesses, earles, and vicounts of this nation, deceased, during those times. By I.T</title>
                 <author>Trussell, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Ephraim.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Pakeman, Daniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 242, 245-260, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE REVEREND, AND RIGHT Worshipfull, Sir IOHN BRAMSTON Knight, Lord chiefe Iustice of his Maiesties Bench, Sir WILLIAM IONES, Sir GEORGE CROOKE, Sir ROBERT BARCKLEY Knights, the Learned Iudges of that Court.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Icence mee (I humbly beseech your Reverend fatherhoods) with the contrite penitent: Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niously to acknowledge my Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, which is over-much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption in undertaking, more in publishing, but most in thus presenting this my Collection: But withall to appeale from the barre of Rigor, to the borde of favour, and thereat to obtaine this extenuation of censure; That being it was begun with a good intent, prosecuted to a seeming good end, and is now in all befitting hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse presented to procure protection, that I may passe without publicke reprehension: And
<pb facs="3"/>
sithence words and writing are not reall according as they are spoke or writ but as they are appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by others: Let your noble dispositions but make a favourable exposition of what is done: And then I am confident I shall untoucht passe the pikes of scorne and reproofe; In earnest expectation whereof, humble and hearty prayers to God, the giver of all good gifts for our long lives, in health and hearts ease here, and sempiternall happinesse hereafter, shall not want daily to bee powred out, by him that hourely rests,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships reallest in all service and duty, IOHN TRVSSELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>