<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY OF ALL HONOVR FOR RELIGI∣on, Pietie and Iustice, the Reverend Iudges, and Iustices of Peace for the Countie of Oxon.</title>
           <author>James, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107692_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04344</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14459</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY OF ALL HONOVR FOR RELIGI∣on, Pietie and Iustice, the Reverend Iudges, and Iustices of Peace for the Countie of Oxon.</title>
                 <author>James, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Iesuits downefall : threatned against them by the secular priests for their wicked liues, accursed manners, hereticall doctrine, and more then Matchiavillian policie. Together with the life of Father Parsons an English Iesuite</title>
                 <author>James, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY OF ALL HONOVR FOR RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Pietie and Iustice, the Reverend Iudges, and Iustices of Peace for the Countie of Oxon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue <hi>Religion</hi> the only badg of a <hi>Christian,</hi> hath two marks whereby it is certainely knowne; to wit, <hi>Zeale,</hi> and <hi>Constancie. Zeale,</hi> for it must not be cold, nor luke warm; but fervent and hot: <hi>Constancie,</hi> because it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth not for a season, and continueth but a while, but abideth vnto the end, vnto the death, for ever. This zeale which is so necessarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in all men, but more properly in <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi>▪ hath appeared <hi>Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> and <hi>Right VVorshipfull</hi> most evidently, in your late proceedings against <hi>Popish Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants,</hi> at, and before the last <hi>Sessions,</hi> holden for this <hi>Countie,</hi> at an <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. 19.</note> vnvsuall time, and with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extraordinary care &amp; provision, for the sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, finding, fining, and restraining of the most dangerous persons of either sexe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Of your <hi>Constancie</hi> likewise &amp; perseverance in prosecuting so good beginnings, smal cause haue we to doubt, considering the goodnes of the cause, and the greatnes of autority, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with both your hands and hearts are strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from aboue, to the great ioy of all his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties</hi> loyall subiects, Gods faithfull servants. What remaineth now, but that we of the <hi>Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> for our parts, should second these happy beginnings with our vttermost indeavors? by adding the word vnto the sword, perswasions &amp; cōferences, vnto those sharper means &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosiues which are applied, shewing our selues ready to offer vp, not only our labors, but our selues also for the good of such as haue bin se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the <hi>Priests,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iesuits,</hi> but rather by the <hi>Iesuits</hi> then by the <hi>Priests,</hi> for which cause kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the danger, &amp; being most willing (if it bee possible) to prevent it. I haue taken paines to compile this smal Treatise, that if God shall be pleased in mercy to open their eies, they may see the wicked liues, accursed manners, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall doctrine, &amp; more then <hi>Matchiavillian</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of that Society, which they do so devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, with perill both of soule and body.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>This worke I hope will finde the better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement with them, because it is taken wholly and soly from the writings of sundrie learned <hi>Priests,</hi> who spake as they were moved, vpon consideration of their wicked liues and maners, so that theirs are the proofs, mine the collection &amp; method only, as the <hi>Quotations</hi> in the <hi>Margent</hi> wil sufficiētly declare. I admit, that both <hi>Priests</hi> &amp; <hi>Iesuits</hi> are to be feared more and lesse, as dangerous enimies vnto his <hi>Maiesty,</hi> &amp; the <hi>State</hi>: but chiefly the <hi>Iesuits,</hi> who hold their di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sciples in such servitude, or rather slavery, that whatsoever they say is a law, &amp; that law must be obayed, though God &amp; man, reason or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Kaisar</hi> say to the contrary. Frō such followers, as are once wholly devoted to their company, it wil bee a hard matter for the <hi>Magistrate</hi> (you find it by too lamentable experi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence) to draw either the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the <hi>Magistrat</hi> in things Temporal, much lesse conference and conformity in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters spirituall.<note place="margin">Mat. 8.9.</note> For the <hi>Iesuits</hi> like the <hi>Centurion</hi> in the <hi>Gospell,</hi> haue that command &amp; Iurisdictiō over their inferiors, that if they bid <hi>them goe, they goe, if they bid them doe this, they doe it,</hi> without ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="4"/>
any question whether it be right or wrong, iust or vniust which is commanded: &amp; the reasō is plaine, because they relie altogether vpon the <hi>Iesuit,</hi> and the <hi>Iesuit</hi> vpon the <hi>Pope,</hi> who is the only vnerring person vpon earth.</p>
   <p>A most absurd doctrine, as any is in all <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> wherewith notwithstanding, they haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched the soules of I knowe not how many men &amp; women, otherwise very vertuously and religiously inclined, and what pittie is it, for vs to consider, what <hi>Cimmerian</hi> &amp; more then <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> darknesse they doe liue in, that are thus taught by their ignorāt teachers, that do vow themselues blind obedience? <hi>VVhen the blinde lead the blind,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 15.14.</note>
      <hi>how can it be but that both of thē should fall into the ditch.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now this which is spoken against the <hi>Iesuits</hi> doth not acquit the <hi>Secular Priests,</hi> nor their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. For as long as they goe about, to recō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile men from their true and naturall Prince vnto the <hi>Pope,</hi> and to withdraw their mindes, from religion, vnto superstition, from Gods word, vnto fables, from God himselfe vnto Mammon: causing them that are reconciled, not only to professe all <hi>Popish</hi> points, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="4"/>
to the doctrine of the <hi>Councell of Trent,</hi> as <hi>vnwritten Traditions, Transubstantiation, Purgatory Indulgences, worshipping of Images, &amp; Reliques, Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by workes, the truth of seaven Sacraments, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to one only Pope, &amp;c.</hi> but to make them <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Creed,</hi> and to take a solemne <note n="*" place="margin">This true Catholique faith, without which no mā can bee saved which now I doe willingly professe, and hold, I the same N. doe promise, vow, and sweare, to hold &amp; confes most constāt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by Gods help intire &amp; vncorrupted, even to the last end of my life: &amp; to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure as much as shall lie in me, that my subiects, or those of whō I shall haue care in my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, shal hold, teach, and preach the same. So God help mee and these holy Gospels of God. <hi>A Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith set out, according to the Decree of the Councell of Trent.</hi> Or, <hi>A manifest confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Christian Beliefe, which all vpright Catholike people at al times, being demanded to giue a reason thereof, are bound to confesse.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Oath,</hi> that they will <hi>continue in the profession of all &amp; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them vnto the death, and farthermore, perswade as much as in them lyeth, all others that are vnder thē to doe the like,</hi> we haue iust cause to suspect both their dealings, &amp; to oppose our selues against their proceedings. The which thing you haue begun to doe, <hi>Right Honorable and Right VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull,</hi> to your eternall praise &amp; commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the example and encouragement of others You haue begun well, who shalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hinder you, if God be on your side?</p>
   <p>Goe forward then, I beseech you, in Gods name, both cheerefully and couragiously, you haue our earnest prayers, &amp; shalbe sure to haue our best endeavors (if need require.) I knowe the readines of many learned and graue <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> to further this religious service, amongst
<pb facs="5"/>
which, my selfe being one of the meanest in Gods Church, scarse worthy to be called a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> doe most earnestly desire, to contribute my paines and service, &amp; to make knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the world, the great affection which I beare vnto all sorts of people, thus by the <hi>Iesuits</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serably seduced: whose conversion as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waies sought by good and faire meanes, such as the most wayward &amp; peevishest adversaries cānot iustly except against: so is it my purpose, God willing, so to continue vnto my liues end, both by speech &amp; writing, propagating that faith, whereof his <hi>Maiestie</hi> of al <hi>Princes Christian</hi> may truly be said to be the <hi>Defendor</hi>: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>Iesuits</hi> are his &amp; our chiefest enimies, accept, I beseech you, these few lines, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their liues and maners in generall, &amp; one of the chiefest of them in particular; the matter was ministred vnto me by certaine <hi>Secular Priests,</hi> the method in disposing and digesting of it was mine, to God bee ascribed the glory and benefit thereof, if any shall arise. And thus beseeching him to blesse you all with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of your care, and increase of <hi>zeale,</hi> for the vtter suppressing of all <hi>Poperie</hi> and superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="5"/>
and rooting out of all <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Iesuits.</hi> I humbly take my leaue▪</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From the <hi>Publique Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary in Oxford,</hi>
         <date>Sept. 16. 1612.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in all religious services to command. <hi>THO. JAMES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>