<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE TO THE PROPHECIE OF ISAIAH:</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107143_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4396</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107143</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE TO THE PROPHECIE OF ISAIAH:</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary vpon the prophecie of Isaiah. By Mr. Iohn Caluin. Whereunto are added foure tables: the first touching places of scripture alleaged: the second, of the principall matters handled: the third, of authors and diuers names mentioned: the fourth, of certaine texts cited out of Isaiah in the new Testament, which by the author in the commentarie are compared and reconciled. Translated out of French into English: by C.C</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Cotton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 674, 40 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>A PREFACE TO THE PROPHECIE OF ISAIAH:</head>
   <byline>BY M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN CALVIN.</byline>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey haue been wont to spend many words in setting forth the office of the Prophets.<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ground their doctrin vpon the law.</note> But I see no readier way then to referre them to the law; whence their doctrine is drawne, as the riuers from the fountaines. For they set the law before them for their imitation, so as by good right we may affirme and hold them to be the expositors thereof, in whom there is nothing separate from it.<note place="margin">Whereof they are the Expositors. The law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines three points:</note> Now the Law containes three points. First, the doctrine of life: secondly, the threatnings and promises: thirdly, the couenant of grace, which is founded in Christ.</p>
   <p>For as touching the Ceremonies, they were exercises, by which the people were held in the seruice of God, and in godlinesse; according to the Contents of the first Table.</p>
   <p>The Prophets then expound the doctrine thereof more at large; and lay that foorth in more plaine termes, which is brieflie contained in the two tables; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that which the Lord principallie requires.</p>
   <p>As touching the threatnings<note place="margin">Threatnings:</note> and promises<note place="margin">Promises:</note> which <hi>Moses</hi> touched in generall; they applie them to their owne times, and describe them particularly. Lastlie, that which is said obscurely in <hi>Moses,</hi> touching Christ and his grace; they set it foorth more perspicuouslie, and alleage more ample and abundant testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the free couenant.</p>
   <p>But that the thing may be more cleere, we must fetch the matter further off; namely, from the Law it selfe, which God ordained as a perpetuall rule for his Church, that it might alwaies be in mens hands: and that all their successors should follow it.</p>
   <p>Now because this doctrin of the law sufficed not this obstinate &amp; vnruly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the Lord also foreseeing that they would neuer be held in, vnlesse it were by some bridle: hee addes a prohibition,<note place="margin">Prohibitions.</note> not to seeke to Magitians, Southsay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Inchanters, Sorcerers, nor to such as regard the times, or the flying of birds,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.9.10.11.12.</note> to such as asked counsell of familiar spirits, or at the dead; because such things were an abomination to the Lord.</p>
   <p>And to preuent the replies which they might make, namely, that their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion should be worse, then that of the infidels, who had their Southsayers, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologers, Sacrificers, and such like, of whom they might aske aduice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel; but they shuld be destituted of any that might be able to giue them satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in doubtful and intricat causes: herein, to take away al pretext, &amp; that they might not defile themselues in these execrable customes of the Gentiles, God
<pb facs="10"/> promiseth to raise them vp <hi>Prophets,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.</note> by whom he wil manifest his wil, who also shall faithfully teach them whatsoeuer hee shall giue them in charge; that they might haue no cause to complaine for the time to come, as if any thing were wanting vnto them.</p>
   <p>I grant, that in that place <hi>Moses</hi> mentions a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and not Prophets. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding it is a change of the number, to wit, the singular for the plurall, a thing common in the Scriptures. And howsoeuer the place ought properly and principally to bee vnderstood of Christ (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> expounds it Act. 3.) in regard he is the Prince of the Prophets, and that all of them, with their doctrine also depend vpon him, and with one consent aime at him: yet by this name, which is collectiue, it also comprehends the rest of the Prophets.</p>
   <p>The Lord then hauing promised them Prophets, by whom hee would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto them his counsell and will, he commanded the people to rest in their exposition and doctrine. Not that the Prophets should adde any thing to the law, but that they should faithfully expound the same, and conserue the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie thereof.</p>
   <p>Whence also it is, that <hi>Malachi</hi> exhorting the people to persist in that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.4.</note> saith, or rather God by him: <hi>Remember the Law of Moses my seruant, which I gaue him in Horeb for all Israel.</hi> Thus bringing them backe to Gods law <hi>only;</hi> and commanding them to be <hi>content therewith.</hi> But would <hi>Malachi</hi> haue them to despise the <hi>Prophets</hi> then? No. But forasmuch as the prophesies are dependan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the law, and that the law summarilie comprehends them all, this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion sufficed. For such as are well acquainted with the summe of the doctrine, and principall heads of it, hauing their willes well inclined thereto; it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that they will not contemne the prophesies: for it were a thing too fond to boast of hauing affection to the law, and yet in the meane while not to make any account of the diuine interpretation thereof: such as are some at this day, who are so shamelesse,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that they dare brag of louing Gods law, and the whilest cannot endure to bee admonished or reprehended by the doctrine which is drawne and collected from the same.</p>
   <p>Thus when the Prophets deale with mens manners, they bring in no new thing,<note place="margin">The first ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> but explane those things which were misunderstood in the law. As for example, the people thought they had done their duties to the vtmost, when they had offered sacrifices, and obserued the ceremonies: for the world is wont alwaies to measure God according to their owne ell, and to botch him vp a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall seruice. This corruption the Prophets reprooue sharpely, shewing that all ceremonies are nothing where the integritie of the heart is wanting; and that God will be worshipped by faith, and a right inuocating of his name. This was manifested to them plainely enough in the law, but it was needfull it should take a deeper impression, and that they should be put againe in mind of it. The hypocrisie,<note place="margin">The second t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ble.</note> wherewith men maske themselues vnder the vaile of ceremonies, was to be discouered.</p>
   <p>As touching the second table, the Prophets thence drew their exhortations, shewing how all wrong, fraud and violence was to be abandoned. The Prophets office then was nothing else, but to hold the people in obedience to Gods law.</p>
   <p>In the threatnings<note place="margin">Threatnings.</note> and promises they haue something more speciall. For what <hi>Moses</hi> propounded in generall, they describe in particular. Besides, they had visions,<note place="margin">Visions.</note> which were proper to them: by which the Lord reuealed things to come, that so they might applie the promise and threatnings to the peoples vse, and might further assure them of Gods will.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Moses</hi>
      <note place="margin">Moses.</note> threatens, <hi>God will pursue thee with the sword, the enemies shall vex thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> and within, domesticall contentions shall <hi>annoy thee. Thy life shall hang as by a thread; thou shalt tremble at the shaking of a leafe;</hi> and such other things.</p>
   <p>But the Prophets<note place="margin">The Prophets</note> say: <hi>Behold, God hath raised against thee the sword of the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans, and of the Egyptians:</hi> also, <hi>God hath armed these to the battell. This citie shall be destroyed at such a time.</hi> The like is to be said of the promises.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Moses</hi>
      <note place="margin">Moses.</note> saith, <hi>If thou obseruest the commandements, God will blesse thee.</hi> And then he goes on in recounting blessings in generall.</p>
   <p>But the Prophets<note place="margin">The Prophets</note> in particular affirme, <hi>The Lord will blesse thee in such a thing.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Also the Lord promiseth by <hi>Moses</hi>
      <note place="margin">Moses.</note> in these words, <hi>Although thou wert scattered and driuen to the vtmost parts of the earth, yet from thence will I gather thee.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But the Prophets<note place="margin">The Prophets</note> promise, that albeit the Lord hath scattered them <hi>as farre as Babylon, yet within</hi> 70. <hi>yeeres he will cause their captiuitie to returne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And as touching the free couenant which God made with man through Christ, the Prophets are much more euident;<note place="margin">Couenant of grace.</note> and doe much more confirme the people in it. For they <hi>set Christ before their eies,</hi> when they would comfort the faithfull, and raise vp their minds to the hope of his comming, euen as it were to the foundation, and to the place of the couenant, vnto whom the effect of the promises was to be referred.</p>
   <p>Whosoeuer shall ponder these things, shall easilie perceiue what hee is to seeke in the Prophets, and whereunto their writtings tend. But for the present, it sufficeth that we haue pointed it foorth as with the finger.</p>
   <p>Hence we may soone gather how wee ought to handle the doctrine of the word, and how we ought to imitate the Prophets; who so much admired it, that thence they collected the admonitions, reprehensions, threatnings and consolations, to applie them to the peoples vse.<note place="margin">Note.</note> For though it be not dailie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto vs what we ought to doe, yet are wee to compare the conuersation of the people of our times, with that of the people of old; and by histories and examples to denounce the iudgements of God. Namely, that from the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance he tooke vpon such sinnes in that time,<note place="margin">God alwaies like himselfe.</note> he will likewise be reuenged vpon those that reigne euery where in our time. Why so? Because he is alwaies like himselfe.</p>
   <p>The faithfull teachers then must come furnished with the like wisdome, if they meane to handle the doctrine of the Prophets profitablie. Thus much as touching the prophesies in generall.</p>
   <p>To come to our Prophet <hi>Isaiah:</hi> the inscription<note place="margin">The inscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> sufficiently shewes both what he was, and in what time he published his prophesies. For his father is here na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to wit, <hi>Amos</hi> brother of <hi>AZarias</hi> king of Iuda.<note place="margin">Isaiah de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended of the blood Royall.</note> Whence it appeares hee was of the blood royall: and of this opinion are all the ancients. And yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his stocke, nor neere affinitie to the King (for the Iewes affirme he was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law of <hi>Manasseh</hi>) could hinder him from being put to death in hatred of his doctrine, neither was he respected any more, then if he had been of some base estate or condition.</p>
   <p>The names of the Kings here mentioned, set foorth the time,<note place="margin">The time when Isaiah Prophesied.</note> in which hee prophesied. There are some who thinke that he began about the end of <hi>VZi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> raigne. And they take their coniecture from the vision which is recorded in the sixth chapter, by which he testifies hee was confirmed. But this conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture is too weake; as shall be shewed in place conuenient. It rather appeares by the inscription, that he prophesied in the daies of <hi>Vziah;</hi> of which I see no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="11"/> to the contrarie. How euer it bee, it plainely appeares that he prophesied aboue 64. yeeres. For <hi>Iothan</hi> raigned 16. yeeres: <hi>Ahaz</hi> as much; <hi>Hezekias</hi> 29. This makes 61. Ad those in which he prophesied vnder <hi>Vziah;</hi> and afterwards vnder <hi>Manasses,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isaiah put to death by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasses.</note> who put him to death: These at the least will make vp 64. yeres; in which <hi>Isaiah</hi> ceased not to performe the office of a Prophet. And it may well be that he prophesied longer: but of this we can gather no certentie from the historie.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Isaiah a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erne for all Pastors.</note>This then ought to be seriouslie marked of all the Ministers of the word, that from his example, they may learne patiently to beare the burthen of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, though it be cumbersome and painefull: not thinking it any disgrace to suffer many sore and tedious trauels, seeing they haue so many worthie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes set before them. I grant it must needs discourage them exceedinglie, when they see that things goe not forward; and that their labours take not such good successe as they desire: thinking it better to leaue all, rather then to bestow so much labour in vaine. They haue need therefore often to remember, and to set before their eies such examples. (Why so?) Because <hi>Isaiah</hi> fainted not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he gained little by so many painfull trauels.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ieremiah</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ieremiah.</note> also ceased not by the space of 50. yeeres to call vpon this people, who in the meane while hardned their hearts the more: and yet wee see they forsooke not their charge, whatsoeuer difficulties came betweene. Euen so must wee follow our vocation, and constantlie beare all sorts of encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances.</p>
   <p>Note also the circumstance of the change of Kings<note place="margin">The change of Kings.</note> which are here numbred vp, chap. 1.1. For it is impossible that in so great diuersitie, the State should al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies continue alike. No doubt but many troubles fell out. And yet our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet perseuered with an inuincible constancie; and neuer suffered his heart to be ouercome of feares.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
      </label> But some may aske whether <hi>Isaiah</hi> himselfe put this title to his prophesie, or some other. <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
      </label> None of the expositors that I haue read, answers this question. For my owne part, albeit I am not very well satisfied, as touching this question, yet I will shew what I thinke.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">How the Prophecies were colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note>After the Prophets had preached to the people, they gathered a compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous summe of their sermon; which they affixed to the gate of the Temple, that the prophesie might the better be viewed and learned of all. And after it had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there a sufficient time for some certaine daies; the Ministers of the Temple took it downe, and put it into the treasurie of the Temple, that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie thereof might continue for euer. Very likely it is (I say) that the bookes of the Prophets were thus gathered, as may appeare by the second Chapter of <hi>Habacuk;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Haba.</hi> 2.2. See chap. 30.8. and chap. 8.1.2. The Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the singular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God.</note> whosoeuer be disposed to consider the same well: as also from the eight of this prophesie.</p>
   <p>Now this was done no doubt by the speciall prouidence of God, that by the Priests themselues, whose office it was to conserue the prophesies for such as should succeed, it is come to passe that wee at this day enioy these trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures; which they for the most part lightly esteemed. For the Priests were the greatest enemies, that the Prophets had to deale withall.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>