<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Priests, said to be
vnited with the Archpriest.
{inverted ⁂}</title>
           <author>C., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107159_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17505</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4321</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Priests, said to be
vnited with the Archpriest.
{inverted ⁂}</title>
                 <author>C., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A replie vnto a certaine libell, latelie set foorth by Fa: Parsons, in the name of vnited priests : intituled, A manifestation of the great folly and bad spirit, of certaine in England, calling themselues seculer priestes. VVith an addition of a table of such vncharitable words and phrases, as by him are vttered in the said treatise, aswell against our parsons, as our bookes, actions, and proceedings</title>
                 <author>Clark, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 106, 6 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Priests, said to be
vnited with the Archpriest.
{inverted ⁂}</head>
   <p>REuerend and my deere bretheren, whom with my soule I
loue, and honour with my hart, I cannot but be sory to see
you so vniustly abused by the slights and cunning deuises of
the Iesuits: and more, to see you, (whom wisedome and
discretion should make perfect and expert in the affaires of our
poore afflicted Church, so applaude their proceedings, that worke
your bane, or at the least, by holding your peace, to approoue such
actions in them, as tend to the ouerthrow of your selues. Tell mee I
beseech you, in your owne vnderstandings, are you not highly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
in bearing the name of these two late Libells, viz. the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi>
and <hi>Manifestation:</hi> in both which, not onely the honour of
priesthood is impeached, and our whole Cleargie disgraced, deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
and sought to be held in slauery, and subiection to the Iesuits &amp;
theyr creatures, but also such vndutifull actions and practises, as
haue beene attempted by them, or any other Catholicke from the
beginning of her Maiesties raigne, vntill this day, are maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
defended, excused, or iustified: whereby your liues are enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
as accessary to all treasons, plots, &amp; practises done, or attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
against our Soueraigne and Country, by such parsons: in that
to approue, defend, or maintaine any action, is (as you knowe) to
make the approuer, defender, and maintainer, accessary thereto:
iudge then what cause you haue to thanke such Maisters, for this
theyr good office, in laying snares to entrappe you withall: and
thinke whether this deuise be not a plot of purpose to bring you into
as great obloquy with your Prince, (as through theyr own vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
practises) they haue brought themselues, thereby to turne the
sword of persecution vpon all (as heeretofore) for some particuler
mens offences. Deere brethren, if you regard not the wrongs, and
oppressions doone to vs your brethren, and neerer vnto you in all
right of reason, then the Iesuits are; if you regard not the deiection
and oppression of your Cleargie, which they violently seeke; if you
respect not theyr actions, and attempts against your natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
and neerest friends: yet regard your selues, respect your owne
liues, haue a care to the common, and generall good of altogether,
insiduated, and betrayed by them: disclaime from such actions,
<pb facs="3"/>
wherein you haue no part, neither desire (I thinke) to haue. I
know your harts to be loyall, let them not be stained by a false im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
from a deceitfull Iesuit. Beleeue me, her Maiestie dooth
make difference betwixt practisers in matters of state, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and therefore suffer not your names to be brought into question
for such odious dealings, by the cunning policies of Fa. <hi>Parsons,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowling
thē to the approbations of such hatefull trecheries. And if
there were n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> difference at all made (as I know there is) yet were
it glorious to die a Cath: priest, in profession of the Cath: fayth,
without taint, or imputation of those foule crimes. But some of you
happily may be ignorant, how farre you are abused in this kinde:
vouchsafe but the reading ouer of this reply to the latter Libell, &amp;
you shall easily perceiue more danger to be couched therein, then
you are aware of, and thereby see the better what wrong is offered
you, in publishing the same in your names. If in the perusing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
any word may seeme ouer-sharpe, which yet I haue endeuoured
to auoyde, consider I beseech you the deformity of some matters
vniustly &amp; vncharitably auerred against vs, &amp; that all such sharpe
words touch onely one man, the Author of these iniurious Libels,
and <hi>Architect</hi> of this whole businesse, and then I hope you will
with more ease yeeld pardon to such excesse: If any other faults ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in stile, or defectiue handling of matters obiected occur, beare
with the author, this beeing his first worke, and hudled vp in hast,
without such helpes, as longer time might haue affoorded him, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
him in all things as fauourable a censure as you may: who is
ready to protest in the sincerity of a Catholicke priest, that neyther
malice, anger, passion, nor desire of reuenge, drew him to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
this worke, but onely a sincere opinion of iustice, and innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
so much impugned by Fa: <hi>Parsons,</hi> in defence wherof hee
thought himselfe bound (as well in respect of the common cause, as
his owne particuler interest therein) to shew his best indeuours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend and brother
VV. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>