<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, GEORGE Marquesse Buckingham, Ʋiscount VILLIERS, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of England; Iustice in Eyre of all his Maie∣sties Forrests, Parkes, and Chases beyond Trent, Master of the Horse to his Maiestie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Ma∣iesties Bed-chamber, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuy Counsell of England and Scotland.</title>
           <author>Blount, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107642_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18335</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4917</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107642</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, GEORGE Marquesse Buckingham, Ʋiscount VILLIERS, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of England; Iustice in Eyre of all his Maie∣sties Forrests, Parkes, and Chases beyond Trent, Master of the Horse to his Maiestie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Ma∣iesties Bed-chamber, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuy Counsell of England and Scotland.</title>
                 <author>Blount, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the history of the valorous and witty knight-errant, Don Quixote of the Mançha : VVritten in Spanish by Michael Ceruantes: and now translated into English</title>
                 <author>Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 276, 279-504, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, GEORGE Marquesse Buckingham, Ʋiscount VILLIERS, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of England; Iustice in Eyre of all his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Forrests, Parkes, and Chases beyond Trent, Master of the Horse to his Maiestie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Bed-chamber, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuy Counsell of England and Scotland.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Noble Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR humble ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant hath obseru'd in the multitude of books that haue past his hands, no small varietie of Dedications; and those seuerally sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Presenters ends: Some, for the meere ambition of Great names; Others, for the desire, or need
<pb facs="3"/> of Protection; Many, to win Friends, and so fauour, and opinion; but Most, for the more sordid respect, Gaine. This humbly offers into your Lo: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, with none of these deformities: But as a bashfull stranger, newly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued in <hi>English,</hi> hauing originally had the fortune to be borne commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to a <hi>Grande</hi> of <hi>Spaine;</hi> and, by the way of translation, the grace to kisse the hands of a great Ladie of <hi>France,</hi> could not despaire of lesse courtesie in the Court of Great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> then to bee receiued <hi>of your Lo: delight;</hi> his study being to swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten those short starts of your retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from publique affaires, which so many, so vnseasonably, euen to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestation trouble.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By him who most truely honours, and humbly professes all duties to your Lordship. <hi>Ed: Blount.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>