<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A SHORT METHOD OF ALL THE BOOKES OF THE HOLY BIBLE: DECLARING,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107136_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17242</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4093</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107136</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A SHORT METHOD OF ALL THE BOOKES OF THE HOLY BIBLE: DECLARING,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the head-corner-stone: by builders still ouer-much omitted : that is; a forme of teaching Iesus Christ, out of all the Holy Scriptures, both of the Old Testament (that are canonicall) and of the New; ... The whole worke being digested into two seuerall tomes: eyther of which tomes, hauing two bookes therevnto appertaining: as more at large is to be seene in the next leafe. Togither with certaine tables of diuers sorts, for the better vnderstanding, and vse of these bookes; ... By Edm: Bunny, Batcheler of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Bunny, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 577, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biblical_epitome">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>A SHORT METHOD OF ALL THE BOOKES OF THE HOLY BIBLE: DECLARING,</head>
   <argument>
      <p>In what order those Bookes may be taken (as commonly they are sorted vnto vs) for the readier finding of such places, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> these Bookes following by the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations we are directed vnto: (the better if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ad by heart; and not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete to be taught vnto Children, for their readier helpe heereafter.)</p>
   </argument>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the <hi>Holy-Bible</hi> there bee two princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>s; the <hi>Old-Testament</hi> and the <hi>New:</hi> the <hi>Old</hi> consisting of such Bookes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in former Ages were written of Christ; the <hi>New,</hi> of such as are written of him since his comming in the flesh.</p>
   <p>In that which goeth vnder the name of the <hi>Old-Testament,</hi> there be sorts of Bookes; <hi>Canonical,</hi> and <hi>Apocrypha: Canonical</hi> being such, as are the vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Word of God; <hi>Apocrypha</hi> being such, as are not the vndoubted word of God, but yet haue many good Lessons in them.</p>
   <p>Those that are <hi>Canonical,</hi> are of two sorts: some of them for the most part of <hi>Histories;</hi> others, for the most part of <hi>Doctrine</hi> onely. Those that are for the most part of <hi>Histories,</hi> are, first <hi>Genesis, Exodus, Leuiticus, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy:</hi> then, <hi>Ioshua, Iudges,</hi> and <hi>Ruth:</hi> thirdly, two Books of <hi>Samuel,</hi> two of the <hi>Kings</hi> (which are sometimes called also the foure Bookes of the <hi>Kings)</hi> and two Bookes of the <hi>Chronicles:</hi> fourthly, <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah</hi> (called also two of the first Bookes of <hi>Esdras)</hi> and <hi>Ester:</hi> last of all, <hi>Iob.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Those that are for the most part of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> are some of the <hi>Kings:</hi> and some of the <hi>Prophets.</hi> Those that are of the <hi>Kings,</hi> are first, the <hi>Psalmes,</hi> which are (most of them) <hi>Dauids:</hi> then, the <hi>Prouerbes, Ecclesiastes,</hi> and the <hi>Canticle</hi> or <hi>Song,</hi> all which are <hi>Salomons.</hi> Of the <hi>Prophets</hi> there bee two sorts: some of them <hi>Greater;</hi> and some of them <hi>Lesser.</hi> The <hi>Greater</hi> are foure, <hi>Isaiah, Ieremy</hi> (both his <hi>Prophesie,</hi> and his <hi>Lamentations) Ezechiel</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel.</hi> The <hi>Lesser</hi> are twelue, <hi>Hosea, Ioel, Amos, Obadiah, Ionah, Micah, Nuhum, Habacuk, Zephaniah, Haggai, Zachariah,</hi> and <hi>Malachy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Apocrypha</hi> are, one of them set before by it selfe: the others follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after together. That one that is set before by it selfe, is the Prayer of <hi>Manasses,</hi> commonly following the Bookes of the <hi>Chronicles.</hi> Those that follow after together, are the first and the Bookes of <hi>Esdras, Tobit, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,</hi> the rest of <hi>Ester, Wisedome, Ecclesiasticus, Baruk</hi> with the <hi>Epistle</hi> of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi> the <hi>Song</hi> of the three <hi>Children,</hi> the Story of <hi>Susanna,</hi> the Idol <hi>Bell,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> the first and the second of the <hi>Maccabees.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <p> Those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> of the <hi>New-Testament,</hi> are most of them of that praesent time: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> there is, of a time then after following. Those that are of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> time, are some of them for the most part of <hi>Histories▪</hi> &amp; some of them for the most part of <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Those that are for the most part of <hi>Histories,</hi> are most of the <hi>History</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> but one, of the <hi>Apostles.</hi> Those that are of the History of <hi>Christ,</hi> are the foure <hi>Euangelists: Mathew, Marke, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e,</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi> That one that is of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> is the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Those that are for the most part of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> are the <hi>Epistles</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles:</hi> most of them going vnder the name of S. <hi>Paul;</hi> but some of them being the <hi>Epistles</hi> of other <hi>Apostles.</hi> Those that go vnder the name of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> are most of them his indeede: but one of them there is, that some haue thought to be the Epistle of some other Apostle. Those that are his indeed, are some of them written to whole Churches: others to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>ll persons. Those that are written to whole Churches, are, one to <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> two to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to the <hi>Galatians, Ephesians, Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians,</hi> and <hi>Colos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ians</hi> to euery of these one: and two to the <hi>Thessalonians.</hi> Those that are written but onely to certaine seuerall persons, are, two to <hi>Timoth,</hi> one to <hi>Titus,</hi> and one to <hi>Philemon.</hi> That one that some haue thought to be the Epistle of some other <hi>Apostle,</hi> is, the Epistle to the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes.</hi> Those that are the Epistles of other Apostles, are, one of <hi>Iames,</hi> two of <hi>Peter,</hi> three of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and one of <hi>Iude.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That one Booke which was of a time then after following, is the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps,</hi> or the <hi>Reuelation of Saint Iohn.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>