<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>King James I</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107574_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14364</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>King James I</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Daemonologie : in forme of a dialogue, diuided into three bookes</title>
                 <author>James, I., King of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 81, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge at this time in this countrie, of these detest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able slaues of the Deuill, the Witches or enchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hath moved me (beloued reader) to dispatch in post, this following treatise of mine, not in any wise (as I protest) to serue for a shew of my learning &amp; ingine, but onely (mooued of conscience) to preasse
<pb facs="3"/>
thereby, so farre as I can, to resolue the doubting harts of many; both that such as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saultes of Sathan are most certainly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized, &amp; that the instrumentes thereof, merits most severly to be punished: against the damnable opinions of two principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our age, wherof the one called <hi>SCOT</hi> an Englishman, is not ashamed in publike print to deny, that ther can be such a thing as Witch-craft: and so mainteines the old error of the Sadducees, in denying of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. The other called <hi>VVIERVS,</hi> a German Phisition, sets out a publick apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie for al these craftes-folkes, whereby, procuring for their impunitie, he plainely bewrayes himselfe to haue bene one of that profession. And for to make this treatise the more pleasaunt and facill, I haue put it in forme of a Dialogue, which I haue diuided into three bookes: The first spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="3"/>
of Magie in general, and Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancie in special. The second of Sorcerie and Witch-craft: and the thirde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines a discourse of all these kindes of spirits, &amp; Spectres that appeares &amp; tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles persones: together with a conclusion of the wholwork. My intention in this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is only to proue two things, as I haue alreadie said: the one, that such diuelish artes haue bene and are. The other, what exact trial and seuere punishment they merite: &amp; therefore reason I, what kinde of things are possible to be performed in these arts, &amp; by what naturall causes they may be, not that I touch every particular thing of the Deuils power, for that were infinite: but onelie, to speak scholasticklie, (since this can not bee spoken in our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) I reason vpon <hi>genus</hi> leauing <hi>species,</hi> and <hi>differentia</hi> to be comprehended therein.
<pb facs="4"/>
As for example, speaking of the power of Magiciens, in the first book &amp; sixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: I say, that they can suddenly cause be brought vnto them, all kindes of daintie dishes, by their familiar spirit: Since as a thiefe he delightes to steale, and as a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, he can subtillie &amp; suddenlie inough transport the same. Now vnder this <hi>genus,</hi> may be comprehended al particulars, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereupon; Such as the bringing Wine out of a Wall, (as we haue heard oft to haue bene practised) and such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; which particulars, are sufficientlie proved by the reasons of the general. And such like in the second booke of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft in speciall, and fift Chap. I say and proue by diuerse arguments, that Witches can, by the power of their Master, cure or cast on disseases: Now by these same reasones, that proues their power by the
<pb facs="4"/>
Deuil of disseases in generall, is aswell proued their power in speciall: as of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening the nature of some men, to make them vnable for women: and making it to abound in others, more then the ordinary course of nature would permit. And such like in all other particular sicknesses; But one thing I will pray thee to obserue in all these places, where I reason vpon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils power, which is the different ends &amp; scopes, that God as the first cause, and the Devill as his instrument and second cause shootes at in all these actiones of the Deuil, (as Gods hang-man:) For where the deuilles intention in them is euer to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, either the soule or the body, or both of them, that he is so permitted to deale with: God by the contrarie, drawes euer out of that euill glorie to himselfe, either by the wracke of the wicked in his justice, or
<pb facs="5"/>
by the tryall of the patient, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the faithfull, being wakened vp with that rod of correction. Hauing thus declared vnto thee then, my full intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this Treatise, thou wilt easelie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, I doubt not, aswel my pretermitting, to declare the whole particular rites and secretes of these vnlawfull artes: as also their infinite and wounderfull practises, as being neither of them pertinent to my purpose: the reason whereof, is giuen in the hinder ende of the first Chapter of the thirde booke: and who likes to be curious in these thinges, he may reade, if he will here of their practises, <hi>BODINVS Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monomanie,</hi> collected with greater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, then written with judgement, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their confessions, that haue bene at this time apprehened. If he would know what hath bene the opinion of the Aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes,
<pb facs="5"/>
concerning their power: he shall see it wel descrybed by <hi>HYPERIVS, &amp; HEMMINGIVS,</hi> two late Germaine writers: Besides innumerable other neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terick Theologues, that writes largelie vpon that subject: And if he woulde knowe what are the particuler rites, &amp; curiosities of these black arts (which is both vnnecessarie and perilous,) he will finde it in the fourth book of <hi>COR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NELIVS Agrippa,</hi> and in <hi>VVIERVS,</hi> whomof I spak. And so wishing my pains in this Treatise (beloued Reader) to be effectual, in arming al them that reades the same, against these aboue mentioned erroures, and recommending my good will to thy friendly acceptation, I bid thee hartely fare-well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IAMES R<seg rend="sup">x</seg>.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>