<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           <author>I., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107703_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14492</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107703</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 <author>I., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newcastles call, to her neighbour and sister townes and cities throughout the land, to take warning by her sins and sorrowes : Lest this overflowing scourge of pestilence reach even unto them also. As also a direction, how to discover such sins as are the procurers of Gods judgments by divers methods. By R. Jenison, Dr. of D. Whereunto is added, the number of them that dyed weekely in Newcastle and Garth-side, from May 6. to December 31. 1636</title>
                 <author>Jenison, Robert, 1584?-1652</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Colby (Coleby), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 72, 95-251, that is 271, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <p>and there told of the <hi>Meanes,</hi> both of the <hi>Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> and also, <hi>Ruine</hi> of Cities and whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
   <p>Be yee pleased now to take in good part, a word or two, spoken, I hope, not out of season, in the mournfull and sad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this my <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Nurse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">— Foelix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uicumque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>olore, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erius dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es posse ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere tuo.</note> in whose name I make bold to salute you all in the Lord, and to wish you the happiness to be warned in time by that bittercup of ours, wherin God, by Pestilence, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to have begun to you all. The times require every ones helpe to seeke
<pb facs="2"/>
to quench this fire of wrath begun in the Land▪ I heartily wish that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie others of much abler parts, would in this kind of popular and familiar Discourse and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on put forth themselves, and stoope to such neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie and edifying Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For my part, as the case is, I, though the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of most, expect not who shall begin. God hath begun with us here: <hi>The Lyon hath roared—the Lord hath spoken, I cannot</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my abilitie, setting aside all respect of credit with men of the world) <hi>but prophesie;</hi> &amp; that not by
<pb facs="3"/>
word here onely, but by writing (such is my desire of the publicke good, and such is the occasion here offred by Gods beginning in this fierce manner with us.) The benefit you may, by <hi>Gods</hi> blessing, and your own good indeavour, reap hereby, will be, either a <hi>prevention of</hi> and freedom to you, frō this spreading evill (which I chiefly by this Dedication do desire and intend:) or a <hi>Direction</hi> how to carry your selves (&amp; that with comfort) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Gods</hi> hand, if it reach also unto you.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 26.9, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>The truth is, <hi>When Gods judgments are in the earth,
<pb facs="3"/>
the inhabitants of the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ill</hi> (at least should) <hi>learne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ghteousnesse.</hi> The wise and just will so doe, <hi>Who wait for God in the way of his judgements.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. opened.</note>
      <hi>They will prepare to meet God,</hi> and to prevent judgments, which othervvise are threatned, and seeme to make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them.<note place="margin">How wee may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Gods judgments.</note> Which they doe, or should doe by these meanes:</p>
   <p n="1">1. By <hi>taking warning <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> by</hi> judgements inflicted on others, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5, 6, 7-11. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3-5. The want whereof God takes spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall notice of, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
   <p n="2">2. By doing that in our <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
   </p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <p n="4">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. By seeking, and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the pardon of Sin,</hi> upon Repentance. Sinne once pardoned, is neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> more remembred or pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nished, <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.25. Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> so forgives, as hee als<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> forgets.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. By <hi>mortifying</hi> such sinnes as raigne in us, or a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Coloss</hi> 3.5. &amp;c. Seeing such ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>emplary judgements; a Pestilence, war, &amp;c. com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> not for smaller faylings but for sinnes against con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> grosser evils, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.5.6.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. <hi>By newnesse of life</hi> and <hi>by bringing forth fruit meet for repentance</hi>—so w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
escape wrath to come, and cutting downe, <hi>Math.</hi> 3.7. 8-10. By these meanes it will concerne you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet God; whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o you will find to meet you in mercy; as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Prodigall ran to meet his sonne, and to welcome him. <hi>Men have not heard—neither hath the eye seene, O God besides thee what hee hath prepared for him that waiteth for him: Thou meetest him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth and worketh righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, those that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thee in thy waies, Isa.</hi> 64.4, 5.</p>
   <p>Now because men are apt to make ill use of <hi>Gods</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
judgements on others, to mis-judge them, and to harden themselves in their security,<note place="margin">Four Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>usions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ut of <hi>Luke</hi> 13.4, 5. touching the use of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on others.</note> consider we what our Saviour teacheth us, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5- <hi>Think yee that these were Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners above all men that dwelt in Ierusalem? I tell you nay: but except yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, yee shall all likewise perish.</hi> Whence these <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions</hi> doe readily offer themselves.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Conclus. </seg>1</label> 1. <hi>Extraordinary, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth (yea and sudden) death doth sometime befall such as are not the greatest Sinners.</hi> I suppose those seventie thousand of <hi>Davids</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects who died by Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb facs="5"/>
among the other Tribes, were not greater Sinners than <hi>Ierusalem</hi> it selfe; <hi>Vpon which, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell stretched out his hand to destroy it.</hi> Yea, the good King vvould make these (in that case especially) more innocent than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, saying — <hi>Loe, I have sinned— but these Sheepe, what have they done?</hi> when God shewed his severitie against <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Israel,</hi> having removed them out of his sight; and when the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> onely was left and spared,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 18, 19. <hi>Eze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> 16.51, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> yet saith God to <hi>Iudah, —They are more righteous than thou.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. On the other hand it <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Conclus. </seg>2</label> is
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>in thee my power, and that my name may be declared in all the earth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>et.</hi> 2.9.</note>Howsoever, God <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves the unjust unto the day of judgement to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>s</hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> 31.</note> hee hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a day of purpose for them.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. God (in some cases) respects <hi>his owne Glorie,</hi> more then mens deserts, &amp; so spares them a while, though unworthie. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.26. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.8, 9-13, 14-21, 22.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Chiefly: God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members <hi>his covenant</hi> and promise, who will reserve to himselfe a Church on earth in the greatest defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb facs="6"/>
provocations and destructions of his people: he will,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.19, 20, 21</note> and doth ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve <hi>a remnant</hi> (who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise deserve ill at his hand, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.59, with 60.) See <hi>Isa.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. <hi>What if some did not believe? shall their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe make the faith of God of none effect?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Si quoties peccant ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mines, &amp;</note> If God in generall defections and judgements thereupon, should consume in his wrath, all that deserve it, where should hee have a Church on earth to serve him? hee must and will have some, in whom hee wil magnifie his mercie. <hi>It is of the Lords mercies</hi> (said
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the time of the captivitie, when so many had perished) <hi>that wee are not</hi> (all) <hi>consumed, because his compassions fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>le not.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>et.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Here is no merit to bee pleaded in such case.<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>om.</hi> 2.4.</note>
      <hi>Gods</hi> sparing mercies leade the way to his pardoning mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Hee often spares the unworthy, that they, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome with his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,<note place="margin">&amp; 9, 6.</note> might relent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, seeke and find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and that so his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and word might <hi>take effect</hi> in that <hi>remnant</hi> which is according <hi>to the Election of Grace.</hi>
      <note place="margin">&amp; 11.5.</note> Hence it is, that even among those in <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> on
<pb facs="7"/>
whom Gods irrevocable sentence of famine,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.19, 20, 21, 22.</note> noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some beasts, sword and pestilence had passed, yet a remnant was reserved, in whom God magnified his mercie, and for example of others. It were a happy thing, if such among us, as are either thus far spared, or have escaped, could see and make use of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. This hath been done by others, why not now by us?</p>
   <p>Wee reade concerning <hi>Waldus</hi> (from whom the <hi>VValdenses</hi> tooke their name)<note place="margin">Acts and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>um.</note> that making mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with many of his rich
<pb facs="8"/>
neighbours, one of the company, suddenly fell downe dead: whereupon, hee apprehending Gods displeasure, tooke war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, gave himselfe to Reading, Almes, Prayer; and exhorted others to the like.</p>
   <p>The like might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Gee,</hi> escaping in that deadly downefall of neere an hundred Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists in the Black-friers in <hi>London.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Conclus. </seg>3</label> 3. <hi>In case of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on others, and our owne sparing, wee are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rashly to censure them, nor hastily to justifie our
<pb facs="8"/>
selves as innocent. Christ</hi> himselfe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> because of his sufferings, was esteemed stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon despised.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Acts</hi> 28.4▪</note> So was <hi>Paul</hi> mis-judged, because of the Viper; And the blind man, in that hee was borne blind. But Christ, though hee forbid not a wise consideration of <hi>Gods</hi> judgement on Sinners, yet corrects such rash censures as men readily use, and prescribes an <hi>Order,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to begin at home, and not to secure our selves, knowing that God often <hi>judgeth some,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 32.</note>
      <hi>that they may
<pb facs="9"/>
not be condemned with the world.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18.</note>
      <hi>Iudgement</hi> usually <hi>begins at Gods owne house,</hi> that others thence may learn, not to justifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but rather, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, to expect like, or greater wrath.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Conclus. </seg>4</label> 4. Lastly, <hi>God warnes and cals all (carelesse Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) to repentance, by his corrections and judgements on some, or else hee so sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons them to like, or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wrath. Except yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, yee shall all likewise perish.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">1. <hi>Its a mercie when God makes others examples to us.</hi> The end of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="9"/>
and Historie, is to make us wise and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, lest wee bee made Examples and Histories to others. And among men, Executions are done for the living, not for the dead, who cannot be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by Example or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, as the living may be.</p>
   <p n="2">2. <hi>Certaine destruction will befall such as take no warning by others.</hi>
      <note place="margin">See <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.3-24.27.28. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 17.6.7.8-18.</note> God lookes wee should profit by the example of his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure, even on <hi>enemies,</hi> much more on friends, both <hi>Forefathers, Ierm.</hi> 7.12.13.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.20.21.
<pb facs="10"/>
22.23-30.31.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.9-12.13.</note> and <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and equals.</hi> Not to take warning by such (es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially after so many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warnings, wherein God is not wanting to any of us now) is a signe and fore-runner of speedy vengeance. So God look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Iudah</hi> should have taken warning by <hi>Israels</hi> captivity—but his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is—<hi>yet her treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous sister Iudah feared not,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.7.8.9.10.</note>
      <hi>but went and played the Harlot also:—and yet for all this her trecherous sister</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah <hi>hath not turned unto me with her whole heart, but fainedly.</hi> What hereupon
<pb facs="10"/>
followed?<note place="margin">
         <hi>King.</hi> 17.15.</note>
      <hi>Because Iudah (which tribe onely now was left) walked in the statutes of Israel which they made; Therefore saith God, I will cast you out of my sight,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 75.</note>
      <hi>as I have cast out all your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 <hi>King</hi> 21.13.</note>
      <hi>even the whole seed of Ephraim. And I will stretch over Ierusalem the line of Samaria, and the plummet of the house of Ahab.</hi> The like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of not profiting by others evils is made, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 9.20.21. and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.11.12. <hi>I haue overthrowne some of you, as God overthrew</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah, <hi>and yee were as
<pb facs="11"/>
a fire-brand pluckt out of the burning, yet haue ye not returned unto me, saith the Lord. Therefore thus will I doe unto thee:</hi> that is, even overthrow thee, as <hi>Sodom</hi> was overthrowne: Now this accordingly came to passe for not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king warning in time,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.</note> as <hi>Ieremy</hi> lamenting, doth bewaile. What then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, but as it followeth in <hi>Amos,</hi> and as wee haue already directed, that wee in time <hi>prepare to meet God.</hi> To which end, and for our further warning and wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, I referre you as to the example of Gods dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure,
<pb facs="11"/>
against this place of<note n="*" place="margin">From <hi>May</hi> 6. till <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb</hi> 31. 1636. there haue died of the plague within li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties 5027. without, some 500.</note> ours, so to the insuing treatise it selfe, now publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed as for our owne, so also chiefly for your spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall good, which is most heartily wished, and shall be still sought of God by him, who professeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe at this time the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of New-castles</hi> good meaning towards you, and</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, and the Churches ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, R. I.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>New-castle,</hi>
         <date>the 2. <hi>of</hi> Ianuary 1636.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>