<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE THOMAS
Lord Cromwell, Baron of Oukeham
in Rutland-shire, Vicount Lecall in the King∣dome
of Ireland, and one of his Maiesties Honourable
Priuie Councell in that Kingdome: and Colonell of a
Regiment of Foote vnder the most illustrious Prince
ERNESTVS Earle of Mansfield, W. C. wish∣eth
that happinesse which he himselfe
desireth.</title>
           <author>C., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107365_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4318</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107365</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE THOMAS
Lord Cromwell, Baron of Oukeham
in Rutland-shire, Vicount Lecall in the King∣dome
of Ireland, and one of his Maiesties Honourable
Priuie Councell in that Kingdome: and Colonell of a
Regiment of Foote vnder the most illustrious Prince
ERNESTVS Earle of Mansfield, W. C. wish∣eth
that happinesse which he himselfe
desireth.</title>
                 <author>C., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Dutch suruay : VVherein are related and truly discoursed, the chiefest losses and acquirements, which haue past betweene the Dutch and the Spaniards, in these last foure yeares warres of the Netherlands, with a comparatiue ballancing and estimation of that which the Spaniards haue got in the Dutchies of Cleeue and Iuliers, with that which they haue lost vnto the Dutch and Persians, in Brasilia, Lima, and Ormus. VVhereunto are annext the Mansfeldian motiues, directed vnto all colonels, lieuzanant-colonels, sergeant majors, priuate captaines, inferiour officers and souldiers, whose seruice is engag'd in this present expedition, vnder the conduct and commaund of the most illustrious Prince Ernestus, Earle of Mansfield</title>
                 <author>W. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE THOMAS
Lord Cromwell, Baron of Oukeham
in Rutland-shire, Vicount Lecall in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of Ireland, and one of his Maiesties Honourable
Priuie Councell in that Kingdome: and Colonell of a
Regiment of Foote vnder the most illustrious Prince
ERNESTVS Earle of Mansfield, W. C. wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
that happinesse which he himselfe
desireth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, I made bold
to consecrate vnto your most
iudicious censure, this Dutch
Suruay or ballance, which
if it proue waight in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance
of your estimation, and
appeare in the triall as free
from errour as it is from partiality, the Author
shall thinke his endeuours fortunate. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues
which inuited me to this Dedication, were
first of all your knowne zeale to equity and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;
<pb facs="3"/>
for the sacred priuiledges whereof, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlanders
haue fought most resolutely for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
yeares together to the wonder of their friends,
to the terrour and astonishment of their mortall
Enemies: So that if we shall admire the greatnes
of the <hi>Heluetian Cantons</hi> raised out of the ruines of
the house of <hi>Austria,</hi> or the fortune of the <hi>Venetian</hi>
Cōmon-wealth, erected out of the Reliques of the
Romane Empire declining in <hi>Italy,</hi> we may iustly
wonder at the swelling power of this Estate, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned
by God in this latter age, to checke the
greatnes of <hi>Castile,</hi> whose seuere and rigorous
dealing made them first to quit the yoake, and
vindicate their liberty from <hi>Philips</hi> tyrannie and
oppression. The next motiue which imboldned
me to this attempt, was your gracious promise
made vnto me by the mediation of a noble Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,
for farthering me with a place according
to my calling, in this new intended iourney:
which if I may enioy vnder your Honors fauour
and commaund, I hope that God will so assist
me with his grace, that the bent of my meane
endeuours shall wholy tend to the seruice of
God, my Country, and your Honoured selfe.
Vnto this discourse is added, besides a briefe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
vnto those, who are designed
for vndertakers in this expedition vnder Count
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Mansfield;</hi> the which I doe not, because I thinke
their resolutions to neede the spurre, for ours
commonly are so forward, that they neede the
bridle, but that those spirits who are either igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
or iealous of the motiues, may rectif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e their
mindes by the knowledge and consideration
of them. Thus desiring your Honours
fauourable acceptance, I leaue
and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most obliged Seruant. VV. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>