<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The preface vnto the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107328_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12492</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22820</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107328</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The preface vnto the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the blessed masse, and the sacrifice therof : prouynge that it is auayleable both for the quycke and the dead and that by Christes owne and his apostles ordynaunce, made [and] set forth by Rycharde Smyth doctour in diuinitie, and reader of ye kynges highnes lesson of diuinitie, in his maiesties vniuersitie of Oxforde. Wherin are dyuers doubtes opened, as it were by the waye, ouer and aboue the principall, and cheyfe matter</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Herford (Hereford, Hertford), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>clxxxx, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="ix" facs="13"/>
   <head>¶ The preface vnto the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy prophet Dauyd, good chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten reader, saithe that the truth of our lorde abideth for euer, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> albeit many and diuers men haue from tyme to tyme, euen frō the begynnynge of the churche, both spoken, &amp; wrytten also bokes againste it, yet they coulde neuer preuayle, but lost their laboures, &amp; got their confusion, and endlesse damnation. Wherfore though the {pro}phet Daniel doth say, <hi>Prosterne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur</hi>
      <note place="margin">Danie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>veritas in terra.</hi> The truth shal be troden vnder the feete on the earth, yet y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> is not ment that al the people of god shulde treede it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their fete, &amp; dispise it, but that
<pb facs="14"/> in the tyme of Antichriste, fygured by Antiochus, of whome the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet sawe a vy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>on, as in the eyght chapiter of Daniel it apereth: the continuall sacrifice, that is the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the masse, as I wyll by gods grace hereafter proue, shold be abolished and put away, for the space of thre yeres and the halfe, (how longe Antichrist shal reigne) Daniell in the twelfte chaptre te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifienge the same. Of the whiche place, and other mo lyke, written <note place="margin">Luther is an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichristes mes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sanger, to make all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye agaynste his cōminge which firste of all men spake agenst the sacrifice of the holye masse. except one Peter de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bruis.</note> by Daniel, we maye well gather, that Antichristes tyme approcheth and draweth very nie, for as much as Marten Luther, and his folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, do trauaile so earnestly (but yet all in vayne) to take awaye the holye sacrifice of the blessed masse, whiche all chrysten nations from the fyrst institution thereof, made by chryste oure sauioure at hys
<pb n="x" facs="14"/> laste supper, euen tyl our tyme, the space of a thousand and fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeres, was euer beleued, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and receaued, for a sacrifice auayleable, and profitable bothe for the quicke and the dead, which thinge shall be openly, and plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousely declared, god wyllyng, here after in this booke, not only by the scripture, but also by general coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celles, and the expositions of the el<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dest, and best learned doctours, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarynge the said scripture, so that no man, which listeth not to winke at the lyght of the truth, nor is not maried to his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne opinion, shall haue any excuse to laye for his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, throughe want, and lacke of knowlage of the truth. Therefore reade this booke without al affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diligētly, not regardyng who made it, nor againste whome it is made, but what matter it doth cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne,
<pb facs="15"/> be it neuer so rudely, &amp; gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set fourth, for the easyer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge of it. Folowe the wyse mans counsaile, sayeng. <hi>Non con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tradicas</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccle. 4.</note>
      <hi>verbo veritatis.</hi> Say not against the worde of truth, for yf thou do, thou shalt laboure all in vaine, and gaine therby the wrath of god, and his indignation, with payne euer to endure, in hell, with the deuyll, which stode not in the truthe, as Christe dothe affirme. <note place="margin">Ioā. 8.</note> This saith Paule writyng to the Romaynes after this sort. <hi>Iis autē</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note>
      <hi>qui sunt ex cōtentione, &amp; qui non acquiescunt veritati, credunt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem iniquitati, ira &amp; indignatio.</hi> To them the wrath, and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of god shall come, whiche are geuen to contention, or strife, and do not quietly obeye the truth, but beleue the wronge or falsitie. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this our sauiour christes <note place="margin">Math. 16</note>
      <pb n="xi" facs="15"/> sayeng, What shal it auaile man, if he wynne the whole worlde and thereby lose his soule? What es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge <note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> shall a man make for his soule? If thou hast therfore erred with Peter, receauynge false doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, defēding it, and persecuting the teachers, and mayntainers of the truth, be not ashamed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake thyne errour, and againe to embrace the truth. Paule persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the truth, but he forsoke his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour when god called him. Saint Austen erred, but he retourned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to the truth, and vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recanted his errour. Thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other haue done, whiche hadde gone from the truth, whan it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed god of his greate mercy to call them, &amp; to gyue them the spirite of truth, for the exilyng the spirite of errour. I maye well saye to them, that folow Martyn Luthers wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <note place="margin">Luther.</note>
      <pb facs="16"/> errours, and damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, and namely that, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste the sacrifice of the holye masse (neuer improued before his daies) as saynt Paule saide to the Galathians, greatly wonderinge <note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> at their blyndnes. <hi>Quis vos fasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauit non obedire veritati?</hi> Who hathe bewytched you not to obeye the truth? As though he had sayd, ye haue had the truth so plainlye, and perfectly taught you, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte ye were witched, ye could not so erre, as ye now do, forsaking the same. If saynt Paule dyd iustlye iudge the Galathians witched, because they had forsakē the truth of the gospell, (which they learned not longe before) throughe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticement, prouocation, and persua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion of false teachers, that then did preache to them, howe moche more iustlye maye a man saye to them
<pb n="xii" facs="16"/> whiche are shamefullye deceaued, and blynded by Martyn Luthers fond, folyshe, and deuellysshe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne? <hi>Quis vos fascinauit verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti non obedire?</hi> Who hath witched yow, not to obeye the truth? hath-Marten luther deceaued, and wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched you? Hath he blynded you, that ye can not se the truth, which heretofore, sence Christes byrth, no man attēpted to do in this matter of the masse? Hath he deceaued you <note place="margin">Excepte one Peter de br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s which was in saynt Ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>des time.</note> whiche is the autoure, maintenar, and defender of many, and sondry plaine heresies? Hath he witched you not to obeye the truth, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the sacrifice of the blessed masse, whiche so setteth forth, and auaunceth only fayth, that he stic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Only f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yth.</note> not to saye, and defende, that only through faith god forgeueth mannes synnes, nothing helpyng therunto his penaunce, feare, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,
<pb facs="17"/> praier, forgiuinge his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors <note place="margin">George Ioyes opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> trespaces, nor any like thing, yea that only fayth shuld saue mā, though he lyued neuer so yll? And because saint Iames in his epistle doth playnly condemne, &amp; reproue that his deuyllysh opinion, and saynt Ihons Apocalypsis also dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proueth the same erroure, he was not ashamed to denye them both, affirmynge that these bookes are not scripture, nor wrytten by Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and Ihon the apostle. Is not this a blynde doctour? Is not he worthye to haue credence geuen to hym, in matters of our faithe, whiche doth not feare to deny the holye scripture, for the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of a fonde, and a wicked heresye, against the scripture, the hole churche of christendome, and all wryters, that truly write vpon the scripture, euen from christes
<pb n="xiii" facs="17"/> tyme, to these our dayes? What man, or woman, is so madde, to be <note place="margin">Luther deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mās f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e wyll, whiche dyd Symon Magus (as S. Clement testifiethe) that was the fyist heretik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> after christe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> byrth.</note> leue him which denieth the fre wyl of man, and ascribeth both synne and vertue onlye to necessitie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>othinge to man, as Luther doth, sayeng that we can not chose but synne when we do synne, nor chose but we must neades do well, when we do any good dede? Is not this a great blyndnes? What can be more against reason, and goddes holye worde? What doctryne can he more pestilent, and noysome to good lyuyng? For if this doctrine were true, as it is moost false, we shoulde neade no lawe of man, nor of god, no preachyng, no teaching, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o good counsaile, nor any sembla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le, or lyke helpe to lyue the better with all. Martyn Luther also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eth <note place="margin">Luther say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that god doth gyue no grace by the sacramētes.</note> that god geueth any grace man thorow the blessed sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.
<pb facs="18"/> Is not this man worthy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to be beleued of vs christē people<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> He teachethe that a christen ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> shuld not warre agaynst the Tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. Is not this holsome doctrine &amp; godlye: yea is it not rather met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for a Turke thus to write, then▪ christen man? Beware therefore good christen reader, of his pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and contagious doctrine.</p>
   <p>Reade not his bookes, nor none o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Heresye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes shold not be redde.</note> his disciples makynge. They a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> full of poyson, althoughe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> seme neuer so good, and frutefull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as commōly doth all heresy, at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> firste taste and syght. The kynge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> maiesty, lyke a most christē princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hath put fourth a proclamation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> late, straightly chargynge, and cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundinge, that no man, or wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man do kepe after the last daye o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> August next insuinge any boke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Englysh, that conteyneth in it an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="xiiii" facs="18"/> yll, and hurtefull doctrine.</p>
   <p>This godlye commaundemente ought to be obeyed of vs, not only for feare of temporall, and bodilye punishmente, but to eschewe also gods displeasure and wrath, whose ministre he is, and by whome he <note place="margin">Prouer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eygneth, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scripture affirmeth. If thou hast ben deceaued by Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Ro. 13.</note> this blynde teacher, retourne againe to the truth, with a peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hart. Folow this holy Tobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <note place="margin">Tobie. 14.</note> counsaile. Serue the lorde in dread, and truth. Bye the truthe, &amp; sell it not againe, as Salamon <note place="margin">Prouer. 23.</note> doth coūsaile the. Instauntly pray with the holy prophette Dauyd, <note place="margin">Psal. 118.</note> saienge. <hi>Ne auferas de ore meo verbum veritatis.</hi> Let not o lorde, the worde of the truthe, be taken from my mouth. Abyde in christe by loue and charite, and kepe his commaundemētes, and then thou
<pb facs="19"/> shalt knowe the truth (as our saui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our saith) and the truth shall make <note place="margin">Ioā. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the fre, from al errour, ignoraunce synne, and wretchednes, and bring the to the endles ioyes of heauen, the which Christ the truth, dyeng for the truthes sake, bought moste dearly, with the sheddynge of his precious bloude, for his faythfull seruauntes, to whome with his father, and the holy gooste, be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and honour for euer. Amen.</p>
   <p>Take in good worthe this my laboure, gentle reader, thoughe in all poyntes the treatyce shall not lyke the, and no maruayle, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was made in haste within the space of a monethe, whan I myght steale an houre from my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther busines of studye.</p>
   <p>At London, the yere of our lorde. M. D. xlvi. The xx. day of Iulye.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>