<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Welton in prayse of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107043_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2497</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107043</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Welton in prayse of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Psalmes of Dauid in meter : the plaine song beeing the common tunne to be sung and plaide vpon the lute, orpharyon, citterne or base violl, seuerally or altogether, the singing part to be either tenor or treble to the instrument, according to the nature of the voyce, or for foure voyces: with tenne short tunnes in the end, to which for the most part all the Psalmes may be vsually sung, for the vse of such as are of mean skill, and whose leysure least serueth to practise: by Richard Allison Gent. practitioner in the art of musicke: and are to be sold at his house in the Dukes place neere Alde-gate</title>
                 <author>Alison, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Barley (Barlow), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Alison  (Allison), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Morley, Thomas, Assignee (with assent, etc.) of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>150 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>Iohn Welton in prayse of <hi>the Author.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>DIuine <hi>Apollo</hi> God of heauenly Muses</l>
      <l>The Garden walkes for his repast frequenting,</l>
      <l>In Allies-son bright shining there he vses,</l>
      <l>Oft to attend the gracious Nymphes presenting</l>
      <l>Psalmes of all sorts, with instruments and voyces,</l>
      <l>Of sundry aires and sundry are their choyses.</l>
      <l>In those faire walks they vse the exercises</l>
      <l>Of Psalmes and Hymnes and spirituall songs deuining▪</l>
      <l>Perfuming aire with their swete sacrifices</l>
      <l>From earth to heauen by sacred meane inclining.</l>
      <l>Long may they haunt those pathes with sacred blissing▪</l>
      <l>To charme the noise of venemous vipers hissing.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>