<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND POTENT MONARCH, IAMES</title>
           <author>Casaubon, Meric</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107684_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18107</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4751</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107684</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND POTENT MONARCH, IAMES</title>
                 <author>Casaubon, Meric</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vindication or defence of Isaac Casaubon : against those impostors that lately published an impious and vnlearned pamphlet, intituled The originall of idolatries, &amp;c. vnder his name, by Meric Casaubon his sonne. Published by his Maiesties command</title>
                 <author>Casaubon, Meric</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Bonham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 75, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND POTENT MONARCH, IAMES</head>
   <head type="sub">By the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>Most gracious Souereigne,</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which I haue here in a few dayes writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for the <hi>Defence</hi> of my <hi>Father,</hi> I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue proceeded from your Maiesty, as the first Author of it; who beeing so highly offended at the iniury which <hi>Casaubon's</hi> name
<pb facs="3"/>
receiued, that by your Royall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie the deceitfull plotters of it were duely punished, I thought it would be some reproach to mee, if a <hi>Sonne</hi> should conferre nothing to the pious vindicating of his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And yet it is not so much the defence of <hi>him,</hi> that I haue here vndertaken, as the vindicating of the <hi>Truth</hi> it selfe, which your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y hath so much disdained, though in a good cause, to haue beene so ill handled by a furious and inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate writer. Our Aduersaries shall be more indifferent to you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if your Royall Maiestie be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with the forgeries which they bring to maintaine a bad cause, when <hi>You</hi> are so much offended with the falshoods that are brought
<pb facs="3"/>
against them by others, that would otherwise seeme to haue vndertaken the defence of a good cause. And though such may please themselues with their owne fancies, whom any thing wil please that maketh for the vpholding of such a Religion as they professe; yet it was most proper for your Sacred Maiestie (whose Learning and Loue of purer Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on are of equall eminencie) both to detect, and to shew your Royall indignatiō against these Impostors, that were cloaked ouer with so faire an appearance. Surely happy is our Cause, that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uch a Defender! For who can now doubt of the Truth of that doctrine, which must haue nothing to defend it, but the Armes of Truth it selfe? Where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore
<pb facs="4"/>
I present vnto your Maiestie, with all humility, that which I haue here written for the Truth, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly because <hi>You</hi> were so graciously pleased to accept it before it came to publike view, but chiefly that I might oppose the Authoritie both of <hi>Your</hi> Sacred Power and exquisite iudgement against those Impostors, that durst presume to offer a false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intituled Pamphlet to the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of our most Noble and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Prince. God long preserue your Maiesty, the greatest of Kings, to flourish with all kind of happines, for these your Kingdomes, and his Churches benefit.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble Seruant and Subiect,
MERIC CASAVBON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>