<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipful Sir Robert Ier∣myn, Knight, and to the right worshipful his godly and vertuous wife, the Lady Iudith Iermyn, Thomas Stocker wisheth continuall increase of all spirituall and earthly good thinges in this life, with an earnest zeale to the glorious Gospell of Christe Iesus, and perseueraunce of practise thereof vnto the ende and in the end, and after this life▪ euerlasting ioy and blisse in the life to come through the same Christ Iesus our Lorde.</title>
           <author>Stocker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107289_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17724</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4460</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107289</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipful Sir Robert Ier∣myn, Knight, and to the right worshipful his godly and vertuous wife, the Lady Iudith Iermyn, Thomas Stocker wisheth continuall increase of all spirituall and earthly good thinges in this life, with an earnest zeale to the glorious Gospell of Christe Iesus, and perseueraunce of practise thereof vnto the ende and in the end, and after this life▪ euerlasting ioy and blisse in the life to come through the same Christ Iesus our Lorde.</title>
                 <author>Stocker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two and twentie sermons of Maister Iohn Caluin : In which sermons is most religiously handled, the hundredth and nineteenth Psalme of Dauid, by eight verses aparte according to the Hebrewe alphabet. Translated out of French into Englishe by T.S</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <distributor>Harrison, John 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 190 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipful Sir Robert Ier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myn, <hi>Knight, and to the right worshipful his godly</hi> and vertuous wife, the Lady <hi>Iudith Iermyn, Thomas Stocker</hi> wisheth continuall increase of all spirituall and earthly good <hi>thinges in this life, with an earnest zeale to the</hi> glorious Gospell of Christe Iesus, and perseueraunce of <hi>practise thereof vnto the ende and in the</hi> end, and after this life▪ euerlasting ioy and blisse in the life to come through the same Christ Iesus our Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vniuersally (Right Worshipfull) is as it were a diuine Maistresse, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bothe vertue and true faith: yet notwithstanding the Booke of Psalmes hath ouer and besides that in a manner an expresse image of the state and condition of soules, and therfore ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry necessary for all people in generall. Howbeit this hundreth and ninteene Psalme, namely contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a perfect art and a woonderfull vehemencie of the Kingly Prophet, in setting foorth and highly extolling the prayse of Gods lawe and the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy thereof: wherein hee cannot satisfie himselfe, nor yet sufficiently expresse the affection which he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth thereunto, adding moreouermany notable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes and consolations, wherfore it is most meete
<pb facs="3"/>for all the children of God to haue it alwayes bothe in their heartes and mouthes, and so continually me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating thereon as this holy Prophet did in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, they may also finde the like comfort, whenso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer and whatsoeuer affliction shall assaile them, and also to flie and abhorre that which is wicked and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in the sight of the Lord.</p>
   <p>Which Psalme beeing deuided into twoo and twentie partes, by eight verses aparte, according too the Hebrew Alphabet, the godly and learned Father and moste famouse furtherer of the glorious Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of our Sauiour and Redeemer Christe, hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that order, very religiously handled and drawne into as many Sermons, too the benefite and comfort of all the true and faithfull Scholers in the Schoole of God, which shall diligently reade them, and earnnestly striue to followe the same direction in their life and conuersation.</p>
   <p>Which Sermons according to my poore skill, I haue englished frō the French, and haue taken bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to dedicate and offer this my simple trauell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Worships, as a speciall token of my good will in Christ: beseeching you to accept of this my labor, not according to the rude translation, but the goodnesse of the matter which they propound, and my heartie affection vnto you. And the rather haue I beene enbo dened this to doe: both for that I haue beene crediblly informed off, either of your greate paines taking in reading ouer such like godly works as also that my selfe am <hi>Testis oculatus,</hi> of your dayly presence and diligent attention at all Sermons and godly exercises vsed in this countrie of Stuff. Whose good &amp; godly beginnings with the rest of the right
<pb facs="3"/>worshipfull both men and women in these partes (and all others of what state and condition so euer they be) I heartely beseech our good God and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful father, euen for his Christ, his trueth, &amp; mercyes sake, to increase, strengthen, and continue witth day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly practise of the same, in some measure in your liues and conuersation, with full perseueraunce vntoo the end of your dayes here, without which all the rest is but labor lost. For as the Apostle witnesseth, we are made partakers of Christ, if wee keepe sure vnto the ende that beginning wherewith we are vpholden.</p>
   <p>The Lord God therefore by his holy spirit work these effects in you and in vs all that professe his gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and leade our aduersaryes (when it shall please him) into the trueth, as he is God of trueth: that whē his sonne Christ our Sauiour shall appeere in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wee may be founde to haue walked without halting in whatsoeuer hee hath thought meete to open to vs for our saluation, From Mildenhall the 4. of Nouember. l579.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships to command</hi> in the Lorde <hi>Tho. Stocker.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>