<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Lupton to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107904_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72470</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14724a.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Lupton to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bathes of Bathes ayde : wonderfull and most excellent, agaynst very many sicknesses, approued by authoritie, confirmed by reason, and dayly tryed by experience: vvith the antiquitie, commoditie, propertie, knovvledge, vse, aphorismes, diet, medicine, and other thinges therto be considered and obserued. Compendiously compiled by Iohn Iones phisition. Anno salutis. 1572. At Asple Hall besydes Notting [h] am</title>
                 <author>Jones, John, physician</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 35, that is 34, 4 leaves, 2 folded tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>Thomas Lupton to the Reader.</head>
   <l>JF such are worthy of reproche that neuer cease to toyle,</l>
   <l>For priuate gayne, their country men therby to hurt or spoyle,</l>
   <l>Then they deserue great prayse and fame, whose study watch &amp; payn</l>
   <l>Do profet them they neuer knew, wyth dayly welth &amp; gayne,</l>
   <l>And if the greater common good, the greater prayse doth craue,</l>
   <l>Then they that publeck welth procures, deserues the more to haue.</l>
   <l>For though wyth many worldly welth, is chiefly now preferd,</l>
   <l>Yet syck and lame and yrcksome soore do health much more regard.</l>
   <l>For who, though he haue Cresus welth in sicknes can be glad,</l>
   <l>Wher health is not, though welth be there, what Ioy can ther be had.</l>
   <l>Yet doth the poore and healthfull wretch oftymes reioyse we see,</l>
   <l>But if that sicknes dwell with welth, then myrth from thens doth slee.</l>
   <l>If this be trew, then Iones deserues both double prayse and fame,</l>
   <l>That tooke such payns for comom helth, this Ayde of Baths to frame.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>