<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107302_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18925</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107302</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlye, and pithie exhortation, made to the iudges and iustices of Sussex, and the whole countie, assembled togither, at the generall assises. By William Ouerton, Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of the Queenes Maiesties iustices appoynted for the peace vvithin the same countie</title>
                 <author>Overton, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60+ pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing occasion the laste Lente to be at Estgreene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stedde, it was my chance (gentle Reader) to heare a very learned and frutefull Sermon, made the same present time before the whole assembly of the Sheere. I tooke suche profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of it my selfe by hearing it, and heard it so generally commended of others, that I could not but deuise how to make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to many, that which was there vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but to fewe, that so the benefite of it might redound also to many. I maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes haue blame of the Authour to put it foorth in printe without his knowledge and consent, but if he knewe howe muche good he did to those fewe that heard him, I trust he will not be offended, if by my meanes he doe more good to a greate number that hearde him not, but shall reade him, for the exhortation is so tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered,
<pb facs="3"/>and the conueyance of it in suche sorte, that though ye can specially applye it but to some men, yet ye maye vse it so generally, that it wyll edifye any man. If all therefore shall reade it, it wyll pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite all, bycause it hathe matter that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for all. But if those reade it that are Iudges of circuites, and Iustices of the peace, or Iurie men, or suche other like, that haue anye calling that way, it will profyte suche men most, bycause to suche it most apperteyneth. And surely, I wysh aboue all other, that Iudges, and Iustices, and whosoeuer they be else, that vse to giue charge to the people, yea, and those also that haue the charge gyuen them, shoulde alwayes before they goe aboute such businesse, reade ouer and peruse thys little peece of worke, that thereby they myghte be stirred vp to deale more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly in Gods causes, and in matters of Religion, than commonlye they are wont to do, I doubt not, but like good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect would follow such reading of it, as did
<pb facs="3"/>then followe the hearing of it. For thys I sawe, and hearde my selfe the same tyme, when the Iudges were come from the Churche to the Hall, and were nowe sette downe, and the Countrey before them, they did not onely imparte to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude what great fruite and comforte they had receyued themselues by hearing that Sermon (giuing it a singular commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the eares of all men, euen from the benche where they sate) but also then tooke occasion thereby, to gyue a verye quicke, and vehemente charge to the graunde Iurie, yea, and to the Iustices themselues, and to all others that had anye office or authoritie in the Sheere, to looke more narrowly to matters of Religion, than heeretofore they had done, and to endeauoure themselues by all meanes possible, to conserue the peace and vnitie of Christes Church, and to search out, and see punished all that were offenders to the contrary. And to tell you the truth, it did my heart good to see so graue &amp; wise a
<pb facs="4"/>mā (Iudge GAVDIE by name) to giue so carnest and godly a charge, in God and the Gospels behalfe, such good frute followed in that good Magistrate, by hearing so good and godly a Preacher that day. And I would all others that be of the same cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that he is of, mighte haue as good ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heereafter to reade him, as he hadde then to heare hym, that like fruite maye come of it, when oportunitie shal serue, for the fruite that followed was great. Well, I will not cōmend the Preacher vnto thee, (I shoulde but darken his due prayses by mine vnsufficient praysing of him) but I wil cōmend thee to the reading of this his worke, and when thou hast redde it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him thy selfe as thou seest cause. In the meane time, I wil pray vnto God both for him and for thee, and for vs al: for him, to encrease his talēt in preaching: for thee, to enslame thy zeale in hearing: for vs all, to amende oure negligence in following. And so I bidde thee farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy vvelbeloued brother in Christ.
<hi>M. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>