<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Covell, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107556_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17985</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4644</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107556</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Covell, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tithes examined and proued to bee due to the clergie by a diuine right : VVhereby the contentious and prophane atheists, as also the dissembling hypocrites of this age, may learne to honour the ministers and not to defraude them, and to rob the Church. The contents heereof is set downe in the page next following. Written by George Carleton Batchelour in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Carleton, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 39, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing wee are fallen into these last times, times dangerous and filled with much euill, wherein the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of pietie doe dayly decrease, and the Church her selfe euen with that small portion which shee hath left, is become an vsuall praie, either to the prophane Atheist, that will violently rob her, or to the cunning hippocrite that vnder pretence of long prayers will deuoure Gods house: I thought it fit to recommend this learned trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise to the indifferent reader, that men of place in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, indued with knowledge to support the truth, may make a conscience to assist the clergie for obtaining their owne right, least vnder coulour of some vaine title or pretense of custome, the Lord himselfe complaine both against them and vs, that his house is a house of prayer, and we haue made it a den of theeues. Our land, I confesse, is faire and blessed like the kingdome of Canaan, but many of the people are like the Anakims, that eate vp the clergie thereof: and though <hi>Iosias</hi> were a good king, yet the times were euill, and a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment <note place="margin">Numb. 13. 33.</note> of the former sinnes reserued in Gods iustice to the <note place="margin">2. King. 22. 20.</note> dayes that followed. And howsoeuer wee cannot with <hi>Iosua</hi>
      <note place="margin">Spelunca la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronum. Ios. 10. 23.</note> finde kings in this caue, yet I feare mee, wee may fetch out more then fiue times fiue of our great families made richer by the spoiles of the Church, who haue either come in dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blingly like <hi>Icroboams</hi> wife, or boldly like <hi>Pharo</hi> to the Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, <note place="margin">1. Kings. 14.</note> saying of the clergie, <hi>this people is stronger then we are, come let vs work wisely with them, least they multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. 1. 9. 10.</note>
      <pb facs="4"/>
and without a witnesse, the leprosie of <hi>Gehezie</hi> stic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth so fast vnto their families, as many of our most auncient houses, I am perswaded, haue beene ruinated by this meanes, for the Church liuing dealeth as the Arck with <hi>Dagon,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.</note> casteth that downe which they had of their owne. If some of them delt but as <hi>Dauid</hi> with <hi>Saul,</hi> cut off the lap of our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it were well (yet I would wish them to haue remorse <note place="margin">1. Sam 24. 5.</note> for it) but to vse the Clergie as the king of the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> did the messengers of <hi>Dauid</hi> (who shaued of halfe <note place="margin">2. Sam. 10. 4.</note> of their beards, &amp; cut off their garments in the middle) it is a contempt which the Lord wil not suffer to escape vnpunished.</p>
   <p>Now I doubt not but the diligent perusing of this treatise shall so perswade the consciences of all that are not alreadie forestalled by some great sinnes, <hi>that tithes are the Lords</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 50.</note>
      <hi>portion, holy to himselfe, that this portion he hath giuen to his ministers that serue at the Altar,</hi> and so consequently that they may not safely detaine that from the Clergy which belongs vnto them, but rather make restitution with al humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and desire the Lord with penitent harts to receiue at our hands the tenth part, which in a peculiar manner holily is his owne portion (for by another right, <hi>the cattell are his,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 50.</note> that are on a thousand hils) that so in mercy hee may blesse vnto vs, the nine parts that remaine of all our substance, this fruit if it shall bring vnto thee that readest, and rest and peace to the poore Clergy, that are torne with contentions for their owne right, wee shall haue iust cause to reioyce for thy good, and be ready to recommend our further paines to tho blessing of thy prayers, and the benefit of this Church.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Lambeth. <date>Ianu. 4. 1606.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>WILLIAM COVELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>