<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, Richard, by Diuine pro∣uidence, Lord Bishop of Durham, my very honourable good LORD, and Diocesan.</title>
           <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107447_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04166</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14306</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107447</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, Richard, by Diuine pro∣uidence, Lord Bishop of Durham, my very honourable good LORD, and Diocesan.</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs ansvver vnto Iohns question: or, An introduction to the knowledge of Iesus Christ, and him crucified : Deliuered in certaine sermons in the famous towne of New-castle vpon Tine. By Thomas Iackson, Dr. of Diuinitie, vicar of Saint Nicolas Church there, and fellow of Corpus Christi Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 207, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, <hi>Richard,</hi> by Diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, Lord Bishop of <hi>Durham,</hi> my very honourable good LORD, and <hi>Diocesan.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Reuerend <hi>and</hi> Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing here detayned, vpon occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made knowne in part vnto your Lordship, I thought my selfe bound in duety and conscience to render an account, as well of my time spent in this my absence, as whilest I was present at my charge. Though this I cannot for this time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, saue onely in part. These papers which I now consecrate to your Honours protection containe onely the first-fruits of my Labours in that worthy and famous Congregation, which it pleased your Lordship about a yeere
<pb facs="3"/>
agoe, (for which I euer rest yours bounden) to commit vnto my trust. Yet these being all that I took with me to peruse in my absence, which I well hoped should haue beene much shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, these are all that I could at this time present your Lordship withal, humbly beseeching they may bee accepted as an vndoubted pledge of my duty and obseruance to your Lordship, and of my vnfaigned desire and resolution to set forward that worthy and religious Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (from which I haue receiued much true comfort and many kindnesses) in the wayes of truth, as well by my pen in my absence, as by my voyce whilest I am present. So, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending this <hi>Introduction</hi> to your Lorshippes patronage, and your Lordship to the gracious patronage and protection of the Lord Iesus, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Study in Corpus Christi Colledge in Oxon.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20. 1624.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships, in all duety and seruice,
THOM. IACKSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>