<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREPARATION AND INTRODVCTION TO THE HISTORY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107372_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17808</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4497</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107372</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREPARATION AND INTRODVCTION TO THE HISTORY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Annales : the true and royall history of the famous empresse Elizabeth Queene of England France and Ireland &amp;c. True faith's defendresse of diuine renowne and happy memory. Wherein all such memorable things as happened during hir blessed raigne, with such acts and treaties a past betwixt hir Matie. and Scotland, France, Spaine, Italy, Germany, Poland, Sweden, Denmark, Russia, and the Netherlands, are exactly described</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96, 435, 5, 232, 251-292, 2 pages, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <head>A PREPARATION AND INTRODVCTION TO THE HISTORY.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE All-glorious,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Qu. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by the Fathers side.</hi>
      </note>

 All-vertuous, incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, inuict, and match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Patterne of Princes, the Glory, Honour, and mirror of Woman kind, the Admiration of our Age, ELIZABETH, Queene of <hi>England,</hi> was by the Fathers side truely Royall, being Daughter to HENRY the Eighth, Grand-child to HENRY the Seuenth, and great Grand child to EDVVARD the Fourth: of the Mothers side indeed vnequall,
<pb facs="20"/>
yet nobly descended, and had many great Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces spred through <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Her great-Grandfather was <hi>Iefferay</hi> of <hi>Bolene,</hi> descended from the famous House of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> who, in the yeere 1457. was Maior of <hi>London,</hi> and was then graced with the Dignitie of Knighthood: a man of much integrity, and of such reputation, that <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> Baron of <hi>Hoo</hi> and <hi>Hastings,</hi> Knight of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of S. <hi>George,</hi> gaue him his daughter and heire to wife: he was of so great meanes, that he marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Daughters into the famous houses of the <hi>Chenies, Heidons,</hi> and <hi>Fortescues</hi>: he left a great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie to his sonnes; and by Will gaue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds sterling to the poore of <hi>London,</hi> and two hundred to the poore of <hi>Norfolke</hi>: Hee had to Sonne, <hi>William Bolene,</hi> who was made one of the eighteene selected Knights of the <hi>Bath,</hi> at the inauguration of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third. To whom, <hi>Tho.</hi> Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> (who was had in so great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimation with the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> that hee only of all the Peeres of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had place and voice in the Parliament, and before the Barons of <hi>England</hi>) gaue him his Daughter and Coheire to wife; he had by her (besides the Daughters which he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Shelton, Caltrop, Chaire,</hi> and <hi>Sackuil,</hi> beeing very rich, and of renowned Race) <hi>Tho. Bolene,</hi> who beeing but a Youth, <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> then Earle of <hi>Surrey,</hi> and afterwards Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> a famous
<pb facs="20"/>
Warrier, chose him to bee his Sonne in Lawe, and gaue him his Daughter <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to wife. HENRY the Eighth employed him in two honourable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassies, after hauing made him Treasurour of his House, Knight of the Order of Saint <hi>George,</hi> and Vicount <hi>Rochford,</hi> afterwards Earle of <hi>Wilton</hi> and <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Lord Priuie Seale. He,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The birth of the Lady Anne Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene.</hi>
      </note>

 amongst other Children, had <hi>Anne Bolene,</hi> who beeing sent in her tender yeeres into <hi>France,</hi> was seruant to <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Wife to <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12. afterwards to <hi>Claudia</hi> of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> wife to <hi>Francis</hi> the First; and after her death, to <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Alanson,</hi> who from her cradle, was a speciall fauourour of the Protestants Religion in <hi>France.</hi> Afterwards, she being retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>England,</hi> and entertained to be one of the Queenes Maids of Honour, in the twentieth yeere of her age, King HENRIE being eight and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, fell vehemently in loue with her, for the modest behauiour which accompanyed her beauty, and the <hi>French</hi> iollity which seasoned her modesty: but not being able to ouercome her chastity, he sought to haue her to wife, in hope to haue a Linage by her.</p>
   <p>Now before, (to take this matter a little more deepely) after he had liued seuenteene yeeres with <hi>Katherine</hi> his wife, who was of a pious conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of the <hi>Spanish</hi> grauitie, but subiect to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borsements, that of all her Children, shee brought
<pb facs="21"/>
foorth none liuing, but MARIE, he begunne to distaste her, by the cunning practice of Cardinall <hi>Wolsey,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The King fals in loue with Anne of Bolone.</hi>
      </note>

 who was then raised to the highest degree of power and authority about the King, but in some fort ouer swayed by his owne affections: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing displeased with <hi>Charles,</hi> the fifth Emperour, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to <hi>Katherine,</hi> because he had denyed him the Arch-bishopricke of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and then aspiring to the Papasie, his hatred to him, and his loue so affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately carried toward the <hi>French</hi> King; he so wrought, that he purposed a wife for <hi>Henry</hi> out of <hi>France.</hi> The King beeing prone to his pleasures, prepared this scruple of conscience,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The reason why he puts away his wife.</hi>
      </note>

 That the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age which he had contracted with <hi>Katherine,</hi> who before had beene wife to his brother <hi>Arthur,</hi> was forbidden by the Diuine Lawe, although Pope <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the second had giuen a Dispensation for it. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he did inculcate into the Kings eares, how greatly he had offended God in marrying <hi>Katherine,</hi> and how grieuous a sin he should wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in if hee kept her: that hee had incurred the Sentence of Excommunication; that God had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his wrath vpon so vnlawfull a Marriage, not suffering a Male to liue, that was begotten of her, and that if there were not a lawfull Heire assigned to the Kingdome, no other thing was to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but that those mortall and cruell wars which had beene but lately lul'd asleepe, should be awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="21"/>
with new slaughters of his people; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he ought, for the taking away of all scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from his conscience, to repudiate her, and that by assuring himselfe of a Successor in a lawfull line, he should prouide for the safety of his soule (which and likewise yeeres had been polluted with incest) for so many of his Kingdome.</p>
   <p>These reasons caused the King to entreate Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Seuenth, to depute some to take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedge of this cause, and either to confirme the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation by authority of holy Scriptures, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue him of the Sentence of Excommunication, and to declare this marriage to be of no force, and that it might be lawfull for him to marry any other woman whom he should thinke fit, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Canon to the contrary. Hereupon the Pope delegates Cardinall <hi>Wolsey,</hi> and the Cardinall of <hi>Campepe,</hi> to whom he secretly gaue a Bull to this effect, that he approued of the Kings vowes, and granted his requests so farre as God would giue him leaue, if the marriage which he had contracted with <hi>Katherine</hi> should be found vnlawfull, and so declared to be. But this Bull was to bee conceal'd or publisht according to the successe of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Affaires in <hi>Italy.</hi> Then these questions begun to be moued euery where, whether it were lawfull for a man to take his brothers wife? or, it beeing prohibited by the Diuine Law, whether the Popes
<pb facs="22"/>
Dispensation could make it lawfull, or no? And when many Academies of Christendome, and the most learned men had giuen their opinions, and resolued that such a Marriage was repugnant to the Laws both of the Old and New Testament, howsoeuer the Popes Dispensation might legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate it. The King became more passionatly amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of the Lady <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Bolene</hi> then euer, and the Cardinall (repenting himselfe too late of what hee had begun) grew discontented, and wrought so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hand,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The King entreats the Pope for expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
      </note>

 that the Pope by his pontificall authority refused to confirme the opinions of the Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and by delayes after delayes, the busines was drawn into length, both at <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; in <hi>England.</hi> The Cardinall feared <hi>Bolene,</hi> who for the loue that shee bore to the Euangelicall Doctrine, hated his proud and insolent carriage; and the Pope feared the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who at that time was powerfull in <hi>Italy,</hi> who maintained, to his vtmost power, the cause of <hi>Katherine</hi> his Aunt: neither would the Pope pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke HENRY, because hee had lately employed both his paines and pence, to redeeme him from the Emperours men, who kept him prisoner. HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE boyling in choler for this refusall (yet dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling it) both by Ambassadours and Letters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually solicited,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Peeres doe the like.</hi>
      </note>

 and humbly prayed the Pope, (and after him the Prelates and Peeres of <hi>England,</hi> by request signed with their owne hands, which
<pb facs="22"/>
they caused to be carried and presented at his feete) to confirme by his Apostolicall Authority, what the two Academies of <hi>England,</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, and very learned and most entire men, both within and without the Realme, had set down for a truth, and were ready to mainiaine it, both by word and writing: representing vnto him, that it would be a remarkeable vnhappines, if He should not obtaine this fauour from the Apostolicall Sea, He beeing the onely man that had employed his Sword, his Pen, his word and power, to defend the authority of the Pope, and resisting many that stroue against it, should bee the onely man to bee denyed the benefit of it; and therefore they coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to grant it, for feare that intestine warres should rise for the right of Succession.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, the Clergie fearing lest the Pope should proscribe the Kingdome, and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the King, by seuerall Letters put him in mind of the sad discord which had been betweene Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the second, King of <hi>England,</hi> and representing vnto him many reasons of importance, infinitely besought him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in the very same words that <hi>Gilbert,</hi> Bishop of London did at the same time, (<hi>viz.</hi>)
<q>WEe most humbly beseech you, to shut vp for a time your burning zeale within the
<pb facs="23"/>
bounds of modestie, lest by interdicting the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or cuting off the King from the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Catholike Church, you cause the ruine of many particular Churches, and irreuokeably turne from your obedience both the King and infinite numbers with him. Cutting off brings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire, whereas dressing the wound often cureth. And therfore, if there be a wound, it is more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, if it may bee your pleasure, to labour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently to cure it, lest by cutting off a most noble member of the Church of God, you trouble beyond expression, as matters now stand. The Blood-Royall cannot be ouercome till it hath ouercome, and is not ashamed to yeeld after it hath conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Hee must be wonne with meekenes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ruled with admonitions and patience. What is it to haue lost some temporall things by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or by a continuall patience to lose more, as the times now are? Whether is Seuerity to bee withdrawne, when ruine and slaughter threaten a People? To cast many goods into the sea, when the prouoked waues with the confusion of hideous surges threaten a Ship-wrack?</q>
   </p>
   <p>But the Pope and Cardinals could not endure that the Papall authority should be questioned in matter of Dispensation, and all maner of contempt for the space of fiue yeeres little more or lesse, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb facs="23"/>
to lend an eare thereto,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The King seeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Pope.</hi>
      </note>

 but were of opinion that the King ought to be cited to <hi>Rome</hi>: Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that this Prince, who was full of courage, being stirred vp to wrath by the arrogancy which some Ecclesiasticall persons had lately shewed, thought that for the iustnesse of his cause, hee was vniustly dealt with, most vnworthily for his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dignitie, and most ingratefully considering how much good he had done for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>; that almost all at one time hee diuorced <hi>Katharine,</hi> depriued <hi>Wolsey</hi> of his goods, and drew a great summe of mony from those Bishops who had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the authority of his Delegation, to the preiudice of his Royall preeminence; accepted the title of <hi>Soueraigne head, next vnder Christ, of the Church of England,</hi> which was offered vnto him by a Synod, and by both the Vniuersities of <hi>England</hi>; with the consent of the Peeres of his Kingdome, made <hi>Anne Bolene</hi> Marchionesse of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> for the noblenesse of her extraction, and the merit of her vertues, (so are the words;) hauing apparelled her in Royall Robes, he married her,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Marrieth Anne.</hi>
      </note>

 and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to be sacred, Queene. <hi>Clement</hi> the Seuenth was much displeased, (but to little purpose) iudged the former marriage to be of force and Canonicall, and pronounced that the King had incurred the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie of the great excommunication.</p>
   <p>Of this Marriage was ELIZABETH borne at
<pb facs="24"/>
      <hi>Greenwich,</hi> vpon <hi>Thames,</hi> the seuenth day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1533. Shortly after, the marriage contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with <hi>Katherine,</hi> was iudged by authority of Parliament, incestuous and void, and that with <hi>Anne,</hi> lawfull by the Diuine Law, and ELIZABETH Heire of the Kingdome, if Issue-Male of the Royall Line should fayle. All sweare fidelity to the King, and to the Heires which he had or should haue by <hi>Anne.</hi> And as it was considered vpon, that <hi>Paulus</hi> the Third would againe at <hi>Rome</hi> proclaime against this Marriage, and that within the Realme certaine Religious Women of <hi>Kent,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>A Nunne of Kent sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned.</hi>
      </note>

 suborned by some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men, cast out at randome some indiscreete words against <hi>Anne,</hi> ELIZABETH, and the King, as if they had been strucken with some diuine fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Authoritie of Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall giuen to the King.</hi>
      </note>

 The Title of the <hi>Soueraigne head of the Church of England</hi> is giuen to the King, with all manner of authority for the reforming of errours, heresies, and abuses, and the oath of fidelity to the Heires which hee should haue by <hi>Anne</hi> is confirmed. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse three yeeres scarce passed, but giuing himselfe to new Loues, to distrusts, to wrath, to murther, and to bloud; to make way to his new Loue <hi>Iane Seymor,</hi> he accused <hi>Anne</hi> (who had miscarried of a Male-Childe) to haue defiled his Bed, and for a light suspition put her into the hands of iustice, where being examined, shee so resolued the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which were made vnto her, that the whole
<pb facs="24"/>
multitude which were there present, iudged her innocent, and that she was circumuented. She not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding is condemned by her Peeres, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told of it, sent to the King, and pleasantly thankes him for many benefits which shee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from him, <hi>viz.</hi> that shee not being very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by extraction, hee had vouchsafed to adde to her condition, the dignity of Marchionesse, to make her his companion of honour, and to raise her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Royall Maiestie: And which is more than all this, that not being able to aduāce her to an higher on earth, he pleased to lift her vp to heauen, where shee should enioy eternall glory with innocent soules.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Anne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</hi>
      </note>

 Shee tooke her punishment quietly and Christianly, wishing all happines to the King, and pardoning all her enemies.</p>
   <p>The day following, hee married <hi>Iane,</hi> and by authority of the Parliament, declares the marriage with <hi>Anne</hi> to be no lesse vnlawfull and voyd, than the marriage with <hi>Katherine,</hi> and that MARIE and ELIZABETH, their Daughters, were illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, and to be excluded from the Succession of the Kingdome. <hi>Iane,</hi> being in labour of EDWARD, (who succeeded his Father in the Kingdome) dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before hee was borne, and hee cut out of her wombe.</p>
   <p>The King being but little grieued for the death of his Wife, forthwith applyes himselfe to new
<pb facs="25"/>
Loues both in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to procure friends: Neuerthelesse, as he was of an ambiguous minde, and fearefull of euery thing, lest the Papists should rise in Rebellion, and the Nobles moue sedition, or ioyne with his forreine enemies, hee caused some to be beheaded for light and trifling matters, &amp; some before euer they were heard: and euery houre hee punished the Papists,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The King exerciseth his cruelty vpon Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists and Lutherans, and his aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice vpon the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries.</hi>
      </note>

 as Traytors which did perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in defending the Popes authoritie; and beeing transported with couetousnesse, hee tooke occasion (and subiect by the vices of humane frailtie, as of idle and free liuing) to demolish the great Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, as he had done the smaller, that were full of venerable antiquity and Maiesty, tooke all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which had beene gathered of many yeeres, and at the same time burned Protestants aliue for Heretiques, by vertue of a Law called the Law of the <hi>Six Articles,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The Law of</hi> Six Articles.</note>

 made against those which did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Transubstantiation, the celebration of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist vnder one kinde, the single life of Priests, Vowes, priuate Masses, and auricular confession.</hi> In so much, that at one time, and in the same place, hee exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his crueltie against the Papists, causing them to be hanged and quartered: and against the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, causing them to be burned aliue. By which acts, he made himselfe terrible in his owne King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to be holden a Tyrant abroad: and first,
<pb facs="25"/>
being reiected by <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> daughter to the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> whom hee desired as riuall to <hi>Iames</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> his Nephew: afterwards, of <hi>Christian</hi> of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> Dutchesse of <hi>Milan,</hi> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child to <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth. In the end, seeking the friendship of the Protestants of <hi>Germanie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>He marries and diuorces Anne of Cleue.</hi>
      </note>

 with much adoe he obtained <hi>Anne of Cleue</hi> for his wife. But beeing as readie to distaste Women as to loue them, turning his heart away from her as soone as he had marryed her, put her away, as not beautifull enough for a Prince, grounding himselfe vpon this, that shee had beene betrothed before to the Duke of <hi>Lorraine's</hi> Sonne, and that shee had some womanish weaknesse that made her vnfit for mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. But it was to take in her stead <hi>Katharine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> daughter to <hi>Edmond Howard,</hi> and Neece to <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> whom he beheaded the yeere following, accusing her to haue violated her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity before shee was married, and opens the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all-Bed to <hi>Katharine Parre,</hi> a Knights daughter,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Katharine Parre.</hi>
      </note>

 and the second time Widdow.</p>
   <p>Now when through intemperancy of his youth, he perceiued the vigor of his body to decay; being angry with the French King for hauing ayded the <hi>Scots</hi> against the <hi>English,</hi> hee reconciles himselfe, and makes alliance with the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>French,</hi> who hauing quite forgot the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce of <hi>Katharine</hi> his Aunt, secretly giues him hope
<pb facs="26"/>
to reconcile him to the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Reconciles himselfe with the Emperour Charles.</hi>
      </note>

 After, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing resolued to set vpon <hi>France,</hi> thereby so much the more to worke himselfe into the Emperours friendship, and quickly to cure the vlcers of his conscience,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Assures the succession to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
      </note>

 propounded to the Parliament, which was then assembled, that when hee should happen to dye, and his Sonne EDVVARD without issue, MARIE should first succeed to the Crowne, and afterwards, shee leauing none, ELIZABETH. That if neither left any, the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> should deuolue vpon such as he would designe ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Letters Patents or by Will. Which passed for a Law, with the good liking and consent of all, and that the penaltie of <hi>Laesae Maiestatis</hi> should be inflicted vpon any that should goe against it.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Take Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne.</hi>
      </note>

Being returned from <hi>France,</hi> after he had taken <hi>Bologne,</hi> and consumed much treasure, and beeing sad and heauy to see <hi>England</hi> deuided by new o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions which daily sprang vp, and <hi>England</hi> groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for sorrow to see her selfe so exhausted of her riches, her Money corrupted with Brasse, her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries, with the Monuments of great antiquity, ruined, the bloud of Nobles, Prelates, Papists, and Protestants promiscuously spilt, and entangled in a <hi>Scottish</hi> warre,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dyed.</hi>
      </note>

 hee died with a perpetuall fluxe of Grease flowing from him, caused by a poysonous inflammation in the thigh: <hi>An.</hi> 1547. he breathed his last. A magnanimous Prince, but I know not
<pb facs="26"/>
what confused temper of spirit he had: great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues he had; and no lesse vices.</p>
   <p>EDVVARD his sonne hauing scarce attained to the age of tenne yeeres, succeeded him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sixth suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth his Father.</hi>
      </note>

 and had for his Protector, <hi>Edw. Seymor</hi> Duke of <hi>Sommerset,</hi> his Vnkle, vnder whom the <hi>English</hi> hauing taken vp armes, for to reuenge the violated faith of the match agreed vpon betweene <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> Queene of <hi>Scotland</hi>; the <hi>English</hi> obtained a notable victory ouer the <hi>Scots</hi> neere <hi>Musselborough</hi>; this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Law of <hi>Six Articles,</hi> and others which had beene established by King HENRY the Eighth, against the Protestants, are suppressed, and those which tended to the abolishing of the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie confirmed; the Masse abrogated;<note place="margin">
         <hi>The doctrine of the Gospel is brought in.</hi>
      </note>

 the Images taken out of the Temples; the Bookes of the Old and New Testament imprinted; the Diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice celebrated in the vulgar Tongue; the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist distributed vnder both kindes: But neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the auaritious sacriledge fell rauenously vpon pillaging the goods of the Church, Colledges,<note place="margin">
         <hi>A misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reigne vnder a King that is a Childe.</hi>
      </note>

 Quiers, Hospitals, as things iudged to bee for su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious vses: ambition and enuy among the great ones, audacitie and disobedience among the Commons, so insolently exulted, that <hi>England</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be raging madde with rebellious tumults, taking sides, deprauation of money, and withall, the euils that are accustomed to be during the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority
<pb facs="27"/>
of a King, these wasted and consumed within the Land: Also, dammage was receiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; as the losse of Forts which the <hi>English</hi> had made in <hi>Scotland</hi> and in <hi>France,</hi> and the Towne of <hi>Bologne,</hi> which had cost so much, which, to the shame of the name of <hi>English,</hi> was deliuered vp into the French Kings hands for money, with all the Fortresses of the Countrey of <hi>Bologne</hi> which the <hi>English</hi> had built, the Cannons and Munitions of warre; when <hi>England</hi> was so disioynted by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision, that it was not able to keepe them; and <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour hauing no will to ayde it, although he was intreated, in consideration of the alliance with him, excusing himselfe for that it had beene conquered since; no, not to accept of it, being offered vnto him <hi>gratis.</hi> And to adde an ouer-plus of infelicity, the Protector not being wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry enough of the subtilty and deceits of <hi>Dudley,</hi> Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor is sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to death.</hi>
      </note>

 is by vertue of a new law condemned of Felony: for, entring into counsell how to take away the liues of some of the Kings Councellors, <hi>to wit,</hi> of <hi>Dudley,</hi> and some others, hee lost his head, and his Sonne by a priuate Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of the greatest part of his patrimony, and of his Fathers honours. The King being vnprouided of his faithfull Guard, is snatched away (vncertaine whether by sicknesse or poyson) before hee was ripe, leauing an incredible griefe with his people
<pb facs="27"/>
for the great and excellent vertues which hee had, farre surpassing his age.</p>
   <p>At the same dolefull and heauy time, <hi>Dudley</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing broken the fraternall amity that was between the Protector and <hi>Tho. Seimor</hi> his brother, vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of an emulation of Women, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Queene Dowager, wife to <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the Dutches of <hi>Somerset,</hi> the Protectors wife, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other things, to conuict <hi>Thomas,</hi> of <hi>Crimen laesae Maiestatis,</hi> that he intended to reduce the King into his owne power, and to marry ELIZABETH the Kings Sister; shee indeed ignorant of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, grew vp in yeeres,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Elizabeth in fauour with her brother.</hi>
      </note>

 and was in singular fauour with EDWARD her brother (who neuer saluted her, but called her his <hi>sweet Sister</hi>;) as also with the Peeres, and the Common-people. For she was full of grace and beauty, and worthy of Soueraigne Authority, of modest grauity, cleere and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted, of a happy memory, and indefatigable in the studies of best letters, insomuch that before she attained to the Age of 17. yeeres,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Her studies.</hi>
      </note>

 she very well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood the Latine tongue, the French, the Italian, and the Greeke indifferently. Neither wanted shee skill in Musicke that was beseeming a Prince, and she sung and plaid cunningly and sweetly. With <hi>Roger Ascham,</hi> who was to guide her in her Studies, she read the Common places of <hi>Melancthon,</hi> all <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero,</hi> a great part of the History of <hi>Titus Liuius,</hi> the
<pb facs="28"/>
choice Orations of <hi>Isocrates</hi> (wherof she translated two into Latine) <hi>Sophocles</hi> Tragedies, and she read the New-Testament in <hi>Greeke.</hi> By which meanes she adorned her tongue with pure words, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed her mind with the best documents, and good learning, not for pompe or ostentation, but to recreate her life, and frame her selfe to vertue, that among the learned Princes of her time, shee was held Miraculous.</p>
   <p>But the death of EDVVARD interrupted the studies of the Liberall Arts: For scarce was he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, but <hi>Dudley</hi> Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> (who earnestly coueted the Kingdome for <hi>Iane Gray,</hi> to whom he had affianced his Sonne) vsed some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to perswade her to quit the right which shee had to the Kingdome for a certaine summe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and great possessions in Land. She modestly answered, that they ought first doe well to agree with <hi>Mary</hi> her elder Sister, because that during her life, she could pretend no right to it. Anon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by the publike voice of a Cryer, <hi>Iane Gray,</hi> HENRY the Eighth's Neece by his second Sisters Daughter, was proclaimed Queene of <hi>England</hi>: the cause thereof being sought out, was found to bee, that in regard of a Lawe by Act of Parliament, which had neuer been duely abrogated, MARIE and ELIZABETH had beene declared illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, (although that by the same Lawe the King
<pb facs="28"/>
their Father had declared, that after EDVVARD the Sixth, if Issue fayled, that they should succeede him in order) and that by the Ciuill-Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> such Sisters could not hereditarily succeede EDVVARD, because they were not Cousin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, but (as our learned in the Law say) of the halfe Blood. They adde likewise, that HENRY the Eighth had by his last will nominated <hi>Iane Gray.</hi> Moreouer it was shewed, what danger there were, if MARIE and ELIZABETH should mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie stranger Princes, which would re-establish the Popes authority, which was reiected out of the Kingdome. And to that purpose they produce Letters Patents that EDVVARD the Sixth a little before his death had perfected, and many of the Peeres, Bishops, Iudges, and others, by their signes in writing had fortified; neuerthelesse, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will that the Lords and the Commons bore to the Daughters of HENRIE the Eighth, within twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes had driuen away this storme, and MARY proclaimed Queene through all parts of <hi>England,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Mary is proclaimed. Elizabeth ioynes with her.</hi>
      </note>

 who comming toward the Citie of <hi>London</hi> with an Armie, ELIZABETH (not to bee wanting, her Sisters cause and hers being yet disquieted) went accompanied with fiue hundred Horse to meet her vpon the way.</p>
   <p>In the first Assembly of the Parliament that MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY caused to bee holden, what things soeuer had
<pb facs="29"/>
beene decreed against the marriage betweene Qu. <hi>Katharine,</hi> and HENRY the Eighth, were abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and it was iudged lawfull by the Diuine Law, and at all times, and at all places auaileable for these reasons, Because it had bin contracted by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of both their Parents, of most Illustrious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of most graue Personages as well of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Spaine,</hi> and with a graue and constant deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the learnedest men of Christendome, and consummated by the procreation of Children. The same religious Seruice, and administration of the Sacraments which were in vse at the decease of HENRY the Eighth, are re-established; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing without any mention of acknowledging the Popes authority, which thing put the Queene and Cardinall <hi>Pole</hi> into great trouble and vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, who thinke that for matter of the marriage, consent of Parents, and the iudgement of the wise, did but onely depend vpon the Dispensation of Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the second: and were very angry that the vse of the Sacraments were permitted to those who were not as yet well and duely receiued into the Church, without the authoritie of the Pope. But the States of the Kingdome (and MARY be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought her selfe of it) feared to receiue and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Popes authority which they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready shaken off, neither could they suffer that the Queene should quit the Title of <hi>Soueraigne head of
<pb facs="29"/>
the Church of England,</hi> to which the most part of them, Prelates, Peeres, and Common-people, had sworne to HENRY the Eighth, his heires and successors, and there were many of them that had got their riches from those of the Church.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The English with much adoe subiect themselues to the power of the</hi> Pope.</note>

 But tooke it greatly to heart to forsake him, perswading herselfe that all the right that she had to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England,</hi> was vpholden by no other meanes, then by the power of the Pope, who gaue sentence of her side, after her Father had declared her illegitimate. Verily, many at that time had the Popes power in such hatred, and a strangers yoke, that within tenne dayes after that MARY was married to <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine, Tho. Wyat,</hi> and many others of <hi>Kent,</hi> brake out into rebellion, perswading themselues, that this marriage was made to no other end, but the more rigorously to presse them downe vnder the <hi>Romane</hi> yoke, by the strength of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and dispatch ELIZABETH out of the way, who was next heire to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England. Charles</hi> the fifth Emperour know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what spirits were in <hi>England,</hi> and that Cardinall <hi>Pole</hi> was going with power of Legate from the Pope, cast a blocke in the way (not without the Queenes counsell) lest he should trouble businesse not as yet established, that he should not come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England</hi> till fifteene moneths were expired, when the third Parliament was ended, and the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb facs="30"/>
of MARY and <hi>Philip</hi> should be celebrated by the Dispensation of Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the third, because they were allied in the third degree, and that the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> himselfe had heretofore contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to marry her, being then vnder age, for time to come. At last, being dismissed from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, he came into <hi>England,</hi> by demands and obte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations propounded orders, that the lawes against Heretikes might be re-established, all Lawes pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished against the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> since the twentieth yeere of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eighth abolished, and the whole body of the Kingdome reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The which with great difficulty he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, yet not before the goods taken from the <hi>Monasteries, Colledges, Bishops, &amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Vpon what conditions they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church of Rome.</hi>
      </note>

 and <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth, were confirmed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on like Couenant, to the Queene and the possessors, lest the Kingdome should be disquieted. Foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hereupon, he absolued both the Clergie and people, of the crime of Schisme, and Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the third, himselfe with great ioy, celebrated a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Masse at <hi>Rome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Reioycing for it at Rome.</hi>
      </note>

 ordained Prayers, published a Iubile, and granted a plenarie Indulgence to all who had giuen God thankes for the revnion of the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi> Then is sent vnto him <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> Viscount <hi>Montaigue, Thomas Thurlbe,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and <hi>Edward Carne,</hi> to giue thankes for the pardon which he had granted for the Schismes, and
<pb facs="30"/>
in the name of the King, the Queene, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that due submission and obedience should be performed to the Pope and See of Rome. <hi>Iulius</hi> then being deceased, <hi>Paulus</hi> 4. gaue them audience and publike conference in the Apostolike Palace, and in the Hall of Kings, receiued their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, approued the pardon and absolution granted by Cardinall <hi>Pole</hi>: And for the well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing of <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> he,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ireland e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected a Kingdome by the Pope.</hi>
      </note>

 out of the fulnesse of his power, erected for euer <hi>Ireland</hi> to be a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and adorned and marked it with dignities and Royall preheminences. The which the States of <hi>Ireland</hi> had liberally offered to <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and the Queene a little before vsed and enioyed the same. But these things are not for this place.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Romane</hi> Religion seemed then to be well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished in <hi>England</hi>: howbeit the Ecclesiasticall company seeing that <hi>Mary</hi> was now fortie yeeres old, growne dry and sickly, scarce hoping for any ofspring,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The Papists feare Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
      </note>

 began forthwith to be afraid of ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH: For they knew she was brought vp in the Protestant Religion, and obserued that all men cast (as vpon a rising Sunne) both heart and eye vpon her. Therefore they seriously consult from the very beginning of <hi>Maries</hi> Raigne, how to preuent that the Religion now called backe, should receiue any detriment by her. The wiser and more conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious sort iudged it to be an exceeding foule crime
<pb facs="31"/>
to destroy Royall Linage, and <hi>Mary</hi> herselfe, who was a godly Princesse (though displeased with her Sister, for the discord of their Mothers) yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine sicke-braind fellowes (who neither durst vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake any thing, nor performe any thing by right or wrong to establish the Catholike Religion) did thinke it fit. And it happened very commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, for them, that <hi>Tho. Wyat, Peter Carew, Iames Crofts,</hi> and others for the Protestants, seditiously endeuoured to doe rash and turbulent things, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring with all haste to mary ELIZABETH to <hi>Edward Courtney,</hi> Earle of <hi>Deuon-shire.</hi> She, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty hereof,<note place="margin">
         <hi>They perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute her.</hi>
      </note>

 is thrust into prison: first of all vncertaine rumors are dispersed, that she was a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of sedition, thereupon many are brought in question for their heads, and others brought to the Racke. <hi>Croft,</hi> with a religious asseueration openly affirmed, that she was no way guilty, and out of all offence for sedition. <hi>Wyat</hi> also, it was thought, (who was ready to vnder-goe his last punishment) would haue accused her, and hee openly professed the same: Neuerthelesse she is put into the hands of Keepers, who hurry her this way and that way, at length her Seruants and Maides are laide in fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; harder dealing then her dignity deserued.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The Kings of France &amp; Spaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her.</hi>
      </note>

In the meane time, the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>Henry</hi> the second, by priuate Letters, full of loue, comforts her, and by many and great promises seekes to
<pb facs="31"/>
draw her into <hi>France</hi>; whether for loue, or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to beget her a greater danger, I will not say, to make way to the Queene of <hi>Scots</hi> his Neece to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> after Queene MARY. In like manner, <hi>Christian</hi> the Third, King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> who long before made profession of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants Religion, endeuours all he can, and treates vnder-hand to marry her to <hi>Frederick</hi> his Sonne.</p>
   <p>Which when the Papists of <hi>England</hi> perceyued, they againe threaten perill and mischiefe, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her, cry out, that all of the Romane Religion, Queene and Kingdome, are in ieopardy while shee subsists, therefore necessarily to condemne her, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Laesae Maiestatis,</hi> or as a depraued Heretique: and during that storme, whilest cruelty was rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously exercised vpon the meaner sort of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, <hi>I. Storie,</hi> Doctor of the Law, and others, cunningly giue it out in all places, in seuerall assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, that they vnderstood it was practising to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate and ridde out Heresie (ayming at her) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sparing the smallest branches. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, moderating her selfe (imitating the Mariner when a storme violently increaseth) heard diuine Seruice, according to the rule of the Romish Church, came often to Confession,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Shee is for feare of death con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to follow the Romish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
      </note>

 and verily bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oft rudely and churlishly disturbed by Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Pole,</hi> the terrour of death made her confesse her selfe to bee a Romane Catholique. Howbeit
<pb facs="32"/>
MARY hardly beleeued it, not forgetting that her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, being forced by the same apprehension, had by Letters written to her Father with her owne hand (which I haue seene) renounced for euer the authority that the <hi>Pope</hi> pretended to haue in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and acknowledged her Father to be [<hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Head of the Church of England</hi>] and that the marriage betwixt him and her Mother was ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuous and vnlawfull. Neyther could the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> and other Prelates, perswade themselues to it, who to assure the Romane Church, wished her to be taken out of the way. But <hi>Philip,</hi> MARY'S Husband, and other <hi>Spaniards,</hi> being more iust on ELIZABETHS behalfe, would not heare of that; Not that the fortune of an afflicted Princesse moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them so much to mercy, as their owne reason circumspectly aduised them. Because (fore-seeing) if ELIZABETH were cut off, that by <hi>Marie,</hi> Queene of <hi>Scots,</hi> (next Heire to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> now married to the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of <hi>France,) England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> might be ioyned to the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>France</hi>; then which, nothing could be more fearefull to the greatnes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with whom they haue continuall warres.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>They goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to send her out of the Kingdome, and exclude her from the succession thereof.</hi>
      </note>

When therefore without impietie they could not put ELIZABETH to death, many thought it would be most aduisedly done, to remooue her farre from <hi>England,</hi> and marry her to <hi>Emanuel Philibert,</hi> Duke
<pb facs="32"/>
of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> Neyther did this please <hi>Spaine,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had purposed her for <hi>Charles</hi> his sonne. And <hi>Thomas Cornwallis,</hi> who was of the Queenes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, likewise disswaded it, telling Her, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Englād</hi> would hardly beare it, yea in no wise suffer it, that the next Heire of the Kingdome should be carryed away into a forreine Countrey: At which time, MARY, for her inueterate hatred to ELIZABETH, and because shee refused to marry with <hi>Sauoy,</hi> grew to that heat of anger, that shee ouer-charged her with reproaches, and often-times would not stick to say, that <hi>Marie,</hi> Queene of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was the certaine and vndoubted Heire of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> next to her selfe. These con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations holden against ELIZABETH, were taken away by a warre which MARY denounced in the behalfe of her Husband against <hi>France,</hi> which although that was the prime and principall cause, shee neuerthelesse alledged others, and those most true, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>France,</hi> against the Lawes of couenant, had nourished and sustained by his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and ministers, the Rebellions of the Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Wyat,</hi> the machinations and workings of <hi>Dudley</hi> and <hi>Ashton</hi> against her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, sent out Pyrats against the <hi>English</hi> Merchants, furnished <hi>Stafford</hi> with Ships and Armes to possesse the Castle of <hi>Scarborough,</hi> had attempted by wicked practices to surprize <hi>Callais,</hi> permitted <hi>English</hi> mony
<pb facs="33"/>
to be counterfeited and adulterated in <hi>France,</hi> and inuaded the Low-Countries, which the <hi>English</hi> by couenant are bound to defend. In this flaming warre, and the <hi>Scots</hi> stirred vp by the <hi>French</hi> inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Frontiers of <hi>England,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Calais lost.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Calais</hi> is lost, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles of <hi>Lisbanck, Newnambrig, Mere, Oyes, Hammes, Sandgate,</hi> the Castle and Towne of <hi>Guines,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the frequent Funerals of Prelates, which sad presage seemed to fore-shew the displeasure of the diuine power, MARY, neglected of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and with concocted griefe for the losse of <hi>Callais,</hi> (which had beene <hi>Englands</hi> rightfully two hundred yeeres) with a Feuer and the Dropsie, the seuenteenth day of Nouember 1558.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Qu.</hi> Mary <hi>dyes:</hi>
      </note>

 departed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reigned fiue yeeres &amp; foure moneths: A Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of a holy behauior to al, her piety to the poore, liberalitie to the Nobles, and Clergie, can neuer enough be praysed. But, the time was infamous, by the incredible crueltie of Prelates, who polluted <hi>England</hi> through all parts, with a most sad &amp; dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full spectacle, in burning the Protestants aliue. For (as some haue obserued) there were more consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of all rankes, Bishops, Ministers, and common people, by this vengible and direfull way of death these fiue yeeres, than <hi>England</hi> saw in all the seuen and thirtie yeeres of HENRY the Eighth.</p>
   <p>In the reigne of <hi>Iohn,</hi> Christians against Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with vs, began to tyrannize with flames. The
<pb facs="33"/>
same day that MARY dyed, within a few houres after, Cardinall <hi>Pole,</hi> Arch-bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>And Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> Pole.</note>

 tormented with a quartane Feuer, expired. A man whom pietie, learning, and integritie, had made much more famous than the splendor of his Royall Race, though hee was Nephew to <hi>George,</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> Brother to <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>England.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>