<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107013_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07105</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107013</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of schisme : Shewing, that al Catholikes ought in any wise to abstaine altogether from heretical conuenticles, to witt, their prayers, sermons. &amp;c, deuided into foure chapters, whereof 1. Conteineth sundry reasons to that purpose, grounded for the most part vppon scriptures and fathers. 2. Examples out of holy Scripture. 3. Examples out of ecclesiastical histories. 4. Answeres to the chiefe obiections. By Gregorie Martin Licentiate in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Martin, Gregory</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 <publisher>Carter, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>180 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onstantius Emperor,</hi> father vnto Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the great,
<note place="margin">Eus. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Const. lib. 1. ca. 11.</note> offered vnto his nobilitie this Condition, That as many as would offer Sacrifice vnto the Idols, shoulde haue both accesse vnto his royal persō, dwel in his Court, and haue offices &amp; great honour in the common wealth. They that would not thus doo, shoulde haue no accesse vnto his person, no familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with him, should beare no office in the common wealth, but should be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the Court, and also be depriued of such offices and honours, as present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye they did enioy. Forthwith y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole Court is deuided in two partes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Emperour easily might perceue eche mans mind, faith, truth, &amp; religiō: for the true Christians were by and by readie humbly to depart, rather thē by tarying to violate their faith for world lye honor. Then Constantius opening his secrete purpose, blameth the dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling sort, calleth them dastardes,
<pb facs="3"/>faint harted Cowardes, traitors vnto their God, and his truth, and flatterers vnto their Emperour, men vnwoorthy to liue in his seruice. For howe wil ye kéepe faith vnto me your master (saith he) that haue violated your faith vnto the eternal God? ye are cōuicted of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie vnto God, howe can yée be true vnto man? The others he commended highly for their cōstancie, pietie, &amp; true faith, he iudgeth thē woorthy to haue rule &amp; charge of earthly thinges, that had shewed thē selues faithful to God. They are (saith he) like to be true vnto their Emperor, that haue shewed them selues true and faithful to God, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the custodie of his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to them, the charge &amp; gouernment of the Empire he layeth in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the rest he did vtterlye banishe as pernitious flatterers, turne-coates, and hipocrites. Verily, the fact was heroical, &amp; woorthie the father of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine, it was the very way to trye true men from flatterers, faithful ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts from false deceauers. For he that wil not sticke to violate his faith,
<pb facs="3"/>his religion, &amp; his conscience towardes God, for lukers sake, who can thinke that such wilbe faithful and trusty vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man? Great therfore is the ouersight of our dayes, wherein he that can best dissemble, he that can violate his faith vnto God and his Churche, for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye preferment, is taken for most trus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and faithful: he that wil come to the Church, although it be neuer so muche against his conscience, he that wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue their what shal I cal it, although he wisheth it in his belye that deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it, is thought to be best to be trus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the greatest affaires &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest busines about the prince. But this good Emperour iudged them vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to haue charge about men, that made no consciēce to violate their faith vnto God. But one wil say,
<note place="margin">4. Reg. 5. Obiectio.</note> Naaman the Assirian was permitted by Elize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us the Prophet, to goe with the king into the temple where Idolatrie was, and yet neuer impaire his conscience: euen so may we go to the Churche for obedience sake without hurting our conscience, or violating our fayth to
<pb facs="4"/>God.
<note place="margin">Resp.</note> If Elizeus gaue him leaue (as you gesse, which yet the text proueth not) to goe to doo his master temporal seruice, not in respect of religion, but according to his office, it was, (as you confesse) but by leaue of the prophete, whom God did wil then to be obeyed: but he that is Elizeus nowe, doth geue you no such leaue, but doth commaund the contrarye, whose voyce you are bounde to obeye, els this example of Naaman wil condemne you. For if he durst not doo so much, as his temporal office vnto his master in the temple without the prophetes leaue, how dare you doo an acte of religion, to further heresie against the expresse cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him,
<note place="margin">Deut. 24. Math. 19. Marc. 10. Heb. 7. Galat. 3.</note> who is greater in office then Elizeus? Moyses gaue the Iewes <hi>libellū repud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> a letter of diuorce, not that it was so frō the beginning, but <hi>propter duritiā;</hi> because of the hardnes of their heartes, because of the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Iewes, for the olde lawe brought nothing to perfection, gaue no grace, but was a time of infancie: but now infancie is passed into mans age,
<pb facs="4"/>and grace is geuen more aboundantly to men. The time a time of perfection that wil admit no such diuorce, no such licence (as you séeme to say) Naaman thassirian had, who was but a Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite or a Catechumene.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> Also there were no such weaklinges to take scandale at his presence in the Temple of Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, as are here in the Sinagoge of heretikes. You may not therfore draw this example of Naaman to coulour your offence, no more then may these that now doo put away their old wiues and take new, vse this example of the old law to cloake their aduoutry.
<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> For vnlesse your righteousnes doo excéede y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> righteousnes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Scribes &amp; Pharises, ye can not enter into the kingdome of heauen. Also heresie &amp; schisme are two most gréeuous sinnes, yet distinct accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that whereto they are directlye opposite of them selues:
<note place="margin">S. Tho. 2.2</note> as heresie of it self is repugnant vnto faith, Schisme opposite vnto the vnitie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal charitie. And therfore, like as fayth and charitie are two diuers vertues, (although whosoeuer lacketh faith, is also voide of charitie) So Schisme and
<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>and heresie are two diuers vices, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though who that is an heretike, is also a schismatike,
<note place="margin">Hier. su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per epist. ad Galat.</note> yet not euery Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike is an heretike: as teacheth S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome. <hi>Inter schisma &amp; haeresim hoc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, quòd haeresis peruersum dogma habet, Schisma ab ecclesia seperat. &amp;c.</hi> Betwéene Schisme and heresie these are the oddes, That heresie hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a peruerse opinion against an article of fayth, Schisme seperateth from the Churche: yet like as the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of charitie is the very high waye towardes the losing of a mans faith, according to that of S. Paule, <hi>A qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quidam aberrantes, conuersi sunt in vaniloquium.</hi> From which some wandring (charitie and such like) are resolued into brablinges. So is Schisme the high way into heresie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at first Shisme may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode somewhat diuers from heresie it selfe, yet in thende there is no Schisme that doth not coyne forth-with some heresie to haue a colour to reuolt from the Church. And therefore commonlye the sinne of Schisme hath bene more
<pb facs="6"/>gréeuously punished in the Scriptures then infidelitie or Idolatrie.
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> For we reade, that the sinne of Idolatrie was punished by the sword, by mans execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> But of the sinne of Schisme we reade, <hi>Si nouam rem fecerit Dominus, vt aperiens terra os suum deglutiat eos, et omnia quae ad illos pertinent. etc.</hi> If our Lorde should doo a newe thing, that the earth opening her mouth doo swa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe them, and al thinges that doo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto them, and liuing, they shal descende to hel, by this you shal knowe that they haue blasphemed our Lorde God. Also the tenn tribes, which through Schisme reuolted from the kingdome of Dauid, were most grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uously punished,
<note place="margin">3. Reg. 12.</note> and in fine fel from Schisme to Idolatrye. Moreouer, as longe as Abraham abode amonge the Chaldeis, who were Idolatrers,
<note place="margin">Gen. 13.15-17.</note> it is not found that our Lord appered much vnto him, althogh, as it may be thoght, he was a good man: but when he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thence, we reade, that often God appered vnto him, and as of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite most singuler, doth put him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb facs="7"/>of his deliuerie.
<note place="margin">Gen. 33.</note>
      <hi>Ego do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min{us} qui eduxi vos de terra Hurr Chal deorum.</hi> Iacob the beloued did refuse to goe into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> company of reprobate Esau, although by giftes he had pacified him, neither woulde suffer anye of his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes to be among his herdmen.
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.</note> Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels playe with Isacke did so offende Sara, that it is called in Scripture per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>secutiō. Hard it was, (although Abrahā prostrate besought it) to saue Lot from the wrath of God in Sodoma: yea, his wife for looking once backe towardes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place where the wicked were,
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally punished:
<note place="margin">Math. 26. Luk. 22.</note> and Peter the prince of thapostles by entring into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> palace of the high Superintendent, &amp; warming him self at their fire, is driuen to deny his faith: Iohn the beloued could not escape their hands, but by leauing his gaberdine behind, glad to escape starke naked. These are written for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.</note> that we shoulde beware of false heretikes and Schismatikes, whose spéech créepeth as doth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> disease of a cancar,
<note place="margin">Ca. Apost. 63.</note> &amp; infecteth those that it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. The Church therfore, as a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mother, hath by Canons of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="7"/>vtterlye forbidden her children to come nere the forsaken company,
<note place="margin">Con. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. can. 9.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.33.</note> as by the cotations in the margent may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere. <hi>Bruno</hi> a learned writer saith, that ech prouiso wherby heresies &amp; schismes are to be auoyded, doo consist in these:
<note place="margin">Bruno.</note>
      <hi>Haereticorum communione, collegiis, conuenticulis, Scholis, praedicationib{us}, &amp; doctrinis, libris falsis, ab haereticis, vel compositis, vel deprauatis</hi> By com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with heretikes in their colleges, conuenticles, or prophecying, prechings, schooles, or in bookes, either by them fally made, or by their notes corrupted: for as by these things being suffred, heresies &amp; Schismes doo grow, encrease, take rooting, and infect: So these occasions being prohibited &amp; cutt off, they are either suppressed or vtterly extinguished. To communicate with heretikes in these thinges, is for thrée causes forbidden by the Churche, and that vppon paine of the censures therof. The first, because heretikes are cutt from the Churche, with whom neyther the Churche, nor they of the Churche ought to haue eyther felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipp
<pb facs="8"/>or communion. Secondly, because Catholikes communicating in any of the premisses with heretikes, <hi>corum se peccatis inuoluant,</hi> doo wrapp them selues (to be giltie) in their sinns, as it is written, Depart from the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of these wicked men (Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes) touche nothing that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth vnto them,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> least in their sinnes you wrapp your selues. Thirdly, least in vsing their societie, you be made one of them.
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 1. Cor. 10.</note>
      <hi>Qui stat videat nè cadat.</hi> For their spéeche and company doth infect. <hi>An emulamur dominum?</hi> Shal we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke or trye whether God dare punish vs? Are we stronger then he, that we can abide his displeasure? We doo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day prouoke him to anger, when we come to the conuenticles of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. It is not good to sustaine his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure. And therfore is it forbidden by the Constitutions of the Apostles.
<note place="margin">Const. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>post. lib. 5. ca. 4. Et i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. Vide F. Turria.</note>
      <hi>Impios haereticos qui impoenitentes fuerint. &amp;c.</hi> The wicked heretikes that haue seperated them selues from the faithful Catholikes, cast off, for they are impenitent, and charge the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes
<pb facs="8"/>to abstaine from their felowshipp by al meanes, neither let them haue anye communication with them in spéeche or prayers, for they are aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries and thieues to the Churche, they begile the flock, defile the heritage. We warne you therefore, that ye auoyde them, least they intangle your soules in their snares, for it is not lawful to runne with théeues. No man can serue two masters at once. Thus farre the Apostles. We sée what charge they gaue to the children of the housholde: For like as the life of the body procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the quickening spirite (for vntil the breath of life was into the nosethrils of man breathed,
<note place="margin">Aug. Ser. 186. &amp; in Ioan.</note> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was senselesse, without life,
<note place="margin">A fitt si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> for the life of the body is the soule, made after the Image of God: al the members as long as they remaine in the body, haue life and strength effectual to their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed operation procéeding from the soule, in the same body for that purpose abiding. But if either legge, arme, eare, or nose be cut off from the body, the life of the soule foloweth it not, it is deade,
<pb facs="9"/>vnprofitable, wretched, and miserable: the life of the soule foloweth not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided member: Euen so, looke what the soule of man doth in the natural bodye of man, the same doth the holy Ghoste in the mistical bodye of Christe. By Baptisme we haue put on Christe.
<note place="margin">Gal. 3. Rom. 6.</note>
      <hi>Quotquot in Christo baptizati estis, Christum induistis.</hi> We are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into his body, as truly, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> leggs, armes, and head, are by sinewes orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically ioyned to the life of thy soule. So truely are they that haue putt on Christe in Baptisme, vnited vnto the mistical body of Christe, which is the Catholike Churche: The soule or life of which body is the holy Ghost,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> like as the life of man is his soule. As long as we remaine in this bodye mistical, in this vine, as true members, as true branches, so long haue we life, grace, &amp; giftes proportionable vnto the part, that we occupie in the mistical body. If we cutt off our selues by heresie, by schisme, by going into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church, where it is, or where any part of the schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical seruice therof is said or preached, we haue no more the life, graces, and
<pb facs="9"/>giftes of the holy Ghost, to merite life euerlasting, then hath the leg or arme, cut off from the body, the life of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> soul, which onely remaineth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body. The graces of the holy Ghost doo not folowe a deuided mēber, what good works soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he doo, they helpe nothing to merite life, but he is a dead mēber withered to be cast into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euerlasting fire of hellish paine and woful miserie. <hi>Vbi ecclesia,
<note place="margin">Iren. li. 3. cap. 40.</note> ibi &amp; spiritus, &amp; vbi spiritus dei, illic ecclesia &amp; omnis gratia, spiritus autem veritas.</hi> Wher y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church is, there is the spirit, &amp; where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spirite of God is, there is the Church &amp; al grace, &amp; the spirit is truth. And S. Augustine saith: <hi>Qui ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiā relinquit,
<note place="margin">Aug. tract. 1. in 1, Ep. Ioh.</note> quomodò est in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sto?</hi> How is he in Christ, that forsaketh y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church of Christ? how is he in Christ, that is not in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ, which is his Catholike Churche? To trye whether thou be a member of this Church (good reader) peruse this booke for thy saluation prepared not by one man, but by the whole Church, whose voyce thou art bounde to obeye: and if thou findest thy selfe to lacke, vse the remedie therein prescribed to saue thy
<pb facs="10"/>saue thy soule, and praye for them that for thy behoofe haue set it foorth. From Remes within the Octaues of Al Saintes. 1578.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By your countriman G. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>