<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE
TO THE AVTHOR OF
CHARITY MAINTAINED.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107216_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18610</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5138</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107216</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE
TO THE AVTHOR OF
CHARITY MAINTAINED.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The religion of protestants a safe vvay to salvation : Or An ansvver to a booke entitled Mercy and truth, or, charity maintain'd by Catholiques, which pretends to prove the contrary. By William Chillingworth Master of Arts of the University of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Chillingworth, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 413, 3 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE
TO THE AVTHOR OF
CHARITY MAINTAINED.</head>
   <head type="sub">WITH AN ANSWER TO HIS
Pamphlet entituled a Direction to N. N.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the first newes of the publication of your Book, I
used all diligence with speed to procure it; and came
with such a mind to the reading of it, as S. <hi>Austin</hi> before
he was a setled Catholique, brought to his conference
with <hi>Faustus</hi> the Manichee. For as he though that if
any thing more then ordinary might be said in defence of the Maniche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Doctrine, <hi>Faustus</hi> was the man from whom it was to be expected:
So my perswasion concerning you was,<hi>—Si Pergama dextrâ defendi
possunt, certè has defensa videbo.</hi> For I conceiv'd that among the
Champions of the Roman Church, the English in reason must be the
best, or equall to the best, as being by most expert Masters train'd up
purposely for this warre, and perpetually practised in it. Among the
English, I saw the Iesuites would yeeld the first place to none; and men
so wise in their generation as the Iesuits were, if they had any <hi>Achilles</hi>
among them, I presum'd, would make choice of him for this service.
And besides, I had good assurance that in the framing of this building,
though you were the only Architect, yet you wanted not the assistance
of many diligent hands to bring you in choice materialls towards it;
nor of many carefull and watchfull eyes to correct the errors of your
worke, if any should chance to escape you. Great reason therefore had
I to expect great matters from you, and that your Book should have in
it the Spirit and Elixir of all that can be said in defence of your
Church and Doctrine; and to assure my selfe, that if my resolution
not to believe it, were not built upon the rock of evident grounds and
reasons, but only upon some sandy and deceitfull appearances, now
the wind and storme &amp; floods were coming which would undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
overthrow it.</p>
   <p>2 Neither truly were you more willing to effect such an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
in me then I was to have it effected. For my desire is to goe the
right way to <hi>eternall happinesse.</hi> But whether this way lye on the right
<pb facs="6"/>
hand or the left, or streight forwards; whether it be by following a
living Guide, or by seeking my direction in a book, or by hearkening
to the secret whisper of some privat Spirit, to me it is indifferent. And
he that is otherwise affected, and has not a travellers indifference, which
<hi>Epictetus</hi> requires in all that would find the truth, but much desires in
respect of his ease, or pleasure, or profit, or advancement, or satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of friends, or any human consideration, that one way should be
true rather then another; it is oddes but he will take his desire that it
should be so, for an assurance that it is so. But I for my part, unlese I
deceive my selfe, was and still am so affected as I have made professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
not willing I confesse to take any thing upon trust, and to believe
it without asking my selfe why; no, nor able to command my selfe
(were I never so willing) to follow, like a sheepe, every sheepheard
that should take upon him to guide me; or every flock that should
chance to goe before me: but most apt and most willing to be led by
reason to any way, or from it; and alwaies submitting all other reasons
to this one, God hath said so, therefore it is true. Nor yet was I so
unreasonable as to expect Mathematicall demonstrations from you
in matters plainly incapable of them, such as are to be believed, and
if we speak properly, cannot be known; such therefore I expected not.
For as he is an unreasonable Master, who requires a stronger assent to
his conclusions then his arguments deserve; so I conceive him a
froward and undisciplin'd Scholar, who desires stronger arguments
for a conclusion then the matter will bear. But had you represented
to my understanding such reasons of your Doctrine, as being weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in an even ballance, held by an even hand, with those on the other
side, would have turn'd the scale, and have made your Religion more
credible then the contrary; certainly I should have despised the shame
of one more alteration, and with both mine armes and all my heart
most readily have embraced it. Such was my expectation from you,
and such my preparation, which I brought with me to the reading of
your book. Would you know now what the event was, what effect
was wrought in me, by the perusall and consideration of it? To deal
truly and ingenuously with you, I fell somewhat in my good opinion
both of your sufficiency &amp; syncerity: but was exceedingly confirm'd
in my ill opinion of the cause maintained by you. I found every where
snares that might entrap, and colours that might deceive the simple;
but nothing that might perswade, and very little that might move an
understanding man, and one that can discerne between discourse and
sophistry. In short, I was verily perswaded that I plainly saw and
could make it appear, to all dis-passionate and unprejudicate Iudges,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> a vein of sophistry and calumny, did run clean through it from
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> begining to the end. And letting some friends understand so much,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> my selfe to be perswaded by them, that it would not be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
unproper for me, nor un-acceptable to God, nor peradventure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
unserviceable to his Church, nor justly offensive to you (if
you indeed were a lover of Truth, and not a maintainer of a Faction,)
if setting aside the second Part, which was in a manner wholly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb facs="6"/>
in particular disputes, repetitions and references, and in
wranglings with D. <hi>Potter</hi> about the sense of some super-numerary
quotations, and whereon the main question no way depends, I would
make a faire and ingenuous Answer to the first, wherein the substance
of the present Controversy is confessedly contained; and which, if it
were clearly answered, no man would desire any other answer to the
second. This therefore I undertook with a full resolution to be an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary
to your errors, but a friend and servant to your person: and so
much the more a friend to your person, by how much the severer and
more rigid adversary I was to your errors.</p>
   <p>4 In this work my conscience beares me witnesse that I have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to your advice <hi>proceeded alwayes with this consideration, that
I am to give a most strict account of every line, and word that passeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
my pen;</hi> and therefore have been precisely carefull for <hi>the matter</hi> of
my book to defend truth only, and only by Truth. And then scrupulou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly
fearefull of scandalizing you or any man with <hi>the manner</hi> of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
it. From this rule sure I am, I have not willingly swerved in either
part of it, and that I might not doe it ignorantly, I have not only my
self examined mine owne work, perhaps with more severity then I
have done yours, (as conceiving it a base and unchristian thing to goe
about to satisfie others with what I my self am not fully satisfied;)
But have also made it passe the fiery tryall of the exact censures of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
understanding judges, alwaies heartily wishing that you your selfe
had been of the <hi>Quorum.</hi> But they who did undergoe this burthen as
they wanted not sufficiencie to discover any heterodoxe doctrine, so I
am sure they have been very carefull to let nothing flip dissonant from
truth or from the authorized doctrine of the Church of England,
and therefore whatsoever causelesse and groundlesse jealousy, any
man may entertain concerning my Person, yet my book, I presume,
in reason and common equity should be free from them: wherein I
hope that little or nothing hath escap'd so many eyes, which being
weighed in the ballance of the Sanctuary will be found too light. And
in this hope I am much confirm'd, by your strange carriage of your
selfe in this whole businesse. For though by some crooked and sinister
arts, you have got my Answer into your hands, now a yeare since and
upwards, as <hi>I</hi> have been assured by some that know it, and those of
your own party; though you could not want every day faire oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunityes
of sending to me, and acquainting me with any exceptions,
which, you conceived, might be justly taken to it, or any part of it,
then which nothing could have been more welcome to me, yet hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you have not been pleased to acquaint mee with any one. Nay
more, though you have been at sundry times, and by severall waies
entreated and sollicited, nay press'd and importun'd by me, to joyne
with me in a private discussion of the Controversy between us, before
the publication of my Answer, (because I was extremely unwilling to
publish any thing which had not passed all manner of tryals,) as desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
not that I, or my Side, but that truth might overcome on which
Side soever it was) though <hi>I</hi> have prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sted to you, and set it under my
<pb facs="7"/>
hand, (which protestation by Gods help I would have made good) if
you, or any other would undertake your cause, would give me a faire
meeting, and choose out of your whole Book any one argument,
wherof you were most confident, and by which you would be content
the rest should be judged of, and make it appeare that I had not, or
could not answer it, that I would desist from the work which <hi>I</hi> had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken,
and answer none at all; though by all the Arts which possibly
I could devise, I have provoked you to such a tryall, in particular by
assuring you that if you refus'd it, the world should be inform'd of
your tergiversation, notwithstanding all this you have perpetually, and
obstinately declined it; which to my understanding is a very evident
signe that there is not any truth in your cause, nor (which is impossible
there should bee strength in your arguments, especially considering
what our Saviour hath told us, <hi>every one that doth evill hateth the light,
neither commeth to the light, least his deeds should be reproved; but he
that doth truth commeth to the light that his deeds may be made manifest
that they are wrought in God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>5 In the meane while though you despaired of compassing
your desire this honest way, yet you have not omitted to tempt
me by base and unworthy considerations to desert the cause which I
had undertaken; letting me understand from you, by an acquaintance
common to us both, how that <hi>in case my work should come to light, my
inconstancy in religion</hi> (so you miscall my constancy in following that
way to heaven which for the present seemes to me the most probable,)
<hi>should bee to my great shame painted to the life;</hi> that <hi>my owne writings
should be produc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d against my selfe; that I should bee urged to answer my
owne motives against Protestantisme, and that such things should be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished
to the world touching my beliefe,</hi> (for my painter I must expect
should have great skill in perspective) <hi>of the doctrine of the Trinity, the
Deity of our Saviour, and all supernaturall verities, as should endanger
all my benefices present or future:</hi> that <hi>this warning was given me, not out
of feare of what I could say (for that Catholiques if they might wish any ill
would beg the Publication of my booke, for respects obvious enough,) but
out of a meer charitable desire of my good and reputation:</hi> and <hi>that all this
was said upon a supposition that I was answering, or had a minde to answer
Charity maintained; If not, no harme was done.</hi> To which co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>us
premonition as I remember, I desired the Gentleman, who dealt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
us to return this answer, or to this effect, that I believed the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of the Trinity, the Deity of our Saviour, and all other super-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
verities revealed in Scripture, as truly and as heartily as your self,
or any man: and therefore herein your <hi>Charity</hi> was very much <hi>mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken;</hi>
but much more and more uncharitably in conceiving me a man
that was to be wrought upon with these <hi>Terribiles visu formae,</hi> those
carnall and base fears which you presented to me, which were very
proper motives for the Divell and his instruments to tempt poor spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited
men out of the way of conscience and honesty, but very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous,
either for Teachers of truth to make use of, or for Lovers of
truth (in which Company I had been long agoe matriculated) to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="7"/>
to with any regard. But if you were indeed desirous that I should
not answer <hi>Charity maintained,</hi> one way there was, and but one,
whereby you might obtain your desire; and that was by letting mee
know when and where I might attend you, and by a fair conference, to
be written down on both sides, convincing mine understanding (who
was resolv'd not to be a <hi>Recusant</hi> if I were <hi>convicted,</hi>) that any one
part of it, any one argument in it, which was of moment and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
and whereon the cause depends, was indeed unanswerable.
This was the effect of my answer which I am well assur'd was delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:
but reply from you I received none but this, that you would
have no conference with me but in Print; and soone after finding me of
proof against all these batteries, and thereby (I fear) very much en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
you tooke up the resolution of the furious Goddesse in the Poet,
madded with the unsuccessefulnesse of her malice, <hi>Flectere si neque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
superos Acherontamovebo!</hi>
   </p>
   <p>6 For certainly those indigne contumelies, that masse of porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
and execrable calumnies, wherewith in your Pamphlet of <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
to N. N.</hi> you have loaded not only my person in particular, but
all the learned and moderate Divines of the Church of England, and
all Protestants in generall, nay all wise men of all Religions but your
own, could not proceed from any other fountain.</p>
   <p>7 To begin with the last, you stick not in the beginning of your
first Chapter, to fasten the imputation <hi>of Atheisme &amp; irreligion upon all
wise and gallant men, that are not of your own Religion.</hi> In which uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable
and unchristian judgment, void of all colour or shadow of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability,
I know yet by experience that very many of the <hi>Bigots</hi> of
your Faction are partakers with you. God forbid I should think the
like of you! Yet if I should say, that in your Religion there want not
some temptations unto, and some Principles of irreligion and Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isme,
I am sure I could make my assertion much more probable then
you have done, or can make this horrible imputation.</p>
   <p>8 For to passe by <hi>first,</hi> that which experience justifies, that where
and when your Religion hath most absolutely commanded, there and
then Atheisme hath most abounded; To say nothing <hi>Secondly,</hi> of your
notorious and confessed forging of so many false miracles, and so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
lying Legends, which is not unlikely to make suspitious men to
question the truth of all; Nor to object to you <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the abundance
of your weak and silly Ceremonies &amp; ridiculous observances in your
Religion, which in all probability cannot but beget secret contempt
and scorne of it in wise and considering men, and consequently Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isme
and impiety, if they have this perswasion setled in them (which is
too rise among you, and which you account a peece of <hi>Wisdome and
Gallantry</hi>) that if they be not of your Religion, they were as good be of
none at all; Nor to trouble you <hi>Fourthly</hi> with this, that a great part of
your Doctrine, especially in the points contested, makes apparently for
the temporall ends of the teachers of it; which yet I feare is a great
scandall to many <hi>Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>x Esprits</hi> among you: Onely I should desire you
to consider attentively when you conclude so often from the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="8"/>
of Protestants, that they have no certainty of any part of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
no not of those points wherein they agree, whether you doe not
that which so magisterially you direct me not to doe, that is, proceed <hi>a
destructive way, and object arguments against your adversaries, which
tend to the overthrow of all Religion?</hi> And whether as you argue thus,
<hi>Protestants differ in many things, therefore they have no certainty of any
thing:</hi> So an Atheist or a Sceptique may not conclude as well, Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
and the Professors of all Religions differ in many things, therefore
they have no certainty of any thing? Again I should desire you to tell
me ingenuously, whether it be not too probable that your portentous
Doctrine of Transubstantiation joyn'd with your fore-mention'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion
of, <hi>no Papists no Christians,</hi> hath brought a great many others
as well as himselfe to <hi>Averroes</hi> his resolution, <hi>Quandoquidē Christiani
adorant quod comedunt, sit anima mea cum Philosophis?</hi> Whether your
requiring men upon only probable and <hi>Prudentiall motives,</hi> to yield a
<hi>most certaine assent</hi> unto things in humane reason impossible, and telling
them, as you doe too often, that they were as good not believe at all,
as believe with any lower degree of faith, be not a likely way to make
considering men scorne your Religion, (and consequently all, if they
know no other) as requiring things contradictory, and impossible to
be performed? Lastly, whether your pretence that there is no good
ground to believe Scripture, but your Churches infallibility, joyn'd
with your pretending no ground for this but some texts of Scripture,
be not a faire way to make them that understand themselves, believe
neither Church nor Scripture?</p>
   <p>9 <hi>Your calumnies against Protestants in generall are set downe
in these words, Chap.</hi> 2. §. 2. The very doctrine of Protestants if it bee
followed closely, and with coherence to it selfe, must of necessity induce
<hi>Socinianisme.</hi> This I say confidently, and evidently prove, by instancing
in one errror, which may well be tearmed the Capitall, and mother Heresy,
from which all other must follow at ease; I mean, their heresy in affirming,
that the perpetuall visible Church of Christ, descended by a never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted
succession from our Saviour, to this day, is not infallible in all
that it proposeth to be believed, as revealed truths.</p>
   <p>For if the <hi>infallibility</hi> of such a publique <hi>Authority</hi> be once impeached;
what remaines, but that every man is given over to his own wit, and <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course?</hi>
And talke not here, of holy Scripture. For if the true Church
may erre, in defining what Scriptures be Canonicall; or in delivering the
sense and meaning thereof, we are still devolved, either upon the <hi>private
spirit</hi> (a foolery now explo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed out of England, which finally leaving every
man to his own conceits, ends in <hi>Socinianisme)</hi> or else upon naturall wit,
and judgement. for examining and determining, what Scriptures contain
true or false doctrine, and in that respect, ought to be received, or reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.
And indeed, take away the authority of Gods Church, no man can
be assured, that any one Book, or parcell of Scripture, was written by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
inspiration; or that all the contents, are infallibly true; which are the
direct errors of <hi>Socinians.</hi> If it were but for thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> reason alone, no man,
who regards the eternall salvation of his soule, would live or dye in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testancy,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
from which, so vast absurdities as these of the <hi>Socinians</hi> must
inevitably follow. And it ought to be an unspeakable comfort to all us
Catholiques, while we consider, that none can deny the infallible authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of our Church, but joyntly he must be left to his own wit and waies; and
must abandon all <hi>infused faith,</hi> and true Religion, if he doe but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
himselfe aright.</p>
   <p>In all which discourse, the only true word you speak is, <hi>This I say
confidently:</hi> As for <hi>proving evidently,</hi> that I believe you reserved
for some other opportunity: for the present I am sure you have been
very sparing of it.</p>
   <p>10 You say indeed confidently enough, that <hi>the denyall of the
Churches infallibility is the Mother Heresy, from which all other must
follow at ease:</hi> Which is so farre from being a necessary truth, as you
make it, that it is indeed a manifest falshood. Neither is it possible
for the wit of man by any good, or so much as probable consequence,
from the deniall of the Churches Infallibility to deduce any one of the
ancient Heresies, or any one error of the Socinians, which are the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies
here entreated of. For who would not laugh at him that should ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
thus; Neither the Church of Rome, nor any other Church is infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<hi>go,</hi> The doctrine of <hi>Arrius, Pelagius, Eutyches, Nestorius, Photinus,
Manichaeus</hi> was true Doctrine? On the other side, it may be truly sayed
and justified by very good and effectuall reason, that he that affirms
with you, the Popes infallibility, puts himself into his hands and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
to be led by him at his ease and pleasure into all Heresy, and even to
Hell it self, and cannot with reason say (so long as he is constant to his
grounds) <hi>Domine cur ita facis?</hi> but must believe <hi>white to be black and
black to be white, vertue to be vice and vice to be vertue;</hi> nay (which is
a horrible but a most certain truth) Christ to be Antichrist and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ
to be Christ, if it be possible for the Pope to say so: Which I say
and will maintain, howsoever you daube and disguise it, is indeed to
make men Apostate from Christ to his pretended Vicar, but reall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.
For that name and no better (if we may speak truth without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence)
I presume he deserves, who under pretence of interpreting the
law of Christ, (which Authority without any word of expresse war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
he hath taken upon himself,) doth in many parts evacuate and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve
it: So dethroning Christ from his dominion over mens conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and in stead of Christ, setting up himself. In as much as he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
that his interpretations of any law should be obeyed as true and
genuine, seeme they to mens understandings never so dissonant and
discordant from it, (as the Bishop of Rome does) requires indeed that
<hi>his interpretations</hi> should be the <hi>Laws;</hi> and he that is firmly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
in mind to believe and receive all such interpretations without
judging of them, and though to his private judgment they seem unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable,
is indeed congruously disposed to hold adultery a veniall sin,
and fornication no sinne, whensoever the Pope and his adherents shall
so declare. And whatsoever he may plead, yet either wittingly or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly
he makes the Law and the Lawmaker both stales, and obeyes
only the interpreter. As if I should pretend that I should submit to the
<pb facs="9"/>
Laws of the King of England, but should indeed resolve to obey them
in that sence which the King of France should put upon them what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
it were; I presume every understanding man would say that I did
indeed obey the King of France and not the King of England. If I
should pretend to believe the Bible, but that I would understand it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the sence which the chiefe Mufty should put upon it, who
would not say that I were a Christian in pretence only, but indeed a
Mahumetan?</p>
   <p>11 Nor will it be to purpose for you to pretend that the precepts
of Christ are so plain that it cannot be feared, that any Pope should ever
goe about to dissolve them and pretend to be a Christian: For, not to
say that you now pretend the contrary, (to wit), <hi>that the law of Christ
is obscure even in things necessary to be believed and done;</hi> and by saying
so, have made a fair way for any fowle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> interpretation of any part of it:
certainly that which the Church of Rome hath already done in this
kind is an evident argument, that (if she once had this power unquesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd
and made expedite and ready for use, by being contracted to the
Pope) she may doe what she pleaseth with it. Who that had liv'd
in the Primitive Church, would not have thought it as utterly impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,
that ever they should have brought in the worship of Images and
picturing of God, as now it is that they should legitimate fornication?
Why may we not think they may in time take away the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
from the Laity, as well as they have taken away half of it?
Why may we not think that any Text and any sence may not be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
aswell as the whole 14. <hi>Ch.</hi> of the <hi>Ep.</hi> of <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinth.</hi>
is reconcil'd to the Latine service? How is it possible any thing should
be plainer forbidden, then the <hi>worship of Angels,</hi> in the <hi>Ep.</hi> to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lossians?</hi>
then <hi>the teaching for Doctrines mens commands</hi> in the Gospell
of <hi>S. Mark?</hi> And therefore seeing we see these things done which
hardly any man would have believ'd, that had not seen them, why
should we not fear that this unlimited power may not be us'd hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
with as litle moderation? Seeing devices have been invented how
men may worship images without Idolatry, and kill innocent men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
pretence of heresie without murder, who knowes not that some
tricks may not be hereafter deuis'd, by which lying with other mens
wives shall be no Adultery, taking away other mens goods no theft?
I conclude therefore, that if <hi>Solomon</hi> himself were here, and were to
determine the difference, which is more likely to be mother of all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy,
The <hi>deniall</hi> of the <hi>Churche's</hi> or the <hi>affirming</hi> of the <hi>Popes infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi>
that he would certainly say <hi>this is the mother, give her the child.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>12 You say again confidently, that <hi>if this infallibility be once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached,
every man is given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ver to his own wit and discourse:</hi> which,
if you mean, <hi>discourse,</hi> not guiding it selfe by Scripture, but only by
principles of nature, or perhaps by prejudices and popular errors, and
drawing consequences not by rule but chance, is by no means true; if
you mean by discourse, right reason, grounded on Divine revelation
and common notions, written by God in the hearts of all men, and
<pb facs="9"/>
deducing, according to the never failing rules of Logick, consequent
deductions from them, if this be it, which you mean by <hi>discourse,</hi> it is
very meet &amp; reasonable &amp; necessary that men, as in all their actions,
so especially in that of greatest importance, the choice of their way to
happinesse, should be left unto it: and he that followes this in all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions
and actions, and does not only seeme to doe so, followes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
God; whereas he that followeth a Company of men, may
oftimes follow a company of beasts. And in saying this, I say no more
then S. <hi>Iohn</hi> to all Christians in these words, <hi>Dearly beloved believe
not every spirit, but try the spirits, whether they be of God, or no:</hi> and
the rule he gives them to make this tryall by, is to consider whether
they <hi>confesse Iesus to be the Christ;</hi> that is, the Guide of their Faith, and
Lord of their actions; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> whether they acknowledge the Pope to be
his Vicar: I say no more then S. <hi>Paul</hi> in exhorting all Christians, <hi>to try
all things and to hold fast that which is good;</hi> then S. <hi>Peter</hi> in cōmanding
all Christians, <hi>to be ready to give a reason of the hope that is in them:</hi>
then <hi>our Saviour</hi> himselfe in forewarning all his followers, that <hi>if
they blindly followed blind guides, both leaders and followers should fall
into the ditch;</hi> and again in saying even to the people, <hi>Yea &amp; why of your
selves iudge ye not what is right?</hi> And though by passion, or precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
or preiudice; by want of reason, or not using that they have, men
may be and are oftentimes led into error and mischiefe; yet that they
cannot be misguided by discourse truly so called, such as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed,
you your selfe have given them security. For what is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
but drawing conclusions out of premises by good conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence?
Now the principles which we have setled, to wit, the
<hi>Scriptures,</hi> are on all sides agreed to be infallibly true. And you have
told us in the fourth chap. of this Pamphlet, that <hi>from truth no man
can by good consequence inferre falshood;</hi> Therefore by discourse no
man can possibly be led to error: but if he erre in his conclusions, he
must of necessity either erre in his principles, (which here cannot have
place,) or commit some error in his discourse; that is indeed, not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
but seeme to doe so.</p>
   <p>13 You say thirdly with sufficient confidence, that <hi>if the true
Church may erre in defining what Scriptures be Canonicall, or in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
the sense thereof, then we must follow either the privat Spirit, or
else naturall wit and iudgement, and by them examine what Scriptures
containe true or false doctrine, and in that respect ought to be received or
reiected:</hi> All which is apparently untrue, neither can any proofe of it
be pretended. For though the present Church may possibly erre in her
judgement touching this matter, yet have we other directions in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
the privat spirit, and the examination of the contents, (which lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
way may conclude the negative very strongly, to wit, that such or
such a book cannot come from God, because it containes irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
contradictions, but the affirmative it cannot conclude, because the
contents of a book may be all true, and yet the book not written by
divine inspiration:) other direction therefore I say we have, besides ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of these three, &amp; that is, the testimony of the Primitive Christians.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
14 You say Fourthly with convenient boldnesse, That <hi>this infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
Authority of your Church being denied, no man can be assur'd, that
any parcell of Scripture was written by Divine inspiration:</hi> Which is an
untruth, for which no proofe is pretended, and besides, void of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty
and full of impiety. The first, because the experience of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Christians is against it, who are sufficiently assur'd, that the
Scripture is divinely inspir'd, and yet deny the infallible authority of
your Church or any other. The second, because if<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I cannot have
ground to be assur'd of the divine authority of Scripture, unlesse I first
believe your Church infallible, then I can have no ground at all to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
it: because there is no ground, nor can any be pretended why I
should believe your Church <hi>infallible,</hi> unlesse I first beleeve the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
divine.</p>
   <p>15 Fiftly and lastly, You say with confidence in abundance, that
<hi>none can deny the infallible authority of your Church, but he must aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
all infus'd faith and true religion, if he doe but understand him selfe:</hi>
Which is to say, agreeable to what you had said before, and what out
of the abundance of your hearts you speak very often, <hi>That all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians
besides you, are open Fooles, or conceal'd Atheists.</hi> All this you
say with notable confidence (as the manner of Sophisters is, to place
their confidence of prevailing in their confident manner of speaking,)
but then for the evidence you promised to maintaine this confidence,
that is quite vanished and become invisible.</p>
   <p>16 Had I a mind to recriminate now, and to charge Papists (as
you doe Protestants) that they lead men to Socinianisme, I could cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
make a much fairer shew of evidence then you have done. For
I would not tell you, you deny the infallibility of the Church of
England, <hi>ergo</hi> you lead to Socinianisme, which yet is altogether as
good an Argument as this; Protestants deny the infallibility of the
Roman Church, <hi>ergo</hi> they induce Socinianisme: Nor would I resume
my former Argument, and urge you, that by holding the Popes infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility,
you submit your selfe to that capitall and Mother Heresy, by
advantage whereof, he may lead you at ease to believe <hi>vertue vice,</hi> and
<hi>vice vertue,</hi> to believe Antichristianity Christianisme, and Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Antichristian; he may lead you to Socinianisme, to Turcisme,
nay to the Divell himselfe if he have a mind to it: But I would shew
you that divers waies the Doctors of your Church doe the principall
and proper work of the Socinians for the, undermining the Doctrine
of the Trinity, by denying it to be supported by those pillars of the
Faith, which alone are fit and able to support it, I mean Scripture, and
the Consent of the ancient Doctors.</p>
   <p>17 For <hi>Scripture,</hi> your men deny very plainly and frequently, that
this Doctrine can be proved by it. See if you please this plainly taught,
and urged very earnestly by Cardinall <hi>Hosius, De Author. Sac. Scrip.
l. 3. p.</hi> 53. By <hi>Gordonius Huntlaeus, Contr. Tom. 1. Controv. 1. De verbo
Dei C.</hi> 19. by <hi>Gretserus</hi> and <hi>Tanerus, in Colloquio Ratesbon:</hi> And also by
<hi>Vega, Possevin, Wiekus,</hi> and <hi>Others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>18 And then for <hi>the Consent of the Ancients,</hi> that that also deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb facs="10"/>
it not, by whom are we taught but by Papists only? Who is it
that makes known to all the world, that <hi>Eusebius</hi> that great searcher
and devourer of the Christian libraries <hi>was an Arrian?</hi> Is it not your
great <hi>Achilles, Cardinall Perron,</hi> in his 3. Book 2. Chap. of his Reply to
<hi>K. Iames?</hi> Who is it that informs us that <hi>Origen</hi> (who never was questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
for any error in this matter, in or neere his time) <hi>denied the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
of the Sonne and the Holy Ghost?</hi> Is it not the same great Cardinall,
in his Book <hi>of the Eucharist</hi> against <hi>M. du Plessis. l. 2. c.</hi> 7? Who is it
that pretends that <hi>Irenaeus hath said those things, which he that should
now hold, would be esteem'd an Arrian?</hi> Is it not the same <hi>Perron</hi> in his
Reply to K. <hi>Iames,</hi> in the fift Chap. of his fourth observation? And
does he not in the same place peach <hi>Tertullian</hi> also, &amp; in a manner give
him away to the Arrians? And pronounce generally of the <hi>Fathers
before the Councell of Nice,</hi> That <hi>the Arrians would gladly be tryed by
them?</hi> And are not your fellow Iesuits also, even the prime men of
your Order, prevaricators in this point as well as others? Doth not
your friend M. <hi>Fisher,</hi> or M. <hi>Flued</hi> in his book of the Nine Questions
proposed to him by K. <hi>Iames</hi> speak dangerously to the same purpose,
in his discourse <hi>of the Resolution of Faith,</hi> towards the end? Giving us to
understand, <hi>That the new Reformed Arrians bring very many testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
of the ancient Fathers to prove that in this Point they did contradict
themselves and were contrary one to another: which places whosoever shall
read will cleerely see, that to common people they are unanswerable, yea
that common people are not capable of the answers that learned men yeeld
unto such obscure passages.</hi> And hath not your great Antiquary <hi>Petavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
in his Notes upon <hi>Epiphanius in Haer.</hi> 69. been very liberall to the
Adversaries of the Doctrine of the Trinity, and in a manner given
them for Patrons and Advocates, first <hi>Iustin Martyr,</hi> and then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
all the Fathers before the Councell of Nice, whose speeches he
saies, touching this point, <hi>cum Orthodoxae fidei regula minime consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt?</hi>
Hereunto I might adde that the Dominicans and Iesuits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
them in another matter of great importance, viz. <hi>Gods Presci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
of future contingents,</hi> give the Socinians the premises, out of
which their conclusion doth unavoidably follow. For the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ans
maintain on the one Side, that <hi>God can foresee nothing but what he
Decrees:</hi> The Iesuits on the other Side, that <hi>he doth not Decree all
things:</hi> And from hence the Socinians conclude (as it is obvious for
them to doe) that <hi>he doth not foresee all things.</hi> Lastly, I might adjoyn
this, that you agree with one consent, and settle for a rule unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
that no part of Religion can be repugnant to reason, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you in particular subscribe unawares in saying, <hi>From truth no man
can by good consequence inferre Falshood,</hi> which is to say in effect, that
Reason can never lead any man to error: And after you have done so,
you proclaime to all the world (as you in this Pamphlet doe very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently,)
that <hi>if men follow their Reason and discourse,</hi> they will (if they
understand themselves) be led to Socinianisme. And thus you see
with what probable matter I might furnish out and justify my accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation,
if I should charge you with leading men to Socinianisme! Yet
<pb facs="11"/>
I doe not conceive that I have ground enough for this odious impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
And much lesse should you have charg'd Protestants with it,
whom you confesse to abhorre and detest it: and who fight against it
not with the broken reeds, and out of the paper fortresses of an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
Infallibility, which were only to make sport for their Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;
but with the <hi>sword of the Spirit, the Word of God:</hi> of which we may
say most truly, what <hi>David</hi> said of <hi>Goliah's</hi> sword, offered him by <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,
non est sicut iste, There is none comparable to it.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>19 Thus Protestants in generall, I hope, are sufficiently vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
from your calumny: I proceed now to doe the same service for the
Divines of England; whom you question first in point of learning
and sufficiency, and then in point of conscience and honesty, as preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricating
in the Religion which they professe, and inclining to Popery.
Their Learning (you say) consists only in <hi>some superficiall talent of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
languages, and elocution, and not in any deep knowledge of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,
especially of Metaphysicks, and much lesse of that most solid, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
subtile,</hi> &amp; (O rē ridiculā <hi>Cato</hi> &amp; jocosā!) <hi>succinct method of School-Divinity.</hi>
Wherein you have discovered in your self the true Genius
and spirit of detraction. For taking advantage from that wherein envy
it self cannot deny but they are very eminent, and which requires great
sufficiency of substantiall learning, you disparage them as insufficient in
all things else. As if forsooth, because they dispute not eternally, <hi>Vtrū
Chimaera bombinans in vacuo, possit comedere, secundas Intentiones? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
a Million of Angels may not sit upon a needles point?</hi> Becuase they
fill not their brains with notions that signify nothing, to the utter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination
of all reason and common sence, and spend not an Age in
weaving and un-weaving subtile cobwebs, fitter to catch flyes then
Souls; therefore they have no deepe knowledge in the Acroamaticall
part of learning! But I have too much honour'd the poornesse of this
detraction to take notice of it.</p>
   <p>20 <hi>The other Part of your accusation strikes deeper, and is more cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable:
And that tels us that,</hi> Protestantisme waxeth weary of it self;
that the Professors of it, they especially of greatest worth, learning, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
love temper and moderation: and are at this time more unresolved
where to fasten, then at the infancy of their Church: <hi>That</hi> their Churches
begin to look with a new face: Their w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lls to speak a new language: Their
Doctrine to be altered in many things for which their Progenitors forsook
the then Visible Church of Christ: For example, the Pope not Antichrist:
Prayer for the dead: Limbus Patrum: Pictures: That the Church hath Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
in determining Controversies of Faith, and to interpret Scripture;
about Freewill, Predestination, Vniversall grace: <hi>That</hi> all our works are
not sinnes: Merit of good works: Inherent Iustice: Faith alone doth not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify:
Charity to be preferr'd before knowledge: Traditions: Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
possible to be kept: <hi>That</hi> their thirty nine Articles are patient, nay
ambitious of some sence wherein they may seem Catholique: <hi>That to</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage
the necessity of wife and children in these dayes is but a weak plea
for a married minister to compasse a Benefice: <hi>That</hi> Calvinisme is at length
accounted Heresy, and little lesse then treason: <hi>That</hi> men in talk and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="11"/>
use willingly the once fearfull names of Priests and Altars: <hi>That</hi> they
are now put in mind that for exposition of Scripture they are by Canon
bound to follow the Fathers: which if they doe with syncerity, it is easy to
tell what doome will passe against Protestants; seeing by the confession of
Protestants, the Fathers are on the Papists side, which the Answerer to
some so clearly demonstrated, that they remain'd convinc'd: In fine, as
the Samaritans saw in the Disciples countenances that they meant to goe
to Hierusalem, so you pretend it is even legible in the fore-heads of these
men, that they are even going, nay making hast to Rome. <hi>Which scurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
libell void of all truth, discretion and honesty, what effect it may
have wrought, what credit it may have gain'd with credulous Papists,
(who dream what they desire, and believe their own dreams,) or with
ill-affected, jealous, and weak Protestants, I can not tell: But one thing
I dare boldly say, that you your selfe did never believe it.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>21 For did you indeed conceive, or had any probable hope, that
such men as you describe, men of worth of learning and authority too,
were friends and favourers of your Religion, &amp; inclinable to your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
can any man imagine that you would proclaim it, and bid the world
take heed of them? <hi>Sic notus Vlysses?</hi> Doe we know the lesuites no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then so? What are they turned prevaricators against their own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?
Are they likely men to betray and expose their own Agents and
instruments, and to awaken the eyes of jealousy, and to raise the clamor
of the people against them? Certainly your Zeal to the Sea of Rome,
testified by your <hi>fourth Vow of speciall obedience to the Pope,</hi> proper to
your Order, and your cunning carriage of all affairs for the greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
and advancement of that Sea, are clear demonstrations that if
you had thought thus, you would never have said so. The truth is, they
that run to extreams in opposition against you, they that pull downe
your infallibility and set up their own, they that declaim against your
tyranny, and exercise it themselves over otheres, are the Adversaries
that give you greatest advantage, and such as you love to deale with:
whereas upon men of temper &amp; moderatiō, such as will oppose nothing
because you maintain it, but will draw as neere to you, that they may
draw you to them, as the truth will suffer them: such as require of
Christians to believe only in Christ, and will damne no man nor Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
without expresse and certaine warrant from gods word: upon
such as these you know not how to fasten; but if you chance to have
conference with any such, (which yet as much as possibly you can you
avoid and decline,) you are very speedily put to silence, and see the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defensible
weaknesse of your cause laid open to all men. And this I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
believe, is the true reason that you thus rave and rage against them,
as foreseeing your time of prevailing, or even of subsisting, would
be short, if other Adversaries gave you no more advantage then
they doe.</p>
   <p>22 In which perswasion also I am much confirmed by considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the sillynesse and poornesse of those suggestions, and partly of
the apparent vanity and falshood of them, which you offer in justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of this wicked calumny. For what if out of devotion towards
<pb facs="12"/>
God; out of a desire that he should be worshipped as <hi>in Spirit and truth</hi>
in the first place, so also <hi>in the beauty of holinesse?</hi> what if out of feare
that too much simplicity and nakednesse in the publique Service of
God may beget in the ordinary sort of men a dull and stupid irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
and out of hope that the outward state and glory of it, being
well dispos'd and wisely moderated, may ingender, quicken, increase
and nourish the inward reverence respect and devotion which is due
unto Gods Soveraign Majesty and power? what if out of a perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and desire that Papists may be wonne over to us the sooner, by the
removing of this scandall out of their way; and out of an holy jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy,
that the weaker sort of Protestants might be the easier seduced to
them by the magnificence and pomp of their Church-service in case it
were not removed? I say, what if out of these considerations, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors
of our Church, more of late then formerly, have set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
to adorn and beautifie the places <hi>where Gods honour dwells,</hi> and
to make them as heavenly as they can with earthly ornaments? Is
this a signe that they are warping towards Popery? Is this Devotion
in the Church of England an argument that shee is coming over to
the Church of Rome? Sir <hi>Edwin Sands,</hi> I presume every man will
grant, had no inclination that way; yet he forty years since highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
this part of devotion in Papists, and makes no scruple of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing
it to the imitation of Protestants: Litle thinking that they who
would follow his counsell, and endeavour to take away this dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
of Protestants, and this glorying of Papists, should have been
censur'd for it as making way and inclining to Popery. His words to
this purpose are excellent words, and because they shew plainly, that
what is now practis'd was approv'd by Zealous Protestants so long
agoe,<note place="margin">Survey of Religion. <hi>Init.</hi>
      </note> I will here set them down.</p>
   <p>23 This one thing I cannot but highly commend in that sort and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:
They spare nothing which either cost can perform in enriching, or skill
in adorning the Temple of God, or to set out his Service with the greatest
pompe and magnificence that can be devised. And although, for the most
part, much basenesse and childishnesse is predominant in the Masters and
contrivers of their Ceremonies, yet this outward state and glory being
well disposed, doth ingender, quicken, increase, and nourish the inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,
respect and devotion, which is due unto Soveraign Majesty and
Power. And although I am not ignorant that many men well reputed have
embraced the thrifty opinion of that Disciple who thought all to be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
that was bestowed upon Christ in that sort, and that it were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
bestowed upon him on the poor, (yet with an eye perhaps that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
would be his quarter Almoners,) notwithstanding I must confesse,
it will never sink into my heart, that in proportion of reason, the allowance
for furnishing out of the service of God should be measured by the scant
and strict rule of meere necessity, (a proportion so low that nature to other
most bountifull in matter of necessity, hath not fayled no not the most igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
creatures of the world,) and that for our selves no measure of heaping
but the most we can get, no rule of expence but to the utmost pompe we
list: Or that God himself had so inrich'd the lower parts of the world
<pb facs="12"/>
with such wonderfull varieties of beauty and glory, that they might serve
only to the pampering of mortall man in his pride; and that in the Service
of the high creator Lord and giver (the outward glory of whose higher
pallace may appear by the very lamps that we see so farre of burning glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously
in it) only the simpler, baser, cheaper, lesse noble, lesse beautifull, lesse
glorious things should be imployed. Especially seeing as in Princes courts,
so in the service of God also, this outward state and glory, being well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spos'd,
doth (as I have said) ingender, quicken, increase and nourish the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
reverence, respect and devotion, which is due to so Soveraign majesty
and power. Which those whom the use there of cannot perswade unto, would
easily by the want of it be brought to confesse; for which cause I crave
leave to be excused by them herein, if in Zeal to the common Lord of all,
I choose rather to commend the vertue of an enemy then to flatter the vice
and imbecility of a friend. <hi>And so much for this matter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>24 Again, what if the names of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Altars</hi> so frequent in
the ancient Fathers, though not in the now Popish sense, be now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd
and more commonly used in England then of late times they
were: that so the colourable argument of their conformity, which is
but nominall, with the ancient Church, and our inconformity, which
the Governors of the Church would not have so much as nominall,
may be taken away from them▪ and the Church of England may be
put in a state, in this regard more justifiable against the Roman then
formerly it was, being hereby enabled to say to Papists (whensoever
these names are objected,) we also use the names of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Altars,</hi>
and yet believe neither the corporall Presence, nor any Proper and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory
Sacrifice?</p>
   <p>25 What if Protestants be now put in mind, that for exposition
of Scripture, they are bound by a Canon <hi>to follow the ancient Fathers:</hi>
which whosoever doth with syncerity, it is utterly impossible he should
be a Papist? And it is most falsely said by you, that you know that to
some Protestants, I cleerly demonstrated, or ever so much as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took,
or went about to demonstrate the contrary. What if the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists
be censur'd somewhat roundly by a Protestant Divine for affrm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
that <hi>the keeping of the Lords day was a thing indifferent for two
hundred yeares?</hi> Is there in all this or any part of it any kind of proofe
of this scandalous calumny? Certainly if you can make no better argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
then these, and have so little judgement as to think these any,
you have great reason to decline conferences, and <hi>Signior Con</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite
you from writing books any more.</p>
   <p>26 As for the points of Doctrine wherein you pretend that these
Divines begin of late to falter, and to comply with the Church of
Rome, upon a due examination of particulars it will presently appear,
First, that part of them alwaies have been, and now are held constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
one way by them; as the Authority of the Church in determining
Controversies of faith, though not the infallibility of it: That there is
Inherent Iustice, though so imperfect that it cannot justify: That there
are Traditions, though none necessary: That charity is to be preferr'd
before knowledge: That good Works are not properly meritorious
<pb facs="13"/>
And lastly, that faith alone justifies, though that faith justifies not
which is alone. And secondly, for the remainder that they, every one
of them, have been anciently without breach of charity disputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
Protestants, such for example were the Questions about the
Popes being the Antichrist, The lawfulnesse of some kind of prayers
for the dead, the Estate of the Fathers souls, before Christs ascenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
Freewill, Predestination, Vniversall grace: The Possibility of
keeping Gods commandements. The use of Pictures in the Church:
Wherein that there hath been anciently diversity of opinion amongst
Protestants, it is justifyed to my hand by a witnesse, with you, beyond
exception, even your great friend M. <hi>Brerely, whose care, exactnesse and
fidelity</hi> (you say in your Preface) <hi>is so extraordinary great.</hi> Consult
him therefore: Tract. 3. Sect. 7. of his <hi>Apology:</hi> And in the 9. 10. 11. 14.
24. 26. 27. 37. Subdivisions of that <hi>Section,</hi> you shall see as in a mirror,
your selfe prov'd an egregious calumniator, for charging Protestants
with innovation and inclining to Popery, under pretence forsooth,
that their Doctrine beginnes of late to be altered in these points.
Whereas, M. <hi>Brerely</hi> will informe you, they have been anciently, and
even from the begining of the Reformation, controverted amongst
them, though perhaps the stream and current of their Doctors runne
one way, and only some brooke or rivulet of them the other.</p>
   <p>27 And thus my Friends, I suppose are cleerely vindicated, from
your scandalls and calumnies: It remaines now that in the last place I
bring my selfe fairely off from your foule aspersions, that so my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
may not be (as indeed howsoever it should not be) any disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
or disparagement to the cause, nor any scandall to weake Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</p>
   <p>28 Your injuries then to me (no way deserved by me, but by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
in opinion from you, wherein yet you surely differ from me as
much as I from you,) are especially three. For <hi>first</hi> upon heere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay, &amp;
refusing to give me oportunity of begetting in you a better understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of me, you charge me with a great number of false and impious
doctrines, which I will not name in particular, because I will not assist
you so farre in the spreading of my own undeserved defamation: but
whosoever teaches or holds them <hi>let him be Anathema!</hi> The summe
of them all cast up by your selfe, in your first chap. is this, <hi>Nothing
ought or can be certainly believed, farther then it may be proved by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of Naturall reason:</hi> (where I conceive Naturall reason is oppos'd
to supernaturall Revelation) and whosoever holds so <hi>let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema!</hi>
And moreover to clear my selfe once for all, from all imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of this nature, which charge me injuriously with deniall of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall
Verities, I professe syncerely, that I believe all those Books of
Scripture, which the Church of England accounts Canonicall, to be
the Infallible word of God: I believe all things evidently contained
in them; all things evidently, or even probably deducible from them:
I acknowledge all that to be Heresy, which by the Act of Parliament
<hi>primo of Q.</hi> ELIZ. is declar'd to be so, &amp; only to be so: And though
in such points which may he held diversly of divers men <hi>salvâ Fidei
<pb facs="13"/>
compage.</hi> I would not take any mans liberty from him, and humbly
beseech all men, that they would not take mine from me! Yet thus
much I can say (which I hope will satisfy any man of reason,) that
whatsoever hath been held necessary to salvation, either by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique
Church of all ages, or by the consent of Fathers, measur'd
by <hi>Vincentius Lyrinensis</hi> his rule, or is held necessary either by the
Catholique Church of this age, or by the consent of Protestants, or
even by the Church of England, that, against the Socinians, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
whatsoever, I doe verily believe and embrace.</p>
   <p>29 Another great and manifest injury you have done me, in charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
me to have forsaken your Religion, <hi>because it condus'd not to my
temporall ends,</hi> and suted not with my desires and designes: Which
certainly is a horrible crime, &amp; whereof if you could convince me, by
just and strong presumptions, I should then acknowledge my selfe to
deserve that opinion, which you would faine induce your credents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
that I chang'd not your Religion for any other but for none at all.
But of this great fault my conscience acquits me, and God, who only
knowes the hearts of all men, knowes that I am innocent? Neither
doubt I but all they who know me, and amongst them many Persons
of place and quality, will say they have reason in this matter to be my
compurgators. And for you, though you are very affirmative in your
accusation, yet you neither doe, nor can produce any proof or presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
for it, but forgeting your selfe, (as it is Gods will oftimes that
slanderers should doe) have let fall some passages which being well
weighed, will make considering men apt to believe, that you did not
believe your selfe. For how is it possible, you should believe that I
deserted your Religion for ends, &amp; against the light of my conscience,
out of a desire of preferment, and yet out of scruple of conscience,
should refuse (which also you impute to me,) to subscribe the 39 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,
that is, refuse to enter at the only common dore, which here
in England leads to preferment? Again how incredible is it that you
should believe, that I forsooke the profession of your Religion, as
not suting with my desires and designes, which yet reconciles the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying
of the pleasures and profits of sinne here, with the hope of
happinesse hereafter, and proposes as great hope of great temporall
advancements to the capable servants of it, as any, nay more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Religion in the world; and instead of this should choose Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme,
a Doctrine, which howsoever erroneous in explicating the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries
of Religion, and allowing greater liberty of opinion in specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
matters, then any other Company of Christians doth or they
should doe, yet certainly which you, I am sure, will pretend and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
to explicate the Lawes of Christ with more rigor, and lesse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence
and condescendence to the desires of flesh and blood then
your Doctrine doth! And besides, such a Doctrine by which no man
in his right mind, can hope for any honour or preferment either in this
Church or State or any other! All which cleerely demonstrates that
this foule and false aspersion, which you have cast upon mee, proceeds
from no other fountaine, but a heart abounding with the gall and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse
<pb facs="14"/>
of uncharitablenesse, and even blinded with malice towards
me, or else from a perverse zeale to your superstition, which secretly
suggests this perswasion to you, That for the Catholique cause no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
is unlawfull, but that you may make use of such indirect and
crooked arts as these, to blast my reputation, and to possesse mens
minds with disaffection to my person, least otherwise peradventure
they might with some indifference hear reason from me. God I hope
which bringeth light out of darknesse, will turne your counsells to foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnesse,
and give all good men grace to perceive how weak and rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
that Religion must be, which needs supportance from such tricks
and devices! So I call them because they deserve no better name: For
what are all these Personall matters, which hitherto you have spoke of,
to the businesse in hand? If it could be prov'd, that Cardinall <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>
was indeed a Iew, or that Cardinall <hi>Perron</hi> was an Atheist, yet I
presume you would not accept of this for an answer to all their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
in defence of your Religion. Let then my actions and intentions
and opinions be what they will, yet I hope truth is neverthelesse truth,
nor reason ever the lesse Reason because I speak it. And therefore the
Christian Reader, knowing that his Salvation or damnation depends
upon his impartiall and sincere judgment of these things, will guard
himself I hope from these impostures, and regard not the person but
the cause and the reasons of it; not who speakes but what is spoken:
Which is all the favour I desire of him, as knowing that I am desirous
not to perswade him, unlesse it be truth whereunto I perswade him.</p>
   <p>30 The third and la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t part of my Accusation was, that I answer ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
of <hi>Principles which Protestants themselves will professe to detest:</hi> which
indeed were to the purpose if it could be justified. But, besides that it is
confuted by my whole Book, and made ridiculous by the Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
premis'd unto it, it is very easy for mee out of your own mouth
and words to prove it a most injurious calumny. For what one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion
is there is the whole fabrick of my discourse, that is not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
deducible out of this one Principle, That <hi>all things necessary to
salvation are evidently contain'd in Scripture?</hi> Or what one Conclusion
almost of importance is there in your Book, which is not by this one
cleerly confutable? Grant this, and it will presently follow in opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to your first Conclusion, and the argument of your first Ch: that
amongst men of different opinions, touching the obscure and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
Questions of Religiō, such as may with probability be disputed
on both Sides (and such as are the disputes of Protestants;) Good men
and lovers of truth of all Sides may bee sav'd; because all necessary
things being suppos'd evident, concerning them, with men so quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
there will be no difference: There being no more certain signe that
a Point is not evident, then that honest and understanding and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
men, and such as give themselves liberty of judgment, after a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
consideration of the matter differ about it.</p>
   <p>31 Grant this, and it will appear <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the means whereby
the revealed Truths of God are conveyed to our understanding, and
which are to determine all Controversies in Faith, necessary to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined,
<pb facs="14"/>
may be, for any thing you have said to the contrary, not a
Church but the Scripture; which contradicts the Doctrine of your
<hi>Second Chapter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>32 Grant this, and the distinction of points Fundamentall and not
Fundamentall, will appear very good and pertinent. For those truths
will be fundamentall, which, are evidently delivered in Scripture and
commanded to be preach't to all men; Those not fundamentall which
are obscure. And nothing will hinder but that the Catholique Church
may erre in the latter kind of the said points: because Truths not neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary
to the Salvation, cannot be necessary to the being of a Church; and
because it is not absolutely necessary that God should assist his
Church any farther then to bring her to Salvation; neither will there
be any necessity at all of any infallible Guide, either to consigne unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
Traditions, or to declare the obscurities of the faith. Not for the
former end, because this Principle being granted true, nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written
can be necessary to be consign'd. Nor for the latter, because
nothing that is obcsure can be necessary to be understood, or not mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.
And so the discourse of your whole <hi>Third Chap:</hi> will presently
vanish.</p>
   <p>33 Fourthly, for the Creed's containing the Fundamentals of simple
belief, though I see not how it may be deduc'd from this principle, yet
the granting of this plainly renders the whole dispute touching the
Creed unnecessary. For if all necessary things of all sorts, whether of
simple belief or practice be confess'd to bee cleerly contain'd in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
what imports it whether those of one sort bee contain'd in the
Creed?</p>
   <p>34 Fiftly let this be granted, and the immediate Corollary in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
to your fift Ch: will be and must be, That, not Protestants for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting,
but the Church of Rome for imposing upon the Faith of
Christians, Doctrines unwritten and unnecessary, and for disturbing
the Churches peace and dividing Vnity for such matters, is in a high
degree presumptuous and Schismaticall.</p>
   <p>35 Grant this sixtly, and it will follow unavoidably that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
cannot possibly be Heretiques, seeing they believe all things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently
contain'd in Scripture, which are suppos'd to be all that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
to be believed: and so your <hi>Sixt Chapter</hi> is cleerly confuted.</p>
   <p>36 Grant this lastly, and it will be undoubtedly consequent, in
contradiction of your <hi>seaventh Chapter,</hi> that no man can shew more
charity to himself then by continuing a Protestant, seeing Protestants
are suppos' to believe, and therefore may accordingly practise, at least
by their Religion are not hindred from practising and performing all
things necessary to Salvation.</p>
   <p>37 So that the position of this one Principle, is the direct overthrow
of your whole Book, and therefore I needed not, nor indeed have I
made use of any other. Now this principle, which is not only the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
stone or chief Pillar, but even the base, and adequate foundation
of my Answer; and which while it stands firme and unmoveable, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but bee the supporter of my Book and the certain ruine of yours, is
<pb facs="15"/>
so farre from being, according to your pretence, detested by all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,
that all Protestants whatsoever, as you may see in their Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of confessions, unanimously professe and maintain it. And you
your selfe, C. 6. § 30. plainly confesse as much, in saying, <hi>The whole E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difice
of the faith of Protestants is setled on these two Principles: These
particular Books are Canonicall Scripture: And the sense and meaning
of them is plain and evident at least in all points necessary to Salvation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>38 And thus your venome against me is in a manner spent, saving
only that there remain two litle impertinencies, whereby you would
disable me from being a fit advocate for the cause of Protestants. The
first, because I refuse to subscribe the Artic. of the Ch. of England: The
second because I have set down in writing motives which sometime
induc'd mee to forsake Protestantisme, and hitherto have not answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
them.</p>
   <p>39 By the former of which objections it should seeme, that either
you conceive the 39 Articles the common Doctrine of all Protestants;
and if they be, why have you so often upbraided them with their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
and great differences? Or else that it is the peculiar defence of the
Church of England, and not the common cause of all Protestants,
which is here undertaken by me: which are certainly very grosse mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stakes.
And yet why hee who makes scruple of subscribing the truth
of one or two Propositions may not yet bee fit enough to maintain
that those who doe subscribe them are in a saveable condition, I doe
not understand. Now though I hold not the Doctrine of all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
absoluetly true, (which with reason cannot bee requir'd of mee
while they hold contradictions,) yet I hold it free from all impiety,
and from all error destructive of Salvation, or in it self damnable: And
this I think in reason may sufficiently qualifie me, for a maintainer of
this assertion, that <hi>Protestancie destroies not Salvation.</hi> For the Church
of England, I am perswaded that the constant Doctrine of it is so pure
and Orthodoxe, that whosoever believes it and lives according to it,
undoubtedly he shall be saved; and that there is no error in it which
may necessitate or warrant any man to disturbe the peace or renounce
the Communion of it. This in my opinion is all intended by Subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,
and thus much if you conceive mee not ready to subscribe, your
<hi>Charity</hi> I assure you is much <hi>mistaken.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>40 Your other objection against me is yet more impertinent and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous
then the former: Vnlesse perhaps it be a just exception against
a Physitian, that himself was sometimes in, and recover'd himself from
that disease which he undertakes to cure; or against a guide in a way,
that at first before hee had experience himself mistook it, and after,
wards, found his error and amended it. That noble writer <hi>Michael
de Montai'gne,</hi> was surely of a farre different mind; for hee will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
allow any Physitian competent, but only for such diseases as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
had pass'd through: And a farre greater then <hi>Montai'gne,</hi> even he
that said, <hi>Tu conversus confirma fratres,</hi> gives us sufficiently to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
that they which have themselves beene in such a state as to need
conversion, are not thereby made incapable of, but rather engag'd
<pb facs="15"/>
and oblig'd unto, and qualified for this charitable function.</p>
   <p>41 Neither am I guilty of that strange and preposterous zeale (as
you esteeme it) which you impute to me; for having been so long
carelesse in removing this scandall against Protestants, and answering
my own Motives, and yet now shewing such fervor in writing against
others. For neither are they other Motives, but the very same for
the most part with those which abused me, against which this Book
which I now publish, is in a manner wholly imployed: And besides,
though you Iesuits take upon you to have such large and universall
intelligence of all state affaires and matters of importance, yet I hope
such a contemptible matter, as an answer of mine to a litle peece of
paper, may very probably have been written and escaped your obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.
The truth is, I made an answer to them three yeares since and
better, which perhaps might have been published, but for two reasons:
one because the Motives were never publique, untill you made them
so; the other, because I was loath to proclaime to all the world so much
weaknesse as I shewed, in suffering my selfe to be abus'd by such silly
Sophismes; All which proceed upon mistakes and false suppositions,
which unadvisedly I took for granted; as when I have set down the
Motives in order by subsequent Answers to them I shall quickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate,
and so make an end. The Motives then were these.</p>
   <p>1 Because perpetuall visible profession, which could never be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Religion of Christ, nor any part of it, is apparently wanting to
Protestant Religion, so farre as concernes the points in contestation.</p>
   <p>2 Because <hi>Luther</hi> and his followers, separating from the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> separated also from all Churches, pure or impure, true or false
then being in the world; upon which ground I conclude, that either Gods
promises did faile of performance, if there were then no Church in the
world, which held all things necessary, and nothing repugnant to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
or else that <hi>Luther</hi> and his Sectaries, separating from all Churches
then in the world, and so from the true, if there were any true, were <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
Schismaticks.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>3 Because, if any credit may be given to as creditable records, as any
are extant, the Doctrine of Catholicks hath been frequently confirmed;
and the opposite doctrine of Protestants, confounded with supernaturall
and divine Miracles.</p>
   <p>4 Because many points of Protestant doctrine, are the damned opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of Hereticks, condemned by the Primitive Church.</p>
   <p>5 Because the Prophecies of the old Testament, touching the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of Kings and Nations to the true Religion of Christ, have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished
in and by the Catholicke <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, and the Professors of
it; and not by Protestant Religion, and the Professors of it.</p>
   <p>6 Because the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is conformable, and
the doctrine of Protestants contrary, to the doctrine of the Fathers of the
Primitive Church, even by the confession of Protestants themselves; I
meane, those fathers, who lived within the compasse of the first 600. years;
to whom Protestants themselves doe very frequently, and very confidently
appeale.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="16"/>
7 Because the first pretended Reformers had neither extraordinary
<hi>Commission</hi> from God, nor ordinary <hi>Mission</hi> from the Church, to preach
Protestant Doctrine.</p>
   <p>8 Because <hi>Luther,</hi> to preach against the Masse (which containes the
most materiall points now in controversy) was perswaded by reasons sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested
to him by the Divell himselfe, disputing with him. So himselfe
professeth in his Book <hi>de Missa Privata.</hi> That all men might take heed of
following him, who professeth himselfe to follow the Divell.</p>
   <p>9 Because the Protestant cause is now, and hath been from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
maintained with grosse falsifications, and Calumnies; whereof their
prime Controversy writers, are notoriously, and in high degree guilty.</p>
   <p>10 Because by denying all humane authority, either of Pope, or
Councells, or Church, to determine Controversies of Faith, they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished
all possible meanes of suppressing Heresy, or restoring unity to the
Church.</p>
   <p>These are the Motives; now my Answers to them follow brie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly
and in order.</p>
   <p>43 To the first: God hath neither decreed nor foretold, that his
true Doctrine should <hi>de facto</hi> be alwaies visibly prfessed, without any
mixture of falshood.</p>
   <p>To the second: God hath neither decreed nor foretold, that there
shall be alwaies a visible company of men free from all error in it selfe
damnable. Neither is it alwaies of necessity Schismaticall to separate
from the externall communion of a Church, though wanting nothing
necessary: For if this Church suppos'd to want nothing necessary, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
me to professe against my conscience, that I believe some error▪
though never so small and innocent, which I doe not believe, and will
not allow me her communion but upon this condition, In this case,
the Church for requiring this condition is Schismaticall, and not I for
separating from the Church.</p>
   <p>To the third: If any credit may be given to Records farre more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable
then these, the Doctrine of Protestants, that is the Bible hath
been confirm'd, and the Doctrine of Papists, which is in many points
plainly opposite to it, confounded with supernaturall and divine Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,
which for number and glory outshine Popish pretended Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,
as much as the Sunne doth an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> those I mean which
were wrought by our Saviour Christ and his Apostles, Now this
book, by the confession of all sides confirm'd by innumerous Miracles,
foretels me plainly, that in after ages great signes and wonders shall
be wrought in confirmation of false doctrine, and that I am not to
believe any doctrine which seemes to my understanding repugnant to
the first, though an Angell from Heaven should teach it; which were
certainly as great a Miracle as any that was ever wrought in attestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of any part of the doctrine of the Church of Rome: But that true
doctrine should in all ages have the testimony of Miracles, that I am
no where taught; So that I have more reason to suspect and be afraid
of pretended Miracles, as signes of false doctrine, then much to regard
them as certain arguments of the truth. Besides, setting aside the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="16"/>
&amp; the Tradition of it, there is as good story for Miracles wrought
by those who lived and died in opposition to the Doctrine of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
Church, (as by S. <hi>Cyprian, Colmannus, Columbanus, Aidanus</hi> and
others,) as there is for those that are pretended to be wrought by the
members of that Church. Lastly, it seemes to me no strange thing
that God in his Iustice should permit some true Miracles to be
wrought to delude them, who have forged so many as apparently the
professors of the Roman Doctrine have to abuse the World.</p>
   <p>To the fourth: All those were not<note n="a" place="margin">See this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd by Bellar: <hi>de Script: Eccles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>in Philastri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>:</hi> by <hi>Petavius Animad in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piph. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrip. operis▪</hi> By S. Austin▪ <hi>Lib. de Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Haer.</hi> 80▪</note> Heretiques which by <hi>Philastrius,
Epiphanius,</hi> or <hi>S. Austine</hi> were put in the Catalogue of Heretiques.</p>
   <p>To the fift: Kings and Nations have been and may be converted by
men of contrary Religions.</p>
   <p>To the sixt: The Doctrine of Papists, is confess'd by Papists contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to the Fathers in many points.</p>
   <p>To the seaventh: The Pastors of a Church cannot but have autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
from it, to preach against the abuses of it whether in Doctrine or
practice, if there be any in it: Neither can any Christian want an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
commission from God to doe a necessary work of Charity after a
peaceable manner, when there is no body else that can or will doe it.
In extraordinary cases extraordinary courses are not to be disallowed.
If some Christian Lay-man should come into a country of Infidels, &amp;
had ability to perswade them to Christianity, who would say he
might not use it for want of Commission!</p>
   <p>To the eighth: <hi>Luthers</hi> conference with the Divell might be, for
ought I know, nothing but a melancholy dreame: If it were reall, the
Divell might perswade Luther from the Masse, hoping by doing so to
keep him constant to it: Or that others would make his diswasion
from it an Argument for it, (as we see Papists doe) and be afraid of
following Luther, as confessing himselfe to have been perswaded by
the Divell.</p>
   <p>To the ninth: <hi>Illiacos intra muros peccatur &amp; extra.</hi> Papists are
more guilty of this fault then Protestants. Even this very author in
this very Pamphlet hath not so many leaves as falsifications and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies.</p>
   <p>To the tenth: Let all men believe the Scripture and that only, and
endeavour to believe it in the true sense, and require no more of others,
and they shall finde this not only a better, but the only meanes to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
Heresy, and restore Unity. For he that believes the Scripture
sincerely, and endeavours to believe it in the true sense, cannot possibly
be an Heretique: And if no more then this were requir'd of any
man, to make him capable of the Churches Communion,
then all men so qualified, though they were diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
in opinion, yet notwithstanding any
such difference, must be of necessity
one in Communion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>