<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>o the moste excel∣lente Prince, Edwarde the syxte, by the grace of God, Kyng of England, Fraunce and Irelande, Defendour of the fayth, and in earth, immediatly vnder God, supreme head of the church of Englande and Ire∣lande: your graces humble and obey∣saunt subiect Gwalter Lynne wy∣sheth aboundance of all grace and Godlynes wyth a long and prospe∣rous raygne.</title>
           <author>Lynne, Gwalter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107499_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17967</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107499</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>o the moste excel∣lente Prince, Edwarde the syxte, by the grace of God, Kyng of England, Fraunce and Irelande, Defendour of the fayth, and in earth, immediatly vnder God, supreme head of the church of Englande and Ire∣lande: your graces humble and obey∣saunt subiect Gwalter Lynne wy∣sheth aboundance of all grace and Godlynes wyth a long and prospe∣rous raygne.</title>
                 <author>Lynne, Gwalter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The thre bokes of cronicles, whyche Iohn Carion (a man syngularly well sene in the mathematycall sciences) gathered wyth great diligence of the beste authours that haue written in Hebrue, Greke or Latine : Whervnto is added an appendix, conteynyng all such notable thynges as be mentyoned in cronicles to haue chaunced in sundry partes of the worlde from the yeare of Christ. 1532. to thys present yeare of. 1550. Gathered by Iohn Funcke of Nurenborough. Whyche was neuer afore prynted in Englysh. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <author>Carion, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lynne (Lin), Walter (Gualter, Wouter van)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, cclxv, cclxvii-cclxxix, 13 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o the moste excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente Prince, Edwarde the syxte, by the grace of God, Kyng of England, Fraunce and Irelande, Defendour of the fayth, and in earth, immediatly vnder God, supreme head of the church of Englande and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande: your graces humble and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt subiect Gwalter Lynne wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth aboundance of all grace and Godlynes wyth a long and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous raygne.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsyderyng that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thynges past (most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prince) is most necessarye for such as woulde passe ouer the tyme to come in a decent and Godly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that the greatest nombre of youre Maiesties people doo not vnderstande other languages, then theyr naturall tounge:</p>
   <p>I haue thought it my duetye (beynge one that spendeth all hys tyme in the settynge forth of bokes in the Englyshe tounge) emongest all other to set forth thys shorte Cronicle.</p>
   <p>Wherein is briefly declared all that is nedefull to be knowen, concernyng thynges done in tymes
<pb facs="3"/>
passed. The learned haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> the latyne tounge, and therfore my laboure maye seme the lesse profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto them. But yet yf my knowledge would haue serued me to haue translated it as eloquētly as it is written in latyne: I doubt not but the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned also myghte haue founde some swetnes in my laboures. And not wythstandynge my rudenes (most excellent Prynce) I trust your maiestie wyll (after your accustomed clemencye) accept my good wyll, whyche thynge I do not doubte shall encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage all faythfull englyshe men to embrace my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures and gather the fruytes of the same. To prayse the worcke which being set forth to be reade of all men wyll prayse it self, were but a labour halfe loste, for such a thing nedeth no prayse, but is so ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifestly good that all men that reade it shalbe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to prayse it. Other prayse therfore I wyll not geue it, but that it is a worcke worthy the name of so excellent a prynce as your mayestye is, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worthy to be embraced of all your faythfull subiectes. Whyche thynge I most hartely wyshe to come to passe to the glorye of God, your Maiestyes honour, and the profyte of all your fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full subiectes. Sobeit.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces humble subiect and dayly Orator
Gwalter Lynne▪</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>