<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
A PREFACE IN THE NAME OF THE CHVRCHES OF FRAVNCE AND BELGIA, VVHICH PRO∣fesse the reformation of the Gospell. ⁂</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107818_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5155</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
A PREFACE IN THE NAME OF THE CHVRCHES OF FRAVNCE AND BELGIA, VVHICH PRO∣fesse the reformation of the Gospell. ⁂</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An harmony of the confessions of the faith of the Christian and Reformed Churches : which purelie professe the holy doctrine of the Gospell in all the chiefe kingdomes, nations, and prouinces of Europe: the catologue and order whereof the pages following will declare. There are added in the ende verie shorte notes: in which both the obscure thinges are made plaine, &amp; those thinges which maie in shew seeme to be contrarie each to other, are plainelie and verie modestlie reconciled, and if anie points doe as yet hang in doubt, they are sincerelie pointed at. All which things, in the name of the Churches of Fraunce and Belgia, are submitted to the free and discrete iudgement of all other Churches. Newlie translated out of Latine into English. Also in the end is added the confession of the Church of Scotland. Alowed by publique authoritie</title>
                 <author>Salnar</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thomas, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 111, 202-593, that is 609, 41, 24, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="3"/>
A PREFACE IN THE NAME OF THE CHVRCHES OF FRAVNCE AND BELGIA, VVHICH PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse the reformation of the Gospell. ⁂</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mbrose in a certaine place saith notablie, <hi>There ought to be no strife, but conference, among the seruants of Christ.</hi> For, seeing the dulnes of mans vnderstanding, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie in heauenlie matters, is such, that we can not oft times perceiue matters otherwise verie plaine, it can by no meanes be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that by mutuall conference, and friendly, and brotherly debating of the matter, we come to verie great light. And that especiallie seemeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and needful, that some should be set on edge by others, that those thinges which the Lord hath particularlie bestowed vpon seuerall members of the Church, may redound to the common bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the wholl bodie, and that all sinister affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on set a part, Christ, who is the Fathers wisdome,
<pb facs="4"/>
and the onely Master and teacher of the Church may be heard: and as he is the Prince of peace may so by his spirit ioyne together our mindes, that if it be possible, we maie all think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> one and the same thing in the Lorde. But to striue▪ braule, and fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and frowardlie to contend, as fensers doe, is so farre from becomming men that are taught of god, as that it is not seemely for modest or ciuill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. And if so be that in all, yea euen in the verie least affaires of mans life, that rule of modestie is to be kept, what, I pray you, is to be done, when we are in hand with God and Gods matters? Surelie holie things are holily and deuoutly to be handled, in the feare of god &amp; loue of our neighbour. Who, if he goe out of the way▪ is by the Spirit of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be called backe againe: but if he take the right waie, he is more and more to be instructed therein, to the end it may appeare, that we are not driuen by any motion of man, but that in all things our mindes are ruled and gouerned by God. Yet alas, such is the spot and staine of our times, that the euill custome of writing whatsoeuer, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of railing, hath seised vpon the wits &amp; mindes not of meane men onely, but euen of those▪ whom i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> most of all behooued to doe the cleane contrary. The roble of Iesuites, and such other like fellows, (whose verie rewarde is the earnest of bondage and cursed speaking) how shameleslie and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouslie they are caried against vs and the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: &amp; woh what bitternes they cast out against vs such things, as they haue bin taught in the schoole of shamelesnes, it ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e be sufficientlie perceiued of any man.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, when they feele them selues pressed with moste strong reasons, and ouercome with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse places of scripture, they runne to cauills and slaunders, as to the onelie refuge of their errours. They say wee haue reuolted from the Catholique Church▪ that we might follow the diuers imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men: they cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e aloud that we are heretikes, schis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atiques, and sectaries, and they oft times in mockage cal vs Confessionists: and moreouer they la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e in our dish, that wee neither agree with our selues, nor with others, whoe detest the bishoppe of Rome: but there are as many Religions among vs, as there are Confessions of Faith. And that they may seeme to procure credit to themselues, and to giue a check to the Germane Churches especiallie, they bring forth both certeine other writings, and especiallie that <hi>Forme</hi> of Agreement, of late pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished in Germanie, in which there are certaine things to be seene farre differing from those aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Confessions of Faith, which the Churches of the Gospell haue euen since the beginning giuen out. But let them so thinke, that the fault of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie is not to be laide vpon those, whose faith alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether relieth on moste sure grounds of scripture: that they are no schismatiques who intierly cleaue to Gods Church such an one as the Prophets &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles doe describe vnto vs: nor to be accounted sectaries, who embrace the truth of God, which is one and alwaies like it selfe. What doe they mean, I praie you, by the name of Confessionists so often repeated? For if euerie man be commaunded to make confession of his Faith so often as Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the edifying of the Church shall require;
<pb facs="5"/>
what a wonderfull or strange thing ought it to seeme, if Cities, if Prouinces, if wholl kingdomes haue made profession of their faith, when they were falsely charged by the Popish sorte, that they had gone from the doctrine of the true beleeuing Church? but they will saie, there ought to be one confession of faith and no moe: as though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth, a confession of faith were to be valued ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the words, then by the thing it selfe. What therefore will they saie to our ancetours, who when they had the Apostles Creede, yet for all that set out the Nicene, Chalcedonian, and manie moe such like Creedes? Those Creedes, saie you, were generall. Yea surelie, but so generall▪ that a great part of the world in those elder times follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the frantique heresies of the Arrians, whom the godlie forefathers by setting forth those Creedes desired to bring home into the Church againe. <hi>The trueth,</hi> saith Hilarie, <hi>was by the aduise and opinions of Bishops many waies sought, &amp; a reason of that which was meant was rendered by seuerall confessions of faith set downe in writing:</hi> And a litle after. <hi>It ought to seeme no maruell right welbeloued breethren, that mens faiths began to be declared so thick: the outrage of heretiques laieth this necessitie vpon vs.</hi> Thus much saide Hilarie. What that Athanasius, Augustine, and many other auncients set forth their Creedes also, that the puritie of Christian faith might more and more shine sorth. Therefore if Kingdoms, Cities, &amp; and whole prouinces haue priuatelie made confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of their faith, this was the cause therof, for that hitherto the state of times hath not suffered, that a generall Councell of all those, who professe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb facs="5"/>
religion, might be holden. But if it once come to passe (and the Lord graunt that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches maie at length inioy so great a benefit) then there may be one onelie confession of faith extant, conceiued in the same wordes, if the state of the Churches shal seeme to require it. Let them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaue of in mockage to terme vs Confessio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistes, vnles perhaps they looke for this answere at our hands, that it is a farre more excellent thing to beare a name of confessing the faith, then of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the trueth. For euen as moe smal streames may flow from one spring, so moe confessions of faith, may issue out from one and the same truth of faith.</p>
   <p>Now to speake somewhat also of those, who while they will seeme to embrace the trueth of the Gospell, and renounce popish errours, shew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues more vniust towards vs, then was meet they should, we are compelled to finde want of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an charitie inthem. This one thing in deed was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, that after so many daungers, losses, banish ments, downefalles, woes without number, griefes and torments, we should also be euill intreated by those, of whome some comforte was rather to be looked for. But that ancient enimie of the Church is farre deceiued (by whose subtilties this euil is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so wrought for vs) while he hopeth that we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e by his craftes be ouerwhelmed. But bearing our selues bolde on that loue, which the mercifull God through Iesus Christ our Lord beareth vnto vs, and whoe hath planted a loue and feare of him in our mindes, we leape for ioye in these verie thinges, and boast with the Apostle, that it will neuer be, (the same grace of God alwaies preuenting vs) that
<pb facs="6"/>
tribulation, anguish, hunger, nakednes, the sword, false accusation, or cursed speaking shall withdraw vs from the trueth once knowne and vndertaken. For we knowe that saying of Chrysostome to be true, <hi>It is not euill, to suffer; but to doe euill.</hi> Neither are we anie whit disgraced hereby, but they whom I know not what distemperature whetteth against vs hauing deserued nothing, &amp; to repaie them like for like, quitting rayling with rayling, far be it from vs, whom God vouchsafeth this honour, that being fashioned like to the image of his Sonne we might through good reporte and euill reporte walke on, vpholden with the staie of a good conscience, yea we haue resolued with our selues not only to abide the open wronges of our enimies, but euen the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine of our bretheren, although neuer so vniust.</p>
   <p>And what we furthermore think of the doctrine of our Lord Iesus Christ, the confession of our faith, set forth manie yeares agoe, hath made it knowen to the wholl world: and we haue God, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, together with men, witnesses of that sincere endeuour, by which we laboured, and doe as yet, to the vttermoste of our power, labour to set vp againe and maintaine the pure worshipe of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs out of Gods word.</p>
   <p>And, euen as we shewed our selues to be readie at all times to render a reason of the hope that is in vs: so we thought it a matter worth the paines, to make all men priuie to that bonde which one our parte is verie straight with the holie and truelie Catholike Church of God, with euerie Saint and sounde member thereof, that so farre as we c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, we might deliuer, partlie our selues, partly
<pb facs="6"/>
the Churches ioyned with vs from those moste greeuous crimes, by which some mens speaches &amp; bookes are laid to our charge. And when we be thought our selues by what means it might best be done, this especiallie for the present time seemed a meet waie vnto vs, which would giue offence to no man, &amp; might satisfie al that would yeald vnto rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, namelie to publish this <hi>Harmonie</hi> of confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby it might sufficientlie be vnderstood, howe falselie we are charged, as though we, that haue reiected popish errors, agreed not at al among our selues. For (to beginne with those stout main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of the Romish tyranny, who wil yet seeme to be defenders of the truth, this conference of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions will plucke euery visard from their faces, when as itshal plainely appeere, that al the opinions in these confessions of faith were in other sondrie words so laid down, that yet the same truth alwaies abideth, &amp; there is none at al, or very litle difference in the thinges themselues. And how narrow must they needs perceiue the boundes of that their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Churche to be, when it shalbe openlie knowen, that so many kingdomes, prouinces, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, peoples, &amp; nations professing the truth of the Gospell, doe with common consent renounce the abuses and orders of the Romish Church? As for those whome (without anie desert) it pleaseth to count vs among the Arrians and Turkes, they shal see also how farre through the benefit of God we be from such hainous and wicked errours. And they also, who accuse vs of sedition shall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue how reuerentlie we thinke of the dignitie of kings, and the Magistrates authoritie, and they to
<pb facs="7"/>
conclude that not being content with those pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique confessions of the Churches of Germanie, may by laying against vs that forme of new agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment seem worthelie more and more to seuer them selues from vs, and who haue alreadie very pithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie been refuted by moste learned writings, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so shall, if true agreement be earnestlie sought, be satisfied with this Harmonie. For (that we maie freelie saie as it is in deede) that long rancke of names sealed and written at that booke is such, that it seemeth rather to stand idlelie in the field, then to fight manfullie.</p>
   <p>And if it had pleased vs to followe this pollicie, we might haue set downe the names not of seuen or eight thousand meane men (most famous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and some other excepted) of whome it maie worthelie be doubted, whether there euer were anie such, or what they were, but also the names of farre moe Churches. And this our diligence had beene farre more commendable, namele, beeing bestowed, not in wringing out and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging from village to village some hundreds of names, but in laying out the opinions of moste gracious Kinges, moste renoumed Princes, of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nations, and peoples, of moste mightie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes and Cities: of which a great parte hath not bin vsed to dispute in corners, or to trifle, but hath knowen these manie yeares how euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bloode to suffer manie and greeuous thinges for Gods trueth sake. But we know that the truth hath not it warrant from men, nor by men: it is simple, it wilbe simplie published and taught. Therfore we are purposed for this time not to deale by any long
<pb facs="7"/>
disputation with anie man, but bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lie to open the meaning of the reformed Churches, to knit all the Churches of Christ together with one bond of brotherlie loue, to keepe peace with all men, and so farre as it ought to be done, to iudge well of all men: yea and to intreat those, whoe thinke som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what too hardlie of vs, that if we disagree from the confession of no Church that doth truelie beleeue, they would themselues also beginne to be of the same minde with vs, and quietlie, and soberlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with their bretheren, of what thinges they shall thinke good, rather then themselues to slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; giue the aduersaries occcasion to rayle vpon the Gospell. But if they will not doe it, let this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and euerlasting monument witnes to all that come after, that we and all of our side are &amp; shall be free not onelie from the grieuous reproches, with which wee are vndeseruedlie laden, but also with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame of all the hurlie burlies and dissentions that haue beene hitherto and that (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) are peraduenture like tobe more greeuous, vnles it be speedelie preuented on both sides.</p>
   <p>And seeing in this Harmonie we speake not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with our owne, but euen with the mouth of all those nations, whose confessions we haue brought into one forme of one and the same doctrine; we hope it will come to passe that not so much the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall names of the French, Belgia, and other Confessions shal hereafter be heard, as that one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vniuersall, simple, plaine, and absolute Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of all Churches (speaking as it were with one &amp; the same tongue of Chanaan) shall be seene▪ and that they who were thought to be farre wide (as
<pb facs="8"/>
hath hitherto not altogether without desert by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of ouer many mens priuate writings beene thought of vs and the brethren of the Confession of Auspurge) if so be that men keepe within the boundes of the Confessions, and all cauilling and sophistrie be laide aside and as well faithfull as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable exposition be admitted, shall be thought very neerelie to agree in al things. And this was the cause why we desired to put the confession of Aus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purge, together also with that of Saxony, &amp; Wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temberge, in this Harmonie, that it might be the more easilie known, that both we agree with them in all particular points of faith, and that there are verie few matters hanging in controuersie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs. For concerning that doubt about the Lords Supper, in the, thing and of the thing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> selfe, there is no strife, we differ in certaine adiuncts and circumstances of the thing. In the thing it selfe, I saie, we agree: although as the gifts of God are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, so some do more plainly, some do not so plain lie, and perhaps not so fitlie, vtter that which they thinke. For we all acknowledge that the holie signes, haue not a bare signification, but that by the ordinance of God they assure our consciences that the things themselues are as truelie and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie giuen of God to all that come, as the signes themselues are giuen by Gods minister. But this questiō remaineth, whether as the signe, so also the present thing it selfe be giuen to the body, or rather the present signe be giuen to the bodie, but the present thing giuen onelie to the minde and faith▪ Againe, whether as both be giuen to al, so both be receiued of al, of some vnto life, and of other some
<pb facs="8"/>
vnto death. In like sort, we all beleeue the true Communication of the true bodie and the true bloode of our Lord Iesus Christ. The controuersie standeth in the manner of communicating, but who may therefore of right thinke, that the holie vnitie of the Churches is to be plucked a sunder? That they of our side were alwaies desirous of peace and agreement, the historie of the conference at Marpurge, and such things as were afterward done in the yeare 1536. doe sufficientlie witnes.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, so often as there appeared any hope of agreement, it is cleare, that there was no other cause, but the importunitie of some certaine men, why new and sudden braules beeing raised, the matter could not come or long continue in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement which was hoped for. For that we may let passe very many other things, although in the beginning it were openlie knowne among all, that there was no controuersie betweene vs (no not so much as the verie Papists excepted) in the opinion about worshipping the mysterie of the holie Trinitie; loe about the latter end that vnhappie monster of Vbiquitie came forth, which if it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, will quite ouerthrow the true doctrine of Christs person, and his natures. Hence then come the distractions of Churches, hence come so deadlie quarrellings. But seeing this wholl matter hath beene often handled by verie learned men, it is no time for vs to deale any farther therein. For it is sufficient for vs to shew in few wordes, that our men so farre as was possible, alwaies prouided for the peace of the Church.</p>
   <p>Neither truelie hath any man cause after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb facs="9"/>
of certain moderators (such as not long since haue beene) why he should perswade himselfe that we would here of this hotch-potch of opinions make a certaine medlie as it were of contrarie qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. But we leaue all thinges wholl, that euerie one may so know his owne words beeing compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the sayings of others, that he shall finde nothing forged, nothing taken away, nothing put to, or wrested. And to conclude, the forme and drift of this wholl work, if it be more narrowlie vowed, shal not vnworthily be iudged a sound body of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stian doctrine, framed and alowed by the writings, and as it were by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> common councell of the godlie Churches well nigh of all <hi>Europe.</hi> For here all the chiefe points of our Religion, beeing discussed and approoued, are by the publique authoritie of all the chiefe nations in Christendome with one consent published and knit together: yet we must confesse, as we afore touched, that through the manifolde and busie braulings of priuate persons, and glosses (as men commonly speak) the matter was brought farre from the groundes thereof to things cleane besides the purpose and impertinent. For first there beganne to be dealing onely about the supper: then it came to Christs Ascension and sitting in heauen: and within a while after to the personall vnion of both his natures, and what stay will there be in the ende? for many, (by all mens leaue be it spoken) seeme to be delighted with this continual striuing, that howsoeuer, and whatsoeuer it might coste them, they might not be vnknowne. But it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Disciples of Christ to seeke peace, and to despise glorie. For as Bernard saith, <hi>They that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>peace, and seeke after glorie, they lose both peace and glorie.</hi> A way therefore with those speaches, <hi>I am of Paull, I am of Cephas,</hi> &amp; let that one saying be heard, I am Christs, I am the Churches.</p>
   <p>There is something that may be misliked, yet there are verie manie things that may wel be liked: the same ground work of faith abideth, let therfore the same loue continue: and let vs not think much to take them for brethren, whome God vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth to take for sonnes: neither let vs despise those, for whome Christ despised him-selfe. That thing is assuredlie true, and very much liked of vs, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in holy doctrine is to be thought of smal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: but rather that euen in the least pointes thereof a certeine faith and full assurance is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, flat contrarie to the wauering of the Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mikes: yet we can not like of too too much peeuish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, through which some do straight waie vpon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie smal occasion cal their brethren heretikes, schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, vngodlie, Mahumetanes: let these spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches be throwne out against Atheists, Epicures, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, Arians, Anabaptists, and such like mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous persons, which desire to haue the Lords field vtterlie destroied: but let vs euerie daie grow in faith and loue: and let vs teach the flocks commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our charge, to feare God, to hate vices, and follow after vertues, to denie the world and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: obeying the commaundement of our Lord &amp; teacher Iesus Christ, who biddeth vs not tobraule but to loue each other. Whose example in gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Church if we will follow, we shal raise vp those that are afflicted, take vp those that are fallen, comfort the feeble, waken the drousy, &amp; not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlie
<pb facs="10"/>
denounce Gods wrath against sinnes, and shall draw out the sword of the same word which is no blunt one against hypocrites, wolues, dogges, swine, goates, and to conclude against all wicked ones which in our Churches mingle them-selues with the true sheepe, and which cause the word of God to be euill spoken of. It were a farre better thing surelie then that which some do, busying the sharpnes of their wit in making of certeine trifles, that forsooth the knowledge of such subtilties, may shake out of our mindes all conscience. It was iustlie said that the strength of the gospel was wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened through the thornie subtelties of schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questions: and we through our wayward disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions what els do we, then cause that the authority thereof be not strengthened, but rather weakned, and doe euen stagger among the wicked. We read it excellentlie written in Liuie, a verie graue wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that <hi>not onelie grudges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ut also warres haue an end, and that oftentimes deadlie foes become faithfull confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, yea and sometimes Citizens: &amp; that by the same speeches of the people of Rome, very bitter or cruel enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haue bene taken vp betweene men of great account.</hi> And that which these few wordes wrought with the heathen, shall not godlines toward God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine at the hands of Christians, of deuines, and of Pastours of Churches? yea if the trauell of reading &amp; diligentlie examining &amp; conferring of this booke shall not be irksome, if vpright and sincere iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if not preiudicate opinions, but the loue of one truth shall beare swaie in al mens hearts, it will shortly obteine it. That olde contention about the celebrating of Easter very hotlie tossed to and fro
<pb facs="10"/>
for two hundred years, or there about, between the Greekes and the Latines, was long since by vs thought worthie of laughter: but we must take good heed, lest in a matter not altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, we seeme to be wiser then both, if so be that we desire to haue the Church wholl, and not to leaue it rent vnto the posteritie, and would haue our selues be counted not foolish among men, and not stub born in the sight of god. There hath scarce beene anie age, which hath in such sort seen al Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches following altogether one thing in all points, so as there hath not alwaies been some difference, either in doctrine, or in ceremonies or in manners: and yet were not Christian Churches through the world therefore cut a sunder, vnles peraduenture then, when the Bishop of Rome brake of all agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; tyrannically <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ioyned to other Churches, not what ought to be done, but what him-selfe would haue obserued: but the Apostle did not so. Barnabas in deed departed from Paull, and Paull also withstood Peter, and surelie for no trifle: and yet the one became not more enemie or strange to the other, but the selfe same spirit, which had cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled them from the beginning, neuer suffred them to be disioyned from them-selues. It is the fashion of Romists to commaund, to enforce, to presse, to through out cursings, and thunder excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the heades of those that whisper neuer so litle against them: but let vs, according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the holie Ghost, suffer, and gentlie admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish each other: that is, keeping the groundwork of faith, let vs build loue vpon it, and let vs ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie repaire the walls of Sion lying in their ruines.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
It remaineth, that through the same Lord Christ we besech our reuerent brethren in the lord, whose confessions published we set forth, that they take this our paines in good parte: and fuffer vs to leane, as it were to a certaine staie, to the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the reformed Churches, against the accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and reproches of the common aduersaries of the trueth. But it had beene to be wished, that we might at once haue set out all the Confessions of all the reformed Churches: but because we had them not all, therfore we set out them onelie, that were come to our hands, to which the rest also, so farre as we suppose, may easilie be drawne. And we also could haue wished, that the thing might haue bin made common to all the reformed Churches. But when as the state of our Churches seemed to force the matter, &amp; that they could not abide any longer delaie, the right well beloued brethren will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don vs, with whom by reason of the time we could not impart both the Harmony it selfe, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations▪ as also the intent of this wholl edition. Whereas moreouer we haue put to moe confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of one and the same nation, as of Auspurge, &amp; Saxonie, as also the former and latter of Heluetia, that was not done without cause: for besides that one expoundeth another, we thought it good also hereby to ridde them from all suspicion of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy and wauering in opinion, which the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries are wont to catch at, by such repetitions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> confessions.</p>
   <p>Yet why we would not adde some confession<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the brethren of Bohemia often repeated, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> straight way shew a cause▪ and we hope that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
reason will easilie be liked of them. And we haue set downe euerie where two, yea and in some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces three editions of Auspurge, for this respect, lest in this diuersitie we might seeme to haue picked out that, which rather fauoured ourside, &amp; to haue vtterlie misliked the other. Wherein notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we haue not euery where followed the order of times, in which euery of them came to light, but the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ppie which we had in our hands printed at Wirtemberge 1572. with a double edition. And w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> therefore thought it meete to passe ouer the Apologies adioyned to the confessions (as of Auspurge, Bohemia, Sucueland, and England) as wel that the work might not grow to be exceeding bigge, as also that we might not seeme rather to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease disputations &amp; controuersies, then to make an Harmony of doctrine. And as for our obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, our minde was to meete with the cauills of sophisters, who we know well enough will take holde on the least matters, that they may thereby set vs on worke. Wherefore lest they should charge vs to set out a discorde rather then a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde of confessions▪ we haue added in the end very short obseruations, in which we lay open those things which might seeme somewhat obscurelie spoken, and doe fauourablie and freelie, giuing them an interpretation, expounde those thinges, which either haue, or seeme to haue any shew of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie. And we beseech the brethren to beare with vs therein, as the most distressed, and desirous of the peace and agreement of the Curches among those, who in these last times haue imbraced the truth of the gospel. For God forbid, that we should
<pb facs="12"/>
desire to be counted Censurers of others, who are ready rather to be taught of our brethren, and to be strengthned in this face of truth, which is begun. We would therfore haue them so to thinke, that these obseruations are laid before them, that they maie iudge of them, and maie, if they shall thinke it any where needefull, better and more fitlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their owne opinion, and in the meane while accept of our paines.</p>
   <p>YE therefore moste gracious Kings, Dukes, Earles, Marquesses, moste famous Barrons, &amp; noble Lords, ye Cities, and Common wealthes, ye most wise Pastours, Doctours, and, to be short, all Christian people, professing the trueth of the Gospell, be present in soules and bodies, suffer not the poyson of discord to spread any farther: but kill this hurtfull serpent, and receiue with a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an minde as is meete, and as is offered vnto you this most sure token &amp; earnest of the euerlasting friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the French and Belgian Churches with you, offered to you in the face of the whol world: that we beeing by a friendly league coupled together in Christ may vanquish all Antichristes, and may sing that hymne to the Lord our God, <hi>Beholde how good and ioyfull a thing it is, brethren to dwell together in vnitie.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>