<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his much honoured Friend,
Mr. IAMES HAYVVARD,
upon his Translation of EROMENA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107086_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3075</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his much honoured Friend,
Mr. IAMES HAYVVARD,
upon his Translation of EROMENA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eromena, or, Love and revenge. Written originally in the Thoscan tongue, by Cavalier Gio. Francesco Biondi, Gentleman extraordinary of his Majesties Privie Chamber. Divided into six books. And now faithfully Englished, by Ia. Hayvvard, of Graies-Inne Gent</title>
                 <author>Biondi, Giovanni Francesco, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 195, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To his much honoured Friend,
M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> IAMES HAYVVARD,
upon his Translation of EROMENA.</head>
   <l>SPare minuts thus spent (most accomplisht Friend)</l>
   <l>Much should I erre shold I not much commend;</l>
   <l>For thy retired houres, (by proofe) I know,</l>
   <l>Thou in more serious studies dost bestow,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>As</hi> Engin, Stratagem, Fortification,</l>
   <l>Meanes to extend the confines of a Nation;</l>
   <l>In which as judgement doth already crown thee,</l>
   <l>Imployment in the future may renown thee;</l>
   <l>Since in the <hi>Mathematick</hi> Art (I meane</l>
   <l>Those parts most usefull, and whence we may gleane</l>
   <l>An <hi>Enginiers</hi> perfection) I know none,</l>
   <l>In <hi>Theorick</hi> and <hi>Practick</hi> hath out-gone</l>
   <l>Thee for thy time. On then in thy progresse,</l>
   <l>As for thine own thy Countries good no lesse;</l>
   <l>Nor hast thou of thy travells made that use</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
Which many doe, to bring home the abuse</l>
   <l>Of Forreigne Climes, their complement, their fashion,</l>
   <l>Not their known vice, t'infect thy home and nation;</l>
   <l>Thy purpose and thy practise was not such;</l>
   <l>For thy endeavours have not been so much</l>
   <l>To see as know: for neither hast thou pierc't</l>
   <l>
      <hi>France</hi> to attain her garb, but to be vers't</l>
   <l>In her best <hi>Dialect;</hi> nor <hi>Almaigne</hi> known,</l>
   <l>To make their healthing, not their tongue thine own:</l>
   <l>Thee thine approved <hi>Temperance</hi> hath taught</l>
   <l>The <hi>Teutons</hi> lofty language, not deep draught;</l>
   <l>And to thy minde gave a more pleasing gust</l>
   <l>The <hi>Thoscans</hi> stately strain than lothsome lust.</l>
   <l>Of these thy waies I cannot but approve,</l>
   <l>Both 'cause I know them, and because I love</l>
   <l>To see thee constant in them; doe but then</l>
   <l>Impart thy <hi>Talent</hi> to thy Countrymen,</l>
   <l>By culling out the choisest <hi>Forreigne</hi> flowers,</l>
   <l>To plant in <hi>English</hi> soil and make them ours.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>