<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all the faithfull dispersed people of God, in what Countries and Nations soeuer, Conrade Badius wisheth Grace, and peace from our Lorde and Saui∣our Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107259_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17690</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4437</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107259</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all the faithfull dispersed people of God, in what Countries and Nations soeuer, Conrade Badius wisheth Grace, and peace from our Lorde and Saui∣our Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diuers sermons of Master Iohn Caluin, concerning the diuinitie, humanitie, and natiuitie of our Lorde Iesus Christe : as also touching his passion, death, resurrection, ascention: togeather with the comming downe of the holy Ghoste vpon his Apostles: and the first sermon of S. Peter. The order of which you shall finde in the page ensuing</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 203, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To all the faithfull dispersed people of God,</hi> in what Countries and Nations soeuer, Conrade Badius wisheth Grace, and peace from our Lorde and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne vnto vs (Christian Readers) what the proude secte of the Pharisees was, in whom, although there was nothing els but darknesse, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, yet boasted and bragged they of them selues, to bee the most notable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretors of the lawe, insomuche, that from thence they tooke their name, as if the verie marowe, and secret meaning of the scriptures had beene enclosed and fast shut vp in their breastes. And yet in the meane while, in stead of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the poore people with true and wholesome doctrine, they instructed them I know not with what mockeries and vaine ceremonies, which they them selues had inuented, cleane besides the worde of God. And so, after the like manner doe our great Doctours of Sorbone, and all our howling Monkes and Fryers deale at this day with vs: of which company, the one sorte of them, although they thinke them selues to be the pillers of the Church, fellowes with the Apostles, and the verie shoppe of the holie Ghost, from whence wee must fetch the full exposition of the scriptures, and the verie assured resolution of all the pointes of religion, yet tell they vs nothing els but vaine and doltish tales, either busie them selues about curious questions, and ful of Sophistrie, besides a thousand other subtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, seruing to no edification in the whole world. The other sort of them, in stead of the word of God, preach nothing els, but constitutions and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces of their owne making, for the establishing of the tyrannie of their holie Father the Pope, the verie Antechrist and enemy to the truth: and the third sort, vomit and cast vp arrogant and proude speeches in the Pulpyt against the children of God, &amp; against all such as Iesus Christ hath reuealed him selfe vnto, in these latter dayes, calling them Lutherans, and seditious persons, falsly deuising a thousand leasings against them, and in steade of feeding their miserable starued sheepe with the true foode of the worde of God, they are faine to moysten their soules with those pestilent
<pb facs="5"/> kindes of poisons, whereas they should be fed with spiritual and heauenly nurriture.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, dearely beloued brethren in our Lorde and Sauiour Iesus Christ, whensoeuer that God sendeth vnto vs any good and faithfull tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, who sincerely and purely deliuereth vnto his Auditorie the worde of the Lorde, wee ought to make a meruellous great account of him: for, we shal finde verie few such men as will faithfully acquite them selues of their charge and function: and we ought amongst other things greatly to reuerence all those whom God hath endowed with speciall graces and the gift of enterpreting▪ Euen as at this day the faithful Pastor and good seruant of God Iohn Caluin, hath made that precious talēt which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpō him verie profitable, whose Sermons yelde vnto vs a good te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony therof, which also, (in the iudgement of indifferēt men) were not slightly made, nor hastily hudled vp, but duely &amp; truely premeditated and rightly deliuered vnto the capacitie of his flocke, hauing alwayes in open shew, the liuely impression of the benefit of the Lord Iesus in their hearts. Neither are these like vnto common places caught in a net, either yet bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Sermons, which may serue for any text of scripture, as a stoole for al feete: But are true, sincere, plaine, and meete expositions seruing for the text which he had to treate of: neither are they stuffed with friuolous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations: either yet filled with ambitious inuectiues. For, as it is verie needful that the superstitions of Poperie shoulde, by the worde of God, bee daily enueighed against, to the ende they, might be cleane rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and scowred out of our heartes, as a strong sauour wherewith we haue beene seasoned euen from our infancie, yet if the place which hee hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led did not orderly speake against such abuses, hee woulde not passe the boundes of his Texte, and crye out, vpon them: as the Papists, alwaies, and to no purpose, like Mastife Curres barke and baye against the Gospell, renued in this latter age of the worlde: But his manner was to holde a plaine and direct course, tending to edification, without omitting any thing which might serue and make for the honour of God, and instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Auditorie. I woulde, if it pleased God, there were a great many moe his lyke: For then I knowe, that the Church of Christ, should be greatly eased and furthered: But it is out of al doubt, that our vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse is the cause why God sendeth not moe faithfull Pastours at this present then are: for if there bee any that will duetifully discharge their office, and deliuer the word of God freely (as Saint Paule commaundeth) reproouing sinne, and setting them selues against iniquitie, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce
<pb facs="6"/> of his honour, by whom they are sent, they are foorthwith fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously dealt with, rayled on, and slaundered. As questionlesse, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie before saide, who for his vprightnesse, and great fidelitie by him vsed in the executing of his charge, hath gotten such a mightie number of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as that they which neuer see nor heard him, neither yet euer read two wordes of his woorkes, haue wished his death. Howbeit, God be thanked for it, his good conscience and the testimonie which hee had before God, his Angelles, and the faithful which daily heard him, did so assure him that men did him wrong for wishing of him so great hurt, as that they encouraged him, constantly to pursue the Lordes workes. He sawe howe hardly his maister was dealt with, and after him the Apostles: and therefore it greeued him not to follow their steppes, because he knew that God was of power able to defende and keepe his pledge, and that they which suffred for his sake, should be taken to be worthie of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Nowe, because all men could not bee of that Church whereby they might be partakers of the heauenly foode which this good shepheard many yeares ceased not to administer: and that it was very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that they which were newly come to the charge which hee had, might see his manner of teaching, and so followe it: and likewise, that they which thought hee did nothing els but speake euill and crye out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Pope, and all his rable of shauelinges, thundring against their traditions, without any other handling of the Scripture, or els that hee went about none other thing but to bring the people vnto a carnal liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and thereby cast of the obedience and subiection which they ought to Kinges and Princes, to the end therefore that they might read his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and thereby see that hee hath great iniurie done vnto him in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this blame laide vpon him, and cease the yl opinion which they haue conceiued of him, many godly honest men determined to prynt a certein of them, but especially Lawrence of Normandie, whose zeale and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuersation is sufficiently wel knowne, &amp; hath for many yeares besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed all his studie &amp; trauel to prynt bookes for the edifiyng of the Church. In verie deede, I must needes say thus much (as I haue in the preface of the Sermons of the tenne Commaundementes let you before vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande) that the Authour was not willing nor yet consenting here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too: not that hee woulde hinder the benefite and fruite that hereby might redounde to the Church: but wished that his Sermons might passe no further then vnto his owne flocke: as well for that they
<pb facs="6"/> were specially made for his sheepe, vnto whose capacitie he fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him selfe the best he could: and therefore thought that an other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and disposition were more requisite therin for the publishing them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode in the view of al the world: but as for the ouer looking of them to the ende to polish them, ouer and besides that his leasure would not serue him, hee would neuer busie himselfe about the matter. For if he himselfe had meant to haue put them foorth, he intended to haue made new homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of them, and better penned, and not to haue published any thing sodē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spoken by him. Neuerthelesse, we seeing the great benefite which might come by the putting abrode of these Sermons, were not afeard somewhat to displease and disobey him heerein, to the end we might make you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of those excellent riches, which wee possesse in this litle Angle and corner of the world, so abhorred and detested, howbeit precious in the sight of the Lord. In deede we were so much the bolder, by reason of the liberal dealing of our honorable Lords and magistrates, who desiring the aduancement of the Church of God, haue priuiledged vs to print them.</p>
   <p>Now, when we see that we were to make choyse of such a great nūber of collections as were of them, we thought it best to set a few of them abrod to the end that as we see them thankefully receiued, so also we might goe forward in putting foorth of moe. This then is the order which wee haue taken.</p>
   <p>In the first place, we haue set downe a congregation vpon the beginning of the Gospell of S. Iohn, where is largely handeled the diuinitie of our Lord Iesus Christ. Now by this word <hi>Congregation,</hi> I meane a certaine as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble, which is made one day in the weeke at the Church, where euery Minister in order handleth some text of the scripture, more like the maner of a reading then of a preaching: that being done, if any of the rest vnto whome the spirite of God hath reuealed any thing tending to the better vnderstanding and laying open of that which hath beene spoken, hee hath free libertie to speake.</p>
   <p>After that foloweth the Sermon, touching the natiuitie of Iesus Christ. Next to it wee haue placed the Sermons of his death and passion, of his resurrection and ascention, of the comming downe of the holy Ghost vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apostles, Of the first Sermon that Peter, made after he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Ghost. Last of al, we haue set downe a Sermon treating of the last comming of Iesus Christe.</p>
   <p>After we had thus doone, and thinking to haue finished this booke it pleased God to graunt vs to come to the hearing of the most excellent ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons
<pb facs="7"/> that are possibly to be hard or spoken, vpon the end of the fiftie two Chapter of the Prophet Isaiah, &amp; vpon al the fiftie three, wherin the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of the death and passion of our Lorde Iesus Christe is set foorth, and so liuely pictured out that a man would thinke that the holy Ghost meant to set before our eyes Iesus Christ condemned in our name, and nayled to the crosse for our sinnes, to the end that he suffering the punishmente for them which was due to vs, and bearing the wrath and iudgement of God for our sakes, hath deliuered vs from eternal death, which Sermons doe so agree with the Sermons going before, which wee haue heere set downe, that wee coulde not choose to ioyne them vnto them, because we woulde not bereaue you of so great a benefite. Moreouer, wee haue had respect to choose out those Sermons aswell as we coulde, which were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such dayes as the Lordes Supper was administred in this Churche, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well for that that there is a farre greater and more effectuall vehemencie in them, as also for that the point of this Sacrament is therein more cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shewed, for the which at this day, is the greatest contention and striefe in the worlde. And therefore we haue determined hereafter too deliuer vnto you the Sermons, which this godly learned man hath made vpon the tenth and the eleuenth Chapter of the Epistle of S. Paul to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, wherein is manifestly set foorth the true institution of the Supper &amp; the corruption and abuse which sithence haue come vnto it, liuely refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Wherefore, if wee perceiue that these presents like you, wee will vse all the meanes possible that God shal graunt vs, to make you partakers of the heauenly riches, which he vouchsafeth vpon his seruants heere in this Church. In the meane while wee beseech you dearely beloued to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that blessed coursse, and not feare the threats and cruelties of tyrants, who thinke at this day to do god high seruice in persecuting Iesus Christ in his members: and set before you this incorruptible crowne and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting prepared for you, if you constantly perseuere vnto the ende in your holy calling, knowing that the sufferings which you abide in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent life, are not worthie the glory of the life to come: wherevnto wee may attaine through Iesus Christ our Lord.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Geneua.</hi>
         <date>1563.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>