<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Mistrisse Katherine VVoodford (vvife to maister Iames Woodforde Esquier) and cheefe Clarke of the Kitching to the Queenes Ma∣iestie Leonarde Mastall vvisheth a prospe∣rous estate in health long to continue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107290_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07184</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107290</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Mistrisse Katherine VVoodford (vvife to maister Iames Woodforde Esquier) and cheefe Clarke of the Kitching to the Queenes Ma∣iestie Leonarde Mastall vvisheth a prospe∣rous estate in health long to continue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The husbandlye ordring and gouernmente of poultrie : Practised by the learnedste, and suche as haue bene knowne skilfullest in that arte, and in our tyme</title>
                 <author>Mascall, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Dewes, Garrat.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To Mistrisse Katherine VVoodford (vvife to maister Iames Woodforde Esquier) and cheefe Clarke of the Kitching to the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie Leonarde Mastall vvisheth a prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous estate in health long to continue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He remēbraunce of your VVorshipfull Parentes, gentle mistrisse VVood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, vnto whome my father &amp; his family haue alwayes borne good vvill, and you shewing likewise a continuall courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie towards me and them, perceiuing also youre vvise and orderlye vsing your house for your familie &amp; hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes vvith a desired minde to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the same in knowledge, howe to vse and gouern Poultrie to profit for maintenance of your said housekee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, which thing you haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to know, vvith the ordring of straunge vvildfoule, how to preserue and keepe them to pleasure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.
<pb facs="3"/>I hauing known your parents (in Brestall) and you from my youth, shewing herein my good wil towards you and your fathers house, to far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and pleasure your desired minde therein, the remembraunce thereof hath moued me at this present to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise and translate out of Frenche Columella and Stephanus into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, certaine orders for gouernment of the sayd poultrie, and also the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of diuers other vvildfoule, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides manye other approued collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; practises learned in this realm, necessary to bee knowne to all good housholders, desiring you to bee the patrone and defender hereof in print, in so doing I shall thinke my trauaile vvell bestowed, and my time vvell spent. Thus I leaue, vvishing you a prosperous estate, vvith increase of vvorship long to continue to the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of God.</p>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>