<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his worthy good Friend,
Mr. IAMES HAYWARD,
upon his Translation of EROMENA
out of the Italian.</title>
           <author>Salisbury, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107086_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3075</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his worthy good Friend,
Mr. IAMES HAYWARD,
upon his Translation of EROMENA
out of the Italian.</title>
                 <author>Salisbury, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eromena, or, Love and revenge. Written originally in the Thoscan tongue, by Cavalier Gio. Francesco Biondi, Gentleman extraordinary of his Majesties Privie Chamber. Divided into six books. And now faithfully Englished, by Ia. Hayvvard, of Graies-Inne Gent</title>
                 <author>Biondi, Giovanni Francesco, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 195, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To his worthy good Friend,
M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> IAMES HAYWARD,
upon his Translation of EROMENA
out of the Italian.</head>
   <l>THere is a sort of people use to be</l>
   <l>Most captious, though of least capacity,</l>
   <l>Who when, as almost still, they meet with Strains</l>
   <l>Too high and lofty for their stupid braines,</l>
   <l>They say, they see no wit in't; good cause why,</l>
   <l>Tis too far distant from the purblinde eye</l>
   <l>Of their dull knowledge; whence it comes they sleight</l>
   <l>All that they cannot understand aright.</l>
   <l>I hate their humour; yet not so that I</l>
   <l>Should onely on meere contrariety</l>
   <l>Praise all I apprehend not. Friend, your Book,</l>
   <l>(Although I partly ghesse what pains you took</l>
   <l>To gain the <hi>Language,</hi> how the Seas you crost,</l>
   <l>What time, what travell, and what coyne it cost)</l>
   <l>Yet dare I not <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>mend, unlesse I were</l>
   <l>A perfect <hi>Linguist,</hi> and a <hi>Traveller;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For to thy censure is requir'd more art</l>
   <l>Than conning or some <hi>Dictionary</hi> by heart,</l>
   <l>Or an <hi>Italian</hi> Grammar: he must sweat,</l>
   <l>And coole again, fare hard, endure the heat</l>
   <l>Of forreigne Climats; and, whats ten times worse,</l>
   <l>Humour each people, keep an open purse,</l>
   <l>And a close heart, passe through such misery,</l>
   <l>You'd rather think his work well done, than try</l>
   <l>How he came by his knowledge: 'twill suffice</l>
   <l>The man that can consider, and is wise</l>
   <l>Enough to know the motive to his pains</l>
   <l>Was not vain-glory, nor the hop'd-for gains</l>
   <l>Of praise, or profit; nor to merit thanks</l>
   <l>From some great <hi>Lord</hi> his <hi>Patron:</hi> Mountebanks</l>
   <l>Of art there are, whose aymes be these; but he</l>
   <l>Disclaims such basenesse, shames to <hi>Poesie.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
His end is onely that he may delight</l>
   <l>His Reader, shewing how th' <hi>Italians</hi> write,</l>
   <l>And what their fancies are: Nor doth his wit</l>
   <l>Seek out some <hi>Satyre</hi> to translate, lest it</l>
   <l>Should nip our vices of the newest fashion,</l>
   <l>So neare, that some might think 'twere no translation:</l>
   <l>Nor covets he that to the world be known,</l>
   <l>He hath a <hi>Muse</hi> or <hi>Genius</hi> of his own</l>
   <l>Can teach his Pen a method: and for stuffe,</l>
   <l>His <hi>Travells</hi> might afford tales strange enough</l>
   <l>To please the times with; but his wiser brain,</l>
   <l>Gives to your censure first a Strangers vein;</l>
   <l>So a <hi>Translatours</hi> name may faults excuse</l>
   <l>Not of his own, but of anothers <hi>Muse,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>If there be any: for, who knows the tongue,</l>
   <l>May see he hath not done his <hi>Author</hi> wrong;</l>
   <l>But rather how th' <hi>Italian</hi> he refines</l>
   <l>In these his smoother and more polisht lines.</l>
   <l>Yet in the <hi>Authors</hi> praise, whom I nor know,</l>
   <l>Nor understand, thus far Ile dare to goe,</l>
   <l>Knowing our <hi>Translatours</hi> judgement to be such,</l>
   <l>I dare presume he likewise merits much;</l>
   <l>For had his work not been a piece well writ,</l>
   <l>'Thad known no language but <hi>Italian</hi> yet.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>THOMAS SALUSBURY.</signed>
Ex Templo interiori Ar.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>