<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣AN READER.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107471_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69076</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4707.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107471</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣AN READER.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of Christian religion. Or, the whole bodie and substance of diuintie. By T.C</title>
                 <author>Cartwright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 378, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any haue bin sorrie (good Reader) to see some wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of this learned and godly Author come forth in publike, since his death, with so many defects and maimes. To giue an instance hereof, there is an exposition of the Epistle to the Colossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, published vnder his name; wherein hee hath had very much wrong done to him: it being nothing else but a bundle of raw and imperfect notes, taken by some vnlearned hearer, neuer perused (or so much as seene) by the Author himselfe. Wherein there is scant any good coherence of matter to be found, or any perfect periods and sentences handsomly knit together, or sutably depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one vpon another.</p>
   <p>This Treatise of Religion, now reprinted, was the first; whereof of there was much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation
<pb facs="3"/> and desire; as of that which would be of more generall vse to all sorts of people: in which respect the Author himself was known to make more account of it, and would (if God had prolonged his daies to haue perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the same according to his own wishes) haue giuen fuller satisfaction to his iudicious and impartiall Reader. His purpose was, to set downe in most plaine and familiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, all the necessarie points of positiue Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, whereunto God (in a gratious measure) hath inabled him; as may appeare euen by the first impression, though it were published with many wants and imperfections.</p>
   <p>What paines and faithfulnesse hath been vsed in this second edition, for the supply of defects, and amendment of the faults of the former, will appeare to them that shall take time and paines to compare them together.</p>
   <p>His helpe was principally vsed herein, who was well acquainted with the Author and his purpose; and who hath done no more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in effect, then what he had helpe in, either from the Authors owne little Catechisme, or from some directions in the best and last co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie that he left behind him, or which the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie
<pb facs="3"/> of the method which he propounded did require.</p>
   <p>The first edition (as appeares) wanted a beginning; by meanes whereof the whole worke was as the trunke of a body without the head; the reason whereof was the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing of the doctrine of the Scripture, (wherewith he first began the Treatise) into a more fit place; this as neare as can bee, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Authors mind and speciall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, is supplied in the first Chapter: the like transposition of other particulars, not well vnderstood by his seruant that copied forth the booke, afterwards was a cause of the multitude of other errours also, which wee hope are now sufficiently amended, all particulars being brought to their proper places. Only there is in the exposition of the last petition of the Lords Prayer, a large dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of Gods gouernment concerning sinne; which were to bee wished had been brought backe to the tenth Chapter, which is the first and fittest place for that argument to bee handled in: and also whether by the Printers negligence, or his that writ the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, there is one whole question and answere
<pb facs="4"/> which belongs to the latter end of the seuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter, placed out of order, and set in the beginning of the eighteenth Chapter. There are also (to my griefe) many other verball faults which the Printer and the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriber must diuide betweene them, which though they may bee easily discerned by the iudicious and aduised Reader, yet may make others to stumble; and therfore I earnestly pray thee good Reader (which thou easily maiest doe) that thou wouldest amend them in the first place, according to the direction following.</p>
   <p>Further thou art to be entreated that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after thou esteeme nothing to bee his, but what shall bee published or approued by them, to whom by his last will and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament hee committed the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall and examination of his writings. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>