<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of Master Philip Melancton.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107599_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06507</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16981</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of Master Philip Melancton.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A faithful admonition of a certeyne true pastor and prophete : sent vnto the Germanes at such a time as certain great princes went about to bryng alienes into Germany, [and] to restore the papacy, the kingdom of Antichrist [Et] c Now tra [n] slated into English for a like admonicion vnto all true Englyshe harts; wherby they may learn and know how to consider [and] receiue the procedinges of the English magistrates and bishops. With a preface of M. Philip Melancthon</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Freeman, Conrad, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Preface of Master Philip Melancton.</head>
   <p>AS our sauior Iesus Christ y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sōne of God offered vp himselfe vpon the crosse vnto his eternall father for our sinnes (Marye &amp; Iohn standing next vnto him) immediatli before his death▪ he gaue to Iohn a special char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ouer his mother Mari▪ wherby he signified that he wold al men, and spe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially Rulers &amp; gouernors to haue the care &amp; charge of his pore church,<note place="margin">The chief charge of officers.</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch suffreth in the world cōtempt, slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; affliction: wherfor al men vpon earth &amp; specially the true members of Christes true church, frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning of the worlde vnto the end, oughte to consider with them selues, &amp; standing vnder the crosse of Christ, ther to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold &amp; ponder this maruelous worke that the sōne of God shuld bear &amp; su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffre such terrible wrath of his eternal father for vs, &amp; embrace the syngular grace &amp; mercy purchased therby vnto vs: &amp; we al to shew our selues thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful therfore: knowing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our hole life &amp; death also oughte to be directed vnto
<pb facs="8"/>
this ende, specially, that God may be praised: and aboue all, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this great and singular wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> might be preserued. And againe y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we ought to be thankful for this wōder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful benifite of god. And therfor to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>intayne &amp; preserue that church of his which doth preach, teach and imbrace this true and sicere doctrine, &amp; calleth vpō the very true God in the knolege of Christ, according vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayeng of our sauiour Christ vnto Peter wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thou art cōuerted, confirme &amp; streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy brethren. Wherunto al men do applye and endeuour them selues (if they be not altogether rude &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, but haue any sparkle of godlye knowledge and of the true faythe in their heartes) namely that mankynd should not lyue lyke a brute beast, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng onely an easye lyfe for himselfe, but alwayes to labour, how the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God may best be furthered, and the true religion best maintained and preserued. And this is my ernest desyre, that all christian heartes inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the feare of God, woulde a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/>
this present, consider and remember, what dutie and allegeaunce they owe vnto God in these daungerous &amp; tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome dayes, and in this heuy time. For in asmuch as it is moost euident that the pope (the sworne enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> al true Christians) doth al that he ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> possibly, to the entent to suppresse the true doctrine, &amp; Religion, which hath bene preached, and maintained these certayn yeares, and to stablish and set vp againe his Idlatrous seruice and supersticious errours. It is he that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth kinges and princes. And vsing the crafty conueiaunce of wicked by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopes and priestes, moueth theim to murther and shedding of bloud, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch by bringyng Aliens and straūgers sworne vnto hym, into all Realmes▪ meaneth at lēgth to subuert, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe the auncient lawes, and whole state of noble and godly cōmon wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and so to work a general destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for euer.</p>
   <p>Nowe what euery honest and true heart ought to do in such case, al godl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> men indued with any godlye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
<pb facs="9"/>
may easly perseiue &amp; consider</p>
   <p>And fyrst thus muche are al menne bounde vnto God,<note place="margin">All men boūdē to geue no aid to the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of idola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rye.</note> that thei minister no maner of ayde nor assistaūce wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by Idolatry or false religion myghte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> strengthened or maintained, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>g as it is writen. Thou shalt not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e thi self parta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er of other mēs sines</p>
   <p>Item ii. Cori. vi. Ye shall not helpe the vnfaithful, or the vnbeleuers (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand) to confyrme or stablyshe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. For howe can Christ and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ial agree to gether? And what a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye thyng is it, for the temple of God to be stuffed with Idols? Now are ye the temple of the liuing God, as God saith, I wil dwell in them, and walke in them, and I wil be theyr God and thei shalbe my people. Wherefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and seperate your selues a waye from them, saith the Lorde.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Euerye Christian oughte to open hys faythe to others.</note>Secondarely, euery one that dothe not vtterli cōtemne and despise God, is this much also boūd vnto him, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he mynde and desire to haue his fayth &amp; beleife in God, knowne vnto other. For thereunto is mankinde specially
<pb facs="9"/>
created, that we should know &amp; praise God, and also witnes and testifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other of hī. And our sauiour Christ himselfe saith, he that denieth me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, him wil I denie agayne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my heauenly father. And this cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession must be made according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans callyng, state, and degree. Such as be preachers and ministers, must cōfesse him, by preaching of true doctrine. Suche as be rulers and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, must confesse him, by abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing, and subuertynge of Idolatry and supersticion, and by maintaining of true doctrine and religion. And all that can helpe, by any maner of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, either with body or goodes, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maintenaunce of the same, oughte to endeuour thē selues earnestly therun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to, according to the saieng of S. Iohn i. Iohn. iii. Hereby do we knowe the true loue, that, like as Christ bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his lyfe for vs, euen so shoulde we bestowe our liues for the bretherne. Let euerye one consider, and ponder these and suche lyke aduertisementes by them selues, and hauyng alwayes
<pb facs="10"/>
an eye, and respect vnto the same, let them than reade, and marke this trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tise folowyng with diligence.</p>
   <p>And specially for asmuch as al men are not of one mynde, but some take &amp; esteme the true honour of God, the true inuocatiō, religion, and doctrine for the most special and most necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thyng to be sought, and some not. And agayne some are more feruent &amp; constant in the same than some other. Least thorow the euyl persuasions of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worst sort, mani other which know not the matter, nor the daunger ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, might be seduced and led amysse, this admonition and aduertisemente therfor, shalbe very necessari and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. For let the enemies of God &amp; of our coūtrey pretend what thei wil, that thei meane not to be of councel, nor to subuert our olde auncient law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: whā thei haue once their purpose, we shal se that that was their speciall drifte.<note place="margin">Fayre wordes ar trappes to catch foles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> For al their fayre wordes, and flatteryng perswasions are nothyng els, but traps to deceiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> simple sort w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, till they haue wrought their feate.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>Some of them pretēd, and say: tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thei minde nothing lesse, than to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish the Supremacy of Antichrist the B. of Rome, but if it were wel sought it would appeare, that moost of theyr practises and fetches come frō Rome. And that a great part of these procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges haue not bene wroughte, nor practised without his aduise. What if vertuous and godlye princes, whiche haue set them selues against his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, haue bene betraied and destroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the subtile practises of such im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of his, as haue borne swynge by their dissimulation about such vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous princes. O howe many subtilties hath Sathā, to assaulte Christes king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome with? I warrāt you it hath cost the b. of Rome mani a nightes watch, yea, many a pound, before these prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises were brought to this passe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch are nowe abrewyng. Yet hath god left some holes open, wherby such as haue any vnderstandyng, maye spye theyr driftes. For why do they holde godly, vertuous, learned &amp; most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy councelours in prison, but onely
<pb facs="11"/>
because thei feare, least thei wold hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and withstande some of theyr en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises and procedings? Let al those therfore that beare true heartes tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes theyr countrey, suffre them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be admonished in time.</p>
   <p>For if the Spanyardes do once en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter into our country,<note place="margin">What the cōming in of Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes wyl grow to.</note> and maye be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffred to nestle theim selues there, they wil not only at length crepe into the chiefe Dukedomes, Erledomes and lordships, and deale the same among them selues, but also wil establishe the Idol of Rome, and the whole cursed Papaci again: which al our countrey shal repent and rewe for euer.<note place="margin">Priestes care not what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Realme, so that theyr hooryshe kingdome floryshe.</note> And yet that is the chiefe thyng, that the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual prelates (in geuyng theyr ayde and councel therunto) doo seke. They care not what becom of this whole no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble nacion, nor what villany bee use<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> therin (as the Spaneyardes are most vyle and beastly people geuen to vice and brutishnes) so that they maye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and mayntaine theyr kingdome of Idolatry and supersticion, and may raigne again. The Lord of heauen dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoynt
<pb facs="11"/>
and subuert theyr enterprises▪ For whatsoeuer thei can alledge, or pretend, to charge those with, whiche haue imbraced, and setfurth the true religion, as many as haue any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent knowledge and vnderstandyng (if they wyll not speake against theyr own conscience) must nedes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confesse, that diuers hyghe pointes, and necessary articles of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten religion, haue bene sincerely and purely taught, and declared by them. And diuers notable errours haue by them bene disclosed, which before wer taught, and preached openlye in Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, wherby the people were piteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seduced. And now such as haue tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully laboured,<note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note> and traue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to setfurth the truth to abandon such Idolatry, and supersticion, as the people hath bene extremelye blynded with, to plant true, necessary and hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some doctrine, &amp; to roote out al falshod &amp; hipocrisie, thei are rewarded for their labour with imprisonment, depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theyr liuynges and goodes, &amp; with such like rewards. Other causes
<pb facs="12"/>
may wel be pretended of the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and common cutthrotes, as we may heare, but these are the very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in dede. How long God (which is iust in al his workes) will suffre &amp; vse them as his scourges (as Dauid saith the wicked manne is a scourge of the Lord) that let thē loke vnto. For wher thei pretend, that much disorder, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sension, negligence, securitie, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence did raigne amōg the professors of the true religion, without redresse or reformation, &amp;c. It cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor they them selues wil not deny but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al this is true in dede. And more ouer that they are laden with diuers infyrmities and sinnes, as wel priuate and secret, as open and manifest also, and that there haue bene many wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des among them (as euermore haue bene in the true church of God) which haue alwayes waxen, and sprong vp amonge good corne. As with Dauid▪ Nathan &amp; other true mēbers of gods church in those dayes, sprang vp Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salon, Achitophel, and other vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wedes. But what than? Sholde
<pb facs="12"/>
the people of God, by reason of suche offences, or bycause of theyr owne or of other mēs infyrmities, vtterli haue denied, and reiected the true doctrine and religion, and yelde to Idolatry &amp; supersticion: as our (yea rather Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes) aduersaries would haue vs now to do? Why do not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> higher powers, the Ioly prelates, and the faut spiers labour to redresse, and refourme suche offences, as they se in any of thē, that haue professed the sincere Religiō? Or why at the least did they not labor to restore the true discipline of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gospel, that therby such offēce giuers, might haue ben redressed, &amp; brought to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Christē penaūce, for the welth of theyr own soules, &amp; a good exāple vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mani other▪ Why did thei not this I say? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hy? Mary because some of them feared, least they them selues might paraduenture, be the fyrst, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the true discipline ought to be exercised. Let them fyrste examyne theyr owne consciences, and then tell me, whether I haue saide any thyng▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut the truthe or no? No, no, the true
<pb facs="13"/>
discipline (if it myght haue bene frely restored) wolde not haue suffred suche offenses to haue raigned, neyther in high nor in lowe, neither in the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual nor yet in the lay sorte, as the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries haue found faute with, and pretended for the onely causes, which haue kept them from the same profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. The godly preachers haue testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied sufficiently in their open exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that such disorder, dissolutenes of lyfe, slaūderous exāples, mispēding of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> time, with vngodli &amp; vnprofitable pastymes, as haue bene vsed of the gentlemen disars, and the lady carde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiers (as wel in the Court as in the countrey) wer not agreable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fessiō of Christes gospel. What could thei do more, but openly rebuke such enormities, seing thei wold neuer suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theim, to exercice the true ordre of discipline, vpon any transgressors? If this discipline (which hath long bene earnestly called for) mighte haue bene optained, a nombre of vnpreachyng prelates, of idle belly byshops, should not haue bene suffred, to loiter as thei
<pb facs="13"/>
did, and to spēd the patrimony of the Church vnprofitably. But nowe we may se, that thei plaied the dissēbling lurkers, gapyng, workyng and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisyng for a Day, wherin thei myght shew them selues, as thei wer, and as thei now appeare, wher as the ryght order of discipline wold haue brought them to the true profession of sincere Religion, and also to the practise ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in theyr vocation. And so would it haue done also my Lordes, and gētle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, scrap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alls, which vsed the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel for a cloke of theyr couetuousnes. In summa, we lacked nothing but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline, to haue refourmed al the enor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mities w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, whatsoeuer they haue bene that our aduersaries haue found fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> with, in the profession of our true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. But let them lay al the faults, infirmities, and offenses, which they haue marked, &amp; espied in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> professors of the gospel vpon one heape, they al together (if ther wer a thousād mo of them) are farre inferior, and incompa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rabli lesse, then the manifold errours, impietie, and Idolatry of the Masse,
<pb facs="14"/>
of the latine seruice, of the inuocation of saintes, of the filthy and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble pretensed chastitie, that is of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domitical single life of priestes, and of such other hipocrisie and supersticion▪ as our aduersaries go about with fire and fagot, with tooth &amp; naile, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; to set vp for the seruice of god.</p>
   <p>For notwithstanding that among the membres of the true church, and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong the professors of the true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ther raigne mani and diuers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmities and enormities, which they espie daily in them selues, yet the true godly sort do conceiue true and harty repentaunce, for theyr weakenes, and thei remain nor continue not therin, as the spiritual professors of single life do, in theyr hordome and filthy abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. And what soeuer infyrmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thei haue otherwise. Yet this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible vyce haue they not, (thankes be to God) to maintaine Idolatry, wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingli to persecute y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth, nor to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the godly professours of the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. These detestable vices, murther, blasphemy and Idolatry, whiche are
<pb facs="14"/>
the most true and infallible tokens of the papistes and aduersaries of Christ are not to be found amōg them. For these workes are the speciall workes of the deuyl, whiche he practiseth and worketh in his membres, wherby he declareth and speweth out his poysō malice, and hatred agaynst God,<note place="margin">Ihon. viii</note> as it is written, Ye are of the deuil, whiche is a lyar and a murtherer.</p>
   <p>These are synnes, whiche all men oughte specially to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lee, and dayly to pray earnestly vnto God, that he wil preserue them, that thei fal not into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of these abhominations.</p>
   <p>And he that loketh vpon the life of the professors of the Gospel, and also of the papistes, And by reasō of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, which he seith in both theyr liues, standeth in dout to which of thē he may ioyne himselfe, he ought to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membre and to consider this, that he ought in no wyse to take parte wyth them which are Idolators, maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of blasphemies, persecutors, and murtherers of the true membres of Christ. And though they should ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their liues therupon, and goo the
<pb facs="15"/>
same way that Abell went. Yet haue they this notable comfort, that God heareth their praiers, and wil be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful vnto them. For all other synnes shal be forgeuē: but the manifest blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming of God by idolatry, that is to saye, he that either mainteineth, or helpeth to maintaine idolatry or false religion, &amp; is a persecutor and a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of the true professors, or a fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of such murtherers, shall neuer be forgeuen. And God knoweth manye of the contrary part, which do refrain from persecuting of the true doctrine, for non other cause, but to thintent to auoide these .ii. pointes (blaspheming of God and murther) for Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp; for theyr own saluations sake. And it is manyfest inough, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> dyuers of thē (thākes be to god) haue sought neither pleasure nor mony, nor digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor yet any other thyng, that the world estemeth, but rather haue suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much sorow, misery &amp; opprobrye. Now if such should spend theyr lyues as Abel did, and suffer death thervpō, such a death should be more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="15"/>
vnto them, then al the lyfe &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Cain, then all the pompe and riches of the Cardinals and bishops. For al mē are detters vnto death not withstanding. But this must euerye one of vs alwaies consider, howe we may stand (after this lyfe) before the iudgement of God, and of his whole churche, at the latter day euerlasting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. And as we haue before our eyes the ensamples of Abel, Ieremy, Iohn the Baptist, Christ him selfe, Paule &amp; other of the Apostles, how thei al wer murthered of tyrannes, euē so let thē be sufficient wytnesses vnto vs, that after thys lyfe, another euerlastyng iudgement shal be holden and kepte. And therfore let al men take it for an high honor, and for a singular grace to put theyr liues in ieopardy, for the confession of the true faith &amp; religion of God: as Christ saith: Fear not thē which can do nothing but slea the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as for the soule thei cānot slea. &amp;c. And for asmuch as it mai wel appear that this is the scope &amp; end of al prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises of the Lords &amp; Bishops by theyr
<pb facs="16"/>
procedings, to bring in the bishop of Rome again, &amp; to establish his idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try &amp; errors, wherbi they mai raigne, and abuse the people agayne, as they haue done in times past, and to bring our countrey to a perpetuall destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Note wel.</note> it is most certaine, that al honest and true hartes, may laufullye refuse to obey them, and ought in any wise refuse to helpe or to ayde them. And where as they wyl obiect, &amp; saye that subiectes ought to obey al cōmaūde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, &amp; procedynges of theyr ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, although it may be briefely answered vnto thē,<note place="margin">Byshops ar not ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gistrates.</note> that the Bishops &amp; Prelates, which are the chiefe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this miserye, are not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, whom the inferiour people are boūd to obey, yet let thys answer stay al mens consciences, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of the cōmon welthe,<note place="margin">The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate maye not passe hys boundes.</note> is suche an ordinance of God, wherin the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate hath his apointed boundes, as wel as the subiect. And for asmuch as God is the hyghest Lorde, if the worldly magistrate attempteth, any thing against him, the inferiour sorte
<pb facs="16"/>
may laufully refuse to obeye him,<note place="margin">Inferiors maye in thys case laufullye disobey. Abdias. iii. re. xviii</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging for thē selues, that thei cānot, nor may not disobey God, to obey &amp; to serue thē. As for an exāple: Abdias did very wel in keping the prophetes priuely in dennes, &amp; secret places, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the cōmaūdemēt of his king which cōmaūded thē all to be slayne. And in like maner the Armeniās dyd wel, &amp; nothing but rightfully, in detē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theyre church &amp; theyr countrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Emperour Maximiane. Victorinus was a great prince, which in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tyme of Gallienus, had y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors autority, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gouernmēt at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, &amp; did gouerne ther very laudabli, yet was he laufulli slain of his owne se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cretarie, which foūd him abusing his wife. Marius also a noble prince, did pardō a yong souldier, &amp; set a crowne vpō his head, because he s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ew his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain (which captain, notwithstanding was Marius high frende) because he did it in his own defēse. Such factes in Christen mē ar right &amp; lauful, &amp; do please God wel. Yea they are speciall testimonies of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iudgemēt of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="17"/>
vnlawfull violence, and intolerable pride, and presumpcion of Tyrannes.</p>
   <p>And what is it els but tyrannye, to go about to set vp manifest idolatry, to separate godly mē from their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wiues, to bring in straūgers, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che shal subuert the state of the cōmō welth and such like? For it is easy to perceiue, that if the Spaniardes, and theyr traine, maye once beare rule in the Cities, Dukedomes, &amp; Lordshyps of our countrey (whiche God of hys mercy forbid that euer they shuld do) wher as hetherto, thorow gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull prouidence, the auncient lawes and good ordinaunces of our cōmon welth, haue bene preserued, they wyll go about to abolish &amp; to subuert thē▪ and at length brede much inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and misery in our natiō. Against the which inconueniences all godlye parentes, housholders with theyr wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, childrē, and families, ought with most harty sighinges cal and cry vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to god, that for the furtherance of his knowledge, and for the glorye of hys owne name, he wyl preserue his true
<pb facs="17"/>
religion amōg them, and that he will not suffer these churches and naciōs▪ wherin his truth hath bene confessed and preached, to decay nor to be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. And that such praiers may be made the more earnestly, &amp; with out let or hindraūce, we al ought to amēd our liues, in the feare of God, in true faith, and in al other vertues, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryng the sayeng of the Lorde in the prophet: Turne vnto me,<note place="margin">Iere. xiii.</note> and I wyll turne vnto you. Doutles the matter is waighty, and (end how it will) ther is lyke to be a wonderfull alteracion in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmon welth, and also in religiō,<note place="margin">We fele i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> alredy.</note> that is most sure. And I wōder much, that wise mē, which know and se wel inough, what wil be the end of suche procedynges,<note place="margin">Note wel▪</note> wyll notwythstanding seme to be workers, and furtherers of suche matters, as they do not allowe in theyr consciences. But surely it is no mans deuise nor working, but it is the diuils in hel, which rage and raue, because they wold gladly woorke an vniuersal destruction and miserye, in al Christēdome. Wherfor it wer best
<pb facs="18"/>
for such as be in authority, and of any power, not to be hasty in folowing &amp; satisfieng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lustes of princes, and the practises of wicked bishops and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Antichristes impes. For seyng the malice and spite of the Diuel; and of the idolatrous sort, is so feruēt and great, it wil minister occasiō to a wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful alteracion; which paraduēture they them selues shall repent. But I besech al godly hartes, that they wyll earnestly pray vnto God, that he wil graciously preserue the cōmonwelth, and auncient lawes of our countrey, and specially hys owne churche, that hys true worde and religion may cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually sound therin.</p>
   <p>Last of al let al Christen harts bear this wel in rememberaunce, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in his degree, and to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of his power, is bound to apply hys vttermost indeuour, towards the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of Christes true religion, &amp; likewise towards the defence of their coūtrey, and the auncient priuilegies of theyr naciō. That is the special end of our lyfe in this world, and no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="18"/>
thing can we do in thys lyfe. And forasmuche as the state of oure tym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> nowe, is muche like vnto the state of the Machabes, and euē the like prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises and subtelties now pretended, &amp; attempted, as were than: euerye one mai take good and profitable instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiōs out of the same bokes and story. Our Lorde Iesus, our onelye true shepherd, &amp; head captain, defend hys Church against assaults which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diuell, Antichrist and his impes nowe deuise, &amp; practise ther against Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>