<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Ihon Caluin to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1561</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107154_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17662</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4415</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107154</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Ihon Caluin to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The institution of Christian religion, vvrytten in Latine by maister Ihon Caluin, and translated into Englysh according to the authors last edition. Seen and allowed according to the order appointed in the Quenes maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1561</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe, Reyner (Reginald)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 70, 269, 1, 171, 3 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Ihon Caluin to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the first setting out of this worke, because I did not loke for that successe, which the Lord of his vnmeasura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodnesse hath geuen, I had (as men vse to do in small workes) for the more parte lightly passed it ouer. But when I vnderstode that it was receiued with that fauor of all the godly, which I neuer durst haue desired, muche lesse haue hoped for: as I verily felt in my hart that much more was geuen to me than I had deserued, so I thought it should be a great vnthankfulnesse if I should not at the least after my sclender abilite endeuor to answere so fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable affections towarde me, and which of themselues prouoked my diligēce. And this I attempted not only in the seconde setting fourth of it: but how oft sins that time the worke hath ben emprinted, so oft it hath ben enriched with some encreasce. But although I did not then repent me of the labor that I had employed: yet I neuer helde my selfe contented til it was disposed into that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which is now set before you. Now I trust I haue geuen you that whiche may be allowed by all your iugemētes. Truely with how great endeuor I haue applied my selfe to the doing of this seruice to the Chirche of God, I maye bring fourth for an euident witnesse, that this last winter, when I thought that the feuer Quartaue had summoned me to death, how much more the sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse enforced vpon me, so much lesse I spared myselfe, til I mighte leaue this boke to ouerliue me, which might make some part of thankfull recompense to so gentle prouoking of the godly. I had rather in dede it had ben done soner: but it is sone enough if well enough. And I shall then thinke that it is come abrode in good season, when I shal perceiue that it hath brought yet more plē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful frute than it hath done heretofore to the Chirch of God. This is my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desire. And truely ful ill it were with me, if I did not, holding my selfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the allowance of God alone, despise the iugementes of men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be the foolishe and frowarde iugementes of the vnskilful, or the wrongfull and malicious of the wicked. For although God hath throughly settled my minde to the endeuor bothe of enlarging his kingdome, and of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the common profit: and though I am clere in myne owne conscience, and haue himselfe &amp; the Angels to witnesse with me, that sins I toke vpon me the office of a teacher in the Chirch, I haue tēded to none other purpose but that I might profit the Chirch in mayntayning the pure doctrine of godlynesse: yet I thinke there is no man, that hath ben snatched at, bitten, &amp; torne in son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with moe sclaūders thā I.Vuhē my epistle was now in printing, I was cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainly enformed that at Augsburgh where the assemblie of the states of the Empire was holdē, there was a rumor sprede abrode of my reuolting to the
<pb facs="3"/>
Papacie, and the same was more gredely receiued in the courtes of Princes than was mete. This forsoothe is their thankfulnesse who are not ignorant of many trialls had of my stedfastnesse, which trialls as they shake of so fowle a sclander, so they should with al indifferent and gentle iudges haue defended me from it. But the Deuell with his whole route is deceiued if in oppressing me with filthy lies, he thinke that by his vniust dealing I shalbe either the more discouraged or made the lesse diligent: because I trust that the Lorde of his vnmeasurable goodnesse wil graunt me that I may with euē sufferāce cōtinue in the course of his holy calling. Vvhereof I geue to the godly reders a new profe in this setting fourth of this boke. Nowe in this trauail this was my purpose so to prepare and furnish them that be studious of holy Diuinitie to the reding of the worde of God, that they may bothe haue an easy entrie into it, and goe forwarde in it without stombling: for I thinke that I haue in all pointes so knitt vp together the summe of religion, and disposed the same in suche order, that whosoeuer shal wel haue it in minde, it shal not be hard for him to determine both what he ought chefely to seke in the Scripture, and to what marke to apply whatsoeuer is conteined in it. Therefore, this as it were a way being ones made plaine, if I shal hereafter set fourth any expositiōs of Scripture, because I shal not nede to enter into long disputations of articles of doctrine, and to wander out into common places: I wil alway knitt them vp shortly. By this meane the Godly reder shalbe eased of great peine▪ and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, so that he come furnished aforehand with the knowlege of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent worke as with a necessarie instrumente. But because the entente of this purpose, doth clerely as in mirrors appeare inso many commentaries of mine, I had rather to declare in dede what it is, than to set it out in wordes. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel frendly Reader, and if thou receiue any frute of my labors, helpe me with thy praiers to God our Father.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Geneua, <date>the first day of August in the yere. <hi>1559.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>Augustine in his vii. Epistle.</bibl>
      <q>I professe my selfe to be one of the number of them, which write in profiting, and profit in writing.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>