<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Epistle to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107416_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17883</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4549</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Epistle to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Admirable events : selected out of foure bookes, vvritten in French by the Right Reverend, Iohn Peter Camus, Bishop of Belley. Together with morall Relations, written by the same author. And translated into English by S. Du Verger</title>
                 <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Brooks (Brooke), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 357, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Authors Epistle to the <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He enterprise which I have taken in hand, is to wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, or rather to encounter with thosefrivolous books, which may all be compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed under the name of Romants, which would require the hands which fables attribute unto <hi>Briarius,</hi> or the strength which Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets give unto <hi>Hercules:</hi> the hands of that Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to handle so many pens, and the vigour of that <hi>Heros</hi> to undergoe so painefull a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: but what cannot a courage do, anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a zeale of pleasuring his neighbour, and provoked by desire to advance the light of vertue, and to lessen vice. O why hath not my pen the vertue to cure the wounds that these wicked books cause in this world! or at
<pb facs="6"/> least, why cannot it devoure those monsters, which the writers of those aforesaid workes, meere inchanters of mindes cause to appeare in the formes of bookes? or like as an Eagles feather devours all other feathers, so might my pen devour all those other pens. When shall the light of vertue, &amp; verity dissipate the shadowes of vice and vanity? will the false Dagons never fall before the Arke of serious, true, and beneficiall entertainments of the minde? at least if these my labours could cure those who are miserably infected with often viewing these Pamphlets: If the losse of so much time may be called imployment, I should not thinke my labour spent in vaine, nor my pen unprofitable. But when I see this mischievous tree, which I strive to cut down, casting forth so many branches, as I lop off, and doing like the Vine, which never sprouts so well, as when it is cut, it makes me feare a labour like unto that of <hi>Danaides,</hi> or of <hi>Sisy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus.</hi> Who would not wish for as many hands as <hi>Briarius,</hi> for to oppose so many stiles, which are used in that so vaine, and so wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton a kinde of writing? And who would not
<pb facs="6"/> wish for the arme of <hi>Hercules,</hi> to overcome this <hi>Hydra,</hi> whereof I can no sooner strike off one head, but up springs another? You would thinke the fable of <hi>Cadmus</hi> a truth in this subject; and that of the ancient Serpents teeth, there growes up armed men to fight in defence of lyes: that if <hi>Hercules</hi> (according to the proverb) could doe nothing against two, what may we think to doe against these legions?</p>
   <p>Now to overthrow so many fabulous Bookes, I undertake not my combat direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if I were confuting heresies, for it is not needfull that I should trouble my self to prove the obscurity of darknesse, nor to shew the falshood of these Romants, Adventures, Chivalries, and other such trash, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse themselves fabulous in their Prefaces, and whose reading full of fantasticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of faynings, of impossibilities, of absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, of inchantments, of extravagancies, and such like trumpery, sufficiently sheweth their impertinency, which were (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle saith) to combat against the aire, and to tunne without end, or at the most to imitate
<pb facs="7"/> that idle Emperour, who made warre onely against flyes By what manner doe I then la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to overcome my adversaries? it is by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, setting relations true and beneficiall, in the place of those that are prophane, fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and not onely unprofitable, but for the most part pernicious, to the end that those whose great leisure causeth to seeke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to imploy their time, may finde where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to entertaine their desires.</p>
   <p>Even as truth is constant, so falshood is wavering and differing, &amp; is capable of more different formes, then the <hi>materia prima,</hi> or the Proteus of Poets, which is the cause that these Authors, who love vanity, and follow after lyes, set forth their works in as many fashions, as they please. This variety being no small attractive unto those that passionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affect such kinde of reading: and it is no small advantage, that fantasticall relations have over those that are true, for those are made at pleasure, like leaden rules, or images of waxe wherewith you may doe what you will, filling them with monstrous incounters, surmounting both probability and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="7"/> things which delight and wonderfully suspend the minde: in briefe, they stuffe them with so many baits, that the licourishnesse of the sawce makes them loose the taste of the meat, which of it selfe is without savour or relish, and most commonly hurtfull: whereas narrations of things, which have truely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, are tyed to more subjection, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man may order them handsomely, and slip in some convenient dressings, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse conscience obliges to keep faithfully to the ground and body of the History: and yet in the particularities which are added, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for connexion, or imbellishment of the recitall: the Author is strictly tyed to the bounds of probability, out of which he may not swerve a nailes beadth, without discredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the whole worke. For although fables, parables, and poeticall fictions, do sometimes hide in them good precepts, and many seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous examples, yet the instructions loose much of their credit when they are mixed amongst vaine inventions: and when they doe not leane to the solid foundation of truth, even as the Manna of <hi>Calabria</hi> looseth much of its
<pb facs="8"/> vertue, when it is gathered of flowers which grow in places that are too moist.</p>
   <p>Now amongst the multitude of these wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which like unto Reeds, have nothing but a pleasing verdure, and a faire shew of stately words, hollow and empty without any solid substance, there are one kinde, which may be called an Ants nest, a seed-plot or nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery of these wanton inventions, and that is it which beares the titles of tales and novels: amongst Italians, those of <hi>Boccace</hi> for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of language, are much esteemed, but they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o full of impurities, impieties, fopperies, and absurdities, that I have sometimes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how such a wit, capable of so many good things, hath wasted time in tales (setting aside their filthinesse) more befitting an old wife that would bring a childe to sleepe, then a person professing learning: they doe also make account of those of <hi>Baudell,</hi> which I have never seene, they esteem them because of the stile, but as I have heard by those that have read them, they containe such beastli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and abhominations, that they have not onely beene supprest by authority of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate,
<pb facs="8"/> as pernitious to good manners, but also by publike detestation: true it is that there was amongst the rest, some sad events which had beene gathered and translated into our tongue by <hi>Bell Forest,</hi> whereof he hath fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his tragicall histories, yet some of them would deserve correction, being full of flesh and bloud. They have also those of <hi>Giraldy,</hi> of <hi>Sausonin,</hi> of <hi>Straparolle,</hi> full of so much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiousnesse and dishonesty, that it is pitty to see these Bookes in the hands of youth, who sucke this Heraclian honey (sweet but vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous) through the sight, and which by its reading, teacheth such corruptions and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, as but by the practise of most dissolute persons would never be taught them.</p>
   <p>Moreover, in all these stories (for the most part) invented at will, there is su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h manifest fopperies, and such great want of judgement in the Authors, and of likelihood in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that it is a strange thing, that reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble spirits can be payd with such counterfeit and uncurrant coyne. Truely, wee are not men, but by reason, and when this light of our soule is out of its Eclipticke line, and
<pb facs="9"/> strayed from its way, we fall into bottomlesse pits of absurdities: but what shall we doe to cure those that delight in their follies?</p>
   <p>Amongst the Spaniards, above all writers of Romants, and great tellers of tales, novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and stories, those of <hi>Ceroantes</hi> are much esteemed: and truely having red them, I have found his wit to be very great in those small things. A man of the world, a great gyber and scoffer, and who handsomely, and to the uttermost, sets out his wares. <hi>Deigo Agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> hath followed these, adding unto his the surname of morall, because of the morals which he drawes at the end of those occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, which he recites. This man in my minde is more judicious, and lesse insolent, although he takes licence to flye out some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a little. Among our French, a fine wit, in truth, and who hath a fine stile, hath recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated himselfe in writing French tales or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, which farre surpasse the Italian, and are no whit behinde the Spanish: he is mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in his imaginations, and modest in his words, hee hath not deigned to set his name to this worke, wherein he seemes but to
<pb facs="9"/> have onely tryed his penne, which he desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateth to some higher and more serious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Another hath given us a taste of histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall diversities, but this booke is so little, that it is but a shew, which breeds a wish for an ampler piece. Vnto this may be annexed the tragicall Histories of <hi>Bell Forrest,</hi> and those made by <hi>Rosset,</hi> bearing the same title.</p>
   <p>These are the writings of that sort, which have fallen under my view, not that I have taken patience to reade them distinctly, but I have runne over some pieces of them, only as to feele their pulse, and informe my selfe of their language and Country. But for to say in generall what mine opinion is of these and all such like confused heapes of frivolous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, I cannot better compare them then to dainty garden knots &amp; borders which have Serpents hidden under their flowers, or unto fine fields: pleasing unto the eye, but full of Hemlocke and Aconitum, or unto Sallets, wherein are poysonous hearbs, or unto those fine Gold-Smiths workes, wherein are inserted base mettals,
<pb facs="10"/> and counterfeit stones, or unto those liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish <hi>Spanish</hi> dishes of meat, called <hi>pot porride,</hi> delicious in taste, but prejudiciall to health; or unto the horse of <hi>Troy,</hi> out of which came ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med souldiers, by whom that beautifull City was turned into ashes. I say not this so much to disgrace my adversaries, as to give testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to truth.</p>
   <p>Now (my deare Reader) it is this kinde of bookes which I strive to supplant by these singular Events, which I heare offer unto thy view, thou shalt not see therein those pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Eloquence, nor those industrious or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments wherewith those Antagonists a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne their ridiculous tales, to make them glyde the sweether into the mindes of them that spend time abouttheir Chymera's. But thou shalt here finde naturall beauties with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out art; I meane, examples which borrow all their grace and worth from the force of truth which upholds them, and whose testimonies are seene in the times, places, and persons.</p>
   <p>All these Events, which I call singular, as well for being rare and notable, as for having no connexion the one with the other, each
<pb facs="10"/> one making its body, hath as it were underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, either to cry downe a vice, or to extoll a vertue. The eng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ayme at, as being (as it is also the end of all good history) to withdraw from evill, and to excite unto good, to breed a holy horrour of bad actions, and a just de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of actions that are good, ever (as occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on serves) adding a few words, short, but pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, like to so many spurres, which pricke forward to well doing, and so many Bits which hold backe from the doing of evill, sometimes shewing the recompnce of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and sometimes the punishment of vice, to the end that love and feare may support the good, and retaine the bad in their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. This is the mark at which this worke wholly levels, whose intention at least can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamed.</p>
   <p>As for the manner I am to advertise thee, that I study as much as I can for brevity, and thereupon abridge it of all the trimmings with which I extend my other Histories, where giving my minde scope, as in a full sea, I hoyse up sayles, and run at large, as the course of my penne carries me: here I cut my
<pb facs="11"/> Vine, and nip of its buds, yea I clip my wings to keep me from soaring: I keep close to the matter, &amp; give little liberty unto my thoughts, to spread into digressions, if they be not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, and as it were bred in the subject, by reason whereof I have weaned my self from the sweet milke of poesie, and have abstained from putting any verses in these Events. I have also taken away the other graces, as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postrophes, dialogismes, cōplaints, speeches, conferences, letters, orations; in briefe, all that might enlarge or embellish, so that in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of our other relations, these are but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgements of histories, and as it were Ske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letons, nothing remaining but the bones of each Event, stript of the ornaments which might have set forth their bodies in a far fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer hew. In the art of painting, little pieces have their graces, as well as great pictures, which have all their dimensions: so have abridgements in their kindes, as well as lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ampler discourses: and as stronger blowes are given by a short weapon, then by a long; a wound with a Dagger being no lesse dangerous, then that with a sword: even so it
<pb facs="11"/> happens that the mind draws more profit frō an example restrained within the bounds of its subject, then from another whose super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous relations may either distract the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or leave it languishing: many times smal streames are more delectable then great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and the least springs more pleasing then torrents, and meats cut in small bits, are swallowed with most ease. There be mindes which foyle in reading a history of great length, humane patience being not of any great extent: but when Events are set downe in such a manner, as the end is not farre from the beginning, this is it which incourageth the reader, and both giveth him a desire of seeing further, and also eases him in reading, besides variety is alwaies more delectable, and gives better content, then uniformity, &amp; pleasure is a bait to a reader, which those that write, should in no wise contemne.</p>
   <p>This booke of Events is a Garland made of many flowers, a honey composed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearbs, whose juyces are different, a treacle made of divers ingredients, and wherein the Serpent of vice is seasoned with so many
<pb facs="12"/> antidotes, that in liew of hurting, it will doe good. It is a worke of inlaying, where each piece making its body, hath a severall colour and vertue, and all together make a prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, which will not be unpleasant, except it be unto those muddy unsettled spirits, who can like nothing of anothers doing, being burthensome unto themselves, and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some unto all the world.</p>
   <p>If I did write these Histories rather to please men, then to benefit my neighbour, it may bee I should be faine to feare their censures, and seeke to conjure or appease their bad humours. But should I entertaine such a thought, as to purchase reputation in this world, then would I set my selfe in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other posture, and would give unto my pen a subject more flashing, and ranging, but being too weake to soare into high matters, I am content that it shall keepe so low, even to touch the ground: and that bringing more profit to my neighbour, it should yeeld little or no fame unto the Author.</p>
   <p>Examples of good and evill have a like vertue, (provided) they meet with a disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="12"/> according in the soules of them that see them. For many reade books for curiosity, others for variety, or to passe time, and for want of other imployment, another with envy, few with sincerity, few with a desire to profit, and to put in practise the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions they finde therein; from whence proceeds the ill usage of so many Authors, with so much ingratitude and cruelty; that who so sets forth a Booke, exposes himselfe unto the mercy of mockers and detracters: drones which do but hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me about flowers, without gathering any honey from them; and as Spiders, who make venome of all that they reade.</p>
   <p>But let them say on, some good soules (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse) whose dispositions are inclined to vertue, will be glad to finde profitable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions set do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne, and sweetly mingled with varieties of pleasures fitting their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. And therefore I have strov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> by the helpe of my pen to publish examples worthy to be noted, to the end that wee may grow wise by the good or evill hap of others. This is the marke aymed at by all these Events,
<pb facs="13"/> which I have gathered in the great field of the world. It is your part, deare Reader, to extract honey out of the hardest stone, oyle out of the flint, studying a reformation of manners in this schoole of humane actions; Remembring alwaies that the secret (and if I may so say) the great worke of prudence and justice, is to avoyd evill, and to imbrace good.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>