<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS PROLOGVE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107642_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18335</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4917</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107642</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS PROLOGVE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the history of the valorous and witty knight-errant, Don Quixote of the Mançha : VVritten in Spanish by Michael Ceruantes: and now translated into English</title>
                 <author>Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 276, 279-504, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS PROLOGVE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow God defend! Reader, Noble or Plebeyan, what ere thou art: how earnestly must thou needs by this time expect this Prologue, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing that thou must find in it nothing but reuenge, brawling, and rayling vpon the Authour of the second <hi>Don Quixote,</hi> of whom I onely say as others say, that he was begot in <hi>Tordesillas,</hi> and borne in <hi>Tarragona?</hi> the truth is, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I meane not to giue thee content. Let it be neuer so generall a rule, that iniuries awaken and rouze vp choler in humble brests, yet in mine must this rule ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit an exception: Thou, it may be, wouldst haue mee be-Asse him, be-madman him, and be-foole him, but no such matter can enter into my thought; no, let his owne rod whip him; as hee hath brewed, so let him bake; else where he shall haue it: and yet there is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which I cannot but resent, and that is, that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrates vnto me my age, and my <note n="a" place="margin">He lost one of his hands.</note> mayme, as if it had been in my power, to hold Time backe, that so it should not passe vpon mee, or if my mayme had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne
<pb facs="4"/> me in a Tauerne, and not vpon the most famous <note n="b" place="margin">At the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Lepanto.</hi>
      </note> occasion which either the ages past or present haue seene, nor may the times to come looke for the like: If my wounds shine not in the eyes of such as behold them; yet shall they be esteemed at least in the iudgement of such as know how they were got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. A Souldiour had rather be dead in the battell, then free by running away: and so is it with me, that should men set before me and facilitate an impossibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, I should rather haue desired to haue beene in that prodigious action; then now to bee in a whole skinne, free from my skarres, for not hauing been in it. The skarres which a Souldiour shewes in his face and brest, are starres which leade others to the Heauen of Honor, &amp; to the desire of iust praise: and besides it may be noted, that it is not so much mens pens which write, as their iudgements; and these vse to be better'd with yeeres. Nor am I insensible of his calling me Enuious, and describing me as an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. What Enuy may be, I vow seriously, that of those two sorts, that are; I skill not but of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Noble, and ingenuons Enuy, which being so, as it is, I haue no meaning to abuse any Priest; especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he hath annexed vnto him the Title of <hi>FAMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAR</hi> of the Inquisition: and if he said so, as it seemes by this second Author, that he did, he is vtterly decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: For I adore his wit, admire his workes, and his continuall vertuous imployment; and yet in effect I cannot but thanke this sweet Senior Author, for say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that my Nouelles are more Satyrick, then Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar; and that yet they are good, which they could not be, were they not so quite thorow. It seemes, thou
<pb facs="4"/> tellest me, that I write somewhat limited, and obscure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and containe my selfe within the bounds of my modestie, as knowing, that a man ought not adde mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery to him that is afflicted, which doubtlesse must needs be very great in this Senior, since he dares not appeare in open field, in the light, but conceales his Name, faines his Countrey, as if hee had committed some Treason against his King. Well, if thou chance to light vpon him, and know him, tell him from mee, that I hold my selfe no whit aggrieued at him: for I well know what the temptations of the Diuell are; and one of the greatest is, when hee puts into a mans head, that he is able to compose and print a booke, whereby he shall gaine as much Fame as money, and and as much money as Fame. For confirmation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I intreat thee, when thou art disposed to be merry and pleasant, to tell him this Tale.</p>
   <p>There was a Mad-man in Seuill, which hit vpon one of the prettiest absurd tricks that euer mad-man in this world lighted on, which was: Hee made him a Cane sharpe at one end, and then catching a Dogge in the street, or elsewhere, hee held fast one of the Dogges legges vnder his foot, and the other hee held vp with his hand. Then fitting his Cane as well as he could, behinde, he fell a blowing till hee made the Dogge as round as a Ball: and then, holding him still in the same manner, hee gaue him two clappes with his hand on the belly, and so let him goe, Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to those which stood by (which alwayes were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) how thinke you, my Masters, Is it a small matter to blow vp a Dogge like a Bladder? and how thinke you, Is it a small labour to make a Booke? If this
<pb facs="5"/> Tale should not fit him: then, good Reader, tell him this other; for this also is of a Mad-man and a Dog. In <hi>Cordoua</hi> was another Mad-man, which was wont to carry on the top of his head, a huge piece of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not of the lightest, who meeting a masterlesse Dogge, would stalke vp close to him: and on a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, downe with his burden vpon him: the Dogge would presently yearne, and barking and yelling run away, three streets could not hold him. It fell out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards among other Dogges (vpon whom hee let fall his load) there was a Cappers Dogge, which his Master made great account of, vpon whom hee let downe his great stone, and tooke him full on the head: the poore batter'd Curre cryes pittifully. His Master spies it, and affected with it, gets a meat-yard, assaults the mad-man, and leaues him not a whole bone in his skinne; and at euery blow that he gaue him, he cryes out, Thou Dogge, Thou Thiefe, my Spaniell! Saw'st thou not, thou cruell Villaine, that my Dogge was a Spaniell? And euer and anon repeating still his Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell, he sent away the Mad-man all blacke and blue. The Mad-man was terribly skarred herewith, but got away, and for more then a moneth after neuer came abroad: At last out hee comes with his inuention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and a bigger load then before: and comming where the Dogge stood, viewing him ouer and ouer againe very heedily; he had no minde, he durst not let goe the stone, but onely said, Take heed, this is a Spaniell. In fine, whatsoeuer Dogges he met, though they were Mastifs or Fysting-Hounds, hee still said they were Spaniels. So that after that, he neuer durst throw his great Stone any more. And who knowes
<pb facs="5"/> but the same may befall this our Historian, that hee will no more let fall the prize of his wit in Bookes? for in being naught, they are harder then Rockes: tell him too, that for his menacing, that with his booke he will take away all my gaine; I care not a straw for him: but betaking my selfe to the famous Interlude of <hi>Peren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denga:</hi> I answere him, Let the Old man my Master liue, and Christ bee with vs all. Long liue the great <hi>Conde de Lemos</hi> (whose Christianity and well-knowne Liberalitie against all the blowes of my short fortune, keepes me on foote) and long liue that eminent Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Cardinall of <hi>Toledo, Don Bernardo de San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doual y Rojas.</hi> Were there no printing in the world, or were there as many Bookes printed against mee, as there are letters in the Rimes of <hi>Mingo Revulgo;</hi> these two Princes, without any sollicitation of flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or any other kinde of applause, of their sole boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty haue taken vpon them to doe me good, and to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour me; wherein I account my selfe more happy and rich, then if fortune, by some other ordinary way, had raised me to her highest: Honour, a Poore man may haue it, but a Vicious man cannot: Pouerty may cast a mist vpon Noblenes, but cannot altogether obscure it: but as the glimmering of any light of it selfe, though but thorow narrow chinkes and Cranyes, comes to be esteemed by high and Noble spirits, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently fauoured. Say no more to him; nor will I say any more to thee: but onely aduertise that thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that this Second part of <hi>Don Quixote,</hi> which I offer thee, is framed by the same Art, and cut out of the same cloth that the first was: in it I present thee with <hi>Don Quixote</hi> enlarged, &amp; at last dead and buried,
<pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/> that so no man presume to raise any farther reports of him; those that are past are enow: and let it suffice that an honest man may haue giuen notice of these discreet follies, with purpose not to enter into them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more. For plenty of any thing, though neuer so good, makes it lesse esteemed: and scarsitie (though of euill things) makes them somwhat accounted of. I forgot to tell thee that thou mayst expect <hi>Persiles,</hi> which I am now about to finish; as also the Second part of <hi>Galatea.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>