<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Churche off England / and all that Loue the trueth in yt: Thomas Cartwright Wisheth mercy / and peace / from God our Father / and from our Lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107569_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18080</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4714</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107569</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Churche off England / and all that Loue the trueth in yt: Thomas Cartwright Wisheth mercy / and peace / from God our Father / and from our Lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second replie of Thomas Cartwright: agaynst Maister Doctor Whitgiftes second answer, touching the Churche discipline</title>
                 <author>Cartwright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schirat, Michael</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Heidelberg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, dlxvi, that is dclxvi, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Churche off England / and all that Loue the trueth in yt: Thomas Cartwright Wisheth mercy / and peace / from God our Father / and from our Lorde Iesus Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church off God so ofte vs scripture not compared onely / but fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured in the Citie Ierusalem: serueth for instruction / in this cause. For as in yt / the wal first broken downe / was last made vp againe / and that more then 14. yeares after the temple buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">
         <hi>Esr.</hi> 6. 15. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> so is yt commenly in the spirituall wal off the churche / whiche is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline the lorde appointed / aswel for strenght of yt / as for houlding out of all aduersarie power / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yt be corruption off doctrine or manners. The first is to be seen / in the Act. of thapostles: where (after the churches gathered by preaching) there was an eldership seuerally placed in them) to whom the execution of the church discipline doth especially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain. The other may as easily appear / to him that considereth the estate off the churche after the Apostles / by monuments off those times: in which allwaies as this fort off gouernement left by them was first suffred to decaie / so the purenes of doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne decreased: vntill the churche yt selfe (except a few stones here and there scattered) was browght to heapes off dust. Yf y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked / why the discipline hauing right to entre with the doctrine: findeth not alwaies / that fauour amongest men. The cause <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant / that when Satan can not gain this first point to houlde the doctrine owt off a city or Kingdome: he sweareth after the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond / that yt may be there with smallest fruict / and shortest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. Wherin let (I beseche yow) be considered: his doings / against the building off the wal off Ierusalem. For if he bestirred himself so / in hindering that materiall wal: it wil be les meruaile / yf for hinderance off this spirituall he trudge to and fro / open his whole pack off subtilties / and as yt is in prouerb <hi>bestovv both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>vet and dry.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p> And first touching the persons he vseth / in his fight against both: they are not much vnlike. For in steed off a bastard kinde off <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Esr.</hi> 4. 12 <hi>Neh.</hi> 6. 1.</note> Israelites / Apostataes from God and his tru seruice (which were there the foreine enemies): we haue now the Papistes / who (as shal appear) he set in the forward of this battail / against the discipline now propounded. And as now we haue within the church / whiche couered with the name off the gospel and off the teachers theroff / giue a more daungerous assault then the Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes: So were there then euen off the <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Neh.</hi> 6. 10. 17. 18. 19.</note> Iewes them selues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der gouerners and Prophetes / which secretly and openly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them selues. As for the practises / they are so like in bothe: that all which will open their eies / maie easely espie the same worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. For as the enemies then placed their cheef strenght / in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusations against the church / that <hi>yf it vvere</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Esr.</hi> 4. 12 <hi>&amp;c. Neh.</hi> 2. 19.</note>
      <hi>suffered to laie the foundaciōs of the vval it vvould moue seditiō, and rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Kinge:</hi> euen so our aduersary / to arme the Prince aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inst this cause / soundeth nothing more then rebellion / sedition / and suche like. Yf this were not able to discrie / or (at least) to giue warning off this vnfaithfull dealing: yet this may. That these are the verie weapons off the papistes / which not able amongest vs with so great succes to be vsed by them selues as those which are knowne enemies: haue bene ministred to the D. that being thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne owte off his hand in whose mouthe is the gospell / they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght be thowght to haue bene made for defence / which were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for ouerthrow of yt. For where Brentius teacheth / that the ministers owght not to beare dominion ouer the churches like princes: Hosius accuseth him / that by the same meane / <hi>he vvent about to</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Lib. de haeres. nost. tep.</note>
      <hi>displace Caesar.</hi> And vpon like occasion / that <hi>vve vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>de le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>git. iudic. rerū eccl.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>ouerthrovv al kingdomes and superiority: that men might doe) vvat they liste. That yf the Almans, had once</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de cathol. ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>shaken off the Pope: they vvould shake off, Caesar sone after.</hi> Yf these be compared with diuers off the D. accusations / and namely with that page 455. lin. 1. yt will be meruail that (onles he were in this point taught by the same spirit Hosius was) he could iump so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen / not onely with the like accusation / but almost with the same wordes. But this shall better appeare / in discours off this boke
<pb facs="3"/> where ys shewed not onely that he hathe the like / but the verie self same cause with the grossest Papistes. I say the grossest / for that in some pointes / as off the churches election and pastorall residence / there are found off them more fauorable to the trwth then he: which ioining with Catholike writers both ould / and of our time / haue written against the estate off the Popish churche in that behalf.</p>
   <p>And that no mans simplicity be abused by an owtward profession off the gospell / as thowgh yt were vnlike that they w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich professed yt should be enimies to the trwe discipline: or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible that the same whiche cry out off the Tyranny off Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ / shoulde refuse the moderat and wholsom gouernement of Christ: yt may please them to vnderstand that this cause hathe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this bydden the assault not off the Papistes alone / but euen off them which make shew off so deadly war with papistry: that the greatest force of their resistance / hathe bene a feare ether pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended / or vainly phansied / least the gyuing place to the discipline shoulde draw after yt the popishe Tyranny. <note n="a" place="margin">M. Cap i to vnto M. Farel in the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke off M. Cal. Epist</note> Capito a man off singuler learning and godlines / affirmeth that it was obiected vnto them whiche <hi>vvente about to restore the discipline. that they vvould be Tyrans ouer the churche vvhich vvas free, and cal back againe a nvve popedome.</hi> M. <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Vpon</hi> 4. <hi>Ephes.</hi>
      </note> Bucer: <hi>Satā goeth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that by restoring of the discipline, the faithfull Ministers should be thovvght to seek ambitously the same Tyranny, vvh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich Antechrist did.</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">In the li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe off M. Calu.</note> M. Beza <hi>vvhen the Eldership and excō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatiō vvere to be instituted: there vvāted not vvhich cried ovvt, that the popish tyranny vvas by that meanes called back again: also that the magistrats office, vvas therby in parte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded.</hi> Now if these slaunders be compared with the <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>pa</hi> 299. 27. <hi>line pag.</hi> 459. 47. <hi>lin. item pa.</hi> 560. <hi>lin.</hi> 5. <hi>item pa.</hi> 646. <hi>li.</hi> 29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> Answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: al may vnderstand / that althowgh / the instrments vsed ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ainst the discipline vary in tyme and countrie / yet the autor (misle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ading some by simplicitie / and thrusting other headlong throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh couetousnes or ambition) ys the same in our countrey / which was then in Germany / Fraunce / or Sanoy. For that the discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne now propounded / is the same whiche suffered this cōtradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on off certein professors off the Gospell / shall manifestly appear
<pb facs="4"/> in this discours: and may be partly vnderstode both by Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap> letters / written to comfort a ministre off Geneua then Wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for yt / as by Bezas wordes which particularly note one or two partes therof. Nether can disagreemēt of the fauourers the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reoff / in interpretation of some place / signification of some word / alteration off some circumstance (yf any be) hinder this: no more then diuers pictures off one face / hauing al the same great and principal drawghts / can hinder vs from acknowledging the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me visage in them al: albeit one be more coningly drawn then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / haue more liuely and orient couloures then other / haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne smal line more or les then other. Onles peraduenture / men wil be so vnaduised / to denie the doctrine off the Gospell to be the same professed at Geneua / at Zurick / at Witemberg: because the professors / had in some smaller points their seueral Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
   <p>Another principall kinde off artillery / wherwith the D. le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueleth at this wal off church discipline: is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>haccusation / off Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptistry. This also (as may appeare) is taken from the Papistes. For when the persequuting off the churche in Fraunce (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re together with the doctrine this discipline was established) was misliked off the Almanes: the French to appease them said / <note place="margin">Calu. in his praefa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to the psames.</note>
      <hi>there vvere none so cruelly handled, but Anabaptists and troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesome felovves, vvhich vvould ouerthrovv not religion onely, but the vvhole order off the commē vvealth.</hi> And althowgh the D. hath in this behalf trauailed mightily / and gathered (as yt were) a heape off stones to throw at vs: yet for feare off being conuincted off so manifest vntrwthes he dare not throw one / but priuilie and as yt were vnder hand: saying / <hi>he will not accuse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he will not condemne any.</hi> that is: he will (forsothe) not flea vs him self / but hould our legs / while other flea vs. But he shal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so escape / the iudgemement off God. For yf he were giltie / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 20</note> which kept their garments that cast the stones: how much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re shall he / that put stones in their handes. althowgh / yf we were suche: we owght so to be noted / that others might take heed / off suche detestable heretikes. All which false surmises with diuers others of <hi>Donatism Papism puratanism.</hi> We might with one
<pb facs="4"/> sentence off the holy man Iob / haue refuted. For so are they not onely vntrw / but for the moste parte without al colour of trwth: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob</hi> 31. 35 36.</note>
      <hi>that taking our aduersaries boke off accusations vpon our sh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oulders, and applying them vnto our heades</hi> (that al might read and see them) wee might <hi>as off a crovvne,</hi> or robe haue receiued commendation by them. Howbeit / because there was some da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unger least the D. lofty titles / and glittering estate might ether seduce som simple ones / or vtterly carie away those whose mindes were forestalled with some preiudice against the cause we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein: I thowght good once at large / ād peece by peece / to lay forth the vnworthines of his accusations. Now I see / there is no end of his vnhonest charges: I meane not by further answer in pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit off his oulde / or auoiding his nwe / ether weary my selfe or the reader. For seing the vntrwth off them / is in the eies and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res off all: why shoulde I trauaile to stop his Throate / which (as an open sepulchre off vntrw sumises) wil as (seemeth) neuer with any reasonable answer be filled vp.</p>
   <p>And that yow may haue a taste off his equitie: note (I bese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che yow) his answers vnto our defence. <hi>This is wel said, if vnfained:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 33. <hi>pag.</hi> 55. <hi>pag.</hi> 33.</note>
      <hi>These glorious wordes are but mistes, to blind the eies off the simple: The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptistes would saie the like.</hi> Verely if they say so they shall deteste them selues / with all their wicked phantasies: and gyue as soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a Confession of the trwth / as the Doctor can make any. But let vs imagin him selfe accused off all these pointes / which he sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth of vs: I would gladly know / what he would answer. Let him conceiue his purgation as effectually / and in as good wordes as he can / make al the protestations he can / offer him self to what examination he can: how easie ys yt for his aduersarie with the same equitie he vseth towardes vs / to dashe al. <hi>This is wel said, but it is fained: there was neuer heretike, which to hide bis poison, pretended not some colour off truth, &amp;c.</hi> And by the grace off God / we are as far / yea further also (as shall appeare) from al pointes off Anabaptisme / then he. <hi>But (saith he) let the like effectes proceding of like</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 33.</note>
      <hi>causes, and in like maner: iudge the likelihoode betweene the Anabaptistes, and them.</hi> Truly yf he proue the causes like / the controuersie is at an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>de. And if the searche off the trwth had bene his marke: here he
<pb facs="5"/> would haue begon / where the triall is certaine / and not off the effectes. Which allthowgh they be falsly surmised: yet some are suche / as maie ensue (albeit after another sorte) aswell the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching off the trwth / as the publishing off falshood.</p>
   <p>And surely if the Anabaptistes / when they rose in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny / had met with suche confuters: yt is very like / that they (now put to flight) would haue occupied the greatest part off it. But the godlie mynisters / assured of a good cawse / prouoked to most solemn disputations: where all seyng their vanities / might lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to deteste them / and them selues (made to vnderstand their fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies) might be stricken with shame / which might bringe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. This they did by example off the Godlie learned in times past / and off Augustine namely: Who prouoketh the Donatistes and Manichies to Disputation / in the hearing off all his church. This cause therfore if yt should not preuaile / by force off trwthe yt must gaine / throwghe the indirecte meanes / and cowardly fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght off the Answerer: so far from procuring this trial / that he accuseth <hi>me as desirous of popular praise: because refusing his priuat confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rence</hi> (as he some where hath affirmed) I onely put him in min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 354.</note> / of a disputacion. Wherto also perteineth / that he counteth yt <hi>Anabaptistical:</hi> that this ys propounded <hi>in places where the gospell hath</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 12. 34.</note>
      <hi>bene alredy planted.</hi> As if there were a fitter place / to propounde the Discipline: then vvhere the doctrine / hathe allredie beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. where shoulde the vvall be fitlier made: then where the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / is before builded. Where / the diche caste: but where the Orche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde / is alreadie planted. Yf yt had bene preached / where was ignorance / or small knowledge of the gospell the would haue tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en great aduantage. for that they might so haue abused the blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnes of their heares to cause them beleue that which those that haue their eyes open could not be brought vnto. Now they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in places / vvhere the gospell was planted: he will make that also serue for a stepp / for his accusation to clime vp by. So that howsoeuer we behaue our selues / what commoditie off circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance soeuer we haue: the D. hathe suche an engine / that he can not onely cause yt not to serue for vs / but also make against vs. For sure I am / no place could haue bene les suspected then Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Cambridge / two off the highest hills in all the realme:
<pb facs="5"/> from whence bothe the sounde off yt might be the easilest caried into all other places / and which abounding with knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge off the gospell / were fittest to iudge off the goodnes off the cause. Wherin I doubte not / but the good hande off Gods dire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction / and the example off the Apostells: haue bene considered. who that they might haue fuller sheues off the seed of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine / preased to the chief and moother cities / making their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte / that the mother being won / the daughters round abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wte vvould be easilier intreated. And althowghe yt come to often to pas / that there is some Amazias / or high preist nere the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / which vseth both his eies to watche that none come thether / to disquiet his vnlawfull possession: yet forsomuche as it is as impossible to pull the winges off the winde that yt should not blow / or shut the windowes off the heauens that they should not raine / as to stop that trwth / which God in his holy worde hath breathed / and doeth raine by the clowdes off his mynistery: I dowbt not / but the voice off yt is come to the highest / and shall haue that fruict in time / which God hath disposed off. Yf yt should not: yet euery faithfull mynister is detter vnto his flocke / <note place="margin">20. <hi>Act.</hi> 27.</note> off the whole trwth learned owt off the worde off God: aswell for reioicing their heartes in encrease of knowledg / as that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might bewail their synnes for want off yt: and forthwith be stirred to continuall praier / that God would encline the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces heart and off others in autoritie / to gyue yt that defence w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich apperteineth.</p>
   <p>Nether doe we therefore call vpon the examination off our doctrine / as thowgh we feared least our behauiour should be examined / or as if yt resembled the Anabaptistes maner of liuing: but that I might shew / how disorderly the D. goeth to worck. For althowgh before the Lord / we (and I for my part especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) as myserable synners hang down our heades and couer our faces: yet our behauiour (throwgh his grace) towching that sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised of vs / ys such) as we nothing fear / but with all indifferent iudgement yt conteineth plentifull remedy / against the sting off all suche slaunderous tonges. Wise Physicions / when the desease is vnknown: seeke yt by owtward tokens off pulse / vrine / &amp;c. Yf we had nourished any night or corner doctrine / which we whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spering
<pb facs="6"/> in the eares of certeine / woulde not haue had come owt of the doores of our priuat houses: yt should haue bene accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for wisdom / by signes and coniectures to haue inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into our couert opinions. But now seing we haue Fanckly and openly published our iudgementes and as yt were on the Faire and Market daies proclaimed them / offering them in scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / in churches / by preaching / by writing / not onely to the tast off the commen people but to the examination of the best learned: after al this to inquire by signes and tokens / is to seek his aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary whiche standeth hard by / to call for him which is present. And yt is as if one / to know what iudgement an other is of: had rather take his mark by the colour of his coat or tag of his point / then by his speache or hand writing. And if it were / the good will off God: I would (for this matter) he had a window / to look into our consciences. To make and ende of answer / to these sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises / whatsoeuer is proper ether to the heresie off Papistes / Anabaptistes / Donatists / or puritanes: that wee vtterly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / vnto the bottomles pit off hell. But if amongest the filth of their herises / there may be found any good thing (as yt were a grain off good corn in a great deal of darnell): that wee willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue / not as theiree / but as the Iues did the holy Arke from the Philistines / wherof they were vniust owners. For herein yt is trw / that is said: <hi>the sheep must not lay dovvn her fel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavvse</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>August.</hi> 2. <hi>lib. Serm. de mōte.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>she seeth the vvolf somtim clothed vvith yt.</hi> yea yt may come to pas / that the Synaguog off Satan: may haue some one thing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> somtime / with more conuenience / then the trw and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike churche off Christ. Such was the ceremonie off powring water once onely vpon the childe in baptisme / vsed with vs and in the moste reformed churches: which in some age / was vsed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely by those off the Eunomian heresy. As for the Answerer / let <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sozom.</hi> 6. <hi>lib.</hi> 20 <hi>c.</hi>
      </note> him remember that the iust Iudge liueth: before whome (if he doe not speedelie repent) one day notwithstanding his gloses <hi>(I <hi>accuse none,</hi> I <hi>apply yt to none)</hi>
      </hi> he muste houlde vp his hand / with Satan the Prince off the accusers off the children off God: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runto I doubt not but his own conscience is his Apparitor / and hath giuen him summonce. And thus much for answer / vnto the D. generall / partly accusations and partly surmises: against the
<pb facs="6"/> fauourers / off the church discipline now propounded.</p>
   <p>There folow / particular charges: against the autors off the admonition / and against me. Those against them haue bene an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered / and the answers so far forth as they touche the cause / are in this boke mainteined: sauing certein new charges. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I dowbt not but they will take yt in good part / that I vse silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: seing that some of the smaller thinges are such as lie not in my knowledg / and some so manifestly vntrw / that they need not fear any credit to be gyuen vnto them: the D. him selfe (as I thinck) not belieuing them. Of his accusations against me / because some haue eie aswel to the speakers as to the thinges spoken: I trust / yt shall not be greuous / yf I answer somthing. Especially when in this preface / beside other thinges: I purpose (God willing) to Synk / nigh half his later book. For if one would make suruey off reproches / vntrw surmises / and false accusations / wherwith he hath frawght yt: beside a nwe lode which he hath charged the second edition off his first boke with: he should (I suppose) finde / nigh one half spent in those wares. Wherin he dealeth with me / as certein beastes; which pursued cast forth behinde them an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cicero.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>li. de nat. deorum.</hi>
      </note> sauour / therby to affray their hunters from further chasing them. In deed / they are very vnpleasant: but the good sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour off the trwth / and off honest behauiour in thinges he accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth me off / hath (by the grace off God) so comforted all the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses off my minde / that he hath not escaped by this pollicie.</p>
   <p>Some off his accusations / touche the cause: but the most part / touche yt not. Off this later kynd one sort are off my maner of liuing▪ albeit he count yt <hi>a childishe kinde off confuting, that one should leaue the cause, and take him self to the person.</hi> Here / my ministerie is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerslie <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag</hi> 25.</note> accused: as that I did not seke for the ordre off priesthood as it is called: for that is that he meaneth I <hi>should haue done by othe or els departed the Colledge.</hi> The answer hereto is longer / then this <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 799. <hi>pag.</hi> 709.</note> treatise may embrace: which I am readie to exhibit before him / to whom it belongeth: because I am prouoked / I humbly desire him to receiue the cause. But in a word: yt ys a meer cauill. For the meaning off the statute off the howse / is to prouide that men should not turne their studies / to other professions off law &amp;c: but that there should be to furnish the Colledge off a numbre
<pb facs="7"/> off preachers / off which I was one / as sone as I entred. Nether was there any dutie of mynisterie / which the Colledg could requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re off me; that I was not inabled to doo according to the lawes of the churche off England / by vertue off that mynisterie / which I had receiued. So that the law yt self (as that whose meaning was fulfilled euen with my entrie) did not require yt. Also the corruption off the law / or at the least off his interpretation (bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men to beg a ministery and therby after a sorte to testifie off them selues that they befit for yt) might after knowledg that I owght not to beg it / iustly kepe me back. By how muche more / I were worthie to be condemned / if (as he accuseth) I had <hi>ambitiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly desired to be the Queenes maiesties diuinitie reader:</hi> for which / I neuer <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 586.</note> opened lip. Yf I had / how knoweth he / I did yt <hi>ambitiously:</hi> who maketh yt <hi>lawful, to aske yt.</hi> So that onles / he know my hart: my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 48.</note> for it (yf any had bene) is iustified by his diuinity. The life / I answer to an other not vnlife: that I <hi>earnestly desired, the degree</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 781.</note>
      <hi>off doctorship.</hi> Wherin beside that I moued nothing / but yelded onely to the request off certein frindes: I had (before my grace propounded in the scholes) the aduise off more than a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen learned ministers. Who considering / that I had the office off a Doctorin the vniuersitie: were off opinion / that (for the good they estemed might be done therby) I might swalow the fond and idle ceremonies / which accompanie yt. His fourth is / that I <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 12. <hi>pag.</hi> 446.</note>
      <hi>haue forsaken the ministerie.</hi> wherunto I answer / as I <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>In this boke pa.</hi> 154. <hi>li.</hi> 16.</note> haue for them whom he likewise chargeth. His fift / that I my selfe <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 225.</note>
      <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching before here and there where <hi>I</hi> thowght good,</hi> now condemne yt in others: the answer whereof / is partly page 45. line 17. off his / and partly page 41. line 20. off my boke. The last / <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 354.</note>
      <hi>that <hi>I</hi> refused his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence:</hi> which is vntrwe. For beside that I answered / that yt was meet the doctrine I had taught openly / shoulde be defended op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enly / : and beside that also I went to two off the vniuersitie Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors / to be conferred with: I offered my self to his priuat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference / which althowgh he had promised / yet vnder pretence that I was (as he said) vncorrigible / he would not performe. The truth is / he offered priuat conference by writing: but hauing before experience off his vnfaithfulnes many waies / I refused
<pb facs="7"/> yt. And thus muche to his accusations / towching as well my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mming to and goyng from the ministerie: as also off my behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in yt. Of the most wheroff / there are diuers witnesses: and off all / the Lord him self bothe witnes and iudge / whose presence in this defence I set before myne eies. Vnles peraduenture / that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so may seem to appertein hether: that by defence off this cause / I <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 173.</note> woulde <hi>chuse my selfe the place off my mynistery.</hi> Wherof I lay euill foundations / which teache that no man may place him self: but wait / for his calling: especially when by his doctrine / I may feed in euerie pasture / and lightlie grasing or taking the vppermost of one / streight way goo to an other.</p>
   <p>In the other part of my life / after he had thrust me out of the Colledge: he accuseth me for <hi>going vp and downe doing no good, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>p.</hi> 241. 283</note>
      <hi>at other mēs tables.</hi> that I was not idle / I suppose he knoweth to well: Whether well occupied or no / let it be iudged. I <hi>liued</hi> in deed / <hi>at other mens tables,</hi> hauing no hous nor wife of myne own: but not without their desire / ād with smal delight of mine / for feare of euil tonges. And althowgh I were not able / to requite yt: yet towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des some I went abowte yt / instructing their children partely in the principles off religion / partly in other learning. His other accusations / beside the cause: are off my maner off writing. The matter is blamed: for that (as he saith) <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 207</note>
      <hi>yt consisteth wholy of other mens notes and collections, and that <hi>I</hi> haue</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 412.</note>
      <hi>scarce red one off the autors which <hi>I</hi> haue alledged: yea and that <hi>I</hi> also</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 123.</note>
      <hi>contēne them, namely maister;</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels Catechism. And for the forme. It is blamed as vndutifull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 1. 9.</note>
      <hi>Archbishops, bishops, &amp;c.</hi> namely the <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 423.</note>
      <hi>Bishop of Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and himselfe especially. That off contempt off M. Nowels / and other mens workes: I detest as intollerable arrogancie. The other / wherin the question is off great reading: I let pas. For yf he be learned / and I not / haue read them all and I scarce one: it will easely appear to the learned: beside that (as I haue said) it towcheth not the cause. Onely I admonish / that he doe yt hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / with better ground. For notwitstanding (it is like he hunteth me with moe howndes / then I him: yet beside those places I confes my selfe to haue receiued / he noteth not many / and (that excepted off Ierome mistaken for Musculus) not one trewlie.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p> Let vs therfore come to the forme. Where in my behauiour towardes the bishop of Salisbury / I would gladly know of him / what wordes he could haue prescribed me: wherby I might mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re modestly haue dissented from him. So that vnles the simple defence of the cause / be misbehauiour: I am well assured / there is no dutie broken. For my speches off the Archbishops / &amp;c. general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / yf all should be taken either in this or the former book against their persons / which I speak against their offices: his accusation should not be / altogither vntrew. But as condemning these of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or their corruptions / I make no conscience to speake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuously off them: so diuers off the persons which beare them / both for their learning / ād proof of godlines shewed in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes past / I will not cease to reuerence / vntil which (I hope wil not be) by open enimitie against a knowne trwth / their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciēces shall think them selues vnworthy. And this to an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent reader / shal suffice: for towardes the D. I haue no remedie / which expoundeth all duetifull sayinges <hi>counterfaict humilitie, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Smooth wordes to get credit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>My dewtie towardes him / is accused diuersly / of <hi>vnbrother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pa.</hi> 4. 8. 9 12.</note>
      <hi>vnfaithfulnes, wante of good will:</hi> made heinous / by circumstance of <hi>periury and vnthankfulnes</hi> Wherein I wil not answer / that I vsed not you as maister / because yow vsed not me as felow: but ask <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 1. 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> yow / wherin this breache off duetie consisteth? Yf <hi>Iowe yow fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> Iowe yt more vnto the lorde: yf <hi>good will,</hi> the trwth must be preferred: yf <hi>the master of Trinitie Colledg</hi> be a frend / the trwth is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re: Yf yow <hi>a brother,</hi> the trwth owght to be <hi>brother, sister, mother and al.</hi> Against what part off trw fidelitie ys yt / to reproue him openly by writing: which had openly by writing spoken euill off that / which I was / and am perswaded to be the euerlasting trw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th off God / and reuiled those / which mainteined yt. Against what poinct / off good will / to haue shewed him the way / whom I iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be owt: to light him a candle / whom I saw in this poinct to grope in darcknes. And if I did yt sharper / then your tast can like off / beside that bitter thinges / are often wholesomer then sw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eet: yow should not thinck muche to be stricken with the back off the sword / which haue smitten others with the edge / nor to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtlie
<pb facs="8"/> pricked vvith some empaire off your credit / vvhich hauē thrust others throwgh / in taking from them so muche as lay i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yow / al opinion both of godlines and learning. Yow doubt / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I <hi>meant good faith when <hi>I</hi> called yow a brother:</hi> take heed lest in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no credit vnto others / yow leaue no place for others to giue any to yow. And if I had offended / in these: yet my vnthākfulnes / can not be great. Yow neuer gaue me any thing in my bosome or secretly / what yow haue giuen by sound off trump and openly: can not be hidden. But my reproches, and (as yow often cal them) <hi>gybes:</hi> can not be excused. yt is not meet / that I should my self sit in iudgement off my owne modestie: yt ys vnreasonable also / that yow the partie grieued should. For as selfeloue may blinde mine eyes / and (as parents in their children) not onely cause me not to see the blemishe / but also to thinck yt an ornament: so may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure dasel yours / and cause your iudgement to decline to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che on the one side. My conscience dōth not hetherto accuse me / in this behalfe: others also whom this hath misliked / vvil pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duenture be more fauourable: if it be first considered / that yow account diuers for pleasant speaches / which are not / therby to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide that yow could not answer. Of which sort is that 767. line 6. and 576. line 23. Secondly / if yt be considered / that yow take some thinges otherwise: then I vvrote them. For example / where I note your homelie mirth <hi>of the curst wife, and theef which stole the</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 707.</note>
      <hi>priests purse,</hi> to haue bene <hi>vvith the baggipe and not vvith ether the harpe or lute:</hi> yow expound it / as thowghe I had taken my self <hi>to the countrey wherin yow were born.</hi> Which verely I ment not / but had regard onely to the greke prouerb / wherof Tully maketh <note place="margin">In orat. pro Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raena.</note> mention: <hi>that those vvhich could not come to the honour to handle the harpe, vvere content to vse the bagpipe.</hi> Which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident / in that I oppose <hi>countrey,</hi> not <hi>your countrey, <hi>your mirthe, to learned mirth.</hi>
      </hi> Here also (seemeth) should be considered / how yow haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oden vs: vvith those reproches / vvhich yow accuse me of. Wherin / not to waste paper in rehersall of all: I will onely giue a tast of your later book, for that / off your other boke in w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich all know your intemperancie: yow denie there is any suche thing / because I gathered yt not. <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</note>
   </p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="9"/> Adders and Sepentes swarme amongest. <hi>yovv pag.</hi> 50.</q>
   <p>
      <hi>A <hi>mind ful of reuengement,</hi>
      </hi> 799. <hi>Ould rancour,</hi> 2. <hi>Stomackes suche, and arrogancy so great,</hi> 12. <hi>Stoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cke swelling,</hi> 109. <hi>Boiling,</hi> 56. <hi>Spirit of yowrs bursteth,</hi> 37. <hi>He swelleth like the sea</hi> 423. <hi>Reueale that lump off arrogancye and ambition,</hi> 467. <hi>deep dissembled hypocricie,</hi> 467.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A <hi>face puffed vp with arrogancy and vaineglorie,</hi>
      </hi> 799.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Maner off writing spitefull mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious contemptuous owtragious,</hi> 12. <hi>Arrogant,</hi> 32. <hi>Scoulding,</hi> 12. <hi>pratling,</hi> 512. <hi>lying,</hi> 467. <hi>A <hi>shameles and wicked lie,</hi>
      </hi> 422. <hi>Tonges vnnatural</hi> 6. <hi>VVauering, wicked, wretched,</hi> 422. <hi>Hoat eloquence,</hi> 409. <hi>Hoate Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,</hi> 45. <hi>Cynicall Rhetoricke,</hi> 391. <hi>Lucians Rhetorick,</hi> 489. <hi>Figure off lying,</hi> 812. <hi>VVhether will this vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous mouthe reache?</hi> 445. <hi>VVordes serpentine and viperous,</hi> 422. <hi>He blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth owt, stormeth against me,</hi> 56. <hi>Roreth like a Lyon,</hi> 423.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Off a diuine become a scorneful iester,</hi> 577. <hi>Your veine off gybing and iesting,</hi> 25. <hi>Flowting,</hi> 91. <hi>Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant scoffs and frumpes,</hi> 336. <hi>Heath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish floutes and frumpes,</hi> 470. <hi>Boke pestered with moe stoutes and iestes then hardinges. VVhat dronken poet, prophane Philosopher, or boy off grammer schole knoweth not &amp;c.</hi> 151. <hi>Heathnish confuting,</hi> 25. <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>she abusing scripture,</hi> 262. <hi>VVilfull deprauing,</hi> 16. <hi>Conuicted wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> 56.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Archbishop hathe cause to thanck yow for your gentilnes,</hi> 374. <hi>A <hi>daunsing deuise,</hi>
      </hi> 337. <hi>Suche a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie man in scripture, and so profound in all knowledge, pag.</hi> 9. <hi>I <hi>suppose yow vse them as meanes to cast vp your melancholy which yow call zeale,</hi>
      </hi> 39. <hi>But soft man a while yow do but dreame</hi> 209.</p>
   <p>Let him take all these wherof diuers are often repeated / and if he be ashamed off them / hide them: yet for any word off repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue vsed in either off my bookes / I will finde both moe / and more bitter in his later boke / wheroff I haue not once made mention. Where also it owght not to be forgotten how his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond boke is as heauie with this kind off stuffe as his first: yf not haeuier. They say / it is better <hi>to be beaten</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Arist. in his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick ad Theode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cten.</note>
      <hi>second: because the hardnes off angre, is commonly broken vpon the first.</hi> But (yt
<pb facs="9"/> seemeth) the Answerer dronck in more off his angre / then he po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wred forth. Lastly / let it be considered whether his answers are (for the most part) so ridiculous / that if he which is said to haue <note n="a" place="margin">Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus.</note> wept so muche had replied vpon him: he could easelier haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulden hoat coles in his mouth / then haue absteined from those salt sayinges / which he so sore complaineth off. Here I omit / that the scripture doth diuers <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 5 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. 12. 13.</note> times vse this kinde off reprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Also that the most <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>August:</hi> 15. <hi>l. cōtra Faust. Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nich. c.</hi> 4.</note> modest spirit off all the auncient writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers not permitteth onely / but as yt were exhortethe / to a <hi>merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full kinde off deriding.</hi> So that / the mind being pure: the thing yt self vsed moderately to discredit sin / can not be condemned.</p>
   <p>His accusations / vvhich touche the cause follow: vvhere ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bridging the magistrates autoritie / often repeted but neuer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / shall be seen in the proper places. There / shall appeare that I haue browght it into no smaller roum: then the vvord off God hath shut it / and the best learned and godliest writers both nwe and ould haue plainly taught of yt. In which point / let yt be also here obserued: how there be no wordes so fenced against all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils / vvhich the D. vvill not assay to depraue. For vvhere I cited examples to proue / that men are said to doo thinges wherof they <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 156,</note> are the cheif and principall and not the onely doers / and amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest them alledged that off Moses which appointed officers by <note place="margin">
         <hi>Exo.</hi> 18. 25 <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. 15 <hi>pag.</hi> 157.</note> the peoples consent: he feareth not to say / that I therby <hi>pushe at the ciuil magistrat, ād infinuat that the prince may not appoint vnder officers without the peoples election.</hi> But let him answer / what is the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherwith (I will not say) <hi>I <hi>pushe:</hi>
      </hi> but so much as towche yt with my litle fingar? ys it because I say / those gouernours were chosen with consent of the people? the scripture (as is after sh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewed) doth manifestly proue yt. Or did I euer teache it in pulpit / <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 198. <hi>off this boke. Decad</hi> 5. <hi>serm.</hi> 4.</note> mention it in disputation / defend it in talk / wherby these wordes might with more likelihood / be haled vnto suche a sense? what would this man haue done (trow yow) if I had (as Maister Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger doth) vpō that place of Moses concluded / that the peoples consent / owght to be in the election off their Pastor. Not vnlike to this / is that wherby (vpon a rule brought and applied as well by other learned men / as by me to the Ecclesiasticall election) he
<pb facs="10"/> would insinuate: that I meant yt should be translated <hi>to the ciuill estate.</hi> Where appeareth: that there is no sparke off equitie in him. For if the rule were giuen generally / then my applying of it onely / to Ecclesiasticall elections / doth rather call yt from being vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standed off the ciuil: if it be giuen of it alone / then it is clere that I vsed it accordingly. Beside that I haue shewed / that it is far otherwise in the ciuill then in the Ecclesiasticall gouernement: and that thinges vnlawful in one / are notwithstanding lawful in the other. But thus must I <hi>restore that I neuer toke:</hi> and be <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 69. 4. <hi>Psal.</hi> 35. 11 <hi>pa.</hi> 10. 14. 118. 171. 195.</note>
      <hi>accused off thinges vvhich I not onely neuer did, but not so mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as knovv off.</hi> Here also falseth / an other accusation of <hi>flatterie off the people, with iniurie to the magistrate.</hi> Where him selfe gyueth, me at least this testimonie / that I haue bene euil scholed in that craft: which haue chosen masters / that can do so litle for me. Yf the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te off our commen wealth had bene suche / as wherin the people had born the sway: his accusation vntrw / should yet haue had some colour off trwth.</p>
   <p>An other accusation / is off wrong <hi>in not setting downe his boke:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 2. 16. 27. 72. 89. 280. 593. 656.</note> as one <hi>looth it should be compared, and for fear my corrupt dealing should appear.</hi> But this accusation / lieth against the most part of learned men: which hauing confuted aduersaries off the trwth / haue not onely not set downe there bokes / but not giuen their readers so particular addres for conference / as I did. Here therfore / ether let him absolue me: or condemn me / with them. That I did yt not in suche respect as he saith / I haue protested: the truth wheroff shall now appear. And withall / that notwithstanding his setting downe: let the reader iudge whither he vseth (as he saith off me) <hi>friuolous replies, childish collections, fraudulent deprauing</hi> off my boke. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side that he hath passed by diuers reasons off mine vntowched: <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag</hi> 16.</note> yea and as shal (God willing hereafter appeare) guilfully left out of his own boke / in one or two places. And because I am entred into his dealing / hauing bene tied now full two yeares / to turn this stone of his writinges: it wil not be amis to admonish of so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of his practises / wherby the reader may the better know how to turn himself in them / ether present or to come / if he kepe on the some course. In the reste therfore off his boke / beside repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="10"/>
/ furmises / &amp;c: one part is spent / in naked affirmacions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owt proof / vented often by questions etherfond or from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose / and in dry testimonies off men: both which are (as other his furniture) repeated / and that sometimes again and again. That where the Cuckow / trobleth but once a year: he with his vntunable repetitions off one thing to the same purpose / trobleth all the year long. Yet hath he / euery hand while: <hi>to be short.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In his testimonies / beside that yt shall appeare / that so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as make to the cause they are almost euery one ether falsified / or drawen from the meaning of the autors: yt is first to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / that to answer the places off scripture alledged / yt is verie like that he first turneth to Maister Caluin / if he be against him he goeth to aske fauour at other: if no body answer nothing / yet he bringeth sondry times euen that nothing / that is to say which maketh not for him / sometime also against him. Secondly / where in his former boke / he propoundeth certein thinges / as his own: not able to maintein them in this / he callethe for the autors as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance / of whom he hath not so muche borowed them / as taken them against their willes. yet he counteth yt <hi>vaine glorie, to take</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>owt off an autor, and to conceale his name</hi> Notwithstanding / if he had knowen from whom his collections came / which he vseth / and had bene thankfull to his autors / in that sort he saith we owght: we should often haue had in the margent / for <hi>Augustin, Ambrose, Chrysostome, &amp;c.</hi> Pigghius / Hosius / Harding / &amp;c. To let pas diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se reasons I gaue him / which he neuer thāked me for: but hideth them as well as he can / by taking them vp before hand / or he came to the place where I giue them. Thirdly where his autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is nameles / and goethe vnder this generall title / <hi>other learned men thinck otherwise, a learned man saith so:</hi> haue yt for suspected / off popery. For that / in some off those places: he can haue no other autors but Papistes / as I am persuaded. Last off all / that he doth often bately recite them / vvithowt applying them to his matter: or gathering his argument off them. The cause vvheroff is / for that they are not hable / to beare any argument / the vanity whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rof / vvould not forthewith appeare / if it vvere gathered. Which is manifest / for as muche as vvhere any colour off argument do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="11"/> but peep / there he presseth them diligently: vvhich practise he vseth in his other proofes / albeit he precisely reprehendeth it in the autors off the Admonition.</p>
   <p>Touching the other part of that which remaineth in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / standing ether of his reasons against our cause / or answeres off the reasons against his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>in bothe yow may obserue / that the prouing off that in question / by that which is likewise dowbted of / occupieth a great roume. In his answers to mine / he will oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en acknowledge no argument: Because yt is not set down in the precise ether order off propositions / or other exact form of Sillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gism. Which (I thinck) is a streighter law / then any writer he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath bene bound vnto: yet I will not refuse it / if he vvil gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue me an example: the matter hauing now bene so largely debated / to the vnderstanding of the simpler sort. Let him therfore / if he dare trust his cause: deal that way / an other vvhile. As for diuers particular faultes / in his lodgick / and grammer throwgh euill translation / considering that they bring no preiudice to the truth in question / and hurting not the vnlearneder / are quickly espied off the other: I am well content / to hould back. Thus muche / to the Answerers both generall and particular accusations and sur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mises: in suche sort / a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I meane (God willing) neuer vpon any his importunity to returne vnto againe. For as for that page 21. line 3. and suche other as haue manifest confutation in the places owt off vvhich they are raised / they are most vnworthy the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
   <p>Hauing spoken thus muche for their causes especially / wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich misinformed by the D. haue no good opinion of the discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne now propounded: yt remaineth to say something for theirs / vvhiche acknowledging yt for the trwth off God / doe not stretch forth their handes to bring yt in / or at the least / not with that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour which owght to be. Wherin yt seemeth they doe not so ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consider that before alledged / of the vse of the discipline / the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in the churche / that the wal abowt the citie / or hedg about the orcheiard. Yf we thinck / that men vvhiche vvoulde be safe from their enemies / need not greatly to trauail after a wal / or they wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich vvould haue their tender plantes bring plentifull fruict and be vntowched off hurfull beastes / not muche to labour after a
<pb facs="11"/> hedg or diche for safegarde of them / then we may also thinck / that the church / and the doctrine of the Apostels wherupon the church is builded / may long continw and florish vvithowt the discipline lefte by them. But if / the one be not to be looked for: the hoping for the other / will but deceiue vs. Whereof if there were no proof / but our own experience: the case is clearer / then can be wel deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For vvhereof cometh it that so many thowsandes (I will not say of men and women) but of townes and villages remain in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ignorance of all dutie towards God / and their neighbour: that the estate off their ox (vvhiche vvith his last breath shal end his labour / and hear no more the voice of the whip) is a thousand times better then theirs / vvhom euerlasting tomentes of body and sowl vvait for / and must assuredly ensue if they so remaine. Cometh it not hereof / that in steed of a learned ministery / vvhiche shoulde shewe them the right way / be thrust vppon them at the pleasure / or permission off the bishop / and appetite off the patrone / blinde guides vvhich scarce knowe a foot of it them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: yea which sometimes (as cometh to pas in sondry popishe priestes that remaine) endeuour to turn them out off the way / if happily any were entred? Wheroff cometh it that off those which haue able ministers to feed them: diuers townes can not yet get owt of this condēnation, ys it not thereof / that some pastors like couetous nourses charging them selues with moe / then they are able to nource / suffer them all to starue? that other some more vnnaturall then the dragons them selues (which laie owt their brestes / vnto their yong) by dispensation / turn awaie their faces quite from them? whose mouthes / are almost neuer open to tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / but vvhen their handes are likewise to receiue? And if some in a good intent to help many / lend one hande to one congregation / and his other vnto another: yet when ether of them require both handes to be pulled owt off the mire wherin they stick so fast / his fault being a great deal les then the others / the peoples condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation remaineth the same. Wheroff also ys y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> / that in diuers off those Townes where the gospell hath daily shined: the darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ignorance / hath not bene put to flight. Cometh yt not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roff / that many speaking smally to purpose off the text they han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle / or blowing vp their sermons ether with poetes fables / say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges
<pb facs="12"/> off Philosophers and that oft in straunge language / ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ze them rather with a wōndermēt of their learning / then edifie thē in faith and trw repentance. And not that onely / but therby also bring them owt of al tast with all simple and plain kind off teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: so that they which doe not so / are called by reproche English Doctors. Which by oftē meetings of the ministers / in exercice off Prophecie or interpretacion of some scripture / through mutual censures and admonitions: would easely be remedied.</p>
   <p>Wheroff is it / that euen vvhere the gospel is soundly and abūdandly taught: knowledg hath not accordingly folowed. Ys it not therof / that the principles / and groundes of religiō are not by Catechism laid forth: that those of whose ether capacity or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligēce yt is doubted / are not (that a supply may be made) particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly examined? Wheroff cometh yt that Arians / Valentinians and Anabaptistes / in diuers sortes with suche other detestable heretikes: are so rife / in many places of the land. Ys it not therof / that there is no eldership / which might assist the pastor / to espie them out: no pastorable by substancial reasons to conuince them: no autoritie there to decide of them / or after decision by ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall censures to punish them. Wheroff cometh yt / that horrible blaspheming the holy and most reuerend name of God / quarre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and fighting / dronckennes / filthy speaking / fornicatiō / adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery / slaundering and suche like / run ouer almost in euery place / off which some are so open that there is no night or corners sowght to hid them / but are doen in the high streates / and at noon daies: yea (which is fearful) that often there is more daunger to them that reproue these faultes / then to those which cōmit them. Ys it not hereof that there is no eldership to watche ouer these offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / to admonish the offenders / and by ecclesiasticall censures to correct them. Wheroff cometh it / that in so many excellent lawes / prouided against roges and beggers: there are yet (to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest breach of the law of God / and hasard of the commen wealth) such nombers. Ys it not heroff / that the office off Deacons / wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich god had ordeined for that purpose (the bare name remaining) is abolished: and that the Lord will giue no blessing to those good lawes / because his order is neglected. Finally hereof it cometh / that hauing a gracious Prince mainteining / and her honorable
<pb facs="12"/> Counsall fauoring the preaching of the gospell / in so long and qu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iet peace / apt for the furtherance off yt: there is notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding so smal fruict that (sauing a few which the lord hath gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) for the generall estate of the Realme / the Gospell may seem hetherto rather to haue shined for further condemnation of it / then for light or heat of saluation / ioined therwith, what price therfore we set of the glory off God / what accompt we make off the saluacion of our countrey: that estimacion we must kepe / off the discipline off God / left vnto vs by his holy Apostels.</p>
   <p>This if it were deeply weighed: it would cause vs to break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwgh the lets which (I see) stay some / and make other some to faint in the furtherance of this cause. For some whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that this cause might gaine / throwgh a mind abhorring from contention / especially inward / an with them of the same re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: stande further of from yt / then otherwise they would. Wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erin I willingly acknowledge Rebeccas affection: a figure off the churche off God. For notwithstanding she praied / vnto the lord for children: yet feeling them striue within her Womb / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Genes.</hi> 25. 22.</note> wished she had neuer conceiued. But alas / the state off men is not so happy: to obteine any excellent thing / without strift. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and falshood haue often times easy entrance / whilest the husbandmen sleep: but because the ennemy alwaies waketh / the trweth must fight / or euer she / can get any thing. wherin / to pas by an infinite number of examples: that which is proper to this place (off the daungerous assaultes which this cause suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at Geneua) ys worthy off your consideration. For albeit the contention there was not in Iudgement onely / and in wordes / but with great disorders and tumultes / to the present daunger off the citie: yet M. Caluin / and other faithfull seruantes of God / <note place="margin">In M. Cal. Epistles.</note> offred them selues not onely to los off their ministery / and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shment / but euen to death / rather then they would goe one foot back / from that truth off the discipline / which they had learned owt off the word off God / which had bene / rashly doen / if the matter had bene off so smal importance: as that (for redeming off peace) they might haue let the cause of the disciplin fal / or laid it aside / vntill a fitter time. There are (God be praised) no tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes nor vprores with vs / and I hope there shal be none: but as
<pb facs="13"/> yt is not lawful for vs to moue any / so to withdraw the hand from defense off the cause / for feare of them to be moued by oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / is against dutie.</p>
   <p>There are others / which as the espies off the land of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <note place="margin">
         <hi>Nomb.</hi> 13 28. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> / confessing it good and profitable for the churche: yet in respect of the manifold lets / affirme it a thing impossible: and therby not onely discorage them selues / but weaken the handes off other. And euen here also / I see Rebecca again. For yt appeareth by the lordes answer vnto her / <hi>tvvo peoples should be deuided ovvt of her bovvls:</hi> that she was in some dispair off hauing strenght / to <note place="margin">
         <hi>Genes.</hi> 25. 23.</note> be deliuered of her desired seed / considering the daungerous w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restlings and struglinges / in her womb. And in deed / if we consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our selues / if we look vpon our own armes: I graunt the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les against it / are higher then will be scaled / the gates and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / are stronger then wil be broken throwgh / the children come to the birth / there wil be no strenght to bring forth. For herein casting our accōptes / we must wait for not onely the misliking of our brethern / which be misled / the hatred of the obstinat Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes which see their kingdō vnreparable / if this get place: but the deadly enimities off Hypocrites / and Atheistes / which wil not suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer their vntamed lustes to come vnder any yoke off correction / nor their lose affections off riotous pleasures / proud ambition / and vnsatiable couetousnes to be bound / vvith any bandes off wholesome discipline.</p>
   <p>But of the other side / if we look vnto the lord / and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty arme which not onely with a blast of his mouth striketh the walles / and breaketh the gates in peeces / but also maketh the high walles to fall / and the yron gates to open of their owne accord / which maketh not onely the weak / but euen the barē wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to bring forth: No difficulty or impossibilitie in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment off men owght to turne vs from any lawfull endeuour / to promote the cause. The example off the wall in Ierusalem finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed / notwithstanding al the enimies: serueth here / for our confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. For if the lord / stretched forth his hand for furtherance of that material wall: he will not in the aduauncing off this spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual / hould it in his bosome. Yf he forsoke not his seruantes / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heathen Princes: he will not be wanting to them vnder Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.
<pb facs="13"/> Hetherto belongeth / the example in Geneua: before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. The whole estate off the Citie almost / from the highest vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lowest (amongest whom were also the greatest part off the ministers) was bent against yt: two or three simple men scarce able to traine their legges after them / hauing no other armour then the trwth and a good conscience / stand for it. Yf flesh and bloud should here sit in iudgement / the field were lost / or euer yt were begun: the freendes off the discipline / should (for that they toke the defense in hand) be accounted fooles / for that they would not cōpound the matter / mad men. But what was the issue? Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the Lord so magnified his word / in the hand of his seruātes / that after trial off their patience by diuers troubles / the Capitai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes against yt / came to shameful end / a number yealded / the rest that continued their enemitie / durst not shew yt / the trwth yt self was established / and so (to the singuler commendation off that citie) remaineth. And shall we / in so great a nomber whose heartes the Lord hath inclined to fauour this cause despaire? e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially seing yt ys easier to be established with vs / then with them: and may here be setled / withowt so muche as a dog mouing his tong / which was not there / withowt daungerous vprores. For where no wholsom law can pas there / onles the most part consent: onely / the hundreth part with vs / weigheth down all the rest.</p>
   <p>Yt remaineth / that as the Iwes in the wal off Ierusalem / did euery one according to the abilitie the Lord had blessed them <note place="margin">
         <hi>Nehem.</hi> 3</note> with builde his part: so those / whose hartes the lord hath ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened with the knowledg of this truth / should as their callings / and meanes which the lord hath giuen them will serue / lay their handes to the work. That those whom the lord hath giuen fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or acces vnto her maiestie / would set before their eies the exāple of that worthy courtier Nehemias: which (forgetting his priuat profit and preferment) for full recompence of all his faith <note place="margin">
         <hi>Neh.</hi> 2. 5.</note> full seruice vnto his Prince / was glad to obtein at his hand the building vp of the walles off the citie of God: and therfore not to reserue the grace and credit they haue with her highnes / for their owne matters / but to bestow yt vpon the Lordes. That the Prince her selfe / woulde consider how (to let pas the daunger
<pb facs="14"/> vnto her sowle) vnworthy yt ys off her honour / if throwgh vntrw reportes ether against the cause / or fauourers therof / she turne away her eare from hearing / and taking knowledge of it: seing a heathen king / did not admit suche rumors against that which concerned the glory off God: althowgh they were offred thick and three fould / and that by his one coutrey men / against the Iwes / whiche were but straungers. Finally / that we all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually / pray to the lord: that he would vouchsafe to open their eies whiche are yet ignorant in this behalf / confirme those which haue knowledge / and confound thē (if any be) which ether for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour / or lucres sake / willingly bend thē selues / against the trueth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>