<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE Lord Marquesse of Buckingham.</title>
           <author>Cade, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107370_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17514</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4328</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107370</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE Lord Marquesse of Buckingham.</title>
                 <author>Cade, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Saint Paules agonie : A sermon preached at Leicester, at the ordinary monthly lecture: specially touching the motions of sinne, remaining in the regenerate. By A. Cade, Bacheler in Diuinity, and of Bilsdon in Leycester-shire</title>
                 <author>Cade, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE <hi>Lord Marquesse of Buckingham.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our goodnesse continually prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised in your greatnesse, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of many, bindes all highly to honour you, and account you as a Conduit ordayned of God to conueigh many benefites from his <hi>Royall Maiesty</hi> vpon inferiours. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which, your Honourable kindnesse to me, in prouiding for me, without my sute or knowledge, a right famous and noble place, to rayse my fortunes, and exercise my Ministery in, (the like whereof many haue sought with great sute, cost, and labor, and haue not found) deserueth all thankefulnesse that can bee imagined, much more then can bee performed. But feeling my selfe too weake for the greatnesse of that place (not for my doctrine, the soundnesse &amp; whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somnesse whereof I am ready to testifie and iustifie, if need require, with my bloud) but by the weaknesse
<pb facs="3"/> of my voyce, not able to reach the halfe of that spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Church and numerous people. I humbly pray your Honour to take without offence my Refusall, and my harty desire that that great and worthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may be furnished with a man of a stronger voyce and better sides, who may doe there much more good then my selfe: who in my declining yeares must rather affect a more retired life, and a charge more possible to be performed with better sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to my selfe and to Gods people. I shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore honour your goodnesse and your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse for this fauour, which I publikely protest by the Dedication of this Sermon, in Stile simple, but in matter sound and substantiall: which hauing lately preached, I thought good to publish, at the request of many my good friends of religious hearts: the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to oppose the spreading of those opinionate &amp; fansifull younglings, who drawing bad iuyce from <hi>Arminius</hi> and <hi>Vorstius,</hi> beginne to bud and blossome in our Academie, whence nothing but good and wholesome food should be brought into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. To shew how firmely our doctrine in these points is founded vpon the Scriptures, and consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Fathers of the Primitiue, and all succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, and what exceeding good vse and profite it yeeldeth, and how farre these men swerue from it, and from al true experience of Gods Saints in the state of Grace and Regeneration: I haue penned &amp; published this Sermon, and wish all good men to put to their hands to represse all such hurtfull grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innouations, disquieting, distracting, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing
<pb facs="3"/> the peace and beauty of our Church, to the offence and hazarding of many Soules. And so I cease to trouble your Honour, but shall neuer cease praying for you, and honouring you as fitteth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours most humble and thankefull Chaplen,</hi> Anthony Cade.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>