<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS FRIENDS, KINSFOLKES, and Alies, of Bath Bristoll, welles, &amp;c. Iohn Iones, Gentleman, Graduate in Phisike, sendeth gree∣ting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107904_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72470</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14724a.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS FRIENDS, KINSFOLKES, and Alies, of Bath Bristoll, welles, &amp;c. Iohn Iones, Gentleman, Graduate in Phisike, sendeth gree∣ting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bathes of Bathes ayde : wonderfull and most excellent, agaynst very many sicknesses, approued by authoritie, confirmed by reason, and dayly tryed by experience: vvith the antiquitie, commoditie, propertie, knovvledge, vse, aphorismes, diet, medicine, and other thinges therto be considered and obserued. Compendiously compiled by Iohn Iones phisition. Anno salutis. 1572. At Asple Hall besydes Notting [h] am</title>
                 <author>Jones, John, physician</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 35, that is 34, 4 leaves, 2 folded tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="54"/>
   <head>TO HIS FRIENDS, KINSFOLKES, and Alies, of Bath Bristoll, welles, &amp;c. Iohn Iones, Gentleman, Graduate in Phisike, sendeth gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a lostie Style and longe discourse vnto them that desire playnnes, and couet breuitie, is a thing irkesome: so a plain sence and an hartie affection vttered to friends (as mee semeth) is most alowable. And for that the manifold cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesies and great commodities receyued, as wel in youth, as of late yeares at the handes of diuers friends, kinsfolkes, alies, &amp;c. In the Counties of Gloucester, Dorset, Deuonia, Worcester, &amp; Sumerset, were one principall cause, which emboldened mee to take in hande this myne enterprise. I could not but signifie the same vnto you (myne assured good friends) especially hauing (without offence be it spoken) in the goods of Fortune few equalles, in the douries of Nature fewer, in furniture of mynde none, and chiefly in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of the holy Scripture, as good sheepe, followers a good sheepheard, the right reuerend Father in God, Doctor Barkley, my very good Lord and singular Moecenas of all the learned.</p>
   <p>I may not here forget my singular good Lady, the Lady Syden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, nor hir worthie Sonne Mayster Henry Sydenham, in wyse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome comparable to Cato, in valiantnes nothing inferiour to Hec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, whose singular good will forced mee for their sakes, to deuyse somewhat that might benefyte vniuersally: which (whatsoeuer it bee) I beseeche you all to accepte gratefully as a small presente of myne vnfayned hart towardes you. Fare yee well.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>¶From London. <date>Anno. <hi>1572.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>