<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE INGENVOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107115_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17474</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4293.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107115</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE INGENVOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diatelesma: the fifth part or number : Comprehending the principall actions of Germany, France, Spaine, and the Neatherlands. Continued from November, 1637</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 114, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE INGENVOVS READER.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Claudere quae Coenas Lactuea solebat Auorum,</l>
         <l>Dic mihi cur nostras inchoat illa dapes?</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be questioned, why the Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Neatherlands, vvhich used to stand in the Reare, should leade the Van, in this discovery; It is here, as in a ranged Battell, Faces about, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not either Files or Ranks, but the Posture onely: and it first presented it selfe to my Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, was first brought downe Methodically, and first came to the Presse. If it be a mistake reprehensible, it was <hi>Error Protographi,</hi> and the Printer is not to be blamed. But the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, in the disposition of this Relation, by mistaking the Title over-head, in the 3. Chap. and interrupting the Title of the Low-Dutch Story, by interweaving a New one, was <hi>Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Typographi,</hi> herein excusable, that it was
<pb facs="3"/>brought unto him by loose sheets, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, vvas vvilling to have ended it with the Tournament, more pleasant than the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Warre: or else, as the best of Latine Poets doth sometimes make a Breach in his Verse, upon the Breach of a Speare; would shew his Fancie, in expressing the tumultuary Actions of Warre, by the <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of his Papers. However it hapned, he craveth your conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence at this Errour, and doubteth not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it from such as you, who can more easily reduce the last sheet of that History to its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, than he can recompose it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>