<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE CHIEFE RESOLV∣TIONS OF THIS Suruey.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107072_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16151</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3070</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107072</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE CHIEFE RESOLV∣TIONS OF THIS Suruey.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The suruey of Christs sufferings for mans redemption : and of his descent to Hades or Hel for our deliuerance: by Thomas Bilson Bishop of Winchester. The contents whereof may be seene in certaine resolutions before the booke, in the titles ouer the pages, and in a table made to that end. Perused and allowed by publike authoritie</title>
                 <author>Bilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 678, 14 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE CHIEFE RESOLV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS OF THIS Suruey.</head>
   <p>THe cleerenes and fulnes of the Scriptures in the worke of our Redemption is exactly to be reuerenced; so as no man ought to teach or beleeue any thing touching our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Christ, which is not expresly witnessed in the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures: much lesse may we distrust the manifest words of the holy Ghost to be impertinent or vnsufficient in declaring the true price and meane of our redemption.</p>
   <p>The maine ground of the Gospell, which the Apostles preached, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full receiued, wherein they continued, and whereby they were saued, was this; That <hi>Christ died for our sinnes according to the Scriptures, and was buried, and rose the third day; according to the Scriptures.</hi> Since then we are reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne, we must acknowledge none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death of Christ then that which he suffered in the bodie of his flesh, after which he was buried, and from which he rose the third day, which death the Scriptures most apparently describe to be the death of Christs bodie.</p>
   <p>If we were <hi>redeemed by the bloud of Christ, and God proposed him</hi> (to be) <hi>a Reconciliation through faith in his bloud, which was shed for the remission of sinnes;</hi> we may not presume to appoint a new price of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or new meane of our reconciliation; since by the bloud of <hi>his crosse Christ hath pacified both the things in earth, and things in heauen; and the bloud of Iesus Christ cleanseth vs from all sinne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Scriptures doe no where teach, nor mention the death of Christs Joule, or the death of the damned, which is the second death, to be needfull for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. We must not therefore intrude our selues into Gods seat to ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne a new course for mans redemption.</p>
   <p>If <hi>the Spirit doe quicken, and the iust liue by faith, and he that abideth in loue, abideth in God,</hi> who is life; it was vtterlie impossible, but the soule of Christ in that abundance of Spirit, euidence of Faith, assurance of Hope, and perfection of Loue, which he alwayes retained, should alwayes liue to God.</p>
   <p>Life and death being opposed as priuatiues, and so not to be found in one and the same subiect at one and the same time; the soule of Christ alwayes liuing, could neuer be dead. Neither could a dead soule be pleasing to God, (who is whole life, and therefore hateth death as contrarie to his nature;) when yet he was alwayes well pleased with Christ.</p>
   <p>Where some imagine extreame paine in Christs soule may be called the death of his soule; that position is repugnant to the Scriptures: for the greater the paine which the soule feeleth, and endureth with innocencie, confidence, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and patience, (such as were all Christes sufferings) the more the soule liueth and cleaueth to God, for whose glorie it suffereth so much smart; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in Martyrs, whose soules do most liue in their greatest torments.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>The late deuice of hell-paines in Christes passion is not only false, but also su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous: for the true paines of hell neither are, nor can be suffered in this life, where, by Gods ordinance extreame paine driueth the soule from the bodie: much lesse can man or Angell endure them with obedience and patience, as Christ did all his paines. And what need was there of hell-paines in the crosse of Christ, since God can by euery meanes, or without meanes raise more paines in bodie or soule, than any creature can endure.</p>
   <p>Christs soule could not be strooken with any horrour of Gods displeasure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, since in his greatest anguish he professed God to be his God, and his Father, and by prayer preuailed for his persecutors (as appeared after by their conuersion) and gaue eternall life to the soule of the Thiefe hanging by him, and beleeuing on him. Now to giue life is more than to haue life; and restore others to fauour he can not, that himselfe is in displeasure.</p>
   <p>Hell-fire, which the damned and diuels do and shall suffer, is a true and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fire prepared by the mightie hand of God to punish aswell spirits as bodies; and this errour, That the fire of hell was only an internall or spirituall fire in the soules and consciences of men, was long since condemned in Origen by the Church of Christ.</p>
   <p>Reiection therefore, desperation, confusion, horrour of damnation, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and eternall fire, which are the torments of the damned, and true paines of hell, can not without blasphemie be ascribed to Christ. Christ therefore suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red neither the death of the soule, nor the paines nor horrors os the damned, or of hell.</p>
   <p>Euery sinne is common to the whole man, who is <hi>defiled</hi> euen with <hi>thoughts</hi> that be euill; not only because the bodie is the <hi>Seat,</hi> wherein, and the <hi>instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> whereby the soule worketh; but also for that the first <hi>infection</hi> of sinne commeth to the soule by the bodie, and the first <hi>information</hi> and <hi>prouocation</hi> to sinne riseth from the senses and affections, which are mooued with corporall spirits; and all the parts and powers of the bodie attend the will with most rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die subiection to haue each sinne (which the soule conceiueth) <hi>impressed on</hi> them, and <hi>executed</hi> by them. And therefore the suffering for sinne in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Mediatour, must be common both to bodie and soule in such sort, that as in transgressing, our soules are the principall Agents, so in the suffering for sinne, his soule was the principall Patient.</p>
   <p>Christ would vse no power to assuage the force and violence of his paines, (though he wanted none, as appeareth by his ouerthrowing them with a word, that came to apprehend him;) but submitted himselfe to his Fathers will with greater obedience and patience, than any man liuing could. We may therefore safely beleeue, That the iustice of God <hi>condemning sinne in</hi> (Christes) <hi>flesh,</hi> proportioned the paines of his bodie, <hi>in which hee bare our sinnes,</hi> to the strength of his patience; and so both his paines and his patience farre exceeded all mens. The rather for that Christes sense did not faile him by degrees, as ours doth, when the paines of death are extreamest, which driue our soules from our bodies; but hee did in most perfect sense feele the sting and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of paine to the last breath; by reason he was of his owne accord, at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant appointed by his Father, to breathe out his owne soule, and so did, to the great admiration of the Centurion that obserued it; and consequently hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb facs="8"/>
firmnesse of voice, and exactnesse of sense, all the while his paines were at sharpest.</p>
   <p>The soule is punished in this life by her <hi>vnderstanding, will, affections,</hi> and <hi>senses,</hi> according as their obiects, directed and strengthened by God, make vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and vehement impressions; the torment of hell-fire being the iudgement of another world. Neither is God the tormenter of soules in hell with his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate hand, but by his wisdome and power hath ordained euerlasting fire, as an externall Agent aboue nature, to take vengeance of damned men and diuels according to their deserts.</p>
   <p>No Scripture doth teach, That God with his immediate hand tormented the soule of his Sonne on the Crosse, or in the Garden; notwithstanding Christes soule was full of feare and sorow in the Garden, and of griefe and paine on the Crosse: all which outward and inward passions ne did, ne could peruert Christs will, nor oppresse his power; but they must all be voluntarie, that they might all be meritorious; and the more Christs power was to admit them, when he would, as he would, and because he would; the more his obedience was to the will and hand of God, who forced nothing on Christ against his will, but by that which was offered and suffered, tried the obedience of his Sonne, and accepted all from him as a most willing Sacrifice.</p>
   <p>The wrath of God punishing our sinnes in the person of Christ, was neither such as the Damned in hell, nor as the Reprobate in earth doe suffer; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther common to the members of Christ, who must drinke of this Cuppe, haue fellowship with his afflictions, and be conformed to his death, though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer feele the true paines of hell, nor haue their soules tormented by Gods im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand. Neither was it any other wrath, than such as might stand with Gods loue towards his Sonne, (who did not hate him for our sakes, but loued vs for his) and was Fatherly tempered to the strength of Christes manhood, and graciously ouerruled and quenched by the fauour that God bare to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of his Sonne. And therefore the termes of <hi>meere and proper wrath</hi> (if they meane proper to the damned) are false and impious in Christes sufferings, which neither in <hi>maner, measure,</hi> nor <hi>purpose,</hi> did agree with the torments of the damned.</p>
   <p>The true and full satisfaction for our sinnes, must not be deriued from the singularitie and infinitie of Christes paines, longer and greater than which the damned and diuels doe euery one suffer; but from the dignitie of the person, who being the only and eternall Sonne of God that made vs, humbled himselfe in our stead, and in our nature to restore vs, and offered recompense for our sinnes, which was his submission and obedience vnto the death of the Crosse, more pleasing to God than our condemnation to hell could haue beene: for in this ballance betweene the wrath of God against our sinnes, and the loue of God towards his Sonne, neither was his iustice neglected, nor his loue ouer sway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but a sweet and wise temper of both was prouided for the manhood of his Sonne, first to suffer with patience, and then to raigne with glorie; that all the sonnes of God might be the more willing and readie by his example to obey the will, and abide the hand of God, before they did enter into his Kingdome.</p>
   <p>The Scriptures witnessing, that the Sacrifices of God are a troubled spirit, this might not want in Christes Sacrifice for sinne; but he approching the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
<pb facs="9"/>
of God with and for our offences, lawfully might, and exceedingly did feare the greatnesse and iustnesse of Gods anger against our iniquities; and as deeply sorrowed, that Gods holinesse was so carelesly despised, and highly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased with our manifolde iniquities. Which inward sacrifices of feare and sorrow for vs, and our sinnes, in the person of the Mediatour, were no lesse ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God than the simple suffering of paine.</p>
   <p>Since Gods power is despised, where it is not duely feared, and sinne is iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, where the displeasing of God is not thorowly sorrowed; in presenting vs and our cause to God, Christ was to yeeld for vs, and in our behalfe that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite submission and feare to the power of God prouoked, and contrition and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to the holinesse of God offended, which we could neuer haue done. And without these to offer to beare the burden of our sinnes, was to make light ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our sinne against God, and of Gods wrath against our sinne, which was farre from the Sonne of God.</p>
   <p>There might therefore in Christes sacrifice for sinne not without iust cause appeare exceeding feare and sorrow, yet both religious, and measured by the rules of obedience and humilitie, though passing grieuous to the soule of Christ. Neither were these submissions and afflictions of Christs soule answerable to his perfection, and our transgression, if they did not reach to the highest degree of feare and sorrow, that mans nature in Christ was capable of, without distrust of Gods fauour, or dislike of his iustice.</p>
   <p>Christ did not pray in the Garden contrarie to his Fathers knowen will, but made an expresse and speciall reseruation thereof euen in the first part of his prayer. Neither was he amazed and confounded in all the powers of his soule and senses of his bodie, as these Presumers teach, but he prayed with faith, and suffered with obedience; both which require perfect <hi>vnderstanding, will,</hi> and <hi>memorie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Manie things might concurre to increase Christes sorrow in the Garden, as the reiection of the Iewes for spilling his bloud, the dispersion of his Church, all flying and forsaking him; the continuall rage of Satan against his weake and fearefull members; Christ now in his temptations and afflictions beholding theirs with great compassion and griefe of heart: which is it that Hilarie saith; <hi>Et tristitia de nobis est, &amp; oratio pro nobis est. Christ sorrowed for vs, and<note place="margin">De Trinitate li. 10.</note> prayed for vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>An Agonie is properly a vehement contention of minde to preuaile in that we vndertake, rightly weighing and striuing to remoue the difficulties and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments obiected to hinder the euent.</p>
   <p>Christes bloudie sweat, if it were naturall, must proceed rather from zeale and intention of minde, than from feare and sorow; which coole the bloud, and quench the spirits; whereas the spirits must be mightilie kindled, and the bloud much heated and thinned, before it can issue forth by sweat. And since by the words of Saint Luke, Christ fell into an Agonie after an Angell appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from heauen, and comforted or strengthened him (with a message from God) it seemeth rather an effect of Christes intentiue prayer which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there mentioneth; than a consequent to any other passion or paine.</p>
   <p>Christes intentiue prayer, after comfort receiued by an Angell from heauen, might proceed from his ardent desire, care, and zeale of our redemption from
<pb facs="9"/>
the wrath of God, and protection from the rage of Satan. And therefore, as the Prophet foreshewed he should not onely beare the sinnes of many, but pray for the Trespassers, Christ might spend all the spirits and powers of bodie and soule in most vehement and feruent prayer, euen vnto a bloudie sweat, to haue all his members pardoned their sinnes, and reconciled to God by the sacrifice of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which he would offer for them; and also to haue Satan cast out from accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing them, and in the end trodden vnder their feet.</p>
   <p>If Christes bloudie sweat were supernaturall; we must aske no cause there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but leaue it to his sacred will, who could aboue nature doe what he would. That it was no proofe of hell paines, appeareth plainly, because Christ after in greater paines on the Crosse did not sweat bloud; and of all those, whom these men imagine suffered hell paines in the Scriptures, no one can be produced, that euer sweat bloud.</p>
   <p>The word (forsaking) vsed by Christ in his Complaint on the Crosse, doth not in all the Scriptures inferre the paines of the damned; but in the wicked it noteth reiection, desperation, and feare of damnation; and in the godly it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth want of protection, or decrease of consolation in their troubles. In Christ it might shew the <hi>time,</hi> the <hi>cause,</hi> the <hi>maner,</hi> or the <hi>griefe</hi> of his being so long forsaken, and left to the rage and reproch of his persecutors, without any sensible signe of Gods loue towards him, care for him, helpe in his troubles, or exse in his paines; but it doth not prooue, that Christ thought himselfe forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Gods fauour, grace, or spirit; which feare or doubt could not be in him without a manifest touch of error, and want of faith.</p>
   <p>Christ neuer feared nor doubted, that he should or could perish vnder the hand of God persuing our sinnes in the bodie of his flesh; but for the ioy set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, endured the Crosse, <hi>and despised the shame;</hi> and as S. Peter sayth of him at the time of his suffering, he alwayes <hi>beheld God at his right hand, that he should not be shaken;</hi> and <hi>therefore his heart reioyced, and his tongue was glad, and his flesh rested in hope, because his soule should not be forsaken in hell, nor his flesh see corruption.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Christ was made a curse for vs, in that he suffered the temporall and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall curses of the Law threatned vnto sinners, as all sorts of afflictions belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this life, and in the end, a painfull and shamefull death, by which he abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished the spirituall and eternall curse of God due to vs for sinne; but he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer inwardly, truely, nor eternally accursed of God, since by tasting of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall curse for a time, he made vs partakers of his spirituall and celestiall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednesse for euer.</p>
   <p>Christ who knew no sinne, was made sinne for vs, that is, either the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, our sinnes, or the sacrifice for our sinnes: for <hi>we were healed by his stripes, and he gaue himselfe for vs a sacrifice of a sweet smell to God.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then an holy and acceptable sacrifice to God for sinne, he was neither defiled nor hatefull to God with our sinnes: but suffered, <hi>the iust for the vniust;</hi> that is, he tooke vpon him the punishment of our sinnes, though he were most inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and by the holinesse of his person, submitting himselfe to the death of the crosse, purged our vncleannesse; by his innocencie, couered our guiltinesse; and by his fauour with God, reconciled vs that were enemies.</p>
   <p>Christ bare the full punishment of our sinnes; that is, not all which we should
<pb facs="10"/>
haue borne; for then he must haue beene euer lastingly reiected, confounded and condemned to hell fire, which are most horrible blasphemies; but he bare so much of the punishments of this life, where he suffered, as in his person by the iust iudgement of God was most sufficient for all our sinnes.</p>
   <p>TOuching Christs descent to hell, the words are plainly cited by Peter out of Dauid, that <hi>Christes soule</hi> (after death) <hi>should not be left in Hades,</hi> which Saint Luke in his Gospell vseth for the place where torments are prepared for the wicked af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life. And in that sense is the word vsed thorowout the New Testament; as likewise the Greeke Fathers tooke it for the place vnder the earth, whither the soules of all men were condemned for sinne, and where the Diuels detaine and torment the wicked. That Christ likewise <hi>descended to the lower parts of the earth, and to the (bottomlesse) deepe</hi> after death, is vouched by Saint Paul; whereupon the whole Church of Christ from the beginning hath confessed his descent to hel to be a point of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian pietie.</p>
   <p>Peters Sermon (in the second of the Acts) intended not simply to proue that Christ was risen from the dead, as Lazarus and others were; but affirmed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of him, That God raised him vp, to set him on Dauids Throne; that is, to make him King of <hi>Glorie.</hi> This he prooueth, In that Christes <hi>flesh could not see corruption, nor his soule be forsaken in hell;</hi> which was verified in none, no not in Dauid (who were all dead, and saw corruption) but only in the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sias. It was therefore impossible, that either death or hell should detaine Christ, but he was to rise Lord of death and hell, and the Sauiour of all his from both; as appeared by his <hi>ascending to heauen, and sitting at the right hand of God.</hi> Neither was this strange to the Iewes, who were taught to expect that to be performed by the Messias, which God promised by his Prophet; <hi>O Death, I will be thy death: O Hell, I will be thy destruction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Sheol</hi> in the Olde Testament signifieth the Graue, and Hell; that is, the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whither the dead bodies of all men went, and whither the soules of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dead in sinne descended after death. And therefore where it is distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed from the death of the bodie, or referred to the soule after death, as it is in Dauids words applied by Peter to Christ, it apparently signifieth Hell.</p>
   <p>The ends of Christes descent are likewise deriued from the Scriptures, as the destroying of the Diuels kingdome, and triumphing ouer powers and principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and making an open shew of them, spoiling them by deliuering all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, dead, liuing, and yet vnborne, from the right, power, and feare of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death; taking into his hands <hi>the Keyes of Death and Hell,</hi> that he might be Lord of all, in <hi>Heauen, Earth, and Hell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Creed is not a Collection of Greeke or Hebrew phrases vnknowen to the people, but a short summe of the Christian faith prouided for the simpler sort of men to learne by heart. And therefore, as nothing is superfluously repeated, so nothing is obscurely couered in it. And though this Article, <hi>He descended to
<pb facs="10"/>
hell,</hi> wanted for a time in some Churches, euen as some part of Scripture did, yet was it retained by all Christian Writers, as a ground of true religion from the Apostles time; and professed in some Churches very anciently in their Creed, and at last generally receiued in all places.</p>
   <p>All the Fathers of Christes Church with one consent teach this as a point of the Christian faith, That Christ after death descended to hell; insomuch that Austen resolutely sayth, <hi>Who but an Infidell will denie, that Christ was in<note place="margin">Epistola. 99.</note> hell?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Where Abrahams bosome was, neither was, nor is agreed amongst the learned: only Austen rightly inferreth out of Christes words, That being a place of comfort, and farre off aboue Hades (where the rich man was tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) with a great Gulfe setled betwixt those two places, it could be <hi>no part, nor<note place="margin">Epistola. 99.</note> member of hell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The rest, which are very many, appeare by the seuerall Titles ouer ech Page, or by the Table prouided to finde the same with more facilitie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>