<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>C., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107143_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4396</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107143</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary vpon the prophecie of Isaiah. By Mr. Iohn Caluin. Whereunto are added foure tables: the first touching places of scripture alleaged: the second, of the principall matters handled: the third, of authors and diuers names mentioned: the fourth, of certaine texts cited out of Isaiah in the new Testament, which by the author in the commentarie are compared and reconciled. Translated out of French into English: by C.C</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Cotton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 674, 40 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F such pretious esteeme (Christian Reader) were the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of this reuerend author in the Church of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua,</hi> that albeit some of them were by himself<note n="*" place="margin">To wit, his ordinarie Lectures vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which being read in the Schooles, were by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries there, taken from his mouth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tim, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vnder the title of his lessons, or readings, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed.</note> spoken, and others of them<note n="*" place="margin">Namely, his Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ch were written by him at spare times in the house.</note> written in Latin; and that in fauor of the learned especially: yet because with his more then ordinarie depth of iudgement he alwaies matched a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular simplicitie and plainenesse, so that hee therein stoopes to the capacitie, euen of the simplest; it was thought fit, that by some of good note in the said Church, they should all be translated into the vulgar French, for the benefit of all such as vnderstood the same.</p>
   <p>Which commendable zeale and godly care of theirs, as it worthily prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked many of this our Church for the common good, (at the happie entrance of our late deare and dread Soueraigne Ladie Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> into this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) to translate diuers of his Commentaries vpon the bookes both of the<note n="*" place="margin">Genesis, Ioshua, and Psalmes.</note> old, and<note n="*" place="margin">All the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelists, Acts, Rom. &amp;c.</note> new Testament into English; so if their good beginnings had been seconded by answerable proceedings, thousands might, I doubt not, haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the like fruit by those that are yet<note n="*" place="margin">Namely, his lessons vpon the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, Ezechiel, &amp;c.</note> vntranslated, which they haue done by the former. Wherefore, this seruice to the Church of God hauing been a long time neglected, and not hearing of any that purposed to set his helping hand to this so necessarie a businesse, I thought it might happily prooue a labour not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnseasonable nor vnprofitable, if according to my poore abilitie I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured either to continue forth those former good beginnings, or at least thereby to quicken vp the care of such as are much more able then my selfe, to prosecute the same.</p>
   <p>To which purpose (good Reader) some few yeeres since, for the first assay, I selected out of this learned Authors workes in French, his Commentary vpon the Hebrewes, not before translated; which being authorized, I was bold soone after to present thee therewith. Now because, as I suppose, it hath not passed abroad without some good fruit, it hath the rather incouraged me once more, whilest I profited my selfe in reading this Commentarie vpon the princelie Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> to haue some respect of thy profiting also. For which cause thou hast the same now, as the former; translated, allowed, and also published (if thou wilt) for thy particular vse and profit.</p>
   <p>As touching the fruit that is thence to be reaped, it would bee much better that thy self from thine owne experience mightest be able to report, then for me here at large to dilate. Only this I thinke I may not omit: if in reading this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie thou wouldest haue the difficulties therein cleared; thy iudgement in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things not obscure, either rectified, or confirmed; thy meditations concer-cerning diuers sorts of instructions, menaces, reprehensions, promises, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations enlarged;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 8.27. <hi>to</hi> 35.</note> loe here a <hi>Philip</hi> readie at hand in any of these things to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb facs="8"/> thy desires. To conclude, if thou entrest vpon the reading of this booke, and wouldest indeede benefit thy selfe thereby, then giue me leaue to vse the Apostles exhortation (though by him vsed to another purpose) <hi>Be not wearie in weldoing,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9.</note> but proceed on constantlie, <hi>so shalt thou</hi> (I doubt not) <hi>in due season reape, if thou faint not.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Farewell, and profit more and more in the studie of Gods word, neuer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Lord rest day nor night, till in the truth of thy heart, thou canst in some good measure professe with these three Worthies following, that thou likewise hast made the same thy chiefe repast, delight and treasure.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <p>
            <note place="margin">Job.</note>I haue not departed from the commandements of his lippes, and I haue esteemed the words of his mouth more then mine appointed foode: <bibl>
               <hi>Iob 23.12.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </p>
         <p>
            <note place="margin">Jeremiah.</note>Thy words are found by me, and I did eate them, and thy word was vnto mee the ioy and reioycing of mine heart: <bibl>
               <hi>Ier. 15.16.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </p>
         <p>
            <note place="margin">Dauid.</note>The law of thy mouth is better vnto mee then thousands of gold and siluer: <bibl>
               <hi>Psalm. 119.72.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ, C. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>