<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND Reuerend Mr. Doctor Ward, Arch∣deacon of Taunton, and Vice-chance∣lor of the Vniuersity of Cambridge, and Master of Sidney-Sussex Colledge: R.I. wisheth all attainable hap∣pinesse in this life, and hereafter.</title>
           <author>Jenison, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107702_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04378</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14491</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107702</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND Reuerend Mr. Doctor Ward, Arch∣deacon of Taunton, and Vice-chance∣lor of the Vniuersity of Cambridge, and Master of Sidney-Sussex Colledge: R.I. wisheth all attainable hap∣pinesse in this life, and hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Jenison, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The height of Israels heathenish idolatrie, in sacrificing their children to the Deuill : diuided into three sections: where is shewed in the first, the growth and degrees of this, and generally of other sinnes and idolatries. In the second, that the Deuill was the god of the heathen; with the meanes by which he obtayned that honour. With a large application to our times, against popery, shewing the pride thereof, and malice both against soule and body; together with the meanes, sleights, and policies by which it seduceth, killeth, and in the person of the Pope, raiseth it selfe to its present height. In the third, the blinde zeale of idolaters. Deliuered generally in two sermons preached at S. Maries in Cambridge: the first whereof is much inlarged: by Robert Ienison Bachelor of Diuinitie, and late Fellow of S. Iohns Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Jenison, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 149, 7, 30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="87"/>
   <pb facs="87"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND Reuerend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Doctor <hi>Ward,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and Vice-chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the Vniuersity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Master of <hi>Sidney-Sussex</hi> Colledge: <hi>R.I.</hi> wisheth all attainable hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse in this life, and hereafter.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>Right Worshipfull Sir,</hi> and <hi>Euer-honored Tutor:</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I looke backe and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (as duty bindes mee,) in what age of the world, in what ripenesse of the Gospell, in what Climate and Region, I was brought forth, together with the means of my education and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; Then doe I finde my selfe for euer bound in soule and body to the mercy and goodnesse of the Almighty Lord God, who thus gaue me my life, being, and motion, and all other my abilities, with the blessed opportunity of place, time, and
<pb facs="88"/>
meanes of the Gospel, with a call to the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, for the eternall saluation of mine owne poore soule and others: Yet so, that my Parents, Friends, Kindred and Countrey, as also my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structors and Tutors, may iustly vnder God, and according to his will claime a share and interest in mee. My desire is, in some acceptable measure to bee answerable to my duty in all the parts of it. Now my whole life and strength is, and euer shall be consecrated to the Honour and Seruice of my Lord and Master IESVS CHRIST: to whose glory, I haue, by his grace, spared time from mine ordinary ministeriall paines, to publish this present Treatise, for the behoofe, information, and inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of my Christian Brethren to glorifie God by a zealous walking with him. And for my kindred and Countrey, among other parts of my dutie daily performed on their behalfe; I thought good to expresse my thankfulnesse to the whole State of the Towne and County of <hi>Newcastle,</hi> by dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them the two former Sections of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, in respect not onely of my breeding among them, but chiefly of that encouragement which from their bounty my studies and Ministeriall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours doe finde.</p>
   <p>Now, good Sir, I should much forget my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and respect to you, who vnder God, were the onely Tutor and formor of my studies in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity, if remembring my thankfulnesse to others, I should passe by your selfe. (Though I forget not my mother the Vniuersity, nor the Colledges, Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> and <hi>Immanuel:</hi> the latter whereof gaue
<pb facs="88"/>
me entertainment and lodged me with you sixe yeares, the other nourished and helped to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mee twelue yeares. Other requitall then this thankfull acknowledgement, for them I haue not at this present.) Giue me leaue then thus publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to expresse my dutifull respect and thankfulnesse to you also, by dedicating to your name this third Section, contayning a Sermon preached in your hearing,<note place="margin">
         <hi>March</hi> 5. 1614.</note> at a solemne Assembly in Saint <hi>Maries</hi> in Cambridge. Your right to it, as to all other my abilities in this kinde, is the greatest of any mans.</p>
   <p>I spare to speake what further right you haue in mee, and how much I am beholding (in my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular) to the example of your integrity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable course of life, of your great and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall paines, humility, and modesty euery way, you being as eminent in and for humilitie, as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in eminency of gifts. But I dare not presume to presse these while I praise them: I know you had rather so bee, then be knowne to bee, further then Gods glory and the necessity of the Church requires; and so you neither are nor can be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. I will conclude, propounding the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of your wonderfull diligence and constant paines, as also modesty, to such as in the Ministery seeke their owne ease, and follow their pleasures, and by the Ministery seeke dignities and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to themselues. Doubtlesse labouring with like singlenesse of heart and modesty of minde, they should finde little cause to doubt so much of Gods Prouidence, as to despaire of <hi>Prouision</hi> proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to their gifts. You haue found it vnsought
<pb facs="89"/>
for, but shall finde the fruit and reward much more hereafter. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. I will not presume to stirre vp you, but my selfe, and other sluggards, in and with the words of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ignat. epist. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> to one <hi>Mary,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And thus I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Newcastle vpon Tine,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>April</hi> 19. 1621.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours euer in the Lord, ROBERT IENISON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>