<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Advertisement to the Christian Reader, concerning the scope of the Booke, with some passages of the Life of the Authour.</title>
           <author>Weekes, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107879_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18711</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5217</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107879</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Advertisement to the Christian Reader, concerning the scope of the Booke, with some passages of the Life of the Authour.</title>
                 <author>Weekes, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miscellanea philo-theologica, or, God, &amp; man : A treatise compendiously describing the nature of God in his attributes, with a lively pourtraiture of his wisedome in ordering, and disposing of the celestiall, and terrestriall bodies. Containing much variety of matter theologicall, and philosophicall; wherein many secrets in scripture, and in nature, are unbowelled, with solid proofes, and apt applications singular for brevity, and perspicuity. By Henry Church</title>
                 <author>Church, Hen (Henry)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Norton, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 280, 83, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>An Advertisement to the Christian Reader, concerning the scope of the Booke, with some passages of the Life of the Authour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>RVE, and solid knowledge layes its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in God; he that will know himselfe, and the sublunary Creatures, as they are, must first <hi>see, and know him</hi> (by faith) <hi>that is invisible:</hi> The studie of the knowledge of God in his Attributes gives a man a possession of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, on earth, <hi>Its life eternall to know thee, &amp;c.</hi> This knowledge is the basis, and foundation of that <hi>precious Faith</hi> the Apostle speakes of: <hi>They that know thee, trust in thee:</hi> So that before a man can with the <hi>wise Builder, build on the Rock</hi> he must <hi>beleeve that God is.</hi> This godly Man <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. HENRY CHURCH</hi> began here; his maine studie was this saving Knowledge: and this he did not by starts, and fits; but daily (as his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling did permit him.) Great was his wisedome, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie in the husbanding of his time, for as he chose <hi>Maries</hi> Part, so hee was carefull of <hi>Martha's;</hi> a good Christian, and a provident Husband. Those that knew his Employments, many urgent in the world, and wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, how he could spare time, or find time for these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations. I may answer for him, <hi>he loved much,</hi> and therefore with <hi>Marie</hi> was resolved to doe much. Hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied himselfe in his pleasures, in his diet, and in his sleepe, <hi>hee bare the yoke of the Lord in his youth,</hi> I have
<pb facs="4"/> heard, that when hee had libertie to sport himselfe, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, his pleasure, <hi>his delight was,</hi> in his Closet, with the <hi>Law of GOD,</hi> hee prevented the dawning of the day, and with <hi>DAVID meditated of GOD in the night-watches,</hi> hee could not intend to be idle, hee had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his Master <hi>CHRIST, who went about doing good,</hi> hee filled-up his vacant houres either with doing, or receiving good; as if hee had exactly learned that charge of the Lord by <hi>Moses, These words which I command thee, thou shalt</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Iunius</hi> Whet them or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>int th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>morie.</note>
      <hi>rehearse them continually to thy Children, and thou shalt talke of them, when thou tariest in thy house, and as thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest by the way, and when thou liest downe, and when thou risest up.</hi> Hee knew not onely for himselfe, but for others; his light was on a <hi>candle-stick, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a bushell,</hi> hee did not with the <hi>Idle Servant, hide his Talent,</hi> but improved it to a good increase. Hee was greedy of all advantages to glorifie God: if hee was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, this was his covetousnesse, <hi>hee coveted the best things.</hi> He was of a compassionate spirit, ready to doe good both to the Soules, and Bodies of others. Hee lived as lent to himselfe, and given to others. How sedulous he was to instruct the Ignorant, to reclaime the wandring, to releeve those that were in want, to settle the unstable soule, those that knew him, can judge. He withstood er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; hee was an Enemie to errour, for hee received the truth in the love of it. Hee was a Friend to truth. Hee endeavoured to comfort afflicted Consciences, for by observing his owne heart, and Conference with such, he attained a singular dexteritie this way. In his Booke you may heare him yet speake, that is now dead. His Religion lay not in Tongue, but in his Heart; not in a <hi>forme of godlinesse, but in power;</hi> as if he had learned to doe what once <hi>Minutius</hi> said, <hi>Non multa loqui, sed vivere.</hi> The scope, and end of this good Mans studies (I suppose) in this Booke was chiefly for himselfe, and his Familie
<pb facs="4"/> that it might like a fruitfull Spring, supplie himselfe, and them.</p>
   <p>Againe, his friends knowing his desire hee had to the publicke good, as also the favourable acceptance of his two former Bookes in the hearts of good men,<note place="margin">viz. The Good mans treasury Divine letters.</note> already printed, gives us good incouragement to adventure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on a publicke Censure.</p>
   <p>Reade it through before you judge, I hope you shall find it profitable, and abounding with much varietie; under briefe Heads drawing on the Reader to delight to studie God in his Attributes, and to inlarge them in thine owne Meditation: as also hee represents God to thee in the glasse of the Creature, and among the rest, Man the Epitome of all; that while thou art poring after curious speculations, and secrets of Nature, hee endeavours wisely to divert thy thoughts, by apt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication heaven-ward. To satisfie the Iudicious.</p>
   <p>If thou shalt except against any thing, consider its a <hi>Posthumus</hi> issue, then I hope you will pardon both the Author, and the Printer.</p>
   <p>For Censorious Criticks I care not to satisfie. <hi>The Blessing of the Almightie be with it.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Imprimatur, THOMAS WEEKES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>