<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOVRABLE and religious Knights, Sir Thomas Wharton, and Sir Thomas Wentworth of Wood∣house: And to the right worshipfull and vertuous Knights, Sir Thomas Hoby, Sir Iohn Iackson, Sir Iohn Thorney, Sir Timothy Hutton, and Sir Richard Sal∣tonstall; together with their well-affected La∣dies: And to that graue Matron, and worthy Patronesse of pietie, Mrs. Elenor Bowes of Aske: TIMOTHY IACKSON wisheth grace, mercy, and peace, from the Father and Prince of peace.</title>
           <author>Jackson, Timothie</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107498_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04198</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14320</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107498</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOVRABLE and religious Knights, Sir Thomas Wharton, and Sir Thomas Wentworth of Wood∣house: And to the right worshipfull and vertuous Knights, Sir Thomas Hoby, Sir Iohn Iackson, Sir Iohn Thorney, Sir Timothy Hutton, and Sir Richard Sal∣tonstall; together with their well-affected La∣dies: And to that graue Matron, and worthy Patronesse of pietie, Mrs. Elenor Bowes of Aske: TIMOTHY IACKSON wisheth grace, mercy, and peace, from the Father and Prince of peace.</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Timothie</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and plaine, yet orthodoxall and methodicall exposition vpon S. Pauls second epistle written to the Thessalonians. By Timothie Iackson Master of Arts, of Christs Colledge in Cambridge, now preacher of Gods word at Wragbie in Yorke-shire</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Timothy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 123, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE and religious Knights, Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Wentworth</hi> of <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house:</hi> And to the right worshipfull and vertuous Knights, Sir <hi>Thomas Hoby,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Iackson,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Thorney,</hi> Sir <hi>Timothy Hutton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonstall;</hi> together with their well-affected La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: And to that graue Matron, and worthy Patronesse of pietie, M<seg rend="sup">rs</seg>. <hi>Elenor Bowes</hi> of <hi>Aske:</hi> TIMOTHY IACKSON <hi>wisheth grace, mercy, and peace, from the Father and Prince of peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Alling to mind (Honorable and right Worshipfull) your manifold and singular fauors, to me ward, (on my part altogether vndeserued) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought with my selfe, how I might in some sort, testifie the thankfullnesse of my mind,<note place="margin">Ingrat<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m si dixeris, omnia dixeris.</note> and so be freed from that capitall crime of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
<pb facs="3"/>so odious both to God and man. Hauing at length perfected this briefe Commentary, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it for the Presse, I resolued to dedicate it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you (Honorable, Worshipfull, and most louing well-wishers) to whom I am so many wayes obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Accept of it, (I beseech you) as our Sauiour Christ did of the widowes mite: and vouchsafe it shelter, and protection from the iniury of the times: and doe not despise it for the meannesse and raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of it; for it is the truth of God, and wholsome meate, though (as I must needs confesse) too too meanly cooked. Besides, it is an infallible token of my louing heart, and thankfull minde. If these first fruits of my poore labours, shall be acceptable to you, and profitable to the Church, I shall be ready hereafter to take more paines in the like kinde. The God of blessing, blesse you and yours, with all good things in this, and a better life, and the God of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences, recompence into your bosomes, all your kindnesses shewed vnto me: And the God of all glory giue you all, grace, to glorifie him in this life, in your seuerall places, that yee may bee glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of him, and with him in the life to come. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>May the</hi> 7. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1621.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honours, and Worships, to be commanded in the Lord, <hi>TIMOTHIE IACKSON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>