<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VVORSHIPFVL and reuerende fathers maister Noel, Deane of Poules, M. Mullins Archdeacon of London, maister D. Walker, Archdeacon of Essex, &amp; maister Towers professor of diuinity, his singuler good friendes and Patrons, R. V. wi∣sheth all health.</title>
           <author>V., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107211_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17648</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4403</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107211</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VVORSHIPFVL and reuerende fathers maister Noel, Deane of Poules, M. Mullins Archdeacon of London, maister D. Walker, Archdeacon of Essex, &amp; maister Towers professor of diuinity, his singuler good friendes and Patrons, R. V. wi∣sheth all health.</title>
                 <author>V., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine, vpon the Epistle to the Colossians. And translated into English by R.V</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 86 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE VVORSHIPFVL and reuerende fathers maister Noel,</hi> Deane of Poules, M. Mullins Archdeacon of London, <hi>maister D. Walker, Archdeacon of Essex, &amp; maister</hi> Towers professor of diuinity, his singuler good <hi>friendes and Patrons,</hi> R. V. <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth all health.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>MAny in the dedicatiōs of their trauails are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to set forth the praises of such parsons as they do dedicate the same vnto. And surely J thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse if flattery be absent. For who is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norāt that <hi>virtus laudata crescit,</hi> praise vertue, and it shall encrease. I speake not this right worshipful and reuerende fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the ende that J meane to do the like to you, although no man that knoweth you but he will say you worthelye deserue the same: for if J shoulde either praise your learning or diligence in your vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="3"/> which euery where is knowen, or your, godly cōuersation which vnto your nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est frendes is well tried, or your libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which all those that haue neede, but spetially the Godly poore haue found and daily do fynde, who might iustly reprehēd me: but letting passe these thinges to the consideratiō of vpright iudges, I purpose to shew and that very brieflye what hath moued me to dedicate this present booke vnto your worshippes. you knowe that I receaued at your handes (that worthye man maister D. Watts beynge then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, whom with reuerence I remember) that liuinge which J haue: and althoughe you sell not your benefices (as manye in these dayes do) yet reason woulde that J should not remaine vnthankefull for the same, though it were a greate deale lesse then it is. And wheras want of abilitye
<pb facs="3"/> vvould not suffer me to recōpence other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvyse your good will, yet rather then still <hi>I</hi> should continue vnthankeful, I chose this litle commentary of that worthye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther M. <hi>Caluine</hi> to supply that which els might be left vndon: vvherin J vvish that my hart lay open to be vievved: then vvould you not more regard the thinge it selfe, vvhich no doubt is vvorthy the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting, thē the good vvil of him that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senteth the same vnto you. Fare you vvel. At high Easter the first of Nouember.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to commaund <hi>R. V.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>