<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Generous and Wel-disposed Reader.</title>
           <author>Heigham, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107802_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18601</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107802</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Generous and Wel-disposed Reader.</title>
                 <author>Heigham, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ghosts of the deceased sieurs, de Villemor, and de Fontaines : A most necessarie discourse of duells: wherein is shewed the meanes to roote them out quite. With the discourse of valour. By the Sieur de Chevalier. To the King. The third edition reviewed, corrected, and augmented in French, and translated by Tho. Heigham, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Chevalier, Guillaume de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 151, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Generous and Wel-disposed Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Commaund or Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie that a man can haue, is to be Monarch of his owne Minde: And he that is not so, runs from errour to obstinacie, to ruine, and to destruction. This Author hath not done like him, who seeing his friends house on a fire; because he would not be the messenger of euill newes, let the house burne downe: but doth (as you may see) ingenuously and ingeniously, piously and passionately (without feare or flattery) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue and instruct both the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie.</hi> By which also all that are wise, and honest, and haue any propension to gaine this power ouer themselues, may attaine vnto it, by learning (in this <hi>Booke</hi>) what true <hi>Honour, Ʋalour, Magnanimity,</hi> and <hi>Martyrdome</hi> is. You may perceiue that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,
<pb facs="4"/>
enuy, pride, and ambition, which are all off-springs of idlenes, were the abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute motiues to all these murthers. And some will thinke that God, by the <hi>Kings</hi> bloody ende, did shew his anger against him for his remisnesse in these preuentions. Giue me leaue then, out of my affection to all that would doe well, to admonish them to shunne by all meanes, this deuouring monster <hi>Idlenesse,</hi> so odious to God and good men. It was one of the sinnes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> it is the mother and nurse of all sinnes and iniquities. No man can expresse the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mischiefes that it hath produced. But because I thinke, the false opinions of many (who hold all employments vnworthy a Gentleman, but gaming, and sporting) doe much hurt, I will set you downe examples, and reasons to the contrary. I haue read of a <hi>Noble-man,</hi> that did so much hate <hi>Idlenes,</hi> that when he had nothing to doe of greater moment, he would make Butchers-pricks, saying, they might happily be vsefull to some; at the least (saith he) they will in the making with-draw me from vain thoughts, idle words, and wicked actions.</p>
   <p>There was a <hi>Baron</hi> of this Realme, a very excellent Gold-smith: my selfe haue scene
<pb facs="5"/>
a faire siluer standish of his making. A Knight I knew of an auncient family, that made it his daily exercise to make nets.</p>
   <p>Some worthy Gentlemen there are, that are excellent Painters, some grauers, some perfumers, and the like: all expressing ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous spirits, and diuine dispositions. For the soule of man is alwaies in action, still imagining or contriuing good or euill; and euery action that is honest is profitable and laudable, and farre from basenes or disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. There is no man so noble or free borne, but ought to doe somewhat to the seruice of God, his Prince, or Countrey; and he that can make that his pastime, pleasure, and delight, is infinitely more blessed then other men.</p>
   <p>These considerations did pricke me for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to translate this <hi>Booke,</hi> who being not bred, nor aduanced to any vocation of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, nor naturally inclined to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties aboue mentioned, or the like; did thinke this my best remedie against that contagious disease of <hi>Idlenesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It may be, that Critticks as wel as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians will reade this <hi>Booke,</hi> and as they doe the holiest bookes of all, will deride and traduce both that and the Author: But <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
saith, It is no sinne, but a glory for a man to suffer iniurie, and that such are to be answered with silence. I doe publish it for the good of others, to serue as a Pilot to conduct honest men with honour, and safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their iourneyes end; as also vpon the importunitie of some especiall friends of mine. And if I may find that it doth passe with good acceptance, I shall bee encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to make further triall hereafter. If not, I will make my future endeauours onely to content my selfe, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your wel-wishing friend, THO. HEIGHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>