<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107921_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18244</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4863</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107921</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cato variegatus or Catoes morall distichs: translated and paraphras'd, with variations of expressing, in English verse. By Sr. Richard Baker Knight</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Boler, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Anne</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 102, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Lover of Learning, translated these<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
of <hi>Cato</hi> into English, some twelve
years since: whose labour, I cannot blame:
but tying himselfe, strictly to the words; he
could not alwaies, either so fully, or so gracefully, expresse
the mening: for indeed, the words of one language, cannot
alwaies be reached, by the very same words of another:
which made an Able man, in this cause to say: <hi>Nec
verbum verbo curabis reddere.</hi> And therefore seeing
the sence especially in precepts, is principally to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded,
there is iustly a liberty given, in this kinde, not
onely to use Periphrases, but Paraphrases also, as the
cause may require, which liberty if I be censured by any
to have used too liberally: Yet so long as <hi>Sensus est
in tuto,</hi> and nothing is said, but what is drawn, <hi>Epo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia
verborum:</hi> I expect to be excused at least, if not
commended: And if many of these, seeme rather Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrases,
or rather Collateral Conceits then translations:
yet seeing they tend all to the same sence: and that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
translations are sent before, as set alwayes next the
latine: they are but after the fashion of young men; who
weare thin cloaths, in cold winter, but haue good warm
wast-cotes vnder them, and some men, may bee of that
<pb facs="3"/>
disposition, to take as much delight, in the conceit of the
Expressing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as in the expressing of the conceit-And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
this kinde of writing, seemes not onely away of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation,
but a Fruit: Not only an Exercise, but a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
of Invention; and if there were nothing else, but
the Variety; we see, how much the Eye, is delighted with
varietie of colours, in the same obiect; the Eare, with
variety of Descant upon the same Plaine song; &amp; euen
Nature herselfe, seemes delighted with it: For, who
doubts, but into one forme of a Flower, she could have
infused all kinde ofsents; and all, of sappes, but that shee
takes a pleasure, in the variety of Formes. Some man will
perhaps say; Here is variety indeed; but one well done
were better then all: what good doth choice, where All is
Refuse stuffe? It is true: but let this man bring better
stuffes out of his warehouse; &amp; then, let these be thrown
away: till then, he may content himselfe with these; They
may keepe him warme, though not make him fine. And
seeing there is variety of Iudgements; it is not unfit, to
tender them, variety of Expressings: some may take
better with one Iudgement: some, with another:
and oftentimes, one Expressing, gives lustre to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
and makes the reason, which lay hid before
to looke abroad: which is not yet, another thing; but
the same thing, in another light: and lastly, being Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
of Morality; they cannot haue too many allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb facs="3"/>
How soever it be; the worke I am sure, is such, as
need not repent me, of one moneth spent in writing it:
Nor thee, whosoever thou art of one houre spent in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
it. I have quoted in the margent such places in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
writings, as are consonant &amp; agreeing with these
Precepts of <hi>Cato;</hi> that we may see, how farre it hath
pleased God, to illuminate even Heathen men, in matters
of Morality. And I intended, to have set at the end, a
Patterne of the like variety in Latin; done eyther by
<hi>Virgil,</hi> or by <hi>Ausonius:</hi> and translated in a greater
variety into English: but considering, this present work
is it selfe, nothing else, but variations: I have chosen
rather to omit it, least it might be thought, a supernume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie
idlenesse: yet thus much, we may gather by it; that
even the Ancients scorned not, this variety of expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing;
either as an exercise to the Writer, or a delight
to the Reader; and seeing it hath beene now so long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne;
it may come in also, as a novelty: and so I may
suppose my selfe to haue two good supporters, (varietie
&amp; noueltie) to helpe to beare out my own imperfections.</p>
   <p>Now for the <hi>Cato,</hi> that was the Author of these ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
whether it were a Person, or but a Name onely, (as
<hi>Cicero</hi> called his booke <hi>De senectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e Cato Major,</hi> to
giue it the more lustre of grauitie) it is uncertaine, but
certaine it is, what <hi>Cato</hi> it was, is nothing certaine: and
not much more certain, what time he liued; only <hi>Io. Scal.</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
by some probable coniecture gathereth: that he lived, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
the times of the Emperours <hi>Commodus</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus:</hi>
which might well bee: seeing the <hi>saeculum</hi> of
yeeres,<note place="margin">about an. Dom. 170.</note> next proceeding; was in sobriety of manners, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the Romans, of all other, the most flourishing.
And though the Emperours themselves were not yet
Christians; yet they made approches toward it, in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
Doctrine, as neere, as could be: as, well testifies that
excellent Booke of Morality: written by the learned
Emperour, <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antonius;</hi> father vnto
<hi>Commodus:</hi> which, to the great commendation of the
Translatour, is lately published amongst us: out of which
perhaps this <hi>Cato,</hi> whosoever hee was, might make
choice of some speciall Precepts: and put them, into short
Disticks; for the better reteining them in memory. And
for my selfe; if any man thinke me Repuerascere; and
to enter upon a worke, that were fitter for a schoole boy:
let him know, that one Planudes, long since, and of late,
<hi>Ioseph Scaliger,</hi> two excellent men, &amp; of singular lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;
haue Both of them, thought it no disparagement
to their grauitie, to translate them into <hi>Greeke;</hi> as, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
learned men haue likewise done into other langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;
whose Examples, I dare boldly oppose to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
of any, or all Inferiour Iudgements.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>