<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107278_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19628</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6062</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107278</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mikrokosmographia : a description of the body of man. Together vvith the controuersies thereto belonging. Collected and translated out of all the best authors of anatomy, especially out of Gasper Bauhinus and Andreas Laurentius. By Helkiah Crooke Doctor of Physicke, physitian to His Maiestie, and his Highnesse professor in anatomy and chyrurgerie. Published by the Kings Maiesties especiall direction and warrant according to the first integrity, as it was originally written by the author</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Helkiah</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 877, 888-1111, 3 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="514"/>
   <pb facs="514"/>
   <head>❧ The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I intended first this excellent labour (Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader) my absolute purpose aymed at the ingenious worke of M. <hi>Ambrose Parae,</hi> (Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the most Christian King of France, <hi>Henrie</hi> the third) a man of admirable perfection in his Art and profession; whereto I was the rather inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, because his first fiue Bookes beginneth with this present Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Anatomy, a matter much affected by mee. But finding his scope farre short of so deliberate a determination, &amp; that more mature discourse flowed from those two famous Anatomists, <hi>Iaspar Baubinus</hi> and <hi>Andreas Laurentius,</hi> with diuers other Authors writing on the same argument, I made choise for this time to be gouerned by their worthy enstructions; although to my no meane care and cost it hath risen to so great a volume, which (in the first intention) was imagined to comprize the whole frame or building. Yet let me not be misinterpreted heerein, as one fearefull to aduenture on a worke of farre greater moment, the Authors being so renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the expectation only to the publique benefit of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. For thus much I assure thee, the Figures, Pieces, and Shapes belonging to the remaining Bookes of <hi>Paraes</hi> Chirurgery, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prepared, &amp; the worke it selfe fully translated for the presse, which by thy gentle acceptance of this my first aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this kinde, will flye vnto thee with the swifter speed.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>