<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Summary Of Errors By Doctor Whitgifies]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107569_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18080</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4714</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107569</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Summary Of Errors By Doctor Whitgifies]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second replie of Thomas Cartwright: agaynst Maister Doctor Whitgiftes second answer, touching the Churche discipline</title>
                 <author>Cartwright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schirat, Michael</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Heidelberg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, dlxvi, that is dclxvi, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary_of_errors_by_Doctor_Whitgifies">
   <pb facs="359"/>
   <argument>
      <p>To note onely the errors / corruptiōs and shameful falsifyinges of the D. in suche sort as he hath pretended in my book: were to make a new book. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there is much void paper / I wil gyue the reader an assay on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ely / of those conteined in the treatises which I hādle in this book. And those shal be not off the capital matters betwene vs: but off such as are browght to vnderset them / quoted according to his own book whereby yt shal appeare / that for the defence off this cause he troubleth heauen yt self: and in earth ouerthroweth both estates / Ciuil / and Ecclesiasticall.</p>
   </argument>
   <p>THe vvhole lavv of god generally, is abrogated, pa. 121. li. 39.</p>
   <p>The scripture speaketh not one vvord off preaching or bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing priuately or openly, page 89. line 6.</p>
   <p>The scripture hath not commaunded, nether can yt be by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary collection theroff gathered: vvhether vve should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the communion clothed or naked, page 24. line 21.</p>
   <p>The scripture hath appointed no discipline for the correcting off suche as shall contemn the hearing off the vvord and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier, page 88 line 47.</p>
   <p>He matcheth the iudiciall lavves off god, gyuen vnto the Ivves: vvith the Turckes lavves, page 149 line 32.</p>
   <p>HE alovveth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sentence off Cyrill vvhich condemneth the iustice off g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 chunk">
         <desc>…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 chunk">
         <desc>…</desc>
      </gap>ishing those by aeternall death vvhich suffered corpor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ath vnder the lavv page 149. line 48.</p>
   <p>He matcheth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>shing off saithe by consideration off the creatures, vvith popishe imagety, page 571. line 2.</p>
   <p>TO maintein the sole election off the bishop: he vvould ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the free elections off magistrates, in cities and Boro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvgh Tovvnes taken avvay, page 171. line 49.</p>
   <p>VVherby he vvill haue the forme of gouernement off the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvealth framed vnto the form off the church: vvheroff notvvithstanding and that most vntrvvly he accuseth me.</p>
   <p>Likevvise that vnder the gospell there is no punishment off the body laid vpon a transgressor: but that if he repent, so that
<pb facs="359"/> he may seem vvorthy to haue the punishement vvithdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvn, he may finde forgiuenes, page 150. line 9.</p>
   <p>No man vvhat crime soeuer he hath committed: is to be seclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from any lavvful vocation if he repēt. And by vocation: he meaneth publike office, page 146. line 23.</p>
   <p>The externall gouernement off the church, vnder a Christian magistrate: must be according to the kinde and form off go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, vsed in the common vvealth, pa. 389. li. 5. vvhich (beside the absurditie) vtterly ouerthrovveth the liberty: vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich him self pretendeth that the church hath, in disposing off yt.</p>
   <p>In the Apostels times, yt vvas permitted to all men: to preache, the vvord off God, page 191. li. 16.</p>
   <p>Beside Pastors there are novv vvith vs, Apostles Prophetes, and Euangelistes, page 229. line 6.</p>
   <p>ALthovvgh there vvere a sufficient nomber off able men to supply the places of the reading ministers: yet the reading ministers, ovvght to kepe their places still page 485. lin. 5.</p>
   <p>The vvord, ys as effectual red: as preached Page 569. lin. 23. To those, vvhich vnderstand the scriptures: they are as vvhot and lightsom red, as preached, page 573. li. 34.</p>
   <p>publike reading in the church, is as solem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> matter: as Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chising the youth, page 425. lin. 43.</p>
   <p>Yt may be, that some men be more aedified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> simple rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding off the scriptures▪ then by sermons pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>80. li. 30.</p>
   <p>To that I say, that nether homilies, nor Apocrypha are to be compared ether in goodnes vvithin them selues, or fruict to the hearers, vvith the scripture or reading thereof: he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvereth that that maketh against sermons, as vvel as aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inst homilies: and rather against sermons, then against them, Page 717 li. 52. VVherby he affirmeth, that homilies are both better in them selues, and more fruiteful to the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arers: then sermons.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>