<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The explication of this Bookes FRONTISPICE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107372_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17808</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4497</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107372</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The explication of this Bookes FRONTISPICE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Annales : the true and royall history of the famous empresse Elizabeth Queene of England France and Ireland &amp;c. True faith's defendresse of diuine renowne and happy memory. Wherein all such memorable things as happened during hir blessed raigne, with such acts and treaties a past betwixt hir Matie. and Scotland, France, Spaine, Italy, Germany, Poland, Sweden, Denmark, Russia, and the Netherlands, are exactly described</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96, 435, 5, 232, 251-292, 2 pages, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The explication of this Bookes FRONTISPICE.</head>
   <l>The Pillers deckt with Arms, Palms, Laurell bows,</l>
   <l>Supporting the Rare PHOENIX, to you shows</l>
   <l>The Nobles, on whose loyall prudent brest,</l>
   <l>The Phoenix-Queene, ELIZA'S peace did rest:</l>
   <l>Whose Wisedomes pillars did vphold her Crowne,</l>
   <l>As columnes, on which rested her renowne.</l>
   <l>Their stable valour did support this land;</l>
   <l>And all her proud insulting foes withstand:</l>
   <l>For whose exploits it pleasd her Maiesty</l>
   <l>To dub, some Knights of dreadlesse chiualry;</l>
   <l>Whom she not only did to Knighthood rayse,</l>
   <l>But of this kingdome made them props and stayes.</l>
   <l>And those whose merits added to their worth</l>
   <l>Renowned Glory, Honour to their birth.</l>
   <l>In whose true worthy acts she most delighted,</l>
   <l>She, with the Order of the Garter, knighted.</l>
   <l>Some she restor'd in their Ancestors place▪</l>
   <l>Made viscount Bindon, one of Noble Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>Some Earles, some Barons, all she did restore,</l>
   <l>Or did create as they had won before:</l>
   <l>Other shee summon'd, by her wisedome's choyce,</l>
   <l>To Parliament as Peeres to have there voyce:</l>
   <l>Whose prudence, and whose valors (vnder God)</l>
   <l>Prou'd Englands peace, to Spaine a heauy rod.</l>
   <l>The fired townes, which on each side are plac't,</l>
   <l>Do memorize how Spaine was once disgract:</l>
   <l>When that braue Essex, Englands Generall,</l>
   <l>With Nottingham, that famous Admirall,</l>
   <l>Their Citie Cadiz did with force surprise</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o crowne their countrey with their victories.</l>
   <l>And Cumberland, whose fame no Age can blot</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ooke Por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arico with his Thundring shot</l>
   <l>That Spanish towne; yet his victorious force</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lew the resisting, pardn'd with remorse</l>
   <l>Those that with bended knees did him entreat,</l>
   <l>He would not them nor theirs of life defeat.</l>
   <l>Now vnderneath DRAKES famous ship is show<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>Whose bright renown swift Honors trump hath blow</l>
   <l>How he therein did circuit earth's whole frame▪</l>
   <l>And in his voyage added to his fame.</l>
   <l>The glory of a prize won through his paine,</l>
   <l>The <hi>CACAFOGVE,</hi> Royall Ship of Spaine.</l>
   <l>At the two corners, two great Spanish Fleets</l>
   <l>Your gazing eyes with admiration greets.</l>
   <l>One is consum'd by vnquench't flames of fire,</l>
   <l>The other is ore'whelm'd through NEPTVNE'S ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>Which moralizeth, our good God doth bend</l>
   <l>His wrath, gainst those that Albions ill inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>Which wrath did fall most mercilesse on Spaine,</l>
   <l>And euer will to their disgrace remaine.</l>
   <l>One thousand (doth) fiue hundred eighty seuen,</l>
   <l>Their ambitions with infamy, make euen.</l>
   <l>The Port of Gilbaltars straights, sure can tell,</l>
   <l>How that a Spanish Fleet (by <hi>DRAKE</hi>) there fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>The very seas will witnesse, that with foure</l>
   <l>Of royall Ships, he burnt two hundred more.</l>
   <l>If you enquire, from whence those Royals came;</l>
   <l>From Englands shore, Spaines fury for to tame.</l>
   <l>To end, the Fleet of Eighty-eight doth show,</l>
   <l>England was ayded in that ouerthrow</l>
   <l>Giuen to Spaine, by God, whose potent hand</l>
   <l>Preseru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d ELIZA'S glory, and her land.</l>
   <l>Gainst those that owe true Religion spight,</l>
   <l>Both seas and earth, for Albions cause will fight.</l>
   <l>Not to the seas let's bend, but to that power</l>
   <l>Which must preserue vs, at the dreadfull houre.</l>
   <l>And as 'tis meet so let vs prostrate fall</l>
   <l>Vnto our Hope, our Ayde, our Generall.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>