<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORTHIE (AND VVORTHILY OF ALL WHO KNOW YOV TO BE MVCH HONOVRED) Mris SVSANNA STRANGVVAYES, Wife of GYLES STRANGVVAYES Esquire, Sonne and Heire to Sir IOHN STRANGVVAYES Knight.</title>
           <author>Puede-Ser, Diego</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107640_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18334</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4914</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107640</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORTHIE (AND VVORTHILY OF ALL WHO KNOW YOV TO BE MVCH HONOVRED) Mris SVSANNA STRANGVVAYES, Wife of GYLES STRANGVVAYES Esquire, Sonne and Heire to Sir IOHN STRANGVVAYES Knight.</title>
                 <author>Puede-Ser, Diego</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Exemparie nouells : in sixe books. The two damosels. The Ladie Cornelia. The liberall lover. The force of bloud. The Spanish ladie. The jealous husband. Full of various accidents both delightfull and profitable. By Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra; one of the prime wits of Spaine, for his rare fancies, and wittie inventions. Turned into English by Don Diego Puede-Ser</title>
                 <author>Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Blaiklock (Blacklock), Lawrence.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 323, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORTHIE (AND VVORTHILY OF ALL WHO KNOW YOV TO BE MVCH HONOVRED) M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg> SVSANNA STRANGVVAYES, Wife of GYLES STRANGVVAYES Esquire, Sonne and Heire to Sir IOHN STRANGVVAYES Knight.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Oung Ladies and Gentlewomen that are studious of reading good Bookes, (such as your selfe oft converse withall) when they finde their eyes waxe dull and weary, put their booke from them; and for their better refreshing and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, change the Sceane, and breathe themselves a while, till their spirits being thereby revived, they turne to their wonted strength and vigour. I have seene some of your <hi>Sexe,</hi> (especially such as have beene gentily bred) when they have
<pb facs="3"/>
wrought hard with their <hi>Needle</hi> upon some cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Worke,</hi> have laid that aside, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a Lute in hand, or some other musicall <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument,</hi> and playd a <hi>Lesson</hi> or two thereon, to recreate themselves therewith, and anone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fall to their worke afresh: So naturall is it to all sorts of persons whatsoever to take delight in <hi>Variety.</hi> To harpe alwayes on one string, is harsh to the <hi>Eare.</hi> To feed still upon one <hi>Dish,</hi> doth but glut the <hi>Stomacke.</hi> Your wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest and learnedst Men both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-weale,</hi> will sometimes leave off their more serious <hi>Discourses,</hi> and entertaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with matters of harmelesse <hi>Merriment,</hi> and <hi>Disports.</hi> Such are these <hi>Stories</hi> I present unto your view. I will not promise any great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit you shall reape by reading them: but I promise they will be pleasing andd elightfull; the <hi>Sceane</hi> is so often varied, the <hi>Passages</hi> so pretty, the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents</hi> so strange; and in the end brought to so happy a <hi>Conclusion.</hi> Here, though one bit (as we say) will draw downe another, you shall not cloy your selfe. These are but a few of running ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting dishes: Take (as you like) here and there a little of each sort: which will but whet your <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke,</hi> and set an edge on your <hi>Appetite,</hi> against you come to feed your <hi>Vnderstanding</hi> with meats more nourishable and substantiall. If you shall
<pb facs="3"/>
but kindly accept, and take in good part (which the sweetnesse of your Disposition cannot otherwise choose) this poore Pittance, you will encourage me to invite you to a more solemne <hi>Feast,</hi> worthier your selfe, and him, who shall ever love and honour your <hi>Vertues</hi> and <hi>Goodnesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Don Diego Puede-Ser,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>