<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO MY LORD DE SVLLY, Duke and Peere of FRANCE, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107802_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18601</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107802</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO MY LORD DE SVLLY, Duke and Peere of FRANCE, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ghosts of the deceased sieurs, de Villemor, and de Fontaines : A most necessarie discourse of duells: wherein is shewed the meanes to roote them out quite. With the discourse of valour. By the Sieur de Chevalier. To the King. The third edition reviewed, corrected, and augmented in French, and translated by Tho. Heigham, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Chevalier, Guillaume de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 151, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>❧ TO MY LORD DE <hi>SVLLY, Duke and Peere of FRANCE, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatise of Duells, is not dedicated to your For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but to <hi>your</hi> Ʋer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>which</hi> is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall cause thereof. The most part doe runne after prosperitie, <hi>I am none of the great number.</hi> My eies are onely set vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your rare merit, by which you shine, by which you gouerne. It is accompanied with felicitie, and fauour. For this regard, the present Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course (made for the Publique) hath neede of your Fortune: Seeing that the King testifieth so expressely, that he esteemeth your Prudence
<pb facs="6"/>
and Probity (ornaments so knowne, so admired) you may make it of Validity. Your humour is wholly carried thereunto, by the knowledge, by the sensible apprehension of so great a mischiefe. It shall be a Christian worke, worthy of your zeale to the seruice of his Maiestie, and good of the Estate. You shall anew oblige <hi>France,</hi> doe not frustrate it (if it please you) of the helpe which it expecteth from your Vertue in so faire an occasion. You are inuited thereunto, a man may say obliged, seeing that you are one of the eyes of our great Monarch: You shall get Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in this affaire. Faire actions ought to bee produced without designe of glorie in time to come: But in doing for the Common good, it is not vnlawfull to encrease the reputation of his Name. Let your excellent spirit iudge if this action which is hoped for, will not be a reliefe of all the others, whereof <hi>France</hi> hath had a true feeling. Whereupon I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
      <signed>Your most humble, and most obedient seruant, CHEVALIER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>