<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107409_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17864</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107409</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An examination of those plausible appearances which seeme most to commend the Romish Church, and to preiudice the reformed : Discovering them to be but meere shifts, purposely invented, to hinder an exact triall of doctrine by the Scriptures. By Mr Iohn Cameron. Englished out of French</title>
                 <author>Cameron, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 173, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader: for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting mistakes, giue me leaue to aduertise thee, that in many passages of this book beside the <hi>running title,</hi> J haue vsed the word <hi>Preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> in a sense, not very vsuall in English, make it answere to the French word <hi>Preiugè,</hi> which my Author vseth, not for an ill preconceit, as wee commonly take it, but for such a plausible appearance, as before due examination, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> bee a probable ground for any <hi>preconceit</hi> of a thing, either good or bad. So <hi>Antiquitie</hi> is a Preiudice for the Papists, and against vs, because that before a iudicious examination, it is a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ground for common braines to conceiue well of their Religion, and to mistrust ours. Secondly, I haue not beene so superstitious in expressing my Authors word, as I haue obserued some transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb facs="3"/>
to be: I haue not <hi>construed,</hi> but <hi>translated,</hi> keeping (as neere as I could) an euen course be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Pedant</hi> &amp; a <hi>Paraphrast:</hi> For when the <hi>Originall</hi> is not to be learned by the Translation, I tbink it not only lawfull, but also conuenient to make vse of that liberty. The neglect of it, I take to be the reason, why commonly <hi>Translations</hi> are thought to tast <hi>flat</hi> in respect of the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall.</hi> I shall not wonder if some slipps haue escaped mee, seeing a man may be as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdly ouer seene by too much animaduersion, as by none, and (which is the misery of the most circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect diligence) a man may dote as much by ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing through a thing, as by staring beside it: yet I hope there are none so <hi>grosse</hi> as that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse either my Author, or his Reader.</p>
   <trailer>Farwell.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>