<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VVORSHIPFVLL Company of the Barber-Chyrurgeons, the Maister, Wardens, Assistants, and Comminalty of the same; HELKIAH CROOKE, Physitian and Professor in Anatomy and Chirurgery to His MAIESTIE, wisheth Happie and prosperous Successe in Your PROFESSION.</title>
           <author>Crooke, Helkiah</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107278_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19628</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6062</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107278</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VVORSHIPFVLL Company of the Barber-Chyrurgeons, the Maister, Wardens, Assistants, and Comminalty of the same; HELKIAH CROOKE, Physitian and Professor in Anatomy and Chirurgery to His MAIESTIE, wisheth Happie and prosperous Successe in Your PROFESSION.</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Helkiah</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mikrokosmographia : a description of the body of man. Together vvith the controuersies thereto belonging. Collected and translated out of all the best authors of anatomy, especially out of Gasper Bauhinus and Andreas Laurentius. By Helkiah Crooke Doctor of Physicke, physitian to His Maiestie, and his Highnesse professor in anatomy and chyrurgerie. Published by the Kings Maiesties especiall direction and warrant according to the first integrity, as it was originally written by the author</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Helkiah</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 877, 888-1111, 3 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE VVORSHIPFVLL Company of the Barber-Chyrurgeons, the <hi>Maister, Wardens, Assistants, and Comminalty of the same;</hi> HELKIAH CROOKE, Physitian and Professor in Anatomy and Chirurgery to His MAIESTIE, <hi>wisheth Happie and prosperous Successe in Your</hi> PROFESSION.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Maisters and Worshipfull Friends. As from the first I intended this Labor vnto your behoofe; so now hauing by Gods assistance brought it to an end, I offer it vnto you as a token of my Loue: Not that I doubt but there are some among you who as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues stand in no neede of my helpe, so they are also able to haue set out this Banquet with greater variety and to haue Cooked it fitter for you as being better acquainted with your diet and appetites. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is now a long time since your <hi>Banister</hi> (that good old man) first presented you with a seruice of this kinde, and no man hath seconded him; I haue aduentured to commit vnto you these first fruites of my vntainted fame: which if you shall kindly entertaine and make such vse thereof as I may not think my labour misbestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you shall encourage me cheerefully to run on that course which I haue propounded to my selfe to further your profiting in that Noble Art which you haue taken vpon you to professe. For when I first began, I intended the Anatomy to be but an entrance into a worke of Chyrurgerie, which I had digested into a forme fit, as I thinke, first to ground and establish you in the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Theory or Contemplatiue part of your profession, and after to builde you vp vnto the practise of the same. And because the Body of Man is the Subiect of your Art, without the knowledge whereof it is impossible for a Chirurgeon to work with any confidence or certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of successe, I began with Anatomy.</p>
   <p>In the next place shall follow a Discourse of the constitution of mans body, as he enioyeth a perfect or apportionated health by a due Mixture of the principles whereof he consisteth; of the Temperament of each part arising from that mixture; of the Offices or Functions proceeding from that temperament, and such other things as will fall in with the same. For as it is a rule in Geometry, that <hi>Rectum est index sui &amp; obliqus, That which is Right measureth both it selfe and that which is crooked;</hi> so in our Art, he that knowes what should bee the naturall disposition of euerie part will be best able to iudge when Nature declineth from that integrity, and how far the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination is from the true and genuine constitution. This part indeede is Philosophicall, but I shall make it so plaine, if God will, that a very reasonable capacity shall be able to apprehend it. After you haue knowledge of the healthfull and sound constitution which is the rule of the rest, I teach the Natures, Differences, Signes and Prognosticks of diseases, so farre as it necessarie a Chyrurgeon should know, that is to say, of Tumours or Apostemations, of Woundes, Vlcers, Fractures, and the like. Then followeth the Method of Curing by Indications, which are many and intricate, but I haue referred them (not without great labour) to outward diseases and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated all by examples to make the better impression in your minds. In the next place I handle the Operations of Chyrurgery in generall, where you haue all the Instruments of your Art; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, Swathes, Ties, Bands and Ligatures, described by <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Oribasius,</hi> and those also of the new Chyrurgeons inuentions, with their Figures, interpretations, and manner of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. Afterward I descend to the operations in particular, as to Diuision, Simple &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound; Simple in Section &amp; Vstion; Compound with Extraction and Extirpation. To Iunction also, Simple and Compound, Simple in Adduction, Adaptation, and the way how to Conteine them so fitted together. Compound with Addition of such decayed Naturall parts as may bee restored or imitated by Art. Then I come to the cure of Tumors of all kindes both Simple and Compound: of Wounds whether they bee made <hi>Caesim</hi> or <hi>punctim,</hi> by Contusion, by Arrowes, Engines or Bullets, with Laceration or with out: of the bytings or stinging of venomous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with their seuerall Antidotes: of burnings, scaldings, and such like.</p>
   <p>Next I proceed to Vlcers, putride, sordide, sistulated, cancerous, gangrenated, sphacelated
<pb facs="5"/>
and such as are virulent, with the Accidents that vse to accompany them: to Luxations also and Fractures with their kinds and accidents. Afterward I handle those generall diseases which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the whole body, as the Gowt, the Leprosie, the Meazels, the Pox of both kindes, the Plague and such like: and then proceede to the particular diseases from the Head to the Foote, wherein the Chirurgeons helpe is required. Finally, I intreat of the Matter of Chyrurgery, that is, of the Nature of those Drugs, Hearbs and Minerals which he hath neede to vse; of their corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and preparation, of the manner of compounding his Medicines both for outward applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and such inward as may conduce thereuuto. And so I thinke I shall haue finished the Art of Chyrurgery throughout.</p>
   <p>I acknowledge that which I haue promised to be a great labor, and more then any man whom I haue yet seene hath accomplished: but the ground being long a goe laide in my priuate studies and reserences continually now for these sixteene yeares accommodated vnto those groundes, haue brought it to such forwardnesse as I can be content to finish it with as much hast as my oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions will giue leaue, if I see that this Anatomicall labour is acceptable and of vse vnto you. I know well there are some who thinke and do not stitke to affirme, euen before your publique Assemblies, that you haue meanes enow already, &amp; haply more then they would you had. Their reason can be no other, but because they would holde you alwayes abnoxious to themselues. For my part I conceiue of the Art of Chyrurgery as of a part of Physick; and therefore of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons as Citizens of the Physitians Commonwealth: the difference is, that wee hauing most<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what better meanes by education to aduantage our wittes, apply them vnto the more abstruse part of the Art separated from the sense and consisting in contemplation and collection; the Chyrurgeon worketh by his eye and with his hand, and dwelleth as it were in the Confines of that Countrey whose inner part we inhabit. If therefore they warrant the frontiers and keepe their Stations well and duly therein, may not we better attend to improoue the portion that is allotted vnto vs? But wee are both like couetous Farmers, who incroach vppon and get more grounds into their hands then they can well manage, for getting that wholesome counsel of the wise Poet:
<q>
         <l>Laudato ingentia rura—Exiguum colito.</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>Praise a great Farme but occupy a small.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>For surely if we aduise well with our selues, Physitians shall find work enough (though they med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with the labour of the hand) to minde the subiect of their Art, I mean Anatomy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in too many of vs are wanting to our selues and others; the causes of diseases; the signes of the part affected; the skill of praediction; the method of curing and the choise of Medicines, with a world of intricate worke beside in apprehending occasions, expecting and imitating the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and endeauors of Nature, remoouing her obstacles, strengthning her operations &amp; the like. And if we want imployment in these, it seemeth to me more fit to fit our selues thereunto, then casting behinde our backes the care of such needfull studies to take vp our precious time in dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing or attending broken heads, strained or luxed ioynts, new wounds or old Vlcers, or in play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apothe caries as some do, who vnder the name of Cordials of x. li. an ounce, Potable Golde, precious Quintessences and preparations of Minerals, do obtrude vpon the worlde ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notable impostures or dangerous poysons, ayming indeede at nothing so much (if at any thing else) as at their priuate gaine and the concealing of their ignorance which would neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily be detected if they should communicate their practise to Apothecaries as other ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Physitians doe. But of these I haue spoken more largely in an Animaduersion vpon <hi>Crolius</hi> his Admonitory preface in Latine, and shall haue fitter occasion to speake more elswhere, when I shall be very plaine against those that come in my way.</p>
   <p>To returne whence I haue digressed. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> the Father and Author of <hi>Physicke,</hi> the true paterne of ingenuity, put that for one clause in the Oath which himselfe solemnly tooke, and which he would haue all Physitians take, that they should not cut any man for the Stone, but leaue that worke for them that accustome themselues to performe it; by that one instance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his custome, interdicting a Physitian all manuary labour as knowing he should finde worke enough to fit his minde for greater difficulties. On the other side the Chyrurgean should content himselfe with the limits of his profession and not vsurpe vppon the possession of the Physitian, which he doth (somtimes indeede for his profit) but seldome without the detriment of the patient, especially if there be any difficulty in the businesse. I do not deny, but that a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon, yea a Diuine, or Gentleman, if he lay good foundations and build therafter vpon them may be a Physitian as well and as good as the best of vs: but it is not ordinary for men of Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Trades or other professions to be so qualified: the more honour it is for them that bee. But certainly if euery man would containe himselfe within his own tether, and presse no further then he is guided by right reason and his reason warranted by experience, we should not heare of so many soloecismes and notable in congruities which are daily committed, nor some (otherwise worthy men) be marked with the blacke coale of filthy auarice, the basest and most preiudiciall vice that is incident to learned men.</p>
   <p>Neither yet do I thinke it fit, that the Physitian should be ignorant in the Chyrurgical part, but able to guide the Chyrurgeon that is not able to guide himselfe, to assist and confirme him that is, and to amend a fault when it is committed: but for the work of the hand, I take it to be more lawfull for him then expedient, more honourable to be able and not to do it, then profitable to do it though he be neuer so well able. Albeit to say the truth, the fault is more common on the Chyrurgeans part then on the Physitians; and by so much the greater, by how much the danger
<pb facs="5"/>
of not doing well is more in very many, then the disreputation or disaduantage can be to a few (and very few they be indeede of the better sort) who do all they can.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, because some men are importunately bolde aboue their skill, shall it not be thought fit that all may learne that they ought to haue skill in and is an essentiall part of their profession? Let them then learne it (saith the Physitian) as we do. As much as if he should say to his patient that is not able to helpe himselfe: There is an excellent Medicine for your malady in <hi>Galen</hi> I pray you seeke it out. It is indeede a disease in our common-wealth, that Chyrurgeons haue no better meanes to instruct themselues; but such a disease as (among the rest) i, verie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull for the Physitian. For sure I am, if they had those meanes that wee haue, they would easily (as it is in the prouerbe) wipe the fat from our beards; not only because of their nūbers, but especially because they are interessed alwaies in a part of our profession: so that if they were as wel able as willing to take vpon thē the whole, we should be faine either to conuert our studyes some other way, or feed vpon their leauings which would be but short Commons. If therefore you will say they meddle so much now, what will they not vndertake when they are better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided? Surely not so much: for who are those that busy themselues most in the matter of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, but such as are least able. The able and discreet Chyrurgeon when hee hath learned anie thing hath also learned the difficulty of physicke, and will bee readier to pray in aide of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Physitian, then he that runs boldly headlong without foresight of danger.</p>
   <p>Seeing therefore it is necessary Chyrurgeons should be instructed for the behoofe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, whose generall good is to be preferred before all particulars; why should we not be rather willing to instruct them our selues when we may holde them within the compasse of their owne Art, then driue them to seeke other helpes to our preiudice? Now then, among all the parts of our Art there is none that the Chyrurgeon hath more need of, or that is of more vse for himself then Anatomy, none that doth lesse inable him to practise physick, it being a mere Natural study, teaching him where to seek the Veine hee must open; how the ioynt should bee reposed which he findeth luxed; what parts are nere the wound which he searcheth and therefore may be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with it; which way the Fibres, Vessels and Tendous run that in his incisions he may not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late them; how to cast on his Bands to conteine a Fracture or Luxation; how to auoide the most sensible &amp; vsefull parts in Trepaning, Cauterizing, dismembring and such like: but of medicine and the cure of in ward diseases in Anatomy not a word. The inward parts are alio indeed Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, whose position at least (you will grant vnasked) it is fit the Chyrurgeon should know; else when we appoint a plaister to the Liuer he may lay it to the left side, when for the Spleen on the right. But he may be directed. That is not perpetual; Physitians are not in all places, nor al men fit to entertaine them when they are to be had. Beside, a Chyrurgeon should not alwaies bee an apprentice, but at length a Maister of his Art, fit to instruct others not alwaies standing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eede of instruction himselfe, vnlesse it be in difficulties, when I know no Physitian but will be glad of assistance. Add hereto, that al Physitians in all ages, kingdoms and free states, haue written their Anatomy and Art of Chirurgery in their mother-tongues, or afterward translated them for the vse of Chyrurgeons; which is so wel knowne that it were in vaine to make repetition of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. To come to our selues; we finde many examples of learned men and good Patriots, who haue bene willing to take great paines and to be at great Charge for this purpose.</p>
   <p>Amongst the rest D. <hi>Caw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>wel</hi> sometimes President of the Colledge of Physitians in <hi>London,</hi> first translated <hi>Moores Tables,</hi> and (a learned man though he were) was not ashamed to do that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to his country as to make himselfe, as some vnworthily and scornfully terme it, <hi>A bridge for asses to passe ouer by.</hi> He also promised <hi>Oribasius de Laqutis,</hi> which his labor seemeth to haue bene interrupted by his death or otherwise lost, to the great detriment of Chyrurgery. But for Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy he did not onely take paines in it, but was also at great cost tò cut the Figures in Brasse, which he left remaining in your hands (my Maisters of Chyrurgery) as a testimony of his great desire to further your profiting in that part. Moreouer that honorable person the Lord <hi>Lumley</hi> erected▪ Chyrurgery Lector in the Colledge of Physitians allowing liberall maintenance to a Doct. of Physick to read the same twice a weeke, partly in Latine, and pattly also in English for the vse of the Chyrurgeans, and to go ouer the whol body of Anatomy euery year a part which Lecture is not so duly followed and frequented, as it is performed at this time by D. <hi>Dauies,</hi> of whom I cannot but make worthy mention hauing receiued not onely great contentment but profit also by his learned readings. You haue also among you a laudable custome to procure a Doctor of Physick to read vnto you, and to prouide that his Lectures be duly attended by those of your society: and the Physitians. I doubt not, thinke they haue done wel in singling out a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man to instruct you. Onely your care must be, to feed vpon that rather which is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> then vpon that which is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, vpon that which is good for nourishment rather then vppon that which will delight and fill but not feed your minds: to attend the plaine-song rather then the diuision or descant, which doth oftentimes corrupt the Musick if the auditors care be not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to distinguish them. Finally, you haue Anatomies both priuate for your profiting &amp; publick for the honor &amp; reputation of your Company read in your Mothertoong. And truly me thoght it did me good to see so graue a company of gowned Chyrurgeons attending vpon it, so good order, so great a Crowne of worthy Auditors, so liberal entertainment a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it: which I do not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to flatter you, for flattery is to attribute more then desert, but partly to commend your praise-worthy care; partly if it were possible to stir vp our selues to a lawfull emulation.</p>
   <p>To returne. These many paternes, these worthy presidents first warranted me, after perswaded me to spend those houres which I might spare from my employments in these &amp; the like labors.
<pb facs="6"/>
For which as I esteeme my owne profiting to be a sufficient &amp; answerable reward, so I did &amp; do hope that my paines being communicated to others would returne vpon me with aduantage; that aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage I meane, which is most welcom to honest minds, that is, a conscience of hauing improued though but a single talent. It were in vaine to Apologize for my selfe that I haue not had that time, those op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, those meanes which are required to an exquisit Anatomist, because (it may be answered) I might then haue held my hand and giuen way vnto such as had them. There is indeed a time when a man should stand much vpon the consideration of his strength. There is also a time wherin it is lesse dishonor to want power then will, ability then good endeuour. He that first scales the battlements of a Casile or Citadel though his body bee not sufficient to oppose against a whole squadron, yet if hee win the wall and make way for the victor, deserues a Murall Crown. Whilst other men (put case) more able, haue looked on &amp; pittied themselues, I haue giuen the onset, with courage enough if not too much, <hi>&amp; viui peruenimus;</hi> but with what dextery is in you to iudge. Many obiections are made against me. First, that being a professed Scholler I should haue written in Latine. That indeed had bene easier for me by far, hauing the words made to my hands, the passages chalked out, and plenty of Authors to haue gleaned from and a litle latine, such as it is to haue varied my discourse: but it had bin most ydle, my purpose being to better them who do not so wel vnderstand that language. I shold, said another, haue made an Anatomy of my owne. Such Guls little know what it is to write an Anatomy; thittie yea forty yeares practise (which are more then the daies of my life) in dissection, and a hundred bodies more or lesse, small and great euery yeare, hath bin thought little enough to make an Anatomist fit to teach this learned age; for which I dare boldly say, no man amongst vs that knowes himselfe can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme himselfe sufficient, because we want those meanes which other Countries affoord their profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors. Another closeth more cunningly with me, <hi>Surely it is well done if it were well to do it.</hi> Such limited and reserued commendations I disavow: my reason is, because whilst they commend the beautie of the wall they vndermine and demolish the foundation. My counsell and end that by my right I require should be approued, my performance not so: what reater tort or wrong can there be, then to take a man by the beard with the one hand to kisse him, and to smite him vnder the fift rib with the other &amp; spil his bowels vpon the earth. The Figures are obscoene as <hi>Aretines.</hi> A shamelesse accusation; for they are no other then those of <hi>Vessalius, Plantinus, Platerus, Laurentius, Valuerdus, Bauhinus,</hi> and the rest; no other then those which were among our selues dedicated to three famous Princes, the last a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Queene. For my adding the History of the partes of Generation, I haue already giuen account, partly to his Maiesty, partly in my Prefaces to the fourth and fift bookes. To leaue these men to their contradictory and detracting spirits, I returne vnto my selfe. My present worke is for the most part out of <hi>Bauhine</hi> for the History, Figures, and the seuerall Authors quoted in his Margents. The Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies are mostwhatout of <hi>Laurentius,</hi> with some additions, substractions and alterations as I thought fit and my wit would serue. The Method I haue altered throughout, transported the Tables as seemed best vnto me, reuised and made choise of the quotations in <hi>Bauhine,</hi> and interposed them in their owne places. I also added Praefaces to euery booke conteining the argument and purport thereof: &amp; in the subsequent discourse many passages partly out of my owne obseruations, partly as I met with them in approued authors. The streame and current of <hi>Bauhines</hi> discourse because it is very hard, intricate, and full of long continued sentences, I haue broken off and parted as it might best be vnderstoode, which was one thing that made the volume to swell. The words of Art mostwhat I haue kept that you might not be vnacquainted with them, yet haue I also rendred them as well as I could into our language.</p>
   <p>The first booke is almost wholy out of <hi>Laurentius</hi> sauing for some passages, so is the fift, and had not the bulke of the volume growne too great, and so too chargeable to the Printer, I intended beside these thirteene Bookes; one of the Dissecting of Liuing Creatures; another of those things which happen rarely in Anatomy: a third of the method of Anatomy, the grounds whereof I had from that excellent and oculate Anatomist <hi>Petrus Pauius</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> my Maister and moderator in Anatomy, intreating of the choise and preparation of the bodye to be Dissected, of the Complements and endowments required in an Anatomist, of the place fit to make Disse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in, the manuarie Instruments named onelie in the first booke; the manner and order of dissection; how the parts do arise, where to finde them, and againe to repose them in their owne places before they be offered to the spectators and Auditors, and finally howe to prepare and compose the Scheleton; all which you may haply light vpon hereafter. Heere you haue the worke perfected, not onely as <hi>Bauhine</hi> hath it in three Venters &amp; the Ioynts, but also after those, the kinds of Flesh, Simple, musculous, with the exact story of the Muscles thoroughout the whole bodie, the flesh of the Bowels and the Glandules. In the next place, the Vessels, Veines, Artcries and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, with their diuarications and divisions from their originals euen to the extreme parts. Then the Membranes Ligaments, Gristles and Fibres. And lastly, that cragged and rockie treatise of the Bones. In all which I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Natures and Definitions of euery particular and the explications of them: their differences and divisions with their Vses and Actions; all which are omitted by <hi>Bauhine</hi> in his Theater, but supplyed by me, partly out of <hi>Laurentus,</hi> partly out of those Dictates I gathered from <hi>Petrus Pauius</hi> before named. Finally, betwixt the 7 booke which contained the history of the vpper Venter that is the Head, and the ninth of the loyntes, I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposed a Booke of the Senses, collected out of <hi>Bauhine, Laurentius,</hi> and <hi>Iulius Casserius Placentinus,</hi> who wrote ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry accurately of that subiect, many of whose disputations I haue also added. One thing I craue pardon for aboue all the rest and that is <hi>Placentinus</hi> his Praeface before the Controversies of the eight booke, which indeede was not done by me, &amp; the matter it selfe, to say truth, I do not so well like. Again, although I revised the Presse, or rather the sheets &amp; proofes, as they call them, my selfe; yet being sometimes out of Towne about my practise, &amp; oftner though in towne yet necessarily called away from attending the correction, many literall faults haue escaped, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially in the Greeke, and some more then literall, yet few such as will stumble the Reader, and fewer, it may be, then could be imagined should escape a worke of such vncouth argument to the Compositors, and written besides in a Schollers running hand. Thus much I thought good to advertise you of, my kinde and VVorshipful Friends, and so to commend my labor to your good acceptance and your honest endeavors and studyes in this and other parts of your Art to Gods blessing.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my house in S. Annes Lane,</hi>
         <date>this last of May, 1615.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>By your Louing Friend
HELKIAH CROOKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>