<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107626_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68249</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14395</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107626</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>His Maiesties speech to both the houses of Parliament : in his Highnesse great chamber at Whitehall, the day of the adiournement of the last session, which was the last day of March 1607</title>
                 <author>England and Wales, Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing receiued (gentle Reader) diuers and different Copies of his Maiesties Speech to this last Session of Parliament in Whitehall, at their recession in the Passion weeke; my labour hath bene to conferre all these copies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with the helpe of some gentlemen that were auditors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to make such an extraction as J here present vnto thee. Which though J dare not maintaine to bee a true and full relation of all his Maiestie spake, as beeing farre
<pb facs="3"/>short both of the life of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties eloquent phrases, and fulnesse of the matter: yet seeing (as I hope) it conteines most of the substantiall reasons and Arguments that therein were vttered, and that it is a thing desired by so many, though not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related by any, J haue taken the boldnesse to present it vnto thee, such as it is, being the rather at mine owne suite permitted to Print it, for es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing the wrong that might be done vnto thee, by the publishing of so many false copies that begin already to be spread thereof. And thus hoping of thy kinde acceptance of this my well meant labour, J bid thee farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>