<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title> To the most noble Translatour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107359_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6385</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107359</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title> To the most noble Translatour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The reply of the most illustrious Cardinall of Perron, to the ansvveare of the most excellent King of Great Britaine the first tome. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Du Perron, Jacques Davy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bogard, Martin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 262, 261-295, 294-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_translator">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> To the most noble Translatour.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>I Would commend your labours and I finde</l>
      <l>That they were finis'd with such ease of minde</l>
      <l>As in some sence the praise I giue must fall</l>
      <l>Vnder the title of Mechanicall,</l>
      <l>When those who reade it come to vnderstand,</l>
      <l>The paines you tooke were onely of your hand</l>
      <l>Which though it did in swiftnesse ouergoe</l>
      <l>All other thoughts yet to your owne was slow.</l>
      <l>As the Sunne Beames no sooner do appeare</l>
      <l>But they make that which stands in their light cleere</l>
      <l>Your bright soule did but once reflect vpon</l>
      <l>This curious peece, and it was cleard', and done.</l>
      <l>But that a Woemans hand alone should raise</l>
      <l>So vast a monument in thirty dayes</l>
      <l>Breeds enuie and amazement in our sex</l>
      <l>Of which the most ore weening witts might vex</l>
      <l>Themselues thrice so much time and with farre lesse</l>
      <l>Grace to their Workmanshipp or true successe.</l>
      <l>Why should I not speak truth without offence?</l>
      <l>Behold this Mirrhor of French Eloquence,</l>
      <l>Which shee before the English view doth place</l>
      <l>Fill'd with the whole Originall truth and grace</l>
      <l>That the most curious Author would auow</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> were his owne well pleas'd, if hee liu'd now</l>
      <l>And though you know this where to weack a frame</l>
      <l>To rayse vp higher the greatnesse of your name</l>
      <l>Which must from your owne rich inuentions grow,</l>
      <l>As Riuers from the springs whence they first flow:</l>
      <l>Yet bee who truly knowes your noblest will</l>
      <l>To profitt others and your various skill</l>
      <l>In choseing and in marking cut the wayes</l>
      <l>May thinck this might add something to your praise</l>
      <l>As hee who coppying a rare Picture, shall</l>
      <l>Equall, if not exceede, the Originall,</l>
      <l>By many shalbee held in as high fame</l>
      <l>As was the first inuentour of the same.</l>
      <l>Nor can your worke bee any whit disgrac't</l>
      <l>By those who think it done with too much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>;</l>
      <l>For had it beene in Michaell Angells power</l>
      <l>To perfect his great iudgment in one hower,</l>
      <l>Hee who for that should valew it the lesse,</l>
      <l>His owne weake iudgment would therein expresse,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>And though wee in a common Prouerb fay,</l>
      <l>That Rome was not built all vp in one day:</l>
      <l>Yet could wee see a Citty great as Rome</l>
      <l>In all her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in one minute come</l>
      <l>To such perfection, wee might more expresse.</l>
      <l>Our wonders, and not make the glory lesse.</l>
      <l>So I conclude with modest truth, and dare</l>
      <l>All their free Censures who can but compare</l>
      <l>And whosoere shall try may spend his Age</l>
      <l>Ere in your whole work hee shall mend one Page.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>