<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Newton to the Freendly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107134_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17156</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4034</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107134</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Newton to the Freendly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bulleins bulwarke of defence : against all sicknesse, soarenesse, and vvoundes that doe dayly assaulte mankinde: which bulwarke is kept with Hilarius the gardener, &amp; Health the phisicion, with the chirurgian, to helpe the wounded souldiours. Gathered and practised from the most worthy learned, both olde and new: to the great comfort of mankinde: by VVilliam Bullein, Doctor of Phisicke. 1562</title>
                 <author>Bullein, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 85, 9, 46, 2, 43, 9, 33, 2 leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Thomas Newton to the Freendly Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ue proofe doth shewe, so doth Experience teach</l>
      <l>That handcraftsmen (when Sūne is gone to glade)</l>
      <l>If slender light theyr weary Eyes empeach,</l>
      <l>Or hindre them, in that theyr toyling trade,</l>
      <l>(For that theyr sight is dimme with darknesse made)</l>
      <l>Of custome vse to couet open Ayre,</l>
      <l>And bryng theyr woorke into more lightsome layre.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Mynde of Man in Bodies Pryson kept</l>
      <l>Is pressed downe, and fetired lyes full fast▪</l>
      <l>All rest, all case, all Ioy is from it swept,</l>
      <l>Unlesse it bee reuiu'de wyth souereygne tast</l>
      <l>Of sacred Lore, or worthy Woork<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s forepast:</l>
      <l>By which one meane, it bayles it selfe from Gyeues,</l>
      <l>And (mauger Spight) with comfort great suruiues.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This worke thus pend by Bulleins busie brayne,</l>
      <l>With trauayle, toyle, expence, and mickle charge</l>
      <l>(Which prooues &amp; shewes how glad he was &amp; fayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>To help ech sorte, and set his Minde at large:</l>
      <l>As one (saunce f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>are) by help of Palias (Targe)</l>
      <l>Hee franckly heere vnto the learned Crew</l>
      <l>Beequeathes and giues with frendly eye to vew.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>It was at first but roughly hewen out</l>
      <l>Himselfe that tyme in Prison fast detayned,</l>
      <l>No maruaile thē, though scapes &amp; faults did sprout,</l>
      <l>Syth hee the while from liberty was wayned:</l>
      <l>Yet his goodwill, his skill, and loue vnfayned</l>
      <l>Hee kept not backe, but offred it to all,</l>
      <l>In hope thereby to pleasure great and small.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If God on hygh had lent him longer dayes</l>
      <l>Hee would the same haue repecus'd agayne</l>
      <l>And brought in frame, as mountayne Beare astates</l>
      <l>Wyth licking Tōgue, hir whelpes in shope to traine:</l>
      <l>But gone hee is, with Christ aboue to raygne:</l>
      <l>Hee playnly spake, hee playnely wrate also,</l>
      <l>His Lyte, and Speache did both together goe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>His pleasaunt Pen, his mery Minde, and Wit</l>
      <l>Did most men please, yea all of iudgment found:</l>
      <l>Tride truth hee tolde, and nayle on head hee hit:</l>
      <l>Examples stoare in all his Bookes are found.</l>
      <l>Whose sappe and fruict doth to ech sexe redound.</l>
      <l>Blinde Empiricke, ne Doggeleach could he brooke,</l>
      <l>No cosening Mate, no popishe Clawback<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s looke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>In lieu of paynes thus taken for thy sake,</l>
      <l>Afoorde him thankes, and good report withall:</l>
      <l>Of Ashes his so mayste thou some awake,</l>
      <l>As prest as hee, t'assist thee in thy thral.</l>
      <l>Few faultes (I trust) and they but very small</l>
      <l>Are left beehinde: God graunt to thee, and mee</l>
      <l>(Good Reader) grace our faultes, &amp; sinnes to flee.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <date>1579.</date>
      <signed>Thomas Newtonus, Cestreshyrius.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Ad adyta virtuti aditus.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>