<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ERRATA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107677_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18071</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107677</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ERRATA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The preachers trauels : Wherein is set downe a true iournall to the confines of the East Indies, through the great countreyes of Syria, Mesopotamia, Armenia, Media, Hircania and Parthia. With the authors returne by the way of Persia, Susiana, Assiria, Chaldæa, and Arabia. Containing a full suruew of the knigdom [sic] of Persia: and in what termes the Persian stands with the Great Turke at this day: also a true relation of Sir Anthonie Sherleys entertainment there: and the estate that his brother, M. Robert Sherley liued in after his departure for Christendome. With the description of a port in the Persian gulf, commodious for our East Indian merchants; and a briefe rehearsall of some grosse absudities [sic] in the Turkish Alcoran. Penned by I.C. sometimes student in Magdalen Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Cartwright, John, of Magdalen College, Oxford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 107, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>ERRATA.</head>
   <p>PAg. 6. l. 26. read corn and. p. 10. l. 32. read Mildenal. p. 25. l. 26. r. Maidin on an house. p. 25. l. 31. r. then for. pa. 28. l. 26. r. funera. p. 30. l. 26. r. Ararat. p. 37. l. 5. r. as. p. 38. li. 21. r. was. p. 50. l. 22. r. street. l. 25. r. street. p. 63. l. 35. r. was. p. 65. l. 5. r. inexorable. p. 68. l. 25. d. one. p. 73. l. 8. r. firre p. 75. li. 24. r. is this. p. 84. l. 1. r. Siras. l. 2. d city. p. 85. l. 14. r. antique.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>