<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>I. WEBBE, D. OF PHYS: TO HIS MVCH ESTEEMED Friend, FRA: L. Esquire.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107976_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18843</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5305</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107976</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>I. WEBBE, D. OF PHYS: TO HIS MVCH ESTEEMED Friend, FRA: L. Esquire.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The familiar epistles of M.T. Cicero Englished and conferred with the: French Italian and other translations</title>
                 <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 919, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>I. WEBBE, D. OF PHYS: TO HIS MVCH ESTEEMED Friend, FRA: L. <hi>Esquire.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our in-bred loue of knowledge, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualiz'd with able industrie; and your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause, and furtherance of a publicke benefit, brought vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted.
<pb facs="5"/>
In that an office free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done to any peculiar person, is very laudable; but exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it selfe to an vniuersality; obliegeth, and vniteth all men. For, as the mutuall participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of particulars, and their vse, and faculties in a body naturall: So breedeth it, a louing harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and perpetuity, in that which is politicall: harmony of minds, through vniting courtesies; perpetuitie of being so, by an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate acceptance, and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgement. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, there is not onely an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of fauours, out of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of fortune: but from th'elaborated experience also, of such as are not enuious, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth a willing demonstration of all, either infused, or acquired sciences; euer binding, by reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated offices, the receiuer to a
<pb facs="5"/>
new addition of thankefulnesse, and the giuer to parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ipate through a former deseruing gratitude. And this was the mayne occasion that I, (true friend) breaking the ice of my long concealed blessings, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, laid open to your view those christall, and abounding fountaines, which, who so tast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, so instantly be-deweth his vnderstanding, with so recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Balsamum, that it spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the coldest Winter, and is euer fruitfull. This powerfull and celestiall water, is (as you beheld) enuironed with a guard of auncient Authors, of the most admired perfection in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions; and such, as from the riches of their wisedomes, haue left rules, precepts, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; as legacies, regalities, and prerogatiues; by which all after-ages,
<pb facs="6"/>
conditions of men, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; haue beene, and must be instituted, maintain'd, and gouerned. All these, though they bewray'd a willingnesse, to embrace you, and graunt you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse vnto that fountaine: yet through an auncient familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, begunne in childhood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your selfe, and <hi>Cicero,</hi> which was one of them, you sought this courtesie rather from him, and hee gaue rather way thereto, then any other. And as he was euer of an affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble disposition, &amp; had beene well read in the conditions of all men, and, delighted to be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, by the most illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnderstandings; hee so ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted your inclination, that, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me from clensing, (as my custome is) and purifying that fountaine, he requested me, in
<pb facs="6"/>
token of his affection, to present you with one volume of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles. I ask't him which? Hee answered; the Familiar. In what Language? English. Whereat I blush't, and smiled. Hee gathering, mine inward thoughts by mine outward car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, sayd; Blush not to bee made a Translator of so ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Bookes as mine Epistles; In that, things the more ordinarie they are; argue the more vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall acceptance: and besides, men of greater shew, haue held their translations of lesser mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for their greatest orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: But blush to thinke that <hi>Cicero,</hi> whose letters bewray his conuersation, and whose conuersation was with Consuls, Kings, Imperator's, Praetors, Quaestors, Tribunes, Generals, and friends of his owne ranke,
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Caesar, Pompeius, Lepidus, Antonius, Brutus, Cassius, Cato, Plancus, Lentulus, Deiotarus, Octauianus,</hi> and such great Potentates; and at that time when all the world was subiect vnto one domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and himselfe in it a chiefe Commander; I say blush, to conceyte that he, should reduce such Epistles into Volumes, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for little ones. And wrong not thine owne iudgement so farre, as to imagine, that euery man of thy Nation, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, which is desirous, and worthy to read mine Epistles, is able to vnderstand them in their originall: goe on then; for those that ruled all men haue beene rul'd by me; be thou then ruled; and goe on. When I heard this, my shamefull blush was turned to a daring bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;
<pb facs="7"/>
which made mee replie, Commaund: but, thou art the whole worlds greatest Orator; and I, when these are ended, shall be but a young Translator; Let me bring thee a <hi>Sydney,</hi> a <hi>Great L: Chancellor,</hi> or a <hi>Sandys</hi>; that can parallel thy Latine, with our English Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. No, sayd mine Author; they haue done; doe thou. With that, I asked him, how? Hast thou forgotten, sayd hee, that, <hi>Epistolas quotidianis verbis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>exere solemus</hi>? Here I grew silent: but not so silent, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous; For, hence came these Epistles. Neither did I forget a French <hi>Doletus,</hi> and <hi>Italie's Manutius,</hi> who had dared as much, and were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded. But when I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most at an end, and met with, <hi>aliter scribimus, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>os so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los
<pb facs="8"/>
quibus mittimus, aliter quod multos lecturos puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> I was absolutely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to commend my former labours, to the secretest of all friends, a fire. But you, at that very instant, sent by destinie, repriued them: and requested my patience once more to reade them, and returne you them. 'Tis done, and by these you shall receiue them. Send backe your censure; and Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>