<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fetherstone, Christopher</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107245_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17676</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4429</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107245</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fetherstone, Christopher</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An abridgement of the Institution of Christian religion written by M. Ihon Caluin. VVherein briefe and sound aunsvveres to the obiections of the aduersaries are set dovvne. By VVilliam Lawne minister of the word of God. Faithfullie translated out of Latine into English by Christopher Fetherstone minister of the word of God</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 398, 30 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>CHristian reader, it is a common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe that manie handes make light vvorke. But I haue had experience in this vvorke, that many hands haue made long vvorke, or rather no vvorke. This booke at the first publishing thereof, for more expedition vvas deliuered to foure to be translated. In vvhose hands it hath lyen dispersed, partly done, partly vndone, for the space almost of these three yeares. VVherby the publishing therof hath ben hindred. At length I vvas requested to take in hand the trāslating of the vvhole vvorke, vvhich through Gods mercifull assistance I haue accomplished, going in truth through the vvhole vvorke, except that vvhich I my selfe before had done. vvhich I make knovvne (gentle Reader) not as hunting after praise, but to let thee vnderstād that I haue not published other mens doinges vnder mine ovvne name, but mine ovvne labours, as touching the
<pb facs="3"/>
translation. And for thy more ease in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this vvorke, and for the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding thereof, I thought good to note thus much, that vvhere in reading thou shalt find this marke (*) it directeth thee vnto the margēt, shevving vvhere thou maist read that more largely, vvhich is there brieflie noted. Againe vvhere thou shalt find, Obiect. it signifieth an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, vvhereby the matter in hande is contraried by the aduersarie, vvhere An. it signifieth an ansvver to the same obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. VVhich thinges I thought good to note for thy greater ease. And thus besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching God to blesse thee in reading these my labours, I conclude.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy brother in Christ Christopher Fetherstone.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>