<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107359_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6385</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107359</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The reply of the most illustrious Cardinall of Perron, to the ansvveare of the most excellent King of Great Britaine the first tome. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Du Perron, Jacques Davy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bogard, Martin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 262, 261-295, 294-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>THOV shalt heere receiue a <hi>Translation</hi> welintended, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein the <hi>Translator</hi> could haue noe other end, but to informe thee aright. To looke for glorie from Translation, is beneath my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if I had aimed at that, I would not haue chosen so late a writer, but heere I sawe stored vp, as much of antiquitie, as would most fitlie serue for this purpose. I desire to haue noe more guest at of me, but that I am a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique,</hi> and a Woman: the first serues for mine honor, and the second, for my excuse, since if the worke be but meanely done, it is noe wonder, for my Sexe can raise noe great expectation of anie thing that shall come from me: yet were it a great follie in me, if I would expose to the view of the world, a worke of this kinde, except I iudged it, to want nothing fitt, for a <hi>Translation.</hi> Therefore I will confesse, I thinke it well done, and so had I confest sufficientlie in printing it: if it gaine noe applause, hee that writt it faire, hath lost more labour then I haue done, for I dare auouch, it hath bene fower times as long in transcribing, as it was in translating. I will not make vse of that worne-out forme of saying, I printed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> against my will, mooued by the importunitie of Friends: I was mooued to it by my beleefe, that it might make those English that vnderstand not French, whereof there are maine, euen in our vniuersities, reade <hi>Perron;</hi> And when that is done, I haue my End, therest I leaue to Gods pleasure.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>