<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107078_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17384</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4211</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary: or, sermons vpon the second chapter of the first epistle of Saint Peter : vvherein method, sense, doctrine, and vse, is, with great variety of matter, profitably handled; and sundry heads of diuinity largely discussed. By Nicholas Byfield, late preacher of God's Word at Isle-worth in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 922, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any and great are the means which the Lord hath beene pleased, since this latter Spring of the Gospell (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne aboue an hundred yeeres agoe) to afford vnto his Church, for opening of the mysteries of the Gospell. Neuer since the Apostles times were the Scriptures more truly interpreted, more fully expounded, more distinctly diuided, or more powerfully pressed, then in our Times. The number of those who haue taken good paine in this kinde, is not small. Wee may well put into the Catalogue of them, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this <hi>Commentary vpon the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter of the first Epistle of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Master <hi>Nicholas Byfield</hi> by name; who continued, for the space of twenty yeeres, to take more then ordinary paines in the work of the Lord. Hee had a singular gift in diuing
<pb facs="5"/>
into the depth of those points which he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to handle. As the many other Treatises which in his life time he published, doe verifie as much; so, in particular, this <hi>Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> here commended vnto thee. In it thou shalt find, besides the Grammatical exposition, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical resolution, and Theological obseruations, many diuine points copiously handled by way of Common-place; which hath made the booke to arise vnto that bignesse that it hath. In this manner of handling the holy Scriptures, hee hath not gone alone. Many of the main Pillars of the reformed Churches haue beaten out a path before him; as, <hi>Martin Bucer, Peter Martyr, Musculus, Zanchius, Lauater, Perkins,</hi> and sundry others. The large vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of <hi>Peter Martyrs Common-places,</hi> was gathered out of his <hi>Commentaries</hi> on the holy Scriptures. The Church of God hath reaped much good by such copious and distinct handling of heads of Diuinity. Their labours therefore, who take paines therein, are not to bee concealed from the Church. If it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Lord to haue continued the life, liberty and ability of this his Seruant longer vnto his Church, he had (questionlesse) gon on further in this course which hee so well began: and so
<pb facs="5"/>
might wee haue had by his paines as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat a <hi>Commentarie</hi> on the two Epistles of <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> as we haue vpon the Epistle of <hi>Saint Paul</hi> to the <hi>Colossians,</hi> published by this <hi>Author.</hi> In his life-time he entred vpon the third Chapter, and went thorow a good part thereof: all which is fairely copied out, and prepared for the presse. But there is so much matter in that which remaineth, as it will make a competent Treatise by it selfe. This I make knowne, not that thou shouldst let this Book alone, till the other be published: for, when it is published, it cannot bee bound vp with this in one volume, by reason of the bignes of both of them. As care hath been had to print this <hi>Commentary</hi> on the second Chapter, euery way answerable to the former on the first Chapter: so like care shall be had of printing that which remains, answerable to them both; that so you may haue all the labors of this faithfull and painfull Minister of Gods Word, on this part of Scripture, in three euen volumes: which is in a manner as good, as if they were all in one volume. They may, for their matter, be well distinguished into seueral volumes: for, though one continued Scripture be handled in them all, yet the points in euery
<pb facs="6"/>
of them are different. In this respect, there is an <hi>Alphabeticall Index</hi> in the latter end, that by the help of it, you may the more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde out such points as you most desire to reade.</p>
   <p>If the <hi>Author</hi> bee of force to commend a Work the more, this Work may receiue no small commendation from the <hi>Author</hi> of it: for, hee was a man of a profound iudgement, strong memory, sharp wit, quick inuention, and vnwearied industry. He was in his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery very powerful, and that vnto all turns, as we speak. When he had to doo with tender and troubled consciences, he was a <hi>Barnabas,</hi> a sonne of comfort: but when hee had to doo with impudent and obstinate sinners, hee could make his face hard and strong, and shew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self like to <hi>Boanerges,</hi> the sonnes of thunder. Graue, sober, and temperate he was in his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; and yet, with his intire familiar friend, he could be modestly pleasant. God gaue him a great measure of patience; and hee had in his very body that which tried his patience: for, it appears, that he carried a torturing stone in his bladder fifteen yeers together, and vpward. I haue heard it credibly reported, that fifteen yeers before his death, he was by a skilfull Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion
<pb facs="6"/>
searched; and that, vpon that search, there was a stone found to bee in his bladder: whereupon hee vsed such meanes as were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed to him for his ease, and found such help thereby, as he thought, that either the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which searcht him, was deceiued; or that the meanes which hee vsed, had dissolued the stone. But time, which manifesteth all things, shewed, that neither his Chirurgion was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor yet his stone dissolued: for, it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to growe bigger and bigger, till at length it came to bee of an incredible greatnes. After his death hee was opened, and the stone taken out; and being weighed, found to be <hi>33</hi> ounces and more in waight; and in measure about the edge, fifteen inches and a halfe; about the length, aboue <hi>13</hi> inches; about the breadth, almost thirteen inches: it was of a solid sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; to look vpon, like to a flint. There are many eie-witnesses besides my self, who can iustifie the truth heerof. A wonderfull work of God it was, that he should bee able to carry such a stone in his bladder, and withall to doo the things which he did. He was a close Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, witnes the many Treatises which time after time he published in print. He was also a diligent Preacher; for, constantly hee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb facs="7"/>
twice on the Lords Daies: and in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, when many of the Gentry and City came to his Parish at <hi>Isle-worth,</hi> and dwelt there, he spent an houre on Wednesday, and another on Friday, week after week, in expounding the Scripture in his Church: very seldome was he hindred by the forementioned stone in his blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. This course he kept till about fiue weeks before his death; when the paine came so vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently vpon him, as it wasted his vitall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, yet did it no way weaken his faith: but, as the outward perished; so was the inward man renewed in him. He earnestly praid, that the extremity of the pain might not make him vtter or doo any thing vnbeseeming his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and profession: but withall, he aduised his friends to consider, that he was but as other men; and thereupon to iudge charitably of his carriage in that case. Many heauenly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions issued from him in that time of his visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, vnto the last period thereof. Quietly, meekly, and patiently he endured; till that su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest Chirurgion of all, Death, had eased him of all his pain. In his soule he euer liueth: and in his name he will continue to liue so long as the Church enioyeth his Works, more lasting than Marble Monuments.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>Now, O blessed Sauiour and Head of thy Church, as thou transplantest some of thy Plants out of thy Nurcery, the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; plant others, wee beseech thee, in their rooms, that thy Church may neuer be vnfurni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed of able, painfull, faithfull, and powerfull Ministers.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>WILLIAM GOVGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>