<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107710_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00791</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10910.4</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answer to a pamphlet, intituled: The Fisher catched in his owne net : In vvhich, by the vvay, is shevved, that the Protestant Church was not so visible, in al ages, as the true Church ought to be: and consequently, is not the true Church. Of which, men may learne infallible faith, necessarie to saluation. By A.C</title>
                 <author>A. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>English College Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smith, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>GEntle Reader, although I doubt not, but al that be wise and iudicious especially if they duly consider the occasion and state of the question, lately treated (in a Conference betwixt D. <hi>White</hi> and D. <hi>Featly</hi> Ministers; and M. <hi>Fisher</hi> and M. <hi>Sweet</hi> Iesuits) wil ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily discerne (euen by that false Relation, which is set out in print by a Protestant) that the Protestants Cause hath not gained any thing: Neuerthelesse, because those who be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially affected, or of meane capacitte, may (as it is to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diuers doe) conceiue and speake amisse of this matter, to the disgrace of the Catholike Cause, and the preiudice of their owne and other mens soules: I haue thought it needful to set out a true Relation of the occasion, progresse, and issue of that Conference, and this in such sort, as diuers falsehoods of the Protestant Relator, may be easily perceiued, and the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Protestants Cause may be euidently discouered; which is also so bad, as it seemeth it cannot be supported, but by setting out such lying Relations; the sight and considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, maketh me more easily beleeue that to be true which I haue read, viz. <hi>That a decree was made by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines<note place="margin">Eudaimon Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fens. p. H. Garn.</note> in Geneua, defyning it lawful to lye for the honor or credit of the Gospel;</hi> and that conformably to this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, an English Minister being told that one of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowes had made lyes in stead of proofes of his Protestant Religion, did answer, saying: <hi>He cannot lye too much in<note place="margin">D. Bishop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Rob. Abbots.</note> this cause.</hi> It must needes be a weake and bad cause, that needeth to be supported by such weake and bad shifts. I for my part wil not promise, to haue perfectly remembred and
<pb facs="3"/>
set downe euery word that passed in this Conference, especially spoken by by-standers; nor to haue strictly obserued the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise order of euerie passage: but for the substance, and truth of the matter that I doe relate, I assure, that there shal not be found any falsehood, vnlesse it be in some of those Parcels; which I doe not relate of my selfe, but out of the Protestant Relator: whose Relation ordinarily as I doe not contradict, vnlesse it be vpon necessarie occasion; so I doe not intend to approue: but simply relating what it saith, I wil leaue it to others to iudge, what they thinke fit of it. Onely this I wil say, That euerie one may beleeue it so farre, as it relateth any thing, which may aduantage the <hi>Catholique Defendants,</hi> and their Cause, or disaduantage the <hi>Protestant Disputants,</hi> and their Cause. For it is certaine, that no man wil lye for the aduantage of his Aduersarie, or his Cause; nor for his owne disaduantage. But in such things as it hath set downe aduantagiously for the <hi>Protestant Disputant,</hi> or his Cause, there is iust reason to suspect it; in regard I am told, that <hi>D. Featly</hi> himselfe (who is said to be the Author) hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, That more is said in the Relation, then was said in the Conference it selfe; and I am sure something is left out, which was said, and something mis-reported. This being premised, by way of Preface, I wil begin to discourse of the matter it selfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>