<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Pettie, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107863_Bo2_3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04626</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14747</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107863</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Pettie, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of patience in tribulation : first, preached before the Right Honourable the Countesse of Southampton in her great heauines for the death of her most worthy husband and sonne: afterward inlarged for the helpe of all that are any way afflicted crossed or troubled. By William Iones B. of D. and P. of Arraton in the Isle of Wight. Herevnto are ioyned the teares of the Isle of Wight, shed on the tombe of their most noble Captaine Henrie Earle of Southampton and the Lord Wriothesly his sonne</title>
                 <author>Jones, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>REader, beleeue me, 'tis not Gaine, nor Fame</l>
      <l>That makes me put in my neglected Name;</l>
      <l>Mong'st learned Mourners that in Sable Verse,</l>
      <l>Doe their last Honour to this dolefull Herse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor did these Lords, by liuing bountie, tie</l>
      <l>To Them, and to their Heires my Poetry:</l>
      <l>For, to speake plainly, though I am but poore;</l>
      <l>Yet neuer came I knocking to their doore:</l>
      <l>Nor euer durst my low obscuritie,</l>
      <l>Once creepe into the luster of their die.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet since I am a Christian, and suppose</l>
      <l>My selfe obliged, both with Verse and Prose;</l>
      <l>Both with my Pencills, and my Pens best Art;</l>
      <l>With eye, tongue, heart, and hand, and euery part</l>
      <l>In each right Noble well-deseruing Spirit,</l>
      <l>To honour Vertue, and commend true merit.</l>
      <l>Since first I breath'd and liu'd within the Shire,</l>
      <l>That giues a Title to this honoured Peere;</l>
      <l>Since twelue long Winters I, my little Flock</l>
      <l>Fedin that <note n="*" place="margin">At <hi>Thorley,</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Wight.</hi>
         </note> Isle that (wal'd with many a rock;</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="39" facs="22"/>
And circled with the Maine) against her shore,</l>
      <l>Hear's the proud Ocean euery day to rore;</l>
      <l>And sitting there in sun-shine of his Glory</l>
      <l>Saw his faire Vertues, read his lifes true Story.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who see's not, I haue reason to make one,</l>
      <l>In this Isle's, Churches, Countries common mone?</l>
      <l>Or thinks that in his losse I haue no part,</l>
      <l>When the whole Kingdome seems to feele the smart?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Let him that list his griefs in silence mutter,</l>
      <l>I cannot hold; my plaints I needs must vtter:</l>
      <l>I must lament, and sigh, and write, and speake,</l>
      <l>Lest while I hold my tongue, my heart should breake.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. PETTIE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>