<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A defence of master Charkes Preface to the answerer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107734_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18440</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5008</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A defence of master Charkes Preface to the answerer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answeare for the time, vnto that foule, and wicked Defence of the censure, that was giuen vpon M. Charkes booke, and Meredith Hanmers : Contayning a maintenance of the credite and persons of all those woorthie men: namely, of M. Luther, Caluin, Bucer, Beza, and the res of those godlie ministers of Gods worde, whom he, with a shamelesse penne most slanderously hath sought to deface: finished sometime sithence: and now published for the stay of the Christian reader till Maister Charkes booke come foorth</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smith, Toby</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>1, 5, 7-107, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>A defence of master Charkes Preface to the answerer.</head>
   <p>IN the first section, there are nothing but wordes, barely affirmed in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>of their readinesse, to haue their spirits proued. And this hee prooueth by their bookes extant, calling to tryall all sectaries: and heere hee maketh an hotchpotch, matching with true Ministers of<note place="margin">So doth Staphi Ius, Ficklerus &amp; the rest, to bring those that were sound &amp; godly into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Christe such heretikes as are them selues. For hee matcheth <hi>Luther,</hi> &amp; <hi>Carolostadius</hi> together, that were at great oddes: <hi>Zwinglius</hi> and <hi>Munser, Caluine,</hi> and <hi>Stancarus:</hi> and yet hee knewe well enough, that neyther <hi>Caluine</hi> nor anye of the rest, did euer agree with anye that fell to heresies, or did maintayne them. But forsooth they haue confuted them: Surely so, as wicked men are wonte
<pb n="11" facs="11"/>
with darkenesse to confute light, in them that were sounde, or to confute heresies in heretikes, themselues being the greatest heretikes that euer were: as Tinkers, who are wont when they indeuour to mend one hole to set downe another, or rather in steede of mending one to make many. O but <hi>they offer daily, and take great paines, yea they come with danger of their liues, to make trial.</hi> Indeede they proclaime defiance &amp; dare not come to the battle: for notwithstanding the cōmandement of their superiors of voluntary trial, I neuer knewe any to come in, but against their willes, to aduouche their errors. But how wil they be tried? Why forsooth, they wil be tried, by themselues, they are the Church, we<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 32</note> are heretikes, intruders, and what not? The spirits of the Prophets must <hi>be subiect to the Prophets.</hi> Nowe they are the Prophetes, to whom wee must render account of al our doinges. But Sir defender (that I may vse Hardinges owne phrase) who made you iudge in your owne cause? You begge shamefully that which is in question. For first wee say that you are no true Prophetes but false Prophetes, you vsurpe the name of the true<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>a Soto. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Church being a false, of the vniuersal (if you be any,) being but a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and therfore may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>as men, as your owne Doctors haue confessed.<note place="margin">VVittenb. cap. de concilijs.</note> Whither thē shal we goe for the trial of spirits? Surely the spirite must be<note place="margin">Alfonsus a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro aduersus Heres lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> iudged by the spirite. For whatsoeuer sauoureth of the spirite, shalbe tried by the spirite, in those that are enlightened by it, in whom the Churche consisteth, and where the spirite is. For the spirite is not without the<note place="margin">Verractus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>cap. 24. &amp;c.</note> Church, and the Church is found in the Scriptures and no where els. And therefore the Apostle saith: <hi>The spirituall man iudgeth al things.</hi> What better way can there be to finde out the spirite of error, but by the spirite<note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 15.</note> of truth: And how shal they be discerned that boast of the spirite, but by<note place="margin">August. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. de correctione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. cap. 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Epi. cap. 3.</note> the only word of God suggested by the spirite? When we offer therefore our spirites to be tried, by the rule of S. Iohn, concerning a true confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iesus Christ, <hi>first also</hi> (as the Apostle saith) <hi>beleued with the heart,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Where know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and trial is to be sought.</note>
      <hi>and then confessed with the mouth,</hi> which also hath this further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, to make vs cal vppon him, and to acknowledge him our onelie Prophete, king, &amp; Priest, derogating from him, none of his offices, but receiuing his whole worde, and bringing into knowledge his whole counsels, submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our selues vnto his will. This must needes be a plaine &amp; euident tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al which indeed the Papists could neuer abide.<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
               <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 19.</note>
   </p>
   <p>This is the cause that they shunne onely Scripture, as a terrible bugge. For if the trial should once come to that, as indeede it ought to doe, the matter would soone be at an ende. I say it ought in all matters of Religion,
<pb facs="12"/>
being necessary to the faith of a christian man, whatsoeuer they be. As for other thinges without that compasse, we refuse not such trials, as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>for them also: But he sayeth: <hi>This is a shifte common to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, suche as Maister Charke is. And the cause thereof Augustine doth testifie of the Heretikes of his time.</hi> But first he should haue prooued vs Heretikes, and then haue giuen vs that name. August. testifieth true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that al Heretikes abuse the letter of the Scriptures, as doe the Papistes, Anabaptists, Familie of loue, and such others. But is not this a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>Heretikes catche at the letter and wordes of the Scriptures, to mainteine their errors. Ergo the scriptures are not the touch stone, to try al spirits by; yea but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>are other thinges to trie the meaning of the scriptures by, &amp; what are they? Forsooth the sense of the Churche: Of what churche? Forsooth of that Synagogue of Rome, of her Doctours, of her generall councelles, and such like conspiracies, and I cannot tell what. As though the scripture written by Gods spirite, shoulde bee expounded by the spirites of men, and of such Erroneous men, as from time to time by the scriptures haue been founde to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>the sonne of God: as though there should bee vncertaintie in GOD, and certaintie in these men: Emptinesse in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>writings of the Apostles, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>in their balde and absurde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>; especially, when they haue deliuered, That <hi>the Scriptures are to be fitted to the tyme, and to be vnderstood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, so that at one time they are to be expounded, according to the vniuersal currant rite</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>or ceremonie.</hi> But if <hi>that ceremonie be changed, then the sentence is to<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. 7.</note> be changed.</hi> Againe, <hi>if the Churches iudgement be changed, why then Gods iudgemēt is also changed.</hi> Farther the scripture, <hi>as touching the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is not of the essēce of the church, which may be vtterly destroyed by</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>a Tyrant, but it is the spirit that quickeneth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Prierias, Ecki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Hogstratus</hi> holde, that the Pope alone may determine all matters of faith, and that the Pope may expounde the scripture as he wil. <hi>Habet au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem interpretandi sacram Scripturam authoritatinè pro suo sensu,</hi> Therefore, what may we hope for, concerning the Synagogue of Rome, that challengeth to be iudge ouer all, seeyng it is prooued by the practise of it, that sometime they interprete the scripture one waye, and somtime another; as afterwardes may appeare by their contradictory doctrines.</p>
   <p>But here M Defender putteth downe <hi>three causes,</hi> why <hi>these newe Teachers appeale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>to Scripture:</hi> Wee must by the way endure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>names, without anie proofe, when it is euident, that they are
<pb n="12" facs="12"/>
the newe Teachers, and we the old: teaching the same doctrine that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,<note place="margin">Our doctrine the same that the Prophets, Christ and his Apostles haue taught.</note> the Prophetes, Christ, his Apostles, and all holie Martyrs haue taught and professed, according to that worde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>the beginning of the world: and they resisting it, and persecuting it. But what are these three? Forsooth the first <hi>is to gette credite with the people.</hi> The seconde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we woulde exclude <hi>Counselles, Fathers, and Auncetours of</hi> the Churche (<hi>who from time to time, haue declared the true sense of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnto vs</hi>) that wee <hi>might haue libertie, and authoritie to make what meaning wee list,</hi> and thereby giue <hi>colour to euerie fansie wee list to teache.</hi> The thirde, because wee <hi>woulde deliuer our selues from all ordinaunces or doctrines, lefte vnto vs by the first pillers of Christe his Churche; not expressely set downe &amp;c.</hi> For the first, whether it bee a way to get credite to cleaue to the worde of GOD, with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, let them iudge that knowe howe contrarye it is to mans corruption, onelye to relye vppon it. Indeede it deserueth credite with all, when they shall see, that wee iustifie God in his woorde, and forsake our owne testimonies, and the testimonies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>and blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>who made him a God, to knowe our purpose, and to enter into<note place="margin">Papists <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>all things for the praise of men.</note> our heartes? We leaue it to all the worlde to iudge, whether they hunt not more for the prayse of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>of men, then we doe: who like proude Pharisies doe whatsoeuer they doe, to be seene of men,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> and to be praysed of them. And therefore bring the scriptures of God into captiuitie vnder men, and vnder their interpretation to flatter them withall. And so in other thinges: they fast and praye <hi>openly, at euery pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> and euery <hi>streete:</hi> they giue their almes like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; blase their vainglorious good woorkes to all men, &amp;c: which also sheweth the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of their heart.</p>
   <p>For the second, touching <hi>Councels, Fathers, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>&amp;c.</hi> Wee (indeede) exclude them from being eyther aboue, or equall with the worde of God, we make them not Iudges, though some tymes in matters of storie, to shewe the practise of the Churche, wee admitte them for witnesses. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>is, because Generall councelles haue<note place="margin">Read all the Fathers, &amp; this shalbe found true.</note> erred, and haue beene one agaynst another, one Doctour agaynst a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother and diuers tymes against them selues. The seconde Councell of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> was agaynst the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> the one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, and the other absoluing <hi>Eutiches.</hi> The second of <hi>Nice,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Councels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels.</note> that of <hi>Franckford,</hi> about images. The first of <hi>Nice,</hi> and those of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Mentz,</hi> and of <hi>Carthage,</hi> about the marriage of Ministers:
<pb facs="13"/>
Those of <hi>Constance</hi> and <hi>Basill,</hi> against those of <hi>Florence</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your holy fathers vsurped Supremacy, and so of diuers others, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Fathers and Doctors, whether you meane the former or the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Fathers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst fathers.</note> it is so also of them. For if councels gathered together in the name of God, hearing eche others reasons, and debating matters for finding out of truth, haue yet thus iarred; to the end we should not rest vpon them as iudges, but onelie vpon the Scriptures: what are wee like to finde amōgst men, yea amongst the eldest; and what then amongest the latest? If in the eldest, as in Irenae the errour of the <hi>Chiliastes:</hi> in <hi>Cyprian</hi> Anabaptisme:<note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> in <hi>Tertullian</hi> the heresie of <hi>Montanus,</hi> that there should come a new <hi>holie Ghost,</hi> a new <hi>Prophesie,</hi> also condemning <hi>seconde marriages,</hi> and<note place="margin">Reade their workes who shal: and they shal find in thē, iudging thē by the Scriptures.</note> denying it to be lawful to flie <hi>in time of persecution:</hi> In Origene in finite, which Hierom writing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>hath noted before vs, and so in all the rest, howe may wee bee iudged by them? we speake not of those that you count errours, but suche as are errours indeede both with you and vs. What shal we say then of <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Scotus,</hi> and your other schoole<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Illirie. lib. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Papist.</note> men &amp; foole men? What shal wee say of your other late writers, of your Popes, &amp; of their Canons in al times? It would fil a whole volume, to declare al their errours and dissentions.</p>
   <p>O <hi>But we cleaue to onely scripture,</hi> that <hi>we might deliuer our selues from traditions,</hi> which you call <hi>ordinaunces</hi> and <hi>doctrines of men,</hi> and<note place="margin">Traditions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, variable, vnnecessary, hurtful &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensiue.</note> surely, we haue also good cause so to do. For as they are infinite &amp; varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, so also they are impious and ridiculous, neither fitte nor possible to be kept. If any can be proued out of the word of God, as deriued from those first pillers of his Church, containing in them no impiety, nor bynding the conscience, as equall with the worde of God, but are proued necessary to order and edification, why these we receiue, and allowe, and follow thē as patterns to directe vs by. But as God and men are to be discerned, so are those traditions of God, and the traditions of men farre vnlike, and differing in authoritie <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And therefore those wicked tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, whiche you haue forged and fayned as necessary to saluation, which want both a commaundement and a promise of God, we vtterly detest them, to wit, of your sundrie sortes of masses, applied to al disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and danngers, your <hi>Vigilles, yeeres mynds,</hi> and <hi>moneths mynds,</hi> your <hi>processions,</hi> churches dedicated to Saintes, your counterfaite <hi>fastes,</hi> from<note place="margin">See their Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall, their masse booke and such other good stuffe.</note> Butter, flesh, cheese and egges: your faigned Reliques of Saintes, your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bread, and holy water, your <hi>Rosaries, blessings &amp; exorcismes,</hi> of <hi>salt, ashes, hearbes, trees, palme, leaues, flowers, oyles, flesh, grease, wine,</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="13"/>
      <hi>cheese</hi> for the <hi>health both of bodie and soule.</hi> Should we not I praye you, vpon the credite of your Synagogue, receiue all these? Is it not a good ease by cleauing to the Scriptures onely, to vnburthen and acquite our selues of all these abhominations? If you may obtayne euery deuise without Scripture, then wee must yeelde a woorshippe to the Asse vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon palme sunday, we must carrie about the Sacrament like Idolaters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>worship the bread: we must haue a <hi>Letanie</hi> of Saintes: wee muste haue your Popishe confirmation: and many iestes in it: we must haue creame and spettlein Baptisme, sensing &amp; swinging to euery idol; we must<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Catechisme.</note> haue an infinite number of <hi>Monkes, Nunnes,</hi> and <hi>Friers,</hi> and euery one tugging for his order, like caterpillers of the earth, eating vs vp &amp; deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs: and together by the eares amongst themselues for their sundrye ceremonies, kindes of seruice, and a thousand such like wickednesses. As for <hi>Martine Luthers</hi> opinion, denying seuen Sacramentes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging 3. and then properly confessing but one, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of <hi>Auspurge</hi> that followed him, teaching 3. and <hi>Melancthon</hi> 4.<note place="margin">See the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions of the Churches, that cleare vs from this slaunder.</note> and <hi>Caluine</hi> but two: and I cannot tel what: because these make nothing for the proofe of that you haue in hande: they shal receiue their answere in another place. Though men haue their sundry opinions, yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is one, and certaine: we stande not to iustifie any mans priuate and particuler opinion, but would haue al mens opinions brought to the triall of the worde of God. Wherein though men doe double many times in their knowledge, in respect of their ignorance, time and grouth, whiche maketh against you: yet the trueth is one, and hath certainely discussed, that there are but two Sacraments, which we onely follow and allow of. But for these places alleaged by you, I adde further, that you might haue considered that Luther wrote that booke <hi>De captiuitate,</hi> not the laste.<note place="margin">VVhē Luthers booke <hi>De cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitate Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</hi> was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</note> For if you had looked either into his great Catechisme, or the little one that was the abridgement of the other, you shoulde haue founde but two. As for <hi>Melancthon,</hi> who holdeth as you say 4; It appeareth you tooke them not by an euen tale. For in his last common places, where hee aunsweareth those wicked articles <hi>Báuaricae Inquisitionis,</hi> he holdeth that there are properly but two Sacramentes, howsoeuer more generally<note place="margin">King Henrie not the head of the Church as the Papistes vnderstand by head, in their Antichrist.</note> the name Sacrament, was common to moe &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Now whereas you bring in M <hi>Caluine</hi> for the title of King Henrie, calling himselfe head of the Churche, and the <hi>Magdeburgens</hi> for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that opinion stil, as M. <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> and they vnderstood it, it was, and is according to the Scripture, that none cā be head of the Churche, but
<pb facs="14"/>
Iesus Christ, who is the onely king thereof. We disclaime not one Pope, and allow another. But as God hath erected Princes, in their seueral do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, to gouerne the people committed to their charge: so wee hold, that they professing the Gospell haue a soueraigne power, and are heads of their dominions, next and immediatly vnder God, and therfore also are chiefe members of the Church, and haue to doe, as appoynted by God to see his lawes receiued and obserued, and iustice administred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest al states and persons, according to the worde of God: your can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred malice therefore, shal not prouoke that mischiefe you ayme at. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are taught of God, are wise to consideral circumstaunces, both what mooued M. Caluin so to write, and in what sense, that title for a time was retayned.</p>
   <p>As for that you write, of the opinion of burning Heretikes, and of bookes being written too or fro, it helpeth your cause little. It is enough,<note place="margin">Heretikes are to be cut off, not such as they cal Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, but suche as they are thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, who are proued to be Heretikes by Gods word. This also he handleth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes.</note> that we haue testified by our example, that Heretikes are to be put to death: and if some Anabaptist or Heretike, that woulde liue as they list, haue started out such books out of their owne dēnes, what is that to vs, seeing we haue both answeared them, &amp; are ready to aunsweare whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they or you can obiect against the truth thereof? Neyther doeth this helpe your crueltie, that put not Heretikes to death, but Christians, and such as professe the Gospel of Iesus Christ against your cursed Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
   <p>Concerning <hi>Luthers</hi> heate against those that he called Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; in regard of those other excellent giftes, that God bestowed vppon<note place="margin">Concerning Luthers heat.</note> him, for the benefite of so many: we doe easily pardon. We thanke God that crawling out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>Dunghil of Poperie, he was no more infected then he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. We doubt not, but if he had liued til these dayes of light and knowledge, he would haue had better iudgement both in that, and some other poyntes of doctrine, which hee did some what too tough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mainteyne. You haue little cause therefore to condemne our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian modestie and holye perswasion; of his and suche like brethrens sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, who though they iumpe not with vs in all thinges, yet holding the foundation, are not to be condemned, as desperate Heretikes. And as for Maister Whitgift, and M. Cartwright, howsoeuer they haue dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and striued about the gouernment of the Church, you shal finde that they both agree against your false Religion, and wicked Abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and as the Lorde shal make them wise by his woorde, they shall set them selues against euerye thing that is not according to it. But
<pb n="14" facs="14"/>
must all the differences and disagreementes of men, that professe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>worde of God, be attributed to the word of God? Is not this a fine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion?</p>
   <p>There are amongest men that professe one God, and one woorde of<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>of the Papists.</note> GOD, greate differences; some are too farre, and some are too shorte, some are wyse to discerne, and some see but a little, some haue a soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der knowledge, and some a weaker: <hi>Ergo</hi> to appeale to the Scripture onely, is an vncertaine thing. All pretende the authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Ergo</hi> all haue it, <hi>Ergo</hi> the Scripture, is a nose of waxe to serue to all purposes, because men abuse it. Muche like as if you shoulde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, the Spyder draweth matter of Venome from the Rose, therefore the Bee must sucke no honye from it.</p>
   <p>But to stay vppon Scripture onely, you say, <hi>It is to denie all Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Doctours, Councelles, histories, examples, Presidents, customes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>and prescriptions,</hi> and <hi>to make our selues Iudges ouer them. Yea, it is to denie the Bookes of Scripture them selues, and the sense,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The papistes account that a fault in vs, which they challenge them selues.</note>
      <hi>reseruing all interpretation to our selues.</hi> But what is this els, but to begge that which is in question? To charge vs with that, whiche your selues vsurpe, and put in continual practise. And howe is this to denye the bookes of Scripture: when wee staye onelie vppon the Scripture? And howe is this to denie the sense of the Scripture, when wee staye vppon that interpretation of the scripture, whiche is by scripture, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is not priuate, of, or by any man, but from the holye Ghost: And is this to denie <hi>Councelles, Fathers, Doctours, Hystories,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, &amp;c:</hi> When wee reade them, consider of them, thanke GOD for the lighte and helpes, they yeelde to vs, by these giftes God hath giuen them; yet, alwayes trying them, and all things by the onely touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, which is the scripture? Is this that Iesuiticall Logicke, that will make vp the mouth of Poperie, against whiche, no man shall dare to wagge? Surelie it is peeuishe, it is foolishe. Yea, <hi>but Catholikes though they giue soueraigntie in all thinges to it,</hi> yet they bynde <hi>them selues also to other thinges besides.</hi> Verie well, that is to saye, though the scriptures be chiefe, yet they set other thinges equall with them. And what other thinges bee they? If they bee of men: Why then it must followe, that you matche the thinges of men with GOD; you make earth equal with heauen; the wisedome of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, you couple to the wisedome of the spirite. And this is one of your chiefest Abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations:
<pb facs="15"/>
your wittes are vnhappie enough, to abuse the truth? But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, whether they haue more libertie to roaue abroade, that haue the<note place="margin">VVho vse grea ter libertie, the Papists or we, we that onelie keep our selues to the scripture or they that roue vp and downe, &amp; are boūded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no lists or boundes.</note> wyde worlde to wander in; or they that are sh ut vp in a parlar? Whether are they looser to choppe and chaunge, affirme and denie, allowe and mislike; that rest in the Scriptures or they that wil wander in euerye wildernesse of mens deuises, customes, prescriptions, and I cannot tell what? Indeede I know that the word of God, is larger then al the world, and he is at greater libertie, that is bound vnto it, then he that wandreth after men; and yet we acknowledge Gods giftes in men, and when the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>speake as the worde,</hi> we acknowledge the worde in them, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence<note place="margin">Chrisost. in Ioh. bomil. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 3. in opere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecto.</note> them for the wordes sake. But if they speake, as <hi>Chrisostome</hi> sayth: <hi>With the voyce of a stranger, then we cannot hearken vnto them.</hi> We know the voyce of Christ, but not the voyce of a stranger. And al that are Christes, doe alwayes speake in Christes voyce, and if this exception be to<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> be taken of them that are Christes: How should we except against them, that haue plainely prooued themselues to be none of Christes? You may therefore put vp your pipes, concerning those whom by <hi>supposition</hi> you cal <hi>Heretikes,</hi> but yet could neuer proue them so to be, for standing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Scripture. As for the interpretation of the Scripture, it is from the Authour of the Scripture, not from mens writings, but from the Scriptures themselues, which are not of any <hi>priuate interpretation,</hi> as<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 20.</note> the Apostle saith: Maister Charke chanteth therefore worthilie, as a good<note place="margin">2. Tim 3. 17.</note> Musition vpon this special point, treading the path of al faithful Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans before him in keeping himselfe fast to the Scriptures, and you like a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Heretike followe the pathes of your forefathers, that dare not be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that rule of righteousnesse, but followe your owne sinneful deuise, and as you are a corrupt flesh flie, so you feede vpon the corruptions and soares of men, because you loue that, which is moste agreeable to your corrupt nature.</p>
   <p>That <hi>Spirites must be tried you confesse, but that full and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>rule</hi> out <hi>of the Apostle</hi> vexeth you to the heart, and howsoeuer you raue<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.</note> at it <hi>bringing in a diuersity of interpretations,</hi> to set them at oddes with M. Charkes, as that the auncient fathers interpreted it of <hi>the Iewes:</hi> and against <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> that <hi>denied the Godhead of Christ, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>his comming in the flesh:</hi> and rather against M. <hi>Charke and his fellowes:</hi> yet it wil sit neerer your skirts, then that you can so easily remoue it. For albeit, it be nothing to the purpose, if you shoulde bring twenty diuers interpretations, of sundry, to preiudice the true meaning gathered natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="15" facs="15"/>
out of the circumstances of the text, yet what letteth that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Doctors, that it should not bee also applyed to you. For Christe is resisted by some, one way, and by some, another: As the Iewes therefore, <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> denied Christe, <hi>dissolued Iesus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Testamente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>in the annotat. vpon 1. Tim. cap. 2.</note> (that I may vse your owne worde) so doe you in truth, though you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse him with your mouthes. For of him with the Iewes you denie him, to bee a sole, sufficient, and onely Sauiour. You destroy his true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, and crucifie him continually, as they did. You stand vpon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer priuiledges, pretend a personall succession, and fathers: euen as they did when yet they crucified the Lord of glory, for which act you praise<note place="margin">Lut. Cortez in li. 3. distin. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Aquin.</note> them, and teache they had sinned deadly, if they had not done it. Euen as the <hi>Ebionites</hi> also taught, that faith was not only sufficient to saluation, but that the keeping of the lawe must bee ioyned with it: so doe you. Againe, you holde with them, that Christe was not before the<note place="margin">Iohn de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Cremata.</note> Virgin Mary. What heresie is there in the worlde, that you doe not communicate withall, in one poynt or other? I haue shewed it largely<note place="margin">Iren aus lib. 1. Epiphanius.</note> in another place, and therefore meane not no we to stand vpon it. With the <hi>Valentinians</hi> you haue deuised an infinite number of Goddes. As the <hi>Collyridians</hi> sacrificed to the virgin Mary, and worshipped her, so doe<note place="margin">August.</note> you. As the <hi>Angelists</hi> gaue diuine honour to the angels, so doe you. As <hi>Montanus</hi> deuisyd lawes for fasting and dissolued Matrimonie, so do<note place="margin">Read <hi>Tapperus Ficklerus,</hi> &amp; the whole broode of them.</note> you. As the <hi>Tatians, Eucratians,</hi> and <hi>Manichees,</hi> cryed out that mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was a carnall kinde of life, and forbade it to those that woulde bee perfect, so doe you. As the <hi>Pellagians</hi> denied concupiscence of it selfe, &amp; without consent to bee sinne, and ascribed to the naturall powers<note place="margin">This may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare through out <hi>S.</hi> August. in many places</note> strength to doe spirituall thinges: and affirmed that a man is saued by keepyng the lawe, so doe you: and it is the greatest matter handeled in this booke.</p>
   <p>Master <hi>Charkes good grace</hi> therefore in interpreting that place of Iohn, cannot bee so easily wyped away. For if Christ must bee confessed, as hee must in deede, then the controuersie is not of the confession of his name in bare wordes, and with the mouth only, but of his power, of his offices, that is to say, of his prophetship, of his kingdome, and of his<note place="margin">They that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the offices of Christ, his kingdome, priesthood, &amp; prophetshippe, they denie Christe.</note> priesthood acknowledged also from the hearte. And though all the papists in the worlde sweare, that they allowe these in Christe, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare the matter with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>flam, that they <hi>allowe Prophetes, teache kinges to raigne vnder him, and priestes to sacrifice vnder him:</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not helpe a whit to cleare them from that iust accusation. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="16"/>
is not, whether there bee Prophetes vnder Christe, Kinges and Priestes (wherein yet they shew their ignorance, seeing it is plaine, that Prophetes as they are strictly taken, suche as were before Christes comming, are nowe ceased: and also that office of Priesthood of sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing for sinne, is ceased, seeing it is done by Christe) but whether they, not resting in that which Christ teacheth alone, nor suffering that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement hee hath established by his woorde, but erecting a false head, which they will haue visible, and generall ouer the whole Churche, whiche can agree to no mortall man, and not contenting them selues with that all sufficient and onely sacrifice, but deuising another most blasphemous and iniurious to his, doe not denie Christ, in that sense, that the Apostle meaneth, to trie all false spirites by. Yea forsooth, <hi>but they allowe Prophetes vnder Christe, ergo,</hi> they rest in Christe the onely Prophete. They allowe Kinges, but they muste bee the Popes vassals: <hi>ergo,</hi> they denie not the kingdome of Christe. They allowe Priestes, that is true: more then euer Christe ordeined: <hi>ergo,</hi> they denie not Christe his Priesthood. These arguments holde thus: what is your name? A poke full of plummes.</p>
   <p>But hee <hi>taketh compassion of master Charkes interpretation.</hi> But what shoulde a man thinke of this? Doth not he, (thinke you) hye the marke as iust, as hee that neuer came neare it, when hee alleadgeth the fourth to the Ephesians, to prooue Prophetes vnder Christe, where the Apostle reckoneth vp all those officers that hee gaue to his<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> churche, for the edifiyng of his church, both those that were before and after Christe, the one temporall, and the other continuall, and yet hee findeth neither Popes nor Cardinals, nor any other of their new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>orders. Concerning kings, the beast may bee ashamed, to say, that these whome hee calleth Puritans, doe denie the office of kings. For it<note place="margin">For he meneth by Puritās not the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists &amp; spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al illuminates, but those that dutiefully seek the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church.</note> is thēselues, &amp; their wicked generatiō, that alwaies haue trampled vnder foote, that order instituted and appointed of God, haue inuaded their offices, and drawen all gouernement both from heauen and earth to that foule and insatiable monster, that man of sin and very Antichriste. These are the Misteries of Puritanisme laide open enough: And whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer such villaines belch out against Iesus Christe and his saintes, yet hee is that Prophet alone that teacheth his people by his doctrine and woord, whiche is absolute, and cannot bee either added vnto or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished from: that onely Priesthood, that hee put out of place all other Priesthoods for to establishe a kingly Priesthoode, whiche is a
<pb n="16" facs="16"/>
spirituall and an holy generation, which nowe offer not any more sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for sinne, but continuall praise for deliuerance from sinne, who is the onely heade of this kingdome, to rule it by the Scepter of his worde and to giue it all necessarie giftes and graces fitte for the beautify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, in that spirituall gouernment, whiche Papistes vnderstande not.</p>
   <p>As for <hi>his traditions,</hi> (not the traditions of Christ and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>)<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> because there can appeare no suche warrant for them out of the worde: therefore they ought not to be compared with the word: They doe impeach the doctrine of Christe and his Apostles. For howe can they stande with it when they are besides it, nay when they are contrary to it? And howe can Antichristes authoritie, which he will haue both spirituall and temporall, whereby hee iusteleth Christe, as muche as lyeth in him, out of his throne, by his lawes that are directly against the lawes of Christe, stande with the power and authoritie of Christe? Let them shewe one iote or title of euidence, if they can for their liues, out of gods holie woorde, for the maintenance of any such vsurped office, of anie suche blasphemous Priesthoode, or sacrifice founde out by the Diuell most derogatorie to that all sufficient and one onely sacrifice of Christ.<note place="margin">Heb. 10. 11. &amp;c.</note> Wee denie not that there is a sacrifice, but wee say it is such a sacrifice, as all Christians offer in that spirituall Priesthood and kingdome, which is nowe reared vp and established by Iesus Christe. And whereas hee asketh howe <hi>the traditions of Christ, and his Apostles impeach the teaching of Christe and his Apostles,</hi> I answere, that there are no traditions of Christe and his Apostles, which wee are bounde to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>and receiue, that haue not speciall warrant and euidence out of the worde of God. If they talke of traditions without the worde, whiche<note place="margin">Authoritie of the Pope vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</note> is the question, what abuses are there, or euer were, that vnder this name may not be thrust vpon the churche of God? As for the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall authoritie of the Pope vnder Christe: let him shewe by any right that euer the Pope had any suche authoritie, either spirituall or temporall, and yet hee challengeth both: can this bee any other, then a diminishing of the Kinglye power and aucthoritie of Christe?<note place="margin">The Masse an Idoll of the Popes making patched togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by many long after Christes ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</note>
   </p>
   <p>And as for the Masse it is so far off from being a sacrifice of the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that can stande with Christe his Priesthoode or sacrifice, that it was neuer instituted by Christe, but patched together by many Popes,
<pb facs="17"/>
quite contrarie to the holy Supper, which is no other sacrifice, then of thankes giuing, in steede of which, when any other is deuised by man, it is derogatorie from his, and most blasphemous, contrary to that sole, and al sufficiēt sacrifice of Christ, offred vp vpon the aulter of the crosse once<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 7. &amp;. 9</note> for al. Therefore it is more then impudencie, that he saith, <hi>that they both teach it and graunt it, but in that maner that it was done:</hi> by whiche maner, they quite marre the matter: abusing that place of <hi>Daniel</hi> chap. 12. to proue their dayly sacrifice of the Masse: and also the first of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie,</hi> which places, as they haue beene often miserably wrenched by them, so they haue receiued their answeres long agoe. The one men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth that the dayly worship shalbe remoued (whereby admit that hee meane the sacrifice of the lawe): the other, that they shall offer to him a pure and cleane sacrifice: <hi>ergo,</hi> must this needes meane the sacrifice of the Masse? And if <hi>Cyrill</hi> and other fathers cal it a sacrifice, meaning the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the newe Testament, which is offered by vs, in the blessed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body and blood of Christe, what haue they gained for their priuate Masse? For the execution whereof they institute of them selues a blasphemous priesthood, making it a peculier office, to a peculier sort of shauelings, vsing a strange language, &amp;c. most contrarie to the worde of God. Wee denie not either the priesthood or the sacrifice of praise, which is the sacrifice of the newe Testament, but as for their blasphemous priesthood and sacrifice which they appropriate to their Pope, and his greasie ones: there is not any one place of Scripture, or any one doctor 600, yeeres after Christe, that speaketh any one expresse &amp; plaine worde for it, howe soeuer they miserably racke the scripture out of ioynt to draw them to their purpose: as namely in their late Testament, applying that which is spoken of Christ, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 16. to the Pope, whiche they make the Epistle at their Masse, for the election of the Pope, reade <hi>He.</hi> 4. their annotations vpon the fift, 7. 9. 10, and 11. &amp;c. The places therefore of <hi>Theoderet</hi> and <hi>Augustine</hi> concerne not vs, but rather such wretches as your selues are, who haue ouerthrowen that true sacrifice of the new Testament in deede.</p>
   <p>Nowe, though by his owne confession he might haue made an end, and for the goodnesse of the matter, might in deede haue put vp his pipes long agoe, yet here wee haue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>onset concerning their reasonable offers of tryall, and that wee admit none. We forsooth <hi>name scripture in woordes to no purpose, seeing the controuersie is about the sense:</hi> Wherein wee (say they) <hi>admit no iudge but our selues:</hi> Wherein he saith
<pb n="17" facs="17"/>
no otherwise but thus, that for the sense wee must not goe to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but to them, who are for sooth the church, and then that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he chargeth vs, falleth flat to his owne head.</p>
   <p>Again, <hi>he is greeued that if they bring scripture, wee shift</hi> it <hi>of with some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>interpretation?</hi> Wherein we know not what hee woulde haue, vnlesse he woulde haue vs to admit whatsoeuer they bring without interpretation. But he belyeth vs, when hee saith <hi>wee shifte it of.</hi> All heretikes as themselues will alleadge the wordes of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">See there how trimly? they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>in defence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>images.</note> but they will not way the circumstances, nor admit one place to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>by another, but abuse the Scriptures, dallying with them as their forerunners did in the 7. session of that trifling <hi>Nicene</hi> councell, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>of images, to their owne destruction.</p>
   <p>Concerning that the fathers wrote in the praise of virginitie, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>denied, but they were to excessiue that wayes: wee also prayse the gift in them that haue it, and yet we derogate not from holy matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: wee dare not affirme, that to liue in matrimonie, is to liue in the<note place="margin">Syricius.</note> flesh, as some of their Popes and others haue wickedly done. The place<note place="margin">The place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>of the 19. of</note> of the 19. of Matthewe, is as yll applyed of you as may bee. For the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of Christe in that place is, to take away that offence that was obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Disciples, that if they might not put away theyr wiues, as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses had practised, then it were not good to marry. But Christe shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that all are not capable of that saying, but to whome it is specially giuen. There are in deed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>from their birth, and Eunuches made by men, and Eunuches, which for the kingdome of heauen sake, haue gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themselues, that are vnfit for mariage, and neede not that remedie either in respect of themselues, or in respect of the gist of GOD, but what maketh this against the lawfull and honourable ordinance of God, appointed to all that haue neede of it? Againe, that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, 1. <hi>Cor. 7. ver.</hi> 38. is a conclusion in respect of circumstances that went before, and not simply in it selfe. For if they haue not the gifte, whether they haue vowed or not vowed, let them marrie, <hi>It is better to marrie then to burne:</hi> your doctrine of forbidding marriage to your<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> vowed creatures, is the doctrine of Diuels. It hath beene the<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> sincke of the whole worlde, and the cause of vnspeakable abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
   <p>Reade into what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>your Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> fell, affecting this sole life: forgette not <hi>Paules</hi> young Widdowes that hee mentioneth. <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Timothie</hi> 5. Reade <hi>Epiphanius, Cyprian lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epist.</hi> 11.
<pb facs="18"/>
aniste, or an Assumptionist, shewe mee what was his order; Tell vs who they were that helde of him, or of his name and office were called Baptistes, vnlesse they were some heretike: and whether it were not safer to followe the best, I meane Christe, then Iohn: wee knowe Christe had his Disciples, and so had Iohn: but Iohn sent his Disciples to Christe, and kept none from him. And though you name <hi>Elias,</hi> Iohn <hi>Baptist &amp;c.</hi> as patrones of Monkerie: yet some attribute theyr beginning to the <hi>Essaeis,</hi> whome <hi>Philo</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>of his Countrie men the Iewes, describeth to haue beene the streightest and holiest<note place="margin">Sozomenus.</note>
      <note place="margin">So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>onius.</note> order: and some ascribe their beginning to Marke: some to one, some to another. But yet I pray you tell vs, by what authoritie you can frame vs so infinite a number since, without any father or author in the scripture, far vnlike those that in time of persecution for sauing of their liues liued in such solitarie places. For your number groweth so great, that I thinke they cannot well bee reckoned, and these latter as that pretende to followe Iesus our Lorde and Sauiour, whome they forgate all this while to make their patrone, exceede all others: and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>are but drudges in comparison of them, vnlesse these last gay A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncianistes put them out of countenance. Euery particuler com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany haue a peculiar patrone, and according to their Cities and Townes, so are their Goddes. Euerie Citie, euerie Churche, euery<note place="margin">Tutelares dei Camp. in Epist. set out by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. us.</note> vyllage, euery house, and euery man worshippeth a peculiar patrone: euen as you appointed to euerie disease, sickenesse and daunger a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Sainte, and these in necessitie must be called vpon as singuler Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours.</p>
   <p>And as your Goddes, patrones, and heades were infinite, so are your meanes to saluation diuers and variable: to wit, by woorkes of supererogation, by pardons from Rome, by Masses, almes deedes, building of Churches, putting on coules, washings, whippings, and a thousande suche trumperies. Your rules and orders, in your seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Monkeries, and fraternities, were of as great diuersitie in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ceremonies, as many, as there are colours in the raynebowe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>yet all must merite saluation: yea, and Cardinall <hi>Hosius</hi> dareth affirme, that these diuers <hi>kindes of worshippes deuised of men, are more acceptable then, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>were commaunded of GOD, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are voluntarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>doone without constrainte.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And surely as these monastical sectes are variable, so they are together by the eares one with another, about their prerogatiues, &amp; who shal exceed
<pb n="19" facs="18"/>
others in the worthinesse of merites. Doe not all the world know, how<note place="margin">In Paris a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>against Iesuits, and wheresoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they come, where other such vermine are, like vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, they gnaw out the bellies one of another.</note> the Priests and Chanons, rayle vppon you Iesuites, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>late deuised order from <hi>Layolas</hi> the souldier? And besides other thinges, doe they not complaine of you, that whilest you woulde be accounted poore, yet you lye in wayte for the wealth and riches of the whole worlde, and vnder the colour of lacking all things, you possesse all commodities what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer? And that there haue growen such a number of sectes and orders, that your Popes, and their councelles haue made canons against them, it is plaine and euident.<note place="margin">Hier. in Epist. ad Eustochiū, ad Rusticum. <hi>Concil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. Concil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>Quest. 16. sub <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
               <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
            </gap>Guliel. de sancto amore. Nicolaus de Cle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
               <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>Concerning the real presence, for which you vrge Luther against vs, with whom, yet you doe not agree, it is worthie no answeare. That spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual presence, which <hi>Ambrose, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Epiphanius,</hi> and <hi>Chrisostome,</hi> in the places by you alleadged doe mainteine, we maynteine and confes. We beleeue such a presence as is aduouched to be in all Sacramentes: we looke not to reason, nor to our senses, but to Faith: but wee may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the nature of Sacramentes, which can be no Sacraments, if there be not the signe, as well as the thing signified: The one offered to the sense, as consisting of an earthly part: the other to faith, as being the heauenlie and spiritual parte. And where as you say, that we haue found out a new<note place="margin">Real presence.</note> exposition of these words: <hi>this is my bodie,</hi> affirming that (we say) it must needes be thus construed, <hi>It is the onely signe of my bodie.</hi> We say not so. It is an impudent slaunder, and you declare of what spirite you are, when you shame not in the light of the sonne, and before al the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>to aduouch such a manifest vntruth. <hi>Amb.</hi> saith: <hi>As thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <note place="margin">An. bros hb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Sacra. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. And. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 11.</note>
      <hi>receiued the similitude of death, so doest thou in the Sacrament drinke the similitude of his blood.</hi> And againe, <hi>in eating &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>the bread &amp; Wine, we doe signifie the eating &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>of the flesh and blood, he offered for vs.</hi> And in the very place by you alleadged: <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>thou wilt say</hi> (saith he) <hi>I see no appearance of blood, no, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. de Sacra.</note> For euē <hi>as thou hast taken a similitude of his death, so thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>the similitude of his most precious blood.</hi> As for <hi>Cyrill,</hi> none is play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<note place="margin">Lib. in Iob. 4. cap. 14.</note> then he, <hi>Christ gaue</hi> (saith he) <hi>peeces of bread to his disciples, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Take yee, eate yee, this is my body Chrisostome</hi> saith: <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Table of his last holy supper for this purpose, that in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi>
      <note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 22.</note>
      <hi>he shoulde daily shew vs bread and wine, for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>of his bodie and blood.</hi> But why doe I enter into this course with you. The Doctors in infinite places, doe testifie the truth of this doctrine, that wee holde and mainteine in our Churche. If you haue any thing, it is either
<pb facs="19"/>
by clipping thē, adding vnto them or diminishing from thē. And though Luther in his time brought not onely 8. but 8. score interpretations, and your not learned <hi>Claudius de Zanctes,</hi> not 84. but 800. and 4. what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this to diminish the authoritie of the Scripture; This is your reasō, Luther in his time noted, 8. sundrie interpretations vpon these wordes, <hi>This is my body,</hi> which yet is malitiously gathered of you, and <hi>Claudius Zāctes</hi> 84. who is an impudēt Frier, &amp; therfore a liar, and althese alledge the Scriptures: therefore there is no fit trial by the scriptures.</p>
   <p>We leane not so to men, that we in their names, receiue whatsoeuer commeth from them: that is common with papistes, that if any thing be thrust vpon you in the name of any whō you like of: by &amp; by, you admit it, how corrupt soeuer it be. And though Luther had his faultes, yet wee may truely say, that he was a man enlightned by Gods spirit, &amp; conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time wherin he wrote, being but newly crawled out of the dūg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil of your corruptions, in that notable fortitude and zeale, wherin he set himselfe against Antichrist, he may in some sort be wel compared to Elias.<note place="margin">This also he mētioneth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward. where looke for further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare.</note> And in regard that he taught the trueth in the most principall matters of faith and religion, we pardon whatsoeuer he hath vttered against our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, (as I haue said before) which you set forth in the 13. &amp; 14. sections, &amp; this shalbe al the answere, I wil vouchsafe to bestowe vppon you at this time for this matter.</p>
   <p>But your conclusion of the premisses is too grosse in the 15. section, where you disfauour the controuersie betwixt vs, concerning our prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to scripture: for we prouoke to God, &amp; you to men. Wee leane not vpon any interpretation, that is priuate, but to that which is frō God, &amp; we refuse not the testimony of men, whē it is not against God.</p>
   <p>Further we <hi>shift no scriptures.</hi> For that concerning vowes, it is playne, that the prophet vnderstandeth that place of the worship of God. For as<note place="margin">Vowes.</note> they receiued benefites vnder the lawe, so they vowed according to the holie purposes of their hearts, such sacrifices as were enioyned by the law of God; &amp; what makes this for the maintenaunce of rash vowes in a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worshippe,<note place="margin">Psal. 76,</note> deuised by sinful men, who neither haue the gifte, nor power to keepe that, which they rashly promise vnto God? And therefore it is iustly so wiped away by M. Fulk. Again tha to ther place of Mat. 19. <hi>If thou wilt be perfect, goe &amp; sel al that thou hast, and giue it to the poore:</hi> who<note place="margin">Perfection in selling all.</note> seeth not that it was singuler for him, that boasted of a perfection aboue other; as also that other declareth: <hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keepe the cōmandements:</hi> &amp; though this belōg vnto all, yet our iustification is not
<pb n="20" facs="19"/>
frō the law, but frō faith, which that this yong mā might haue bin made to see he was beatē frō his hold, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> knowing his own imperfection, he might disclaime it, and rest in that perfectiō of Christ; which also vnles you Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes do (whatsoeuer you boast of a more perfectiō of life in Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thē others, &amp; therfore do as you think, more then you ought, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at least must keep the cōmandements) you cānot be saued. It is pitiful to see your blindnes, how greedily you snatch at that, which yet you cānot<note place="margin">Things spokē to singuler persons, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, &amp; not simply.</note> swallow, &amp; leaue that which is prouided for your euerlasting comforte. Whatsoeuer pertaineth to life or doctrine, is cōmon to all, to serue both for exāple &amp; instructiō, but yet many things are spokē to finguler persons in singuler respects, as the fasting of Christ 40. daies, his going vppon the water, his healing of the sicke, his raising the dead &amp;c. which yet I thinke you wil not so apply, as though al your Iesuites shold do al such things as Christ did. But I know where to haue you. For in times paste, you had some shame, but now you haue gotten harlots forheads.</p>
   <p>That also of S. Iames <hi>cap.</hi> 2. Cōcerning iustification, not by a dead faith, hath bin made plaine lōg agoe, &amp; not only that, but also that whiche you<note place="margin">The place of Iames concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> bring out of the 2 to the Rom. &amp; againe out of 1. Cor. 7. &amp; Mat. 19. where as you had touched them often. But you make no conscience to blot pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per againe &amp; againe, with one &amp; the same thing. You are like vnto flies, who though they iolte thēselues neuer so oftē against the glasse, yet they seeke stil a way to get out. We hold according to the doctrine of Iames, that he that shalbe iustified both before God &amp; mē, must haue a true &amp; a liuely faith, which we discerne by good workes as by fruits, frō that dead faith, which hath no fruits of sanctificatiō, &amp; yet we affirme still with M. Fulk, that those works that do proceed frō the fullest &amp; truest faith that is, cānot iustifie vs in thēselues before God: &amp; therfore whē Abraham is said to be iustified by works, whē he offred vp his sōne Isaack, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meaning is plain, that he was foūd a iustified mā by that worke, &amp; that was before mē, &amp; not before God, otherwise thē as faith being liuely, layeth hold vpō that righteousnes of Christ, which as the apostle saith, is <hi>neither in vs nor</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.</note>
      <hi>of vs. Him that knew no sin, he made sin for vs, that we might be made the righteousnes of God in him, not in our selues.</hi> Such a faith as is true, &amp; thus layde hold of, the righteousnes of Christ, is said to saue vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it apprehendeth Christ, and all his riches: but such a faith as Iames speaketh of, a deade faith, because it layeth no hold of Christe, cannot saue vs. So Saint Iames speaketh by a certaine <hi>Catachresis</hi> or abusion, setting downe woorkes for an effectuall fayth by woorkes: and faith, for a vayne faith; not that the beginning of Iustification.
<pb facs="20"/>
should be of faith, and the perfecting of it of our owne workes and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites. For this were to make God to beginne, and man to ende: when it is plaine, that both to wil, and to performe are onely of God, but because he is in this worke of our iustification, both the beginner and ender, to whom is due the whole glorie. As for your doctrine, it is ful of blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, robbing GOD of his glorie, when you attribute the beginning to God, and the finishing to your selues. The other place, <hi>The doers of the lawe shalbee iustified:</hi> shalbe afforded you; when you fulfil the law, you shalbe iustified by it, and then you neede not Christ. Your places of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie, and marriage are answeared before. Neither Virginitie, nor mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, in themselues can merite any thing before God; before men, they may be preferred one before another, as in some times, and cases, it maye be better for a man, if he haue the gift, to be vnmarried: In other some to be married.</p>
   <p>For Fathers also it hath beene saide before. We reuerence them, and<note place="margin">Fathers.</note> thanke God for these giftes of God in them, that may bring vs any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite or knowledge for the vnderstanding of the worde, but we bring not the spirite of God to be tried by the spirites of men, but all mens spirites to be examined and tried by the spirite of God. Where therefore they faile, it is no reason, that we should fayle with them. The woorde of God must preuayle, that hath confirmed, that amongest his Apostles, there shoulde be no superioritie, <hi>That Peter had no more prerogatiue then the rest,</hi> that that which was saide to one, was sayde to al. And though you would burst for anger, yet M. Fulke shall not be bound to euery thing aduouched by the Fathers, whereof you can bring no sounde proofe or grounde out of the Scriptures. Indeede as they were men, so many times they trifle and erre like men; and this is to teach vs, to rest not in men, nor in their opinions, farther then they rest in GOD, and vppon his worde.</p>
   <p>The same also may be sayd of our owne Writers; and therefore you doe vs the more wrong, when you call vs Lutherans, Caluinistes, Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,<note place="margin">Our owne writers.</note> and I cannot tell what? For as much as we mainteine them no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor relie vpon them, then they mainteine the truth, and stay vpon it. We confesse they were singuler and rare instrumentes of God, to whom the Lorde vouchsafed rare and excellent giftes, for the discouerie of your whoredomes, and for the buylding vp of his Church; but yet they were men, and wherein soeuer they haue erred as men, we perswade our selues we are not bounde to erre with them. That is a thing sit test for Papistes,
<pb n="21" facs="20"/>
whose Babylonical buylding, is vpon the onelie foundation of men, and not vpon Christ and his Apostles. And yet you may take your selues by the noses in this accusation, for where your owne men haue drawn neere the truth, there you disclaime them. <hi>Hic non tenetur magister &amp;c. The</hi>
      <note place="margin">Who is Caie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turene against the whole Church.</note>
      <hi>maister here was asleepe &amp;c.</hi> And why should you denie vs that priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which you chalenge your selues? Will you receiue al things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, at al times, that the doctors, old, or new, your Popes, and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers in times past, or now, haue set downe and aduouched? And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they haue set it downe, must it bee true? Indeede if you take this way, you may beginne and continue, what heresie you liste, you maye mainteine it, and defende it too, how absurd and villanous soeuer it be? But truth shal scatter errors, as the chaffe, and it shal stande and abide for<note place="margin">Disputation.</note> euer. As for disputation, for which you cal so fast, and so often, whenso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer<note place="margin">Peter Martir first: Latimer, Ridley, Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, at Oxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford in Queen Maries dayes. Maister Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot, M. Elmer, Haddon, Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and the rest that dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocatiō house. 1553. Octob. 18.</note> you come to it, you shal gaine as little by it, as your predecessours haue done, that came onely appoynted as you doe. I pray you what gate you, when you disputed with Luther at Wormes, at Ratesbone, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: when Melancthon and Bucer also were assistauntes? What gained you at Poysie in France, when Beza and Peter Martyr, were there face to face against you? What at Oxeforde, when your greatest Doctours in the matter of the Sacrament saide what they coulde for their liues in mainteining your owne corruptions: and Bucer at Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge also disputed (That I omit the disputation in the Conuocation house in the time of Queene Marie) when the swoorde was at your owne commaundement, when before the Lawe you ranne so swifte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that firste shutting out suche as you thought woulde matche you; you declared by that honest man Weston your Prolocutor, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer any might dispute, yet that the matter was alreadie concluded and<note place="margin">Reade M. Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es booke of Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in 1570. <hi>fol.</hi> 1571. <hi>fol.</hi> 1579 &amp; in manie places.</note> determined, with shame enough: when also afterwardes Latimer, Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and Cranmer, those Reuerende, Godlie, learned Fathers, (when their liues lay vpon it) disputed with you, and not onelie they, but euen handie crafts men, men, women &amp; children, in the Apologies they made at your cursed barres did so stoppe your mouths, that you had nothing to say, but to pronounce a cruell and vniust sentence of death against them. Agayne, in the beginning of the happie raigne of our Soueraigne, when your chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest<note place="margin">Conference at VVestminster anno primo Regni Eliza.</note> and best mē were called, &amp; when the time serued best, and was, if euer there were anie most fitte, your selues beeing not displaced; when you had free libertie, I pray you howe did you acquite your selues? Surely like tawle fellowes, you went awaie without giuing anie one blowe,
<pb facs="21"/>
and yet now the battel is ended, and trueth hath triumphed; out of your holes, you keepe a craking and daring of all men, and yet euermore, when you come to shew your forces, they are founde so feeble that you goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ashamed and confounded; as of late your old Doctors of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that durst not abide one poore mā. And your chiefest Champion that had challenged al, and yet being sounded, was found not so emptie of truth, as of al good learning, either in knowledge of tongues, or anie parte of your owne popish Diuinitie. For what could he say more, then other his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters had saide before him? What did hee bring, that hee had not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Melchior Canus? Canisius</hi> (which in disputation, was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly booke that he desired) or out of <hi>Belar minus dictates,</hi> which is (as it were) the onelie Treasurie of al the Papistes, and your owne good mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, which hath ministred the matter, not onelie of this booke, but of all the rest that you, or your traiterous coadiutors, haue foysted foorth, with such speede amongest vs. But where you say that we refuse it, your slander is impudent: Indeed we thinke vnmeete, after the establishment of the trueth, not that anie such boasting challenger, as Campion was, or your selfe is, or may be, should drawe vs to such an action, as though we doubted of the truth, as thogh now it were to be disputed of. We know heretikes of al times haue vsed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> like prouocatiōs, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> with as great cōfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dēce of their cause, euē such as Goliah did against Dauid: but you say we <hi>persecute, imprisō, tormēt, &amp; slaughter thē which offer the same,</hi> wher in you declare the modesty of your spirit, not accusing vs, but our whole<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. King. 17. 4</note> state, &amp; begging that which is in questiō, as thogh you were true profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, &amp; we heretiks, bicause you say so, &amp; therfore that you are persecuted; wheras indeed you are iustly imprisoned, &amp; executed for your dangerous treasōs &amp; rebellions, as were your cōplices, that <hi>were in actual rebellion</hi> against her highnes. But in so often vsing this hot charge, you might haue cooled it with remēbrāce of your sauage cruelty, that all the worlde hath<note place="margin">Reade the spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Inquisitiō, Acts &amp; monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of M. Foxe, M. Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spius historie, in French of their martyrs, and the last French history of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; grouth of the churches in Fraunce. Popish writers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>agreed yet about the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whiche are the bookes and matching their constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with Gods word.</note> wondred at, in racking &amp; roasting the true professors of Christes Gospel indeed, for only matter &amp; cause of religion, you might haue remēbred the trials you vse, &amp; the argumēts you bring against mē of our sort, whē you roast vs aliue, &amp; deuise new vnwonted tormēts worse thē euer did Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris, or the wickedest tirāt that euer liued, without any knowledge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of god let your spanish inquisitiō, your murthers in Frāce, at Rome, &amp; in other places testify the truth hereof. As for your largesse, out of the superabūdāt treasury of your possession, seeming (in your iudgement) to be the best, surest, &amp; easiest meanes, that cā be deuised, or euer were vsed for trial in the church (because you dwel by il neighbors, &amp; haue a good opinion of your selues) they are indeed nothing. For first, for the books of
<pb n="22" facs="21"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>scripture, you know not which they are; you bring in euery riff raff book, yea the beggerly constitutions of your popes, &amp; make thē equal with the scripturs, &amp; thogh you boast of thē, you wil not be ruled by thē, neither for that which is set down expresly, or for that which is set down by implication. Neither doth y<seg rend="sup">or</seg> literal acknowledgmēt stād you in steed no more thē the scribes &amp; pharisies, that had the letter, &amp; the literal vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstāding to their owne hurt &amp; dānation, but no whit of the spirite or<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 20. cap. de libellis, dist. 19. cap. in Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis. Agath. dist. 19. cap. Sic omnes.</note> spiritual meaning therof to their saluation. But is not this a fine argumēt trow you, Christ saith plainly vpon this rock wil I build my church. Mat. 16. But Peters name signifieth a rocke, therfore the church is builded vpō Peter, &amp; so vpon al the popes Peters successors, the most of thē as like Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in doctrine &amp; holines, as an apple is like an oyster. And again, <hi>he that</hi>
      <note place="margin">Read August. vpō this place, and Hierome vpon 38. of Esay.</note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>great among you, let him be as the younger.</hi> Loe, is not this a playne place, that one was greater then others, and we haue no plaine place that there is none greater? Surely if you lay so hardly to our charge, how shall we do? This is plaine geare indeed for your supremacy, so is al the rest, first for your real presēce, <hi>absolutiō, vowes,</hi> (which you bringyet again) <hi>tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiōs, cōmandemēts, works, penāce, retribution or reward, prayer for the dead, sacrifices for the dead, volūtary afflictiōs, almes, praiers of saints,</hi> &amp; such like groūded stuff, as naturally ingēdred from your alledged texts, as a lambe frō a woolf. And surely if these be your plaine textes, what are your crooked ones? Surely if you deale thus with vs after so many aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, we shal haue nothing to reply any further. For these are so playn, as you quite confoūd vs, &amp; none of our shifts cā serue. As plaine as this is: put you on the whole armour of God, that you may stād against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sleights<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> of the diuel. This armour are the priestly garmentes, signifiyng the 7. fold<note place="margin">Gathered out of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Bibles.</note> vertues, that were represēted by the 7. garments, that Christ put on, in the time of his passion, the first garment was the couering of his head: signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> the saluation which is attributed by faith. This the apostle calleth the<note place="margin">Luke 22.</note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>of saluatiō,</hi> wherby is meant also the couering wherwith y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iewes couered the face of Christ, when they strook him vpon the face and said, areed who strook thee? The 2. garmēt was that wherwith he was couered <hi>a sursū &amp; deorsū,</hi> I thinke you meane frō top to toe, which was a white garmēt, &amp; this signifieth the hope which commeth by grace from aboue: &amp; by the merits of the church from below, &amp; of this Paule speaketh. For<note place="margin">Luke 23.</note>
      <hi>you are saued through hope.</hi> This also is represented by the garmēt that<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Herode put vpon christ. The 3 garment that the priest putteth on, is the girdle whiche signifieth righteousnes, whose 2. armes clasping one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is to decline from euil, and to work good. Of this Esay muste needes
<pb facs="22"/>
speake, cap. 11. <hi>And righteousnes shalbe for the girdle of his loynes.</hi> And<note place="margin">Reed <hi>Rationale Diuinorū.</hi> Gab. Biel &amp; Vaux his Catechism and there you shall see suche misteries fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out of the scriptures, as are pitifull to heare: VVhy salte, creame, &amp; spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle are vsed, why they haue lights at noone dayes, why bels ringe not on good Friday, but they vse wodden clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and suche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>stuffe.</note> this pelte was represented by the whippe, wherewith Christe was scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Pilate <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19. The fourth garment, that the Priest put vpon, was <hi>a maniple,</hi> put on the right arme, wherby is signified the strength, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we fight against aduersities, and of this the Apostle saith: <hi>Fortitude is a vertue restrayning the assaultes of aduersitie.</hi> But where this is written I cannot tell, but this is signified by the corde, wherewith Christe was bound, when he was taken by the Iewes, as itis sayde: <hi>They tooke him and bound him.</hi> The fifth garment is the <hi>stoale</hi> of the Priest; or the <hi>orarium</hi> of the Deacon, whiche hath two hanging armes, that signifie prudence and temperaunce. And therupon the apostle saith to <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. Let vs liue soberly, iustly, and godly, in this present world. This stole represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the corde wherewith he was bound, when he was tyed to the piller and whipped. The sixth garment is the aulbe, whereby is signified chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For euen as that couereth the other garmentes, so charitie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the multitude of sinnes. And this doeth that purple garment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present, which the Souldiers put vpon Christ. <hi>Ioh. 19. They compassed him about with a purple garment.</hi> Howe say you Sir, is not heere plaine Scripture, &amp; necessary collections vpon Scriptures? Surely we might haue beatē our braines these 7 yeeres ere we could haue found out the misti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal signification of this profound geare, but we may thank good <hi>Gabriel Biel. Rationale diuinorum &amp; speculū Ecclesiae,</hi> not only for this profoūd stuffe, but for a thousād such other goodly interpretations. I am weary of wading so far into your follies. For as it is in these that I haue set downe, so is it in al the rest, which for breuities sake, &amp; because I make conscience stil to blotte paper with one and the same thing to trouble the Readers I omit.</p>
   <p>As for general Councels, which you say, you admitte and refuse none,<note place="margin">General <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> that euer antiquitie vsed for the trial of a Catholique and Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Spirite: I aunsweare, that though you sayde true, as you doe not, yet these can bee no safe wayes to trie the trueth by, for as hath beene sayde afore, these haue beene contrary one to another, and as there haue beene more then one Pope at once, so there haue beene Councelles ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their seuerall factions in those same Schismes, the moste and<note place="margin">Reade Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius ioyned with Platina, in his Epitom.</note> greatest, and of longest continuaunce in your Church, that euer were in anie Churche in the worlde. Besides that, they haue erred in greate and weightie matters, and most of all your late Chapter of Trent, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if wee had vppon your safe conduite come, wee shoulde haue
<pb n="23" facs="22"/>
had the same intertaynment, that <hi>Iohu Husse</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> had, comming to the councell of <hi>Constance,</hi> against your faith and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, which you aduouch is to bee holden or broken, as shall bee best for the commoditie of the church. And this is your receiued doctrine, that no promise is to bee kept with an heretike: and wee are (as you say) heretikes, therefore you are not bound to stande to any promise you make vs. This is not onely practised by your Pope, and his Cardinalles, but also by such popishe Princes, as stay vpon this his doctrine, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
   <p>And yet for all this great bragge it is plaine, that you admit no gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councels: but wherein they resist your errour, you resist them. As for example, you refuse the councell of <hi>Franck ford,</hi> because it determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against the worshipping of Images, that of <hi>Nice</hi> that permitted Ministers to marry: those of <hi>Constance</hi> and <hi>Basill,</hi> that subiected the Pope vnder the Church, and made him equall with other Bishops, that of <hi>Carthage</hi> also, that curseth him that calleth himselfe vniuersal Bishop, which your Pope doth, and all the rest, if there be any point maintained against your popish religion.</p>
   <p>Concerning the Doctors, which you bring againe and againe to fill vp<note place="margin">Doctors.</note> your booke, sufficient hath beene saide before. And yet wee say <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> did well in vrging <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Pelagian,</hi> with the consent of the Fathers: and so did <hi>Theodosius</hi> to hearken to <hi>Sysinninus</hi> and <hi>Nectari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> good aduise, against the <hi>Arrians.</hi> For the consent of holy fathers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing<note place="margin">Consent in the truth allowed by vs.</note> the truth against errours and heresies, is not lightly to bee estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Neither did we set light by that common iudgemente of these Orthodoxall and sounde fathers, that haue liued before vs, especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their iudgement is grounded vpon the Scriptures. But what serueth this to binde vs against the truth, for tryall of it, to bee iudged by men full of errours, and seeing that immediatly after the Apostles times, the churche was combred with many heresies? I suppose in the first foure hundred yeeres, there were not so fewe as foure hundred heresies, all disagreeing one from another, and all dissenting from the truth of God: In which time yet God raised vp many notable and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulerinstrumentes, that helde vp right the glorious profession of the Gospell, whereby they resisted these heresies and errours, and not by their owne worde, or by their owne authoritie. For how can these bee any warrant or strength of that hope which is for euer? Such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption hath notbeen founde in Gods children, but in those of your
<pb facs="23"/>
fort, who haue lifted vp your selues aboue Angels, and made your selues Iudges ouer the lawe of God.</p>
   <p>As for vniuersalitie, antiquitie, consent, &amp; succession of Popes, which<note place="margin">Vniuersalitie, antiquitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> you haue neuer done with, and bring so often, sometime as markes, and sometime as tryalles, as you doe in this place, they are nothing to the purpose. For Vniuersalitie whiche you call multitude, is rather a marke of the Diuels Synagogue, then of the Church of Christ. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 13. as for the Churche of Christe it is a little flocke: neither doth the woorde <hi>Catholique,</hi> whiche signifieth vniuersall, helpe you one whit, whereby is noted not a multitude, but that how many, or how fewe soeuer wee are, haue beene or shall be heereafter, that professe the Gospell of Iesus Christe, wee make all but one Church. So that the name <hi>Catholique</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>all Christians that euer haue beene,<note place="margin">Catholique, what it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</note> are, or shalbe, and agreeth as vnfitly to you, as generall to particuler, the whole Churche to Rome, which is but a Citie, and a lesse corner of the worlde, then was that part of <hi>Affricke,</hi> wherein the Donatistes would haue shut vp the vniuersall Churche.</p>
   <p>As for departing, we haue no otherwise departed from you then<note place="margin">Howe wee are departed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are gone from the truth.</note> you are departed from the Church, by whom is verified, that which was prophesied, that many should fal, in the last times from the faith, and giue heede to spirites of errour. And the same helping causes, that helde <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> to continue his sincere profession against the <hi>Manichees,</hi> doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. 4. 1. Aug. con. Epist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. cap. 4.</note> holde vs, for we are in deede true Catholikes, and you heretikes, wee are retained in the lappe and bosome of the Church, sucking that pure and vndefiled milke, and you are in the lap of a strumpet drawing the filth and corruption of mans superstition and abhomination: wee haue the consent of all peoples and nations, that are gathered by this voice with vs, and you ioyne in the conspiracie, and treason, of all that are stiffnecked and rebellious against the Gospell. In whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, though there be no end, yea though we be but an handfull, in respect of your confuse heape, yet we haue the consent, and you the dissent, we are Catholike and you schismaticall: rent from the fellowship and body of<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Iesus Christe. The place of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> which you alleadge is plaine for vs. For speaking of the true Catholike church of Christ, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee are members: wee also holde it very needefull, that wee retaine that truth, whiche hath beene, is, or shall bee, retained of all or moste Christians. But <hi>Vincentius</hi> is not of minde that wee shoulde follow the most, the eldest and the greatest consent, as thinges to trie the truth
<pb n="24" facs="23"/>
of God by, and as they are considered in themselues. For who kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>worst, &amp; great consent in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> not, that the most are worste, that errour is very olde, and there may be and is many times consent in iniquitie as well as in veritie. I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>that Antichriste hath beene in the worlde these thousande and fiue hundred yeeres. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 18. The misterie of iniquitie beganne to worke and preuaile, euen in Saint Paules dayes, 2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 1. 2. and in deede this is the antiquitie of your Romishe Churche, whereof you so muche boaste. That the corruption of it, in that Antichristian pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, that inuaded it, and by little and little afterwardes crept along, till it had ouercome and choked it, till that abhomination of desolation foretolde, was nowe placed in that holy place, and temple of God, not so much consisting in the remouing of those first sacrifices of the lawe, &amp; seruice then established as in bringing in a <hi>Maozim,</hi> and vnblooddy sacrifice, such as Christe neuer instituted, I meane that abhominable Idol of the Masse.</p>
   <p>As for their authoritie out of their counterfet <hi>Hyppolitus,</hi> (whose<note place="margin">In their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Testament set out by the scho lers of <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>,</hi> ful of ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.</note> testimonie yet they wrest against vs,) it cannot bee admitted for currant. As for the antiquitie of our Churche, wee proue it by the Testament of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>Christe. And where the doctrine of this is confessed and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued they cannot denie, but there is the Church of God. <hi>My sheepe</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>heare my voice, they followe me, and I giue them euerlasting life.</hi> In deede it is not alwayes so visible vpon earth, neither needeth it<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> such a visible heade, as the Pope is, to whome as <hi>Saunders</hi> saith, it must bee ioyned or els bee schismaticall. It is enough that Christe is the head thereof to comfort it, leade it, and teach it. Wee know that<note place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>before his booke of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Diui. 17. 76. &amp;c.</note> in the worlde <hi>iniquitie shall abounde. All nations shall bee persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that loue his name Mat.</hi> 24. 9. And Paule mentioneth that there shall come an Apostacie before the comming of Christe, <hi>that is a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away of men</hi> from Christe to Antichriste. 2. <hi>Thessa.</hi> 2. 4, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. and Saint Iohn saith: <hi>that the kings of the earth and all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons shall worship Antichriste,</hi> Apocalips 13. 16. and 18. 3. That also the churche for a time shall bee so hid, and inuisible in the earth, that Christe fore warneth his to beeware of them as of lyers, that shall say, <hi>Heere is Christe, or there is Christe:</hi> as it were to point out by places where the churche is. <hi>Matthew</hi> 14. 23. And hee hath not appointed it to bee knowen by such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. But as he saith: <hi>where the carkasse is, thither will the Eagles bee gathered,</hi>
      <pb facs="24"/>
so where Chiriste is holden by faith, there is his churche, which though oftentimes we see not in that beautie and glorie that were meet: in that ministerie and gouernment, which doe liuely paint her foorth as it were in her coulers: yet we must bee of good comfort, and not faint. For such greeuous times are foretolde, that our faith may bee strengthned: <hi>I beleeue the holy Catholike Church:</hi> and that as <hi>Paule</hi> saith <hi>: The foundation standeth sure</hi> and <hi>hath this seale: The Lord knoweth who be his.</hi> 2. Tim. 1. 19.</p>
   <p>Now for consent, <hi>wherein hee woulde haue vs to imbrace the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions and opinions, either of all, or the most part of Priestes and teachers in Antiquitie:</hi> what doth hee els heerein but goe about still to drawe vs from God to men? What would he els, but wrap vs in those inextricable Labyrynthes of mens opinions and contrarieties, that we shoulde neuer bee able to wind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and in meane time depriue vs of that worde of life? Heerein also, they not onely renue that great reproch of<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Belarmi. quest.</hi> 5. <hi>in dicta. scriptis Cocleus. Hosius. Pet. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. Stapletonus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> 7. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. saith: that faith is not learned out of the scriptures. Again, that the holy ghost tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the church many things without thescripture.</note> stainyng the scriptures with insufficiencie, but also in a manner they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spite the authour of them, as though hee had not sufficiently prouided for them, or had depriued them of that whiche is necessarie to their saluation. As if there were more sufficiencie in men, then in God: as if men shoulde supplie that, whiche God either coulde not, or woulde not. This they doe when they binde vs to their definitions and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of their priestes and teachers, and yet dare call the booke of<note place="margin">Censu. Colonien. fol. 2 20.</note> God a matter of strife, affirming it to bee no direction nor guide, but this to bee left to them, and that in such an vnderstanding and meaning, as they giue of it. By them wee must vnderstand the church of Rome, in<note place="margin">Andradi. lib. 2 Concil Trident.</note> whose interpretation without any further adoe we must rest, vpon paine of the blacke curse, and for this cause they binde all their generation to<note place="margin">
         <hi>Andradius in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fen. Conc. Tri. priest of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of Later an in conc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
               <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. Papae. Eccius. Verractus Pighius de Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarch.</hi>
      </note> acknowledge (that I may vse their owne words:) <hi>The holy Catholike and Apostolicall Church of Rome to bee the true mother of all chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and congregations.</hi> And againe, that <hi>the holy scripture is to bee beleeued according to such vnderstanding, interpretation, meaning, &amp; signification, as our mother the holy Church hath alwayes allowed for good, and at this present doth, to whome of right doeth appertaine to</hi>
      <note place="margin">The impietie of the papistes in interpreting the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>
      <hi>giue the scripture a right vnderstanding, sense and interpretation:</hi> yea her creatures most solemnely promise, that they will <hi>neuer vnderstande,</hi> not <hi>interprete the same otherwise,</hi> then according <hi>to the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fathers.</hi> They haue therefore their speciall daliances in the interpretation, shifting it off, some time with a litterall sense, some times
<pb n="25" facs="24"/>
with a spirituall, sometimes it is allegoricall, and sometimes it is Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologicall and Anagogicall. But of all it is not that it shoulde bee,<note place="margin">In antididagma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Colo. sol. 17.</note> but they turne it and winde it like a weathercock, to serue all turnes and to mainteine all their errours, and when no way will serue their turne, then they leaue them and runne to men. I speake not this, as though I denyed all these wayes of interpretation: but to shew their shiftes, that hauing deuised so many, will cleaue to none, but still stay vpon men: in whose writinges there can bee no certaintie, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause<note place="margin">The doctors corrupted and many bastarde writings vnder their names thrust vpon vs.</note> they agree not amongest them selues, as also because their bookes and workes, especially of the most auncient that were either in or next to the primatiue Churche, haue not come vncorrupted to our handes: many haue beene foysted out vnder the names of the best, and others are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: And those that wee are agreed vpon haue many errours. Who will admit for naturall children the<note place="margin">
         <hi>Euseb. li.</hi> 3. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 38 <hi>Nicepb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap</hi> 18. <hi>Epipha. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 1. <hi>to.</hi> 2. <hi>beresis.</hi> 38. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. in vita Clem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> bastarde writinges of <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> who woulde haue both goods and wiues common: of <hi>Dionisius Areopagita,</hi> who builded forsooth a Temple, and yet is said to haue been so poore that he had not a place to lay his head in: of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> of master <hi>Hardings Abdias,</hi> of <hi>Martialis,</hi> and of an infinite number of such like, as farre<note place="margin">Gennadi. in catal. vir. illustrium. Epist Clemen. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. li. 3. ca. 4. lib. 4. cap. 23.</note> vnlike the naturall children of auncient naturall fathers, as you Papists are those fathers whose children you boast to bee, and the Popes that are now those first good Bishops and martyres that were in Rome, and yet<note place="margin">Auctho. in vita Dioni. Theodo. Gaza in prefa., in problem. Alexa. Aprodise. Epist. Ignatii. ad Smir. Reade Buchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerus in his eccl. fol. 66. 67. 68.</note> spite of their heartes, whether they wil or no, you will bee their sonnes: and wheresoeuer the name of churche is founde in any Doctor or father, it must by and by bee vnderstood forsooth of that Babylonicall strumpet of Rome.</p>
   <p>Such also is your succession, vpon whiche you stande so much, vsed, as you say, by the fathers against heretikes for proofe of their religion. And yet who knoweth not, that the succession whereof you boast is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly personall. Whereof Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in his tyme spake not in that Epistle by you alleadged, but had speciall regarde vnto truth, from which thitherunto, they had not declined, in the greatest and most sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancial points of religion, and so may bee saide of the rest. As for that<note place="margin">The popish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>cession <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>brokē &amp; a lame succes sion, wherein they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed thēselues</note> ordinary succession, the scripture is manifest, that it faileth in the church, as by the example of <hi>Ismael,</hi> who followed <hi>Abraham:</hi> and <hi>Esau,</hi> who followed <hi>Isaack:</hi> the Iewes at this day followe their fathers, in all whom is the image of the churche, and yet God chaunged this ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie course, &amp; chose extraordinarily, <hi>Isaack, Iacob,</hi> &amp; vs that be <hi>Gētiles.</hi>
      <pb facs="25"/>
the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, because that first righteousnesse cleaueth in him, and so of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, bee getteth reconciliation, &amp; at length euerlasting life an this you call the mercy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that God hath promised <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Cens. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, to them that worke well, that is to them that fulfill the law of God. So that you make all our life and saluation to consist in the commandement of the lawe, the fulnesse whereof is loue: And yet the scriptures proue quite contrary, that our whole health and salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion consisteth in the merite of Christe: and Paule teacheth, that men are iusufied freely without the workes of the lawe, whose righteousnesse perfourmed and paide to the lawe, is imputed to euery beleeuer: and<note place="margin">Ro. 4. 3. 4, 5.</note> hee addeth to proue this, the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of whome it is saide: <hi>Hee beleeued God, and it was counted vnto him for righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: Nowe to him that worketh, rewarde is not imputed according to grace or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, but according to debt.</hi> But to him, which <hi>worketh not,</hi> but <hi>beleeueth in him which iustifieth the vngodly, his faith is repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to righteousnesse, according to the purpose of Gods grace.</hi> To this ende is that saying alleadged out of Dauid: <hi>Blessed are they whose</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 32. 1</note>
      <hi>iniquities are forgiuen, and whose sinnes are couered,</hi> that is, are not imputed. And hee writeth els where of himselfe, that <hi>hee woulde bee found in Christe, not hauing his owne righteousnes, but that which</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philip. 3. 9.</note>
      <hi>was of the faith of Christe, and of. God, &amp;c.</hi> So that wee see heere a plaine exchange, our vnrighteousnesse is the debt that Christ hath paide of his meere goodnesse, and this paiment is accounted ours by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And on the otherside, all our sinnes are laide againe vpon Christe,<note place="margin">Cens. Col. fol. 46 Conc' Trid. ses. 5. in decrat. de orig. peccat. Caniz. de sacra. bapti. Lind. lib. 3. cap. 19.</note> and that righteousnesse of Christe, wherby he satisfied the lawe, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified the wrath of his father, is become ours through faith, and is trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated vnto vs.</p>
   <p>What shoulde I speake of your other heresies most blasphemous, in iustifiyng concupiscence to bee no sinne, and this lawe of concupiscence,<note place="margin">Tupperus arti 2. de. peccar. originis In iudi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>vni. Coloni. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Pellic. fol. 42. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 44.</note>
      <hi>Thou shalt not lust:</hi> you affirme not to belong to vs: that it doth not forbid vs to haue euill desires: that this euill that dwelleth in our fleshe is forbidden by no lawe, when as the scriptures teache that sinne is simply called <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and Paule proueth that by the lawe, wee<note place="margin">I. Ioh. 3.</note> knowe sinne, and that if the lawe had not saide, <hi>Thou shalte</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 7.</note>
      <hi>not luste,</hi> hee had not knowen that to luste had beene sinne: and<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 28.</note> yet sorsooth, this is one of the greatest matters of Diuinitie, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled<note place="margin">Ioan. 1. 4.</note> in this your rayling defence of the Censure, against the whole<note place="margin">I. Cor. 12.</note> course of the Scripture, and all sounde writers that euer wrote, who<note place="margin">Gal, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <pb n="27" facs="25"/>
not onlie condemne that consent to luste, but euen that titling of our corrupt nature, which according to the newe man is hated, whiche sinne dwelling in vs, not only begetteth, but also nourisheth &amp; bringeth forth.<note place="margin">Chrysost. <hi>homi. in Ma.</hi> 57.</note> Your other heresies I wil not speake of in this place; which albeit you wil<note place="margin">Hierony. in 18, <hi>Ezecb.</hi>
      </note> not confesse to be heresies, yet as long as they are so proued by the word of God, and are stil defended by your church, they put an ende to al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie about it.</p>
   <p>As for your two conditions, to make it a lawful trial, to be obserued of his part, that <hi>will obiect an heresie to another:</hi> one that <hi>the accused partie doe holde such an heresie indeede, and not the likelihood of it.</hi> The other <hi>that the heresie be indeede an heresie,</hi> so accounted and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the primatiue church: although you might haue brought both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, yet we easily admit them. For we in truth charge you not with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing, where of you are not guiltie. Neither doe we say, because suche an heretike and such an heretike, held this or that, therefore it is an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, we reason not so; that is your wonted manner of reasoning. But we saie, such an heresie contrary to the word of God, was holden by such &amp; such an heretike: which you hold in like sort against the word: therfore, in those thinges you iumpe with them, and are Heretikes. Concerning the heresie of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> it is certaine as may appeare out of infinite your writinges, that as hee, with his disciples and followers were enimies to<note place="margin">Reade that whole treatise of iustification, in the Censure of Colen. <hi>pag.</hi> 141. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> the grace of God, so are you: as they mainteined those natural powers, by which they had (as they said an election) to doe, or leaue vndone, that which was good or euill, so say you. And in your opinion set downe, you iumble together mans wil, and the grace of God, teaching that the wil of man holpen with the grace of God, may not onely doe well, but<note place="margin">Antidi. &amp; the consent of Colyne.</note> may fulfill the law of God <hi>expuris naturalibus,</hi> and so be saued: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is so much the more monstrous, because you ioy ne thinges contrarie in one subiect, talking of the grace of God, and of those pure naturals to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, wherat the Apostle saith: <hi>If of grace, then not of works.</hi> If of pure naturals, then what needeth grace? There is no grace where there is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, Neither did the Pelagians vtterly denye grace, when in disputation they were pressed, but confessed more of it, then you doe, as may appeare by Augustine his booke <hi>ad Innocentium.</hi> But this is your religion, and<note place="margin">Lib. 99.</note> alwaies hath beene, that it hath neuer beene at a stay. You boast of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>and consent, but looke howe many heads there are amongest you, so manie monstrous opinions also you holde, euen in the greatest &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest matter of iustification. Some times you attribute to one thing, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb facs="26"/>
to another, and yee are not at one with your selues. You and we both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>that good woorkes are necessarie, and wee agree that what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>we doe, which is good wee doe it by the grace of GOD, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are strengthened through faith to testifie a sincere &amp; an holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; but wee saye that our woorkes are imperfect, wee saye that the fullest and best, that wee canne doe, are too weake to iustifie vs in the fight of God, that they deserue nothing but death and euerlasting destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> you contratiwise affirme, that good workes, serue to clense your<note place="margin">Catholic.</note> sinnes, to pacifie Gods wrath, and to attaine euerlasting life, yea you say,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Perio. in Topicis. Theolog. lib. 1.</note> that there are three thinges, that must be obtained by merite, that is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life, the increase of grace, and the forgiuenes of the punishment<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>serm. 21.</note> of sinne: And yet that these woorkes, commaunded of God, are not the woorkes that onelie please God, but also there are freewill workes,<note place="margin">Compend. Theo. de grā.</note> done at the choyse of man, and that without Faith, as <hi>Andradius</hi> fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.<note place="margin">Andrad. lib. 3. pag. 281. 279.</note> But we knowe by the Scriptures, that these works of mans choyce, can stand vs in no steed. S. Paule condēneth <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer (saith he) is not of faith, it is sinne, and it cannot please God, Good<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 23.</note> fruites, must needes haue a good tree. The branches are worth nothing,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 5. 8.</note> that are not engrafted into Christe, neither haue they anielife, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>Christ their life. And therefore if you wil magnifie the grace of God as you ought, you must confesse, that we are saued by <hi>grace throughly: not of workes, least anie shoulde boast.</hi> You must goe farther of from <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> and ioyne with Christians: who holde, that a man is not iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by workes of the lawe, neither before or after grace, but by the fayth of Iesus Christ. We saith he, <hi>hauo beleeued in Iesus, that wee might bee iustified by the Faith of Christ, and not of the workes of the lawe, by whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che no flesh shalbe iustified.</hi> And because you take it in suche skorne to bee charged with <hi>Pelagius</hi> heresie, I pray you yet consider further your<note place="margin">Galat. 2. 21.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>doctrine; which is, that mans free will moued of God, doeth by consent worke together with the grace of God, so as both doe concurre in the conuersion of a man, or in bringing foorth spirituall actions, to witte,<note place="margin">Concil. Trident.</note> the grace of God, &amp; the natural strength of mans free wil: your own <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dradius,</hi> a chief piller of yours, saith: that the libertie of our free wil, is the<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. lib. 4.</note> efficient cause of the applying of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>to grace; but so, as it is confirmed by diuine helpes: and I beseeche you howe farre differeth this from playne <hi>Pelagianisme.</hi> And yet the Scriptures are playne: <hi>No man commeth vnto mee, vnlesse my Father drawe him.</hi> And Saynte<note place="margin">Io. 6. 44.</note> Paule sayeth: <hi>GOD woorketh both to will and to performe,</hi> in all<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 13.</note>
      <pb n="28" facs="26"/>
spirituall actions, for <hi>the naturall man is enimie to God, neyther are</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 14.</note>
      <hi>wee fitte as of our selues, to thinke anie good thought, muche lesse to doe it.</hi> Therefore, this <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, in spirituall thinges is to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, wher with the powers of men are so diseased, that knowledge wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they can muche lesse haue anye libertie of election. And therefore<note place="margin">Anton. Flor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 1. part.</note> horrible is that doctrine of yours also, concerning the fulfilling of the lawe, that it may not onelie bee satisfied of vs, <hi>in entionaliter, constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionaliter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tit. 11. ca 2 Trident. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Pet. a So to in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser.</note> and <hi>integraliter:</hi> For these are their owne wordes, but also that the fulfilling of it, is in a mans own power, to do these things, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which the law cōmandeth, but ouer &amp; aboue the law, &amp; these are their<note place="margin">Cathar. de lege.</note>
      <note place="margin">Andradius.</note> workes of Supererogation, and these by dispensations and Bulles may be applied vnto others, and vnto their vse serue as their own, to their iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Surely I fayne nothing their owne bookes haue reserued this dung which now I fling in their owne faces. And yet who knoweth not<note place="margin">The lawe of God spiritual.</note> that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>of God is spititual, and that it requireth a perfecte obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>the whole hearte, soule and minde. As Christe himselfe hath expounded in the 5. of <hi>Mat.</hi> concerning the exposition of the 5. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement &amp;c. Seeing no man hath euer bin able to fulfil the law, it must needs follow, that no man can be iustified by it. <hi>He hath shut all vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, that he might haue mercie on all:</hi> and he hath sent his onelye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, that hee fulfilling the Lawe, it might bee to the iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of euerie one that belecueth. Now, if we must needs confesse, that we are not cleare, neither from the sinnes of the first table, nor of the seconde, and the lawe of God requireth not onelie an outwarde obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but also an inwarde, and that perfect from the hearte, and not for a while, but thorow out a mans whole life: it must needes proceede from a<note place="margin">The proude spirites of the Papists.</note> proude spirite, not onelie to boast of the fulfilling of the lawe, but to doe more then the lawe requireth, suche as are your vowed chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and pouertie, whereby you mocke both GOD and men: But howesoeuer you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>the matter withmen, GOD will not bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. A tyme will come when you shall aunsweare it to him. In meane time you shal answere it also to his Churche sor hudling and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Lawe and the Gospell so together. For you Iesuites saye, that this is the doctrine of the Gospell, that if wee will enter into lyfe, wee must keepe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: and yet Saynt Paule sheweth<note place="margin">Censur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 284.</note> a plaine difference. For Moses describing the righteousnes which is of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>saith: <hi>Is a man shal doc these thinges, hee shall liue in them:</hi> but the righteousnesse whiche is of Faith is: <hi>If thou shalte confesse the</hi>
      <pb facs="27"/>
      <hi>Lorde Iesus, and beleeue in thine hearte, that God hath raised him vp from the dead, thou shalt be saued.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now concerning the other iniurie (you say) we offer you in ioyning you with those heretikes, who were named Colliridians, that woorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Virgin Marie: you say, they sacrificed to her, and so doe not you, and therfore you haue wrong: but you must remember, that herein they were saide to worship her, because it was the maner of their worshipping, to sacrifice. But if there be a sacrifice of praise, and of prayer, due onlie to God, and yet you yeeld this without al reason and ground of the worde, vnto that blessed Virgin; What doe you els, but as these heretikes did, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto her? This is but a meere cauil, whereby you woulde auoyde the point, charging vs with an iniurie, that doe you but right, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>in this, but in al the rest, wherwith you are iustly charged, because as they were charged for these thinges done against the truth of God, so are you. The Anthropomorphites ascribed to God the members and lineamentes of a man, so doe you in making an image of GOD the father, of Iesus Christ, of the holy Ghost. The Valentinians had their crosse and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped it, so doe you. The Eutichians denied the truth of Christs bodie, so doe you. The Apostolikes against the warrant of Gods word, vowed and yet kept not continencie and pouertie, so doe your Iesuites, and all the rest of your Popes holie orders. The Marcionists also, were exceeding, in praysing virginitie, in superstitious fasting, &amp; suffering women to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, and so are you: what heresie euer was there, or is there, with whiche you doe not communicate with one point or another, with those (I saie) that are set downe, and condemned for heresies? You are Carpocratians for Images, Hemerobaptistes for holy water. Ossenes and Mercosians for deuised Reliques, and praiers in a strange language. Heracleans in annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them that were at the point of death: Eucralites in abstaining from flesh, and what not? And what sacrifice could you yeeld greater vnto the Virgin Marie, then that you haue giuen her? when in a manner you haue preferred, and laboured to preferre a seruice vnto her before theseruice of God, as may apyeare in your offices, both old and new, authorized euen by your chiefest fathers, and holiest Popes; wherein you abuse moste<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Mariae nuper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, &amp; Pu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Gregorij 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. editum. 1578</note> shamefully the Scriptures of God, applying sundrie Psalms to the Virgin Marie, that were neuer meant of her, as namely, the 8. Psalme, the 18. the 23. the 44. the 45. and al the rest, as fitlye to the purpose, as all the rest of your interpretations are. I speake not of your blasphemous Hymnes. <hi>O gloriosa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>excelsa super sidera, &amp;c. Aue regina coelorum: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <pb n="29" facs="27"/>
      <hi>Dominae Angelorum, salue radix sancta, &amp;c.</hi> But this is most blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and intollerable amongest the rest: <hi>Salue Regina, mater misericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae, vita, dulcedo, &amp; spes nostra salue. Adte clamamus Exules Euae: Adte suspiramus gementes &amp; flentes, in hac lachrimarum valle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>ergo aduocatrix nostra, illos tuos misericordes oculos ad nos conuerte. &amp;c.</hi> Al hayle Queene, mother of mercy, Al haile our life, our sweetnes &amp; our hope. To thee we crie, the exiles of Eue; to thee weegrone, weeping and mourning in this vale of teares. O therfore our aduocate, turne those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>merciful eyes towards vs. It were too tedious, and would require an<note place="margin">Reade that in 16. <hi>fol.</hi> 49. 51. &amp; thorowout the whole Booke.</note> whole volume by it selfe, to set downe al their horrible prayers, in their Breuiaries, Portifories Portuises, that they make to the Virgin and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sayntes: and that with setting such prices vpon them, that they that say such and such a prayer, with so manie <hi>Pater nosters, Aue maries,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Credo,</hi> shal haue so manie yeeres and daies of pardon, <hi>totiēs, quotiēs,</hi> (for that is their Latine.) As for example, whosoeuer shall say this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er following, before our blessed Ladie of pitie, they beeing in the state of grace: <hi>She will shewe them her blessed visage, and warne them of the day and houre of death, and in their last ende, the Angels of God shall yeeld their soules to heauen, and he shall obtaine 500. yeeres, and so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Lentes of pardon, graunted by fiue holie fathers Popes of Rome.</hi> The prayer is blasphemous, and beginneth thus: <hi>Obsecro te sancta Domina, &amp;c. I beseech you holy Lady S. Marie, mother of God, most ful of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, the daughter of the high king, a most glorious mother, a mother of Orphans, consolation of the desolate: the way of those that erre, the saluation and hope of those that trust in thee. A Virgin before her byrth, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>in her birth, &amp; a virgin after her birth: the fountayne of mercie, the fountaine of saluation and grace, the fountaine of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>and gladnes, the fountain of consolation and forgiuenes &amp;c.</hi> The like is, <hi>Aue Rosa sine spinis. Al haile rose without thornes, written for sooth with letters of gold in her breast, and that which was shewed to S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>by an Angel of her: and that, Aue Maria alta stirps lilij castita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Al hayle Mary the high stocke of the Lilie of chastity.</hi> For the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the Pope graunted an 100. dayes of pardon: &amp; that <hi>Aue,</hi> wherein she is called the Queene of heauen, the gate of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, the Ladie of the worlde, for whiche Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> graunted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuen<note place="margin">Fol. 50. 51. 52. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>de beata <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: printed at Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in anno 1534.</note> thousande yeeres of pardon, for saying this before the Image of our Ladye, Also another to her, for whiche <hi>Celestinus</hi> the Pope graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="28"/>
three hundred daies of pardon. Another <hi>Aue,</hi> for which Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> graunted, at the instance of the high and most excellent Princesse Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, late Queene of England, and wife to our Soueraigne Lorde, King Henrie the seuenth, <hi>God haue mercie on her sweete soule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 54.</note>
      <hi>soules,</hi> that euery day in the morning after 3. toulings of the <hi>Aue</hi> bel, 3. times, the whole salutation of our Lady: <q>
         <hi>Aue Maria gratiaple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that is to say, at 6. a in the morning. 3. <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> at 12. at noone, other 3, at 6, at euen other 3: for euery time so doing, is graunted of the spirituall treasure of holie Churche, 3. hundred daies of pardon, <hi>totiens quotiens.</hi> And also our holy father the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. of Canterbury &amp; York, with other niene Bishops of this Realme, haue graunted 3. times in the day 40. dayes of pardon to all them that be in the state of grace, able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue pardon. And this beganne the 26. day of Marche <hi>in anno</hi> 1482. <hi>anno Henrici</hi> 7. And the summe of the indulgence and pardon for euery <hi>Aue marie,</hi> is eight hundred and sixtie dayes <hi>totiens, quotiens.</hi> It muste bee say de at the towling of the <hi>Aue</hi> bell, <hi>Suscipe verbum Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Maria &amp;c.</hi> O Virgin Marie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>the worde, whiche by the Angell was sent vnto thee from GOD &amp;c. This forsooth is the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce they speake of, and their absolutions, when they had committed all their knaueries and wickednesses, to robbe Princes and to cousin them of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Then we must haue suche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>deuised shiftes to occupie superstitious people withall, and one thinge euermore marke, that there was neuer anie suche price set vppon anye seruice done to Christ, as vpon that whiche was done to the Virgin or to some other Saynt.</q> The Virgin had the most, they were so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>vppon the mother, that in a manner they forgotte both Father and Sonne. I am wearie in stirring this filthie Quakemyre of their cursed abhomination, but that I see it verie necessarie, seeing these fine witted Iesuites that will restore all, and dispute the matter agaynst all that can bee brought, defending euerie absurditie, doe so greatly prouoke mee.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 56.</note>
   </p>
   <p>There is another prayer, that whosoeuer sayeth deuoutely, hee hath by<note place="margin">It is called the contemplation of our blessed Lady wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vnder the crosse.</note> the graunt of <hi>Bonifacius</hi> seuen yeeres of pardon, and fortie Lentes; and by the graunt of Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the twentye two, three hundred dayes of pardon. But what spende I breath about beggerlye thinges? There is one prayer not verye longe, whiche yet if a man saye deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>mater dolorosa.</note> in the woorshippe of <hi>Saint Anna,</hi> and our Ladie, and her Sonne<note place="margin">Fol. 85. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <pb n="30" facs="28"/>
Iesus, hee hath graunted by <hi>Alexander</hi> the sixth, tenne thousande yeeres of pardon for deadlie sinnes, and twentye yeeres for veniall sinnes <hi>totiens quotiens.</hi> And because it is so shorte, and yet the gayne so greate, not to depriue thee of suche a commoditie, to bringe thee out of Purgatorie: (For Iam sure the Pope is a manne of his woorde) and thou needest not to feare but it is true, seeyng it is printed and sette downe: I will shewe it thee. <hi>Aue Marye, full of grace, our Lorde is with thee, Blessed arte thou amongest women, and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed is Saynte Anne thy Mother, of whome thou Uirgin Marie cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest foorth without blotte and sinne, and of thee was borne Iesus Christe the Sonne of the liuing GOD Amen. Pater noster Aue, Aue Maria.</hi> Is not heere an easie pennaunce to leade a wicked life, in deadlie sinne tenne thousande yeeres? And then marke howe manye times this may bee sayde in a daye, and then what a summe this woulde mount too. Indeede euen on the other side of the leafe, there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prayer as long though not so profitable, but that is but to bee sayde before the Image of Saynt <hi>Anne,</hi> of <hi>Marie,</hi> and of Iesus, for whiche <hi>Raymundus the Cardinall and Legate</hi> beeing somewhat more charie, wold not lash out of the Spiritual Treasure of the Church, so much as the Pope his Maister did, but onelie graunted an hundred dayes of pardon, <hi>totiens quotiens.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But is not this trimme stuffe, that you translate <hi>Te Deum lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> into <hi>Te matrem laudamus?</hi> where you call her the wife of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Father, whom all the earth doeth woorshippe: Whom all the glorious companie all <hi>Confessours, doe call the Temple of the whole</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Breuiario Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano. fol. 252.</note>
      <hi>trinitie: whome the whole Courte of Heauen doeth honour, as the Queene of Heauen. Thou arte the Ladye of Angelles, the gate of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 45.</note>
      <hi>the Lader of the heauenlie kingdome, and the bedfellow Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus or marrying chamber of the king of glorie. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>art the refuge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>a sinner, the mother of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Sauiour. Saue vs thy people thou Lady of thy seruauntes, that wee may be partakers of thine inheritance, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe O sweete Marie, nowe and alwayes to keepe vs without sinne. O Godlie Marie haue mercie vpon vs, haue mercy vpon vs: let thy great mercie be alwayes with vs, because (O Marie) we trust in thee. In thee (O sweete Marie) wee hope, that thou shouldest defende vs for euer.</hi> What shoulde I blotte paper with the blasphemies contayned in the Rosaries? &amp; what shoulde I rehearse the praier that <hi>Laurence</hi> B. of <hi>Asses</hi> made &amp; graunted 40, daies of pardon to them that saide it in the worship
<pb facs="29"/>
of our Lady, and that which S. Edmond Archb. of Canterburie made and sayde, of the which manie miracles be shewed? What should I speake of<note place="margin">Fol. 47.</note> that prayer, made concerning <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> that traitour, of S. <hi>Erken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walde,</hi> of S. <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> the virgin that had a beard, sodainly growen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon her face, to keepe her from marrying the king of Cicilia: of S. <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin,</hi> S. <hi>Syth.</hi> S. <hi>Dunston,</hi> S. <hi>Elphege,</hi> S. <hi>Brigit,</hi> with her 15. Oos, to be saide before the holie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>in S. <hi>Powles</hi> at Rome, and being said thorow out the yeere there, deliuereth 15. soules out of Purgatorie of the next of<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 59.</note> kinne, and conuerteth 15. sinners to good life, and maketh that the 15. righteous men of his kinne, shal continue in goodlife: and he that saith <hi>S. Gregories prayer before the Image of pitie,</hi> with 5. <hi>Pater nosters, 5.!</hi>
      <note place="margin">32000. seuen hundred and 55. yeeres of pardon.</note>
      <hi>Auies and a Credo:</hi> piteously beholding <hi>those armes of Christes bitter passion, there are</hi> graunted 32. <hi>thousand, 700. and 55. yeeres of pardon?</hi> And <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4. hath made the fourth and fifth prayer, and hath dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled<note place="margin">Fol. 63.</note> his foresaid pardon: I had almost forgotten that goodlie Epistle of<note place="margin">Crux Christi sit mecum: Crux est quam semper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doro, &amp;c.</note> our Sauiour, which <hi>Leo</hi> sent to <hi>Carolus magnus,</hi> which whosoeuer do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth beare about him, and saith it once a day, shal obtaine 40. yeeres of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and fourescore lenttidge, and hee shall not perishe with sodayne<note place="margin">The Crosse of Christe be with me: The Crosse which alwayes I wor shipe.</note> death; and that prayer also whiche muste bee saide before the eleuation and the three <hi>Agnus deis,</hi> for which <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the 6. holie Pope, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ten thousande yeeres of pardon. So there was pardons graunted by <hi>Iohn</hi> 22. and <hi>Innocentius,</hi> for prayers sayde at the Eleuation. <hi>All haile true bodie, borne of Marie the Virgin &amp;c. All haile light of the</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 66.</note>
      <hi>worlde: The worde of the Father: the true Sacrifice, liuing flesh: the whole Godhead: very man. All haile the beginning of our creation, the price of our redemption &amp;c.</hi> This Idolatrie they committed to their <hi>Maozim</hi> their breaden God of Abhomination. But singuler aboue all others is that, which beeing sayde immediatlie after the eleuation of the hoste, bringeth cleane remission of all their sinnes that saye it perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie enduring: Graunted forsooth, by <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4 and by <hi>Iohn</hi> the third, Popes of Rome, which being say de before the image of our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, doth bring as many dayes of pardon, as there were woundes in the body of our Lord in the time of his bitter passion, the whiche were fiue thousande 400. 65. as iust as can bee, but yet they misse of their recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. For in another place they make them lesse. Sainte Augustines prayer also is a goodlye prayer, which, whosoeuer doeth but say, heare, or beare about him, he shal not perishe by fire nor water, in battell, or in iudgement (For though he deserue to be hanged, yet he shall scape)
<pb n="31" facs="29"/>
hee shall not dye any sodaine death, &amp; no venom shal poyson him in that day: and when hee dyeth his soule shall not enter into hell: Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi>
      <note place="margin">fol. 72.</note> fiue petitions also are of goodly vertue, and so are the three prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers written in the chappell of the holy crosse at Rome, whiche for the saying of them, haue allotted tenne hundred thousande yeeres of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don<note place="margin">Ten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>thousand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>of pardon.</note> for deadly sinnes: and this that liberall Gentleman Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. of his large liberalitie graunted, but you must remember to say also a <hi>Pater noster,</hi> an <hi>Aue,</hi> and a <hi>Creede.</hi> If you liue any longer, you may take it for aduauntage. And I pray you forget not to praye to the<note place="margin">Fol. 73.</note> sweete visage or vernackle of our Lorde, for you shall obteine euen by that, tenne thousande dayes of pardon. And if you cannot say this prayer, you may put in steede thereof, fiue <hi>Pater nosters,</hi> fiue <hi>Aues,</hi> and fiue <hi>Credoes in Deum.</hi> As <hi>Campion</hi> saide, aboue all remember<note place="margin">Campion would haue a Credo, for a prayer at the time of his death.</note> to ioyne in <hi>Credo</hi> with mee, when hee was in his prayers at his death. And if you do but deuoutly behold the armes of an image of Christ, you shall haue sixe thousande yeeres of pardon, three thousand for deadly sinnes, and three thousand for veniall sinnes, and I warrant you for the rest. And because you shall not doubt of this, as if it had but a seale of Butter, I tell you, as sure as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was first Pope of Rome, so hee graunted it, and thirtie other Popes that were successours after him, and therefore doubt not of it: and <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. hath confirmed it. After all these many other odde things there are to be had, which would not be lost. For <hi>al help,</hi> which is the prayer that is to be said in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship<note place="margin">Fol. 75.</note> of our Lords wound in his side, bringeth foure thousand dayes of pardon: and S. <hi>Barnards</hi> prayer in the worship of the holy name Iesus, which is written in a table at S. Peters Church in Rome, deliuereth frō the state of eternall damnation, &amp; changeth eternall paine into the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral paine of purgatory, &amp; the paine of purgatory into free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 79.</note> on. And there be prayers for women with child, euen the first Psalm, as well applied as the twentie two for her deliuerie, against thundering and lightning, against the pestilence: to our Ladie, for newe maried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, for all diseases and sortes of people: and one containing certaine verses of the Psalter, whiche Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> learned of the Diuell. For when<note place="margin">Saint <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>he learned of the Diuel.</note> on a certaine time hee was in his prayers, the Diuel tolde him that hee knewe certaine verses in the Psalter, which, whosoeuer said them daylie shoulde not perishe, but hee should haue knowledge of the day wherein hee shoulde die. But the feend would not shew them to Saint <hi>Bernard:</hi> then Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> saide, hee woulde say euery day the whole Psalter,
<pb facs="30"/>
which when the Diuell perceiued, hee tolde Saint <hi>Bernarde</hi> which they weres you shall finde the verses in <hi>Fol.</hi> 125. You may see, howe <hi>Bernarde</hi> learned to pray of the Diuell (as they say) <hi>Luther</hi> learned to knowe that the Masse was euill by the Diuell. Surely it is like that the one shoulde bee as true as the other: I will but tell you one more and so get out (yf I can) of this foule quakemyre: and that is to be saide<note place="margin">
         <hi>Fol.</hi> 144. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>omnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
               <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. &amp;c.</hi> All haile all soules of the faithful, whose bodies rest here, or els where in the dust. &amp;c.</note> as you goe thorowe the Churche yarde, for saying of which, Pope Iohn the twelfth, graunted as many yeeres of pardon, as there were bodies buried, from the time that it was first a Church yard. Do you not thinke that this passeth sacrificing to the Virgin Mary? And doe we not greate wrong vnto them, When wee charge them with heresies? Who care not what they holde, nor what they set downe, but agree as I haue saide with all, and those the most grosse heretikes that cuerliued, not in anie good thinges that they helde (for these are none of theirs) but euen in their greatest corruptions and villanies against God, and his worde, as may appeare by their doctrine and liues, deliuered in all times and ages. And this is verified of them concerning prayer for the dead, as master Fulke hath iustly charged them, ioyning with the Montanistes, among whose heresies that is written: though <hi>Augustine, Ambrose. Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> did also in some sort hold it: For they held it not, as these do, besides the foundation of faith, though it bee an errour in faith: nor in suche grosse manner, though the corruption of that time had preuailed with them to make them erre. Wee doe not therefore abuse the people, but doe holde, that whatsoeuer is condemned for heresie in the worde of God, and so was accounted and conuinced (as stood in and mainteined) in the primatiue Church, that we account &amp; condemne styll for heresie.</p>
   <p>But where hee saith, that wee holde heresies, and culleth out those which are in deede no heresies, but manifest truethes, according to the worde of God, as that of <hi>Aerius</hi> against prayer for the dead, and that of <hi>Vigilantius</hi> for praying vnto Saintes: it needeth no other answere, then that which is set downe alreadie by writers from amongest vs of all sortes. And it is a good answere, that euery thing is not an errour, which<note place="margin">Euery thing is not an errour, which hath bin reckoned for an errour.</note> good men haue reckoned for errours, for so, without all cause, the truth should be condemned, and that which is false shoulde be vpholden and maintained.</p>
   <p>The conditions therefore you speake of are not maintained, seeing
<pb n="3" facs="30"/>
of the greatest heresies, you cannot for all your malice accuse vs of any one. And as for these errours which you woulde haue made so great heresies, they are none, but are according to the truth of God, &amp; as those fathers held them were not so blasphemous, as they are in you, that hold litle or nothing of the foundation of faith.</p>
   <p>As for the maner of heretikes wherewith you fit vs, and still with your former two conditions, whether our or your manners best <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>them and agree with them, shall in a fitter place appeare. As for <hi>Augustines</hi> note of that propertie of the <hi>Donatistes,</hi> that hated (as you say) the sea of Rome, and called it <hi>Cathedram pestilentiae,</hi> the chayre of Pestilence: if wee shoulde graunte that Rome nowe were<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>they reade the name of Catholike Church, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth, it muste needs be ment of Rome. But there is no such word in <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> the same Rome that it was then: how can it fit vs that neuer called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny member of the Churche, the chayre of Pestilence? The <hi>Donatists</hi> in deede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>shut vp the Catholike Churche into a corner of the worlde, and thought other Churches, and Rome amongest the rest, to bee no Church, against whome Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> disputeth in the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Chapter. But of that you mention and specially of Rome which you name, there is no worde, not sillable in the fiftie and one Chapter.</p>
   <p>But this is alwayes your propertie, like obstinate heretikes as you are, to abuse your Readers, with quoting places out of the Doctors for a shewe onely of that, which is not there, as though all went of your side, when neither worde nor matter tending that way, can bee founde in the places by you alleadged. But euen as heretikes are wont, you ly by tradition, and make no conscience, to be daube your margent with shewe of Authorities, when you haue not so much as a syllable to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your errours. Bring mee therefore that place directly out of <hi>Augustine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>When you answere againe, that heretikes call the Church of Rome, <hi>Cathedram Pestilentiae,</hi> when in deede it was a member of the true Church: if they did so, they beare a iust condemnation. But as it is now, it is in deede the seate of Antichriste, despising and persecuting the Catholike Churche of Christe, and forsaking the scriptures, by which it refuseth to be prooued, mainteining false doctrine, &amp; liuing therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all abhominably. And therefore must needes bee the chaire of Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. It must needes heerein agree with the <hi>Donatists,</hi> that drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of a decay of the Church, of an Apostacie and falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, so, as though all, were headged in at Rome, and <hi>you onely as the two Tribes</hi> (as Angustine speaketh) <hi>had remayned</hi>
      <pb facs="31"/>
      <hi>in the temple, that is in the Church:</hi> No, we aske you with <hi>Augustin. Seeing wee doe not beleeue you, howe will yee conuince vs? Will you not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>vs by the holy scriptures, where, with so great manifestation they are reade, to the ende that whosoeuer hee bee, that once beleeueth those letters, hee cannot but confesse these thinges to bee most true.</hi> Againe, if I must therefore bee compelled to beleeue these examples to<note place="margin">He meaneth such as were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> to proue that the vniuer sal church was faln &amp; that his particuler church was the church. <hi>August. lib. de vnitate Ecclesiae cap.</hi> 12.</note> bee true, because they are there written, when I cannot say, they are false which are written: <hi>Why doe not they also themselues, beleeue the same Scriptures, concerning the Church spread throughout the world?</hi> Loe wee beleeue all those things, let them also beleeue that which the Lorde saith: <hi>that repentance and remission of sinnes is preached in his name throughout all nations, beginning at Herusalem:</hi> But what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all this for Rome, or against vs, vnlesse wee shoulde giue that they beg, which is too too absurd, that a particuler Church, is the Catholike churche, that Rome is the vniuersall churche: which though we should<note place="margin">That place out of the 3. booke against the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Petilian, cap.</hi> 4. is set down also for a shewe, seeing we leane not to mē, but look to the vnitie of the spirite in the truth.</note> giue them, yet they are neuer the neare, seeing God neuer forsaketh his, and they are his whome hee hath foreknowen, whom hee hath chosen, whom he doth neuer reiect, but keepeth them amidst all tryals and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, bringing them to rest in the end? Another propertie, whiche must needes <hi>bee ours, is for hating and cōdemning the life of Monkes: and also for drawing Nunnes out of their cloisters, and ioyning our selues with the same in pretended wedlocke.</hi> First, for that place out of the second booke, against the Epistle of <hi>Parmenian,</hi> there is not one worde tending that way, and as for that Epistle to <hi>Eusebius:</hi> In<note place="margin">The like is that out of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōd book <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> deede <hi>Augustine</hi> there complaineth of the breach of their discipline, &amp; that two were allured by the <hi>Cyrcumcelians,</hi> not because they woulde marry, but because they woulde shake of the yoke of the Lordes disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, they went gadding vp and downe like vagabonds, and gaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to drunkennesse, and so hee complaineth of a Subdeacon, but what maketh this against vs? We drawe them not like <hi>Circumcelians</hi> from the religion and discipline of Christe, but beeing <hi>Christians,</hi> and hauing not the gift of continencie, wee giue them counsaile to marrie. The Monkes and Nunnes, which <hi>Augustine</hi> spake of, are as like theirs, as they are vnlike to Christians, whose names they boast: wee drawe them not out in any disordered sort, to bring them to ryot, and to allure them from God, to make them harlots, as themselues commonly did, but wee shewe them of that libertie God hath left, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>them to honestie, &amp; not to villanie, as it is too euident they did, when scarse amongest a
<pb n="33" facs="31"/>
number, fewe escaped from their filthie abuse, by which they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured, many bastardes begotten and murthered, many buggeries con tinually committed, against the worde of God.</p>
   <p>As for the <hi>Arrians,</hi> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> had good cause disputing against them, that abused the scripture, in that same sacred misterie of the Trinitie, to stande vpon that liuely tradition of the Apostles, which is no suche thing, as you intende by tradidion, contrary to the written word of God, but the same was receiued from hande to hand, &amp; agreed with the doctrine of Christe and his Apostles, written and set downe to all posteritie. In this respect that misterie of beleeuing in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the sonne, and the holy Ghoste, was so called in the councell of<note place="margin">Conc. Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopl. 6. Act. 4.</note>
      <hi>Constantinople,</hi> by <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Basill:</hi> and of such like speaketh the<note place="margin">Tertul. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>aduersus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Apostle, when hee saith: Holde fast those traditions which you haue receiued, eyther by our worde or by our Epistle. In this respect<note place="margin">Basil de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Augustine</hi> disputing against <hi>Maximinus</hi> an heretike, appealeth to the<note place="margin">2. Thes. 2. 2.</note> tradition of the Apostles. But what serueth this to maintaine your false named traditions vnder the name of the Apostles, that are but byrdes hatched yesterday, yet calow and scarse couered with feathers, as vnlike those whom you woulde make their dammes, as your selues are, who in all thinges are degenerated from them? Of like consequence for proofe of your Masse, Altars, Chalices, Chrisme, and Priestes vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is that you set downe, as you say, noted by <hi>Optatus</hi> before <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine.</hi> Surely the place by you alleadged, serueth as little to your helpe as the other. Wee denie not but that in the waste made by those barbarous Vandalles: There was great spoyle in the iust iudgemente of God brought vpon the churche, all kinde of learning ceasing almost, and the monuments thereof being vtterly decayed, which one of your great pillers, master <hi>Harding</hi> saith, was because of their schisme from the<note place="margin">Victor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>This was done in the space of 140. yeeres.</note> church of Rome, which was neither so nor so in which yet Rome it selfe was taken, possessed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>by sundrie men, aboue 6. times in a small space. But would you hereby insinuate your Idolatrous Masse, which<note place="margin">Hard. answere <hi>diuis.</hi> 28.</note> then had not halfe the Idolatrous patches, that since haue been added? woulde you insinuate your chalices, which then were no otherwise kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, and taken, then as cuppes fit for that seruice? woulde you insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate your aulters of stone, that tooke their first beginning, from Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> as both <hi>Uolateran</hi> &amp; <hi>Vernerius</hi> testifie? For as in Christs time,<note place="margin">Volateran.</note> there were not many temples builded, so there were not many alters e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and therefore in <hi>Origens</hi> time, it was obiected by <hi>Celsus</hi> that they<note place="margin">Origen cont, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>sum. lib. 4.</note>
      <pb facs="32"/>
had neither images nor aulters, nor temples: and so <hi>Arnobius</hi> sayth, that<note place="margin">Arnobius in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. lib. 3.</note> the Heathen cast this likewise in their teeth: whereby it appeareth, that in their times the church was not acquainted with your prophanations. In deede the name of Masse, of latter times hath been vsed, but it she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not that it was vsed then, or that it was yours wherof they spake (I mean your priuat Masse): no, it was the communion, and according to that they had tables of wood, and no aulters. They might sometime call the communion tables, by the name of aulters, as also some other things by those names that you yet retaine: but this was by <hi>Metaphor,</hi> and as a man would say improperly, rather, for the receiued maner of speech, of the auncient worship instituted vnder the lawe, before the comming of Christe whilest sacrifices endured, then now to prooue such a blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous sacrifice or aulter as yours is. For <hi>Siluester</hi> the first (as some of you write though falsly) was he, that commanded that none shoulde<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 5. Gerson <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>F. 4. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Epist. 50.</note> consecrate at a woodden aulter: and <hi>Bonifacius</hi> was he that first deuided the priest from the people: And S. <hi>Augustine</hi> complaineth that the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natistes</hi> on a time in great rage, brake the boords of the aulter, and wounded the priestes. And that they were made of wood, and stoode in<note place="margin">Reade <hi>August. de verbis domini secund. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. ser.</hi> 24. <hi>Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>ca.</hi> 4. <hi>ex or at.</hi>
      </note> the middest of the Church, &amp;c. It may appeare by this, that hee saith, it was the subdeacons office to remoue the table, which he could not haue done, if either it had beene of stone, or fast fixed against any wall Eastward as your superstitious maner is. And is this your burning charitie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs with those barbarous heretikes the Donatists, or those Vandals,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> being in deede <hi>Arrians,</hi> as all the rest were, that made suche hauocke, not onely of the Churche of Rome, but of the Churches in <hi>Affricke,</hi> of <hi>Antioche,</hi> of <hi>Hippo,</hi> where <hi>Augustine</hi> was, and sundrie others? These were madde against the truth, and we stand for it. It is not we that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Israell, but <hi>Achab,</hi> and his fathers house. Is it all one to rage againste<note place="margin">The Papistes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>vs with Donatists, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, &amp; other heretikes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the people of God &amp; to execute Gods sentence vpon <hi>Baals</hi> priests? For with as good right <hi>Baals</hi> priestes, might haue blamed <hi>Helias,</hi> and <hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus, Iehu,</hi> and such godly princes, for destroying their aulters, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing their temples, shedding their blood, as you blame and charge vs. The difference is plaine, they were <hi>Donatistes</hi> and <hi>Arrians,</hi> &amp; wee Christians: they like sauage and brutish Boares, brake in vpon the Lords inheritance, we labour to keepe out such Boars, Wolues, and beastes, as you are and haue proued your selues to bee. The same may bee saide of that obiected by <hi>Basill</hi> against <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> &amp; his fellowes. You are the <hi>Iulians,</hi> and wee those whome you persecute in Christe, &amp; in his members. But for qualities we shall say more hereafter.</p>
   <pb n="34" facs="32"/>
   <p>For your contentednesse to admit now, what soeuer triall wee will for the finding out of your spirites, surely wee cannot but congratulate your kindenesse. But is this the opinion of all your fellowes, or of yourselfe alone; If of all, then let vs see their handes, authentikclie vppon recorde deliuered vnto vs. Once wee are sure of this that it is against their generall doctrine, as hath beene saide before: If it bee or your selfe, (that I may vse your owne phrase) you are somewhat too cockishe against the common opinion of your Church, to offer so franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet as you saide to M. <hi>Hanmer,</hi> I thinke when it shall come to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, you shall be none of the disputers.</p>
   <p>As for that you write, that you are not daunted, For that <hi>Campion</hi> and <hi>Sherwinn</hi> (that were foreward that way) are taken away by death, surely we thinke so. If the tryall of your cause, had depended vppon them, then your religion had falne with their treason. And thankes be to God howe harde soeuer your heartes bee: yet you haue and had cause to feare, seeing vnder pretence of Disputation, they were prooued to practise <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and to establish an Antichristian iurisdiction, against the crowne, dignitie, and peace of our Soueraigne Queene and Princesse, I giue you warning therefore before, Looke ere you leape: for without doubt your religion and treason are so clasped and twined together, that they will hardly bee sundered. Woulde you dispute with vs, who are to bee shunned? Come you to learne or to teach? Dispute you, as men to bee tryed, or rather as these that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>and woulde subuert both Church and common wealth; You may prate what you list, and write as long as you will: but wise men see well enough where at you shoote, as hath been saide before. And whereas you attribute their obstinacie, which you call constancie, to the mercie and grace of God, you abuse both the name and grace of God, contrarie to the commaundement of God: <hi>Thou shalt not take the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> Besides, you charge God with their treason and superstition, the cause neither being his, not depending vpon any worde of his. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was not for him but against him, and in his iuste indgemente hee found them out, as I doubt not but in time it shall likewise fall out with all those that are so redie (of whom you speake) that carry so treasonable and traiterous mindes: whereto if according to your confession, they be still so bent, and shall pursue that which others left: I beseech the Lorde to appoint the time quickly, that you may receiue a iust recompence, and peace may bee vpon all Gods Israel amongest vs.</p>
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <p>The rest you say, in master <hi>Charkes</hi> Preface is not worth answer, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther surely is that which is answered alreadie, which yet you haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted moste worthie of answere. For your bare affirmation, and wordes is no more proufe and reason then a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, is a milstone: no more is your disabling of our cause in comparison of yours. Not ours but Christes, as yours is not yours, but Antichristes. And wee easily yeelde you, that in respect of the worlde, surely, our cause is somewhat more beggerly then yours. For Satan by Antichriste the Pope, doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, furnish, and decke it with all possible pompe, efficacie, deceite, lying signes and wonders that can bee. Rome is a rose coloured whoore, and your Rochettes and Crochets, your Hattes and crownes are not decked with studdes of Iron, but all to beedawbed with iewels and precious stones. Her cup in her hand is of fine golde. Shee is a whore not for<note place="margin">The glory of Rome.</note> euery man, but kinges and princes commit fornication with her. And<note place="margin">Christe &amp; his truth beggarly in comparison of the pope &amp; his false religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> for vniuersalitie it is cleare that all the inhabitants of the earth, shal wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship the beast, whose names are not written in the booke of life, they are not written in the booke of the lambe that is slaine. Hee shall rule, and giue them a marke in their handes, and no man shall by nor sell, without the marke of the beaste. In deede in this respect, Christe is a beggar,<note place="margin">Apoc 13.</note> true religion is beggerie, and your cause is honourable, and you are the Lordes of the worlde. But heere I must warne you that whilest you talke of your wealth and your honour, yet you forgate not to begge very beggerly, the matter in question. If you had wonne the cause then you might charge vs with pride, and take the name of humilitie. But if you bee so good a Phisition to knowe the disease of an heretike, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you coulde not finde your owne sicknesse to the death: heretikes in deede, and therefore pride such a disease in you, as meane Phisitions may see and handle, knowen to all that knowe but little, seene to them, that are halfe blind, and apparant to the whole worlde without measure. But Christ howe base and beggerly soeuer you make him, yet is hee the high riches and very treasurie of God. And as <hi>Augustine</hi> with the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and consent of those sounde witnesses, standing in mainteinance of the truth, had an honourable cause, and the other, though <hi>Iulianistes, Arrians, Donatists,</hi> and all the rabble of earth and hell, set against him in the strength of flesh &amp; blood, had a weake and beggerly cause, euen so haue you, that haue neither sentence of Scripture, nor sounde Doctor, for the space of the first 600. yeeres to take your parte.
<pb n="35" facs="33"/>
your pith is so poore, of these almost 1200 yeeres, that we can neither see nor feele it, and therefore it is a vaine popish bragge. As for Luther, whō you raue so much against, it is a lie that our religion began with him. For our religiō is the wisedome of God before al beginning. Al the Saints of God that euer were in al the times &amp; ages of the worlde haue euer both opened their mouths, &amp; spoken against Antichrist, &amp; you his members. All the Patriarches, Prophets, Christ himselfe and his Apostles: Yea when Antichrist grew, and occupied that holie place, boasting himselfe as God in the greatest times of darknes, yet God euermore stirred vp (lōg before Luther was borne) sundry excellent spirites to controll his abhominatōs, and to stand for his blessed truth: which as it hath gained against him, &amp; made the towers of his pride to bowe towards destruction, so beeing the breath of Christe, it shall not cease til it haue vtterly ouerthrowne him. But it is to be marked how your popish heate carried you here into a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayneful reproch against one of your own names: when you cal him a Rū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negate Frier. If his order were holy, then you doe amisse because of his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, to disdayne his profession. But a man may see what reuerence, and conscience you beare to your owne titles. And yet me thinks this should not so much gaule you in respect of vs, &amp; cause you so to raue against vs, seing he is one of your owne, and hauing so farre proceeded amongst you, brought out (such is the streight of truth) so harde batterie against you. But blessed be God that euen out of your own bowels, hath bred so sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry &amp; notable instruments, to bewray your falshood, &amp; to vindicate the truth. As for his impugning of vs, take you no care for that. It wilbe best for you to keepe your own heads: as hath bin said. We easily pardon that which may be pardoned, euery man seeth not al things, and some differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may wel stand with the vnity of faith. You papistes, bee not al of a coate, nor all of a religion, your deuision is indeede in the bowels, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of substance and weight; and therefore I trust it is a true Prognosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of your vtter destruction, when God shal appeare in glory. You are deuided into infinite orders, &amp; professions, at warre &amp; contrary one to another. Nay your opinions are so contradictorie, as by no meanes, they canne bee reconciled, and so are your popes, &amp; your Popes Canons. At the death of your popes, you are wont to publish, that they are departed out of this life, to euerlasting happines and rest; and yet you commaunde<note place="margin">In their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>after the death of any Pope.</note> herses to bee set vp, and prayers to bee saide for them: that they may be receiued to happines and rest. Yee glorie of your consent and agreement<note place="margin">Epist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 2. 7.</note> in expounding the scriptures, and yet your doctours teach that the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="34"/>
are fitted and diuerslye vnderstoode for the time, so as they maye bee expounded at one time, according to the curraunte vniuersall ryte of the Churche, but that ryte beeyng chaunged, that also is to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.<note place="margin">Distinct. 8.</note> They forbidde a man to heare the Masse of an adulterer, and yet<note place="margin">Popish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the whole life of manie of their Priestes is nothing else: These Iesuites and Friers commende voluntarie pouertie, as an acceptable seruice to GOD, and yet they perswade menne continually, that the more money they giue and bestowe, the greater shall their pardon bee; and what doe they refuse? They had suche store long agoe of the woodde of the verie crosse that Christe died on in sundrie places, that as <hi>Erasmus</hi> wryteth woulde loade a shippe, and yet it is playne by the Scriptures, that <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cyreneus</hi> did carrie it. They celebrate and stande greately vppon the praise of their Relikes, whiche they aduouche to bee the same, that they woulde make the people beleeue they are: and yet it is playne, the nayles of the crosse are increased without number. The bodies and bones of sundrye Sayntes are in infinite places. Susannaes bodye is at Tolous, at Rome, and in other places: they saye wee must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>of our saluation, whiche is not onelie against the Article, <hi>I beleeue the forgiuenesse of sinnes,</hi> but they also stand vpon absolution, vpon the vse of the Sacramentes to conferre grace, vppon their Bishoppes Bulles and pardons, whiche were needelesse if they spake truelie. In the canon of the Masse they vse this prayer for the dead: <hi>O Lorde remember those whiche haue gone before vs, with the signe of Faith, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <note place="margin">A prayer in their masse.</note>
      <hi>in the sleepe of peace: We beseeche thee, graunt vnto them, and vnto all that rest in Christ, a place of refreshing a place of light and peace.</hi> Nowe if they slepte in faith, and rested in Christe, what needed (I pray you) this prayer? Is not this a pretie mockerye. So they recite in their Masse the woordes of the institution out of the eleuenth of the firste Epistle to the Corinthians: <hi>Take yee, eate yee, drinke yee,</hi> and yet they giue them nothing that stande by, but once in a yeere, vnlesse it bee an emptye blessinge of an emptie cuppe: for lyke Sacriledgers they robbe them of the cuppe. Marriage they make a Sacramente, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the woorde of GOD, and yet their smeared priestes must none of it. When they pray vppon their holie dayes, and call vppon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sayntes whereof GOD neuer gaue them commaundement, they<note place="margin">They haue turned the whole Psalter to the Virgin Marie.</note> saye the Lordes prayer in a sette number, and euer adde their saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whiche agreeth as well to Saintes, as <hi>Dixit Dominus Dominae meae, sede a dextris meis:</hi> The Lorde sayde to my Ladie; Sitte at
<pb n="36" facs="34"/>
my right hande. For what can bee more foolishe, that betrayeth their blockishe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, then to make the salutation of the Virgin, to<note place="margin">Reade Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter turned wholly to the Virgin.</note> an Apostle, and to call the Virgine Marie their father? They teache that a manne maye satisfie the lawe in respecte of the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not in respecte of the intent of the commaunder: and yet who knoweth not that the substaunce of the lawe is nothing els but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse intente and meaning of GOD the Lawe giuer? Of like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde is that also, that they say the Pope is seruaunte of seruauntes, and yet will haue him also Lorde of Lordes, and to beare both the swordes. They glorie that they are Christes Vicars, and yet meane nothinge lesse, then to execure his will expressed in his written woorde. They<note place="margin">Popishe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties.</note> teache wee muste looke for forgiuenesse of sinnes from GOD, and yet they contende that wee muste satisfie for our sinnes, by our good woorkes. They denie that grace is imputed to beleeuers, by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of Christ, fulfilling the lawe, and yet they glorie of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse and merites of Sayntes whiche is to bee imputed to others, and which is greater: they esteeme the woorkes of supererogation so highlie, as taking money, by giuing their Bulles and patentes to others, they both sell them and impute them: they saie that Christe suffered for our sinnes, but not for the punishement of sinne, and yet the strength of the punishment is in the faulte, and Christe suffered those paynes of death both in bodie and soule, to take away those euerlasting paynes and tormentes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>teache that a man may bee saued through<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> grace and good woorkes, when as the rigour of the lawe and grace, are moste diuers as Paule witnesseth: Their fasting is not broken;<note place="margin">Alensis.</note> though they gorge them selues full of the costliest fishe, iunkettes, and sweete meates that canne bee gotten: they sweare by the Gospell, they<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> singe continually like Parrattes without vnderstanding out of the Psalmes, they sense the booke of Gospelles, and vncouer their heade before it, and yet they giue the Scriptures the vilest reproches that can<note place="margin">The places are quoted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> be, calling it a dead letter, a beggerly element, a matter of strife, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, the way to heresie. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>By their monastical life, they pretende a forsaking of the worlde, an holie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and cutting themselues off from the pleasures &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of this life, and yet in all countreyes they haue the chiefest places, dwell in the moste notable Cities, in the pleasauntest and richest soyles for fruites and all commodities, hauing their tenauntes to
<pb facs="35"/>
doe them al kind of homage and seruice, and superfluously to bring vnto thē al delicious things, so that they are rich without labour, poore without<note place="margin">Our Iesuits &amp; Monks howe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>the olde Monks that were Lay men &amp; great Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with their handes, from whose super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement frō God, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded all those eerours &amp; abuses that wee finde in Monkes and Friers at this day.</note> want, and lowe without contempt. Are not these (thinke you) like the Monks of old time that betooke themselues to suche solitary places to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd the sword of persecutors, that laboured with their hands, to supply their necessities, and yet liued in holy exercises, that they might by confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rēce, &amp; mutual helpe, one towards another, be made more fit for the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the gospel? Euen as like as an apple is like an oyster. This is the pith they haue had so many hundred yeeres, &amp; this is the agreement in greate matters of their doctrine, which they make a very Chymaer, ful of moste monstrous &amp; variable opinions. What should I speake of their popes dashing and flashing one against another? Parsons the Censurer or some other Fauorite that lieth in a corner for him, &amp; now after Campiō chief chalenger &amp; defender, wil say <hi>these are not in the bowelles.</hi> Surely if the head be against the head, &amp; principal mēber against principal member, &amp; euery part one against another, here is smal vnitie; &amp; this is the vnitie of poperie, that is not at one with it selfe, nor neuer was, since it brake from Christ and from that vnitie of the spirit. Who can be ignorant that is but<note place="margin">Praemonstraten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis Martin. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. platins.</note> meanely read in stories, how one pope hath thundred &amp; lightned against another, one disanulling that, which his predecessor had established, and when they could not be auenged one of another, whilest they were aliue, did it when they were dead, cursing them to hell, and cutting of the noses<note place="margin">Sigebertus.</note>
      <note place="margin">Benno Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis invita Hilde.</note> of their faces, the fingers of their hands, &amp; casting their dead carcases vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth, either to be deuoured of birdes, or into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> to be eaten of fishes. I will but name the men they are so notorious. <hi>Formosus, Stephanus</hi> the 3. and <hi>Sergius</hi> the 3. These are known almost to al writers: and as these heads are out of order and vnitie, so are their Canons and their decrees, sometime as hereticall (as they cal it) as any of our propositions; and sometimes as ouerthwart, &amp; direct against the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel,<note place="margin">No stay in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note> For that which they graunt in one Canon, they foribid in another: that which they build vp to day, they throwe downe to morrow. As for<note place="margin">No vnitie in Poperie.</note> example, in some Canons, their popish Bishoplike authoritie is mittiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">Distinc. 93. cap. legimus.</note> and all the rest are made equall vnto them. But in others it is so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled,<note place="margin">Distin. 99. cap. 1.</note>
      <note place="margin">Distinct. 4. cap. multi.</note> that all men, what state or calling soeuer they bee of, what giftes soeuer God hath blessed them withall, yet they must be subiect vnto thē, and contrary to that order which God hath appoynted, they muste ryde men, and vse them at their pleasures. Somtime they say, it is lawful for a Christian that is vnmarried to haue a Concubine, and in others, they cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne<note place="margin">Distinct. 34.</note>
      <pb n="37" facs="35"/>
against Gods truth. But your owne bookes, as full as they are of leaues or rather lines, so full they are of outragious and malicious lyes, slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, reproches, reuilinges, and raylings: And let all the Papistes bring forth their whole packe of pelting and lewd writings, &amp; inuectiues, &amp; let them lay them to this learned, godly, and milde reply of M. <hi>Charkes:</hi>
      <note place="margin">The chief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>ter of popish bookes.</note> (who as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, of purpose laboured but too much considering with whom he had to deale to cut off that sharpnesse, which had ben meet he had more vsed against such enemies of God as you are) &amp; thē they shall see the differēce and therfore this lie in the entrāce, cōcernig his entrāce, sheweth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> before you begin, you are a mā <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>spēt of al truth &amp; mo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; such is that you say he begā so hotly with <hi>Cāpion. But that his quiet behauiour cooled him with shame.</hi> (alacke there while) They that knewe <hi>Campion</hi> as well as euer <hi>Parsons</hi> did, knewe his milde spirite well enough. And it is euident, that both in the first, second, and third dayes<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>spirite and behauiour</note> disputation, &amp; generally in all, howesoeuer there were som difference, he behaued him selfe more like a man of defiance, that had beene at libertie in grace &amp; fauor both of God &amp; Prince, then like a prisoner in the tower of London, that in the testimonie of his owne conscience, had to answer, at another barre, and felt the gilte of his own treasons: which if any thing might haue cooled him, no doubt that might haue done it. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer you speak of humilitie, it was not humilitie, nor the assistance and confidence of a good cause, sealed with that comfortable spirite of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse aboue the rest, that made him either gentle or soft, but his owne naughtie cause and conscience, that made him to counterfaite sometimes as I haue alreadie alleadged.</p>
   <p>As for that note of the conference with those of <hi>Wisbitch,</hi> which by your magisteriall authoritie you call a vaine pamphlet, charging that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende man, who hath taken such notable paines in the Church of god,<note place="margin">Howe and by what meanes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>at <hi>VVisbitch</hi> was published.</note> against your heresies. It was not set foorth for any such cause as your malice pretendeth nor by him: it was writen to a priuate friende, as a report of it, &amp; procured to be published before master Fulke knew of it, &amp; was also sufficient to witnes, how distrustfull they were of their cause, or at least that they are not at concorde with you in the opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning disputing with vs, whom they deeme, (as you doe) heretikes. I haue saide of this before, and therefore nowe speake the lesse of it againe. But in your wise Censure those reuerend and learned fathers, as you call them: did <hi>very wisely in contemning his pride, comraing thither vpon vanitie, without warrant:</hi> and yet it is euident by good testimony
<pb facs="36"/>
that hee went by commission from the Bishop of <hi>Eley:</hi> and had better<note place="margin">Conferēce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt D. Fulke and the papists at <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> warrand for that his so dealing then you, who for ought that wee know haue no warrand thus to prouoke vs. And if you say that <hi>Campion</hi> had a commaundement from his <hi>superiours:</hi> we answere, that the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of those forraigne superiours and powers, contrary to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of our prince, and lawes of our countrie brought him to the gallowes, and so it will you, if you come not with better priuiledge. But you say <hi>the falshood of that scroule hath beene discouered to you since by letters from the parties themselues, and that there is nothing in it, that maketh not to our discredite, that it is confessed therein, that after wee had depriued them of all bookes, yea of their very note bookes (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to learned men are the store house of memorie) then we asked whe ther they woulde come to Cambridge to dispute, if leaue might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured. And because they contemned so pearte and cockish a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>&amp;c. Therefore wee say, they refused disputation, &amp;c.</hi> For the firste, I woulde haue it marked, that where you are wont so to complaine of streight and hard dealing by your owne confession heere, there is entercourse of writing betwixt, which because your lauish penne hath not spared to vtter, it may bee a meane in good pollicie, to cause them to bee streightlier looked vnto heereafter, and your selfe to be sought out, seeing their letters can finde you out. But if it bee false, why is it not confuted, and the truth from themselues declared? Perhaps you will say, they haue written: in deede so I haue heard they haue, but as much to the purpose and according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>in deede as it was, as men that had neuer heard of it. And though their followers that hang vpon mens persons without looking to the veritie, may be carried with suche poore deuises, yet you must consider, that wee are not to beleeue them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>owne cause.</p>
   <p>As for taking away their bookes wherof they and you so often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, it is answered, that they were suche as had beene lately written by those of your heresie. The bookes of the holy scriptures and aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Doctours were neuer denied you: and though they made a shewe of<note place="margin">Vpon what cō ditions the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes in <hi>VVis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitch</hi> woulde haue disputed.</note> readinesse to disputation, yet they added such conditions, as were not in any subiect to perfourme. For they woulde bee all set at libertie, they woulde haue all their scattered armie gathered together, and then they woulde pitche the fielde: the rather that they might get that by strength, perforce, and with multitude, that they coulde neuer winne by truthe,
<pb n="40" facs="36"/>
knowledge and learning. And yet these men, of whose readinesse and suite nowe to dispute, you make so much vaunte, at the first they would none of it, and your greatest forefathers (as I haue saide) haue vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Conference at VVestminster, &amp; as is allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged before.</note> shewed themselues against it. Master Fulke therefore neither went of his owne head, nor for any such matter as you dreame of. This you and those of your sort haue alwayes hunted after, as men pusfed vp, that make more reckoning (like hypocrites) of a little prayse and vaine glorie before men then of being approued vnto God. And therefore you carry all men, their persons and learning with the tempest of a proud<note place="margin">VVhat the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists speciallye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>by dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</note> spirite, condemning vs of choler, impatience, and heate, if wee speake but plainely, and yet swallowing vp in your selues the greatest sharpnesse and filth of speeche that may bee: and namely againste suche, whose shoe latchettes you are vnworthie to loose. For what speeche is this to bee vsed to a reuerende learned man in deed, to call him a <hi>pearte and cockishe merchaunt:</hi> who in comparison of gifts, trauaile and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the ministerie of the Gospel, hath done more then any one or all the pack of them euer did, for the maintenance of their own abhominable popery?</p>
   <p>Againe, hee playeth vpon another worde vsed by master <hi>Charke,</hi> when hee saith (and that truly) that they haue <hi>nothing to vpholde theyr popishe religion and to defende it, but lying, tyrannie, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie and rebellion.</hi> Heere hee leaueth the very cause, and looketh backe to his owne ayme, and asketh where those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>and hypocrisie are. As for <hi>tyrannie,</hi> that hee returneth vpon vs, because that iustice is executed vpon suche rebels and traytours as <hi>Campion</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions were: His parte had beene to haue cleared Poperie from this iust charge and to haue cast it vpon the Gospell. As for that iustice whiche vndutifully, and like himselfe hee calleth <hi>tyrannie,</hi> because traytours are racked and quartered, hee myght haue remembred that as well theyr executions against the like transgressours myght haue been called tyrannie. But what their tyrannicall dealing hath beene in<note place="margin">Reade the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of France, Spaine, Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Inquisitiō. &amp;c.</note> deede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>for and in regarde of religion, while in so fewe monethes, they not onely burned quicke, but hanged drowned and killed, more then haue beene executed amongest vs these many yeeres: Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>tyrannie witnesse, in the Inquisition of <hi>Spayne,</hi> in the murthers of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> the blooddie slaughters procured by their meanes in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and all the dominions and kingdomes els where in
<pb facs="37"/>
the worlde, where Antichriste their Pope hath had any dominion. As for his gentle admonitiō to vs whō in contempt he calleth <hi>Ministers,</hi> wherein hee doth so friendly aduise vs for our good, to <hi>confesse our fcare in plaine wordes:</hi> wee will consider of that at further leasure. In the meane time, if hee finde vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>away and leaue our places emptie, let him hardly possesse them &amp; keepe thē, if hee can: and if he and all the rest of thē, as many as shal write, dispute or contend for their <hi>Maozim,</hi> and false religion, shall finde vs too fewe to match them, or too weake to answere them, yet let them not fat their heartes in their sinne, &amp; crie out a victorie against God and against his truth, who is Almightie, and which standeth fast, and shall in the ende preuaile against all their cursed treacherie.</p>
   <p>Another thing he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>at, is master <hi>Charkes</hi> modest &amp; honest defence of master <hi>Hanmer,</hi> hee hauing charged them that nothing could bee had either from the one or the other but words: and why forsooth? Because the disputation cannot bee procured and perfourmed by them, being priuate men, vpon whose warrant, yet if they would like to come, it is like they woulde bee readie, to encounter them, and perfourme the disputation in deede. But because master <hi>Charke</hi> will defende master <hi>Hanmer,</hi> whō by a Rethoricall diminution hee laboureth to abase, with some praise of the one, and disgrace of the other: hee hath raked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and laide out of an heape (as hee saith) of <hi>his fooleries and false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode patched (for sooth) after the fashion of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, some fewe thinges.</hi> But surely if a man woulde but take a little paines, to rake in their dounge, I meane not onely in the foolish writings of many their worshipfull writers, that haue written in controuersies against the religion of Christe, but much more in their patched confuse sermons, he shoulde finde nothing els but ridiculous absurdities, blasphemous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and fooleries, such as woulde make a mans eares to glowe and to tingle either in heating or reading them. I referre the Reader for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies, but to <hi>Eckius, Blyndasinus, Aloysius, Lypomanus, Topiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full writers of Papists.</note>
      <hi>Grenewith, Frier Perine, Tefflerus, Marshall,</hi> and all the rest of that sort not reckoned amongst the best learned: and as for their sermons they are well worse. Hee may bee ashamed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that wee patch our Sermons: For his patches vse nothing but patcherie, whilest their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings are nothing but pratings, toyes &amp; fancies of their owne denising, as farre from the taste of Gods spirite, and the knowledge of the woorde of God, as them selues are from all spirituall feeling and taste of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse
<pb n="39" facs="37"/>
demne it, vnlesse it be done warilie. Sometime they say, if the Pope bee<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 4. 7. Papa.</note> founde negligent of his own saluation and of his brethrens, if he be foūd<note place="margin">De concess. pr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendae tit. 4. cap. 2. ad Apost.</note> vnprofitable, and remisse in his businesse, and altogether without anie goodnes, so that he hurt himselfe and others, &amp; lead thē by whole heapes<note place="margin">Dist. 37. cap. relatum.</note> into hel to the diuel: yet it is not lawful for any mortal man to reprooue him, or to say, sir why doe you so? the reason is, because he is to iudge all<note place="margin">Dist. 16.</note>
      <note place="margin">Causa 27. q. 2.</note> men, and to be iudged of no man &amp;c. And yet their Rubricke gainsayeth<note place="margin">Ca. ter. di.</note> that same blasphemous Canon, as also the Canon admonendi, &amp; <hi>Causa</hi>
      <note place="margin">Dist. 2. de poenit.</note>2.<hi>quest.</hi> 7. It were infinite and tedious to followal, but as they are one<note place="margin">Cap Cbaritas.</note>
      <note place="margin">Dist. 5. de Cōse. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> against another, so they are against themselues: and against their other general doctrine, in many things confirming that, which they so persecute<note place="margin">De consec. distin 2. cap. Quid sit sanguis.</note> with fire &amp; faggotin vs: as for example. <hi>Clement</hi> the Pope saith: that the holy scripture is to be interpreted by it self. The canōs of the Apostles are<note place="margin">Also <hi>ca. Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus.</hi>
      </note> reiected out of <hi>Isiodore,</hi> because they were made by heretikes. It is saide, nothing is to be forbidden that the scriptures forbid not: They teach that<note place="margin">Cap. 22. q.</note> finnes are forgiuen through faith only, &amp; the promise of pardon may be<note place="margin">Dist. 99. cap. 1.</note> obtayned. Againe, they affirme that we being the sonnes of wrath, cānot<note place="margin">Also <hi>dist.</hi> 4. <hi>cap. multi.</hi>
      </note> be saued but through faith in Christ the mediator. And they allowe the<note place="margin">Glossa dist. 23. cap. prae terea.</note> Sacrament to be ministred to the lay people in both kinds, and the glosse<note place="margin">Dist. 93. Ca.</note> is not against it. Against their counterfeit supremacie also, <hi>Cyprian</hi> the<note place="margin">Hadrianus.</note> pope saith, that the other apostles were of the same authority that Peter<note place="margin">Dist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> was. The supremacie of the pope is reiected in the Church, neither hath<note place="margin">Ca. 21. q. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>&amp; cap. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 3. Vnio.</note> the Pope al things in the closet of his breast. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>also the right of choosing the pope, and appoynting the apostolical See vnto the Emperor.<note place="margin">Dist. 43. cap. Si rector.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, they take away the pluralitie of benefices, and ordeine that one<note place="margin">Dist. 38. cap. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noran.</note> priest, shal not haue many churches committed to his charge. They teach as we doe, that al the dutie of priests (as they cal them) consisteth in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,<note place="margin">Dist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. cap. Presbit.</note> and that this duetie also belongeth to Bishops. They forbid their Clarkes to be present at marriage feastes, or to haunte ale houses or ta<note place="margin">Dist. 44. cap. Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> uernes, they must haue no cōuersation with women; the masse of a priest<note place="margin">Dist. 81. cap. Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> which keepeth a whore may not be heard. Their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>that haue not the gift of chastitie may marrie. Their mōkes according to their names must<note place="margin">Dist. 32. cap. Nullus Ca.</note> be solitarie: they may not buyld their monasteries in cities: they must not<note place="margin">Cap. 33. 9. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> be vagrauntes, but get their liuing by the labour of their handes: their Nunnes must not cut their haire, they must deuise no more newe orders,<note place="margin">Dist. 28. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Syracus.</note> but rather keepe one of the best approued. Their auricular confession is<note place="margin">Dist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>&amp;c.</note>
      <note place="margin">Dist. 30. Causa 27. quaest. 2. Dist. 31. cap. Quoniam.</note>
      <note place="margin">Hieron. cap. Si cupis. De consec. Dist. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 30, cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <note place="margin">Sub Innocentio 3. 12. 15. Greg. in decretis lib. 3. dist. 1. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 13. q. 2.</note>
      <pb facs="38"/>
not necessary to saluation, but rather an ordinance of man. And as their canons are, so also are their councels &amp; their interpretations one against another, as hath beene shewed before. The councel of Basil condemneth Eugenius the pope, and hee againe condemneth the whole councel. The contentions &amp; brawles of Monkes and Friers, they are infinite and known, their schismes long &amp; horrible, during many yeres: the mendicāts against the vniuersitie of Paris, &amp; al other orders, &amp; nowe the lesuires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>the bel a way, &amp; ourgoe al others. The Sententionarists and school<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they also agree like cattes and dogges: the writings of Catharin the Archbish, are against <hi>de Soto, Caietane,</hi> is against others. <hi>Tapper</hi> both a gainst <hi>Pighius, Catharine,</hi> &amp; <hi>Durand,</hi> &amp; al the rest. Sometimes they teach concerning iustification, that by only faith in the passion of Christ<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 2. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. super 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. dist. 15. Ambr. Catharin. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> our sinnes are forgiuen, and the promise of pardon to be laide holde of by this onely meane. Another time they teach that Christ hath satisfied for original sins &amp; actual sins going before baptisme: but that we must satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for the rest afterwards. Againe Christ hath satisfied through sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie;<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> but not by efficiency and participation of fruit: Christ hath satisfied<note place="margin">Tapper art. 6.</note> for the fault but not for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, for wee must satisfie for that. Faith doth iustifie <hi>initiatiuè</hi> but not <hi>consummatiuè,</hi> that is, it begins to iustifie, but it doth not performe it. Also precedent workes prepare to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, but workes consequent make it perfect. These are their dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and horrible disagreements, which they cannot discerne in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, not begun yesterday, but such as haue bin continual amōgst them as touching their greatest matters; and yet they can see into our differēces in smal matters, &amp; to make vs at the greater oddes, they can matche vs with such here tikes indeed, as we no more allow of then themselues, nor so much neither, no party protestāts, or rather christians with vs, but with them against Christ and his truth. But the <hi>maiestie of Christendome, in comparison of our poore faction,</hi> as he calleth it, doth much cōfort him. Thankes be to God though the least that yet are best, cannot compare for multitude with the worst that are most: yet he may remember, that wee are not such a poore companie as he would haue vs. For God hath caused his people to grow and increase not from Paganisme to popisme, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of al here sies, as they boast to haue done in the Indies: but from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganisme and false religion indeed, to true christianitie, in <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Flaur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Germanie, Spaine, England, Scotland,</hi> some whole countries ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vtterly abandoned their idolatries and corruptions. And this not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>Maister Charke (whom he dreameth to sit by the fire in his perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,
<pb n="38" facs="38"/>
wherein as in great matters, so in this also he is taken with a foule<note place="margin">So he chargeth him with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king tythes which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>doe not, wherein appeareth vpō what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, he neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>whiche yet were lawfull enough for him. <hi>pag.</hi> 2.</note> lie) may see, but al other christians, whose eies God hath not shut vp in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>to their owne destruction.</p>
   <p>Nowe being growen to some conclusion, he setteth downe what order he wil keepe. And for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>he will set downe his owne cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure wholly againe. For the man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>to heare himselfe speake. But hee pretendeth to doe that bicause M. Charke is obscure. But the truth is, hee prouideth to haue that which he setteth down red fullie of his Catholike broode, but as for M. Charks answere, he knoweth that none of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates must once touch it, vpon paine of the blacke curse, vnlesse he be licensed and authorized thereunto. This is the way that they take, when all the world knoweth that we reade their bookes, and answeare thē tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, and they like butchers curres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>at the worst morsels of ours, and neuer marke the whole drift of the matter, as Sit Parsons, or what parson soeuer els be the defender, hath done, thorow this defence of his censure ageinst M. Charks replie, and in al the rest of his bookes.</p>
   <p>Thus I haue answeared these prefaces, minding not to deale so parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly with the booke: only I wil hereafter deale with those thinges that are personal, which this runnegate prodigal Parsons, (as he is commonly taken, if he be not a parson of another parrish as some thinke) as a heape of filth, hath raked together to discredite those excellent instrumentes of God, which the Lord hath reared vp in his church, for the edifiyng of his Sayntes. And although it could no whit preiudice the truth, as their own writers witnesse, though men had their notorious faults, yet because the holy ghost wil haue the ministers of God to be blameles, I will mainteyn their innocencie, by examining his reasons and witnesses, in order of ech, as they haue liued in their seuerall times, and as occasion serueth, I will lay out of their owne stories, the liues of some of their chiefest popes, the heades and pillers of their owne popish church: and this also I wil doe as briefly as possibly I can.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>