<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107803_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18606</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5134</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107803</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tryall of faith : by the touch-stone of the Gospel, the word of faith. Whereby Christians may discerne whether or no, they have a saving faith. First preached in the parish church of St Nic. Col. Abby London, by William Chibald pastor there; and now published for the further benefit of that his congregation, and all other that confesse with their mouth the Lord Iesus, and with their heart beleeve on him vnto salvation</title>
                 <author>Chibald, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Teage (Teague, Tege), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Samuel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 349, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <argument>
      <p>The Preface containing chiefly an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of one Text of Scripture, that gaue occasion to the writing of this Treatise, and which is also one of the principall grounds of the doctrine taught therein.</p>
   </argument>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecause men are loth to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in the things of the world, therefore doe they trie before they trust: For they try their Gold by waight and touch, before they take it, because all is not Gold that glisters. Now if in ciuill things, tryall be so good, to preuent losse by beeing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; then in spirituall matters it is most needfull, because in them it is both most easie, and also most dangerous to be deceiued.</p>
   <p>Among other spirituall things the gifts and graces of the Spirit are to bee tryed, because euery gift is not a sauing grace; and amongst
<pb facs="7"/>
other gifts and graces of the Spirit, our faith is to be tried; because euery faith is not a sauing faith, as shall be proued hereafter. For Satan, who by his fall,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14.</note> is <hi>become an angell of darknesse, can transforme himselfe into an Angel of light;</hi> not to be one, but to seeme to be one, to the end hee may deceiue: therefore much more can hee by the same his subtill power, transforme that faith, which is but an historicall faith, and which euery member of the Church militant hath; yea, which himself hath,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> into a sauing faith; not to bee it, but to make it seeme to be it, to the end hee may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them that haue it, with a presumption of saluation without any true ground.</p>
   <p>For this, and other like causes, I thought it needfull and profitable to teach my Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to try their faith: and because the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.8. 1. Ioh. 3.23.</note> which is the <hi>Word of faith,</hi> and which doth <hi>command it,</hi> is the best meanes, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs in this triall, and to perswade the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science thereunto. Therfore did I make choyce of a Text, that is a part of the Gospell, to preach on, that doth earnestly exhort vnto it: and it is written in <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>13.5.</hi> in these words: <hi>Examine your selues whether you be in the faith; proue your owne selues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In handling of this portion of Scripture, I propounded these foure things: <hi>1.</hi> I shewed the coherence of the words, which wee call the
<pb facs="7"/>
Context: <hi>2.</hi> I declared the summe and parts, with the circumstances of the same, which is tearmed the Analysis: <hi>3.</hi> I deliuered the sense, by interpreting the words and phrases. And lastly, I propounded and prosecuted the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
   <p>Touching the first, I take the coherence twofold, generall, and speciall. Generall, as it agrees with the matter handled in the three Chapters immediatly going before, and it is thus: Because the reports of the meanenesse of a Preachers calling and gifts, are a likely meanes to disgrace his preaching, and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he deliuers: therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> hauing by his preaching conuerted many to the faith in <hi>Corinth;</hi> the Diuell labours to hinder the progresse of his Ministerie, by raysing vp some to report of him, either that he was not an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle of Iesus Christ, because hee was not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him immediatly while hee liued on the earth, as the other twelue were; or that he was no scholler, because he vsed no vaine ostenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of humane learning in his Sermons, or that he was but a meane man, because hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in no outward port and pompe in the world, as did the Scribes and Pharises: by these or the like slanders many weake Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians being seduced, and <hi>Pauls</hi> Ministerie also traduced by the same: vpon the hearing of it, he doth by many arguments in the <hi>10,
<pb facs="8"/>
11,</hi> and <hi>12.</hi> Chapters maintaine his Apostle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and hauing at large formerly proceeded in his iust defence, he doth in this <hi>13.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conclude his whole discourse of it.</p>
   <p>The speciall dependance is after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Many of the Corinthian Christians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by false suggestions brought to thinke meanely of <hi>Paul,</hi> and to doubt of the efficacie of his Apostleship, they are so bold with him, as to <hi>demand a proofe of Christ spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in him,</hi> chap. <hi>13.</hi> vers. <hi>3.</hi> For answer hereunto, first in the <hi>3.</hi> and <hi>4.</hi> verses, he doth peremptorily affirme, that <hi>Christs power was not weake in him, but mighty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them,</hi> viz. by his Ministery. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he shewes them how they may finde a direct proofe of Christs power in his Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, viz. if they do <hi>but examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, whether they be in the Faith or no,</hi> vers. <hi>5.</hi> intimating thereby, that if they doe but examine themselues, whether they bee in the Faith, they shall find themselues to bee in the Faith; and by finding themselues to bee in the Faith,, they shall find Christ to haue beene in him, because by Christs power on his Ministery, they had beene begotten therunto. And so much of the Coherence of the words, by which the Reader may discerne the drift of the Apostle in them; from whence (besides the principall Doctrine of the Text, which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
<pb facs="8"/>
to be handled at large in the Treatise following) I thinke it proper to obserue two se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerall duties both for Preachers and Hearers.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Doctrines from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence. Preachers Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> Preachers are hence taught from the Coherence, not to stagger, if they heare their Ministery censured, to be weake and fruitles; yea happely questioned, whether a lawful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery or not, euen by them, whom (through Gods blessing) they haue begotten to the Faith, or confirmed therein, seeing <hi>Paul</hi> an Apostle, was no better vsed of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> his Hearers, especially if they shall withall well consider, that Hearers now, are men aswell as the <hi>Corinthans</hi> then, and that the diuell now desires to hinder the successe of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as much as euer hee did, and hath still as good hope to disgrace preaching, by the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of Preachers as euer he had.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> If it be their lot, to haue their Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Sermons so censured, and thereby themselues so disgraced; then to learne by S. <hi>Paules</hi> example, to bee able, and ready to maintaine the same by a iust defence. And for that end to direct their Hearers, how they may finde some arguments to iustifie the suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of their Ministery, by the worke of knowledge, beleefe, sauing Faith, repentance, loue, patience, and the like in themselues or others: to the end, that they may thereby, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fully satisfied, or left without excuse
<pb facs="9"/>
if they shall wittingly shut their mouthes, and not confesse, or their eyes and not see, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Gods ordinance among them.</p>
   <p>These poynts, if they were well known and marked by many Ministers, they would not he so soone weary of painfull preaching, nor so forward to leaue their pastorall charge, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such discontentments, especially if they did well lay to heart, not onely the example of <hi>Paul,</hi> who was not mooued vpon this disgrace to leaue the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> but also the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God deliuered by the Apostle, which is,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.25.</note> That <hi>the seruant of the Lord must not striue, but bee gentle vnto all men, apt to teach, patient in meeknes, instructing those that oppose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, if God peraduenture will giue them repentance, to the acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Truth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Hearers also, and ordinary Christians may hence learne their duty:</p>
   <p n="1">
      <note place="margin">Hearers Duty.</note>
      <hi>1.</hi> To examine themselues of the fruit and effect of the Sermons of their owne Pastors and Preachers, and to try themselues, if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by happely, knowledge, and beleefe, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and faith in Christ, with other graces, haue beene wrought in them, that so they may either iustifie Gods ordinance in its suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie, for their present comfort, or condemn themselues for their owne slacknesse and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proficiencie
<pb facs="9"/>
for their future amendment.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> If by examination they shall find the Ministery of their Preachers to haue beene effectuall among them, by the worke of the fore-named, and other like Christian graces: then thereupon to conclude infallibly, that the Lord Iesus hath beene in their Preachers; his power hath beene seene in their weaknesse, his blessing hath beene vpon their Sermons, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may safely conclude, that God hath <hi>set his seale to their calling</hi> and gifts,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.</note> and thereby approoued them, not only as a lawful, but as a powerfull Ministery.</p>
   <p>These points, had they beene well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, and weighed by our brethren and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen that are gone from <hi>England</hi> to the Low-countries; from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> for a lawfull Ministery, (as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) they might haue saued themselues a great deale of trouble and expence in their remooue. For if <hi>Paul</hi> in his time, by willing the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians to examine themselues, whether they were in the Faith, did purpose, they should by that examination, find themselues to be in the Faith, to the end he might thereby alledge a good argument, to prooue the efficacie of his Ministery by Christs power, working through it, Faith in them: then in these dayes those Christians, that by examination find, that the Ministery of the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath
<pb facs="10"/>
wrought Faith in them, (I say) they may see, and they must acknowledge it, a sound argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to proue the lawfulnesse and efficacie of our Ministery here; or else the Apostles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and exhortation were to no purpose.</p>
   <p>There be many that are gone on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> to look for Christs Church, I wonder, whether or no, they had a sauing Faith, when they went from vs to them, and what they will answere to this question: will they say, no? then (say I) it is well they are gone, and that we are fairely rid of them. But it is impossible they should deny it: for how can they, who pretend such zeale for Gods glory, in leaving their Country, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; friends, to enioy Christs kingdom, (as they vse to speake) and to liue vnder a lawfull Ministery, to iudge and speake so meanely of themselues, that they haue not a sauing Faith? What will they say then? will they affirme, they had a sauing Faith when they departed? then (say I) it was very ill done, to goe away from their Mother-Church, the Ministery wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of had begotten them to the Faith. For if they had the Faith, then was it wrought in them by the Ministery of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> if so, then was that Ministery powerfull in them; and then was Christs power in it; then was it Christs owne ordinance, and why then did they go from hence thither for it? And so
<pb facs="10"/>
much briefly for the coherence of the words, and the collecting and applying of that which is obserueable out of the same for our instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
   <p>The second thing propounded in opening of the Text, was, to shew the summe and parts thereof.</p>
   <p>The summe is an exhortation; and in the exhortation, an argument, to prooue the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and efficacie of <hi>Pauls</hi> Ministery among the Corinthians, namely, because by Gods blessing thereon, they had beene turned from Heathenisme and infidelity, to the Christian Faith; which (sayth hee) they shall easily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, if they do but examine themselues whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in the Faith.</p>
   <p>The parts of the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation are three:
<list>
         <item>
            <hi>1.</hi> The person exhorting <hi>Paul.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>2.</hi> The persons exhorted, the beleeuing Corinthians.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>3.</hi> The duty or action to which they are exhorted; set downe by two words, <hi>examine</hi> and <hi>proove;</hi> amplified by the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, their <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>whether they were in the Faith, or no.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <p>Come we now to expound and interpret the Text, which was the third thing promised, and shal be done, by answering certaine questions; and the questions shall bee propounded first touching the simple words of the Text. <hi>2.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="11"/>
the compound phrases that are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of two or more words together, by my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer whereunto the sense and meaning may appeare, and may easily be vnderstood.</p>
   <p>The simple words are three, namely, <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, prove, Faith,</hi> which are to be distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished into three questions, whereof the first is this:</p>
   <div n="1" type="question">
      <p>
         <label type="milestone">
            <seg type="milestoneunit">Question. </seg>1</label>
         <hi>What it is to</hi> examine <hi>here?</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For answer whereunto I say, that though it bee not hard for Englishmen to conceiue what is meant by this word <hi>examin,</hi> namely, to make proofe or tryall of our selues in some thing: yet because the Originall Greeke word is not alwaies in the New Testament so trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, nor vsed in the same sense for the same kind of Tryall; therefore do I thinke it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to say a little more of the propriety of the word, because it will serue for the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding not onely of this Text, but of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther also in the New Testament where it is vsed.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>I would haue the Reader therfore to know, that the word in the Originall, is sometimes taken in the best sense, for a good tryall, and sometimes in the worst, for a bad one, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the circumstances of the Text where it is vsed, and the good or bad meanes and end of that tryall.</p>
      <p>In the worst, when it is vsed for a bad tryal,
<pb facs="11"/>
it is in our English Tongue properly called <hi>tempting;</hi> and tempting, is an using of some euill meanes, to effect an euill end, (that is) to try if thereby men will be perswaded to doe that which is euill: and so was Christ led by the Spirit into the wildernesse, <hi>to be tempted of the Divell,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.1.</note> to bee tryed by those meanes he then vsed, if happely hee might bee perswaded to sin, and do that which is evill. Now this kind of tryal is not vsed in this text, because tryall by temptation is alwayes exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised about that which is euill on the tempters part, and is forbidden in the Word; but tryall by examination mentioned in the Text, is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied about that which is good, namely, their Faith, and it is commanded therein.</p>
      <p>In a good sense, when it is vnderstood of a lawfull tryall, it is an vsing of some lawfull meanes, to effect a good purpose, namely, to try if by those meanes we may know the nature and condition of the persons, or things that we try, whether they be or no, or be good or no, or be so good as we expect or no; to the end we may accordingly approoue or disallow them: and so the Angell or Pastor of the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesus</hi> is sayd <hi>to try or examine those that said they were Apostles,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.2.</note>
         <hi>and were not,</hi> namely, by examining through the Word, their Doctrine they preached, and the liues which they led;<note place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.20.</note> that <hi>by these fruites hee
<pb facs="12"/>
might know them,</hi> and <hi>discerne them,</hi> not to be Apostles indeed. And such a tryall was this in the Text, because it was an vsing of good meanes to a good end, namely, that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly they might know themselues to be in the Faith; and consequently, know, that Christs power had beene in him, and in his Ministery among them, which was the thing they see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med doubtfull of: and for clearing whereof, he wils them <hi>to try and examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, whether they were in the Faith.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="question">
      <p>
         <label type="milestone">
            <seg type="milestoneunit">Quesstion. </seg>2</label>
         <hi>What it is to</hi> prooue <hi>in this Text.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The second word to bee opened followes, which is <hi>proove;</hi> concerning which, the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions shall be three: <hi>viz. 1.</hi> What is meant by prooving. <hi>2.</hi> Why hee addes this word to the former, and <hi>3.</hi> why he saith, <hi>Prooue your owne selues.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>The word in the Originall Greeke hath many meanings, but most vsually it doth sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to <hi>prove;</hi> but not to proove by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the word in English is often vsed, but to prove by tryall and experiment. So we <hi>prove or try oxen,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Luke</hi> 14.19. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10.</note> to see whether they will beare the yoke and draw; we <hi>proove or try gold in the fire,</hi> to know whether it be pure; and <hi>Ministers are to be prooved or tryed,</hi> whether they haue gifts competent for that calling: and in this sense the Corinthians were to prove themselues, whether they be in
<pb facs="12"/>
the Faith, namely, by experiment and tryall.</p>
      <p>And as touching the second branch of this Question, which is, why he vseth two words to expresse one action: I say, that hee addes <hi>proove</hi> to <hi>examine,</hi> for one or more of these reasons, (as I suppose) either because it is his manner to vse variety of words, to expresse the sense of one by another,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.9.</note> the former by the latter; or because both words doe signifie but one dutie or action, in regard of the thing, which is Faith, to which they are ioyntly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, namely, tryall: or in regard of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it selfe, to shew the necessity of examining our selues, whether we be in the Faith; or in regard of <hi>Paul,</hi> to manifest his desire to haue them practise it; or lastly, in regard of the Corinthians, to teach them the great care, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and conscience that they ought to vse in practising of this Dutie.</p>
      <p>And concerning the reason why he saith, <hi>Prove your owne selves,</hi> (which is the <hi>3.</hi> branch of this Question) I say, he addes those words, either because themselues principally were the parties, by examining whereof they might best find a proofe by the efficacie of his Ministery, for their owne satisfaction: or because thereby he would giue them a close, (but withall a mild reproofe) for beeing so eager and forward in seeking a proofe of him, and of Christ speaking in him: as if he would
<pb facs="13"/>
say, Turne the edge from me to your selues, cease seeking proofe of me any further, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to examine and proove your selues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be in the Faith, and you shall easily discerne the faith of Christ in your selves, and the power of Christ in me.</p>
      <p>Now followes the last of the simple words, which is <hi>Faith</hi>; and of it the question shall be, what manner of Faith it was whereof they were to examine themselues.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="question">
      <p>
         <label type="milestone">
            <seg type="milestoneunit">Question. </seg>3</label>
         <hi>What is the Faith here spoken of?</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For answer to this question, I say, that by <hi>Faith</hi> in this Text, is to be vnderstood, any kind of Faith, which in those dayes was vsual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to the members of any Church, and consequently to any of the members of the Church of Corinth, whether a saving faith, an historical, or a miraculous faith; for all the members of the Church of Corinth had an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall faith, which was a beliefe of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Gospell: and in the iudgement of charity, (for ought that can be proved to the contrary) every member thereof also had a saving faith, and (at least) many members of that Church at that time had a miraculous faith.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.1.2.</note> The reasons of my opinion are two, both taken from my Text: <hi>1.</hi> Because they were to examine themselves of any kind of faith; by the finding whereof in themselves, they might find Christ to be in them; for so
<pb facs="13"/>
he saith, <hi>Know yee not your selves,</hi>
         <note place="margin">vers. 5.</note>
         <hi>how that Christ is in you?</hi> Now by the finding of an historicall and a miraculous faith, (as well, though not so much) as by finding of a saving Faith, the beleeving Corinthians might find Christ to be in them; for by an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall Faith Christ was in them by his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, making them to vnderstand and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the Gospell,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.</note> though it were once foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse vnto them: by a miraculous Faith Christ was in them by his power, causing some of them to doe strange and miraculous works, though they were weake men; even as by a saving Faith Christ was in them by his grace and goodnesse vnto salvation.</p>
      <p>The second Reason to prove, that by Faith in this Text is meant any kind of Faith, is this; because the Corinthians were to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themselves of any Faith, by the finding whereof in them they might finde a proofe of the efficacie of his Ministery: for that is the end wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> wils them to examine themselves, <hi>whether they were in the faith,</hi> viz. because thereby they might find it to have bin wrought in them by his Ministery,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.15.</note> for the proofe of Christs power in it. Now not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>saving</hi> Faith, and an historicall Faith were wrought in the Corinthians by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Gospell, but a miraculous Faith also, as is plaine by the Epistle to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,
<pb facs="14"/>
where doing of miracles, (which were done by a miraculous Faith) is said to bee wrought in them, (and therefore it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly wrought in the Corinthians) by the hearing of the Gospell,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2.5.</note> or by the <hi>hearing of Faith preached.</hi> So that Christ being in the Corinthians by an historicall, and a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Faith, as well as by a saving, though not in the same manner, nor to the same end; and the finding of an historicall Faith and a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous, being a good argument to prove the efficacie of <hi>Pauls</hi> Ministery among them; therefore doe J thinke, (saving other mens better iudgements, vpon better proofes) that the Faith whereof the Corinthian Christians were to examine themselves, was any kind of Faith, an historicall, and miraculous, as well as a saving Faith; and the rather, because by all three kinds a greater proofe will be gained for Christs power in <hi>Paul,</hi> and for the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of his Apostleship thereby, then by any one alone, though it were a saving faith. And thus much for opening and interpreting the simple words of the Text, I descend now to expound the phrases thereof, which are two, namely, <hi>1. What it is to be in the Faith:</hi> and <hi>2.</hi> why he saith, <hi>Whether you be in the Faith:</hi> and first of the first.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="1" type="question">
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" n="1" unit="Question."/>
      <p>What is meant by the Corinthians being in the Faith?</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="14"/>It seemes at first sight,<note place="margin">Answer.</note> a strange manner of speaking, as if Faith were some locall thing that did comprehend in it all beleevers; as the place doth containe in it the thing that is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced there; the house, the inhabitant; but we may learne, that <hi>to be in the Faith,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, but to have Faith to bee in them; and the exhortation is in effect no more, then if the Apostle had said, Examine your selves whether Faith bee in you, or whether God hath wrought Faith in you: and I proove my exposition,</p>
      <p n="1">
         <hi>1.</hi> By other Scripture phrases, namely, because <hi>to be in the Spirit,</hi> is to have the Spirit in them; so <hi>to be in Christ,,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.17.</note> is to have Christ to be in them, namely, by Faith: <hi>to dwell in loue,</hi> is to haue the love of God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16.</note> and our neighbour dwelling in them:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8.</note> to <hi>be in the flesh,</hi> is to haue the corruption of nature dwelling, and raigning in them.</p>
      <p n="2">
         <hi>2.</hi> I prove it by other phrases commonly vsed in our English tongue, as when a man loves a mayd, we say <hi>he is in love</hi>; when hee hates his neighbour, we say, <hi>he is in malice;</hi> when a man is drunke, we say, <hi>he is in drink:</hi> so that the beeing of the Corinthians in the Faith, is the being of Faith in the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or the having of Faith in them: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of which manner of speech, I take to bee one of these; either because he had before spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="15"/>
of <hi>Christ being in him,</hi> and answerable to that would speake of <hi>their beeing in the Faith;</hi> or else, because hee would intimate to vs the certainty of the Corinthians beeing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, and of their having of Faith; even so surely, as if they had bin in the faith it self.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="question">
      <p>
         <label type="milestone">
            <seg type="milestoneunit">Question. </seg>2</label> The next Question is, Why he sayth, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin your selues, whether you be in the Faith? seeing the word <hi>whether</hi> seemes to imply a doubting, and making some question, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had the Faith or no?</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Answere. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>I answere: in the Originall, the words are, <hi>If you be in the Faith,</hi> of you bee in the Faith, is all one in sense with <hi>Whether you be in the Faith:</hi> and neither <hi>if you bee in the Faith,</hi> nor <hi>whether you be in the faith,</hi> doe imply any doubting of their saving Faith. J grant, that in some places it may, but in all it doth not: and therefore it is not necessary it should in this, except the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the places did manifestly shew it; which they doe not here. That neither <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> nor <hi>if,</hi> doe in all places of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament imply Doubting, I proove by one, where <hi>Paul</hi> saith, he wrote to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that <hi>hee might know the proofe of them, and whether they would bee obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in all things,</hi> yet did he not write this, as if he doubted they would not be obedient in all things,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> because in the third verse of the
<pb facs="15"/>
same Chapter, (which hee could not forget) he sayes he was confident in them, <hi>that his ioy was the ioy of them all;</hi>
         <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.3.</note> which he would never haue said, if he had not beene confident of their obedience. And that the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of this Text doe give no light to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that <hi>whether</hi> or <hi>if</hi> did imply my doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I proove thus: If they did, then this doubting must either be in <hi>Paul,</hi> or in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians; but <hi>Paul</hi> could not doubt, whether the Corinthians had the Faith, because hee could not forget what he had written of them in the first Epistle, where he saith, that <hi>in Iesus Christ hee had begotten them through the Gospell:</hi>
         <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note> neither could the Corinthians doubt thereof, because after hee had said, <hi>Examine your selves whether you be in the Faith,</hi> hee addes in the very next words, <hi>Know you not your selves?</hi> that is, Know you not your selves to be in the Faith; implying, that <hi>Paul</hi> was sure they could not choose but know themselves to be in the Faith. <hi>2.</hi> Because the end of this exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination was, that they might more clearely discerne themselves to have it, that so they might thereby find an evident proofe of Christs power in the efficacie of his Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for the iustifying of the same; which they could not doe, if they had not knowne themselves to be in the faith, but had doubted of it.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="16"/>By my answere to these fiue Questions, the interpretation of these words and phrases may be gathered; by the interpretation, the scope and sense of the Scripture collected; and by both, the Doctrines may be better raysed, which was the fourth and last thing propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in handling this Text.</p>
      <p>The points observeable out of the coherence and drift of the Apostle, have already beene touched. That which is to be collected out of the words as they stand by themselves, is but one sentence, or proposition, and consequently but one Doctrine; for it is but an exhortation to one Duty; and that one Duty is exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; trying themselves concerning their Faith; whence the Doctrine of the Text, (speaking according to the <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> and particular both persons and matter) is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly thus:
<hi>The Corinthian Christians must exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and prove themselves, whether they be in the Faith.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But forasmuch as the Exhortation was not written for them onely, although it were written to them onely, therfore from the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothesis</hi> to the <hi>Thesis,</hi> from the particular to the generall, I rayse and propound the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine thus:
<hi>
            <pb facs="16"/>It is the Duty of all Christians to try and examin themselves, whether they be in the Faith, or whether they have a saving Faith.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>This Doctrine shall bee the Subiect of the ensuing Treatise, whereunto J have added this Preface, even this Discourse vpon the opening of that Text, vpon which it is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founded, not onely for an Introduction vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Treatise; but for a maine pillar and proofe of the Doctrine, to which I perswade in the Booke it selfe.</p>
      <p>Now (for a conclusion of my Preface) I humbly pray the Christian and iudicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as to peruse with patience the whole, and with brotherly kindnesse to cover or correct all faults escaped the Author, or Printer, in any part thereof: so by the spirit of meekenesse to informe me, of whatsoever by the spirit of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning he shall observe, to bee insufficiently prooved, or vnsoundly propounded, vpon a sincere purpose, and faithfull promise, (the Lord knoweth) to altar any thing in that kind, at the next Impression: (if ever in the iudgement of the Church it be thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it) if I shall not be able to satisfie them, by bringing better reasons for the proofe of that I have written, then they for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe thereof.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>