<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ A Briefe consideration of the Publi∣shers Preface to Maister Charke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107734_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18440</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5008</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ A Briefe consideration of the Publi∣shers Preface to Maister Charke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answeare for the time, vnto that foule, and wicked Defence of the censure, that was giuen vpon M. Charkes booke, and Meredith Hanmers : Contayning a maintenance of the credite and persons of all those woorthie men: namely, of M. Luther, Caluin, Bucer, Beza, and the res of those godlie ministers of Gods worde, whom he, with a shamelesse penne most slanderously hath sought to deface: finished sometime sithence: and now published for the stay of the Christian reader till Maister Charkes booke come foorth</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smith, Toby</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>1, 5, 7-107, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="3" facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ A Briefe consideration of the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shers Preface to Maister Charke.</head>
   <p>I Meane not to stande vpon words other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then as they comprehend most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest and palpable vntruthes, such as all the world may euen handle. For I know and can witnes, that there is no cause so euil, no doctrine so false and wicked, but that Sathans instruments are furnished,<note place="margin">Sathās instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine euill cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note> from that strong spirite of illusion, to say somewhat in maintenance of it. Wee are eloquent enough by nature, to speake naughtily, and what errour was there euer so grosse that you Papistes coulde not pounze out, and cast some cunning colour vpon it: we know that Antichrist your head shalbe furnished from Sathan his Grandsier, <hi>with al efficacie of deceipt,</hi> yea he <hi>shal come with al power, with signes</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Thess. 2.</note>
      <hi>and lying wonders, with al deceipt of vnrighteousnes in them that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> hauing a <hi>shameful mouth,</hi> and a shamelesse forehead to deceiue the<note place="margin">Luke 21.</note> reprobate. But al this cannot deceaue vs, to whom the Lord hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed mercie, and hath giuen a discerning spirite.</p>
   <p>Concerning M. Charkes long <hi>expectation</hi> therfore, of your promised reioynder for any truth or honestie that he may find in it, it had bin bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the credite of the Writer, it had beene smothered in the begetting and bringing forth, then to haue seene the light, being such an vnnaturall monster, and whiche for the goodnes of it, might haue come foorth, in as sodaine and vntimely a birth as the former did. But where you say, that he <hi>should ghesse at the long trauel, nay, that he knoweth &amp; is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>to the cause thereof,</hi> Surely herein you shew your impudencie. For if he had looked for it, why might it not haue come out long or this? Assoone as the former, for any thing that is in it better. O but <hi>Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath letted, you are destitute of al helpes:</hi> Indeede it is great pitie<note place="margin">No helpes are to be allowed to the wicked.</note> that you should not haue <hi>fullibertie, rest, Libraries, Conference, &amp;c.</hi> to write against the truth, to disquiet her Maiesties subiects, to turne our happie peace into trouble, to practise your treasons: and to broche your heresies to the whole worlde. You complaine like murtherers and
<pb facs="5"/>
theeues because you cannot murther and kil freely.</p>
   <p>Where you threaten further kindnes, that <hi>bee inpart knew that the authour addressed himselfe to a defense, and that the print was disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,</hi> that is euen as true as the other. For ought that euer hee<note place="margin">A popish nest discouered in Oxford shire, where theyr presse &amp; printe was taken, and their workes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> coulde heare or vnderstande, there was no such copie taken with your seditious furniture. In deede some other of your follies were met withall, your nest was discouered, and your cockatrises egges, before they were fully hatched, were broken and dispearsed. But all this is to shew how master <hi>defender</hi> was hindered, and yet what a man he is, that amidst so many losses, hath wrought such a wonder. <hi>Parturiunt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; nascitur ridiculus mus:</hi> The mountaines swell, and there is borne a ridiculous mouse.</p>
   <p>Againe, it was pitie that hee kept not his first resolution vppon the<note place="margin">Iames 1. 8.</note> difficulties alleadged: but a wauering minded man, is inconstant in all his wayes, hee woulde and hee woulde not answere: <hi>Especially ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Charkes booke answering it self,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Of this also he complaineth in the last diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the last preface, which made him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth, to set down his own censure againe at large.</note>
      <hi>being very obscure in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and very weake,</hi> so as it needed no confutation, and <hi>most of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Campion the subiect of the whole matter was now taken, whome wee had so long desired and thirsted after:</hi> but I wonder, whence you drewe such a conclusion, that therefore you looked hee should <hi>bee dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted withal, according to reason, and al our owne promises, openly and publikely, &amp;c.</hi> Was it like that this should giue you any hope, &amp; make you slacke so necessarie a work? no, no, you knewe full well, that whensoeuer you attempted to confute the truth, you should but wash a tile: and if master Charkes booke had beene so easie a pill, for you to swallowe, wee should haue heard of it long ere this: or if it had answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it self your foolish paines might haue been well enough spared. And<note place="margin">But hee knewe well enough by M. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>answere that such disputatiō was dangerous &amp; inconueniēt</note> as for <hi>Campions being taken,</hi> whom you call the <hi>subiect</hi> of the matter, whereby you confesse a man to bee the foundation of your whole work: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>shold his being takē hinder your co urse: Where did any one of vs. much lesse al, promise him or you, any such opē &amp; free disputatiō? Should wee promise that which was not in our power? or if we had been so foo, lish, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>men to haue promised, as he and the rest of you, haue been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>to challenge, how should we haue perfourmed it? Surely I<note place="margin">Disputation.</note> thinke you suppose vs to bee princes, to doe what we lift: because you are insolent, &amp; take vpon you, that for which you haue no warrant.</p>
   <p>Of like consequence is it that you say, <hi>we desired his taking:</hi> whereby you would insinuate, that we thirsted for his death: no no, it is you who
<pb n="4" facs="5"/>
haue alwayes thirsted for blood: we wished him more feare of God, and<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>men.</note> grace, to haue holden him in duety and obedience both towardes him and his Soueraigne, then had he not come to that shameful and deserued end he came to.</p>
   <p>Concerning <hi>our handling him when wee had him, before and after our conference in the Tower, of his making away by death, without any shew or shadowe of crime, and of M. Charkes following him to the place of Execution, with bigge lookes, sterne countenance, proude words, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilesse behauiour, which caused M. Defender to resume his defence, for the honour of Christes martyr (forsooth); and to shewe his valure in reasoning and learning.</hi> These accusations best become an impudent, shamelesse, and lying defender. For he chargeth vs, with that which the magistrate, and lawe layed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>vpon a wicked runnegate and traytor, whereby, in nipping vs, he doth not only belye vs, but reacheth at those whom God hath set in authoritie ouer vs, and at the seate of iustice. And as for our handling of him, we appeale to all that heard the dealing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs, whether in any respect any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>was offered him by vs. But the kingdome of Antichrist must stande by lying. If nowe and then a sharpe word was giuen, for repressing his pride and insolencie: it was all, I am sure he receiued no other blowes from vs. But what a shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse and trayterous defender is this, when Campion vpon recorde is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned<note place="margin">That Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed by the lawes of this Realme.</note> for high Treason according to our publike lawes, that he dare say in print, that <hi>we made him away,</hi> that <hi>there was no shadow nor shew of particular crime cōmitted by him, eyther against Prince or coūtrie.</hi> If his onely Religion, (which yet is high Treason against God, and deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth death an hundreth times more, then Treason against a Prince or countrey) had beene the cause of his death, why is not the same procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with <hi>Watson, Fecknam, Metham,</hi> and the rest at Wisbitch? Why are <hi>Bosgraue</hi> and others, that now vpon better aduise acknowledge her<note place="margin">Witnesse that little Booke set forth of their answeres to those inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the handes of those wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners that dealt with thē.</note> Maiesties foueraignty, and dominion, whether the Pope confesse it or no, (though the law (I say) haue passed vpon them) why are they spared? But they care not whom they strike, and this is the account they make of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to charge them with crueltie, that they may mainteyne their whelpes.</p>
   <p>For the other part of this accusation concerning M. Charke, it needeth no confutation, they that know the man, know him to be no cruell man, and if he followed <hi>Campion</hi> to the deserued place of his execution, he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>as other men did, desirous to winne him to saluation. His
<pb facs="6"/>
lookes and countenance were neither <hi>bigge</hi> nor <hi>sterne,</hi> his wordes were<note place="margin">* You imagine euery man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>like your popes, &amp; popes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: such as Pandolphus &amp; August. were, of whose pride and big lookes euery story is full.</note> neither <hi>proude</hi> nor <hi>mercilesse,</hi> but humble and ful of mercie to haue dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen <hi>Campion</hi> to repentance, if it had beene the good will of God. These properties are inseparable to blood thirstie Papistes, who in Queene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>and in other times since, haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>nothing but crueltie &amp; pride, ioyning with their wordes, swordes; and alwaies concluding with faggot and fire, when they were not able, to doe anie thing with other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. As for his <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> let that appeare as it is, I hope he hath so learned the truth, that he shalbe able to mainteyne it agaynst al your falshood, and if he had not, yet why should the credite of the trueth of God, depend vpon any mans learning: lesse boast, &amp; more roste would make vs better like your prouision.</p>
   <p>That you haue bin so good vnto vs <hi>amiddest so many disturbaunces, when you could not giue vs the whole, yet to send vs a part,</hi> we haue in some sort to thanke you for your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: And specially you (M. Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher) that are so forwarde; but seeing maister defender taking this matter in hand after the death of <hi>good Campion</hi> (as you trayterously cal him, your new dubbed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, but indeede a traitour, for such commonly are your martyrs now a daies) <hi>was so disturbed with</hi> our <hi>spies, Searchers &amp; other persecutors,</hi> I wold wish you to take heed, least you gleane not that which <hi>Cāpion</hi> hath scattered. For certainly if once they catch you, though you should be a Lords fellow, they wil hinder your occupatiō &amp; giue you the reward of a traitor, that thus defēd traitors, scatter your seditious &amp; dāgerous pamphlets &amp; libels against true religion, &amp; the state of the lād. You are not like then to deale brokenly but wholly. The hempe wil be strong enough. And though in our <hi>Princes fauour wee haue gotten</hi> the <hi>start before you,</hi> yet surely you wil get the start before vs in another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, wherein I trust we shal neuer ouertake you. We wil alwayes giue you leaue to haue that aduantage.</p>
   <p>But wheras you speake of our <hi>following the matter with such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, that we allow you no one iot either of curtesy or humanity, or of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable indifferēcy,</hi> it is but a Rhetorical lie. We haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>neither so ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest nor egar, as we ought to haue been, with such obstinate heretikes as you are: we haue talked, conferred, writtē &amp; printed too much with you. For there is no hope in you, &amp; we ought after 2. or 3. admonitiōs by the counsel of the holy ghost to auoid you. But woulde you in good sadnes so<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 10.</note> faine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>with vs? Would you so faine write, conferre &amp; dispute in this<note place="margin">All the sort of them haue lōg agoe testified that there is no disputing with vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>they might haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and vse their old argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: reade their note in the Testament of Rhemes vpō the forenamed place. Harding Apolo. fol. 20. 25. 115. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Stapletō pag. 22. &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite others. Defence. fol. 3.</note> last gaspe of your Romish religiō, contrary to the direction of al your holy fathers &amp; founders? Why, who hath giuen you this commission? Are we
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>
absolued (man) that you may deale with vs? Is not the popes blacke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>yet vpō vs? If it be, wil you haue entercourse with vs? Wel, I know your meaning, you would confer with vs if you might get vs in your mouthes, as the wolfe doth with the sheepe, or as the Foxe doth with the lambes: set you vp againe in your chaires, and put the Sword in your hand, &amp; let you alone, you wil be good enough for vs.</p>
   <p>But it is a wonder to heare how diligēt you make vs; indeed you teach vs what to do, &amp; by your selues, that were so egar against vs for doing good, you teach vs what to doe against your euil. For if we had vtterly <hi>secluded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>frō speech, conference, writing, printing, disputing and stopped</hi> the course of your bookes, as you haue done ours, &amp;c, You had not beene so wilful, as now you are. If we had <hi>attached,</hi> driuē <hi>away, put in prisō, rent on racke &amp; put to death such traitors as you are, &amp; stil shew your selues to be,</hi> both religion for the church, &amp; peace for the cōmon wealth, had bin more assured. If we had left no <hi>Innes, Tauerns, fieldes, stables, barnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>vnsearched</hi> for such vermin, where yet belike you &amp; your cōpanions haue had your haunts, this garboile had bin long agoe euded: our rebelliōs in the North &amp; in Irelād, had bin preuēted &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>your seditious bookes like wild fire, would not haue come tūbling foorth so fast, nor you had such means of your inuasiō against the truth: so many yong gētlemen, &amp; silly soules in the lād had not bin so corrupted, &amp; yet notwithstanding al seuerity, you stil threaten <hi>that we shall not haue any</hi>
      <note place="margin">Either papistes must shew bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euidence or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>they must be the intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note>
      <hi>quiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in our possession, which you cal <hi>intrusiō,</hi> because we entred not by your popes permissiō. <hi>You wil</hi> forsooth <hi>cōtinue your claim &amp; ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; surely we tel you that we meane to maintaine our iust &amp; lawful right &amp; possessiō: you shal haue hard getting it, except you come with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euidēce. It is not the rowt of your Iesuites, nor of your new Annūcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists or Assūptionists that can so winne it of vs. And therfore I giue you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that if you come not better appointed thē your father <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> &amp; the rest haue done, you are like to gaine no more then they haue done in your vniust claime heretofore: so strong is truth against forgerie, &amp; so mightie is the sincerity of Christ against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heresie &amp; treasō of Antichrist.</p>
   <p>But now you say <hi>the credite of our cause is crushed, seeing we flie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pēly: and with furie moue the magistrate against you; which yet you will beare with patiēce &amp; not be discomfited in the middest of al your affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to resist our falshood more then before.</hi> Example <hi>of your good Cā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, &amp; the rest of his companions, who died ioyfully, protested their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, forgaue al frankly; in the middest of al, resisting our foule heresy,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>and so became pure constant Martyrs of their Lorde and maister Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, &amp;c.</hi> Al this is but a stiffe bladder strowted out with wind. For who tolde you that in our owne conceite the truth is crushed? If we had flyen before you, doth the credite of the truth stand vpon our standing?<note place="margin">Bristow mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue 6. fol. 37. motiue 12. fol. 58. motiue 15. fol. 40.</note> If all we were fallen, must the trueth therefore bee fallen? No, no: though none of vs were able to defend that, the truth shall defend it selfe. It is an armour of proofe, whereinto your counterfeite pelfe cannot once pearce<note place="margin">Saunders de <hi>visib. monar. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 78 <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 130. 734.</note> or enter: If we moue the magistrates, against suche daungerous enimies, we doe but our duetie. You are Gods and the Queenes enimies, vnder pretence of Religion you haue continually practised Treason: you stil dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour her, amongest her enemies: you clip her gouernement, and holde<note place="margin">Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Pius Quintus set vp by Felton, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed also by Gregorie the 13.</note> that she is no Queene of yours, nor of ours, because she is an excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate person by the sentence of your Pope, a forteigne priest: whom you holde a God in earth, that cannot erre, and therefore dare not disauouch any his doinges. For this cause you came ouer, to reconcile her subiectes to the Sea of Rome, to discharge them of loyaltie &amp; duetie towards her. Think you not then, that it is our parts, to perswade thē to iustice, to giue<note place="margin">So Saunders saith that Mor ton was sent ouer, so was Campiō, Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win, and the rest of Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Priestes for that purpose. It is the dutie of al the Lords watchmen, to giue warning against immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger. The Papistes patience is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>perforce.</note> thē warning to take heed &amp; to looke about them, seeing also by your bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, both at home in englād &amp; abroad in Irelād, the fire of rebeliō, hath set on fire, the highest beacons amongest vs, her subiectes led vnder your captaines &amp; cōductors in armes against her highnes, &amp; against their own natural countrey. I say nothing of other nations, but it shalbe found whē mē shal learne to iudge aright, that the pope &amp; such as depend vpon him, are the common traytors, to all Christian Princes in Europe.</p>
   <p>As for your patience, proceeding not from faith, it may welbe a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophical patience, but it cannot be the patience of Christiās. And yet what your patience hath bin, your outcries, stirres &amp; insolencies, your vnquiet &amp; vnpacified minds can testifie. The maner of the death of your new mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, shal witnes to al posterities, that they die not with that ioy, comfort, &amp; assurance of truth that the childrē of God feele &amp; tast, that maketh thē to sleepe sweetly, &amp; resolutely, where as yours die doubtingly, &amp; therfore with feare &amp; horror. But I leaue thē to him, who knoweth his own. But this is certaine, an euil cōscience that is not resolute in faith, (<note n="*" place="margin">New Test. of Rhemes. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. in Io.</hi> 15. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</note> which you teach to be presumption) cannot haue that christian ioy &amp; patience that a<note place="margin">Reade that whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of R. Parsons, in that hipocriticall booke of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>Christian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> faithful man doth feele.</p>
   <p>As for <hi>protesting their innocency</hi> it was an aggrauating of their sin &amp; villany, that being so notoriously conuicted by so many proofes, eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and testimonies, they would not yet confesse their offence against God and her Maiestie.</p>
   <pb n="7" facs="7"/>
   <p>As for <hi>their forgiuenesse,</hi> whether it were franke or fainte, that I thinke you cannot tell. There was no cause why they should not forgiue<note place="margin">VVherein he laboureth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to draw men frō faith to works making them the cause of iustification, breathing out his poysō with a sweet breath, &amp; with sweete words coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his deadly venome.</note> all, that had so offended all: But they would not craue forgiuenes there, where they had most trespassed, and therefore they dyed not in perfect charitie. And as for their detesting of <hi>our religion,</hi> the more they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested it, the more miserable and desperate was their estate and condition; that setting themselues against the truth, had not grace to confesse it, but dyed as it were in the field against it. Concerning the <hi>fighting of theyr blood against vs,</hi> we feare not the force of it. For being shed for treasō &amp; falshood, truth cannot bee guiltie of it, neither can it gaine any victorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst true religion. It is not the death but the cause, nor the shedding of blood, but the cause of shedding it, that is to be regarded. If you wil stil poure foorth your blood for treason, and in maintenance of an vsurped and forraine iurisdiction: your blood shalbe vpon your owne heads, &amp;<note place="margin">Leuit. 20.</note> we are cleare frō it. your blood is no innocent blood, to crie for any ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> but it is the blood of Achab, &amp; not of Abel, blessed are the hands<note place="margin">1. Re. 22. 38.</note> that are first vpon you. It is the sworde of Gedeon, and that sworde of<note place="margin">3. Reg. 2. 37.</note> the Lorde that Christian magistrates beare, to execute his iudgementes<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> against such vnnaturall wretches, that rebel against God, and seeke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction<note place="margin">Iugdes. 14.</note> of their owne people. And seeing yee account them so well bestowed, especially <hi>Campion</hi> and <hi>Sherwin,</hi> and all the rest, I am of mind with you, that they were best bestowed so in deede: Idolaters, Theeues, murderers, and traitours, be neuer better bestowed then on the gallows, and the Lorde in mercie that loueth Syon, and forsaketh not his poore Church, bee praysed, for pursuing his enemies to the graue. And he that in his iust iudgement hath thus found them out, will finde you out also, that you shall not goe downe to the graue in peace, except you repente and turne to him: which I pray God you may doe, if it bee his blessed wil, to your owne saluation, and the comfort of many.</p>
   <p>The two thinges which you speake of concerning master <hi>Charks</hi> person, <hi>the one of his writing, the other of his behauiour,</hi> they shall bee considered in their proper place. Master <hi>Charke</hi> craueth no further credite of the Church of God, then he shalbe found to haue dealt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and sincerely according to the worde of God. Hee craueth no te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie of you, nor such as you are: hee boasteth no further of his knowledge, then is meete for a man of his profession, that knoweth what soeuer he hath, he hath receaued it, by the meere dispensation &amp; fauour of God. If he come short in any thing, he refuseth not to bee taught. As
<pb facs="8"/>
for his behauiour towards <hi>Campion, when for sooth hee was within the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mark this frū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per at the phrase of the scripture.</note>
      <hi>reach of his ministeriall power,</hi> by reason <hi>of his high place, gay appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, great wordes, assistance of friendes, &amp;c.</hi> It is but a stale lying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, to fill vp the booke, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>man is sufficiently knowen, to stand vpon none of these things. If God strengthened his ministerie, to daunt suche an aduersarie, which is the thing that most stingeth you, wee praise God for it.</p>
   <p>Whether his dealing be false or true, for which by your assignement hee may weare the garland, hee will sufficiently declare in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere. Hee is olde enough to answere for himselfe: and when these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples come, wee shall consider of them. I loue not to bring sod Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wortes twise; that is a propertie belonging to the papists, and fittest for them that will receiue no answere. That question allo concerning concupiscence, which is the greatest bulk of your booke, shal at this time be omitted of mee, as being often handeled in other places.</p>
   <p>As <hi>for his other trickes which you say proceed not of negligence, sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie or ignorance,</hi> but <hi>must needes bee of set malice,</hi> as for example, <hi>the repeating of diuers vntruths out of Gotuisus concerning the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites:</hi> you say in the first booke hee concealed the authours name, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is most false. For he nameth him often in that booke. Now you say necessitie <hi>compelling him, he confesseth.</hi> Wherein you discredite your selfe, and bring credite to him that hee doth not conceale them: but yet you say <hi>finding in his owne conscience the things to bee false which he reporteth,</hi> whereas his <hi>authour citeth alwayes two bookes,</hi> Censura<note place="margin">As though if twenty had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged one thing, hee that alledged but ten or two, had concealed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Coloniensis, <hi>and</hi> Canisius <hi>great Catechisme,</hi> he citeth but one, and that not to bee had (which is another lye), and <hi>omitteth the other,</hi> whiche <hi>sheweth the falshood both of M. Chark and of his authour.</hi> Yea <hi>which is more, when</hi> Gotuisus <hi>did not belie the Iesuites sufficiently, M. Charke without blushing, will falsifie his wordes to make them more odious.</hi> Is not heere a merueilous long threed drawen out of a little flaxe, and no bottome? What a fine spinster is this, that can make so much of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, of concealing the one, and aduouching the other? As though men were alwayes bounde to alleadge all, and in the very wordes of their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, &amp; also might not choose amongest store which to alleadge: or as though one authour were not to be cited vpon the credit of another, but all the rest must bee discredited. whye doeth not sir Robert confute <hi>Gotuisus,</hi> and so make way to confute master Charke? But as he
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
vseth in other thinges, so in this hee leapeth ouer hilles and dales, and when hee shoulde ouercome the formost, he striketh at the the hindmost, and when hee cannot touche the hearte, hee hitteth the heele. But what are the matters forsooth, that <hi>Gotuisus</hi> saith the Iesuites holde, <hi>The Scripture is as it were a nose of waxe,</hi> and master Charke saith: <hi>theyr wordes are, the Scriptures are a nose of waxe:</hi> What els? <hi>O infinite such things in the treatise, whiche sheweth master Chark to bee a man of no sinceritie.</hi> Is not heere wonderfull a doe about nothing? But I pray you, what difference is there? doth not hee say that the scripture is a nose of waxe, that saith it is as a nose of waxe, that may bee turned and wrested which way a man will? Is not their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine generall, to derogate from the authoritie of the scripture: <hi>that it is a dead letter, a matter of strife, dark, maymed, vncertaine, a nose of waxe, a leaden rule, a lesbeian building, an occasion of all heresies, which comprehendeth not all thinges necessary to saluation.</hi> Is not this doctrine as full in abhomination as that allegation? And therefore Cardinall <hi>Hosius</hi> worse then any Anabaptist, saith: That<note place="margin">Reade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. Col. Censura. Fol.</hi> 17 117. 220.</note> it is a vaine labour, that is bestowed vppon the Scripture, whiche is <hi>bestowed as vppon a dead and beggerly element,</hi> that rather <hi>wee must looke for voyces from heauen that must instructe vs.</hi> This is the foundation of all their vnwritten verities of man his traditious, which they preferre before the worde of God: because (as <hi>Andradius</hi> saith) <hi>It often times commeth to passe, that hee is wrapped in a greater wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse, that breaketh the Ecclesiasticall traditions,</hi> then <hi>those that are Goddes: adding that example of the Sacrament in one kinde &amp;c.</hi> And yet who knoweth not that the holy Scripture, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth<note place="margin">Pet. a Soto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the Scripture vnto vs, as a light shining in a darke place, vntill the day breake foorth? And Christe himselfe (though they woulde haue vs to shunne them) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>vs to search them, as those that witnesse vnto his, both his nature and his will. Abraham also<note place="margin">Psal. 119</note> signifieth to the ritche man that was in hell, that his brethren were<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> to bee taught out of Moses, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, to the ende they<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.</note> might bee deliuered and obtaine euerlasting saluation. So Paule af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth to Timothie, that all Scripture is inspired from aboue,<note place="margin">Luke. 15.</note> and comprehendeth all thinges necessarie to the perfection of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Nowe hee wrote this Epistle, when in a manner all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall
<pb facs="9"/>
writings were committed to writing, as may appeare out of the fourth Chapter. And concerning your traditions, Christ saith: They worship me in vaine with the precepts of men, and Paul plainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth<note place="margin">Collos. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> that will worship in the second to the Collossians.</p>
   <p>For his behauiour <hi>towards Campion in the Tower, whome you so highly aduaunce for singuler learning,</hi> those that were present can tell the vanitie of this accusation. Hee gaue him no vncomely wordes, but such as became both his owne person, and his to whom he spake. The one, being a godly man, standing for the truth: and the other, an enemie &amp; traitour, both against god and it. There was not any one word vttered of barbarous threat: onely hee might, when hee was insolent, bee put in minde of his place and condition.</p>
   <p>Of the like vanitie is it, that <hi>you tell of his turning and speaking to the people,</hi> that <hi>they shoulde prayse God for his good argument, and of shutting the dores to keepe the people in, to heare his prayer.</hi> Hee might perhaps now and then as reason was, admonish the people to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of suche a runnagate Fryer, who hauing challenged our whole churche, shewed himselfe so insufficient to maintaine his owne cause. As <hi>for hatred in his hart, &amp; putting it in execution:</hi> it is too malitious, to be suspected of master <hi>Charke,</hi> or any such of his profession. You are the blood suckers, &amp; the malicious men, whose furie could neuer yet be otherwise quéched, then with the effusion of christian blood. If I lye, thē let all the places and countries where euer you ruled witnes against mee. If master <hi>Charke</hi> had had such malice as you say, yet how could hee put it in execution being a priuate man? To whome did he euer complaine? What inditement did hee euer drawe, or cause to bee drawne against him? Where did he euer goe or intermeddle in any these matters, but when and wherein hee was called? But you may lye by authoritie. For here are no lesse then fiue together: one that he dealt inciuilie. Another, that hee commended his argument to the people, which you set out tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gically. The third, that he did these to get commendation of the people. The fourth, that master <hi>Norton</hi> whom you cal foole wisely, the racke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, vrged his arguments for his owne purpose. The fift, that when he was brought to a <hi>non plus</hi> in arguing, yet hee caused the dores to be shut and no man to bee let out tyll with one consent they had ioyned with him in prayer, to giue thanks for his victorie. Will you neuer bee asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med so impudently to set out your lyes, when your owne side, (if there bee any sparke of modestie or honestie in them,) can conuince them? I
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
      <hi>speake not of Campions breuitie, that in lesse then halfe three woords</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mulus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>seabit.</note>
      <hi>for sooth, dispatched his arguments.</hi> Why did you not set downe his inciuill wordes, the weaknesse of his reasons, vpon what credite you had receiued these informations. Some Papist told you, and you beleeued it, &amp; yet<note n="*" place="margin">In the dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: the last day, when it was agreed, that both sides should stay tyll their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>were set down</note> concerning master <hi>Norton,</hi> Campion confessed that hee tooke his meaning rightly, and was in truth as indifferent for that matter to the one as to the other.</p>
   <p>As for prayer, though Papists like it not, but turne it to a certaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring &amp; charming, and crossing themselues, yet we are taught neither to begin nor end such solemne Actions but with prayer, and to doe those things that we do in the name of the Lorde. If the dores were shut, that such of your sort, which yet had crept in, and were present at the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, could not get out when they would, it was not long of M. <hi>Charke,</hi> who though he were a disputer, and might prouoke to prayer as was meete, yet he was not the porter. As for the setting out of the disputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is not in you to appoint, it may be they are come, or euer they be welcome to you, &amp; nowe they are come I warrant you, <hi>for an egge at Easter,</hi> of any gaine that you can win by them.</p>
   <p>Now with an O ysse, <hi>M.</hi> Charke <hi>is cryed out vpon for greedinesse of vaine glory:</hi> and how is that confirmed? Forsooth, <hi>there be men that haue iudgement in the worlde abroade,</hi> so in deede there are, or els such blinde bayards as your selfe, woulde triumph before the victorie. <hi>O ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny smiled in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>to behold this bypocrisie:</hi> So there are that will reioyce at their owne shame, and as the Prophete saith, Laugh in theyr owne vomit. Yea, <hi>but if wee had parted with an euen hand, as we ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him in al inequalitie:</hi> then we shold haue had bookes of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph set <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>before now. Alacke <hi>Campion</hi> was not the man, that was to be enuied, but pitied. What triumph was there to be had ouer a dead dog, and ouer a shamelesse &amp; impudent Iesuit? The men that were mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with him, hee was not worthie to lick the dust of their feete. It hath<note place="margin">In the preface to the dispu.</note> bin erst shewed, why the disputatiōs were not published soner: &amp; as for <hi>doctor Fulkes looking in Wisbitch,</hi> neither was that published, to shew any triumph of his, but rather to pitie, these poore &amp; beggerly wretches, that being many, durst not match with one, which they woulde neuer<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists at <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> require before they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>dispute.</note> haue doone, if their cause had been good: but they are greate crakers and small <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. All must bee, as they will haue it. They must first bee set at libertitie, haue all their companie together: as <hi>Campion</hi> set downe, to come from beyond the Seas to ioyne with them: The
<pb facs="10"/>
Queene must lay downe her crowne, disanul her lawes, ouerthrowe the truth, and set them in equall hope together with vs, and then the matche is equall.</p>
   <p>As for <hi>Campions</hi> racking, of which you so often speake, it was for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and not for religion. Wee are not to bee charged with it, but his owne wickednesse, whome the Lorde founde out in his sinnes, and brought a iust iudgement vpon him. If it were possible that you might bee brought in an equall hande to deale against vs: we feare you not, wee knowe your learning, your time and standing, wee come not with Saules armour, but with Dauids slyng: and though the oddes were as great betwixt you and vs, as in deede it was betwyxt Dauid and Goliah, to the eie of man: yet wee feare you not. For wee come not in the strength of flesh and blood, with degrees, and time vpon our backes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all knowe we haue had as muche, and as many as you, but in the name of the Lorde, armed with truth, and with your owne swordes, we shall be able, and haue beene, to cut your own throtes: in the name of the Lord of Hostes, we shal vanquish you, &amp; put you to flight.</p>
   <p>Concerning your proud challendge made in the <hi>name of all your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>:</hi> when we know your commission, and what safe conduit you can graunt vs, &amp; haue you bound for our charges, wee will tell you what wee will do. You are like vnto a man that will cast his gloue in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, and no man will file his hands vpon you. And as for your libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, wee knowe it is not with sinceritie: there is a hooke within the baite, and the offer is but to allure vs to your spray. Againe, if wee haue dealt with <hi>Campion</hi> and <hi>Sherwin,</hi> whome you so highly commend, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>them be as they were) &amp; with their fathers and masters, I think we shal not neede to feare you. For if the masters be so weak, what are you their punies and schollers? But one thing I had almost forgotten, that you do not onely request vs, but euen coniure vs to graunt your request. I had not thought you had been such coniurers before now: But to whome speake you, to a prince or subiectes? Is it in our power when we will after the truth established and receiued, to open our gates and portes, to such Runnagates and Traitors? Were you euer refused; Did you euer come in, and were not receiued? You coniure vs to come, and appointe the place, &amp; then you run from vs, and mock vs: drinke you would but draffe is your arrand. O but <hi>feare moueth vs,</hi> to denie this request: In deede as you say, who are most afearde, they that come out, and stand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>keeping that possession by the grace of God, they haue of the
<pb n="10=y" facs="10"/>
truth, or you that when you haue prouoked, are not to be found? If you bee free from treasons, come in deede with a minde to finde out the truth, are in doubt and woulde bee resolued, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>then I doubt not but you may bee hearde? But there is nothing in your mouthes but lyes. For whatsoeuer you crake, you meane it not: If wee haue not truth, conuince vs of error by Gods worde: laie your heads together, examine euerie point, by opening and clearing the controuersies betwixt you and vs: Doe it by short argumentes and sillogismes rightly drawen from the autoritie of the scriptures, so you shal reclaime such as you think are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>from you, confirme such as cleaue to you, and stop our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>for euer heereafter for speaking any thing against you.</p>
   <p>Then you shall neither bee at that cost, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>endure that danger you talke of. For her Maiesties warrant, I can say nothing, but if it should please her to graunt it, I doubt you woulde not bee so readie to performe your promise: and yet there is great oddes betwixt the promise of a faithfull princesse and your promise, that alwayes haue beene false. And I see not, what cause we haue, more to trust your safe conduit of the coūcel<note place="margin">What cause they had, may appear by their own stories, &amp; by the cruell death they were put to.</note> of <hi>Trent,</hi> then <hi>Iohn Husse,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hierom</hi> of <hi>Prage</hi> had, to trust the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Constance.</hi> You are large and gentle in promising, but scant and cruell in perfourming, and that may appeare not onely by your Popes, Popish princes and confederates, but euen by you all, who holde it for a principle, that to dissemble with an heretike, such as you slannder vs to bee, is a good pollicie. And this trusting of your popish genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath cost many a thousand godly men their liues. What iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment others are of, I cannot tell, but for my part, I will truste you no further then I see you. Howsoeuer a woolfe shall counterfet a lambe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>liue in a house like a dogge, as many of you doe, yet you cannot but shewe your woluish natures. And therefore I am of minde, there is no trusting of any of your offers. There is small profite in disputing with obstinate heretikes. And whatsoeuer you prate of disputation, you cannot abide that true disputation, which shall maintaine the truth: but as <hi>Augustine</hi> once saide, you loue to ouercome by a most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent manner, that you may gather that which you neuer brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: that as the manner of all heretikes hath beene, you may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face men, and beeing conuicted of your treason, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, yee may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>to backiting and slaundering.</p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>As for your prouoking of vs out of the lande, it is all one with vs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at home or abrode, to stande for the truth. Wee feare not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>owne people, we can be content before them, to yeelde a reason of our hope, though their iudgement may bee weake sometimes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>it. But seeing you are so francke, if you will sende vs worde of your reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, vnder a conuenient number of your hands, that you are readie in all places, to trie this matter: For wee woulde beeloth vpon suche a fickle man his word, as your selfe is (whose name wee knowe not, vnlesse it be som great <hi>Parson</hi>) to bee so prouoked: but I say, if you will send vs woorde, your names and abiding places, wee will become suiters for you, that at Geneua, or in some other Vniuersitie, vnder the gouernment of the Gospell, some conuenient number of you may bee admitted to set vp your questions and say what you can. As for making of fermons, you shall receiue our answere, when we know your abiding, and howe to send you word. For the passage of your bookes, it is not in vs to graunt, they that are in authoritie are wise to consider, how tollerable they are, being the very bellowes of rebellion, full of falshood, slaunder, and lying, full of false doctrine, heresie, and cursed abhomination, being full fraught of all kind of wicked immanitie and crueltie, not touching the liuing, but the deade, not the common sort of men, but the honour of the moste excellent men, whom God in great mercies towardes his Churche hath raysed vp in these last times, to display your cursed doctrine, and moste abhominable liues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>is the cause of your bitter galle and spite against them.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>