<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL and truly worthy Knight Sir RICHARD ANDERSON of Pendley in Hartfordshire, the blessings of this life, and of that to come, bee multiplied.</title>
           <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107497_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04195</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107497</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL and truly worthy Knight Sir RICHARD ANDERSON of Pendley in Hartfordshire, the blessings of this life, and of that to come, bee multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the holy catholike faith and Church : Diuided into three bookes. By Thomas Iackson Dr. in Diuinitie, chaplaine to his Maiestie in ordinarie, and vicar of Saint Nicolas Church in the towne of Newcastle vpon Tyne. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 206, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL and truly worthy Knight Sir RICHARD ANDERSON of <hi>Pendley</hi> in <hi>Hartfordshire,</hi> the blessings of this life, and of that to come, bee multiplied.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORTHIE SIR;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our vnfaigned Loue to Learning and true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, well knowne by reall testimonies to all true Louers of them, which haue the happines (as my selfe for long time haue had) to be acquainted with you, drew this short Treatise vpon its first returne vnto mee (to whom it hath beene from its first birth a stranger) to take you for its Foster-Father.
<pb facs="3"/>
Could it speake for it selfe, it would, I am perswaded, complaine of wrong, if I should direct it to seeke another Patron, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not acquainted with any Family which beares a more liuely image of a well-ordered Church, than your Family doth. Nor is there any other to whom I more heartily wish all furtherance in good beginnings and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, then I doe to yours, and to that Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Family vnto which you are happily v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited. Of this my desire, &amp; of my best respect vnto your selfe, and to your Noble Lady, I haue no better token for the present, then this Treatise of the <hi>holy Catholike Faith and Church.</hi> Thus commending both of you, with all yours, and it, vnto the blessing of <hi>him,</hi> who is the sole <hi>Fountaine of Faith,</hi> and Head of the <hi>Holy Catholike Church</hi>: I take my leaue, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer in the surest bonds of sincere loue and obseruance, <hi>THOMAS IACKSON.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>From my Vicarage in <hi>Newcastle</hi> vpon <hi>Tine,</hi> this
<date>first of <hi>Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> 1626.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>