<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The prologue of the auctoure that put this boke in wrytinge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107779_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12110</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22415</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107779</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The prologue of the auctoure that put this boke in wrytinge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The shepardes kalender : Here beginneth the kalender of shepardes newly augmented and corrected</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walley (Waley), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>204 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_prologue">
   <head>¶The prologue of the auctoure that put this boke in wrytinge.</head>
   <p>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S here before tyme there was a Sheparde kepynge shepe in the fieldes, whiche was no clerke, ne hadde no vnderstandynge of the letterall sence, nor of no maner of scripture nor wrytinge, but of his naturall witte and vnderstandinge sayde. Howe be it that lyuynge and dyinge be all at the pleasure of almyghty God, yet man may lyue by the course of nature lxxii. yeares or more: this was his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. And he sayth as muche tyme as a man hath to growe in beautie, length,
<pb facs="6"/>
bredthe, and strength. So muche tyme hath he to waxe olde, and feble to his ende: But the terme to growe in beaute, heyght, and strength, is xxxvi. yeare and the terme to waxe olde, feble and weke, and turne to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> erthward, whiche is in all to gether lxxii. yere, that he oughte to lyue by course of nature. And they that dye before this tyme, often it is by vyolence and outrage done to theyr complection &amp; nature. But they that lyue aboue this terme is by good regyment &amp; ensygnements, after the which a man hath gouerned him selfe. To his purpose of lyuing and dyeng, the sayd Shepard sayth that the thinge that we desyre moste in this worlde is to lyue longe, and the thinge that we most feare is to dye soone, thus he trauayled his vnderstandinge, and made great diligēce to knowe and to do thynges possyble and requisyce for to lyue longe, hole, and ioyously, which this present composte &amp; kalender of Shepar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des shewynge and techynge, ¶Wherfore we wyll shewe you of the bodyes celestial, and of theyr nature and mouynges, and this present boke is named the compost, for it comprehendeth sully all the compost, &amp; more for the dayes houres and momentes, and the newe moones, and the eclyps of the sonne &amp; the moone, and the sygnes that the moone is in euery day, and this boke was made for them that be no clerkes to bringe them to great vnderstandinge. He sayde also that the desyre to lyue longe was in his soule, the which alway lasteth, wherfore he wolde that his desyre wer accomplyshed after his death as a fore. He sayde syth the soule dyeth not, &amp; in her is the desyre to lyue long it shulde be an infallible peine, not to lyue after death as afore, for he that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not after his corporall death shal not haue that, that he hath desyred: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to wytte to lyue longe, and shulde abyde in eternal peine yf his desyre were not accomplyshed. So concluded the sayde Sheparde necessarye thynges for hym and other to know and do that whiche apperteyned to lyue after death as afore. And truth it is that he the whych lyueth but the lyfe of this worlde onely, though he lyued an hundred yeare, he lyued not properly longe, but he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>huld lyue longe, that the ende of this present lyfe shulde beginne the lyfe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that is to saye the lyfe euerlastinge in heauen. So a man ought te per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ourme his lyfe in this worlde corporally, that they may lyue spiritually with out ende. For as he sayde one shall lyue euerlastinge without dyenge, and when he hath the perdurable lyfe and shalbe perfyte. ¶And also by this pointe and none otherwyse shalbe accomplished the desyre of longe lyuynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n this worlde. The forsayde Sheparde also knowledged, that the lyfe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his worlde was sone past and gone: wherfore this Sheparde thought that xxii. yeares here in this vale of wretched mysery is but a lytle &amp; a smal terme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> lyfe, to the euerlastinge, the whiche neuer shal haue endynge. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore he sayth, he that offreth him self, here to lyue vertuously in this worlde. After this lyfe he shall receaue the swete lyfe that is sure &amp; lasteth euer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. For though a man lyned here a C. yeares and more, it is but a lyttle
<pb facs="7"/>
terme to the lyfe to come. Therfore sayth this Sheparde. I wyl lyue soberly with these small temporall goodes that Iesu hath lent me, &amp; euer to exyle the desyre of worledly ryches and worldley worshyppe. For they that laboureth for it, and haue loue to theyr goodes, &amp; vayne worshyppes, Oft it departeth mā fro the heauenly treasure. It sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tteth mans hart that God may not entre and byldeth man a place of no reste in the lowe lande of darkenesse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>