<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107303_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08833</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19117</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107303</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The benefite of Christs death, or the glorious riches of Gods free grace : which euery true beleeuer receiues by Iesus Christ, and him crucified. First compiled and printed in the Italian tongue: and afterwards translated and printed in the French tongue: and out of Frenc into English, by A.G</title>
                 <author>Benedetto, da Mantova</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Hebb, Andrew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 106 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THou hast here deliuered to thee, good Reader, a little Treatise, first written in the Italian tongue, and printed at Venice, after that, translated into the French language, and printed at Lyons, and now translated and printed for thee to reade in the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish tongue. Enquire not of the Author, hee is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, and to know him would doe thee but little good. Reade the booke deuoutly, regard the matter of it attentiuely, it may doe thee much good in these euill dayes. This may be counted among the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test euils with which this age is infected, that they which are called Christians, are miserably diuided about Christ. And yet in truth (as the Apostle saith vnto vs,) there is but one God, which is the Father, of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 6</note> whom are all things, and we in him: and one Lord Iesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by him. To discourse on this diuision and the cause thereof, would be to some pleasing, to some it would be displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing. For what one truth can please minds so diuersly diuided? would God it could please all to become one in that one Christ, whose name we all doe carry. In this little booke is that benefit, which commeth by Christ crucified, to the Christians, truly and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably handled: which benefit if all Christians did true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderstand and faithfully embrace, this diuision would vanish away, and in Christ the Christians should become one. To this end reade this booke, and much good in Christ may it doe to all them which doe reade it.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>