<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right vertuous and well-dis∣posed Gentleman, M. Peter Dauison Esquire, Richard Linche wisheth all affluence of worldly pro∣sperities, and the fruition of all celestiall graces hereafter.</title>
           <author>Linche, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107896_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18047</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4691</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107896</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right vertuous and well-dis∣posed Gentleman, M. Peter Dauison Esquire, Richard Linche wisheth all affluence of worldly pro∣sperities, and the fruition of all celestiall graces hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Linche, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fountaine of ancient fiction : Wherein is liuely depictured the images and statues of the gods of the ancients, with their proper and perticular expositions. Done out of Italian into English, by Richard Linche Gent</title>
                 <author>Linche, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>208 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right vertuous and well-dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed</hi> Gentleman, M. <hi>Peter Dauison</hi> Esquire, <hi>Richard Linche</hi> wisheth all affluence of worldly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperities, and the fruition of all celestiall graces hereafter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipful Sir, the first thing that I here wil request at your hands, shall be pardon, in presenting vnto your view a subiect so much disagreeing with your owne dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position. The matter it selfe I graunt can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge no such graue Mecenas, being indeed vvholly fabulous: but the willingnesse of my soule, to shew some signe of gratefulnesse for curtesies receiued, hath inforced me to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture so far vpon your acceptance, as to offer this strange-borne child of idlenesse whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto your fauourable patronage. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I imitate the fashions and vsances of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Persians, vvho alwaies vvhen they saw their king, vvould offer vp something or other that they had about them vnto him, as a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and testimonie of their loue, dutie, and reuerence and one day the king being abroad,
<pb facs="3"/>
one of his subiects vpon the suddain met him, vvho hauing nothing in his hands to giue him, ran in all hast to the vvaters side, and brought him both his hands full of vvater, which the king graciously accepted, &amp; gaue him thanks as for a greater present. This peece of work (Sir, may be compared to those hands ful of water) being indeed of little vvorth and value, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so very hastily performed, vvhich as it is, I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the fulnesse of loue, and do desire a fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable censure for the same: for I knovv, that as a handfull of vvater is an vnmeet present for a king, so this matter so stuft and compacted of poeticall and vaine fiction, is not altogether beseeming the countenance ofso graue and so vvorthy a personage. But my error herein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth vvholly of my vvillingnes to do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might merit your forepassed fauors, and to discouer a good meaning of grateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, though the meanes it selfe perhaps proue not grateful vnto you. Howsoeuer it is, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate it vvholly vnto your selfe, and craue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience if any hastbred imperfection therin of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend your better iudgement. Thus recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending you vnto the safegard of the diuine Maiesty, I vvish you all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes sutable to your vertues.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all loiall fidelitie most assured.
Richard Linche.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>