<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107403_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17588</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4364</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107403</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A solution of Doctor Resolutus, his resolutions for kneeling</title>
                 <author>Calderwood, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Veseler (Veselde), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are become so Apish in the imitation of the English patterne, that where we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imitate in substance, yet we will imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in imaginary formes. Amongst other strange novelties, it behoved us to have Doctors of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; whether they be sufficiently qualified or not. About five yeare agoe, some ministers aspiring to Bishopricks, were inaugurate Academicall doctors, as it pleased the Arch▪ bishop of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Andrewes Mr. <hi>Spottiswood,</hi> that learned Rabbi, to admit or allow. Mr. <hi>David Lindsay,</hi> our master Doctor, so defended the article of kneeling at Perth Assembly, that he did save the credit of the rest of the Doctors, who had been all put to shame unles he had undertaken the burthen, as he himselfe gave out afterward. But how well did he plead the Kings cause, when he was driven to confes, they had neither scripture reason, nor antiquity, and that he condescended onely to avert the Kings wrath from our Kirk? But the Doctor baited with benefites, and hope of promotion to a Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, which he doth now enjoy, hes since that time not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding set forth in print a new light, revealing unto him both scripture, reason, and antiquity. Seeing the Doctor stileth arrogantly his reasons <hi>Resolutions;</hi> let him be called <hi>Doctor Resolutus</hi> for Scotland, as <hi>Iohannes de Baccone</hi> of old was so called for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, that in this also we may be conforme. He mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth under <hi>Dissipate,</hi> the martiall motto of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables
<pb facs="3"/>
Armes; but I will march under <hi>Colligite,</hi> the martiall motto of Christs standaad, and will encounter not with <hi>Goliah,</hi> but with <hi>Thraso,</hi> for so I hope the Reader shall finde him. The halfe of his book needeth no answer: I will answer therefore onely so much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the matter of kneeling: let the judicious Reader con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre this answer with his <hi>Resolutions,</hi> and try boldly, if I have dealth faithfully. The Lord praeserve so many as do yet stand to their oath and profession, that they may continue constant, and not be carried away with every light wind of erroneous doctrine, nor cast down with terrors and threatnings. Such as are already fallen, the Lord give them remorse of conscience, and grace to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thetr fall. Let us all possesse our soules in patience, and cry to God for the dayes of old, and then he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and repaire the breaches made in our walles, and purge our Temples of the corruptions which are already entred.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>