<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace.</title>
           <author>Speed, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107808_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12716</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23032</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A cloud of vvitnesses : and they the holy genealogies of the sacred Scriptures. Confirming vnto vs the truth of the histories in Gods most holy word, and the humanitie of Christ Iesus. The second addition. By Io. Speed</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 287, pages 283, 299-333, 41 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, <hi>Grace and Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy ascents mounting into those sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred buildings, which are laid vpon the foundations of the</hi> Prophets <hi>and</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, (Christ Iesus <hi>himselfe being the</hi> Corner stone) <hi>are the</hi> Times, <hi>the</hi> Persons, <hi>and the</hi> Places <hi>of the Scriptures</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, <hi>which are as strong stayes, to mount into the historicall sight of the sacred Scriptures, as were the steps (though supported with twelue</hi> Lions) <hi>that led into</hi> Salomons <hi>Throne. Any of which either so laid or mistaken, hindreth the eye of some perfect ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iest, that otherwise from them lye open to the sight: so no man can deny, but that in all humane descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, these are the</hi> Sinewes <hi>of the narration; and in the sacred</hi> Text, <hi>these also are the</hi> Cement <hi>that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer together the well squared</hi> Stones <hi>in the</hi> Lords <hi>building, without noise or stroke, either of</hi> Axe <hi>or</hi> Hammer: <hi>And doe still make knowne, how sure by Text, the holy</hi> Spirit <hi>vttereth a vniforme truth. For the euent of</hi> Prophecies, <hi>falling in any</hi> Age, <hi>vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Person, People, <hi>or</hi> Place, <hi>and meeting in the</hi> Center <hi>of a perfect performance; declares the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant accomplishment of Gods determined decrees,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>whether it be in his Iustice vpon the sons of reiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and death, or in his mercy vpon the children of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and life, and are to the mind of the thirsting searcher, as the watersprings were to</hi> Dauids heart: <hi>and more to be desired then the gold refined in the fier seauen times. The discents of the</hi> persons, <hi>the</hi> Genealogies <hi>annexed to the new translated</hi> Bible <hi>doe shew; and what part they beare for illustration of Scriptures, this present</hi> Treatise <hi>in some part doth witnesse; which, had it beene written with a more learned pen, would haue giuen (I know) farre more satisfaction, especially to such as thinke their doctrine condemned by the</hi> Apostle; <hi>or atleast, of lesse vse then other studies of Scripture. Upon which occasion, and the desire of others more moderatly minded, these paines were vndertaken and gone: wherein I haue rather chosen to confirme their vses in a continual dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, then to rippe vp the assertions of an ignorant zeale: lest in opening the obiection, the opinion propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed proue little lesse then blasphemy: as</hi> Solon <hi>in his lawes forbare to mention the punishment for the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of Parents, lest in naming the Fact, the thoughts of the children might be corrupted. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I haue not curiously carued, but rather rough hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the stones to this worke (as the least labourer, and in the last houre of the day) yet the foundation being laid vpon the sacred sure Text, cannot bee tempest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaken, howsoeuer for manner and stile, it may bee found faultie, in the searching eyes of this learned age. And the thing especially aimed,</hi> How God became Man, <hi>and how the</hi> Immanuel Iesus was the Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah of the world, and King of the Iewes, <hi>beside the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>y</hi> Prophets <hi>many testimonies) the Iewish</hi> (Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ins <hi>themselues apparantly grant: whose owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>in their many</hi> Talmuds <hi>(as they are collected from the skilfull in that tongue) are here laid down, without any fainings or falsifyings of their Text.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Some Chapters in this second Edition are added vnto the first, and the Chapters of the first somewhat inlarged with matters of like kind. The purpose of all is, to shew that God in Christ,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Col. 1. 20</note> reconciled the world to himselfe. <hi>And that</hi> Christ is <note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> the seed in whom the world shall be saued. <hi>In former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges reuealed</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor 13</note> a farre off, as in a glasse darkly, <hi>and</hi> through <note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> the vale of Moses. <hi>But in</hi> these <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 1.</note> last times <hi>is seene of vs</hi> Gentiles <hi>in his humanity</hi> face to face: <hi>where the vaile of the old is withdrawne in the new The search of both, in both is commanded, for therein saith</hi> God, <note n="l" place="margin">Iosh. 1. 8.</note> standeth thy life, <hi>and all must be meditated, for therein saith</hi> Moses, is not a <note n="m" place="margin">Deu. 32. 47.</note> vaine word. <hi>And</hi> Christ <hi>giues the testimony, that</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Ma. 5. 18</note> Heauen and earth shall passe, but not a iot or tittle of the word perish. <hi>It was</hi> Timothies <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, that he had been</hi> studious in the holy Scriptures of a child. <hi>And the men of</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Berea <hi>are named</hi> noble, <hi>for examining</hi> Pauls doctrine by the Scriptures. <hi>Let not then a fore-staled opinion of their hardnesse diswade thee from reading nor a secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red conceit, that many things in them doe not concerne thee, (the brand of that Iron that searcheth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science) for</hi> man liueth not by bread onely, but by euery <note n="q" place="margin">Deu. 8. 3.</note> word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. <hi>And in their</hi> learning <hi>(saith the</hi> Apostle) <note n="r" place="margin">Tim. 4. 16</note> thou shalt saue both thy selfe, and them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e are thee. <hi>Of which learning, the Primatiue Saints were so carefull, as</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron</hi> in Psal. 133.</note>
      <hi>Saint</hi> Hierom <hi>recordeth: that euen</hi> seely women contended which of them should learne most of the holy Scriptures with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="7"/>
booke by heart. <hi>And that</hi> * Taylors, Smiths, Weauers, Semsters, Deluers <hi>and</hi> Neatheards, were so skilfull in the sacred Texts, <hi>as</hi> Theodorat <hi>writeth, that</hi> the most secret mysteries therein contained, were familiarly knowne vnto them. <hi>But not any so great as is the my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rie, that</hi> God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man <hi>nor more behoouefull to be knowne, then is his Humanity, in whose righteousnesse the Law is satisfied, and in his fufferings, the world reconciled. Vnto him therefore, the chiefe corner stone of this our building, be as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>bed all</hi>
      <seg rend="sup">s</seg> Praise, glory, wisedome, honour, <hi>and</hi> might: <hi>for whose comming in power to make all perfit, let vs with the</hi> wise Virgins, <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to enter the chamber of our</hi> Bride-groome Christ, <hi>in whom I rest euer thine,</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN SPEED.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>