<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The translatoure.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1537</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107348_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13919</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24219.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107348</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The translatoure.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A goodly treatise of faith, hope, and charite necessary for all Christe [n] me [n] to know and to exercyse themselues therein tra [n] slated into englyshe</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nicholson (Nicolson, Nicolai, Nycolson), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Southwark</pubPlace>
                    <date>1537</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>lxxiii, that is lxxxiii pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The translatoure.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Her are many now a dayes that vse greate disputacions and reasonynge of fayth, thinking to haue faith whā they can reason muche of it. They know that by fayth only a man is iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stifyed, or made ryghteous, but yet they knowe not the grounde &amp; pyth of faith, wherby a man is made righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous. Yee true fayth can better be felt inwardly, than it can be expressed with wordes. It is plāted in at the eare by hearynge of the worde of God, it is groūded and roted in mans harte, by the operacyon of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, workynge in the same worde, and finally (seynge it can not be hyd) it bresteth out in doynge of charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dedes, the which the faythfull knoweth to be accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table vnto God. And by thys workynge or endeuoure to please God, he conceaueth an hope to optayne euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastynge lyfe, wherin he shall rest in ioy with God: not of dewtye, as one that were hyred therto, but only of Gods bounteous goodnesse and mercye. The dyuels also haue an hystoricall fayth of Christe, and beleue al to be true y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is spoken of hym thorow out all the scryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for they can not improue nor denye the treuth of it. But seynge they conceaue not suche an opinion of God, as namely, that God is theyr redimer that by hym and by none other (be he neuer so holy) they be sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, that in hym only they oughte to reioyce, to truste, and to be conforted: therfore is not theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ayth auayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or an occasyon vnto saluacyon but rather (as sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth saynte Iames) a cause to feare and tremble. It is not ynough to be baptysed, and to know by harte all y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> articles of oure faith although euery one that wyl be called a Christian is bounde to beleue &amp; to know the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) but he must also expresse them in hys lyuynge. Yf I be leue God to be a father, and a creator or maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen and earth, and al that is therin of nought, and yet do not seke all ayde, conforte, and goodnesse at hym: how can I haue a true fayth or beleue in hym? howe can I saye truely: I beleue in God the father almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye?
<pb n="2" facs="2"/>
&amp;c. Herken how God complayneth by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Micue. 1. Shulde not a sonne honoure hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (sayeth he) and a seruaunte hys mayster? Yf I be now a father, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> myne honoure? Yf I be the ZORDE where I am feared? sayeth the ZORDE of hoostes. As though he wolde saye: who declareth hys fayth that he hath to me? who soueth me as a son hys ather? not for ony respect or regarde of auaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage that he can optayne by it: but of the inwarde and naturall mocyon of loue that he hath to my goodnesse Or who feareth me as a seruaunt? that dredeth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshment for transgressynge of his lordes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente. For as sayeth Dauid: They are all gone out of the waye, they are all become vnprofytable, ther is none that doth good: no not one By thys is it euydēt what small fayth is founde in the world now a dayes and how lyttell declaracyō of the same: specialy of tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se that can and do moost reason, &amp; dispute of it. Thys I saye, and that in verbo domini that I wolde of god they vttered lesse wordes of fayth, hope, and charyte: but declared them more by outward dedes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. To speake diuinite maketh not a diuine, but to lyue diuinite. Yf wyshyng? myghte do good, I wolde har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye wyshe euery one that can speake muche of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the same mynd, that saynt Augustine was in whā he sayde: The vnlearned stonde vp, and take in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and we synke to hell with all out lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge. Yf we dyd take once hartye grace to vs and bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>syed oure selues to lyue the Gospel, than shuld not we need to be asked a counte of our fayth, than shulde we go on progresse from vertue to vertue, than shuld out lyghte lyghten the weakelynges, lest they do offende at Christe the heade corner stone But alas for pytye, the greate punyshmentes wherewith God doth and wyll punysh vs comme vpon vs because ther is no faithful nesse, ther is no mercye, ther is no knowlege of god in the londe: but swe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tynge lyeng manslaughter thefte, and aduoutrye haue the ouer hand, and one bloudshed dyng so! oweth another. &amp;c. Dse. 4. Loke thorowe the
<pb facs="3"/>
whole flock of them that wyl be seyers of god, that is y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> cytesyns of Ierusalē: Seke thorow hyr stretes also yf ye cā fynd one man y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> doth equal &amp; right, or y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth to be saythfull: and I shall spare hym (sayeth the LORD) For though they can say: The LORD ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, yet to they swear to deceaue. Where as thou: o LORD lokest only vpō saith &amp; treuth. Christ himself hath prophecyed these peryllous tymes of oures say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge: Whā the son of mā cōmeth, suppose ye y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> he shal fynd faith vpō earth? As though he wold say, no. Yee where faith is not, there is an vnbermēt of wyckednes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses: as sayeth Esay. 59. There is equite gone asyde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> rightcousnesse stōdeth afarte of. Treuth is falledown in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> strete, &amp; the thynge y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> is playn &amp; open, may not be shewed. Yee y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> treuth is layed in preson, &amp; he y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> refray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hymselfe frō euell, must be spoyled. Is it not a py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous case to heare y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prophetes thus complayne vpō oure wyckednesse, yee Christe hymselfe? What do we thynke that shal become of vs after thys vapoure ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thā lyfe? What and yf one man had gotten al the worlde, shulde it profyte oughte vnto hys soule after hys departynge hēce? seing he is come naked into this worlde, &amp; must depart naked out of it agayn. Why do mē set so lytie by faith? &amp; regard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> or charite as a thing lyttel worth? where as. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Paul not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stondinge dot cal loue the greatest of the thre theological vertues</p>
   <p>That thou mayest therfor (good te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>der) crercyse theselfe in these thre holy vertues, as namelye faythe, hope &amp; charite or loue: I haue trāslated to thy behofe this lyttel treatyse, treatinge of the same: whose brefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse I trust shal draw thy mind to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reading of it. For by manifest scriytures (the which be here sufficientlye brought forth) thou mayest perceaue y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> power of fayth whereby man is saued y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> which causeth mā to cōceaue an hope of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> lyfe euer lasting. And thus of inward ioy &amp; gladnesse he breaketh forth vnto dedes of charyte, wherby he declareth his in warde gyft of fayth. So y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> finally he cā not chuse but hope to come vnto lyfe eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> which greūt vs he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> created &amp; redimed vs. Amē.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>