<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE
TRANSLATOVR
to the understandingly judicious
READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107086_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3075</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE
TRANSLATOVR
to the understandingly judicious
READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eromena, or, Love and revenge. Written originally in the Thoscan tongue, by Cavalier Gio. Francesco Biondi, Gentleman extraordinary of his Majesties Privie Chamber. Divided into six books. And now faithfully Englished, by Ia. Hayvvard, of Graies-Inne Gent</title>
                 <author>Biondi, Giovanni Francesco, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 195, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE
TRANSLATOVR
to the understandingly judicious
READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Tript now of her <hi>Italian</hi> vail, presents her selfe to thy
view <hi>Cavilier Biondi</hi> his <hi>Eromena,</hi> being the
first volume of his works, highly esteemed in <hi>Italy,</hi>
among the choisest pieces of that nature; as well for
the good liking which that Nation beares to that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
way of <hi>Helidorian</hi> Poesie (I mean an historicall
way of Poetizing, or Poeticall manner of historizing,
or displaying of the fained seeming unfained adventures and actions
of persons reall, masked under the vizard of invented names:) As also
for the Authours peculiar way of imbellishing it more frequently with
<hi>Ethicall</hi> solidity, than superficiall <hi>Rhetorick;</hi> which gained so much on
the <hi>Italian</hi> humour, as it induced divers of that Nobility to procure him
to second it (as sithence he hath done) with another Tome, called <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zella
Desterrada,</hi> so adorned with elevated grave conceits, and variety
of strange (though aptly enterlaced) occurrences, that their desire being
thereby rather exceedingly augmented, than (in the least measure) satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
incited them by (then more than ever) earnest solicitations to re-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune
him to close up what in these two remained unfinished, with a
third and finall Volume; which the Authour (loth to disoblige so many
deserving and noble personages) is now (some while sithence) in hand
withall, having in it's infancy named it, <hi>Il Coralbo,</hi> being (for the
better suiting with his yeares) the graver of the three; so as he intends not
to shew thee the way of pulling by the Curtaine from before the persons in
his former pieces represented, untill he hath withdrawn his now well-nigh
wearied pensill from his, as yet, little more than halfe pourtraied <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Meane time, if thy liking sympathize any whit with that of the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians,</hi>
I may then hope for thy gentle approvement of having imployed
some vacant houres in translating this piece, which, indeed, might well
have merited an abler Pen, and in that kinde of imployment more versed
than mine; though I would not willingly (for all that) be taken (or rather
mistaken) for a Dictionary-tutred <hi>Linguist;</hi> but rather the meanest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
among those, whose <hi>Genius</hi> (in their lesse experienced yeares) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
either rounded them in the eare with that French Adage, <hi>La pierre
sovent remuée n'amasse pas volontiers mousse; Mosse seldome doth
infold that stone that's often rowl'd.</hi> Or was ever so providently cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous,
<pb facs="4"/>
as to admonish them, that the securest survaying of <hi>Transmarine</hi>
territories was in a Map in ones Chamber; and the safest conversing with
<hi>Transalpinan Transalpeninan,</hi> or other remoter Nations, was by discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
privately in ones study with <hi>Rawleigh, Sands, Villamont, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne,
&amp;c.</hi> Whereunto seemeth to allude that of <hi>Martial,</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Aethereas lascive cupis volitare per auras?</l>
         <l>I, fuge, sed poteras tutior esse domi.</l>
         <l>Hast thou a longing gadding vein</l>
         <l>throughout the world to rome?</l>
         <l>Goe, post away; yet know, thou mightst</l>
         <l>have liv'd more safe at home.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>But suffred their greener youth to be swaied by an innate and unresistable
desire of going themselves (more superfluously curious, thou wilt say, than
judiciously considerate) to search after such out-landish flowers as best liked
their fancy, &amp; having found to gather &amp; crop them off their proper stems,
where they naturally grew (for doubt of receiving them at a second hand
withered, vertuelesse, or adulterate) though necessitated for arriving at
them, to force a passage through many a bushie brake, and thorny thicket,
besides the often hazarding the pricking of their fingers to the quick, in
reaching at them, so fenced and entertwined with sharp-pointed brambles,
and smart-stinging briers; Howbeit, thou maist hereafter expect a participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the gleaning of some of them, not much perhaps declined from
their native beauty, odor, and vertue: For the sooner accomplishing
whereof, it shall prove no slender encouragement to have prevailed so farre
with thy courtesie, as that the acknowledgement of my being sensible of
my own incapability may be accepted in excuse of my not voluntary under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going
(by the Authours assent and privity) the burthen of this Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
more for the satisfaction of some noble Friends of mine, (if the
weaknesse of my deserts, supported onely with a desire of honouring merit
in the proper sphere, where it both resides and moves, may presume so to
terme them) than for any over-weaning confidence I ever durst repose in
my own far short sufficiencie, or rather selfe-conscious insufficiency of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
able to accord the far discording strings of two so different languages.
Yet if this cannot satisfie thee whom I have stiled, an <hi>Vnderstandingly ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious
Reader</hi> (than whom, I know no other fit for either my judge or
censurer) doe thou then but ease me of a labour (which I doubt will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
on my unwillingnesse) in translating his <hi>Donzella desterrada;</hi>
which (perhaps) ere thou hast brought to a finall period, will give thee
cause to entertain a milder opinion of the no lesse well-meaning than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
imployment of my as yet bashfull maiden Pen, in a task of this
kinde not the easiest; on whose behalfe I dare yet confidently (and that
without presumption too) averre the same to be, though (in respect of my
not yet fully renew'd acquaintaince with my native tongue) not elegantly;
yet (by the furtherance of my twice two Summers assiduall conversing
with that Nation at their native home) faithfully (not paraphrased, but)
translated. Seeing that I have (as oft as they would endure the being new
<pb facs="4"/>
cast in an English mould) used the Authours own words, rarely ever (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constrained)
varied any phrase of his, and never I am sure strayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
the limits of either his matter or meaning; wherein (upon the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
of some deserving spirits) I have been the more charily obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
to the end, that such as desire to make that (no lesse pleasing than
stately) language their own, might, without any great difficulty to their
(as I presume thou wilt confesse) no small furtherance in that study, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
this Originall, for depth of language not inferiour to the best I ever
yet saw publisht by any of that nation; For which, as I expect not the least
stroaking of applause (it being no other than a recreative imployment, or
rather but the immature fruit of some spare houres, stolen from the Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard
of recreation) so feare I not the ghastliest frown of censure, knowing
that the scope of these mine (how slender soever) endeavours, aime no
lesse at their profit than delight, from which, lest I detain them too long,
I bid thee and them, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <l>YEt e're thou passe, a word, and that's but this,</l>
      <l>Think not all's mine that here thou find'st amisse.</l>
      <l>The Plot and Authours way may chance come short</l>
      <l>Of pleasing all; if so, then blame him for't;</l>
      <l>Suffice it me t'expresse him in our tongue,</l>
      <l>And neither doe his Muse nor meaning wrong;</l>
      <l>Since to th' <hi>Interpr<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
               <desc>••••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> 'tis held a blemish,</l>
      <l>To change or adde, no lesse than to diminish.</l>
      <l>If language thou expects, then pore not here,</l>
      <l>But <hi>Sidney</hi> read, whose Pen ne're yet found peere.</l>
      <l>Some faults here may prove mine, that Ile confesse;</l>
      <l>Yet load not me with th'errours of the Presse.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Man's apt to erre;</hi> and many a first edition,</l>
      <l>For it's escapes pleads Custome and Tradition;</l>
      <l>And so must this, since, <hi>What's once done and ended,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Can ne're by after-view be well amended.</l>
      <l>To quote all scapes might wrong thy patience; then</l>
      <l>Correct but <hi>these more grosse ones</hi> with thy Pen;</l>
      <l>The sense will help thee give the rest their due</l>
      <l>Meaning, and order both.</l>
   </q>
   <closer>Once more, <hi>Adieu.</hi>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>