<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>V., D.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107356_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14357</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24675.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>V., D.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>M. le Hucher minister of Amyens in France compelled to fly from the pure word of holy write; strucke dumme; and made to runne away : Vppon the subiect of the B. Sacrament of the altar. By F. Francis Veron of the Society of Iesus, encountring him with the Bible of Geneua only. In the presence of the Duke de Longueuille. VVith a briefe and easie meanes, by which each Catholike may, in like manner, put to flight any minister or sectarie. Sent from Sieur de la Tour one of the sayd Dukes gentlemen, to Sieur de Rotois, gentleman of the Kings game</title>
                 <author>Véron, François</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Marguerite</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo</hi> things there are (good Reader) which made me (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of thy eternall good) to turne for thy vse this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle treatise into our language. The one the breuity and pleasure it yealdeth, the other the easines and perspicuity, with which it confuteth, it instructeth. The first suteth well to that lazy humour, which heresy hath brought into our country, wherby men haue little gust to read ought, that concernes their soules, and scarse ought of that, vnles it be well seasoned with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary delight. The other (supposing thy capacity, and affection to truth, which if affection misleade me not, is equall to that of most Nations, and by heresy I hope not maliciously peruerted, or at least not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly obstinate therin) makes me presume thou wilt easily see, and quickly leaue that
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> blind mans maze, of the falsly pure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended word, wherin thou hast beene long ledde round. Both of them, by Gods assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, promisse vnto me no little fruite of this small worke, which is that I hartely desyre for thy soules good, and Gods grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy welwiller in IESVS CHRIST. D. V.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>