<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the most High, Noble, and Renovvmed Princesse, our most dread redoubted Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the fayth, &amp;c. Your graces most humble, loyall, and faythfull sub∣iect Henry Lyte, vvisheth long life, perfect health, florishing raigne, and prosperous successe to Gods good pleasure, in all your most Royall affaires.</title>
           <author>Lyte, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107363_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20579</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6984</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107363</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the most High, Noble, and Renovvmed Princesse, our most dread redoubted Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the fayth, &amp;c. Your graces most humble, loyall, and faythfull sub∣iect Henry Lyte, vvisheth long life, perfect health, florishing raigne, and prosperous successe to Gods good pleasure, in all your most Royall affaires.</title>
                 <author>Lyte, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nievve herball, or historie of plantes : wherin is contayned the vvhole discourse and perfect description of all sortes of herbes and plantes: their diuers [and] sundry kindes: their straunge figures, fashions, and shapes: their names, natures, operations, and vertues: and that not onely of those whiche are here growyng in this our countrie of Englande, but of all others also of forrayne realmes, commonly vsed in physicke. First set foorth in the Doutche or Almaigne tongue, by that learned D. Rembert Dodoens, physition to the Emperour: and nowe first translated out of French into English, by Henry Lyte Esquyer</title>
                 <author>Dodoens, Rembert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London ; Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 <publisher>Dewes, Garrat.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Loe, Hendrik van der</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 779, 25 pages, illustrations, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the most High, Noble, and Renovvmed Princesse, our most dread redoubted Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the fayth, &amp;c. Your graces most humble, loyall, and faythfull sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect Henry Lyte, vvisheth long life, perfect health, florishing raigne, and prosperous successe to Gods good pleasure, in all your most Royall affaires.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>WO thinges haue mooued me (most noble Princesse) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing newly translated into English this Herball or Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Plantes (not long sithence, set foorth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Almaigne or Douche tongue, by that paynefull and learned Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>D. Rembert Dodoens,</hi> and sithence that, agayne by the trauayle of sundry skylfull Herbarians into diuers other languages translated) to offer the same vnto your Maiesties protection. The one was that most cleare, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and chearefull countenaunce towardes all learning and vertue: whiche on euery syde most brightly from your Royall person appearing, hath so enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and encouraged, not onely me, to the loue and admiration thereof: but al suche others also, your Graces loyall subiectes, whiche are not to to dull of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding: that we thinke no trauayle to great, whereby we are in hope both to profite our Countrie, &amp; to please so noble &amp; louing a Princesse: whose whole power and endeuour we see therto bent, that vertue &amp; knowledge (the two most beautiful ornamentes of a wel gouerned kingdome) may florish and beare sway: Vice and ignorance (the foes of all goodnesse) may vanish &amp; giue place. The other was, that earnest zeale, and feruent desire that I haue, and a long time haue had, to shewe my selfe (by yeelding some fruite of paineful dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gēce) a thankeful subiect to so vertuous a Soueraigne, &amp; a fruitful member of so good a cōmon Weale. The first of these, hartened or emboldened me against those perswasions of mine owne vnworthynes: which (vndoubtedly) had put me to vtter silence, had I not bene susteined both with the comfortable remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of your highnesse clemencie, and withall consydered, that no gift may lightly be more acceptably presented to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> head, then that, which wholly tēdeth to the preseruation of the rest of the body. Of whiche sort, when I consydered this Historie of Plantes to be, I feared the lesse to present it vnto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie. Knowing that by your Princely clemēcie y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same being receiued, &amp; by your high wisdome &amp; aucthoritie alowed, shal take such place in your body politike, as in the natural, those do that by the head (whiche by reasons rule gouerneth the whole) are knowen to be approoued and condignely allowed. The seconde pricketh me continually forwarde with this or the lyke perswasion: That as a thankeful hart towardes a natural mother cannot be better testified, then by loue shewed and practised towardes her deare children: nor a more acceptable fruitfulnesse be required of any one branche, then that which may redounde to the ornament of the whole stocke: so I in no wise should be more able to shewe my thankful minde towardes your highnesse (the most louing and tender mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this cōmon Weale) then in publishing this historie to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> benefite of your most louing subiectes, as being the best token of loue and diligence that I am
<pb facs="3"/>at this time able to shew vnto either. And (doubtlesse if my skill in the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were answearable to the worthynesse eyther of the Historie it selfe, or of the Authours therof, I doubt not, but I should be thought to haue honoured your Maiestie with an acceptable present. As touching the worthinesse of the Historie it self, truely that thing may not iustly be thought vnmeete to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto a Prince, the knowledge wherof, beside that it is by daily experience knowen to be both profitable to al, and pleasant to many, is aboue al other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties (the diuine knowledge wherby the soule liueth) only excepted, with so high commendations in the holy Scriptures extolled, that not onely the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours therof are accounted worthy of admiration &amp; honor: but euē <hi>Salomon</hi> that royall and wise Kyng, for that he had the knowledge of the natures of Plantes, &amp; was able to dispute therof, from the highest to the lowest, from the Cedar in <hi>Libanon</hi> to the Hysope that springeth out of the wall, is therefore in the sacred Bybel highly dignified &amp; renowmed.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 4.</note> I wyll say nothing of <hi>Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates, Lysimachus, Gentius, Artemisia,</hi> and such noble &amp; mighty Princes: whose delight and lyking towardes this knowledge of the nature of Plantes was such, that as by their diligent inquisitiō they wittily found out the vse of many of them, so, hauing found the same, they disdayned not to denominate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte therto their owne names, which euen to this day many of them do styll retayne. But argumentes to this purpose, are before your most excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie needelesse to be alleaged: aswel because your highnes is dayly cōuersant in the most cleare light of al both diuine &amp; humayne knowledge, whereby you farre more easily see the whole compasse, then men of meane estate are able to conceiue a parte: as also for that the professours of this facultie be with your highnesse had in such price and estimation, that they are not onely by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie and your most noble Progenitours, with sundry Priuileges &amp; liberties endowed, with many &amp; great stipendes and pentions in your Graces Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities and Schooles fostered and mainteyned: but also as they shalbe founde to haue laudably profited therein, so are they aduaunced &amp; called to the charge of your person, &amp; of the persons of your Nobles. And arte being by honor nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished, encreaseth dayly, &amp; putteth al men out of doubt, that they which so em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the professours thereof, do both well lyke and thinke of the facultie, and sufficiently vnderstande both the vse and the excellencie thereof. As touching the Authour of this worke which I haue trāslated, how paineful a man he is, how skilful, and how luckely he hath atchieued this his businesse, as it shalbest appeare by diligent reading ouer his workes: so also may it easily be knowen by the testimonies &amp; iudgementes of the most learned Physitions of this age. Of whom, some are by their owne workes alredy extāt, notable &amp; renowmed, &amp; others (by the great trauaile that they haue bestowed in translating him out of his tongue wherin he wrote into diuers other languages) are made euidēt and famous: but none before this into English. Which hath made me desyrous (folowing their example) to make my Countreymen partakers of such know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as other learned and wise men in other Countries haue thought meete to be made knowen in the natiue tongues of their commō Weales. Touching my selfe this onely I haue to promise, that in this translation I haue vsed my most skil and diligence to please and pleasure al such as delight in this so honest and profitable a knowledge. Most humbly crauyng a fauourable acception hereof at your Maiesties handes, and pardon, if any poynt I haue giuen iust occasion of blame and deserued reprehension.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my poore house at Lytescarie within your Maiesties Countie of Somerset, <date>the first day of Ianuarie, M.D.Lxxviij.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble and faithfull subiect, Henry Lyte.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>