<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT ON THE EPISTLE TO THE HEBREWS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107380_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17650</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4405</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107380</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT ON THE EPISTLE TO THE HEBREWS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie on the vvhole Epistle to the Hebrevves. By M. Iohn Caluin. Translated out of French</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 335, 13 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb n="1" facs="3"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT ON THE EPISTLE TO THE HEBREWS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here haue beene diuers opinions in times past, not onely touching the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors name of this Epistle: but also e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Epistle it self hath bin receiued with much adoe; and that very lately amongst them of the Latine churches. They had it in suspition, as if it fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the error of <hi>Nouatus,</hi> touching the deniall of pardon vnto those which fell backe againe into sinne: but when we shall come to those places where this matter is spoken of, we will shewe that this their sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition was causelesse. Nowe for mine owne part, I doe receiue it without any difficultie at all amongst the Apostolicall Epistles; and doe make no doubt but that it came to passe by the craft and subtiltie of the Diuell, that there haue beene some heretofore which haue indeauoured to out off this Epistle from the number of the Canonicall Bookes. For there is no booke in all the holy Scripture, which more clearely, or liuely speaketh of the Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Christ: neither yet any which doth more highly extoll the dignitie, and vertue of his onely Sacrifice, the which he hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp by his death: neither is there any booke which handleth more fully, both the vse and the abrogating of Ceremonies: In a word, none which instructeth vs better, that Christ is the ende of the Lawe. Let vs not then by any means suffer that the Church of God and we with it, should be depriued of so great a benefit: but on the contrarie, let vs hold it fast, and carefully keepe it. Nowe
<pb n="2" facs="4"/>we neede not much busie our selues in standing to discusse who was the Author of it, some haue thought that S. <hi>Paul</hi> was the Author of it; some others S. <hi>Luke;</hi> others <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and others <hi>Clement;</hi> as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> declareth. Although <hi>Eusebius</hi> in the sixth booke of the Ecclesiasticall historie, maketh mention but of S. <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Clement.</hi> I know very well that since <hi>Chrysostoms</hi> time, it hath beene wholy receiued of the Greekes amongst the Epistles of S. <hi>Paul:</hi> but the Latines were of another opinion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen amongst those which were neerest to the times of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles. To speake what I thinke, I cannot beeleue that S. <hi>Paul</hi> was the Author of it. For there is no great likelihood, to say as some doe, that he suppressed his name of set purpose, because it was odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hatefull among the Iewes. And if this had beene so, why then should he make mention of <hi>Timothy?</hi> for by this onely word he had discouered himselfe, and had laid himselfe open sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their knowledge.</p>
   <p>Contrariwise, the manner of teaching, as also his style, doth giue apparant testimonie that it was not of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> writing, but of some other mans doing: for he which wrote it, confesseth in the second Chapter, that he was one of the Disciples of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles: now this is very farre off from Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> manner of speech. Moreouer the vse and custome of the Catechisme, which he toucheth in the sixth Chapter, cannot properly agree to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time. There are also other reasons, which we will touch when we shall come to the places that giue occasion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I know the excuse very well which some are wont to bring tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the style; to wit, that the difference thereof, doth giue no sufficient ground to stay our iudgements vpon, because that S. <hi>Luk,</hi> or some other did translate this Epistle out of the Hebrew tongue into the Greeke. But it is easie to refute this their conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. I willingly let passe other places which are alleadged out of the Scripture: onely I say, that if this Epistle had beene written in Hebrew, there could not haue beene an allusion in this word <hi>Testament,</hi> whereupon the author of this Epistle doth stay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. I say then, that which he handleth touching the nature of the Testament in the ninth Chapter, cannot be drawne out of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other fountaine then from the Greeke word. For the Greeke
<pb n="3" facs="4"/>word signifieth two things, to wit, Testament, and Couenant: but <hi>Berith</hi> after the Hebrewes, signifieth Couenant onely. This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son will satisfie those that are of sound iudgement to prooue that which I haue said: to wit, that this Epistle was written in the Greeke tongue. As touching that which is brought to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, that it is more probable that the Apostle would not write to the Iewes but in their owne tongue, this hath no more ground then the rest. How few were then to be found which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood the language of their auncestours? Againe, according to the region where euery one dwelt, so had he also learned the language of the same. Now the Greeke tongue was spread fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thest abroad, and was more in vse then any other. I therefore come now to the Argument it selfe.</p>
   <p>First we haue to obserue that the point whereat the Apostle aimeth, is not to perswade the Iewes, that Iesus the sonne of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> was the Christ, and the Redeemer which had beene promised them. For in as much as he wrote vnto them which had alreadie made profession of Christianitie, he takes this article as wholy granted. But his onely drift is to prooue vnto them, what Christ his office is, to the ende they might thereby acknowledge that the obseruation of the ceremonies, were abolished by his comming. We must of necessitie note this distinction. For albeit it had beene a superfluous labour in the Apostle, in speaking to those which were then sufficiently perswaded that Iesus which was already manifested was that Christ; to busie himselfe in proouing the same point still vnto them: yet it was necessarie, that he should declare vnto them what this Christ was: because they did not as yet vnderstand the end; the vertue, nor the fruit of his comming. But whilest they beguiled themselues with a false exposition of the lawe; in stead of taking the solide bodie and substance, they rested themselues in the shadow; and contented themselues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. The like difference haue we at this day with the Papists: for they confesse indeed with vs that Christ is the sonne of God, which was promised to be the Redeemer of the world: but when we come to ioyne issue, as they say, they dispoyle him of more then the one halfe of his power.</p>
   <p>But to the matter; he doth purposely begin his speach with the
<pb n="4" facs="5"/>dignitie, and greatnes of Christ, because the Iewes were of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that there was no reason why the law should be in lesse estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than the Gospel. First of all then, he confirmes the Article whereupon the disputation was: to wit, that the doctrine brought by Christ ought to haue the soueraigne place, because it is the shutting vp and conclusion of all Prophesies. But least the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which they bare to Moses, might be some hindrance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in this behalfe, he shewes that Christ is much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than all others.</p>
   <p>And hauing touched in briefe, wherein he is more excellent, he doth purposely subiect the Angels vnderneath him, to the end that all others with them, might be brought vnder, and abased in regard of Christ. Now this manner of proceeding which he vseth, is very fit; and not without great reason. For if he had begunne the comparison with <hi>Moses;</hi> it would haue beene very odious: but after he hath shewed by the scriptures, that euen the heauenly principalities are beneath Christ; there is neither <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> nor any man els whatsoeuer, which ought to refuse to be rā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with them, that so the Sonne of God may haue the chieftie aboue all, both Angels and men. And therfore after the Apostle hath brought in the Angels vnder the rule and power of Christ; forthwith, as taking more courage vnto him, he comes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, and to expresse how much more <hi>Moses</hi> is inferiour: to wit, the difference is as much as is betweene the master and the seruant. Thus then, when we shall perceiue that he alwaies pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Christ in the soueraigne degree of principalitie, in the first three Chapters, let vs knowe that he aimeth at nothing but this, that when Christ speaketh, all others should hold their peace, and that nothing should hinder vs to giue our whole at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to his doctrine. Although when he sets him before vs, as our brother in our flesh, chap. <hi>2.</hi> he calles and allures vs also by this meanes, to the end we should frame our selues vnder his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and giue our selues wholy vnto him. Now he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingles Exhortations, and threatnings for their sakes that are dull and slouthfull to obey, or; who do obstinately resist. This mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is continued almost to the ende of the fourth Chapter. From thence he beginnes to expound the Priesthood of Christ: the true
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>and pure knowledge whereof abolisheth all the ceremonies of the lawe. But hauing onely in briefe shewed how amiable the lawe ought to be vnto vs, and with what contentment of mind we may be bold to rest our selues in the same, he digresseth a little from his purpose to blame the Iewes, who like little children, did yet alwaies busie themselues in the first rudiments. Where he also striketh them with terrour, by thundring out a most sharpe and fearefull threatning against them: For he shewes that they stand in great danger to be reiected of the Lord, if they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be so slouthfull in profiting. But by and by after, he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swageth this sharpnesse, saying, that he hath good hope, that they would become better. And this is to the ende he might rather encourage them to goe on forward, than to beate them downe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together. Then he returnes againe to speake of the Priesthood of Christ. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And first he shews that it differs from the ancient Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood which was vnder the lawe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> secondly, that it was more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, because it succeeded in the place of the other, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by othe; that it is eternall, and hath alwaies his force, and efficacie: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, because he that exerciseth this office, surmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all others of the tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> in dignitie and honour. Of all which things he shewes that there was an Image and shadow in the person of <hi>Melchisedecke.</hi> Now to the ende he might the more certainely prooue that the ceremonies of the lawe were abolished, he shewes how they, as also the Tabernacle, were instituted to another end, to wit, to serue to the heauenly paterne, to which all was referred. Whence it followes, that they were not to be rested in, vnlesse we would stand at a stay in the midde way, making no reckoning to come to the marke. For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this matter, he alleadgeth the place of <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> wherein there is promise made of a new Testament, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but the correction of the olde. Whence it followes, that the old was earthly and weake. So consequently comming to shew the similitude, and agreement, which is betweene the shadowes and the substance which was manifested in <hi>Christ,</hi> he concludes that all the ceremonies ordained by <hi>Moses,</hi> were abolished by his sacrifice; because the efficacie and vertue thereof is perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and that in it is not onely contained the perfect and full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>of the new Testament, but also the true and spirituall accomplishment of that externall priesthood, which was in force and had place vnder the lawe. Vnto the doctrine he addeth yet another exhortation, which he vseth as a spurre to pricke them forward, to the end, that renouncing all impediments, they might receiue Christ with such reuerence as was meete. As touching so many examples of the fathers, which he reciteth in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth chapter, I thinke he alleadgeth them of purpose to giue the Iewes to vnderstand, that if so be they were to passe from <hi>Moses</hi> vnto Christ, it would be so far off, that they should decline from the holy Fathers, that by this meanes rather they should be the more neerely conioyned with them. For if faith were the principal vertue which was in the fathers, yea the very roote of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; it follows then, that it is this faith also, by which they should especially be acknowledged for the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and of the Prophets. And contrariwise, that all those which followed not the faith of those fathers, were bastards &amp; no children. And surely it is a point which greatly redoundeth to the praise of the Gospell; yea, it should cause vs also to haue it in so much the more estimation, in regard that therein we are found to be such, as haue a sweet accord, and societie with the vniuersall Church, which hath bin since the beginning of the world. The two last Chapters doe containe diuers directions for the rule of a good life: to wit, of hope, of bearing of the crosse, of patience, and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, of the acknowledgement of Gods benefits, of obedience, mercie, and other worke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of loue; of chastitie, and all such like things. Lastly, he shuts vp his Epistle with a praier, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with puts them in hope of his comming to see them shortly.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>