<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107868_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11038</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21302</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107868</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The abuses of the Romish church anatomized. By a vvelwiller to Sion, and to all them that loue the truth in the truth</title>
                 <author>Catholic Church</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, (for so I will stile thee, till I find thee contrary) The intolerable abuses of Pole-shorne Popelings, haue in all ages heeretofore, and are still so great, that many haue been animated, (I had almost said inforced) thereby to shew themselues in Print, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise neuer meant it, if they had not been instigated thereto by their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Lying, Whoring, Swearing, Blaspheming, Pride, Drunkennesse, Couetousnesse, and the like. I my selfe am one of this number; I haue heere
<pb facs="5"/>published a Booke, the first which euer yet set forth, and shall be the last, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse this find kind entertainement. If then (gentle Reader) thou acceptest willingly and louingly, what thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest laid downe plainly and rudely, the Authour will acknowledge himselfe bound to pleasure thee in what hee is able; if otherwise thou play the Crit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, carping at euery thing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struing that ill which was intended well, doe as thou pleasest, vse mee as thou wilt, I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine as thou vsest me, ANONYMVS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>