<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the three Right worship∣ful, The Epi∣stle by the Transla∣tor. and religiously vertuous Gen∣tlewomen, Mistres Anne Osbourne, wi∣dowe of the Right Worshipfull Mai∣ster Peter Osbourne, Esquire Mistresse Dorothie Osbourne, the wife of M. Iohn Osbourne, Esquire. Mist. Grace Chap∣man, the Widow of M. William Chap∣man, Citizen, Encrease of grace in this life, with assured hope of glorie in the world to come.</title>
           <author>T., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107899_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11989</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4769</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the three Right worship∣ful, The Epi∣stle by the Transla∣tor. and religiously vertuous Gen∣tlewomen, Mistres Anne Osbourne, wi∣dowe of the Right Worshipfull Mai∣ster Peter Osbourne, Esquire Mistresse Dorothie Osbourne, the wife of M. Iohn Osbourne, Esquire. Mist. Grace Chap∣man, the Widow of M. William Chap∣man, Citizen, Encrease of grace in this life, with assured hope of glorie in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>T., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vade mecum. = Goe vvith mee : deare pietie, and rare charitie. VVhose flame is stirred vp, to dispell the cold out of the minde. By Otho Casmanne, preacher at Stoade. Translated out of Latine, by H.T. minister. The contents appeare in the page following</title>
                 <author>Casmann, Otto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>272 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the three Right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle by the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note>
      <hi>and religiously vertuous Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, Mistres</hi> Anne Osbourne, <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of the Right Worshipfull Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> Peter Osbourne, <hi>Esquire Mistresse</hi> Dorothie Osbourne, <hi>the wife of M.</hi> Iohn Osbourne, <hi>Esquire. Mist.</hi> Grace Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>the Widow of M.</hi> William Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Citizen, Encrease of grace in this life, with assured hope of glorie in the world to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>HAuing had long experience (Right vertuous Gentlewomen) of your Christian Pietie and Charitie, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon a true knowledge of the word of God, I haue thought good to present vnto you, this short Treatise of a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Writer, Translated by me, for the good liking I had thereof.</p>
   <p>Wherein he directeth euery Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an how to begin, to goe forward, to
<pb facs="3"/> perseuere in the way of Pietie &amp; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, till he haue attained the marke, which is eternall life.</p>
   <p>Not that I thought you, to haue much need of any such direction to be prescribed you, who haue long since both found the way, and practised the course of a Christian life, and by Gods grace shall so perseuere: But yet I iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it might be a good confirmation to you, that you haue not hetherto wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vncertainly in your course, as also that it might be some encouragement vnto you to perseuere.</p>
   <p>But vnto other, who haue not yet either sound the way, or begun to walk, or haue but slowly or faintly gone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in this course, to such, this booke may be both a guide to direct thē in the way of Pittie, and Charitie, and also a spur to stirre them vp to goe forward.</p>
   <p>I haue bene bold to ioyne you three in the Inscription of this Epistle, as my three Charites or Graces, of whom the
<pb facs="3"/> Poets make mention, Three louing and bountifull sisters. And sure I am, that grace is in euery of your Names: and Nature hath ioyned you in Consangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and neere Affinitie (as also GOD hath vnited you in Pietie. Now as in the Etymologie of your Names ye carry Grace, so I doubt not but in your hearts ye possesse the three Christian Graces, Faith, Hope, and Charitie: which by Gods mercy shall neuer leaue you, till they haue brought you to the expected end of your Faith and Hope, euen eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. Which God for his sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christs sake graunt to you, and all true Christians. <hi>Amen.</hi> So fare ye well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vnworthy Pastor, <hi>H. T.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>