<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well-disposed Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107425_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04032</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14089</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107425</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well-disposed Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The secrets of numbers : according to theologicall, arithmeticall, geometricall and harmonicall computation. Drawne, for the better part, out of those ancients, as well neoteriques. Pleasing to read, profitable to vnderstand, opening themselues to the capacities of both learned and unlearned. Being no other than a key to lead a man to any doctrinall knowledge whatsoeuer. By William Ingpen, Gent</title>
                 <author>Ingpen, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 100, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well-disposed Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I haue not collected &amp; selected these Numbers, to infatuate or captiuate thy iudgement: neither is it my meaning to drawe thee into a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth by any strange or new-fangled opinion; beeing not ignorant, how that an itching &amp; pruriginous kinde of scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, diuing into the innermost secrets of forbidden Theology, hath marred the whole Christian world. I wonder, that learned men doe not blush for shame, to blaze abroad to the common view such monstrous and impious paradoxes. Some haue crept-out of late, masking themselues vnder the colourable title of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that with publique authority. But, to speake truly, such manner of mis-begotten labours, raking new and old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganicall fopperies together (except publique authority sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse them in time) wil be the vtter ouerthrow of all Religion. If a man should collect into one intire volume the absurd pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and propositions of all antient and new Hereticks, long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>othered and buried in silence, vnder a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="7 letters">
         <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
      </gap> pretext for the confutation of them, and by this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> should blinde the iudgement, and dazle the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ics of many (simple people; shall
<pb facs="6"/>not a man thinke it were both a damnable, temerarious, and preposterous kinde of enterpize? But these men doe worse, as much as Paganisme exceedeth any heresie whatsoeuer. For, what is it to our Christian Religion established already, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by so many witnesses both from heauen and earth, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with the bloud of so many blessed Saints, to bee made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the religion of Paynims? Is it not enough for vs to know Iesus Christ crucified, to speake with Saint <hi>Paul?</hi> For, admit that it bee done by way of publique detestation and confutation, yet this is not enough. For, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> saith of some heresies, <hi>Nominasse eas tantùm, est refutasse:</hi> so it is heere with such Paganicall superstitions: They are so monstrous, so impious, so absurd, so contrary to our Christian Verity, that they neede no confutation. Nay, more than this; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them, or to bestowe much time in the detection of them, according to <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Rule, is to allowe of them; to giue them the name of Religion, is to supplant Christs true Religion; to open their fopperies by publique writing, is to thrust the old and new Testament by the shoulders out of the Schoole of Christians, and to place insteade of them, the <hi>Alfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che</hi> of the Saracens, the <hi>Fotoque</hi> of the <hi>Iaponians,</hi> and <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> Alcaron. This is, with the old Academicks, to bring in their <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; with the Pyrrhomists, their <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning so many friuolous disceptations; than the which nothing could be found more absurd or pernitious. This is <hi>mouere chor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das non mouendas.</hi> Nay, pray God, beginning with those Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicks and Scepticks, to doubt of euery thing, wee proue not in the end plaine Atheists, or mungrell Christians. Alas, that I should write it! Christian Religion was neuer in so great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, as it is now. For, whereas in times past wee were but halfe Christians, for want of true knowledge and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; now, by reason of too much knowledge (I meane, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the braine) wee are swarued cleane from the rules of
<pb facs="6"/>true Christianity. <hi>Christianitatis simulacrum fortè gerimus,</hi> saith one, <hi>rem ipsam deserimus.</hi> As touching my selfe therefore and this present discourse, a kinde of necessity hath enforced me to make this protestation. I was neuer yet a broacher of newe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions; knowing, that nouelty and singularity were euer the concomitants of heresie. There are three things that haue kept me hitherto in the Catholique faith; The Word of God, the Catholique Church, the Concent of Fathers. In these three I haue placed my anchor. As for Popery and Puritanisme (two mayne opposites and extremes, though the one lesse than the other) I haue alwaies detested. Neither haue I maintained any perfidiousnesse of new error or heresie, as Heretickes are wont to doe: neither haue I beleeued (to speake with <hi>Austin</hi>) <hi>any thing that the Catholique Church vnbeleeueth,</hi> but haue alwaies with Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> thought that to bee the true and orthodox faith, which the Catholique Church hath taught mee. As I haue said in our bookes against Antichrist and his members: so I say again; <hi>Ego nihil sanctum, nihil firmum in meis dict is scriptisue esse volo, nisi quantum probet</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I hope I am an vnworthy member. And again, I wil say with S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> in his Epistle to <hi>Heldibius; Nobis nihil placet, nisi quod ecclesiasticum est: et publicè in ecclesia dicere non timemus ne iuxta</hi> Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorē, Platonem <hi>et discipulos eorum qui sub nomine Christianorū introducunt dogma Gentilium, &amp;c.</hi> See whether S. <hi>Hierome</hi> was not afrayd, that the pleasing doctrine of <hi>Pythagoras, Plato,</hi> and others, would pull downe the austerulous Religion of Christ &amp; his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles. See againe, how dangerously some men goe about, in stead of sound and orthodoxall assertions, contrary to Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s rule, to bring-in bare elements and rudiments of the world, to the scandall of our Christian Religion. Of whom I may truly speake, as <hi>Austin</hi> did of <hi>Dioscorus</hi> and others, who maintained Christs doctrine, with the testimony of Gentiles; <hi>Quid nobis opus est, propter defensionem Christianae Religionis, quaerere
<pb facs="7"/>guid senseris</hi> Anaximenes, <hi>et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lim sepi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>s in ani curiesuate reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere? Quid, inquam,</hi> Democritus, Epicurus, Parmenides, <hi>et</hi> Melissus, <hi>alijque similes huius farine Philasephi sonserius, quorum doctrina erroribus natura e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rationi contrarijs plena suit?</hi> I speake not this by way of an Apology for my selfe, or that I meane to excuse my pen from error co-incident to other men, (it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an infallible or inseparable marke of our mortality), nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to free this numerall discourse presented to thy view, from all manner of exceptions, or stumbling blocks laid in my way. For, I dare not warrant all these Numbers and diuisions, except they bee read with iudgement, charitably, and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderstood, candidously and ingenuously construed. And so I doubt not, but the greater part of them will be found not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sound, according to probability, but Theologically and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxically sound. I meane it of those who are borrowed our of Fathers or School-men. Others taken from those Iewish Rabbines, I dare not vindicate from all exception. In a great house, to vse Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s similitude, there bee vessels of honor and dishonor. And in so large a field as I haue walked, how can it bee, but some things must needs distaste, although perhaps the better part may rellish well? If then any thing offend the palate, or sauour erroniously, God forbid it should bee laid to my charge, who am but the collector, not the Author of them. For, as all my grounds are taken ont of chose Ancients (a few excepted); as namely, <hi>Pythagoras, Plato, Aristotle, Macrobius, Philo, Themistius,</hi> and others: So all our Numbers, and their extendures for the most part, haue been borrowed from sacred Scripture, antient Doctors of the Church Rabbines, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, such especially as sauour any thing of Theologie. Others haue been selected out of Philosophers, both natural &amp; morall, Astronomers, Phisicians, Anatomists, Mathematicians, Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricians Arithmeticians, Paracelsians, ciuill Lawyers, to the number of an hundred and vpwards. All that I haue done to
<pb facs="7"/>the full compleating of this discourse, hath beene, to explane and open such kinde of mysteries as haue been included or shut vp in these numbers. For, though they are called secrets, for their secret and hidden vertues infused in them; yet many of them, by the light which I haue shewed, are liable euen to common capacities. But I haue not vnfolded all, lest I might incurre the displeasure of the goddesse <hi>Eleusina,</hi> or seem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Rules of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> himself, who enioined to his scholars a fiue-yeers silence; and vnder the veile of Numbers (as those <hi>Lullianes</hi> by their primary letters alphabeticall) hath shadowed and coueted the better part of his learning, to the intent the common people should not vnderstand them. If then I should haue made all things common to those vulgar capacities, it would fall out with me, as he saith: <hi>Arcana defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerent esse aroana, &amp; glonia sua, deposite velo, ab indignis &amp; profanis hominibus contaminarentur ac praculcarentur.</hi> As therefore I said before, I dare not warrant them all without exception or limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; being not mine owne proper, but the collections of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men: so now I say again, that I would not haue any man to esteem me from their dignity or indignity, but rather what I am from miue owne proper writings. For, if they shall lay heresie to my charge (which is the greatest impeachment that can happen to a true Christian), I will say with <hi>Ruffinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Est quidem gloriosum Christi exemplo u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iurias tolerare: sed vnem notam haereseωs qui ferat vel dissinnulet non esse Christianum:</hi> And again with S. <hi>Hierom, Nolo in susp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cione haereseωs quenquamesse patientem.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let no man therefore contemn my calling or profession, or pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ferre the persons of men before their qualities, contrary to the Apostle's and <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Rule. The winde bloweth where it listeth: and the Sun shineth illibable (to vse <hi>Lactantius</hi> word) vpon the iust and vniust, without respect of Regions, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, or Climates. It is well said by One, <hi>Deus vbi vult, quando vult, quibus vult, dona sua impertit.</hi> Some perchance will obiect,
<pb facs="8"/>that the better part of these are not properly Numbers, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisions and distinctions. To whom I answer thus: If number be said <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that is, from distribution, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> will haue it, then let them shew mee any diuision or distinction, that can be framed without number, distribution, or propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; without which they may not consist, no more than num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber can without his equall or vnequall parts. And yet they are not all bare numbers included in this discourse: for, besides them, there will be found many Theological Principles, many Rules from Astronomy, Geometry, Physick; morall, naturall, and metaphysicall Philosophie, the Art Spagyrick, Cabala; as no book (I beleeue) of so small a volume, wil contain the like. I haue spaced, besides, among those ancient Hebrew &amp; Iewish Doctors, for the enquiry of sacred Symboles; wherewith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all others, they seem to me most chiefly to abound. Of whom One writeth thus: <hi>Haebraeorum doctrina velut circulus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium figurarum capacissimus, latiùs patet quam vlla alia sectarum disciplina.</hi> Others will say, that I haue been too curious in the vnfolding of them, and that I haue giuen them too much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. I answer: If I should haue blurred my paper with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> with the Cylinders of <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> with the Sphere of <hi>Archimedes,</hi> with the woodden Doue of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitas,</hi> with the strange Paradoxes of Stoicks; I might more iustly bee condemned of curiosity. As touching their vertue, this is mine opinion: I doo hould, with <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>physicks, that Number by it self hath no power of working; for, it is a quantity, and no quality: but the reason of number, which is (as it were) the form or image of time, concluding all the works of nature, worketh things admirable. If therefore thou hast any desire to be one of <hi>Pythagor as</hi> scholars, that is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to art and iudgement, to number well, read this book with attention, sobriety, discretion. I dare assure thee, that it will be a key vnto thee, to open the secrets of any science what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer:
<pb facs="8"/>for, in this little room are inclosed the flowres and blossomes of thirty yeers study, gotten together with great pains, labour and industry. For, whereas I intended, many yeers ago to treat of such a subiect; whatsoeuer by continuall reading liked mee, or was fitting for this present argument, I caused carefully to be set down in my note-book, according to the example of <hi>Plinie</hi> the elder, lest the lubricity of my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry should fail me.</p>
   <p>And now hauing made an whole body of them, partly from addition, partly from illustration, I present them heer vnto thy view; hoping, that from their worth, or from mine intention (which hitherto hath bin to further the studies of yong scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars) they will be acceptable vnto thee. This one thing I must confesse, that, for the space of one whole yeers contemplation in the art of numbring, I got more to the enriching of my poor store-house, than in seuen yeers theorie I was able to doo by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other study whatsoeuer. Yea, more than that, I haue been so rauished with the study of numbers, that if any man will ask me, What is the chiefest Good next to God, that in this life I take delight in? I must answer, Number; if, What the second? Number; if, What the third? Number. So that, as <hi>Auenzaar</hi> the Babylonian saith, <hi>He that knowes to number well, knoweth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly all things;</hi> iumping with <hi>Pythagoras</hi> &amp; <hi>Plato</hi> in this point. Thus, desiring God, with <hi>Lactantius,</hi> that I may liue no longer than to doo good to his Church, and to that Christian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weal wherein I liue, I bid thee Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>