<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The Reverend and Right Worship∣full, Isaac Bargrave, D. D. and Deane of the Metropolitan Church of Christ Canterbury. John Warner D. D. and Deane of Lichfield and Coventrie. Also to the Reverend,

Tho. Iackson.
Will. Kingsley.
Ar. Fruen.
Tho. Paske.
Mer. Casaubon.
Ioh. Ieffery.
Tho. Westly.
Hum. Peake.
Tho. Blechenden.
 Doctors in Divinitie and Prebendaries of Christ Church Canterbury, Grace and Peace be multiplied, with encrease of all honour and happinesse for ever.</title>
           <author>White, Charles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107220_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12105</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5410</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107220</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The Reverend and Right Worship∣full, Isaac Bargrave, D. D. and Deane of the Metropolitan Church of Christ Canterbury. John Warner D. D. and Deane of Lichfield and Coventrie. Also to the Reverend,

Tho. Iackson.
Will. Kingsley.
Ar. Fruen.
Tho. Paske.
Mer. Casaubon.
Ioh. Ieffery.
Tho. Westly.
Hum. Peake.
Tho. Blechenden.
 Doctors in Divinitie and Prebendaries of Christ Church Canterbury, Grace and Peace be multiplied, with encrease of all honour and happinesse for ever.</title>
                 <author>White, Charles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons preached by that reverend and learned divine Richard Clerke, Dr. in Divinitie; sometimes fellovv of Christ Colledge in Cambridge. One of the most learned translators of our English Bible; preacher in the famous metropolitan church of Christ, Canterbury. Since his death, published for the common good, by Charles White, Mr. in Arts, and one of the six preachers of Christ Church, Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Clerke, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72, 8, 73-248, 16, 249-446, 445-577, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO The Reverend and Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Isaac Bargrave,</hi> D. D. and Deane of the Metropolitan Church of Christ <hi>Canterbury. John Warner</hi> D. D. and Deane of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventrie.</hi> Also to the Reverend,
<list>
         <item>Tho. Iackson.</item>
         <item>Will. Kingsley.</item>
         <item>Ar. Fruen.</item>
         <item>Tho. Paske.</item>
         <item>Mer. Casaubon.</item>
         <item>Ioh. Ieffery.</item>
         <item>Tho. Westly.</item>
         <item>Hum. Peake.</item>
         <item>Tho. Blechenden.</item>
      </list> Doctors in Divinitie and Prebendaries of Christ Church <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Grace and Peace be multiplied, with encrease of all honour and happinesse for ever.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Reverend and Worshipfull,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or my selfe, I am neither worthy of note, nor noted▪ but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> booke of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> dedicate to your worthy names, merits both. The Author Doctor <hi>Clerke,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, high<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 21.</note> in worth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, but humble in minde. In <hi>Aarons</hi> brest-p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e was <hi>vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> knowledge, and vertue; in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ctors brest was combined, <hi>scientia▪ &amp; conscientia,</hi> learning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd integrity; of whom that may be said, which is written of S. <hi>Steven,</hi> that<note place="margin">Act. 7. 21.</note> he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, both <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, able bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> is learning, and his life to confound the Adversary. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, learning, and modesty in one man to meete, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, hard and rare saith <hi>Nazianzen.</hi> These met in him. Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>s he was; his<note place="margin">Ep. 187.</note> care of God his true worship, and zeale unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> house, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be forgotten: He delighted in the Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>welling, in <hi>Beth-el,</hi> Gods house was his joy; Divine Sermons had his presence, so had divine Service. Man may pray as <hi>Quandocun{que},</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 8.</note> so also <hi>vbicun{que},</hi> as well wheresoever, as whensoever. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ saith <hi>Theophylact;</hi> Men may lift up pure hands in every place, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> so <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. He not content with
<pb facs="3"/> private prayer in his owne house, daily frequented Gods house, esteeming it his happinesse to offer up▪ both <hi>sacrificium laudis,</hi> his thankesgiving, and <hi>vitulos labiorum,</hi> his prayers to God, in the great Congregation. And that which addes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the honour of his name, he was constant in the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe of God, and faithfull unto death, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as <hi>Clemen.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Clem. Alex. in Protrep. 1 Cor. 16. 13.</note>
      <hi>Alex.</hi> to the last gaspe. Faith requires stability, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, stand fast in it. A souldier must not onely not be a <hi>Transfuga,</hi> fly over to the adverse part, but he must not so much as <hi>stationem deserere,</hi> shrinke one whit from his standing. This Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7.</note> ground was faith, and surely he might say with S. <hi>Paul</hi> at his departure, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>I have kept it. Nazianzen</hi> complaines of some, that did <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, fit their faith to the times,<note place="margin">Orat. 25. ad Const. Aug</note> and so made it, <hi>fides temporum potiùs, quàm Evangeliorum,</hi> as <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larie</hi> speakes. But this worthy, was no time pleaser. <hi>Omnia pro veritate, Nihil pro tempore.</hi> A wise man saith S. <hi>Ambrose, Non</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hexam. l. 4. Hil. p. 308. V. Lyrin. c. 7.</note>
      <hi>cum Luna mutatur, sed permanebit cum Sole.</hi> He was truly wise, his faith, was not like that of the <hi>Arrians, annua, &amp; menstrua.</hi> Nought could drive him from the truth, <hi>Non homines, Non Daemones.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Workes of charity are signes of piety, he was Pious this<note place="margin">500 pound. <hi>ad Pios usus.</hi>
      </note> way too; witnesse his large Legacies to the poore, the soules of many blest him for this. He gave not to all, Almes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, to them that make a<note place="margin">Socrat. l. 7.</note> trade, or living of begging. His pitty was to the weake poore, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> whose hands faile and tremble, to such as live in Hospitals, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> as the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> terme them, houses of mercy, to his owne poore.</p>
   <p>Almes willed by dying men, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as <hi>Athanasius</hi> calles<note place="margin">Tom. 2. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. ad Anti.</note> them, are but dead sacrifices, yet acceptable at death, if there be mercy in time of life: His mercy was great to many poore at his death, great to his owne poore in his life, when<note place="margin">100 pound to Minster. 20 to S. Mary Mount. in London.</note> he made his owne hands his Executors; and his owne eyes his Overseers.</p>
   <p>Modest he was, <hi>Caret ambitione religiosa devotio,</hi> said S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose,</hi> free from ambition, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Naz.</hi> terme; Never active to preferment. Indeed the Lay-world had then learned, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ and that was Greek to him, he abhorred to defile himselfe, to corrupt others. This I can truly relate, and from his own mouth too, the preferment that he had was conferd
<pb facs="3"/> on him unaskt, unlookt for. <hi>Naz.</hi> would not seek honour, nor<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rat. 1.</note> refuse it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. This D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. did not onely not seeke it, but refused it. One onely place in all his time he affected, and made sute for, the Custos-ship of Christs Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> not to better his estate, but to better it; It was his <hi>Ithaca,</hi> and he did zeale the good of it.</p>
   <p>Learned he was. Knowledge caused <hi>Galen</hi> to be called <hi>Naturae miraculum,</hi> this Doctor was <hi>Ecclesiae miraculum.</hi> No man ever knew him, but must needs say, that one of the brightest starres in our East is set. They which knew him well, knew him learned, in all kinde of learning. All Arts are knit, <hi>inter se,</hi> hence <hi>Tertullian, Nulla non alterius aut mater, aut</hi>
      <note place="margin">De Idol. c. 8.</note>
      <hi>propinqua.</hi> This divine had joyned all in himselfe so well, that it is hard to say in which hee was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Q Ennius</hi> cald himselfe <hi>Tri-Cor; A. Gellius</hi> speakes the reason, he perfectly knew three tongues, <hi>Graecam, Oscam, Latinam. Tri-Cor</hi> a fit title for Doctor <hi>Clerke,</hi> he throughly understood three langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <hi>Latine, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew;</hi> the reason as I conceive, that moved Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> in his dedicatory Epistle to Christs Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to stile him, <hi>Trium linguarum peritissimus.</hi> That Colledge had a testimony of his learning in his Hebrew Lectures, so had the Vniversitie in his Disputations, and <hi>Clerums;</hi> so had the Church; when his Majesty of blessed memory, called many to the great worke of the last Translation of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish<note place="margin">Dr. Andrewes Overall. Saravia. Clerke. From the Pentateuch to Paralip. committed to him and Dr. Saravia. He sate Iudge in the Eccles. Court.</note> Bible, he was in that Number, like one of the chiefe of <hi>Davids</hi> worthies, not amongst the thirty, but amongst the first three. And as he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of great learning, so also <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of great paines. His life a continuall labour, either reading, or preaching, or Iudging; or in that which was his felicity, in instructing young Gentlemen, young Schollers. Many may truly say of this Booke as <hi>Cyprian</hi> of <hi>Tertullian, Da Magistrum.</hi> But wise men die, said the <hi>Psalmist</hi> as well as the foolish; There is <hi>Nomen Indeclinabile,</hi> and such a Noune is Death; This learned <hi>Clerke,</hi> this great Grammarian could not decline it. He is worthy to be remembred of us though dead, for he loved us, and our Church, witnesse this pledge of his love to both, his workes. These workes but Sermons, and those not many, yet such as the world hath few better. What <hi>Augustine</hi> spake of a short Text, is true of these Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>Pauca verba, sed magnarum rerum gravida,</hi> theres more
<pb facs="4"/> sound lightly in mens words than substance; in these ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, theres more substance, than sound in words. The words are but few, but full, as <hi>Philo</hi> said of love, so I of these <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. He that reades them, shall have no just cause to complaine with him in the Comedie, <hi>Pol ego &amp; oleum, &amp; operam perdidi.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If my testimony be too slight and slender, (as indeed who can worthily praise him) let it be remembred what <hi>Pliny</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plin. Sec. l. 5. Ep. 10.</note> sometime said to <hi>Antoninus, Pictores pulchram, absolutam{que} faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em raro nisi in pejus effingunt,</hi> an exact face is very seldome drawne but with much disadvantage; much more when a bungler hath it in hand. I may say of him and his workes,<note place="margin">Naz. in Bas. orat. 20.</note> as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> of <hi>Basil,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, here wants his owne tongue to speake the worth of himselfe and workes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, in both there is excellent matter of praise, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, but himselfe alone worthy, because a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone able to commend that matter. But the sea saith <hi>Nazi.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, neede not the rivers, that yet run into it; nor he mine or any others praise. Learned hee was among the living, my desire is he may bee living among the learned. How shall he now live, but by preserving alive this posthume issue of his exquisite braine?</p>
   <p>These Sermons when uttered with his voyce, were heard by your worships with admiration; Printing is a kinde of preaching. <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> notes it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> both preach<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. Strom. l. 1.</note> the word, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: which when the world shall read, they will marvaile, that such excellency could lie so close. But <hi>qualia, qualia,</hi> presuming of your worships favorable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance; not for his sake that dedicates them, for what am I, or my deservings? but for the Authors, whose memory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines yet with you, and you desire (I hope) should doe so with others, I recommend them to your Patronage, and your selves to Gods protection, beseeching him, to vouchsafe you his love, while you live on earth, and to crowne you after death▪ with eternall life in heaven. This is his prayer, who shall remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Devoted to Your Worships in▪ all thankefulnesse and service, CHARLES WHITE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>