<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107704_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04384</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14502</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107704</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine selected epistles of S. Hierome as also the liues of Saint Paul the first hermite, of Saint Hilarion the first monke of Syria, and of S. Malchus: vvritten by the same Saint. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Jerome, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>149, 3, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Haue beene requested by a Friend, whome I know not how either to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or delay; that I would trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late some choyce Epistles, and the three liues of S. <hi>Paul</hi> the Hermite, <hi>S. Hilarion</hi> the Monke, and <hi>S. Malchus,</hi> who was also a most holy man. They were written by that great famous Doctour <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> and now here you haue them in our English tongue. I thinke I need not say (for they who will haue the wit to vnderstand me, do already know) that if it were not for the seruice of God, and for that duty which a man owes his friends, he would take no great pleasure in translating the workes of such persons, as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and eminent, both in knowledge, and in the expression thereof. For when the conceptions are choice, &amp; the power of speech is great in any authour,
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
his translatour is likely enough to find his hands full of worke. <hi>S. Hierome</hi> is so well knowne, and so ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally acknowledged, to haue beene rare in both these kindes whereof I spake, that I make account my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of course is already vnder Seale, though I may haue robbed the Saint of life in many of his passages; for I haue done it against my will, and as we vse to say▪ but in myne owne defence. As for any aduise which you may expect, you shall haue but this from me. If when you read these Epistles and Liues, you obserue any particulars which may eyther be beyond your beliefe in regard of the miracls which are recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or else besids your beliefe in respect that you haue been taught some doctrines otherwise; do but cast your mind vpon considering, that it is no lesse then S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> who is speaking to you. Who liuing in the Primitiue Church, within foure hundred years after Christ our Lord, and hauing flourished with vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled fame throughout the whole world, for incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable sanctity and wisedome, and for learning al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in all sciences, as well diuine, as humane; it is fit that you should deferre much to him, both in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of these miraculous thinges, and in the admittāce also of these doctrins, which are so expresly insinuated by him to haue beene practised by the Catholicke Church of his tyme. I hope you will thinke so too: &amp; in this hope I leaue you.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>