<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The Right Noble and most Excellent PRINCESSE, the Lady Katherine, Dutchesse, Marchionesse and Countesse of Buckingham and Coventry, Viscountesse Villiers, Baronesse Rosse of Hamelake, and of Whaddon.</title>
           <author>Hayward, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S107083_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16156</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3074</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S107083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The Right Noble and most Excellent PRINCESSE, the Lady Katherine, Dutchesse, Marchionesse and Countesse of Buckingham and Coventry, Viscountesse Villiers, Baronesse Rosse of Hamelake, and of Whaddon.</title>
                 <author>Hayward, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Donzella desterrada. Or, The banish'd virgin. VVritten originally in Italian: by Cavalier Gio. Francesco Biondi, Gentleman Extraordinary of his Majesties Privy Chamber. Divided into three bookes: and Englished by I.H. of Graies Inne, Gent</title>
                 <author>Biondi, Giovanni Francesco, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Moseley, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 230, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO The Right Noble and most Excellent PRINCESSE, the Lady <hi>Katherine,</hi> Dutchesse, Marchionesse and Countesse of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Coventry,</hi> Viscountesse <hi>Villiers,</hi> Baronesse <hi>Rosse</hi> of <hi>Hamelake,</hi> and of <hi>Whaddon.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Illustrious <hi>Madam,</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen first I read the hard <hi>fate</hi> of this distressed <hi>Virgin</hi> in the native <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> where she and her <hi>sorrowes</hi> had their birth; I confesse my selfe so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, that I tooke <hi>delight</hi> in the strangenesse of her <hi>misfortunes;</hi> But since returning to a more <hi>considerate</hi> apprehension of her being <hi>exild</hi> by braine-sicke <hi>envie,</hi> meerely for her <hi>vertues</hi> (as were sometime by <hi>Ostracisme</hi> from <hi>Athens</hi> the more <hi>eminent</hi> Cittizens for their fam'd inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity) I then began so feelingly to <hi>compassionate</hi> her case, as to conceive my selfe (in pennance that I so had sollaced me with her sorrowes) <hi>charged</hi> in conscience, (at least in <hi>humane civility</hi> and obliged respectivenesse due to her sex, plight and quality) to either succour or beare a <hi>share</hi> with her in her sad <hi>pilgrimage:</hi> In ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment
<pb facs="4"/>
whereof, having <hi>conducted</hi> her out of her native Country into a forraine <hi>clime,</hi> I there did her the further service of assisting her in the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> to relate her owne disasterous <hi>story;</hi> which I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure my selfe will beget so much compassion in the <hi>nobler breasts,</hi> that she shall finde <hi>among them</hi> a free and hospitable entertainement. Now <hi>Madam,</hi> for her better encouragement I have presented her unto your <hi>Excellency,</hi> whom, out of mine owne long observation as-well as out of the mouth of <hi>fame</hi> (too narrow for so high an expression) I knew to be one of the <hi>rarest</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents of <hi>vertues</hi> that our age could boast of. <hi>Bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed</hi> then though she be, yet will she not thinke her <hi>condition</hi> hard, so she be but received into your <hi>Princely</hi> Patronage. Her Tale (Renowned Madam) may prove pretty company to your grave <hi>retirement,</hi> which when your <hi>Grace</hi> shall but vouchsafe so to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of, you will highly <hi>honour</hi> the slender endevours of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your <hi>Graces</hi> Humblest <hi>Admirer</hi> and <hi>Honorer</hi>
IAMES HAYVVARD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>