<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the discreet and indif∣ferent
Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108299_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the discreet and indif∣ferent
Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Martins months minde : that is, a certaine report, and true description of the death, and funeralls, of olde Martin Marreprelate, the great makebate of England, and father of the factious. Contayning the cause of his death, the manner of his buriall, and the right copies both of his will, and of such epitaphs, as by sundrie his dearest friends, and other of his well willers, were framed for him</title>
                 <author>Mar-phoreus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the discreet and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a world to see this
world (<hi>good reader</hi>)
Neuer deeper dangers
in hand,<note place="margin">Martins vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> nor lesse adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedlie
regarded. Neuer
sleighter toyes in head,
nor more seriouslie followed. Neuer greater
Tragoedies tendred abroad, nor lighter <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maedies</hi>
trauersed at home. Neuer so many
meanes of discorde from others, nor euer so
little concord among our selues. The people
neuer greater benefites, nor more vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;
neuer more quietnes, nor more vnquiet.
The Prince neuer more gratious, the subiects
for a great part neuer so vngratious. And
to be short, neuer better lawes, nor wiser Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates;
yet neuer such libertie in speaking,
<pb facs="5"/>
impudencie in writing, nor mischiefe in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
both priuatelie against particuler per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
(and those of the best) for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing,
and publiquelie for the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
of the Church, and ouerthrowe of
the common wealth as now. The <hi>Authors</hi>
hereof,<note place="margin">Martins cunning and craftie proceeding in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</note> though they shot at both at once,
(whereof the one was and is vsed but as the
vnderground worke to blowe vp the other
whereupon it stands which in the <hi>sueing of
Martins liuerie</hi> shortlie shall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest:)
and desired to see the cleauing of the
pinne, withall the expedition that might pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
be (wherein God be thanked their haste
was more than their good speede): yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
they therein cunninglie by degrees, as
the Foxe did with the Lyon: first peering at
him a farre of; then looking on him, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde
a bush, till at the last, finding his roring
to bee without biting, hee presumed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ett
cheeke by iole with him: Or as that varlet
did, that by oft striking at the picture pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
on a board, that could not controule him;
<pb facs="5"/>
aduentured in the end to strike through and
murder the man himselfe.</p>
   <p>For first of all,<note place="margin">The foure formes of old Martins schoole.</note> some of them which were
the Petties and Punies of that schoole, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
old <hi>Martin</hi> was the master; though then
he was but as some blinde and obscure parish
Clarke that taught in the Belfrie,<note place="margin">The first forme.</note> not presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,<note place="margin">Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shers.</note>
as hee dooth nowe, to presse into the
Church, (that place in respect of the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
being fitter for him) began but rawly
with their little a, b, c. And though their fescue
euen▪ then pointed at Capitall letters: yet for
that time, the farthest lesson they tooke foorth
was but <hi>Title point</hi> in the end; neither could
they come so farre as <hi>Estamen,</hi> because God
for beginning, was no part of their <hi>Crosse
rowe.</hi> VVho like quaint Querristers (for
they loue Musick as the Ape the whippe)
first entred with their <hi>Solfaing</hi> notes, but
not one in rule, (for they loue that neither in
word nor deede) and raught onely at the
ragges; which yet made some iagges in the
seameles coate. And like the <hi>Saint Nicolas
<pb facs="6"/>
Clarkes</hi> on Salsburie plaine (I vse the si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude,
for that <hi>Martin</hi> loues <hi>Sarum</hi> so
well) stept out before vs in the high waie, and
bidde <hi>vs stand.</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
      <hi rend="margQuotes">And these could <hi>not abide
rounde heads to weare square cappes,</hi>
      </hi>
that yet could brooke a round trencher (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie
at another mans square table): <hi rend="margQuotes">nor <hi>a
standing coller</hi>
      </hi> answerable to the neck, that
would weare bowcases, and whole butterie
hatches themselues vpon their backes. <hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>Nor
a woman to weare a kercher</hi>
      </hi> but an inch
beneath the chinne, that would weare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
hattes of the Babilonian blocke, a foote
in length at least aboue their heads. <hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>No
crosse in the browe at Baptisme,</hi> but neuer
so many, at any time in the bagge. <hi>No bells,</hi>
but Libells, and bables of their own. <hi>No Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies
read,</hi> but their own <hi>Hom-lies</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.
<hi>No praying,</hi> either for women labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
with child, or thanks giuing for <hi>women
deliuered. No more praying against
thunder and lightning,</hi> than against <hi>spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe
blasting.</hi>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Their own god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie speach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</note> They would correct <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat,</hi>
         <pb facs="6"/>
not knowing <hi>Quid significat.</hi> They
could not like of any <hi>Benedictus,</hi> for they
were (and yet are still) in their <hi>Maledictus</hi>
and <hi>Malefactus</hi> altogether,</hi> neither could
they then, or yet can they skill of any thing
else. But these men were but bench whistlers,
and shot but at short butts, and but for points
after an halfepenie the dosen, for that they
would not sit out, but bee counted gamesters,
and bee thought to bee able to shoote in a long
bowe, though but a bolte; or in a Crossebowe,
though neuer so small a <hi>quarrell.</hi> Yet these
were good fellowes; for they craued but halfe,
for that they thought some had too much; (as
the manner of such make shifts is to do): and
they had some reason for it, for <hi>Oxonium
petit aequalia</hi> is an olde said sawe, and <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatecclesia,</hi>
was a faire and gentle text for
that purpose.</p>
   <p>Next after these,<note place="margin">The second forme.</note> followed another crue,
somewhat more than a good deale quicker
than these;<note place="margin">Pistlers.</note> who being past their A, b, c, sought
to put together (and thought withall to put
<pb facs="7"/>
vs altogether by the eares) and began their
crooked descant, consisting onelie of discords:
and these like lustie cutters,<note place="margin">Old Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin in his Epistle.</note> drawing out and
<hi rend="margQuotes">brandishing their blades and threatning vs
with <hi>stripes</hi>
      </hi> yea to make our <hi>verie hearts</hi> to
ake if we would not yeelde, aduentured to lay
holde fast on our purses, and like strong
theeues in deed proffered to robbe vs of all our
monnie. And the Captaine Cuffe of this boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
band, was the old Sheepbiter, the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Gentleman this our young masters Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
who then was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>pt from the Bellfree, vp
into the Chauncel of the Church. (O that the
bell rope had not staide him by the waie) and
vnder tooke the trauersing of greater mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
He not content to plucke of the clothes,
pricks at the bodies.<note place="margin">Old Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out al his works.</note>
      <hi rend="margQuotes">He will pull the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops</hi>
and <hi>Bishops</hi>
      </hi> out of their doores by
the eares. Hee will downe with their houses,
though the Gentlemans ancestors neuer built
them. Hee will tumble downe the Churches,
for barnes and stables will serue his deuotion
well inough. Hee must haue their Mannors
<pb facs="7"/>
and lands, to make himselfe, and his beggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
bratts and shifting hang b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, Squires and
Gentlemen. Hee will sweepe away all both
the fish, and the frie at one draug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, with his
netts; and as it were drie vp our verie ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
with the breath of his mouth; and carie
whole Countries before him; and snatch vp
houses and woods, and dales, and hills, and
people, and all, into his budget: so as none
shall dwell with him vpon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e earth. Naie
he goeth farther, and setting his face against
the heauens, he makes a mock of the <hi>Saints</hi> of
God;<note place="margin">Old Martin in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle.</note> yea the mother of <hi>Christ,</hi> (with his sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
sold <hi>Sirs</hi>) &amp; the Scriptures themselues he
beastlie abuseth to his hick scorners iestes.</p>
   <p>This man,<note place="margin">In his Pistle tacking on a blind iest of a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to a text of S. Peter.</note> like a madde dogge runneth
at euerie man without regarde, and with
foming mouth, and venemous teeth, biteth
not by the shinnes, but the verie throat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
careth not whome; not onelie those, whome
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee counteth his enemies (the worst better
than the best of his hey gobetts) but those
also, whome hee saieth vntruesie men call;
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Puritans,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Martin Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor in Thes.</note> and himselfe, accounteth his halfe
faced friends, hee snarleth at; and termeth
Traitors, for that they first set them on work,
(as hee <hi>pittifullie complaining,</hi> sheweth
vnto vs), and now are ashamed of them (as
they well may) and will not gallop with them
so fast as they doo vpon the spurre, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
the bridle beyond all honestie and discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Martin Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior in his Pistle in the margent.</note>
Nay his owne pufellowes (whome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
himselfe best knoweth, and with whome
he may be boldest) he coteth with his own li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie,<note place="margin">Martinistes sawcie knaues, by Martins owne testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.</note>
and calleth <hi>saucie knaues:</hi> which me
thinks, sits close to their backs, without pleite
or wrinkle, and fitteth them so well, as no
Tailour in England could doo it better. And
yet he reuealeth the faults of others so whot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
and reuileth them so bitterlie, as if that
name at no hand appertained to him, or any of
his. The right of spring of him, that is termed
<hi>Sathanas,</hi> the accuser of his brethren, and a
verie limme of him, that is called <hi>Fur &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micida,</hi>
a theefe and a murderer, for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
not but to steale, and kill; and his marks
<pb facs="8"/>
are no dead marks, but liuings, and liues; and
his arrowes all are forkers, and made for mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe,
though fethered yet (as hereafter you
shall heare) with woodcocks whing.</p>
   <p>After him,<note place="margin">The third forme.</note> as if hell had been broken
loose;<note place="margin">Barbarians.</note> out runnes another rabble, of the same
house and famelie, in the <hi>collaterall</hi> line of
leudnes, <hi>Browne, Barowe,</hi> and <hi>Greene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi>
that verie three headed <hi>Cerberus</hi>
the dogge of hell: and these being of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
consort for taking of our purse (for
that wee should not bee able to see belike to
make <hi>Hue</hi> and crie after the theeues) would
haue vs whoodwinckt,<note place="margin">See D. Somes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.</note> and therefore being
verie asses themselues, would needs haue our
<hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>Vniuersities,</hi>
      </hi> the onelie meanes of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
downe. And so might they also the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
afterwards, scatter what heresies soeuer
they should deuise, (for that is their onelie
occupation) as it were in that palpable darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
and beastly barbarisme, without control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
These men, must needs (and so doo) dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
of all degrees; worthie themselues to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
<pb facs="9"/>
by no degrees, but roundels. <hi rend="margQuotes">The Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi>
they will not afforde so much as an hole
to rest in; vnworthie themselues to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
hole (saue the pillorie) to put their heads
in. <hi rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Prince,</hi> may not medle, (saie they)
in matters of religion. Neither must <hi>the
people tarie for the Prince, or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in Church matters:</hi> (neither should
the hangman for such rib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lds). <hi>Churches,
they will haue none. Sacraments, they
care for none.</hi> Ministers,</hi> they neede none.
They make all, and doo all; and are all them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.
<hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>All set praiers, are babling and
blasphemie,</hi> and such praiers only as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
make <hi>Ex trumperie,</hi> is the onelie pure,
&amp; perfect praying. As for the <hi>Lords praier,</hi>
that is but a toye, and a <hi>plaine mocking of
the Lord</hi> to saie it. Yea that it is better for a
man to lie with his <hi>Fathers Wife</hi> (Quaere</hi>
by the waie whether that also be not an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
of their religion); <hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>than to resorte to
the Church, or come into the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
to publique praier.</hi> Lucian</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theist,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
was neuer so irreligious; nor euer <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>
the <hi>runnagate</hi> so blasphemous. And
these comming out as it were with their three
mans song, would confound all, and make a
blacke <hi>fanctus</hi> of the matter: shooting out
their venemous shafts, with mischeeuous
heads, sharpened vpon <hi>Martins</hi> most mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
whetstone. For that they haue issued
from <hi>Martins</hi> schoole, and are <hi>fellowes in
feelde</hi> with them, and fight together, against
both the Church &amp; State, in one and the selfe
same quarrell, shall euidentlie bee proued in
<hi>Martins</hi> liuerie. These are the verie <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>custes,</hi>
that came from the smoake of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomeles
pitte, to darken the Sunne, and the
aire, with faces like men but teeth like <hi>Lions,</hi>
and tailes like <hi>Scorpions,</hi> to sting men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
not men infatuate, but beasts intoxicate,
or rather verie diuels incarnate, sent out to
deceiue and disturbe the world.</p>
   <p>And now last of all (and would GOD it
were so) out steppes mee their <hi>Abaddon,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The fourth forme.</note> a
badde one indeede and the verie worst of all,<note place="margin">Seditious.</note>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>Martin Senior</hi> for sooth, the olde <hi>Martins</hi>
sonne and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eire (worshipt might hee be) and
together with him, a brother of his, one <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin
Iunior, a pretic stripling,</hi> (as he termes
himselfe; and pretie striplings indeede would
they bee, if they were cleane stript, and well
whipt, and trimlie trust vp withall), as ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
varlets both; (they shall pardon me, if for
themselues, I borrowe their owne phrase): as
euer was their Father, or great Grandfather,
or any of that leud linage before them, and
these mens <hi>Cater Cosins,</hi> on the surer side.
And these, to fill vp the iniquitie of their
forefathers, disdainefullie scorne the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie
of Princes and set light of them:<note place="margin">Martin Iu. in Thes.</note> and the
one of them, abusing that most reuerendname,
to the rascall his father, one of the verie
scumme of the people: calleth <hi>him a man of
a kinglie nature;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Martin Sen. in cens.</note>
      <hi rend="margQuotes">and not onelie that, but in
plaine and flat terme maketh a test of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi>
      </hi>
and <hi>the troub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ng of the State, and
offending of her Maiestie,</hi> bee turneth of
with a frumping, <hi>forsooth,</hi> as though it
<pb facs="10"/>
were a toie to thinke of it.<note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note>
      <hi rend="margQuotes">And the other
scoffeth at her Maiesties authoritie, <hi>scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
hir displeasure, iesteth at praying
for hir,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Pag. 23. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nsur.</note>
         <hi>reuileth her lawes, threatneth her
Magistrates;</hi>
         <note place="margin">pag. 22. These things shall euidently be proued in Martins liuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e.</note> nay <hi>hir Maiestie her selfe;
musters her subiects; sturreth vp Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie
men, Gentlemen, and people:</hi>
      </hi> and
plainelie with open mouth and full cheekes,
bloweth vp the trumpet to rebellion; and
as it were with banner displaied (though
lurking in his denne) dooth enter the fielde,<note place="margin">He brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that hee hath 100000. disciples in the realme, and those the strength and sinewes of the land.</note>
and giueth the defiance, except hee haue his
foorth; and pretending his Pistle, bendeth
his Pistoll at vs. Naie further, (that
plainelie proueth him to bee a righte limme
of <hi>Antechrist</hi>) hee rusheth into mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences,
and sitts him downe in the seate
of Gods secrets, and tell vs,<note place="margin">Martin Sen. in cens.</note>
      <hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>that such
an one shall haue a fearefull ende,</hi>
      </hi> for
that forsooth, he resisteth their shamefull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings.
<hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>It shal be the bane to such a one,
both in this life,</hi> (as if he had a purpose to kil
him) <hi>and in the life to come,</hi>
      </hi> (as if hee had
<pb facs="11"/>
the power to damne him. And what is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence?
To moderate and marshall such mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants
as himselfe, and his mates are? An
heynous matter. I meruaile then what shall
become of <hi>Master Recorder of London,</hi>
that euerie moneth, dispatcheth manie lesse
hurtful, and some much more honest, than the
most of these are. <hi rend="margQuotes">Nay the Lorde <hi>hath no
parte in such a one;</hi>
      </hi> whose grace (I vse
that phrase in despite of both the <hi>Martins</hi>
and al the <hi>Martinists</hi>) hath more grace, than
all the rabble of such <hi>Rakehells, and moste
miserable,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Martin the Iu. in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus.</note>
      <hi>and desperate kaitiues.</hi> I doo
returne, but their owne verie words, that
themselues lent vnto those that minde not
to borrowe them, nor to be in their debt. And
these lustie youthes, not contented with the
pon, threaten vs the penknife: nor being sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
with our purse, hackle at our throate.
And these are (as <hi>Martin</hi> the <hi>more</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
more truelie than himselfe is aware of
touching himself and his yoke fellowes) <hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>most
rebellious,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Martin Senior his owne words of himselfe and his fellowes cens. pag. 6. and shall sufficientlie be proued in his Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note>
         <hi>and disobedient to all good
<pb facs="11"/>
proceedings: Traitors and enemies to
her Maiestie: They will ouerthrowe the
states:</hi>
      </hi> to the which they shall adde thus
much (to make it a perfect and a most true
period) they shewe in their writings, that
they saie in their hearts, there is <hi>no God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For (to leaue furder stirring of this stin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
sinke) it is now come to this passe,<note place="margin">The sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance and end of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins lessons.</note> that
if these men may haue their swaie, (but wee
hope first they shall haue their swing) we shall
haue left vs, I will not saie, <hi>No cap, no
coats, no monie, no house, no liuing, but</hi>
(better no life) <hi>no learning, no Magistrats,
no Prince, no Church, no Sacrament, no
praier, no nor God,</hi> for vs to worship, or
feare at all. These men, would I call (as I
well might) <hi>Monsters;</hi> saue that in these
mischeeuous daies, wherein our <hi>Europa,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
become an <hi>Africa,</hi> in bringing dailie foorth
newe monsters, I can account them but ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
<hi>Vermin.</hi> But verie fitlie haue they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
their name of <hi>Marring;</hi> that professe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
else but <hi>marring:</hi> both the names of
<pb facs="12"/>
men▪ and quiet of the common wealth, and
peace of the Churche, and liuings of the
Church, and Churches themselues: and the
rewards of learning, and places of learning,
and degrees of learning, and learning it selfe:
and the lawes of the land, and the authoritie
of the Prince, and last of all (for what can
be lefte after for the Diuell himselfe) sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
Ministers, praiers, yea the Lordes
praier; and so set their brasen faces against
heauen, and bend their forces against the
Lord himselfe. For they are not onelie now
come to shoote at rouers, and seeke out at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie
bowte a newe marke; but begin as fast
as they can, (leauing the obscurer hobbs that
first they began with, to shoote a maine
for the vpshot, at the fairest markes of all.<note place="margin">Martins Cards.</note>
They are now in hande to shuffle the Cardes
(as ill as they will seeme to loue them) and
to confounde all, to amende their badde
games, hauing neuer a good Carde in their
handes, and leauing the auncient game of
<pb facs="12"/>
England (<hi>Trumpe</hi>) where euerie coate,
and sute are sorted in their degree, are run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to their <hi>Ruffe</hi> where the greatest sorte
of the sute carrieth away the game: and to
their <hi>Mawe,</hi> where the fiue fingers is a
carde of great strength, and though the King
and the <hi>Queene</hi> bee in the decke; yet the
knaue must commande all and beare the
swaie.<note place="margin">Martins Dice.</note> And that thou maist knowe them to
bee good Dicers, too; when their Dice are
fo cunninglie coggd: as though they cast
<hi>Sinnes</hi> for the moste parte, yet they maie
in the end with a tripsie Tray, carrie all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie
smoothe; and come once to the sweepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake,
and make a bare boorde, and howe
they meane than to proceede (if they <hi>passe</hi>)
shall bee a <hi>Mumchaunce</hi> for mee; that
are like (as wiser heads no doubte doo see)
to hazard all. For then the Dice are like
to rule all; bee the caster neuer so cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and his heape neuer so great before
him. VVhich point perhappes they will carrie
<pb facs="13"/>
the cleanlier, couering it with this cloke that
(as they pretend in other matters of lesse mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
by them) to reduce all to the precise
forme of the Primitiue Church; so for this
matter especiallie, they being as it were our
newe <hi>Apostles</hi> (and verie <hi>Apostolique</hi> are
their writings no doubte, and their pistles sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth
much of the phrase of the <hi>Apostles</hi>
epistles) all must be sold, and brought to their
feete; that they may set their feete, on the
highest head. For this generation is like the
Iuie, that from the roote groweth vp, and
roundeth it selfe, as it were for pure loue; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
the Elme, and neuer leaueth to creepe
vp, till it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ath aduanced it self to the highest
of all, and suckt out the sappe cleane, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
it vp. The greene leaues make a faire and
a glorious shewe, but in the end, when it hath
clunged close, and climbed aloft, it marreth al
both top and trunke.</p>
   <p>Thus haue I shewed thee (gentle Reader)
a short sight of <hi>Martins</hi> schoole the degrees
of his formes, the summe of his lessons, and the
<pb facs="13"/>
drift, both of the master and schollers: and
for so much as, the olde <hi>Martin</hi> is dead, (as
streight thou shalt heare) were it not that we
are bound rather, for the quiet of the Church,
and safetie of the state, as well to wish the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
extirpation of al such vntractable and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious
scisme sowers, as to worke withall, by
all orderlie meanes we may, to effect the same
in time conuenient, before it bee growne to so
great a head, as will trouble the wisest heads,
and the highest head perhapps to help it: wee
might otherwise praie, with the old woman of
<hi>Siracusa</hi> for the good health and wellfare,<note place="margin">Martin must be prayed for.</note> of
these two yong <hi>Slipps</hi> his sonnes, least after
them come out vnto vs, the great diuell their
grand master <hi>Beelzebub</hi> himselfe, whose
next forerunner, out of all doubt this race of
<hi>Martins</hi> is.</p>
   <p>And these are the yonkers that wee now
vndertake;<note place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins are all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come banc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rupts.</note> the olde <hi>Martins</hi> reuerend
sonne and heire, and his worshipfull Brother;
who being both but newelie come to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
lands and goods, (I meane his good and
<pb facs="14"/>
are ful of them, and therefore can make no one
forme of themselues. And this also, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
other as materiall points, shall in the next
at large be proued.</p>
   <p>These fellowes,<note place="margin">Martin an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but with whoopes and haloes.</note> haue heretofore been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered
to their chiefest matters (which God
knoweth were both fewe and friuolous) by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of the best sorte, (an vnfit match for
these of the basest baggagerie) both grauelie,
and learnedly. But as the Ape, the more sage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
you looke on him, the more he grinneth; and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> substantiallie you reason
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him, the lesse he vnderstandeth: so these
Panions, scorning all modestie, and reiecting
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>, delight in nothing, but in their most
miserable vaine, of resting and foolerie.</p>
   <p>It is therefore thought the best way (for
experience and time tries al things) and some
wisemen wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> before of that Iudgement,<note place="margin">The best way of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering Martin.</note> and
the wise man himself dooth so aduise vs, and
<hi>Martin</hi> the foole himselfe is of the same opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
to answere the foole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, according to their
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>. For I haue here at this time one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="14"/>
plaied with their foolish coxecombe; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing
in my next, to decipher their knauish
head also: and when they shall put off their
fooles coate, and leaue snapping of their wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
dagger, and betake themselues to a sobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
kinde of reasoning, (which will bee verie
hard for such vices to doo) to accept of their
glorious gloue. Till then; wee will returne
them the Cuffe, in stead of the gloue, and hisse
the fooles from off the stage, as the readiest
meanes to out-face them; though (besides that
they hide their heads) they be most impudent,
and canot blush. For what face soeuer they set
on the matter, these Iigges and Rimes, haue
nipt the father in the head &amp; kild him cleane,
seeing that hee is ouertaken in his owne <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Martin the vice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damneth the Plaiers Eigulus, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulum.</note>
And this hath made the yong youthes
his sonnes, to chafe and fret aboue measure, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speciallie
with the Plaiers, (their betters in
all respects, both in wit, and honestie) whom
sauing their <hi>liueries</hi> (for indeede they are
hir Maiesties men, and these not so much as
hir good subiects) they call <hi>Rogues</hi> for play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="15"/>
their enterludes, and Asses for trauelling
<hi>all daie for a pennie;</hi> not remembring that
both they,<note place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins right roges.</note> &amp; their Father, playing the fooles
without any liuerie, are roges indeed, by the
lawes of this land; and that for nothing, now
two yeares together; are the veriest Asses of
all the rest.</p>
   <p>And yet shalt thou finde (good Reader)
in this iesting with him, (but especiallie in
the next) that the foole is bobbd withall in
good earnest, and that he is proued a plaine
<hi>Hermaphrodite,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Martin an Herma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrodite.</note> that is both a foolish knaue,
and a knauish foole also; and the veriest foole
in the world, if he be not as very a knaue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
may soone see, to what passe, both religion,
&amp; the state would shortlie come, if <hi>Mad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,
&amp; his mates marrings, and his sonnes
shiftings,</hi> might by such as are of might,
(which the GOD of all might forefend) bee
made account of.</p>
   <p>These iests, that now we deale withal, are
partlie the old mans monuments; but especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
the elder sonnes <hi>censure,</hi> and the yongers
<pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>Theses.</hi>
      <note place="margin">The occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this worthie work.</note> The first occasion indeed, grew of this
latter, published by the dawling <hi rend="margQuotes">
         <hi>Martin Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or,</hi>
by meanes (as himselfe saith) of certaine
maimed, and imperfect Articles,<note place="margin">The death of Martin the great.</note> which he
found <hi>dropt out of some mans</hi> (belike the
hangmans) <hi>budget,</hi>
      </hi>
      <note place="margin">Mar. the Iu. in Thes. in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion.</note> (whereof you shall heare
more in the next) wherein hee imagineth his
Father (whose articles they were) to be dead;<note place="margin">Martin Sen. in cens.</note>
&amp; that the elder saith also <hi>he cā not gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fay;</hi>
which is the grounde work and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
of our building, here for this time. VVhat
hee omitted I haue supplied; touching the
cause of his death, and manner of his buriall;
for that I would be lothe so memorable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
should be buried with him, (which is but
an Introduction to other matters that short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
shall followe, &amp; sit somewhat neerer them;<note place="margin">His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iuerie &amp; Modells.</note>
vpon the truth wherof thou maist much better
build I wis, then vpon their fond &amp; phroene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
fancies; wherupon they would haue thee,
(if thou were so wise) to found thy faith.</p>
   <p>To conclude; marke <hi>Martins</hi> life, and his
proceedings; and thou wilt saie, his death, and
<pb facs="16"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="16"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="17"/>
funeralls were answerable vnto it. And since
he is dead: let him bee buried also, in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,
and so let his vaine works, together with
his remembrance, lie still (as he dooth) and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> as carrion. And as for these yong <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins,</hi>
both the one, and the other, and all the
broode of such beastlie bratts; assure thy self,
they are not long liued: that in the noses of
all, that are not stuft to much with the Pose
of preiudice, but can smell any thing in the
worlde: do euen now, stinke aboue the ground
aliue. Fare well, And if thou wilt fare well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede:
<hi>Beware of Martin.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>