<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honorable Iames Campe-bell, Lord Maior of the most renouned Citty of London.</title>
           <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1084_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B01146</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6509</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1084</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honorable Iames Campe-bell, Lord Maior of the most renouned Citty of London.</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons Tempe, or, The feild of happines : In which feild are planted seuerall trees of magnificence, state and bewty, to celebrate the solemnity of the Right Honorable Iames Campebell, at his inauguration into the honourable office of prætorship, or maioralty of London, on Thursday the 29 of October, 1629. All the particular inuentions, for the pageants, showes of triumph, both by water and land being here fully set downe, at the sole cost, and liberall charges of the Right worshipfull Society of Ironmongers. Written by Thomas Dekker</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right honorable <hi>Iames Campe-bell,</hi> Lord Maior of the most renouned Citty of <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honorable Praetor:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Triumphes which these few leaues of paper, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to your vew, (Albeit their glories are but short-liued as glittering onely for a day) Boldly show their faces vnto the eye of the world, as Seruants attending on your Lordship onely to doe you honor.</p>
   <p>With much care, cost and curiosity are they brought forth; And, with exceeding greatnes of <hi>Loue,</hi> a free han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded bounty of their <hi>Purse,</hi> a Noble and generous Alacrity of <hi>Spirit,</hi> haue your worthy Fraternity, and much to be honored Brother-hood of <hi>Ironmongers,</hi> bestowed them vpon you.</p>
   <p>It much winnes vpon them, to haue such a Cheife; and you cannot but be glad to haue such a <hi>Society:</hi> By a free Election are you <hi>Londons</hi> Praetor; The Suffrages of <hi>Commoners</hi> call you to your seate. A succession to the place, Takes you by the hand, your Industry hath met with Blessings, those blessings giuen you ability, and that ability makes you fit for a Maiestrate.</p>
   <p>Yet there is a musicke in your owne bosome, whose strings
<pb facs="3"/>being touchd yeilds as harmonius a sound to you, as All theis: And that is, to see your selfe heire to that <hi>Patrician Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> with which your Father was Inuested. Jt was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to him to weare that Robe of <hi>Scarlet,</hi> It it a double glory to you, in so short an age to haue his sword borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
   <p>You haue the voyce of <hi>Senators</hi> breathing out your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, A confluence of <hi>Graue Citizens,</hi> Adding state to your state, The acclamations of People, vshering you along. Whilst <hi>I</hi> (the least part of this Triumphant day) spend such sand as <hi>I</hi> haue to helpe to fill vp the houre glasse, my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice ronning.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Attending on your Lordship</hi> Thomas Dekker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>