<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his kind Friend and Countryman W. Lithgow.</title>
           <author>Murray, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108592_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05597</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15714</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108592</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his kind Friend and Countryman W. Lithgow.</title>
                 <author>Murray, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The totall discourse, of the rare adventures, and painefull peregrinations of long nineteene yeares travailes from Scotland, to the most famous kingdomes in Europe, Asia, and Affrica : Perfited by three deare bought voyages, in surveying of forty eight kingdomes ancient and modern; twenty one rei-publicks, ten absolute principalities, with two hundred islands. ... divided into three bookes: being newly corrected, and augmented in many severall places, with the addition of a table thereunto annexed of all the chiefe heads. Wherein is contayned an exact relation of the lawes, religions, policies and governments of all their princes, potentates and people. Together with the grievous tortures he suffered by the Inquisition of Malaga in Spaine ... And of his last and late returne from the Northern Isles, and other places adjacent. By William Lithgow</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 444, 447-514, 8 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To his kind Friend and Countryman W. Lithgow.</head>
   <l>THy well adventur'd Pilgrimage I prayse,</l>
   <l>Although perform'd with perill and with pain,</l>
   <l>Which thou hast penn'd, in more than vulgar phrase</l>
   <l>So curiously, so sweetly, smooth, and plain.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Yet whilst I wondring call to minde again.</l>
   <l>That thou durst go, like no man else that lives;</l>
   <l>By Sea and land, alone, in cold and raine,</l>
   <l>Through Bandits, Pirats, and <hi>Arabian</hi> Theeves,</l>
   <l>I doe admire thee; yet a good event</l>
   <l>Absolves a rash designe: So hardest things,</l>
   <l>(When humane reason cannot give consent</l>
   <l>T' attempt) attain'd, the greater glory brings.</l>
   <l>Then Friend, though praise &amp; pains rest both with thee,</l>
   <l>The use redounds unto the world, and mee.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>JOHN MURRAY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>