<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>CERTAINE OPE∣NING AND DRAW∣ING DISTICHES TO BE APPLIED as mollifying Cataplasmes to the Tumors, Carno∣sities, or difficult Pimples full of matter appearing in the Authors front, conflated of Stiptike and Glutinous Vapours arising out of the Crudities: The heads whereof are particularly pricked and pointed∣out by letters for the Readers better vnderstanding.</title>
           <author>Whitaker, Laurence</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108718_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19383</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5810</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>CERTAINE OPE∣NING AND DRAW∣ING DISTICHES TO BE APPLIED as mollifying Cataplasmes to the Tumors, Carno∣sities, or difficult Pimples full of matter appearing in the Authors front, conflated of Stiptike and Glutinous Vapours arising out of the Crudities: The heads whereof are particularly pricked and pointed∣out by letters for the Readers better vnderstanding.</title>
                 <author>Whitaker, Laurence</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Odcombian banquet: dished foorth by Thomas the Coriat, and serued in by a number of noble wits in prayse of his Crudities and Crambe too. Asinus portans mysteria</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="distichs">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>CERTAINE OPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING <hi>AND</hi> DRAW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING DISTICHES TO BE APPLIED as mollifying Cataplasmes to the Tumors, Carno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities, <hi>or difficult Pimples full of matter appearing in</hi> the Authors front, conflated of Stiptike and Glutinous Vapours arising out of the Crudities: The heads <hi>whereof are particularly pricked and</hi> pointed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out by letters for the Readers better <hi>vnderstanding.</hi>
   </head>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>A</head>
      <l>FIrst, th' Author here glutteth Sea, Haddock &amp; Whiting</l>
      <l>With spuing, and after the world with his writing.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Yee Haddocks twixt Douer and Calais, <note n="a" place="margin">Imperat.</note> speake Greeke;</l>
      <l>For <hi>Tim</hi> fild your mawes with it in Whitsun <note n="b" place="margin">Viz. An. 1608. <hi>when he began to trauel.</hi>
         </note> weeke.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>B</head>
      <l>THough our Author for's Venery felt no whips smart,</l>
      <l>Yet see here he rides in a Picardy cart.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>C</head>
      <l>THis Horse pictur'd showes, that our <note n="c" place="margin">A word that in the Helueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an tongue sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged traueller.</note>
         <hi>Tatter-de-mallian</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Did ride the French Hackneyes, and lie with th' Italian.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Our Author in France rode on horse without stirrop,</l>
      <l>And in Italy bathed himselfe in their syrrop.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>His loue to strange horses hee sorteth out prettily,</l>
      <l>He rides them in France, and lies with them in Italy.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <head>D</head>
      <l>HE hath crost <note n="1" place="margin">he foure Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Sea and <note n="2" place="margin">he foure Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Land, now the cloudes the text</l>
      <l>Of <note n="3" place="margin">he foure Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> th' Ayre he is climbling; ware <hi>Tom,</hi>
         <note n="4" place="margin">he foure Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> fire is next. saith</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>E</head>
      <l>HEre to his Land-friggat he's ferried by Charon,</l>
      <l>He bords her; a seruice a hot and a rare one.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Here to a Tutch-hole he's row'd by his Gondelier,</l>
      <l>That fires his <note n="d" place="margin">That is, the beauty of her countenance, &amp; sweet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> of her lips did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame his tongue with a diuine &amp; fiery enthusiasme, emptied the Bandolier of his conceipts &amp; inuentions for that time.</note> Linstocke, and empties his Bandolier.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>F</head>
      <l>HEre his Friggat shootes egs at him empty of Chickens,</l>
      <l>Because she had made his purse empty of Chicquins.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Here she pelts him with egs, he saith, of Rose-water;</l>
      <l>But trust him not Reader, t'was some other matter.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>G</head>
      <l>IN vaine here doth <hi>Coryate</hi> pipe and dispute,</l>
      <l>His wench was, Iewes will not be caught with his flute.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Thy Cortizan clipt thee, ware <hi>Tom,</hi> I aduise thee,</l>
      <l>And flie from the Iewes, lest they circumcise thee.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>H</head>
      <l>HE longs for sweet grapes, but going to steale 'em</l>
      <l>He findeth soure graspes and gripes from a Dutch <note n="e" place="margin">A Rascalin; Dutch.</note>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Here is the combat our Author may glory at,</l>
      <l>With Halberd the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> laies on, and with Greeke <hi>Coryat.</hi>
      </l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>I</head>
      <l>HEre is his Trophee victoriously dight</l>
      <l>With case, shoes, and stockings, and lice put to flight.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>See here his poore case, his shoes clowted with cunning,</l>
      <l>His stockings strong-smelling, and lice away running.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>See our louse-bitten Trauellers ragged deuice,</l>
      <l>Of case, shoos, and stockings, and Canniball lice,</l>
      <p>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>This Gibbet the false case and hose doth require,</l>
      <l>That harbour'd the vermine that their Maister did bite.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>K</head>
      <l>THis should be his picture, 'tis rather his Embleme,</l>
      <l>For by <note n="a" place="margin">As being the first letter of his name in Greeke.</note> (K) it notes him, though't little <note n="b" place="margin">But you dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in opinion (<hi>Mr. Laurence</hi>) from all my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friends that haue compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the counterfeited and the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing figure.</note> resemble him.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>This picture vnlike him, showes hee's not come home as</l>
      <l>He went, but chang'd, and turn'd trauelling <hi>Thomas.</hi>
      </l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>This picture vnlike him, showes he's not himselfe,</l>
      <l>But changd since he proued a trauelling Else.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Know Reader, the notes and contents of this booke,</l>
      <l>Are not to be guessed by th' Authors caru'd looke.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>L</head>
      <l>THese be the three countries with their <hi>Cornu-copia,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That make him as famous, as Moore his <hi>Vtopia.</hi>
      </l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>Here France giues him scabs, Venice a hot Sunne,</l>
      <l>And Germany spewes on him out of her Tunne.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>M</head>
      <l>THe horse he bestrid till he mounted his chaire</l>
      <l>Doth kindly bestride him at Bergamo faire.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>He courted a wench, but pennance for his game O</l>
      <l>He doth by lying with horses at Bergamo.</l>
      <p>
         <hi>Or,</hi>
      </p>
      <l>The Italian horse more then the French his loue feeles,</l>
      <l>For he rod on the one, and lay at th' others heeles.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="distich">
      <head>N</head>
      <l>MOst Politike <hi>Thomas,</hi> now thou art no <note n="c" place="margin">The French word for a foole.</note>
         <hi>fol</hi> I see,</l>
      <l>For wanting no money, thou beggest in policy.</l>
   </div>
   <closer>
      <signed>Laurence VVhitaker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>