<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VER∣TVOVS AND WORSHIPFVLL GENTLEMAN, AND HIS SIN∣gular good friend Maister IOHN BARNE Esquire, T. B. C. wisheth grace and peace in this life, and e∣uerlasting happines in the life to come.</title>
           <author>C., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108252_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05094</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15233</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VER∣TVOVS AND WORSHIPFVLL GENTLEMAN, AND HIS SIN∣gular good friend Maister IOHN BARNE Esquire, T. B. C. wisheth grace and peace in this life, and e∣uerlasting happines in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>C., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French academie : wherin is discoursed the institution of maners, and whatsoeuer els concerneth the good and happie life of all estates and callings, by preceptes of doctrine, and examples of the liues of ancient sages and famous men: by Peter de la Primaudaye Esquire Lord of the said place, and of Barree, one of the ordinarie gentlemen of the Kings Chamber: dedicated to the most Christian King Henrie the third, and newly translated into English by T.B</title>
                 <author>La Primaudaye, Pierre de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 659, 670-769, 768-812, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVOVS AND WORSHIPFVLL GENTLEMAN, AND HIS SIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good friend Maister IOHN BARNE <hi>Esquire,</hi> T. B. C. <hi>wisheth grace and peace in this life, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting happines in the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, hauing at length finished the Translation of this French Treatise of Morall Philosophy, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the rather to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to your Worships fauour, bicause your selfe did first commend it vnto me for the varietie of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent sayings and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples wherewith it is reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished. And surely I perswade my selfe, that howsoeuer for want of a skillfull Translator it hath lost much of that grace, which otherwise it might haue had, yet by reason of the matter it selfe, &amp; good disposition obserued through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole booke, it will be of some account with so many as preferre the soundnes of substance before the swelling froth of curious phrases. True it is, that many words vsed by the Author, and retained by me, are almost the same with the originall toongs from whence they were deriued, and peraduenture will sound harsh at the first in their eares that neuer heard them before; but if
<pb facs="3"/>
they will haue patience a while, and let them passe to and fro vpon the file of their teeth, no doubt but in short time they will be as smooth as other Greeke and Latine words which now are taken for meere English. I might heere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge reasons to prooue the necessitie of retaining such words in translating: namely, that many of them are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per names and words of Arte, that as all occupations and handicrafts haue their seuerall names of instruments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their science, so is it with Philosophy, and with euery part thereof: but I make no doubt of finding the Reader fauourable in this point, considering that it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the enriching of our owne language, and hath beene practised by the learned of all nations that haue gone before vs, as is euident to such as are skilfull in the toongs. Concerning the profite of this booke, I referre the Reader either to the title thereof, which promiseth no more (in my opinion) than is performed with aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in the bodie of the same, or else to the Authors Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the Reader, wherein he setteth downe a summarie of that doctrine, which is afterward handeled more at large. Wherein howsoeuer he hath very excellently beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued himselfe, and (as I am perswaded) gone farre beyond those that haue handled the same matter before him, yet considering each mans infirmitie to be such, that he attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to perfection in any worke, neither speaketh all things that are to be spoken of the same thing, nor yet is free from error in those things which he speaketh or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, I exhort all that shall peruse this Treatise following, so farre onely to approoue euery sentence and example of life, as it may be prooued out of the records of holie Scripture. Moreouer, as many as are desirous to be bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the reading of this booke, they must thinke seriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly vpon that ende vnto which this Author had regard when he penned it, which was the same that <hi>Aristotle</hi> had <note place="margin">Arist. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Eth. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note>in writing his Ethicks or booke of Manners: namely, <hi>the practise of vertue in life, and not the bare knowledge and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation thereof in braine.</hi> And, least any man should haue that
<pb facs="3"/>
opinion of these Morall precepts, which all men haue of <hi>Platoes</hi> Common-wealth, or of <hi>Aristotles</hi> Felicitie, of <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> Orator, or of <hi>Moores</hi> Vtopia, that they containe in them rather an <hi>Idaea</hi> of good life, than such a platforme as may be drawne from contemplation into action, he hath ioined works with words, practise with precept, and the fruits of rare examples with the faire flowers of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall instructions. But many are so farre from concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any such excellencie in them, that so soone as they heare the name of <hi>Philosophy,</hi> they thinke they haue suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cause to condemne as hurtfull, all the writings of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers,</hi> alleadging that sentence of S. <hi>Paule: Beware least there be any man that spoile you through Philosophy:</hi> not consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Apostle doth in the very next wordes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound himselfe, and sheweth that he meaneth nothing els but the deceitfull conclusions of mans reason, disagreeing from the doctrine of Christ reuealed vnto vs in his word. I grant that the word of God is onely perfect, and contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in it an absolute rule both of pietie towards God, and humanitie towards men, but it followeth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that we may not vse the benefit of humane precepts, or tread in the steps of heathen men, so farre foorth as their learning and liues dissent not from the truth of holy Scriptures. Will any man refuse pearles bicause they are offered him in base vessels? Or not vse a light bicause it is not put into a siluer candlesticke? And shall we passe ouer without profite, so many good precepts and woorthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of learned men, bicause they proceede from the twilight of naturall knowledge, and not from the cleere sunne-shine of the word of God? Let vs rather harken to S. <hi>Augustine</hi> in his second booke of Christian doctrine, where he hath these words agreeing very fitly to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>As for those</hi> (saith he) <hi>that are called Philosophers, if they</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de doct. chr. cap. <hi>40.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>haue vttred any truth agreeable to our faith &amp; doctrine (especially the Platonists) we are not onely not to feare it, but rather to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it from them as from vniust possessors thereof. For as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians had not onely idols and heauy burdens, which the people of</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Israell were to detest and flye from, but also vessels and ornaments of gold, siluer and raiment, which that people at their departure out of Egypt challēged couertly to themselues for better vses, although not of their owne authoritie, but by the commandement of God, &amp;c. So the doctrine of the Gentiles hath not onely counterfet and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious forgeries and heauy packs of needeles labour, which euery one of vs departing from their societie vnder our Captaine Christ, ought to detest and shun: but also liberall Arts meete to set foorth the truth by, and certaine profitable precepts of manners, yea some true points concerning the worship of one onely God.</hi> What their knowledge was concerning themselues, and their dutie one towards another, the whole Treatise following ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth at large, vnto which I had rather referre you, than vse any needeles repetition in this place. And as for that other point concerning the knowledge of one only God, it is most certaine, that from the light of Nature holpen with industrie, studie, and education, (according to the wisedome and dispensation of God) many notable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions proceeded from sundry of them, as <hi>Augustine</hi> him selfe sheweth by a long discourse in his eight booke <hi>De Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>8.</hi> de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei, cap. <hi>6. 7. 8.</hi> &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Dei,</hi> where among other he alleadgeth these out of <hi>Plato: That God is a spirite, and of a farre more excellent nature than the soule of man, or any other spirite whatsoeuer: that God is one and the same, and alwaies like vnto himselfe: that God is the light of our minds, wherby we attaine to all our knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding: that no man is therefore blessed and happy, bicause he hath abundance of wealth, honor, strength beautie, or of any exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thing, nor yet for any gift of the mind, but bicause he enioyeth God the soueraigne Good.</hi> How diuinely doth <hi>Aristotle</hi> write of God, and of his fatherly prouidence, in his tractate <hi>De Mundo</hi> dedicated to <hi>Alexander?</hi> I know that many with force of reason carying them thereunto, haue vehemently suspected, that this peece of worke came neuer out of his shop. Which although it be granted for true, yet the book it selfe doth euidently declare, that the Author thereof was a meere heathen man, and directed onely by his pure Naturals when he wrote it: which being sufficient to shew
<pb facs="4"/>
how farre the darkenes of nature doth comprehend the light and knowledge of heauenly things, is as much as I <note place="margin">Aristotle de Mundo.</note>require. This treatise being wholy occupied in these two principall points: namely, in the description of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall frame of the world, and in the declaration of the nature of God the workemaister thereof, I will briefly set before you the summe of the last part, which the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher painteth out vnto vs very notably in liuely and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent colours. First he acknowledgeth, <hi>that all things are of God, that they consist and haue their being by his power, that no na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatsoeuer is able to continue, if it be not maintained and preserued by him.</hi> And in setting out the manner of working whereby this mightie power of God is forceable in the gouernment of all things, he goeth beyond the common reach of naturall men, affirming, that although God be present euery where, yet not by any bodily or locall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, as the common receiued opinion then was, <hi>That all things whatsoeuer we perceiue by sight, hearing, or any other sense, were full of Gods,</hi> and as <hi>Seruetus</hi> blasphemously taught of late yeeres, <hi>That God was an essentiall part of euery creature,</hi> but that he gouerneth all things <hi>by his power and vertue,</hi> whereby he effecteth whatsoeuer pleaseth him. Againe, as he subscribeth to the almightie power and prouidence of God in the being and rule of all things, so he laboureth to make knowne the great wisedome of God by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the excellent course of nature, which is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine without inconstancie, beautifull without blemish, &amp; diuers without disorder. For what can be more certaine than the ordinarie course of the Sunne, Moone, &amp; Starres, which haue continued in their appointed race from time to time, and from one age vnto another? What greater certaintie than that which to our comfort appeereth in the mutuall turnes and returnes of times and seasons, of Sommer and Winter, Spring and Autumne, day &amp; night? In regard of which constant continuance of the irreuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order appointed by God in this whole frame, the world is called by the Hebrewes <hi>gnolam:</hi> and in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
<pb facs="5"/>
to that people, it is expressed by this word <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, (which many times signifieth perpetuitie) <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 2. &amp; 11. 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the beautie and glorious shew thereof, what thing more beautifull than the glittering face of the heauens, decked and adorned with starres both great and small, as it were with iewels and pretious stones of all sorts? And for this self same cause it receiued that name of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> from the Grecians, and of <hi>Mundus</hi> from the Latines. Lastly, if we looke either to the variable motions of the Spheres in the ethereall region, or to the contrary qualities of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements in the aerie and lower part of the world, or to the varietie of foules, fishes, beasts, plants, graine, stones, met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, &amp;c. and consider withall what a sweete harmonie ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth from all these, as it were from a well tuned instrumēt that hath strings of all sorts, or like to a liuely picture that hath all kinds of colours mingled in it, or to a well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red citie compounded of sundry occupations, callings, &amp; conditions, of poore and rich, yoong and old, bond and free, we may see if we haue but halfe an eie, and feele if we be blind, that in this rare peece of worke and frame of the world, there is most excellent conueiance without confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, great varietie concurring in vnitie, and diuersitie of all kinds without disorder. All this and much more is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed by the Author of that booke <hi>De Mundo,</hi> (be he <hi>Aristotle,</hi> or some other heathen Philosopher) <hi>to the onely working of the power of the inuisible God, of whome</hi> (saith he) <hi>we must thus conceiue, that for his power he is most mightie, for his beautie most excellent, for his life immortall, and for his vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> most absolute:</hi> and therfore he cannot be seene of any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal creature, but is notwithstanding known by his works. <hi>For all accidents in the aire, in the earth, and in the water, may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called the works of God, who containeth and preserueth this world, of whome</hi> (as <hi>Empedocles</hi> saith) <hi>proceeded,</hi>
      <q>
         <l>All things that were, that are, and shall be here,</l>
         <l>Plants, Men, Beasts, Birds, and fish in waters cleere.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>But this Philosopher not contenting himselfe with this consideration and view of God in his works, entreth into
<pb facs="5"/>
a deeper meditation of his nature, by setting downe a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good exposition, and as it were a Commentarie vpon those names and titles, which vsually were attributed in his time vnto God, thereby to make his powerful gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer all the world more knowne vnto men. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though</hi> (saith he) <hi>that God be but one, yet we call him by many names, as</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>and</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>bicause we liue by him:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, bicause he is of an immutable nature: <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>bicause nothing is done by chāce, but according to his most certaine decree:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>bicause no man can possibly auoide him, or flie from him:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>bicause he abideth for euer. And as for that fable</hi> (faith he) <hi>of the three sisters of destinie, I meane of Clotho that spinneth of Leachesis that draweth out to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ust length, and of Atropos that cutteth off the threed of mans life, it is to be vnderstood of God onely, who (as it was said in old time) is the beginning, midst, and end of all things. To conclude, there is a iustice that is neuer separated from God, which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenger of al transgressions committed against the law of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery one must be well instructed that would be partaker of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane felicitie and happines.</hi> Now iudge, I pray you, whether a Christian may not with profit enter into this schoole of nature, and reape commoditie by this little light of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall knowledge, which as it serued to make them without excuse that were endued therewith, bicause they know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, did not glorifie him as god, neither were thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but became vaine in their imaginations: so it is to be feared, that those selfe same men shal rise vp in iudgement against vs that professe Christianitie, and condemne vs in that great and terrible day. For how many of vs want that knowledge of the eternall power, diuinitie, &amp; prouidence of God, which was in <hi>Parmenides, Plato, Aristotle,</hi> &amp; others, endued onely with the light of nature, whereby they were led from the view of the creatures, to the consideration of the inuisible things of God? And if we looke into the liues of men in these daies, &amp; consider what neglect there is of those mutuall duties which God commandeth vs to exhibite one to another, we shall soone see, that many a million of carnall Gospellers come farre short euen of
<pb facs="6"/>
those ciuill apparant and halfe vertues of the Heathen, &amp;<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Strommat.</note> may therefore be sent backe to learne holines of <hi>Socrates,</hi> iustice and innocencie of <hi>Aristides,</hi> charitie of <hi>Cymon,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right dealing of <hi>Phocion,</hi> fidelitie in perfourming promises of <hi>Regulus,</hi> moderation of <hi>Camillus,</hi> parsimonie of <hi>Curius,</hi> grauitie of <hi>Cato,</hi> &amp; what not of Heathen men, whose sight in these thinges was better at midnight, than ours is at mid-day. But my meaning is not to approoue that Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criphal tradition of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> who saith, that <hi>as the Lawe was a schoole-maister to the Iewes to leade them to Christ: so Philosophy was to the Grecians to bring them to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Now, although this erronious doctrine be as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to truth, as darkenes is to light, and as hel is to heauen, yet did <hi>Andradius</hi> defend it in a booke set foorth by him at their instigation (as himselfe protesteth) who were of greatest authoritie in the late Tridentine Councell. Doth not the Lorde by the mouth of <hi>Esay</hi> tell vs, that there is no light in them that haue not recourse to the Lawe and to the testimonie, and speake not according to his word? <hi>Esay</hi> 8. 20. Dooth not our Sauiour Christ sende vs to the Scriptures for euerlasting life? <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 39. Howe then dare anie professing Christianitie, affirme, that <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers by the light of nature, and knowledge of Philosophie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the direction of the written word of God were made partakers of the righteousnes that commeth by faith,</hi> and so consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of eternall happines? But to let this blasphemous mouth passe, let vs make that account of the writings of men which they deserue, and reape that commoditie by them, which we may without preiudice to the written word. For my meaning is not in commending <hi>Philosophie,</hi> to giue greater credite vnto it, or further to allow the vse thereof, than may stand with the maiestie of the holy and sacred Scripture, which being the Mistres of all humane arts and disciplines, vseth them as hir handmaids to serue and obeie hir. Therefore as it is vnseemly for a maid-ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to go before hir Mistres, to speake before she be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto, or to vse three words for hir one, especially in
<pb facs="6"/>
companie where seruice and modestie is most required: so it beseemeth not the ambassadors of Gods word (vnto whom indeed the knowledge of toongs and humane arts is a singular helpe) to vse these gifts otherwise than as handmaids in their studies and meditations to setue the Scripture to the more plaine and pure exposition of it, seeing they are sent to edifie others, and not to set our themselues. Now when they stuffe a great part of their speech with poeticall philosophicall sayings and examples (as also they are woont to alledge Hebrew, Greeke, and Latine sentences to draw men into admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their great learning) they set the Mistres behind, and giue the first and chiefest place vnto the handmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens. Is not this <hi>To make the crosse of Christ of none effect?</hi> I. <hi>Cor.</hi> I. 17. To vse that kind of preaching that standeth in the inticing speech of mans wisedome; and not in plaine euidence and power, is it not <hi>to build faith vpon the wisedom of men, and not vpon the power of God?</hi> I. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 4. 5. If disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of matter and forme be vnseemely, how vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is it in spirituall doctrine to vse a carnal and humane kind of teaching, I. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 13? to alay the strength of the word of Christ with the waterish sayings &amp; fables of men? to put vpon the naked and glorious face of God the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly clokes of <hi>Poets &amp; Philosophers?</hi> When the Lorde hath sanctified, not the corruptible seede of the sayings of men, but the incorruptible seede of his owne most holy worde to the begetting of faith, are not these new begetters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to bring in another way of regeneration? When Gods will is to haue his children nourished with the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and vnmingled milke of his worde, dare man vse the infusion of water, to the weakening of them whome he ought to confirme? When the King hath appointed for his sonnes and daughters the purest and finest wheate, shall the Steward, as if they were swine, prouide Acornes for them? But I detaine you too long from entering into the pleasant walks of this Platonical Academie &amp; Schoole of Moral Philosophy, which being hewen out of the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest
<pb facs="7"/>
timber of all Countries, was raised vp, and set togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in France, and is newly rough-cast (as you see) by an English workeman: whose earnest desire is to haue this small labour of his knowne to other, and receiued of you as a monument of his gratefull mind towards your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, for the manifold benefits which he hath from a child receiued at your hands. In consideration whereof I am bold or rather bound, to offer my self togither with these my first fruits vnto your good liking, beseeching him that turned your bountifull hart towards me, to knit it so neere vnto himselfe, that he may be your chiefe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in this life, &amp; your only happines in the world to come. Thus commending you and that good Gentlewoman your wife with all yours, to the grace of God, I take my leaue of you <date>this 17. of October.</date>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships euer boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Lord,
T. B. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>