<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE KINGDOME
APPERTEINETH
TO OVR
God.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1558</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108129_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04928</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15070</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108129</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE KINGDOME
APPERTEINETH
TO OVR
God.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first blast of the trumpet against the monstruous regiment of women</title>
                 <author>Knox, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Switzerland--Geneva City</pubPlace>
                    <date>1558</date>
                 <publisher>Poullain (Poulain), Jacques.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Reboul (Rebul), Antoine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE KINGDOME
APPERTEINETH
<hi>TO OVR
God.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>VVonder it is, that amongest
so many pregnant wittes as
the Ile of greate Britanny
hath {pro}duced, so many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
and zelous preachers as England
did somtime norishe, and amongest so many
learned and men of graue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
as this day by Iesabel are exiled,
none is found so stowte of courage, so faithfull
to God, nor louing to their na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue
countrie, that they dare admonishe
the inhabitantes of that Ile how abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
before God, is the Empire or
Rule of a wicked woman, yea of a
traiteresse and bastard. And what may
a people or nation left destitute of a
lawfull head, do by the authoritie of
Goddes worde in electing and appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting
common rulers and magistrates.
That Ile (alas) for the contempt and
horrible abuse of Goddes mercies of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred,
<pb facs="3"/>
and for the shamefull reuolting
to Satan frome Christ Iesus, and frome
his Gospell ones professed, doth iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
merite to be left in the handes of
their own counsel, and so to come to cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fusion
and bondage of strangiers. But
yet I feare that this vniuersall negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gēce
of such as somtimes were estemed
watchemen,<note place="margin">Negligen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemen.</note> shall rather aggrauate our
former ingratitude, then excuse this
our vniuersall and vngodlie silence, in
so weightie a mater. We se our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
set furthe for a pray to foreine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
we heare the blood of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
the mēbres of Christ Iesus most
cruellie to be shed, and the monstruous
empire of a cruell woman (the secrete
counsel of God excepted) we knowe
to be the onlie occasion of all these mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series:
and yet with silence we passe the
time as thogh the mater did nothinge
appertein to vs. But the cōtrarie exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
of the auncient prophetes moue me<note place="margin">The dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gēce of the olde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes of God.</note>
to doubte of this our fact. For Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
did vniuersalie decline frome
God by embrasing idolatrie vnder Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam.
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
In whiche they did continue<note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi>Reg.<hi>12</hi>
      </note>
euen vnto the destruction of their com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon
welthe. And Iuda withe Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
did followe the vile superstition
and open iniquitie of Samaria. But<note place="margin">Ezech.<hi>16.</hi>
      </note>
yet ceased not the prophetes of God
to admonishe the one and the other:
Yea euen after that God had poured
furthe his plagues vpon them. For Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie
<note place="margin">Ierem. <hi>29</hi>
      </note> did write to the captiues in Baby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lon, and did correct their errors, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
instructing them, who did remaine
in the middest of that idolatrouse
nation. Ezechiel<note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>7,8,9.</hi>
      </note> frome the middest
of his brethren prisoners in Chaldea, did write his vision to those that were
in Ierusalem, and sharplie rebukinge
their vices, assured them that they
shuld not escape the vengeance of God<note place="margin">God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way had his people amongest the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, who neuer lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked their prophetes and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note>
by reason of their abominations com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
   <p>The same prophetes for comfort
of the afflicted and chosen saintes of
God, who did lie hyd amongest the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate
of that age (as cōmonlie doth
the corne amongest the chasse) did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie
<pb facs="4"/>
and before speake the changes
<note place="margin">Isaie <hi>13.</hi> Ierem. <hi>46</hi> Ezech. <hi>36</hi>
      </note> of kingdomes, the punishmentes of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannes,
and the vengeance whiche God
wold execute vpon the oppressors of
his people. The same did Daniel and
the rest of the prophetes euerie one in
their season. By whose examples and
by the plaine precept, which is geuen
to Ezechiel, commanding him that he
<note place="margin">Examples what tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers oght to do in this time.</note> shall say to the wicked: Thou shalt die
the death. We in this our miserable age
are bounde to admonishe the world ād
the tyrānes therof, of their sodeine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction,
to assure them, and to crie
vnto them, whether they list to heare or
<note place="margin">Ezech.<hi>2.</hi> Apoca. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> not. That the blood of the saintes,
which by them is shed, cōtinuallie cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
and craueth vengeance in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
of the Lorde of hostes. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
it is our dutie to open the truthe
reueled vnto vs, vnto the ignorant and
blind world, vnlest that to our owne cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demnation
we list to wrap vp and hyde
the talent committed to our charge.
I am assured that God hath reueled to
some in this our age, that it is more
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
then a mōstre in nature, that a woman
shall reigne ād haue empire aboue man.
And yet with vs all, there is suche silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
as if God there with were nothing
offended. The naturall man, ennemy to
God shall fynd, I knowe, many causes
why no suche doctrine oght to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished
in these our dangerous dayes.<note place="margin">Thre chef reasons, that do stay man from spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king the truthe.</note>
First, for that it may seme to tend to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
secondarilie, it shal be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
not onlie to the writer or publisher,
but also to all such as shall reade the
writinges, or fauor this truth spoken:
and last it shall not amend the chief of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders,
partlie because it shall neuer
come to their eares, and partlie because
they will not be admonished in such ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses.
I answer, yf any of these be a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
reason that a truth knowen shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be
cōceled, then were the auncient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes
of God very fooles, who did not
better prouide for their owne quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
then to hasard their liues for rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
of vices, and for the opening of
such crimes, as were not knowen to the
world. And Christ Iesus did iniurie to
<pb facs="5"/>
his Apostles, commāding them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache
repentance and remission of syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
in his name to euerie realme and na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.
And Paule did not vnderstand his
owne libertie, when he cried, wo be to
<note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi>Cor.<hi>9.</hi>
      </note> me, if I preache not the Euangile. Yf
feare, I say, of persecution, of sclander,
or of any inconuenience before named
might haue excused, ād discharged the
seruantes of God, from plainlie rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<note place="margin">Mat.<hi>26.</hi> Act.<hi>18, 21.</hi>
      </note> the sinnes of the world, iuste cause
had euerie one of them to haue ceased
frome their office. For sodeinlie their
doctrine was accused by termes of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
of newe learning, and of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:
persecution and vehement trouble
did shortlie come vpon the professours
with the preachers: kinges, princes and
worldlie rulers did conspire against
<note place="margin">Psalm.<hi>2.</hi> Act.<hi>4.</hi>
      </note> God and against his anoynted Christ
Iesus. But what? Did any of these moue
the prophetes and Apostles to faynt in
their vocation? no. But by the resistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
whiche the deuill made to them by
his suppostes, were they the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed
to publishe the truthe reueled
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
vnto them and to witnesse with their
blood, that greuous condemnation and
Goddes heuie vengeance shuld folowe
the proude contempt of graces offred.
The fidelitie, bold courage, and cōstan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie
of those that are passed before vs,
oght to {pro}uoke vs to folowe their foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steppes,
onles we loke for an other king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome then Christ hath {pro}mised to such
as perseuere in {pro}fession of his name to
the end. Yf any think that the empire of
women, is not of such importance, that
for the suppressing of the same, any mā
is bounde to hasarde his life, I answer,
that to suppresse it, is in the hād of god
alone. But to vtter the impietie and abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination
of the same, I say, it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of euerie<note place="margin">It is neces<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sarie for euerie mā to opē the impietie, whiche he knoweth to hurt his cōmon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welth.</note> true messager of God, to whome the truth is reueled in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.
For the especiall dutie of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
messagers is to preache repentāce, to
admonishe the offenders of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenses,
and to say to the wicked, thou
shalt die the death, except thou repent.
This, I trust, will no man denie to be
the propre office of all Goddes messa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb facs="6"/>
to preache (as I haue said) repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
and remission of synnes. But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of both can be done, except the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
of the offenders be accused and
conuicted of transgression. For howe
shall any man repēt<note place="margin">No man can repēt except he knowe his synne.</note> not knowing wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in he hath offended? And where no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
is founde, there can be no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
to grace. And therfore I say, that
of necessitie it is, that this monstrife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse
empire of women, (which amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest
all enormities, that this day do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
vpon the face of the hole earth,
is most detestable and damnable) be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlie
reueled and plainlie declared to
the world, to the end that some may re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent
and be saued. And thus farre to
the first sorte.</p>
   <p>To such as thinke that it will be long
before such doctrine come to the eares
of the chief offenders, I answer that the
veritie of God is of that nature, that at
<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of Goddes truth.</note> one time or at other, it will pourchace
to it selfe audience. It is an odour and
smell, that can not be suppressed, yea it
is a trumpet that will sound in despite
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
of the aduersarie. It will compell the
verie ennemies to their own cōfusion,
to testifie and beare witnesse of it. For
I finde that the prophecie and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
of Heliseus was declared in the
hall of the king of Syria by the seruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
and flatterers of the same wicked
king, making mētion that Heliseus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared<note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi>Reg.<hi>6.</hi>
      </note>
to the king of Israel, what so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
the said king of Syria spake in his
most secret chamber. And the wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
workes of Iesus Christ were noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
to Herode, not in any greate praise<note place="margin">Mat.<hi>14.</hi>
      </note>
or commendation of his doctrine, but
rather to signifie that Christ called that
tyranne a fox, and that he did no more
regarde his authoritie then did Iohn
the Baptist, whom Herode before had
beheaded for the libertie of his tonge.
But whether the bearers of the rumors
and tidinges were fauourers of Christ
or flatterers of the tyranne, certein it is
that the fame, as well of Christes doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne,
as of his workes came to the eares
of Herod: euen so may the sounde of
our weake trumpet, by the support of
<pb facs="7"/>
some wynd (blowe it from the south
or blowe it from the northe it is no ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter)
come to the eares of the chief offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders.
But whether it do or not, yet dare
we not cease to blowe as God will gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<note place="margin">Rom.<hi>1.</hi>
      </note> strength. For we are debters to mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then
to princes, to witte, to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of our brethren, of whome, no
doubte a greate nomber haue here to
fore offended by errour and ignorance,
<note place="margin">The igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude hath set vp the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie of womē not knowinge the dāger</note> geuing their suffragies, consent and hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe
to establishe women in their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
and empires, not vnderstanding
howe abominable, odious, and detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
is all such vsurped authoritie in the
presence of God. And therfore must
the truthe, be plainlie spoken, that the
simple and rude multitude may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished.</p>
   <p>And as concerning the danger, which
may hereof insue, I am not altogither
so brutishe and insensible, but that I
haue laid mine accōpt what the finish<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge
of the worke may coste me for
mine own parte. First, I am not ignorāt
howe difficile and dangerous<note place="margin">A very dāgerous thing to speake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst olde errors</note> it is to
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
speake against a cōmon error, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie when that the ambitious mindes of
men and women are called to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
of goddes simple cōmandemēt.
For to the most parte of men, laufull
and godlie appeareth, what soeuer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie
hath receiued. And secondari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
I looke to haue mine aduersaries
not onlie of the ignorant multitude,
but also of the wise, politike, and quiet
spirites of this worlde, so that as well
shall suche as oght to mainteine the
truth and veritie of God become en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies
to me in this case, as shall the
princes and ambitious persons, who to
mainteine their vniust tyrannie do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
studie to suppresse the same.
And thus I am moste certeinlie persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
that my labour shall not escape re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension
of many. But because I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre<note place="margin">Accōptes will be had of Goddes giftes.</note>
that accomptes of the talentes
receiued must be made to him, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
respecteth the multitude, nether
yet approueth the wisdome, policie,
peace, nor antiquitie, concluding or
determining any thinge against his
<pb facs="8"/>
eternall will reueled to vs in his moste
blessed worde, I am compelled to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
myne eyes, and shut vp myne eares,
that I nether se the multitude, that shall
withstand me in this mater, nether that
I shall heare the opprobries, nor consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the dangers, which I may incurre
for vttering the same. I shalbe called
foolishe, curious, despitefull, ād a sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of sedition: and one day parchance
(althogh now I be nameles) I may be
<note place="margin">The cause mouing the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to write.</note> attainted of treason. But seing that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
it is, but that ether I shall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
God, dailie calling to my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
that I oght to manifest the veritie
knowen, or elles that I shall displease
the worlde for doing the same, I haue
determined to obey God, not withstan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding
that the world shall rage therat. I
knowe that the world offēded (by God<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
permission) may kill the bodie, but
Goddes maiestie offended, hath power
to punishe bodie and soule for euer.
His maiestie is offended, when that his
preceptes are cōtemned, and his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges
estemed to be of none effect.
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
And amongest his manifold preceptes
geuen to his prophetes, and amongest
his threatninges, none is more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
then is that, which is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced<note place="margin">Ezech.<hi>33.</hi>
      </note>
to Ezechiel in these wordes: Sōne
of man, I haue appointed the a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
to the house of Israel, that thou
shuldest heare from my mouthe the
worde, and that thou maist admonishe
them plainlie, when I shall say to the
wicked man: O wicked, thou shalt as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredlie
die. Then if thou shalt not
speake, that thou maist plainlie admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe
him, that he may leaue his wicked
way, the wicked man shall die in his ini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quitie,
but his blood will I requier of
thy hand. But and if thou shalt plainlie
admonishe the wicked man, and yet he
shall not turne from his way, such a one
shall die in his iniquitie, but thou hast
deliuered thy soule.</p>
   <p>This precept, I say, with the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
ānexed, togither with the rest, that
is spoken in the same chapter, not to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel
onlie, but to euerie one, whom
God placeth whatchman ouer his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="9"/>
and flocke, (and watchmen are they
whose eyes he doth open, and whose cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science
he pricketh to admonishe the
vngodlie) compelleth me to vtter my
conscience in this mater, not withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
that the hole worlde shuld be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
with me for so doing. Yf any
wonder, why I do concele my name, let
him be assured, that the feare of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
punishement is nether the onlie, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<note place="margin">For the Authors name.</note> the chef cause. My purpose is thrise
to blowe the trumpet in the same ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
if God so permitte:t wife I intende
to do it without name, but at the last
blast, to take the blame vpon my selfe,
that all others may be purged.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>