<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The Preface of Iohn Brentius vpon the Pro∣phecie of Ionas.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108281_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16696</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3601</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108281</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The Preface of Iohn Brentius vpon the Pro∣phecie of Ionas.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes from Niniue to Englande, brought by the prophete Ionas : vvhich newes in plainlye published in the godly and learned exposition of Maister Iohn Brentius folovving, translated out of Latine into Englishe by Thomas Tymme minister</title>
                 <author>Brenz, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 81 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶The Preface of Iohn <hi>Brentius vpon the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of Ionas.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apostle Paule wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Corinthians, of the meeting and comminge togither of the Church, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth all thinges to be done in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same congregatiō, to edifying. When ye come togither (sayth he) euerye one of you hath a song,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a reuelation, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng. Seing therefore it is determined that wee must come togither certaine dayes in the weeke: I will take in hande (by the assistance of Gods holy spirite) for our exercise at that time the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Prophet Ionas, to the ende wee may be godly occupied and exercised in this oure meetinge. For wee come not togither in the Church to trifle and playe, but we come to the ende we might be instructed in the worde of the Lorde. Neyther are we created by God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the precious death and bloudshedding of Christ, to the ende we should ryot, lyue in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, and giue our selues to all kinde of filthye pleasure, but we are created and redeemed to the ende we might glorifie God by our lyfe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation. We haue taken in hande therefore to expounde the prophecie of Ionas, that by this prophecie we maye be admonished, of our office, dutie and calling.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>And although the booke of this prophecie be very small, yet notwithstanding, it contayneth an excellent and famous hystorie. First of all therefore, we will declare, who was this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ionas: Then what, and how great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie his prophesie hath: And last of all, we wil shewe the argument, and what the summe of the doctrine contayned in this booke, is.</p>
   <p>First, there are many, which thinke, and iudge the prophete Ionas to be the sonne of the widowe of Sarepta, which receyued and fedde Elias in the time of famine: but their iudgement is neyther likely nor probable. For, of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ionas, we haue mention made in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth Chapter of the fourth booke of Kinges,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.</note> how that Ieroboam king of Israel, reedified his decayed Kingdome, accordinge to the worde of the Lord which he spake by the prophet Ionas, the sonne of Amithay, which was of Gathhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. By the which it appeareth, that hee made not only the sermon contayned in this booke, but many other notable and famous sermons, which are not writtē. For he preserued by his sermons, two of the most excellent kingdomes that were. Excellent was the kingdome of Israell: but in the time of Ionas it was a decayed and ruinous kingdome, by impietie and inuasion of enimies. Ionas therefore, being stirred vp by the holye ghoste, exhorteth the people to repentaunce, and incourageth king Ieroboam valiauntlye to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his common welth: promising, that God will sende a time of mercie, wherein he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store his kingdome. And so in deede it came to passe, that the coast of Israell, from the entring of Hemath, vnto the sea of the wildernesse, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored
<pb facs="5"/> by the goodnesse of the Lorde.</p>
   <p>Famous also was the Citie of Niniue, for in it, was the greatest Monarchie of the whole worlde. But the Lorde had determined to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroye the Citie of Niniue, from the face of the earth. Yet notwithstanding, Ionas saued the same by his sermon. Wherefore, seeing Ionas by hys sermons saued such two excellent kingdomes, he is not to bee counted among the common sort of men, but euen among the chiefest Prophetes that haue beene, eyther before his time, or since.</p>
   <p>Secondly, we must consider the certaintye, and aucthoritie of this booke. The Church as yet, neuer reiected or refused this booke: but haue accounted the same among those, which wee call Canonicall bookes of holye scripture, and which haue Ecclesiasticall, and heauenlye testimonies. Furthermore, we haue our sauiour Christ (as concerning this matter) a sufficient testimony and witnesse, as may appeare by the .xij.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 12.</note> Chapter of Mathew, where he alledgeth the example of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas for his resurrection, affirming, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Ionas out of the Whales bellye, was a type of the same. Furthermore, Christ preferreth the Niniuets, before the Israelites, bicause the Niniuets repented at the one onelye sermon of Ionas, and the Israelites woulde not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto the Lorde by many sermons.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, if euer any man did, or shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after doubt of the aucthoritie, truth, and certaintie of this booke, Christ by his testimonie, hath so confirmed the same, that though an Aungell came from heauen teaching the contrary, he ought not to be beleued.</p>
   <p>Last of all, we must knowe the argument or
<pb facs="6"/> summe of this prophecie, in the which certayne perticuler places are noted.</p>
   <p n="1">1 The first place conteyneth the seueritie of the wrath of God towardes all such as walke diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediently in their calling. Ionas was a Prophet which was most acceptable vnto god, and which before, had done notable things in Israell, and by his sermons had preserued the kingdome of the same: notwithstanding, when hee fled and was disobedient to his calling, he was cast by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God, into the Sea. An example of Gods seuere punishment worthye to bee noted. The lyke we haue of Saule,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> who, disobeying the commaundement of God, reserued part of the pray of Amelecke, for the which disobedience hee was rent from his kingdome. Another example we haue of the prophete,<note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 13.</note> whom the Lion slue by Gods appoyntment for his disobedience. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it is sayde, to obey, is better than sacrifice, and to hearken is better than the fat of Rammes.<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2 The seconde place conteyneth the wonderful, and inspeakeable mercy of God, by the which, he commonly deliuereth all those which call vpon him in truth. Ionas was cast into the sea, and deuoured of the Whale. And although he coulde not be saued and deliuered naturally: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, by the diuine power and clemencie of God, he is supernaturally, and miraculouslye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered. This miracle, to certaine worldly wise men, and contemners of the worde of God, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ridiculous, and like vnto olde wyues tales.</p>
   <p>And amongst all others, scoffing Lucian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing stirred vp of Sathan the Deuill, the father of lyes, to obscure, discredit, and deride this miracle, hath written a booke intituled, <hi>De veris narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> that is, a booke of true narrations: in the which, hee maketh mention of certaine men, which being in a ship, were swallowed vp shippe and all, of a Whale, in the which Whale (sayth he) there were Mountaynes, woods, and Cities, to the which the men arriued with their shippe, and had great delectation there. This fonde fable see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee inuented by Lucian, to deride the Christians, which beleeue the storie of Ionas to be true. But this and many other such are deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Deuill and his ministers, to deride, and deface, true, and godly myracles.</p>
   <p>But let vs vnderstand, that this myracle was done in deede, and that it hath heauenly testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to proue and ratifie the same, as we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie declared. God which created heauen, and earth of nothing, and which raysed, and will rayse the dead to life, could also for a time, saue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue Ionas in the whales belly. Let vs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therefore this myracle to be a declaration of the power and clemency of God, and an example also of the resurrection of Christ, and of all the godly also to euerlasting lyfe, as hereafter GOD willing shall be declared.</p>
   <p n="3">3 The thirde place conteyneth the doctrine of repentaunce. There haue beene many which haue denyed to sinners after their fall any hope of gods grace. And there are manye, which when they haue sinned, perswade themselues that there is no way of saluation left vnto them. Here therefore there are two examples of repentaunce propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs: The one in the Prophete Ionas, who although he fell into disobedience: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, repenting he is receyued into Gods fauour againe.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>The other, in the Niniuets, who although they had greatly sinned, insomuch, that they deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eternall destruction and damnation: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, repenting, they are receyued into Gods fauour, and preserued with their Citie. Let vs therefore turne to the Lorde by repentaunce, being perswaded that the Lorde will receyue vs, and that the Aungels in heauen shall reioyce ouer our repentaunce.</p>
   <p>Thus (gentle Reader) I haue declared, who this Prophet Ionas was, what aucthoritie this booke hath, and which are the speciall places of this booke. The which, if thou well obserue and note, they will profite, to the nourishing of the feare of God, to the encrease of fayth, and to the bringing forth of true obedience, which are the most accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble seruice of God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>