<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Of the vse and profite of histo∣ryes, and with what iudgement they oughte to bee redde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108255_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05076</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15217.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108255</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Of the vse and profite of histo∣ryes, and with what iudgement they oughte to bee redde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epitome of cronicles : Conteyninge the whole discourse of the histories as well of this realme of England as al other cou [n] treys, with the succesion of their kinges, the time of their reigne, and what notable actes they did ... gathered out of most probable auctours. Firste by Thomas Lanquet, from the beginning of the worlde to the incarnacion of Christe, secondely to the reigne of our soueraigne lord king Edward the sixt by Thomas Cooper, and thirdly to the reigne of our soueraigne Ladye Quene Elizabeth, by Robert Crowley. Anno. 1559</title>
                 <author>Lanquet, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 280, 30 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="29"/>
   <head>¶ Of the vse and profite of histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, and with what iudgement they oughte to bee redde.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT FOR MANY CAVSES</hi> (whyche we shall hereafter recyte) the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng of hystoryes doth indifferently auayle all men, yet moste specyallye it perteyneth to kynges and greatte prynces, whose boke it maye be worthely called, because that the knowledge thereof is moste profitable and necessary to all those, whyche haue the gouernaunce of cōmune weales. For not onely the hystoryes of the Gentiles, but also of the holy scryptures, doo in euerye place make mencyon of theym. The holy scryptures, besydes that they make vs certayne of the wyll and woorde of God, and also of the spyrytuall kyngedome of Chryste, teache vs polyticall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministracion, and set forth many notable examples, which in rulynge a publyke weale be necessary to bee knowen, and whereby the myndes of prynces maye be styerred to the study of true nobilitye and vertue. The hystoryes of the Gentyles declare the orygynall and begynnynge of greate empyres, and for what causes there hathe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in theim so gret and so straung alterations &amp; greuous commocyons. In the same is also conteyned preceptes of offyces and vertues, whereby the commune weales may most prosperousely be preserued, contynued and aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And for thys cause hystoryes are moost worthy to be called the bookes of good princis and noble men. Nowe, forasmuche as vnto euery prynce there belongeth a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertue, that is, a politicall or externall, and a fayth and feare towarde god, Exaumples of them bothe be shewed to vs out of hystoryes. Therefore we wyll fyrste speake of ciuyle vertues. Princes, yea and all other, that haue auctorytye in greate affaires and hyghe matters, oughte those examples and actes chyefelye to consyder, wherby they maye be admonyshed, by what meanes they maye mooste prosperouslye exercyse them selfes in the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the weale publike. They must sette before their eyes the examples of good kinges and rulers, and of them
<pb facs="30"/>
must they lerne the necessary dutye and the vpryght trade of gouerning their empyers, that in their reignes, besides the vtilitie and benefyte of the publyke weale, they regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing▪ that iustice and equitie they onely enbraced, that all misdemeanours and offences they greuously pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished: and agayne, that towardes good men and pecible they were alwayes beneficiall and gentyl, that for euery cause they woulde not rayse vp warres, but by wynkinge at iniuryes, reteyne peace, and yet in defence of theyr roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>almes, were neuer the lesse of an inuincible courage and redye will: finally that by their wysedome, power, and strength, that defended their dominions from all outward hostilitye, and the same in true religyon, welth, quietnes, and in all necessarye artes made to flouryshe. In all whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che qualities our most excellent &amp; gracious prince Henrye the eyghte, hath excelled, and is an example to theym all whiche shall succeede. For in hym alone is coniested and heaped all the sundry good qualities of the auncient kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by whyche they opteyned so great renome. Whyche qualityes he hath so practysed in the gouernaunce of hys realme, That I suppose there neuer was in any common weale, any noble prince and gouernoure whiche hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared mo examples of wisedome, or shewed mo benefites and pleasures to hys countrey than hys grace hath. But to the purpose. For the contrary parte.</p>
   <p>¶In the examples of tyrannes they maye obserue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers thynges: as, The ende of them to be miserable▪ and that through theyr crueltie many mischefes and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cōmocions haue chaunced in theyr common weales As it appereth how Pharao for tyrany peryshed, and for lyke cause the Romain kynges were exiled. Princes haue oftentymes distroyed one the other, only for pryde, disdain and enuy, and that many tymes begun vpon nothyng. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as it was the only cause of the cruel warres betwene Cesar and Pompei. The Romayne hystoryes shew, that the desyre of noueltie hath oft been the stirer of moost gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous warres. And the sect and reygne of Machomet had none other begynnyng but of heresy and dissencion of the artycles of the fayth. It auaileth them muche that bee in auctoritye, to marke these thynges in the redynge of hysto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes▪
<pb n="2" facs="30"/>
that they lerne to beware, foresee, and auoyde lyke thynges in their gouernance. For the same chances daily happen, all be it the persones nowe and than be chaunged in the commune weales, ne uerthelesse as pertaynynge to the similitude of busynes and trouble, the worlde remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the worlde, and lyke vnto it selfe. Therfore most tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thucydides (who was a man excellente in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of warrefare, and also wrate the greatte and longe warre, and other sundrye thyges, whiche chanced among the Grekes) sayth, Hystoryes be a treasure, whiche ought neuer to be out of our handes, that therby beynge ayded, we maye the more commodiously handle suche busynesse and like chaunces in the commune weale, for as much as the causes often tymes chaunce almoste lyke.</p>
   <p>¶Furthermore there be axaumples founde in hystoryes, conuenient for euery man priuately in his degree, as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gistrates ought to be obeyede, and that they neuer escaped vnpunished, whiche haue rebelled against theym, euen as Dathan, Absalom, Catiline, Brutus, Cassus, and suche lyke for their sedicion haue ben worthily punished. Of the fidelitie of frendes, as Ionathas saued the lyfe of kynge Dauyd. Of the punyshment for homicide, adulterye, and suche lyke offences, as it appereth by the example of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. But what shal nede many wordes. Euen as in euery arte paternes be geuen to folowe: lykewyse in hystoryes be peinted before our eyes examples of all kyndes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. But yet in examples and deedes it is more euydent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceyued, what the dignytye of vertue, and agayne, what the bacenesse of dyshonestee and vyces bee, than in bare preceptes, because that examples, set as images be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, do not onely openly teache, but also bothe warne and stirre our myndes, so that therby wyth a certayne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite and desyre they be kyndled towardes vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie. For who in hert can be so stubborne and hard, that will not be moued, if he rede anye thynge notable, that is either worthy prayse, or els exāples vtterly to be abhorryd</p>
   <p>I haue shewed briefely how in readyng of hystoryes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of politicall vertues and ciuyle affayres ought to bee obserued, Nowe it perteyneth to a true christen man. (who aboue all thynges oughte to esteeme godlynesse, to
<pb facs="31"/>
knowe, that he maye gather also out of hysteryes, exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of faythe and feare of god: For these be the specyall vertues of good men, which in the syghte of god be moste auailable. Al be it that the hystoryes of the gentyles doo not teache, that god careth or hath oughte to do wyth vs: yet a godly mynde neuerthelesse shall consyder, that the publyke weales in the worlde be conserued by the power of god, and that is the worke of god to punyshe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge all oppressyon, and vyolence, ye and that vnto the heathen God gyueth excellent qualities. For princes can not preserue their empyers agaynst the assaultes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, wythout the syngular benefyt of god, and the ayde of theyr owne vertue and wisedome. And so by thys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a good man maye well suppose, that these actes and punishmentes be the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rkes of god, and therby may lern the feare of god. As that tyrannes haue been greuousely punyshed accordynge to thys sentence: He that taketh the sworde, that is, whyche wythout auctorytye vsurpeth the ryght of reuengyng, he shall peryshe by the sworde. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywyse, it is euydent, that good prynces bee preserued and defended by god, and that also the Ethnykes did well perceyue, in that theyr princes had great affiaunce in the helpe of theyr goddes. For Homere the poete sayth: God casteth his sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>elde in the batayle, to defende the prynces, He feigneth also euery prynce to be vnder the protectyon of his god, as it appereth by the goddesse Pallas, whyche alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yes was presente wyth Achilles. But this thynge is more playnely expressed in the hystoryes of the holy scryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as in Noe, Abraham, Moses, Dauyd, Ezechias, and the other princes and kinges, whom god alwayes preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And their examples be set before the eies of all other princes, that they maye certaynly know, that in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner god wyll defende all good kinges. For thys difference is betwene the holy and prophane hystoryes, that in them be shewed the testymonies of the workes of god, and the whiche do not onely entreate of cyuile matters, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doo represente vnto vs the kyngdome of god, that god geueth his word, that of his mercy he wyll saue vs, wher in the hystoryes of the gentiles be ignorant. Therfore prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipally the hystoryes of the holy scripture ought to be kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen
<pb n="3" facs="31"/>
to all chrysten men, that therby they maye learne the doctryne and stablishement of faithe.</p>
   <p>¶ Fyrst how all thynges were created of god, what was the originall of synne, that agaynst synne Christe institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his kyngdome, gaue hys woorde, and that he shoulde come to take away sinne, and saue vs. Also how god, whā he had gyuen his worde, preserued alwayes the reygne of Chryst, and that the reigne of Christe, that is, the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuers from the begynnynge of the worlde, walked vnder the crosse, and neuerthelesse were pre serued. That Sathā wyth all the power of the worlde assaulted the worde of god. Moreouer, that God meruaylously perfourmed hys promyse aboue the opinyon and capacitie of mans wytte. Also that examples bothe of horyble vengeance, and also of grace and forgyuenes be shewed to vs of God, So vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to kyng Dauid and other chanced remission of syns, that by theyr examples we myghte bee comforted and beleue, that god wyll forgyue. Neyther thys is to be neglected that for the confyrmacion of our myndes, God hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs all sortes of prophecies of externall kyngdomes, that by the fulfillying of them, we maye haue a testimony that our woorde is of god, neyther that any other faythe than ours, is true. And that we maye bee admonyshed by them, whan Christ ought to come, and whan the consum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macion of the worlde shall be. Finally, for the ryghte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandyng the prophecyes, it shall be very expedyent to knowe the successe and alteracion of the monarchies and kyngdomes, wyth the computacyon and noumber of the yeres, whyche be in the hystoryes of the Gentiles exactly set foorth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> the knowledge wherof, euen for thys cause is necessarie for chrystians, that they maie the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the prophecyes, and of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the more certaynely iudge. Certes euery man maye by these thynges esteme, what pleasure and profyte is gathered in readynge of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storyes, and the fruitefull commoditye therof ought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to stire and compell euery man to knowe them.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>