<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Grace from God the Father, the Sonne and the holy Ghooste, be to the Queene of Scotlande.</title>
           <author>White, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108354_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11044</idno>
           <idno type="STC">192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108354</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Grace from God the Father, the Sonne and the holy Ghooste, be to the Queene of Scotlande.</title>
                 <author>White, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of chapiters exhortatiue : set forth in Greeke vvithoute meditatio [n], by Agapetus, minister of the most holy and greate churche of God: and nowe translated most truely out of Greeke into English, by Iames Whit Scotishman, as, the learned in both the tongues may easily iudge</title>
                 <author>Agapētos</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Serle (Searl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Grace from God the Father, the Sonne and the holy Ghooste, be to the Queene of Scotlande.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue been oftentimes deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>synge vvyth my felfe (moste gracious Souereigne) hovve I myghte best vtter my good vvyll vnto your noble Grace, according to my bounden duetie. I haue cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and thought it best, to dedicate thys litle booke to your Maiestie, in the vvhyche the office of a Prince is briefly set forth, not onely tovvards God his superioure: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so tovvards his Subiectes, sheepe vnder hys cure, a matter very proper and conueniēt for your most Royall Person: not bicause your Heighnes knovveth not the same all redye, but bycause it maie put your Maiestie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of that ye knovve. Hovve can there be any thynge vvorthy of knovvledge that is vnknovvē to your most noble Grace: being so vvell learned your selfe, and serued vvith moste learned, Honorable, vvise, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="3"/> &amp; Godly Councellers, so that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iestie must needs see, not only vvyth the eies of your moste beautiful body, but also vvith the eies of your most godli minde: according to Plato sayinge in Phaedro. Δίπλοῦν ὁρῶντες ὁί μα<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>οντες τὰ γράμματα that is, the learned see vvith double sighte: the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Scriptures in deede, maketh the eies of the soule to see perfectly: as vvitnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Prophet. 119. Chapter. Thy vvord is a Lanterne vnto my feet, &amp; a light vnto my pathes, to vvalke &amp; liue, therfore moste gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Queene, in the feare of the Lord, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesary the hering &amp; reading of Gods vvord. by the vvhich in faith feare him and kepe his commaundements: for the true seruinge of God, is the obseruing of his statuts: vvhose statutes, lavves &amp; vvyl can not be knovven, vvithout the light of his vvorde accordynge to Matthevv. the 22. Chapt. Ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vving the Scriptures, knovv then most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souereigne the sacred Scriptures and Testament of Christe oure sauioure: In the vvhich he promiseth to your Maiestie a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="3"/> most precious: after thys temporall a kingdome euerlasting: vvhich your Grace must obteine &amp; possesse by onely faith ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge to the promyse of the Lorde. VVhat is the promise? mercie promised: to vvhome? to all that haue truste &amp; confidence to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued through his mercie: and that Christ our Sauiour is a true promiser, and vvill accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishe his promise to all those vvhiche sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly beleue to be saued freely by him vvith out respecte of any other thing. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyest that euer vvas, is, or shalbe, is by Gods lavve iustly condemned, and throughe hys mercy onely saue, according to Paule. the .3 to the Romaines. Omnes enim peccaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ac destituuntur gloria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ei. All haue sinned, and haue neede of the glory &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God. That your Maiestie, after thys vvorldly kingdome long happely gouerned, maie reigne eternally through his promised mercie obteined by faith: I vvill vvhile lyfe maye laste, continually praye.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties seruant Iames VVhite</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>