<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Preface. ¶To my ryghte worshypfull suster dame Suzan Kyngestone.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1534</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108816_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19735</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6157</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108816</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Preface. ¶To my ryghte worshypfull suster dame Suzan Kyngestone.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A svvete and deuoute sermon of holy saynt Ciprian of mortalitie of man. The rules of a christian lyfe made by Picus erle of Mirandula, bothe translated into englyshe by syr Thomas Elyot knyghte</title>
                 <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1534</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Preface. ¶To my ryghte worshypfull suster dame Suzan Kyngestone.</head>
   <p>THe circumspecte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, whiche is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed one tyme in the yere, to be vexed with feuer, Catarre, or lyke sykenes, preuenteth that tyme by expulsynge the matter, whiche moughte be occasion of suche desseases, and studyeth to reduce the bodye into suche tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce, and so to preserue hit, as the sayde matter shall not be augmented, wherby moughte ensue any detriment: Lyke indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, or rather moche more, ought to be vsed, good Suster, of euery raysonable creature, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste the mooste certayne sike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="3"/>
and fynall dyssolution of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture called corporall death, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so agaynst all worldly vexations and troubles, called the toyes of fortune, or the crankes of the worlde: consyderyng that of any of them neyther the tyme can be knowen, whan they shal happen, nor assured remedy may be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for to repelle theym, onely a pure and constante faythe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge therto ioyned wysedome and pacience, may sustayne theyr assaultes, and stronglye resyste them. As it is excellently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and taughte by the holy doctour and martyr sayncte Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in a sermon which he made to the people of Affrica, where he was Bushop, in the tyme whan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>here was continuall persecution of paynyms, and also mortalitie
<pb facs="3"/>
by generall pestilence. whiche sermone whan I had ones {per} vsed in redynge, I liked so well, that I desyred that all other persones mought vnderstonde it. Remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brynge that many there be (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I doubte not) are as negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente as I in consyderyng those sondry calamities, not withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge that they haue beholden men and women of euery astate, whiche haue dyed eyther before that they looked for death, or in some other wyse than they vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched saulfe, or els forsaken of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune haue lyued in pouertye. Wherfore as welle for theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structyon as myne, howe we may be alway prepared agaynst those naturall and worldly afflictions, I haue traunslated this lyttell boke: not supersticiouselye folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge
<pb facs="4"/>
the letter, whiche is vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elegante, and therfore the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to trāslate into our langage, but kepynge the sentence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Autour I haue attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (not with lyttell study) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce into english the right phrase or forme of speakyng, vsed in this treatise, whiche I haue dedycate and sente vnto you for a token: that ye shall perceyue, that I doo not forgeat you: and that I doo vnfaynedly loue you, not onelye for our allyaunce, but also moche more for your perseuerance in ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu &amp; warkes of true faith, praieng you to communicate it with our two susters religiouse Dorothe &amp; Alianour, and to ioyne in your praiers to god for me, that I may be constante in his seruice, and performe well such other warkes
<pb facs="4"/>
as ben in my handes onely to his honour and glory.</p>
   <p>¶I haue added hereto a litel tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tise, but wonderful frutful, made by the vertuouse &amp; noble prince Iohn̄ Picus Erle of Mirandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, who in abundāce of lerning &amp; grace incomparablye excelled all other in his tyme and sens. whose picture I wolde to god were in all no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mens Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and his grace and vertues in theyr soules and maners. Hartyly fare ye wel. At london the fyrst day of Iuly, the yere of our lorde god 1534.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>