<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The life of Sir Iames Lo∣pez
de Mendoza, Marques of
Santilliana.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108829_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06341</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16809</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108829</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The life of Sir Iames Lo∣pez
de Mendoza, Marques of
Santilliana.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The prouerbes of the noble and woorthy souldier Sir Iames Lopez de Mendoza Marques of Santillana : with the paraphrase of D. Peter Diaz of Toledo: wherin is contained whatsoeuer is necessarie to the leading of an honest and vertuous life. Translated out of Spanishe by Barnabe Googe</title>
                 <author>Santillana, Iñigo López de Mendoza, marqués de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Watkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 116 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The life of Sir Iames Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pez
de Mendoza, Marques of
Santilliana.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir <hi>Iames Lopes de
Mendoza, Marques</hi> of
<hi>Santilliana,</hi> &amp; Earle of
the Realme of <hi>Manca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nares,</hi>
Lorde of <hi>Vega,</hi>
sonne of the Admirall
<hi>Don Diego de Hurtado,</hi> and nephewe to
<hi>Peter Goncales de Mendoza,</hi> Lord of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi>
was a man of a meane stature, verie well
limmed and proporcioned, and of a gracious
countenance, discended of great parentage, a
<hi>Castilian</hi> and verie ancient. He was a man
of a quicke iudgement, and discrete, and of so
great a minde, that neither could the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest
matters that were dismay him, nor the
dealing in matters of smal moment any whit
delight him. In the staiednesse of his person,
and the grauitie of his speach, he shewed him
selfe to be a Gentleman, and of a noble mind.
He was a man, as they vse to say, verie well
spoken, so as hee was seldome heard to speake
any thing that was not woorth the noting:
whether it were in matters of learning, or of
<pb facs="4"/>
disport. He was courteous and of great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteinment
to all such as came vnto him,
specially learned men. After the decease
of the Admirall his father, and the Ladie
<hi>Eleanor</hi> of <hi>Vega</hi> his mother, being left ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
yong and within age, he was disseised of
the <hi>Asturies</hi> of <hi>Santilliana</hi> and a greate
peece of his liuing beside. But comming to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
yeares, &amp; perceiuing himself to be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
abused, verie want and necessitie, which
many times awaketh a good wit, &amp; his great
mind that could not abide to be consined, made
him to vse such diligence, as partly by lawe,
partly by swoorde, hee did shortly recouer his
owne. Hee was both in his meate and his
drinke verie temperate, hauing herein a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
and speciall grace. Touching his incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
he gaue himselfe in his life time vnto
two notable exercises, the one the feates of
armes, the other studie and learning, neither
did his warlike exercises anie whit hinder his
studie, nor his studie was anie impediment to
the conference which he had with the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours
and Gentlemen of his house: about the
trampe &amp; fashion of their armour &amp; Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
of defence, howe to offend the enimie,
how to order his battails, &amp; how to encampe,
<pb facs="5"/>
how to assault, and how to defend fortresses,
and other like actions belonging to martiall
affaires, wherin hee tooke a great deale the
more pleasure, because he had therwith been
brought vp from his youth. And to the ende
that such as serued vnder him might haue
experience of such things as they had hearde
him speake off, hee had alwayes in his house,
Tilt, Turney, and Barriers, with sundry other
exercises belonging to the fielde, to the ende
that his people being alwayes accustomed to
such martiall exercises, might better away
with the paines of a souldier, whē they came
to it. Hee was a gentleman of great nobility
and valour, beeing in his determinations ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
wise and temperate, and in his execution
speedy and resolute: so as there could neither
be founde any rashnesse in his courage, or any
iot of cowardise in his deuises. He had been
Generall in many fought Battailes betwixt
the Christians and the Sarazens, wherein he
both wan and lost. But the greatest and of
most account, was a battaile that was fought
with the <hi>Aragoneses,</hi> and one other at the
riuer of <hi>Torotto.</hi> And these two Battailes
were indeed every hot and blooddy. For figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
without any retire on either side, there
<pb facs="5"/>
were slaine an infinite number on both sides:
at which seruices, because this worthy gētle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
happened to be present, though hee sawe
his owne forces all to weake, and very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete
to match with the enimie, yet because
the enemie was in sight, he thought it a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
shame and reproche to turne his backe
without Battaile, then to loose his life or the
fielde in fighting. Wherevpon he determined
to try the battaile, wherein hee fought with
such egernesse and courage, that although
he was his selfe sore hurt, and all his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
defeated, yet for his own person he gained
the name and reputation of a worthy &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant
Captaine. The sufficiencie of this noble
gentleman beeing thorowly knowen to King
<hi>Iohn,</hi> he was sent Lieutenāt general against
the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> which charge he toke vpō him
with a verye glad and willing minde, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing
a long time vpon the frontiers. During
which season he fought diuers battailes, and
had many sharpe encounters, both with the
king of <hi>Granada</hi> &amp; others of his captaines,
wherin he had alwayes the better. He made
many roades into the Country, where he wan
by fine force the towne of <hi>Huelma,</hi> &amp; draue
the <hi>Moores</hi> to such a streigt, that hee
<pb facs="6"/>
he woulde haue wonne a number of townes
more, &amp; haue done diuerse worthie exploites
had not the king (being by matters of more
importance at home enforced) commaunded
him to make an ende of the warres, and to
conclude a peece vpon the receyt of which cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission
he bare such a hand vpon them as he
brought them in subiection, and caused them
to pay for yearely tribute a great quantitie of
golde, such as neither the king did euer looke
to receyue, nor the Sarazens did euer thinke
to haue payed. And beside this yearely tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,
he compelled them to set at libertie all
such Christian prisoners as remained in their
custodie, all which this good Marques re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
out of captiuitie, and brought them
home to their Countrey. He gouerned with
great wisedome all such souldiours as were
vnder his regiment, behauing himselfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
them both as a captaine and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paniō,
being neither insolent in authoritie, nor
base minded in his familiaritie. For he was
alwayes in heart of such humilitie and
mildnesse, as made him to be beloued of God,
and outwardly of such grauitie and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
as caused him to be reuerēced of men.
He bountifully bestowed vpon his souldiers,
<pb facs="6"/>
what so euer belonged vnto him in right of
his generallship of al such spoyles and booties
as were taken, besides that which he gaue thē
in their necessities out of his owne purse: and
to such as shewed themselues thankefull for
his bountie, he vsed to say, that if we wish wel
to him that doth well vnto vs, wee ought to
giue well to him that wisheth well vnto vs.
and thus maintayning his credite by the
meanes of his great liberality, he was of all
his souldiours greatly beloued, who fearing to
offend him dyd alwayes obserue a perfect dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
in the fielde. His rare and singular
vertues beeing knowen to the king, and how
woorthy he was of honor &amp; dignity, he forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
aduaunced him to the Marqueship of
<hi>Santilliana</hi> &amp; created, him Erle of the <hi>Real</hi>
of <hi>Mancenares,</hi> addorning him with great
lands &amp; reuenues. Sometimes he committed
vnto him the charge of his owne person, and
many times the gouernment of al his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Who had such a special grace in his gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning,
as the Poets of that age accounted him
for his noble behauiour in court, an other <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo:</hi>
&amp; for his great valour in the field a 2
<hi>Hanibal.</hi> He was a great obseruer of al such
things as belōged to perfit māhood, &amp; so great
<pb facs="7"/>
a reprehender of cowardise and faintnesse of
heart, that seeing on a time a Gentleman to
weepe, for the great mishappes that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
vnto him, breaking foorth into some
choler, he sayd vnto him: Oh what a shame
is it to see a Gentleman to shedde teares for
anie thing, howe grieuous soeuer it be, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
onely for his offences towardes GOD?
He was a man of a great minde, which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse
of minde was an ornament &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
to all other his vertues. A couetous
worldling comming vnto him, and telling
him that hee let his landes farre vnder the
value, and promising to make him a much
greater reuenew, as one not willing to giue
eare to any such matter, hee made him this
aunswere: My friend I doe not vnderstand
thy language, goe speake it, I pray thee, to
some other that can better vnderstand thee.
He vsed alwayes to say to those that sought
to liue in pleasure and delight, that much
more delightfull ought to bee vnto vs a
vertuous trauaile, then a life without
vertue, howe pleasaunt soeuer it seeme. He
was of such a pitifull minde, that whosoeuer
came to him in his extremitie, being either
persecuted, or any wayes troubled, shoulde
<pb facs="7"/>
finde reliefe and defence in his house, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding
any daunger that might happen him
for so dooing. Hee did euermore measure
bothe the partyes, and the cause according
as in deede they were, and not as they were
supposed to bee: and in this thing hee had a
moste singular and almoste heauenly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
for he was neuer knowen to make any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
of persons, nor to regarde the riches,
the wealth, or mightinesse of any man, but to
regarde euery man according to the equitie
of his causethe wrote in verse the Prouerbs
that begin, <hi>My Sonne whom I doe deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
loue. &amp;c.</hi> In which Prouerbes are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
almost all the precepts of Morall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy,
whatsoeuer appertaineth to a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
life. He had a very great Library, and
gaue himselfe chiefly to the study of Moral
Philosophy, Histories, and Antiquities, hee
kept alwaies about him Doctours and men
of great learning, with whom he vsed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
of such thinges as he read. Hee wrote
besides diuerse other treatises, aswel in verse
as prose, tending all to the aduauncing of
vertue, and abolishing of vice, &amp; in such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises
he spent the most parte of his leasure.
He was of great fame &amp; renowme in many
<pb facs="8"/>
other Countryes beside Spaine, but alwayes
made more account of the estimation of a
fewe wisemen, rather then the praise of the
multitude, nd because that for the moste
parte wee see that the conditions of men are
answearable to their complexions and that
they are most times euill dysosed that are
euyll complexioned, wee neede not to
doubt but that this Gentleman was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in fauour with GOD, who gaue him
so good a teacher as hee was of ability to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
euery kinde of vertue, and to resist
without any greate paine, euery euill moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of sinne. I will not deny but that hee was
touched with such temptations, as our fraile
flesh doth many times assail the spirit withal,
and that he was sundry times ouertaken, as
well with anger as with the delight of
the flesh, and that he did sometimes offend
aswel in doing more then was mete, as in fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to do that which he ought to haue done,
For being as he was continually cōuersant in
the warres &amp; dayly employed in sundry ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
matters. It should haue beene a matter
of greate difficultie liuing among suche a
number of errours, to carry him selfe
<pb facs="8"/>
cleane without any errour. But if it be true,
that vertues doe make a mery hearte, as
on the other side vices breede heauinesse and
sorrowe, seeing that this gentleman was the
most parte of his time disposed to pleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
it is a greate deale more likely that
he was rather accompanyed with vertues
that bring forth pleasure, then subdued with
vices, that continually doe vexe men with
griefe. And notwithstanding that he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
many misfortunes in the warres, and
that hee sustained diuers griefes, as well for
the death of his Children, as of others
his neere kinsemen, yet he did alwayes beare
them with such a noble minde, as he serued
for an example to all others how to behaue
thēselues in the like cases. He ended his life
with great honour &amp; prosperitie, at the age of
lxv. yeers. And if it may be thought that mē
may after their departure haue any felicitie
in this world (as some suppose they may) we
may assuredly thinke that this gentlemā had
it: for he left behinde him vi. sonnes, wherof
the eldest increased his inheritance with the
estate of a dukedome: his second sonne was
Earle of <hi>Tendilla</hi> the thirde was Earle of
<hi>Curunna:</hi> the fourth was Cardinal of <hi>Spain,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
Archbishoppe of <hi>Toledo,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenca,</hi>
&amp; one of the greatest Prelates that
was in his time: To these foure and to the
two others, <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Don Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tado,</hi>
he left such Lordshippes,
rents, &amp; reuenewes, as made
fiue great houses, besides
his owne principall
house.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>