<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE
BISHOP OF
GALLOWAY
HIS APOLOGIE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108980_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5915</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108980</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE
BISHOP OF
GALLOWAY
HIS APOLOGIE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Bishop of Gallovvay his dikaiologie : contayning a iust defence of his former apologie. Against the iniust imputations of Mr. Dauid Hume</title>
                 <author>Cowper, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 183, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="apology">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE
BISHOP OF
GALLOWAY
HIS APOLOGIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two things requisite in a man, that would
doe good in a publike calling, the one is a good
Conscience, the other a good Name; the first
commends him to God, and obtaines a blessing
to his labours; the next commends him to men,
and procures him the greater credit to effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
the good which hee hath intended, for the
which (said <hi>Philo) Sicut bonum ac honestum esse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philo de mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratione Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>ita &amp; videri a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> haberi pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dest.</hi> As it is a good
thing to be good and honest, so is it also good
that we should be esteemed good, <hi>Nonitaque est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>gligenda fama restum ad cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stodian
tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> ad dignitatem vitae vtilissim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>:</hi> A good name therefore is not to be
neglected, considering it is a singular helpe both for the custodie and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of our life: for this cause hath it alway beene one of Sathans customable
policies, who stands at the right hand of <hi>Ieh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>shuah,</hi> to resist him in well doing,<note place="margin">Zach. 3.</note>
to staine the Name where he cannot corrupt the Conscience, that by disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing
the instruments, he may destroy, at least diminish the good which faine
they would doe: <hi>Hoc est Diaboli <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> seruos Dei mendacio laceret,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cyprian ad Anton.</note>
      <hi>&amp; falsis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> qui conscientiae su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> luce clarescunt falsis ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oribus
sordidentur:</hi> This is the worke of the Diuell, to strike the seruants of
God with the scourge of a lying tongue, to abase their honest name in the
hearts of others, by wrongfull conceptions, and by false reports to defile
them, who are honest in regard of their owne consciences.</p>
   <p>2 It is a difficult thing to liue in a publike calling, and not to be calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated.
So long as our Sauiour liued a priuate life, we reade not that he was
<pb facs="5"/>
either tempted by Satan, or traduced by men, but from the time that by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme
he was consecrate to doe the great worke of the promised <hi>Messiah,</hi> then
Satan set vpon him, and the mouthes of all his cursed instruments were
opened to blaspheme him. Now we know that the seruant is not aboue the
master:<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>n Prolog. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Iob.</note>
      <hi>Si aut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> aut palmarom folia complicarem, vt ins<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore
vultus mei panem comederem, &amp; ventris opus sollicita mente pertrectarem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus
morderet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> reprehenderet, nunc autem iuxta sententiam Saluatoris volo ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari
cibum qui non perit, &amp; geminus mihi error infigitur:</hi> If were set (said Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome)
to weaue a basket of twigs, with the bull-rush, or to twist the leaues of
I'alme-trees, or by any such base occupation, I had no more adoe, but to care
for my belly, that I might eate my bread in the sweat of my brow, I might
doe it all my dayes, and no man bite mee or reproue me for it, but now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause,
according to the saying of our Sauiour, I labour in a spirituall calling,
to nourish my selfe and others with that bread of life which perishes not, a
double error is enforced vpon me, <hi>Virum egregium sequitur proximorum inuidia,</hi>
Enuie alway followes vertue: where it can hurt no otherway, it impugnes by
calumnie:<note place="margin">Nazian.</note> this is, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls it, <hi>Malum grauissimum, generosam enim
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> um virorum constautiam labefactere nititur:</hi> A most heauie euill, for by it
Sathan seekes to weaken the constancie of good men, and so much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
euill is it,<note place="margin">Ambros.</note>
      <hi>Quia non solum falsa componit, sed etiam quae pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gesta sunt decolorat,</hi>
Because, faies <hi>Ambrose,</hi> it not onely forges false things, but falsifies true things,
deforming and defacing that with her vncouth colours, which is done sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely,
and out of a good affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ction.</p>
   <p>3 With the like of these weapons hath Sathan fought against mee in his
peeuish instruments, euer since the Lord called mee to be a Preacher, and no
maruaile, Shall a man trample on a Serpent, and not looke to be stinged?
I haue professed my selfe, by the grace of my Lord, a disquieter of Sathans
Kingdome, I thinke it not strange if hee doe what hee can to disquiet mee,
disquiet hee may, dishearten hee shall not. Shall I be mooued at his lying
Libellers?<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> No: <hi>Absit à seruo Christi tale inquinamentum, vt patientia maiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
praeparata, in minimis excid at:</hi> Farre be that spot from the seruants of
Christ, that their patience prepared for greater, should faile in so small ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> cito iniuria mouetur,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Amb. Off. lib. 1. to. 5.</note>
      <hi>facit se dignum videri contumelia,</hi> Hee that is
hastily moued with a contumely, makes it to seeme that hee is worthie of it.
What then, shall I vtterly neglect his false accusations? No, least by them
any credit I haue to doe good vnto others be stollen from mee. I will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
suffer an <hi>Absolom</hi> nor an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> A Friend nor a Foe, to steale away
from mee the hearts of any of Gods people, if I may stay it. To such there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
as feare God I speake,<note place="margin">August. ad Frat. in Erem.</note> as <hi>Augustine</hi> did to his brethren, <hi>Mihi sufficit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientia
mea, vobis necessaria est fama mea,</hi> To mee my conscience is sufficient,
but for you my good name is necessarie. Of such as are mine Enemies either
of weakenesse or wickednesse, I demaund as <hi>Iacob</hi> did of <hi>Laban.</hi> Now when
yee haue searched all my stuffe, what haue yee found? bring it forth, that
we may see it.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
4 O, forsooth, yee were once otherwayes minded concerning Church-gouernement.
In some things, I confesse, I was, in others not. Paritie in
Church-gouernment I euer thought the Mother of confusion, neither can, I
see that God hath beene the Author of it in any of his workes, yea by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie
of his gifts he declares that hee allowes not equalitie in gouernment,
where here, if any strife be about comparison of gifts, I haue no more to say,
but that hee who in humilitie of minde cannot submit himselfe to obay any
other, was neuer meete to bee a Ruler of others, how great so euer has
gifts be.</p>
   <q>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</q>
   <p>And that Preachers should haue place in Parliament, to giue light out of
the holy Oracle, to the Prince and States of the Kingdome, I euer thought
it both reasonable and necessarie, and did by my publike voice approue it in
that generall assembly holden at <hi>Dundie,</hi> wherein this matter was first mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.
And in these publike Lectures which once in the moneth wee had
in our Presbyteriall exercise, for clearing the Controuersies of this time: I
did in my course openly declare, how in Church-gouernment a happy meane
were to be wished betweene Anarchie and Monarchie, two fearefull euils
in the Church, the one proceeding from paritie, wrought confusion, as
might be seene in the pitifull state of the Churches of Flanders: the other
breeding tyrannie and all sort of oppression: a lamentable proofe whereof
we might see in the Churches of Italy, and other parts vnder the dominion
of that Romish Vsurper: thus is there not so great a cause to charge me with
a change, as is alleaged.</p>
   <p>5 But in that wherein before I misliked Episcopall gouernment, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
least tyrannie▪ libertie, and other euils should follow it, if now, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
a Christian King most carefull out of his rare pietie and wisedome, to
see it vsed vnto the right end, I haue changed my minde, as many others,
both worthie Fathers, and brethren in our Church haue done, to whom the
world cannot denie an honest testimonie: what imputation should this be
vnto me,<note place="margin">Ambros in Psal. 119.</note>
      <hi>Cum mentem in melius mutare non leuit as sit sed virtus,</hi> sith for a man
to change his minde to the better, it is no leuitie nor inconstancie, (as the
lying Libeller termes it) but vertue? Episcopall gouernment was embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
of this Church ere I was borne, and with it wee enioyed the Gospell
for many yeares, and some that were worthie and faithfull men in this
same Ministrie of <hi>Perth,</hi> wherein I haue now laboured by the grace of God
almost this twentie yeares, did discharge (in effect) the same office of a
Bishop in the bounds of <hi>Galloway,</hi> yea by imposition of their owne hands
did ordaine Bishops of other Dioces. If there were then a reason, why the
Episcopall gouernment once embraced, being fallen in decay, the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall
should be established, is it not now possible (thinke ye) to get a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
why both of them should be reunited, the one of them being ordained
<pb facs="6"/>
to honour and strengthen the other, and being reduced to that order and
vse, for which anciently it did serue in the Primitiue Church. Especially
seeing it is done by the fatherly fore-cast and prouident care, (not without
warrant of Gods word, example of the Primitiue Church, nor aduice of the
present Church) of such a King as God hath giuen vs, a Professor, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor,
a Semi-martyt, a Protector, a Preacher, a Propagator of the Gospell
with vs, whose power, for any thing I can yet learne, is greater in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
gouernment of the Church, then we haue well considered of.</p>
   <p>6 O but, say you, by this change, the people are made vncertaine of their
Religion? This cannot be but the bolt of some enemie, or the birth of the
braine of some friend ouer-farre miscaried with opinion. If it hath done euill
to any, it is an argument, their light is weake: for why? doth diuersiue of
externall gouernment import a difference in Religion? Are there not many
famous Churches in Europe, flourishing this day vnder the Episcopall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment?
haue not many Bishops themselues beene honoured with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of Martyrdome, and sealed the truth of the Gospell with their blood,
since the reformation of Religion: <hi>Latmer, Ridley, Cranmer,</hi> and many moe
in our neighbour Church may stand for examples. I will beseech all such
weake Christians to take none offence,<note place="margin">Aug. Confess. Art. 7.</note> where it is not giuen. <hi>Ad v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>itate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
fidei sufficit vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>adem sit doctrina Euangelij &amp; Sacramentorum administratio:</hi> It
is sufficient for the vnitie of faith, that the Doctrine of the Gospell and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
be one and the same: in other externall things, there may be diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie,
yea often times the diuersitie of times, and states of people will require
a diuersitie of externall things, for the furtherance of the worke of edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
   <p>7 The Apostles did all teach one, and the selfe-same Doctrine, but did
not all gouerne their Churches in one and the selfe-same manner: for <hi>Iames</hi>
and <hi>Peter</hi> among the Iewes tolerated Circumcision, which <hi>Paul</hi> among the
Gentiles would not doe; yea, the Disciples of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> testifie
how these blessed Apostles kept the Feast of the Pass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ouer on diuers dayes,
as both <hi>Eusebius</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> doe write: yet was this diuersitie no impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to the propagation of the Gospell by them both. It is euer to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered,
what the worke of edification requires. For that kinde of externall
gouernment which some Churches of Christ hath, and others hath not:
shall there be entertained a Schisme in our Church? and an vnnecessarie and
vnkindly contention, betweene a Christian people, and their most Christian
King. Since to speake in most modest termes, to giue contentment to such
as are not contentious, there is no question of Faith in the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
(Christian people might be ignorant of this disputation about Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
&amp; come to heauen neuerthelesse, if so it might please some of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors)
neither is there a question betweene good &amp; euill, but betweene good
and better; betweene two, whereof either of them haue had their course to
be, when the other was not; euen in this same Church, I doubt not, the iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Reader will consider this, &amp; Wisedome shall be iustified of her children.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
8 But here I know it is obiected by men, euen of moderate mindes, if
such gouernment were better vsed, and these who haue receiued it, did more
good with it, then it would soone purchase credit to it selfe, and be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
liked. These men I see haue nothing against the thing it selfe, but against
the vse of it, by which kinde of argument now commonly it is impugned.
To these it were sufficient to answere, that <hi>Artisicum errata, artibus attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
mon sunt,</hi> the errors of Artisans are not to be ascribed to the Arts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,
or to such as more wilfully reason in this manner, to answere, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>zen</hi>
did the Eunomians,<note place="margin">Nazian.</note>
      <hi>Cum in se <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ihil pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>ij habeant, in nostra illud
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> Where in themselues they haue no strength, they seeke
it in our imbecillitie: <hi>Et de malorum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> sciutilla flammam ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tant &amp; ad
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> affland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> tollunt, vt longè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Babilo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap> superet:</hi> Of a
little sparke of euill in vs, they kindle a great fire, by blowing vpon it with
their secret surmisings, and publike reproches, till they make the flame, which
they haue raised out of a sparke, to mount vp higher then the furnace of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel:
thus is it the manner of men to blame readily where they loue not.</p>
   <p>9 But to goe further with them, as with all reason I require, that the
faults of persons be not imputed to their Offices; so with my heart doe I
wish in all that are imployed with Ecclesiasticall authoritie, so moderate a
behauiour, that no offence should be giuen to the weake, nor cause of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction
to the contrary minded: but that as <hi>Iosephs</hi> preferment, tending
to the good of all his brethren, forced them, who enuied it at the first, to
thanke God for it at the last: euen so, credit may be conquest to vs in the
hearts of them that feare God, by feruent and faithfull aduancement of the
Gospell of Christ Iesus. We should neuer forget that warning which <hi>Ierome</hi>
gaue to a certaine Bishop; <hi>Rusticus Narbonensis, vide ne minor inueni ar is in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> in hoe seculo:</hi> Take heede that thou be not found lesse in
Christ, then thou art named in this world; thou art called a Bishop, so liue,
that Christ that great Archbishop may approue thee for one.</p>
   <p>10 But yet by some carnall and contentious spirits, who liue as if they
were Demi-gods, and in their tongues God had set his tribunall, or had
made them Iudges of the consciences of their brethren, it is obiected, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished,
and carried from hand to hand, in a Libell, as full of lies as lines,
that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> corrupt respects of gaine &amp; glory hath moued me to embrace it: a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
crimination, if I were as guiltie of it, as they are bold to affirme it. I
know it is a horrible sinne to abuse an holy calling to filthie luere: the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
said, that <hi>godl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nesse is great gaine,</hi> that is to say, that great gaine is godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;
<hi>Questum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tatem.</hi> It is a peruerse order:<note place="margin">Beza.</note>
      <hi>Terrena coelestibus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ercari,</hi> to buy earthly things with heauenly, where the spirituall Ministri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
teacheth vs to exchange earthly things for heauenly, such impietie as this
will be punished with a worse leprosie, then that of <hi>Gehazi.</hi> And no losse
abhominable is it, to abuse it to vaine-glory and affectation of honour: it is
a grosser idolattie then that of the Israelites, who of the gold and siluer
which they reserued from the Lord,<note place="margin">Hosea, 2. 8.</note> made a <hi>Baal</hi> to themselues.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
11 To such I will answere, as <hi>Augustine</hi> did to <hi>Petilian,</hi> I am a man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining
to the floore of Christ, if I be good,<note place="margin">August.</note> I am there as corne, if I be
euill, I am there as chaffe, <hi>Sed non est huius areae ventilabrum lingua Petitiani,</hi>
But your Petulant tongue, like the tongue of <hi>Petilian,</hi> is not the fanne of
this floore. If any man thinke hee knowes me better then I doe my selfe, let
him giue iudgement as he pleaseth, and others beleeue him as they list: if they
will credit me of my selfe, my witnesse is in heauen, and my conscience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
me beareth me record, that I was not moued with gaine or glorie, and I
trust to declare it by Gods grace.<note place="margin">Amb. Off.</note> But what? <hi>Bene sibi conscius non debet falsis
moueri, nec putare plus esse Ponderis in alieno co<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>itio, quam in suo testimonis:</hi> Hee
that hath in himselfe a good conscience, should not be moued with false con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions
in others, nor esteeme that there is greater waight in other mens
traducing, then in his owne testimonie.</p>
   <p>12 Now here I know it is expected, that as I haue declined the causes
falsly imputed to me, so I should declare the true causes that moued me, which
now shortly are these.</p>
   <p>13 First, I perceiued a Christian King, by all meanes possible, seeking
the aduancement of the Gospell, for the which it is griefe enough that his
Maiestie sustaineth the greatest hatred and contradiction of the aduersaries,
but more then enough, his Highnesse should want the comfort of his subiects,
professors also: which when I considered, I thought it a matter of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to refuse to serue and follow his Maiestie in so good a course.</p>
   <p>14 Secondly, I saw the weake hearts of many well affected Christians,
through misconception, offended at the very name of a Bishop, not able out
of light and knowledge to giue any reason of their misliking, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
though it be so highly honoured by the Apostle, and commended by
the famous lights of the Primitiue Church, who not onely accepted the
name, but exercised the office thereof, to the great good of the Church: and
that this offence might be remoued, at least so farre as my credit may carrie
me, I haue embraced it.</p>
   <p>15 Thirdly, I perceiued a perillous Schisme, and vnnecessarie diuision in
our Church, for this matter of gouernment, to the great aduantage of the
common Aduersarie, which gap I resolued, for my owne part, not to enlarge
by contention, but so farre as my weaknesse may to close it vp, at least to
make it the lesse.</p>
   <p>16 Fourthly, I considered, that the same reason, that of old forced the
Fathers of the Primitiue Church, in the iudgement of <hi>Ierome,</hi> to induce this
gouernment in the Church, that is, in <hi>Remedium Schismatis,</hi> did more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly
require that it should be restored vnto vs: but of this the lesse I
speake for duties sake, the more I leaue to be considered of them, who know
the truth hereof.</p>
   <p>17 Fiftly, the question among vs when I searched as narrowly as I
could, is about Ierusalems wall, whether it should be circular or quadrangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
round or foure-squared: so the Citie be well, is this a matter for which we
<pb facs="7"/>
should make contention, it being better for the good of the Church, that any
one of them should be, then that thus they should striue together, to the
great hinderance of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>18 Sixtly, and I doe verily thinke that the most famous and reformed
Churches in Europe, who want this gouernment, would be glad to accept it,
vpon this condition, that with it they might enioy the puritie of the Gospel,
which they haue with vs, together with that libertie, fauour and protection
of a Christian reformed King, which we haue, and they want.</p>
   <p>19 For these reasons, as I was determined before, in the priuate calling
of a Preacher, to reuerence and obey others my brethren, clad with the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
of Bishops, the proofe whereof I gaue in these Prouinciall assemblies, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated
by Bishops, whereat I was bound to be present, so haue I at length
embraced it in my owne person, being called there-vnto by the most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
King, and Church of this Kingdome, without any motion, affection,
or petition of mine owne (if there be so much charitie in my aduersaries as
to beleeue me) I could with greater contentment and willingnesse of minde,
haue giuen obedience in all dutifull submission to any of my brethren, nor to
haue had any more publike charge in the Church (if the matter had beene in
my choice.) And this doe I witnesse out of the very truth and simplicitie
of mine heart.</p>
   <p>20 If <hi>Shimei</hi> still will raile, and charge mee with a corrupt affection, let
him be doing till his owne iniquitie reproue him, I am sure no well aduised
Christian will fight with any such armour, for the weapons of our warfare
are not carnall, but spirituall. As for others, who like barking Dogges and
Birds of the night, chatter to themselues in secret confused sounds, which
can bide no triall, back-biting those whom they dare not looke in the face,
for such as these, why shall a man turne out of the way? It is a sufficient pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
to such as this way with their will would hurt mee, that against
their will they shall helpe me,<note place="margin">Aug. cont. liter. Petil. lib. 3. c. 7.</note>
      <hi>Qui volens detrahit same mee, nolens additmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>
meae,</hi> For he that with his will empaites my name, against his will, shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
my reward.</p>
   <p>21 But if such busie idle-bodies will come and labour with mee in the
worke of God, I hope to teach them to bestow their time more profitably,
not to disquiet, as they do, their vnsetled braines with such vanities, as vanish
so soone as they are conceiued, and brought forth, leauing nothing behinde
them but a guiltinesse to themselues, for mine owne part I haue determined
not to be contentious, for that is not the custome of the Church of Christ,
but haue resolued to spend my time and talent I haue saued to the vantage of
my Master, and good of my Brethren, after my weake measure, <hi>Aur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us vtlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teas
minuat sic malleus vrnas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>22 As for others my Brethren, whom I loue in the Lord, and will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
reuerence for the graces of God in them, I wish from my heart that
precept of the Apostle were fulfilled in vs.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.</note> That wee did all speake one
thing, and there were no dissension among vs, but that we were knit together
<pb facs="8"/>
in one minde, and one iudgement, for since the first beginning of this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion,
I euer thought it a lamentable thing, that they whose hearts are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in one resolution to die for Christ, if so the Lord should call them vnto
it, cannot liue together in the vnitie of one minde. But this hath in all ages
beene Sathans policie, where hee cannot disturbe the peace of the Church
with externall euasion, he creepes in like a subtile Serpent, to disquiet it with
internall perturbation, &amp; that oft-times vpon vnnecessarie or small occasions:
where-vpon hath proceeded this great rupture in Ierusalems wall heere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
vs, which as it is seene of vs all, and more then enough talked of by
many, so would to God, our hearts did pitie it, and all of vs endeuoured by
humbled hearts toward our God, by meekenesse of minde, euery one of vs
toward another, to repaire and close it vp againe. And seeing such in the
condition of our humane infirmitie, that our knowledge in this life is but in
part, and so our iudgements in all things cannot be vniforme, let vs take heed
to the next, that difference of iudgements worke not distraction of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
remembring that the wisedome which is from aboue, is peaceable, and
that the zeale of God fights not with the weapons of flesh, such as hatred,
debate,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> emulations, wrath, contentions. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> we liue in the Spirit, let vs also walke
in the Spirit,</hi> expressing the fruits of it in our liues, which are, loue, ioy, peace,
long suffering, meekenesse, goodnesse, wherewith the Lord more and more
endue vs all for Christs sake, AMEN.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord,
<hi>WILLIAM COOPER,</hi>
B. of Galloway.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>