<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108553_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05535</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15657</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108553</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true narration of all the passages of the proceedings in the generall Assembly of the Church of Scotland, holden at Perth the 25. of August, anno Dom. 1618 : VVherein is set downe the copy of his Maiesties letters to the said Assembly: together with a iust defence of th Articles therein concluded, against a seditious pamphlet. By Dr. Lyndesay, Bishop of Brechen</title>
                 <author>Lindsay, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Rounthwait, Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 136, 152, 125, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast here, gentle and courteous Reader, a true and simple narration of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the last generall Assembly kept at Perth, opposed to the false and lying Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course made by the Libeller against the same; with an answer to his Nullities; the Oath, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments propounded against the fiue Articles there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. These paines are chiefly taken for thy informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that thou mayest know the truth and vnderstand both the matter, and manner of proceeding in the said As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly. Since that time, I heare they haue put the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet in Latine, and set forth other Libels full of impious and reproachfull lies against the principall men of our Church. These I haue not seene, and if I had, I would not haue deigned them any answer. For, when leauing the matter, they fall a rayling at the persons of men, that are their betters in all respects, they shew the weaknesse of their cause, &amp; deserue nothing of wisemen, but contempt. This manner of doing is better replyed with the Pillorie, then otherwise. Wee know the eares of many are open to admit detractions, and he liues not, that is not hated by some, who will readily beleeue the most false things: yet, Wickednesse hath not so generally preuailed in the world, nor are we so vnknowne in it, as wee neede any of vs to feare their defamations. If thou, notwithstanding, doest think that such Libels require an answer, I aske thee, How
<pb facs="15"/>
shall it be done? I know no way my selfe, but eyther to vse Apologies or recriminations. And this last were not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficile to doe: for though the Writer goeth namelesse, the Faction to whose pleasure he writes is knowne, and they that sport themselues with such libels, sending them from hand to hand, as matters of some worth. Their persons we could easily pay home, and repone true things vnto them in stead of forged, telling them no other matters, then haue beene tried, confessed, and publiquely acknowledged by those that are hottest in this businesse, of themselues: but these are the weapons of the vulgar, which we disdain to vse, <hi>&amp; vltio haec, Christiano homini maxime indeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> As for Apologies, the Wise man saith, That they leaue suspitions in the Readers mind, <hi>&amp; plures Sermones pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocant, &amp; plurium:</hi> The best Apologie against calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, is, <hi>conuitiatores factis refellere. Luther, Caluine, Beza,</hi> the great lights of the reformed Church, and our owne <hi>Knox,</hi> had many foule aspersions cast vpon them whilest they liued; yet did they not faint in their course, nor do they now heare the worse for them, with posteritie. Fame is not at mans disposing: and if any amongst men haue power of it, <hi>in nostra manu est,</hi> as one speakes, <hi>bene vel secus audire.</hi> We therefore resting in the goodnesse of our cause and conscience, will keepe silence, and not vnderstand such things, passing little with the Apostle to be iudged of them, or of the day of man. He that iudges is the Lord, who will lighten things that are hidden in darkenesse, and make the counsells of the hearts mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest: And then shall euerie man haue praise of God. To his grace I commend thee for now and euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>