<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE TO
Prayer, by way of
Dialogue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108001_Bo3_21_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18910</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5332</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108001</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE TO
Prayer, by way of
Dialogue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe of the Bible : drawne first into English poësy, and then illustrated by apte annotations: togither vvith some other necessary appendices. By Henoch Clapham</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>237, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_on_prayer">
   <pb facs="96"/>
   <head>A PREFACE TO
Prayer, by way of
Dialogue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>Qu.</hi>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aue you penned the
subsequent <hi>Forme</hi> of
praier, to the end that
any other shuld think
they had well prayed,
in having read or said the same over?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ans.</hi> No: Saying over wordes is no
more <hi>Praying,</hi> than reading over wordes
is <hi>Preaching.</hi> As the <hi>Guift</hi> of Preaching is
an immediate vtterance of the Lord his
will conceived in the heart by the spirite
of Iesus: so is the <hi>Guift</hi> of Prayer an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat
vtterance (<hi>Vocall</hi> or <hi>Mentall</hi>) of
things presently conceived in the heart,
by the Spirit of Iesus. For this cause doth
<hi>Paul</hi> tell the <hi>Galatians</hi> 4. 6. that whome
God adopteth in Christ, to them he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
the sprit of Christ: even to this end,
that he may stirre vp the <hi>Heart</hi> of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted
to crye, <hi>Abba,</hi> Father: that is, <hi>To
call vehemently vpon God, as vpon a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Father, not a Tyrant or Iudge.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
none can truly pray, that haue not
this Spirite, as also, because no Requests
<pb n="190" facs="97"/>
(<hi>Vocall</hi> or <hi>Mentall</hi>) is true Prayer, that is
not conceived and suggested by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of God, therefore <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8. 26.
plainly (putting himselfe in the number)
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aith, <hi>Wee knovve not hovve to Pray as vve
ought, but the Spirite it selfe maketh request
for vs:</hi> that is, <hi>The Spirit of Iesvvs putteth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the mouth of our spirite vvhat to praye.</hi>
To prescribe therefore and enjoyne <hi>Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvordes,</hi>
is to strip the Spirit of his office,
and the way to quench our Spirit.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Obiect.</hi> Every one hath not knovvledge
to pray, therfore set formes do help such.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ans.</hi> True: and so doe the written set
Scriptures help such: but yet it followeth
not, that that is praier it selfe: The helpe
to Praier &amp; Preaching, is not our Prayer
and preaching it selfe: the first is a <hi>Cause,</hi>
the second the <hi>Effect:</hi> no Cause and his
Effect are the same: every halfe-pennie
Sophister knowes that. Secondly, where
you say, <hi>Euery one hath not knowledge to
pray,</hi> thereto I answer: every one that is
adopted (as afore) hath the spirit of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus:
every one that hath that spirit, hath a
speaking (not a dumbe) spirite, a spirite of
knowledge and holy Light.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Obiect.</hi> But every one (who is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
to haue Gods spirite) cannot vtter
words orderly as were to be wished.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="191" facs="97"/>
      <hi>Ans.</hi> That is besides the Question: the
Question is this: <hi>Can every one of God his
children</hi> (meaning of aged Persons) <hi>pray
rightly?</hi> I haue saide, they can. Nowe, for
praying so orderly as were to be wished,
I graunt, that young ones in Christ Iesus
cannot pray so fully and methodically, as
these that haue spent som years in Christ
his Schoole. Children cannot speake as
do Elder persons: yet Children (aswell as
Elder persons) can cry vnto the Parents
vpon the feling of some <hi>Want:</hi> even so can
the youngest Babe in Christ. That, the
blessed Apostle teacheth, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15.)
when he saith, that the <hi>Adopted do cry:</hi> as
also (<hi>Verse,</hi> 26. 27.) when hee affirmeth,
that the Spirit teacheth vs to pray <hi>vvith
grones vnvtterable,</hi> the meaning of which
grones is well knowne to God: for hee is
not ignorant of the meaning of his own
spirit. And most grosse headed are such,
as think that any words please God, but
what hee himselfe first breathes into our
hearts by his spirit: for he only accepteth
the fruites of his owne spirit, the fruits of
his Sonnes spirit: which first fruites are
the sanctifier of our whole lumpe. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
to think is flat Idolatrie, and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orie
to the spirite of our onely Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer
IESVS.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="192" facs="98"/>
      <hi>Quest.</hi> Do you then simply condemne
all such as vse the wordes of our Saviour,
as they are set downe?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ans.</hi> No: S. <hi>Peter</hi> (1. 4. 11.) saith, <hi>If
any man speake, let him speake as the vvords
of God.</hi> Better wordes than our Saviour,
than the Apostles, than the Prophetes
haue vsed, we cannot vse: nay, wee must
learne to speake as they before vs haue
spoken, as in other speach, so specially in
<hi>Prayer,</hi> which is, <hi>An holy speach vvith
God.</hi> Whosoever shal vse all or any of our
Saviors words according to knowledge,
and that by the instinct of God his spirit,
which Spirit teacheth the soule, what is
most fit &amp; necessary for the time, to him I
say, <hi>Go in peace.</hi> But if any for customes
sake, and of a foolish superstitious affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to the words, shall vse them, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
forme of speach in the Scriptures, of
such I say, <hi>They are no better than Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
Magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>al inchautaters,</hi> neither knowe
they what prayer meaneth. Two sorts of
People offende against our Saviour his
forme of Prayer: the one sort are such, as
through a Romish custome do value all
their other prayers deade and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
if so they do not annex it: the other
sort are such, as think it vtterly vnlawfull
(because the same is repeated) for to vse
<pb n="193" facs="98"/>
them wordes for Prayer. If our Saviour
(<hi>Marke</hi> 14. 39.) did at his second time of
praying, vse the <hi>same vvords he had before
vsed,</hi> then why should the same in any
Faithfull their vse, be offensiue to vs? But
as our Savior there vsing the same words
did it, because his case was one and the
same vnchanged, so let vs learne then, to
vse the same words, when our case is the
same: otherwise, we shal make holy <hi>Words,</hi>
but prophane <hi>Idoles.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Concluding therefore, that <hi>Prayer is
a povvring out of our soules-feeling accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the present motion of God his spirite:</hi>
as also, that <hi>Neither olde vvords nor newe
vvordes are acceptable to God, otherwise
then they are sent vp to God the Father, in
the name of Iesus, and that by the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
vvorke of the spirite:</hi> I now come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
our Saviour his <hi>Exemplar of Prayer,</hi>
(<hi>Math.</hi> 6.) consisting 1. of a <hi>Preface,</hi> in
these wordes: <hi>O our Father vvhich art in
Heuen.</hi> 2. of a <hi>Supplicatiō</hi> in these words:
<hi>Hallovved be thy name, thy Kingdom come,
thy vvil be done in Earth as it is in Heauen:
Giue vs this day our daily bread, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue
vs our debts, as vvee also forgiue our
detters: And lead vs not into tentation, but
deliuer vs from euill.</hi> 3. It consisteth of a
<hi>Reason,</hi> why Prayer is offered vp onely to
<pb n="694" facs="99"/>
God, in these words: <hi>For thine is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
and the povver, &amp; the glory, for euer.</hi>
4. Of <hi>Faiths Signet</hi> or <hi>Seale</hi> in this word,
<hi>Amen,</hi> or <hi>So it is.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>