<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108580_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05590</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15709</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108580</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gushing teares of godly sorrovv : Containing, the causes, conditions, and remedies of sinne, depending mainly upon contrition and confession. And they seconded, with sacred and comfortable passages, under the mourning cannopie of teares, and repentance. By William Lithgovv</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Bryson, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lithgow, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Prologue to the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou mayst peruse this worke, with kynde respect,</l>
      <l>Cause; none my good intention can controule;</l>
      <l>The style may (not the subject) beare defect,</l>
      <l>Some <hi>Painter</hi> will the fayrest face drawe foule:</l>
      <l>Excuse myne age, if faultie, blame my quill,</l>
      <l>Defects may fall, and not fayle in goodwill.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>My Muse declynes, downe styde her loftie straynes</l>
      <l>And hoarie growes, succumbing to the dust;</l>
      <l>Old wrung inventions, from industrious paynes</l>
      <l>Draw to the grave, where death must feede his lust:</l>
      <l>Flesh flye in ashes, bones returne to clay,</l>
      <l>Whence I begunne, there must my substance stay.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Goe thou laborious pen, and challenge tyme,</l>
      <l>For memorie, to all succeeding ages;</l>
      <l>In thy past workes, and high heroicke ryme,</l>
      <l>And pregnant prose, in thryce three thousand pages:</l>
      <l>Yet dye thou must, and Tyme shall weare thee out,</l>
      <l>Ere seaven tymes seaven, worne ages goe about.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But Vertue claymes her place, and prostrate I</l>
      <l>Must yeelde due honour, to her noble name:</l>
      <l>Shee taught mee to take paynes, its done, and why?</l>
      <l>To make her famous, in her flying fame:</l>
      <l>A Sculler, may transport, a royall Queene,</l>
      <l>As well as Oares, and both their safeties seene.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Trust mee, my paynes, contend, for to bee playne</l>
      <l>No style Poeticke, may this subject clayme:</l>
      <l>Touch but <hi>Vermilion,</hi> you shall see a stayne,</l>
      <l>No fiction, may averre, a sacred Theame:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
Nor dare <hi>Panthoas, Cynthias</hi> herball flowre</l>
      <l>Be seene, nor spread, till rolling <hi>Phoebus</hi> lowre.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then read, misconster not, but wisely looke</l>
      <l>If I divinely, keep a divine stile:</l>
      <l>Which done, thou mayst, take pleasure in this booke,</l>
      <l>An Infant, from devotion, bred the while:</l>
      <l>Like treatise I, before neere wrote; excuse</l>
      <l>This new borne birth, from mine old aged Muse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>See! here in generals, thou mayst observe</l>
      <l>The cause of sinne, sinnes remedy, salt teares;</l>
      <l>Where sharpe particulars, for repentance serve</l>
      <l>To blazon wickednesse, and wicked feares:</l>
      <l>What here is done, to thee, to me, to all,</l>
      <l>May be apply'd, as each one findes his fall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet who can stop, base Critick tongues to carpe,</l>
      <l>For Atheists shall, and Epicures repine;</l>
      <l>So scoffing fooles, on strings of scorne will harpe</l>
      <l>To see this myte, a part of mine engyne:</l>
      <l>But silly Gnats, worse bred then <hi>Berdoan</hi> beasts,</l>
      <l>I slight their spight, my Muse in <hi>Sion</hi> feasts.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Would thou contend with me, who best should write</l>
      <l>On choice of Theames, select<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d between its twaine,</l>
      <l>I could abide thy censure, take delite</l>
      <l>In thy defects, to censure thee againe:</l>
      <l>Since thou sits dumbe, and cannot bite, but barke,</l>
      <l>Peace, hold thy peace, else show me thine owne wark.</l>
      <l>But zealous eyes may come, come, and come soone,</l>
      <l>To read this Task, if pleasd, Lo! I have done.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <salute>To the godly and good Christian,</salute>
      <signed>a fellow suppliant in Christ, WILLIAM LITHGOVV.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>