<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The right Honorable George Earle of Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet At∣ton, Vescie and Vypont, Lord of Westmerland, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter,</title>
           <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108342_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21655</idno>
           <idno type="STC">796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The right Honorable George Earle of Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet At∣ton, Vescie and Vypont, Lord of Westmerland, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter,</title>
                 <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exhortation of Salomon. By H.A</title>
                 <author>H. A. (Henry Arthington)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO The right Honorable George Earle of Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Vescie and Vypont, Lord of Westmerland, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter,</head>
   <head type="sub">Together with the right vertuous Countesse his Ladie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of all blessings and graces needfull.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S vngratefulnesse for bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites receiued, is a sinne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested of God and man, (right honorable and my singular good Lord &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die) so standeth me vppor more than anie other, euer to auoide that suspition, &amp; to shew my thankfulnesse both to God and his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants aboue all others, forasmuch as I (being the greatest sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) haue notwithstanding found greater fauour extended vnto me from the Almightie, my soueraigne Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> her most honorable Councell, and all christian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="3"/>
in remitting of my late monstrous offence committed in Cheape, and receiuing me againe to grace and fauour, more than euer was shewed vnto anie such like sinner since the world began. The remembrance of which most horrible fact, by me comwitted, as it maketh my heart and soule to tremble when I thinke seriously thereof, so my deliuerance causeth me oftentimes to breake out in thankfulnesse vnto his goodnesse, by whose onely power, prouidence and compassion, I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed from so grosse errours, renued and restored to the vse of my senses, repriued from death and endlesse destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reconciled againe into their former fauour, that ioye in the conuersion of such a sinner, as hath bene subtilly sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by sathan: so am I bound to intreate the Lords fauor, to recompence that vndeserued kindnesse a thousaud folde into their bosomes, which I haue had from her excellent maiestie, and all their Honours of her Highnes Councell, with all the rest of Gods chosen children: which duetie by Gods grace I shall dayly performe so long as I liue, and more particularly for all those to whome I am anie way more specially beholden: Then my honorable good Lord and Ladie, seeing next her most excellent Maiestie and honorable Councell in sparing my life, I am most bounden vnto your Hh for the continuall maintenance thereof: her Ladyspip mouing, and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship consenting to renue my Grant from your right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Father: yea, more than so, whereas I was both vnfit and vnable to discharge that office, wherewith I was charged by my Patent, your L. hath disburdned me of the same to attend better matters, and for those grounds which I had in posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, to allow mee one hundreth markes <hi>per annum</hi> during my lyfe, which fauor I acknowledge with all submission and vnfained thankfulnes, and as a further testimony thereof, do
<pb facs="3"/>
humbly present this Treatise folowing vnto your Hh. as most fit, for two causes: The one in regard of the Argument ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which first did spring from most honorable authors: the other in respect of my poore self (who having taken some pains therein, to open the fountaine, that more plentie of wholsome water might flow from thence, to the comfort of others) your Hh. would bee disposed to take the patronage of this second fruit of my true repentance, intreating of the Exhortation of <hi>Salomon.</hi> As my former Seduction was both accepted &amp; allowed of their Hh. whom I had most dishonored in my fall, when I was possest with the spirit of Satan, by that vile Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer <hi>Hacket</hi> and his inchantmentes. To conclude, if your Hh. will vouchsafe to peruse the same, and so farre only to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue thereof, as you shall find it to abide the triall of the true touchstone, the word of God, I shall thinke my paines suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently requited, and be more bounden to pray for your Hh. and all yours, whome the Almightie protect, preserue and prosper with much increase of honor and comfort, both in this world, and in the world to come, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Hh. obidient at commandement, <hi>Henrie Arthington.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>