<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Rablet, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108104_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19035</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108104</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Rablet, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cobbes prophecies : his signes and tokens, his madrigalls, questions, and answeres, with his spirituall lesson, in verse, rime, and prose. Pleasant, and not vnprofitable. Reade that will, iudge that can, like that list</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wilson, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was vpon a time an odde Country Riming Fellow, whose name was <hi>Cobbe:</hi> where hee dwelt, I finde not; and what hee was, it skils not: Onely this I note of him, that it seemes by the Memoriall I haue of him, that he was in his time, as (no doubt are many now adaies) giuen to looke so farre aboue the Moone, that as falling through the Clouds, when he wak't, he knew not where he was: but strange thinges he had in his head, which he set downe as oddely in writing: where if you looke for verse, you are out; if for Rime, you are in: now, if you take delight in old idle Prophecies, strange Signes and Tokens, though they neuer come to passe, and to reade now and than of many a strange Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drigall heere you may haue change to fit your choise; how they will fall fit with your humour I know not, and therefore this is all I will say to you. I know
<pb facs="3"/>the Book Seller will say. <hi>What lack you,</hi> and I say, I wish all may like you; so, till I see you, though I know you not when I meete you, to the Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I leaue you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your well willer as to all honest Men. <hi>Richard Rablet.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>