<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. WILLIAM WALCOT marchant, one of the most vvorthie cōpanie of Marchant Adventurers residing at Hamborough.</title>
           <author>Loe, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108789_Fr7_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16690</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. WILLIAM WALCOT marchant, one of the most vvorthie cōpanie of Marchant Adventurers residing at Hamborough.</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Songs of Sion : Set for the ioy of gods deere ones, vvho sitt here by the brookes of this vvorlds Babel, &amp; vveepe vvhen they thinke on Hierusalem vvhich is on highe. By W.L</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Hamburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 164, 100 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="73"/>
   <pb n="147" facs="73"/>
   <head>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. WILLIAM WALCOT marchant, one of the most vvorthie cōpanie of Marchant Adventurers residing at Hamborough.</head>
   <p>Happines for euer.</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ind frend. Forced fauours vvere euer sleighted, &amp; thankles. But voluntary respects had euer vvith the best, and most noble minds courteous acceptāce hovve small, &amp; meane soeuer the thing vvas. For a mā to giue his soule to his Creator vvhen he sees he must dye, &amp; his goods to the poore,
<pb n="148" facs="74"/>
vvhen he sees he must part vvith them, &amp; to forgoe our sinne, vv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> vve can noe longer follovve yt are cold, yea vnkind obediences. But for a young man to remember his creator in the daies of his yout <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> &amp; in his best, &amp; strongest age <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> bequeath himself euery day to god in prayer, &amp; praise is that<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable, &amp; seasonable sacrifice vvhere vvith the most high is most pleased. To this purpose and noe other god knovveth I haue tendered these voluntary Essaies to diuerse of my masters, &amp; Table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brothers. Let me not seeme to to officious, vvhile I desire to doe good, &amp; expresse my loue. For <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vnto the rest so vnto you Beloued Gā-naunt haue I sent this parcell. Receaue yt, as I meane yt both vvith hand, &amp; hart, &amp; then <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="149" facs="74"/>
am assured; it vvill neuer repent you of your acceptation, nor me of my dedication. The great lord keeper of heauen, &amp; earth keepe you in his feare all the daies of your life, &amp; preserue you for his sauing mercies in Christ Iesus in the end of your life, &amp; for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christ to be required.
W. LOE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>