<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The printer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108255_Bo1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05076</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15217.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108255</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The printer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epitome of cronicles : Conteyninge the whole discourse of the histories as well of this realme of England as al other cou [n] treys, with the succesion of their kinges, the time of their reigne, and what notable actes they did ... gathered out of most probable auctours. Firste by Thomas Lanquet, from the beginning of the worlde to the incarnacion of Christe, secondely to the reigne of our soueraigne lord king Edward the sixt by Thomas Cooper, and thirdly to the reigne of our soueraigne Ladye Quene Elizabeth, by Robert Crowley. Anno. 1559</title>
                 <author>Lanquet, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 280, 30 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <head>¶The printer.</head>
   <p>¶Hitherto the said yong man Thomas Lanquet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued this history called the Epitome of Cronicles, &amp; was than attached with a greuous sicknesse, whereof he dyed▪ whan he was of age .xxiiii. yeres: on whose soule god haue mercy, and the same folowed and finished, by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Couper, who after instāt request to him made, was at length content, to take vpon him the peine, for he well
<pb facs="119"/>
considered, what labour and trauaill it was, accordinge to the first inuencion, to searche and reade ouer so many and diuers histories and cronicles, to accomplishe the saide purpose.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>