<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The preface of Thomas Lanquet to the second parte of the histories of England.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108255_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05076</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15217.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108255</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The preface of Thomas Lanquet to the second parte of the histories of England.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epitome of cronicles : Conteyninge the whole discourse of the histories as well of this realme of England as al other cou [n] treys, with the succesion of their kinges, the time of their reigne, and what notable actes they did ... gathered out of most probable auctours. Firste by Thomas Lanquet, from the beginning of the worlde to the incarnacion of Christe, secondely to the reigne of our soueraigne lord king Edward the sixt by Thomas Cooper, and thirdly to the reigne of our soueraigne Ladye Quene Elizabeth, by Robert Crowley. Anno. 1559</title>
                 <author>Lanquet, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 280, 30 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <head>¶The preface of Thomas Lanquet to the second parte of the histories of England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue hitherto briefli ronne ouer the liues of .72. kinges, which reigned here in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from the arriuall of Brute vnto the comming of Cesar: the history wherof (as I said before) is very vncertaine &amp; obscure. Yet neuerthelesse I haue not varyed from the vulgar opinion therof, but haue brought the same in to a more certaine ordre, conferring them with the other
<pb facs="112"/>
histories and gestes of the world, wherby they haue a bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter apparance of truth. But now, that I am come to this time, in which the Britons beganne to be knowen to the Romaines, and other nacions of the world, hauing also the helpe of credible historiens, whiche before I lacked, I shall the more veritably and in better order set foorthe our histories. And for the better declaracion of this chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, you shall vnderstande, that the numbres set in the inner side of the page, signifie the yeres of the reignes of the kīges of Britain, wherby may be perceiued in what yere of the reigne of a kinge, anye notable thinge in the world was done. As for the historye of Cesar I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered it out of his cōmentaries, and out of the worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Beda whome I thinke more credible than our newe historiens.</p>
   <p>VUhen C. Iullus Cesar had warred seuen yeres in Fraunce and Germany,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>52</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>7</label> comming vnto that part where Calais and Bolayne now stande,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3911</label> he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to make warre into Britaine: whyche vntill that time remayned vnfrequented and vnknowen of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines. His quarell was, because that in the warres of France, he perceyued the Frenchmen to haue much suc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cour and ayde from thense. Wherfore preparinge .lxxx. shippes he sayled into Britain. Where at the first being weried with an harde and sharpe batayle, and after with sodein tempest his nauy almoste destroyed, he retourned again into Fraunce, there to winter his men. The nexte springe,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3912</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>51</label> his nauy beinge newe rigged and encreased,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>8</label> he passed the seas agayne with a greater army: but whiles he went towarde his ennemies on lande, his shippes ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at ankor, were againe by tempest almost lost, for ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thei were driuen on the sides, where thei stack fast or els beyng driuen one vpon an other were destroyed so that .xl. perisshed, the other with muche labour were sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Upon lande also his horsemen ot the first encounter were vanquished, and Labienus the tribune slayne. At the seconde conflicte, not withoute great daunger of his men, he put the britons to flight, and poursued theym to the riuer Thamis: on the further side wherof Cassiuelā with a great multitude of people was kepinge the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<pb n="84" facs="112"/>
but they not hable to resiste the violence and force of the Romains, hid them selues in woodes, &amp; with sodeine eruptions oftentimes inuaded them. But in the meane time theyr strongest citee Troynouāt▪ submitted it self to Cesar, deliuering vnto him hostages: whiche exāple also the other cities folowed. Whereby Cassiuelan after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny losses, was constreigned to giue pledges, and to agre that Britaine should be tributary to the people of Rome Then Cesar, like a conquerour with great noumbre of prisoners, sayled into Fraunce. Thus ended the warres which he made in Britain, whereby he rather opened o waye for his successours to come to the same, thā that he deliuered to them the dominion thereof. This conqueste was made .2255. yeres after the vniuersall floude .1057. after the arriuall of Brute .702. after the buyldinge of Rome, in the second yere of the .182. Olimpiade, the .1116. yere before the conquest made by Willā of Normandy. and .1595. yeres before this present yere of our lord .1547</p>
   <p>Cassius president of Siria, droue the Parthians from thense.</p>
   <p>Cleopatra, quene of Egipte, reigned .xxii. yeres.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>49</label> She was the laste of the house of Lagus,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>12</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3914</label> and by the Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drines was chosen quene, albeit she had a younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom Pompeius receiued into his tuicion, and by him was driuen out of hir royalme: yet Cesar restored hir againe to hir realme, and vsed her company family<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly and after Cesars death. Antonius wedded her, who warred against Augustus: of whom he was ouerthrowē for sorowe wherof, she closed her selfe in a tombe being on liue, and hauing two adders suckinge on her brestes, so died. She was a woman excellinge in plesauntnes quickenes of witte, and sumptuous ryotte, in so muche that at one (banket contending with Antonius in excesse of fare,) she drank aperle resolued in vineger, which was estemed at .100. Sestertium, which after Budei amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the value of 250000. crounes, of our money to fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand poundes.</p>
   <p>The ciuile warres betwene Pompeius and Cesar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, in which .ccc.M. men perished. Cesar in his his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence required the second time to be consul. Marcellus
<pb facs="113"/>
the consul withstode it, and the senate also decreed, that Cesar should not entre the city, without he dimissed his armye. For whiche cause Cesar being displeased, came frō Rauenia, passing ouer Rubicon, to Ariminium. In the meane while Pompeius, with the consulles, fled to Dyrra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hiū in Grece, and Cesar entred Rome, spoiled the tresoury, and besieged Marsiles.</p>
   <p>Aristobulus, being deliuered by Cesar, went into Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, where he was poysoned, and Alexander his son put to death by Scipio.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>1916</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>47</label> Cesar in Corfinio,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Before Britayne knovven </seg>12</label> by submission receyued the armye of Domitius, and suffered him to go frelye awaye. In Spaine he vanquished Petreius &amp; Afranius he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Marsiles, and tooke the towne. From thence he went to Dyrrachium, where he was ouercome and put to flight by Pompeius, and .2400. of his men slayne. And Thessaly they met in the feldes Pharsalia, wher a cruell and doubtful bataile was fought: but at lengthe Pompei was put to flighte, and loste .15000. of his soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours.</p>
   <p>¶Pompeius, sleing to Alexandria in Egipt was slaine by the tutours of the yonge Ptolome,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>1917</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>46</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Before Britayne knovven </seg>13</label> and his head sent vnto Ceser. Who seing it, wept. Thus ended the noble Pompei his life, who for his sundry and incomparable victories, was surnamed the great; he was indued with many noble and princely vertues both of body &amp; minde he had so good a grace in his visage, that from his child hode he meued the people of Rome most entierly to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure him, and also for his singular beneuolence, cōti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of liuing, marcial experience, pleasantnes of spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, fidelitee of maners, and easines in speking to, was meruailously estemed, he neuer required any thīg with out shamfastnes, or granted any thing but with a glad countinaunce. In his visage appered alway both nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and gentilnes, so that when he was in his flouris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing youthe, there shined in him maners both princely and reuerent. When he was sent into Sicily by Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a perceyuing that the souldiours, which were vnder his guiding, scatered and robbed the countreys as he went he commanded euery one of theyr swordes to be signed
<pb n="85" facs="113"/>
with the seale of his ringe, that they shoulde do no wrong to any man by the waye, wherin he declared him selfe to be not onely a valyaunt, but also a iust and righteous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaine.</p>
   <p>Cesar entered Alexandria, and beinge prouoked to ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tail, he vanquished theym, and sette on fyre the nauye of the Egipcians, the flame whereof inuaded the lybrarye of Philadelphus, wherein were burned .40000. bookes. The kinge rebellinge agayne, was slayne with all his ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye, and Cleopatra his sister, restored to the royalme. Then went he into Pontus against Pharnaces, the son of Mithridates, whom at the first encountre he ouerthrue</p>
   <p>C. Iulius Cesar,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>45</label> of whom the Romayne princes were called Cesares,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>14</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3918</label> was the first among the Romaynes that toke on him the name of emperour, &amp; reigned not fullye three yeres, he brought the monarchy of the world vnder the Romaines. In this yere he warred against the Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peians in Aphrike, and vanquished theym at Tapsus, where he toke theyr campe, and .60. elephantes.</p>
   <p>Cato for greefe and sorowe of herte that he had, that his countrey should by Cesar be brought in seruage and thraldome, slue him selfe in U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ica. Iuba, the kinge of Mauritane: hired one to ryd him of his life. Petr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ius and Scipio kylled them selfes. And Cesar commaunded the Neph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eus of the greatte Pompei, and his daughter Pompeia, to be put to death.</p>
   <p>Cesar entred Rome with four triūphes,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>
      </label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>44</label> and was cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ated the fourth time consull,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>15</label> and continuall dictatour, taking on him to be monarche of the whole impire, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thinges brought to passe, he prepared to make warre against the sonnes of Pompei, in Spayne, where fortune was diuers betwene them. And in the last battayle why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was at Munda, a towne in Spayne, they foughte soo sore and harde togither, and suche slaughter was made that the old and assured souldiours of Cesar were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to geue backe, wherby Cesar despairinge to wyn that fielde, would haue killed him selfe, leste after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noume of so many cōquestes and victories, he shuld haue fallen in the power of those yonge men, whose father he had vanquished. But finally, succouring his men, the ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye
<pb facs="114"/>
of the Pompeis was put to flight, the one of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne beinge slayne, the other fleing away. After whiche battayle, Cesar finished those ciuile warres, whiche du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the space of .v. yeres, troubled the whole world. Antipater by Cesar was cōstituted procuratour of Iudea</p>
   <p>Cesar retourned to Rome, he reformed the state of the common weale, amended the calender, reducinge the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the yere, to the course of the sonne, founde out the cause of the leape yere, and in his honour and memorye, the people attributed to him the moneth Quintilis, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che after his name was called Iulius. But he contynued not passing .v. monethes in reste, for waringe insolent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste the senatours, and takinge theyr lybertee frome theim, there conspired against him to the numbre of .260. senatours and gentilmē, among whom Brutus and Cas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sius were chiefe, Whiche in the Ides of Marche, when Cesar came into the senate house, with .xxiii. woūdes, he was slain among the senatours. Thus Cesar lost al that whiche wyth the bloude of .lx. M. citezens, and .1192000. his ennemies, he had gotten. And as he had filled all the world with his ciuile bloud: likewise nowe he filled the se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate with his owne bloud. After this sorte Cesar finished his life, a man in featnes of warre excellinge al other, he wrote no man swifter, and red no man faster, at one time he could endite foure letters at ones, he was furthermore of suche clemency, that those whome he had subdued by warre, with his great gentilnesse, wonne them to be hys veray frendes.</p>
   <p>About this time there was sene in the element, three sonnes in one cercle. And in the suburbes of Rome an oxe spake vnto his plowman: that in vayne he droue him, for shortly not al onely corne, but also men shuld fayle.</p>
   <p>Dolobella was substituted in the place of Cesar, his souldiours at Smyrna killed Trebonius, one of the mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therers of Cesar.</p>
   <p>Antipater reedefied the walles of Hierusalem, he ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Herode president of Galilee.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>42</label> THeomantius, the sonne of Lud, and neuew to Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siuelan,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>
      </label> succeded in the roialme of Britain, and rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned quietly .xxiii. yeres.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="86" facs="114"/>C. Cesar Octauianus Augustus, the second emperour of Rome, reigned in all .lvi. yeres, that is to saye, twelue with Antonius and Lepidus, and .xliiii. alone. As soone as he herde of the deathe of his vncle Iulius, he hasted from Appolonia to Rome to possesse his inheritance, and to reuenge the death of Cesar, here the ciuile wars were againe renued, for the senate fauored the kyllers of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar, but Antonius wold haue suppressed theim with ciuil warre, for whiche cause he was iudged by the senate to bee an ennemye to Rome, and the consules, Hircius and Pansa, with Octauianus, were sente agaynste him: by whom he was vanquished, but the consules were slayne. Than Antonius fled vnto Lepidus, maister of the horse<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, by whose meanes he was recōciled to Octauianus, and they thre ioyntly toke vpon theim the gouernaunce the publike weale.</p>
   <p>Malichus poysoned Antipater, president of Iudea. ¶A greate numbre of the nobilitee in Rome were outla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed by these thre men:<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>2</label> among whom also M. Cicero,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3922</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>41</label> the eloquent oratour was one, who, for soo muche as he had driuen Antonius oute of Rome, and by his sharpe oracy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons caused him to be proclaimed enemie to the weale pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blike, made the saide Antony so much his foe, that in the treatie of peace betwene him and Octauius, he demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Cicero, to do with him at his pleasure▪ whiche was graunted of the vnkinde Octauius, whome Cicero had brought vp, and caused to be made the chiefe gouernor of the Romaines. Wherfore Antonius sent one Herennius (whom Cicero had saued from death by his eloquēce) to slea him, who pursued him as he fledde oute of the citee: whiche thing Cicero perceyuing, abode his comming, ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in a horse litter for weakenes, and prepared his throt to Herennius, who strake of his head, and his right hand and brought theim to Antonie: who caused theim to bee sette ouer the place of ciuile iudgementes in Rome. Cesar and Antonius, committinge the charge of the citie to Lepidus, went with their power against Brutus and Cassius: who had taken Laodicea, pursued Dolobella to deathe, vexed the Tharsenses, toke and spoyled Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but in Phillippo, by Cesar and Antonius, they were
<pb facs="115"/>
vanquished, and slue theim selues. After whiche bataille they deuided the empire betwene them, Cesar takyng for his parte Spaine, Fraunce and Italy, and Antonius all the oryent.</p>
   <p>Pacho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us, king of Parthia, indicted warre against the Iues:<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3923</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>40</label> Antigonus, by his ayd, was constituted king,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>3</label> and toke Phaselus and Hircanus. Phaselus sought his own death, with knockinge his head againste the stones, hys handes beyng not at libertee: and Hircanus, eares were cut of by Antigonus.</p>
   <p>L. Antonius, brother to M. Antonius, moued a newe sedicion in Italy againste Cesar, but at Peru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>a he was vainquisshed, and by the entreatee of the senat, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to him.</p>
   <p>Cleopatra poysoned hir brother, caused hir syster Arsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes to be slain in the temple at Ephesus, and than went to Antonius in Cilicia, whom she folowed.</p>
   <p>Antigonus the .xi. kinge of Iewes, reigned .3. yeres, he was the last of the Iewes,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3924</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>39</label> that was king ouer them.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>4</label>
   </p>
   <p>In this yere Herode, by the senate of Rome, was also appointed to be king of the Iewes.</p>
   <p>Uentidius vanquished the Parthians,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Before Britayne knovven </seg>5</label> and droue them out of Syria:<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3925</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>38</label> he slue Orodes the kings son the same day, that he before had slayne Crassus.</p>
   <p>Sex Pompeius, the son of great Pompei,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>6</label> reised war in Sicily,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>326</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>37</label> Cesar and Antonius went againste him: but finally a peace was made betwene them.</p>
   <p>Herodes the .xii. king of Iewes, and firste of any stran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3927</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>36</label> reigned .37. yeres he besieged Hierusalem,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>7</label> and toke it by the helpe of Sosius presidente of Syria. Antigonus was taken and sent vnto Antonius, who put him to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>. Ananelus was constituted hygh prieste by Herode, and streight depriued.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3928</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>35</label> Hircanus beyng deliuered out of prison,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>8</label> came to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>salem to Herode.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3929</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>34</label> Herode slue Aristobulus the high prieste,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>9</label> and restored Ananelus againe to that office.</p>
   <p>Pompeius brake the peace made with Cesar:<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>10</label> he was dri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen out of Sicily,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3930</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>33</label> and fleyng towardes Asia, was slaine.</p>
   <p>Hitherto extendeth the historie of Appianus of the ciuil
<pb n="87" facs="115"/>
warres of Rome.</p>
   <p>Antonius by reason toke Arrabanes king of Armeny, whom he bounde in siluer chaines, to make him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>11</label> where his treasure laye: whiche whan he had got,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3931</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>32</label> was therwith elated, and moued warre against Octaui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anus, and put awaie his wife Octauia, the sister of Octa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uian, and maried Cleopatra, the quene of Aegypte.</p>
   <p>Octauianus Cesar subdued the Iapides, Dalmacians, and Hungarians.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>12</label> About this time, on the further side of Tiber: in a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon tauerne,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3932</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>31</label> ther sprang forth a fountaine of oyle out of the grounde, whiche for the space of a day ran abundant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly abrode,</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>13</label> The warres betwene Cesar and Antony began, in whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che Antony was ouercome and put to flight.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3933</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>30</label>
   </p>
   <p>They mette again at Pharus vppon the sea, where be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene them was fought a cruell and doubtfull battaile,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>14</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3934</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>29</label> tyll Cleopatra, with .xl. shippes fled, after whom folowed Antony: wherby his men were discomfite, and he for so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, thruste him selfe through with a sworde, and halfe alyue was brought to the tombe, which Cleopatra made for her selfe. Cleopatra, perceyuing that she was kept for the triumphe of Cesar, escaped frome hir keepers to the tombe, wher Antony laie, and there araied in gorgious apparell, settinge to hir breastes twoo adders, dyed in that maner.</p>
   <p>Cesar in the remembraunce of his victorye, builded the citee Nicopolis at Accium.</p>
   <p>An erthquake in Iury, wherby .xxx.M. people perished,</p>
   <p>Herode toke parte with Cesar, and discomfited the Arabikes.</p>
   <p>Iesus, the son of Sabetes, was hygh priest of the Iues. ¶Here ended the kyngdome of the Egypcians, whiche after this time, was gouerned by a presidente of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>15</label> Cesar returned from the orient,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>
      </label> and entred Rome with thre triumphes, and in token of peace,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>82</label> shut vp the temple of Ianus, whiche in .200. yeres before was neuer shutte. In his honour, by the consente of the senate and people, the name of Augustus was geuen to him, &amp; the moneth
<pb facs="116"/>
Sextilis, in the remembraunce of his birth and victories was called August.</p>
   <p>Herode put to deathe his wyfe Mariamnes,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>16</label> and other his nere frendes.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3936</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>27</label>
   </p>
   <p>Corn. Gallus president of Aegypt.</p>
   <p>Cesar opened the temple of Ianus, and made warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Cantabrians and Asturians, two mischeuous people of Spaine, whom he vainquished. Thither came vnto him the ambassadours of India and Scithia, desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the amitee of the Romaines.</p>
   <p>M. Crassus subdued the Thracians, and Corn, Gallus,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>18</label> president of Aegypte,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3938</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>25</label> kylled him selfe: in whose rome suc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceded Sempronius.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>23</label> All Spayne by Cesar was subdued,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>20</label> and the temple of Ianus shut,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3940</label> but it was opened againe through the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocions of the Germaines and other nacions.</p>
   <p>Herode deposed Iesu the hyghe prieste, and constituted Simon, whose daughter he maried.</p>
   <p>In this time Grece by Tiberius &amp; Drusus was subdued.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3941</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>22</label> Drusus, the son in lawe of Augustus,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>21</label> broughte in sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection the Germanes, with other people bordring about them. Cossus in affrike ouercom the Mosulanes, and Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tulanes, and Piso subdued the Uindelicos.</p>
   <p>Peace was made with the Parthians, who restored to the Romaines their baners taken from Crassus and An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tonius,</p>
   <p>Cesar added to the dominyon of Herode, Samaria, Gaza, and diuers other regions.</p>
   <p>Uergil and Horace, most famous poetes, in thys tyme flourished.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>20</label> Cesar sayled into Syria, he graunted to Herode the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uince Auramitides,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3943</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>23</label> and wrate hym amonge the noum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of his frendes.</p>
   <p>CYmbelinus, the sonne of Theomantius, reygned king of Britayn .xxxv yeres.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3944</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>19</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>1</label> Of him there is no no table thinge wrytten, but that in his reygne oure sauiour Iesu Christe, the veraie light of the worlde was borne of the virgin Mary.</p>
   <p>Herode pulled cleane downe the temple, builded by Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabell and Es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a, after the captiuitee of Babylon, and
<pb n="88" facs="116"/>
with moste sumptuous buyldinge reedefied an other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the figure of Salomons.</p>
   <p>Ewin the thirde sonne of Edeir, succeded his father in the roialme of Scotland,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>3</label> &amp; reigned .7. yeres.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3946</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>17</label> A prince giuen al to vice &amp; lechery, for beinge not contente (as they write) with a 100. concubines, with whome he myghte fulfyll his luste, but he made lawes, that it shuld be lauful for his subiectes: to haue as many wiues as they myghte kepe, that the wifes of the commons should be commune to the nobles, and that the lorde should haue the mayden head of al virgines dwellinge in his lordeshippe: whiche last lawe endured vntill the time of Malcolm Cammorre and from thens vntill this time they pay a fine for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcion of theyr maydenhead. When he hadde thus continued .7. yeres, in exercising his tirannye and fylthy lust, he fell in hatred of his lordes, and by theym was de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>posed and slayne in prison.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>5</label> The most blessed and pure virgin sainct Mary,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3948</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>15</label> mother of our saluiour Iesu Christ, was borne of the holye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone sainct Anna.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>8</label> Herode finished the temple,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3951</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>12</label> &amp; the people with great ioy did celebrate a feast</p>
   <p>Herode gaue wiues vnto his sonnes,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3952</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>11</label> for he maryed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristobulus vnto Beronices,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>9</label> the daughter of his sister Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lome, and Alexander to Glafira, the daughter of Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus king of Cappadocia.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>10</label> Metellane nepheu to Edeir,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3953</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>10</label> was chosen king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes a vertuous and quyet prynce, who peaciblye reygned 39. yeres.</p>
   <p>M. Agrippa subdued Bosphorus, in whiche expedicion Herode was.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>11</label> A domestical sedicion beganne in the house of Herode.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3954</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>9</label> for Salome his sister accused Aristobulus and Alexander of Parricide, for which cause theyr father caste theym in pryson.</p>
   <p>About this time Herode presumed, to open the tombe of Dauid, trusting to haue there some great treasure: but when he had founde a precious vesell, and woulde haue entered further, a fyre yssued out of the darke. and destroi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed two of his men, wherby he was let from his pourpose.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="117"/>Warre betwene Herode and the Arabians, in whyche Herode was victour.</p>
   <p>Herode caused his sonnes Aristobulus and Alexander, to be hanged.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3956</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>7</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>13</label>
   </p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3599</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>4</label> There flourished at this time in Rome manye learned men as Uirgil, Horace, Ouide, Saluste, Liuius,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>16</label> Hortensi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us, Antenodorus, with many other.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3961</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>2</label> Cesar the thirde time closed the temple of Ianus:<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>18</label> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall peace was throughout the whole world, he stabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed his publike weale with good lawes.</p>
   <p>Cyreneus presidente of Siria,<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Anni regum britannie </seg>19</label> did first describe and num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre the people of Iudea.<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere of the worlde </seg>3962</label>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">The yere before Christe </seg>1</label>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>