<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE SYR VVILLIAM STANLEY Knight, Coronel of the English Regment. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Gibbons, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108929_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06450</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108929</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE SYR VVILLIAM STANLEY Knight, Coronel of the English Regment. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Gibbons, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A spiritual doctrine : conteining a rule to liue vvel, vvith diuers praiers and meditations. Abridged by the Reuerend Father Levvis de Granada of the holie order of preachers. And deuided into sixe treatises, as is to be seene after the prefaces. Nevvlie translated out of Spanish into English</title>
                 <author>Luis, de Granada</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 208, 229-397, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE SYR VVILLIAM STANLEY <hi>Knight, Coronel of the English Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ment. &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ONORABLE Syr, hauing latelie trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this little vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume out of Spanish into English, I began to thinke, to vvhat person of our nation I might dedicate the same, that not onelie vvould gratefullie accept of so small a trauail, but also vvere able to iudge, as vvel of the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as also of the fruite vvhich maie be deriued to such, as shall list to reade it. At the length a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb facs="3"/>all others, your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable person seemed to me most fitte, for all the respects before mentioned. For if I regard your courtisie to all sortes of men, and your speciall good vvill and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to those of mic coate in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (to saie nothing of mie self in particular;) I maie vvith greate reason be esteemed verie vndis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete, if I should think, that you vvould take this poore offer other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise, then your Nobilitie and courtisie requireth. Also if I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider either your knovvledge in both languages English and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish, or youre experience, and vvounderful good affection to all sortes of spirituall, and Godlie Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises, ioined vvith your Deuotion,
<pb facs="3"/>Pietie and Zeale in the seruice of God; I can not but esteeme you to be a sufficient Iudge as vvell of the translation, as also of the profit, that manie maie take by this little vvoorke. Accept then, Honorable good Syr, the same, as the first frutes, &amp; token of mie good vvill tovvards you; accept it, I saie, vntill I haue put som other thing in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, vvhich maie further the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall auancement of deuoute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, &amp; be more vvorth your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and accept therevvithall mie sincere affection, vvholie addicted to praie for your long life, and prosperitie, vvhich God graunt you, and preserue the same to his greater honour and glorie, and to your ovvne saluation and best
<pb facs="4"/>contentment. Christ IESVS be alvvaies in your safegard.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From our college of the Societie of IESVS in Louan <date>this 19. of March 1599. being the feast of S. Ioseph.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours most humble affectionate. Rich. Gibbons.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>