<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Certaine memorable Notes inserted into this As∣sertion
since the Translation thereof.
By Ric. Ro.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108439_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05297</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15441</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108439</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Certaine memorable Notes inserted into this As∣sertion
since the Translation thereof.
By Ric. Ro.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and true assertion of the original, life, actes, and death of the most noble, valiant, and renoumed Prince Arthure, King of great Brittaine : Who succeeding his father Vther Pendragon, and right nobly gouerning this land sixe and twentie yeares, then dyed of a mortall wounde receyued in battell, together vvith victory ouer his enemies. As appeareth cap. 9. And was buried at Glastenbury. cap. 12. an. 543. Collected and written of late yeares in lattin, by the learned English antiquarie of worthy memory Iohn Leyland. Newly translated into English by Richard Robinson citizen of London. Anno Domini. 1582</title>
                 <author>Leland, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 39 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_notes">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Certaine memorable Notes inserted into this As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion
since the Translation thereof.
By Ric. Ro.</head>
   <p>AS <hi>Pliny</hi> saith, <hi>Ingenui pudoris est fateri per quos
proseceris:</hi> So I must freely confesse the friendly
helps of those which profited me in this purpose.</p>
   <p>First by conference with Master <hi>Steuen Batman,</hi> a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Preacher and friendlie fauourer of vertue and learning,
(touching the praise worthie progenie of this <hi>K. Arthure)</hi> he
gaue me this assured knowledge on this maner taken out of
his Auncient records written at <hi>Aualonia.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Uerses found in certaine Cronicles, wherein were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses
had of <hi>Aruiragus</hi> king of <hi>Brittaine</hi> 45. yeeres after
the natiuitie of <hi>Christe.</hi>
   </p>
   <l>Twelue men in number entered the Vale of Aualon:</l>
   <l>Ioseph of Aramathia was the chiefest flowre of them.</l>
   <l>Ioseph the sonne of Ioseph, his father did attend,</l>
   <l>With other tenne: and Glaston did possesse.</l>
   <p>There al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>▪, this writing did witnesse, that <hi>K. Arthure</hi> of
greate <hi>Brittaine</hi> descēded of the stocke of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> saide <hi>Ioseph</hi> viz.
<hi>Helarius</hi> the Nephewe of <hi>Ioseph</hi> begate <hi>Iosue, Iosue</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<hi>Aminadab, Aminadab</hi> begate <hi>Castellors, Castellors</hi>
begate <hi>Manaell, Manaell</hi> begate <hi>Lambord</hi> and <hi>Vrlard,</hi> and
<hi>Lambord</hi> begate a sonne that begate <hi>Igerna</hi> of which wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
king <hi>Vther Pendragon</hi> begate the noble and renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<hi>King Arthure.</hi> Whereby it plainely appeareth, that
<hi>K. Arthure</hi> descended of the stocke of <hi>Ioseph.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, like wise of the same kindred (whereof <hi>K. Arthure</hi>
came) proceeded these auncient <hi>Brittaines</hi> also.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Peter</hi> the Cosē of <hi>Ioseph</hi> of <hi>Aramathia,</hi> king of <hi>Arcadia,</hi>
begate <hi>Erlan, Erlan</hi> begate <hi>Melianus, Melianus</hi> begate
<hi>Arguthe, Arguthe</hi> begate <hi>Edor, Edor</hi> begate <hi>Lotho</hi> which
maried to wife the sister of <hi>K. Arthure,</hi> of whom <hi>Lotho</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
4 sonnes, to wit, <hi>Walwanus Agranaius, Guerelies,</hi>
and <hi>Garelies:</hi> all which were noble men of authoritie in
<hi>Brittaine</hi> where they dwelt.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
Moreouer he shewed me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut of his auncient records the
interchaunges of king <hi>Arthures</hi> armes which hee gaue in
three chiefes, from the first to the third: viz.</p>
   <p>His first armes he bare in a shield <hi>Gules,</hi> (red) three <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes,
Or.</hi> gold</p>
   <p>His second hee bare in a shield <hi>Vert,</hi> (greene) a plaine
<hi>Crossargent:</hi> in chiefe the figure of the <hi>Virgin Marie</hi> with
<hi>Christe</hi> in her armes.</p>
   <p>His third and last in a shield <hi>Azure,</hi> (blew) three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ownes.
<hi>Or.</hi> (gold.)</p>
   <p>But after knowledge of these seuerall armes, I had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
of a certaine. French booke, wherein he is reported to
aue giuen a shielde <hi>Azure</hi> (blew) 13. <hi>Crownes. Or.</hi>
gold</p>
   <p>This booke beeing in an English mans handes, I was
not so desirous to see it, but he as willingly shewed it &amp; lent
it me. There was in it portracted both the seuerall names,
shieldes, and seuerall armes in colours also depainted of all
<hi>K. Arthures</hi> knights and vnder euery one the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
due vnto him by his cheualrie. Which because the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauing
of their armes was very chargeable, &amp; the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of matter more then I could in so shorte time publish
in the English tongue: I was enforced to content me with
this briefe collection concerning <hi>K. Arthure.</hi> and with the
names of 16. kinges, one Duke, and 149. knightes, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
as were therin printed. viz.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>