<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. WALTER PELL one of the assis∣tants of the most vvorthy cōpanie of the marchants-Adventurers re∣siding at Hamb:</title>
           <author>Loe, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108789_Fr6_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16690</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. WALTER PELL one of the assis∣tants of the most vvorthy cōpanie of the marchants-Adventurers re∣siding at Hamb:</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Songs of Sion : Set for the ioy of gods deere ones, vvho sitt here by the brookes of this vvorlds Babel, &amp; vveepe vvhen they thinke on Hierusalem vvhich is on highe. By W.L</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Hamburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 164, 100 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="62"/>
   <pb n="123" facs="62"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To his much esteemed good frend Mr.</hi> WALTER PELL one of the assis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the most vvorthy cōpanie of the marchants-Adventurers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siding at Hamb:</head>
   <q>Ioy of both vvorlds.</q>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ouing frend. If you vvould die vvell, you must endeuour to liue vvell. Then let your death be neuer so suddaine, It vvill not come vnexpected neither vvill you be vnprepared. The daies, &amp; houers of daies that you haue spent in gods seruice either in praying, or praysing him shalbe
<pb n="124" facs="63"/>
so many cordialls of comforts, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> consciences of vvell led purposes, &amp; vvill so take vp your hart in ioye, &amp; solace, that noe terrour of death, or darkenes shall appale yt. Who vvould not then be busie in this so serious, so sacred a busines? Let vs neuer thinke to be soundly merry, if this be not our musique. Reason, &amp; Religion guides vs here vnto. For veary Reason shevveth vnto vs that vve must all die, &amp; Religion enlighteneth vs hovve vve may dye vvell. Fooles iudge actions by euents, But the vvise for see by iudgmēt of reason, &amp; faith vvhat vvill inevitably ensue. To this purpose all this is sayd. That as I haue in myne endeered loue sent you an introduction herevnto in this paper token so you vvould
<pb n="125" facs="63"/>
accept, &amp; practize it. So shall I euer rest your votary praying to god for your eternall happines in Christ Iesus his sauing mercies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your perpetuall votary.
W. LOE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>