<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBILITIE AND people of England and Scotland, A Poesie made by T. V. Englishman.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108494_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05354</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15507</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108494</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBILITIE AND people of England and Scotland, A Poesie made by T. V. Englishman.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise tovvching the right, title, and interest of the most excellent Princess Marie, Queene of Scotland, and of the most noble king Iames, her Graces sonne, to the succession of the croune of England : VVherein is conteined asvvell a genealogie of the competitors pretending title to the same croune: as a resolution of their obiections. Compiled and published before in latin, and after in Englishe, by the right reuerend father in God, Iohn Lesley, Byshop of Rosse. VVith an exhortation to the English and Scottish nations, for vniting of them selues in a true league of amitie</title>
                 <author>Leslie, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Loyselet (L’Oiselet), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 1, 13-71 leaves, folded plates (woodcut), genealogical table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>TO THE NOBILITIE AND people of England and Scotland, A Poesie made by T. V. Englishman.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>Dravve neare, vvith heedfull eyes this booke peruse:</l>
      <l>VVho that desires assuredlie to knovve</l>
      <l>Those iust decrees, that English people vse,</l>
      <l>For rightfull heyres, to whom the Croune dothe grovve:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVith gloriouse Rases of so riche a soyle,</l>
      <l>And golden bondes of most assured peace,</l>
      <l>VVhiche (after vvarres and many a bloodie broyle)</l>
      <l>Hath long time lasted, and dothe still encrease,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <l>By Henries vvyfe, vvhom Stories seuenth doe name:</l>
      <l>From vvhose renoumed stocke and princelie straine,</l>
      <l>Marie novv present Quene of Scotland came,</l>
      <l>And Iames her sonne, as king to rule and raigne,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Vnder that Pole, vvhiche vve the Northern call.</l>
      <l>This ladie by her predecessors right</l>
      <l>Dothe looke the Englishe Croune to her shall fall,</l>
      <l>Vertue to defend, and people (by her Might)</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To guyde in peace, vvhen Henries heyres are dead:</l>
      <l>VVhiche vvas the eight, in great renoume of late.</l>
      <l>For then, vvith right pretence, vvho can procede</l>
      <l>To gayn saye her, and spoyle her of her state,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And right, to beare the svvaye in Englishe land?</l>
      <l>But lest the simple man should grovve in doubt,</l>
      <l>VVhat lavve allovves her, for their heyr to stand,</l>
      <l>Lesley vvell knovveing all the cause throughout,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As one that loues his Quene, and common peace,</l>
      <l>By busie toyle, hathe brought this thing aboute,</l>
      <l>And dothe his best to make false practise cease.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You Britaines therfore, vvith attentiue heede,</l>
      <l>Dravve neer, and reape the croppe of this his seede.</l>
      <l>Esteme his vvorke, and vveighe his vvarninges vvyse,</l>
      <l>That telles the truthe, still one in vvoorde and mynde:</l>
      <l>Regarde the right of her, vvho once may ryse</l>
      <l>And rule in state: your Quene to heauens resigned.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>"That onlie Realm is in most happie state,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>"VVhiche beares no Tyrannes rule, nor blody band:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>"And whose renowmed Prince doeth euell hate,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>"And rules in peace the people of her land.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>