<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST NOBLE and aboundant president both of Honor and vertue, HENRY Earle of Southampton.</title>
           <author>Blount, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108618_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19211</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5624</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST NOBLE and aboundant president both of Honor and vertue, HENRY Earle of Southampton.</title>
                 <author>Blount, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the vniting of the kingdom of Portugall to the crowne of Castill : containing the last warres of the Portugals against the Moores of Africke, the end of the house of Portugall, and change of that gouernment. The description of Portugall, their principall townes, castles, places ... Of the East Indies, the isles of Terceres, and other dependences</title>
                 <author>Conestaggio, Gerolamo Franchi di</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 324, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST NOBLE and aboundant president both of <hi>Honor and vertue,</hi> HENRY Earle of Southampton.</head>
   <head type="sub">Right honorable and most woorthy Earle,</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not my fortune to be so infortunately read, as to begin (after the common stampe of dedication) with a grai-headed Apophthegme, or some straied sentence out of <hi>Tully,</hi> but in such proper and plaine language, as a most humble and affectionate due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can speake, I do heere offer vp on the altar of my hart, the first fruits of my long-growing ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors; which (with much constancie and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) I haue cherisht, onely waiting this happie opportunitie to make them manifest to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: where nowe if (in respect of the knowne distance, betwixt the height of your Honorable spirit, and the flatnesse of my poore abilities) they turne into smoake and vanish ere they can reach a degree of your merite, vouchsafe yet most (excellent Earle) to remember it was a fire that kindled them, and gaue them life at least, if not lasting. Your Honors patronage is the onely obiect I aime at; and were the worthinesse of this Historie I present, such as might war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant me an election out of a worlde of Nobilitie; I woulde still pursue the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines of my first choise; which hath since beene confirmed to me by my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected friend the translator, a Gentleman most sincerely deuoted to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: For the subiect it selfe I dare say nothing; since it is out of my element to iudge. But I haue heard others report it (and some of them also iudicious) to be a thing first and excellently written in Italian; then translated into French, and generally receiued in both those toongs through all christendome for a faithfull, elegant, sinewie, and well digested historie: what the beauties of it are now in this English habite, I make your Honorable Lordship the first and most competent Censor; wishing that before you begin to read farther, you could but reade my silence.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By him that wants much to expresse his dueties to your Honor, EDW. BLOVNT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>