<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108694_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19346</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5770</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108694</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Cid : a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their Majesties at court, and on the Cock-pit stage in Drury-lane by the servants to both their Majesties</title>
                 <author>Corneille, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walkley, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="4"/>
To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He place of a Prologue let this leafe take up; which would gently advise you to suspend your censure of this translation, till you be skilled in both the languages; for from the ignorant in either I may suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. Some places in the Originall I have changed, but not many: two Scenes I have left out, as being soliloquies and little pertinent to the businesse: some things I have added, but scarce discernable: where he would give me leave, I have followed close both the sense &amp; words of the Author, but many things are received wit in one tongue which are not in another. The Play it selfe, being a true history, though like a Romance (since this age consists of such Play-seers) I would willingly propose to be imitated of our undertakers in the like kinde, I meane for the conveyance, and (as I may call it) the Oeconomy of it: for what concernes the wit and naturall expressions in it; I know I speak to deafe people, whose
<pb facs="5"/>
tares have beene furr'd with' so many Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perboles, which it the wit in fashion, though the same in <note n="*" place="margin">Sen. Rhet. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ua. 1. sub <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nem.</note>
      <hi>Seneca's</hi> dayes, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted madnesse. But if they knew how dissenting with a right care any affected speech is, they would rather trespasse the other way, and not straine nature beyond what we finde it commonly is. But this is no fit Porch for the Temple of love, Ile shut it up, and open you the pleasant way, into which you had rather enter.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>