<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable WILLIAM, Earle of Devonshire. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>May, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108868_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16888</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108868</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable WILLIAM, Earle of Devonshire. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>May, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lucans Pharsalia: or The ciuill warres of Rome, betweene Pompey the great, and Iulius Cæsar : The whole tenne bookes, Englished by Thomas May, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Lucan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones, Thomas 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>310 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable WILLIAM, Earle of <hi>Devonshire.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great subiect of this stately <hi>Poem,</hi> together with the worth of the noble <hi>Author,</hi> haue enboldned me to present the Translation (how meanely soever I have performed it) to your
<pb facs="4"/>
Honourable hand. I cannot but presume that the high, and rich conceits of <hi>Lucan</hi> from your deepe iudgement shall finde their proper, and due approbation, and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, from your noble <hi>candor,</hi> an easie, and gentle censure. The matter of this Worke is a true History adorned and heightned with <hi>Poetical rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> which doe not adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, nor corrupt the truth, but giue it a more sweet and pleasant relish. The History of it, is the greatest of Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb facs="4"/>
the affaires of <hi>Rome,</hi> whose transcendent greatnes will admit no cōparison with other <hi>States</hi> either before, or after it; <hi>Rome</hi> was then at that great height, in which S. <hi>Augustin</hi> wished to haue seen it, which after Ages almost with adoration haue admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and do rather coniecture then fully comprehend. The blood of her valiant citizens, and the conquests, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of so many ages had raised her now to that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy height, in which shee
<pb facs="5"/>
could neither retaine her freedom without great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, nor fall into a <hi>Monarchy</hi> but most heavy and distast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. In one the greatnesse of private Citizens excluded moderation: in the other the vast strength, and forces of the Prince gaue him too ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute and vndetermined a power. The vices of <hi>Rome</hi> did at this time not only grow vp to their power, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it. <hi>Luxury</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> the wicked daughters of so noble a Mother as the <hi>Roman
<pb facs="5"/>
Ʋertue,</hi> began to consume that which brought them forth. These were the seeds of that faction, which rent the State, and brought in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently a change of governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The two heads of this great division (if wee may terme <hi>Pompey</hi> the head of a faction, &amp; not rather the true servant of the publike State) were <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, and <hi>Julius Caesar,</hi> men of greater eminence then the former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges had seene any, whose prosperous atchiuements in
<pb facs="6"/>
forreine wars had too far en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled them to ruine that state, which before they ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The Author of it was a noble Roman, rich in his minde as his large fortunes, of whose happy conceits, and high raptures I forbeare to dispute, or any way anticipate your Lordships iudgement. To whose noble censure I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer both the Author, and my poore endeavours, and shall ever rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships to command, <hi>THO. MAY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>