<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADMONITION TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Fox, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108932_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06521</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16993</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADMONITION TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Fox, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Special and chosen sermons of D. Martin Luther : collected out of his writings and preachings for the necessary instruction and edification of such, as hunger and seeke after the perfect knowledge and inestimable glorie which is in Christ Iesu, to the comfort and saluation of their soules. Englished by VV.G</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 481, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>AN ADMONITION TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the commendation of this worke, and the Author thereof, there
shall not neede I trust at this present any great discourse to be
made, forasmuch as so many good bookes of the same writer be already
set abroad, whereby may sufficiently be coniectured what is to be thought
of this also. Againe because the worke it selfe is such, conteining
such matter of heauenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, that without any further commendation
of other, it yeldeth cause sufficient to commend it selfe. Onely this
then remaineth, to intreat and exhort the reader, but to peruse &amp; reade
the same, who in so doing shall fynde I doubt not, neither to lacke great
cause in vs to set forth these Sermons, nor lesse necessitie in
the readers to bestow paines in perusing and reading them, for the dignitie
of the matter, and singular frute therein to be found. For what more worthie
matter can be, thē to set forth Christ in his right glorie, in his full
riches and royall estate to the hearts and soules of men, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
such as are heauie laden and distressed in spirit? what more
comfortable hearinge, or doctrine more true, then of forgiuenes and
remission of synnes, so graciously purchased, so freely offered
by our Sauiour, so cleerely preached by his ministers? or what riches more
excellent, then faith fixed in Christ, and hope sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in the
promises of life? or what studie more frutefull, then to seeke the
kingdome of God? For <pb facs="8"/> where the frute of all other studies
decayeth and hath his ende, the frute of this study abydeth for euer. And
therefore not without cause we be so willed by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour him selfe,
first to seeke for this kingdome and righteousnes thereof, promising
withall in an other place, that he which seeketh shall fynde. In the
seeking of which kingdom two special notes we haue to learne and search,
first the glorie &amp; grace of the King, secondly the welth and felicitie
of the subiects. In which two partes as the whole summe of all our
spirituall comfort most principally consisteth, groūded in the holy
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: so of all expositors of the same Scriptures, I know none or
fewe, in these our dayes, more liuely to open these comforts vnto vs out of
Gods worde, then this Doctor and Preacher of these Sermōs here following:
which as he hath done most effectually first in his owne tounge to his
contry people, then in Latin to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: so this translator hath no
lesse plainly and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly englished the same for the commoditie and
vse of our contryfolke of England. By whose meanes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie this
vantage we haue now gayned, that we haue gotten vnto vs one good preacher in
England more then we had before, to the comfort and edification of all such
as be disposed to read and learne. So that in such townes and villages,
wherein before were mute ministers, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, this Preacher now
may supplie the lacke, and there be receiued as their person, if they
please, preaching now in their owne speech vnto them, and putting them to
no charges of any tythes. And in other places where more plentie of learned
teachers is, yet notwithstanding no hurt shall come to admit this
stranger as a coadiutor, or felow helper vnto them. Whereby I nothing dout,
but in so doing, all such as shalbe willing to giue eare to this
Preacher, as well they <pb facs="8"/> that be learned, shall fynde wherein to
growe in more perfection, as also the vnlearned wherein to be instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
sufficiently to their soules helth in Christ Iesu. In whom I wish to
thee and to all true Christian readers all spirituall grace and heauenly
wisedom, to blesse thy studies, to prosper thy labours, to
stablish thy faith, to multiplie thy consolations, to direct thy wayes,
and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to glorifie thee both body and soule in his blessed kingdome
for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. FOX.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>
      <figure>
         <byline>T. V.</byline>
      </figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>