<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A generall description of all Africa, togither with a comparison of the ancient and new names of all the principall countries and prouinces therein.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108481_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05331</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15481</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108481</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A generall description of all Africa, togither with a comparison of the ancient and new names of all the principall countries and prouinces therein.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A geographical historie of Africa, written in Arabicke and Italian by Iohn Leo a More, borne in Granada, and brought vp in Barbarie. Wherein he hath at large described, not onely the qualities, situations, and true distances of the regions, cities, townes, mountaines, riuers, and other places throughout all the north and principall partes of Africa; but also the descents and families of their kings ... gathered partly out of his owne diligent obseruations, and partly out of the ancient records and chronicles of the Arabians and Mores. Before which, out of the best ancient and moderne writers, is prefixed a generall description of Africa, and also a particular treatise of all the maine lands and isles vndescribed by Iohn Leo. ... Translated and collected by Iohn Pory, lately of Goneuill and Caius College in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Leo, africanus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60, 420 pages, folded plates, map, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="general_description">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="7"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <head>A generall description of all Africa, togither <hi>with a comparison of the ancient and new names of all the principall countries and prouinces therein.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THat part of inhabited lande extending south<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Africa other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bya.</note> which we call Africa, and the Greeks Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bya, is one of the three generall parts of the world knowen vnto our ancestors; which in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">The greater part of Africa vnknowen in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> ages.</note> deed was not throughly by them discouered, both bicause the Inlands coulde not be trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in regard of huge deserts full of dangerous sands, which being driuen with the winde, put trauailers in extreme hazard of their liues; and also by reason of the long and perilous nauigation vpon the African coasts, for which cause it was by very few of ancient times compassed by nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, much lesse searched or intirely known. Of which few, the principall were <hi>Hanno</hi> a Carthaginian captaine sent by the gouernours of that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welth<note place="margin">When Africa was sailed round about.</note> for discouerie of the saide lande, and one <hi>Eudoxus</hi> that fled from <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaeus Lathyrus,</hi> the king of Alexandria. Howbeit in these latter times it hath beene often<note n="*" place="margin">And since also by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, French, and Dutch.</note> by the Portugals sailed round about, and diligently sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, especially along the shore, euen from the streights of Gibraltar to the enterance of the red sea:<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Dias doubled the cape besore; but returned fearefuily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proceeding any farther. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of this worde Africa.</note> but the first Portugall that euer doubled the cape of Buena esperança, and coasted the south and southeast parts of Africa, in former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vnknowne, was <hi>Vasco da Gama,</hi> in the yeere 1497. who from hence sailed to Calicut in the east Indies, to the vnspeakeable gaine of the Portugals.</p>
   <p>To omit <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> his etymologies of this name Africa; <hi>Festus</hi> will haue it to be deriued from the Greeke worde <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, which signifieth horror or colde, and from <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> the particle priuatiue, as who shoulde say, Africa is a place free from all horror and extremitie of colde, bicause it lieth open to the heauens, and is sandie, drie, and desert. Others say that it is called Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca <hi>quasi Aprica,</hi> that is exposed and subiect to the scorching beames of the sunne, the most part there of lying betweene the Tropicks. <hi>Iosephus</hi> wil haue<note place="margin">Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> was called Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bya.</note> it so called from <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> one of the posteritie of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and others from <hi>Afer</hi> sonne to <hi>Hercules</hi> of Libya. But it was by the Greekes called Libya, bicause it was in old time conquered by <hi>Libs</hi> the king of Mauritania. In the holie Scriptures it is called Chamesis, by the Arabians and Ethiopians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and by the Indians Besecath.</p>
   <p>In situation &amp; shape this land of Africa is almost an islle, being by a very<note place="margin">The situation and shape of Africa.</note> small and narrowe neckland (passing betweene the Mediterran sea and the gulfe of Arabia, <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> the red sea) conioined to Asia, and in extension of
<pb n="2" facs="8"/>
ground being almost twise as bigge as Europe, albeit for inhabitants it is not halfe so populous. Wherefore though in longitude from west to east Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<note place="margin">A comparison betweene Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca and Europe.</note> be shorter then Europe in some places, yet extendeth it so farre vnto the south, that Europe in that respect is nothing comparable vnto it: for Africa containeth almost seuentie degrees in latitude, whereas Europe stretcheth but fiue and thirtie degrees: moreouer Africa is more vniforme and spaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but Europe is of a more distracted and manifolde shape, being in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry<note place="margin">The causes why Africa is so slenderly inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</note> places dispersed &amp; restrained by the sea. Howbeit notwithstanding Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca hath farre greater extension of ground then Europe, yet is it not so po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, nor so commodious to inhabite: for the lande of Africa is in many places vnhabitable; the principall causes whereof are, the scarcitie of water, the barrennes of the soile, being either couered with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sande, dust, or ashes, or else being subiect to extreme heate of the sunne: also there<note place="margin">Sandie seas in Africa.</note> are certaine dangerous heapes of sande, which being raised by the winde, are driuen vp and downe like the waues of a tempestuous sea: In briefe, there are such abundance of venemous and hurtfull creatures, that for feare of them the land in some places can very hardly, &amp; in others by no meanes be manured or inhabited, be it neuer so fruitfull. Wherefore in diuers parts this region lieth waste and vnpeopled: howbeit where it is inhabited, it is exceeding fertile, and that especially in the north parts thereof, lying ouer against Europe, where (according to the report of many historiographers, and cosmographers) it was in ancient times abundantly furnished with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants: so likewise all the westerne coast betweene Cabo de buena espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rança, and Cabo Negro situate about nineteene degrees of southerly lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, containeth many plaines, hils, vallies, and other places most fruitfull and pleasant, it being there a continuall spring, and elsewhere also it is verie fertile, as it shall be declared more at large in the particular descriptions of each region.</p>
   <p>The Equinoctiall circle doth in a manner diuide Africa in the verie<note place="margin">The position of Africa, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens.</note> midst thereof; from whence it stretcheth not onely to each tropique, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so twelue degrees almost beyond them both: wherefore the greater part is comprized betweene the saide Tropiques vnder the Torrid or burnt Zone, for which onely cause the ancient writers supposed it to be vnhabitable and desert in so many places: which indeed is much rather to be ascribed to the waste wildernesse, the barren and sandie soile, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of waters and fountaines. It comprehendeth therefore fully and perfecty the three first northerly climates, and so many and the like climates southerly; for it is situate betweene the eleuenth north Parallele, and the eleuenth Antiparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lele, or south Parallele, both which are equally distant from the Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all on either side. But about either of the foresaid extremes, the longest day consisteth of fowerteene howers and one fourth part, and about the midst, of twelue howers exactly. Likewise as touching the longitude, Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca stretcheth from the Meridian vnder fower degrees to the Meridian vnder fower-score and two degrees of longitude, to wit, from Cabo Roxo, or the
<pb n="3" facs="8"/>
Red cape on the west, to Cape Guardafu on the east side, betweene which two capes is the greatest bredth of Africa.</p>
   <p>Africa hath too narrowe boundes allotted vnto it by <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note place="margin">The boundes of Africa.</note> others, for they disioine the greater part of Egypt and all Ethiopia there-from. Wherefore it is more conuenient in this behalfe to follow <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemey,</hi> and the late writers, limiting the same on the north with the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terran sea, and the streights of Gibraltar; on the east with the Red sea or the Arabian gulfe, and the small neckland of Asia passing betweene the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terran sea, and the said gulfe; on the south (at the cape of Buena esperança, where it endeth in forme of a wedge) with the maine Ocean partly called the Ethiopian sea, as being neere vnto the land of Ethiopia; and on the west, from the hither side of the Equinoctiall line, with the Atlantike Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, (called by <hi>Ptolemey Mare Occiduum,</hi> by <hi>Dionysius Hesperium,</hi> and part thereof by the Spaniards Mar del Norte) but beyond the Equinoctiall line it is bounded westward with the Ethiopian sea.</p>
   <p>Africa hath very many and most exceeding great mountaines, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal<note place="margin">The mountaines of Africa.</note> wherof is Mount-Atlas, whose tops of incredible height rising out of<note place="margin">Mount Atlas.</note> the midst of sandy desertes, exalt themselues aboue the cloudes. This mountaine beginneth westward at that place, where it distinguisheth the Ocean by the name of Atlanticus: from whence by a perpetuall ridge, after many windings and turnings, it extendeth east toward the confines of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt: moreouer it is in most places rounde, hard to ascend, craggie, steepe, impassable, cold, barren, shadie, and euery where full of woods and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, with cloudes alwaies houering about the tops thereof, being forlorn and desolate toward the Ocean, but ouer against<note n="*" place="margin">The prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Alger, Bugia, Constantina, and Tunis.</note> Africa minor, most fertile, and abounding with plentie of corne and of thick woods which are clad with a kinde of mosse no whit inferior to silke.</p>
   <p>The tops of this mountaine are couered with deepe snowes euen in the midst of sommer: and sometimes when the North winds blow any thing sharpe, the snow falleth in such abundance, that it hideth the trees growing vpon the sides therof, and is deadly both to man and beast.</p>
   <p>Moreouer the fountaines which are here found, are so extreame cold in<note place="margin">Extreme cold fountaines.</note> the hottest of sommer, as if a man should dip his hand therein but for a short space, it would loose both life, sence, and motion. Besides Mount At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las<note place="margin">Mountaines called Os Picos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: that is to say, sharpe pointed. Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: Dec. 1. lib. 8. cap. 4.</note> those mountaines likewise are very famous, which being situate on the south part of Africa, are called by the Portugales Os Picosfragosos: for by reason of their surpassing height and craggie cliffes it is impossible to skale them, and they are bare, forlorne, and destitute of all reliefe.</p>
   <p>Likewise the cape commonly called Sierra Leonais as it were framed out of an exceeding high mountaine, which may be kenned a mightie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance off: the top of this mountaine is continuallie ouershadowed with cloudes, which often send forth dreadfull thunder and lightening: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon some think it to haue bin called by Ptolemey, and by Hanno of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage, The chariot of the gods.</p>
   <pb n="4" facs="9"/>
   <p>The mountaines of the moone also, knowen of old, and situate vnder the<note place="margin">Lunae montes.</note> Tropique of Capricorne, being very high and craggie, are inhabited by bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and sauage people, nere vnto which are valleis of such exceeding depth, as if they reached to the center of the earth. Likewise there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mountaines in Angola called Cabambe containing most rich siluer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Also in Africa are certaine mightie lakes, which for their extension seem<note place="margin">The lake of Zembre, which by some others is placed vnder the Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</note> rather to be seas, the principal wherof called by some Zembre, being situate by a number of huge mountaines, and distant from the Equinoctial eleuen or twelue degrees to the south, containeth about fiue hundred leagues in compasse, out of which lake doe spring the famous riuers of Nilus, Zaire, and Cuama, and some affirme very strange sea-monsters to be therein.</p>
   <p>Africa likewise hath many exceeding great riuers, as namely Nilus, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">The riuers of Africa.</note> Senaga, Gambra, Zaire, Abagni, Tagassi, Coluez, Coauo, Cuama, and Maniche, or Rio del spirito santo, all which are in a manner of the same qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and disposition; for with their yeerlie in undations they doe most won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfullie fatten and enrich the soile of the territories adioyning. Nilus the<note place="margin">Nilus.</note> most famous riuer of the world, diuiding Egypt in the midst, and with his ouerflowes making it most fruitefull, continueth in his yeerely increase for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie daies, and forty daies in decrease; to wit, from the seuenteenth of Iune to the sixt of October: and this riuer after a mightie long course through E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia and Egypt, dischargeth his streames into the Mediterran sea. The riuer of Niger, running through the land of Negros, called of old (as Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus<note place="margin">Niger.</note> supposed) by the naturall inhabitants Astabus, and (according to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molius) Hued Nijar in the Arabian toung, is now esteemed by Paulus Ioui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us to be Gambra, and by Cadamosta the riuer of Senaga; but that both of them are deceiued, it is euident out of the description of Sanutus, who put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe the two foresaid riuers seuerallie, and thinketh Niger to be that which is now called Rio grande. This riuer taketh his beginning, as some thinke, out of a certain desert to the east, called Seu, or springeth rather out of a lake, and after a long race, falleth at length into the western Ocean. It increaseth also, for the space of fortie daies like Nilus, and is for so long space decreasing about the verie same time; by which inundation it bringeth such fruitfulnes vnto all the land of Negros (certain mountaines onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) as no place in the world can be imagined more fertile. Senaga or Canaga, a most notable riuer, called, as some thinke, Baratis by Ptolemey, and for the length therof, and manifold strange creatures therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, comparable to Nilus, seuereth by his winding chanel the barren and naked soile, from the greene and fruitefull. Moreouer it maketh a separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene nations of sundrie colours: for the people on this side are of a dead ash-colour, leane, and of a small stature; but on the farther side they are exceeding blacke, of tall and manly stature, and very well proportioned: howbeit neere vnto the riuer on either side, they are of a meane colour, complexion, and stature betweene both the aboue mentioned. It falleth
<pb n="5" facs="9"/>
into the sea by two mouthes, the principall whereof is about a mile broad, vp into the which the sea entreth almost 60. miles. It springeth (according to <hi>Iohn Barros</hi>) out of two lakes (the greater whereof is now called the lake of Gaoga, but heretofore by <hi>Ptolemey Chelonidae paludes,</hi> and the lesser <hi>Ptole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey</hi> calleth <hi>Nubaepalus</hi>) as also out of a riuer named by <hi>Ptolemey</hi> Ghir. This riuer of Senaga hath great variety of strange fishes, and other creatures that<note place="margin">These two ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Senaga and Gambra are not certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be maine riuers of themselues, or branches and mouthes of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> liue in the water, as namely, sea-horses, crocodiles, winged serpents, and such like: neere vnto it also are great store of Elephants, wilde bores, lyons, and leopards. Gambra or Gambea a very great riuer, lying betweene Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naga and Niger, and esteemed by <hi>Sanutus</hi> to be that which <hi>Ptolemey</hi> called Stachir, fetcheth his originall from the lake of Libya, and from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines which <hi>Ptolemey</hi> assigneth to the riuer of Niger: this riuer in greatnes and depth exceedeth Senaga, and hath many vnknowne riuers falling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, and bringeth foorth all kindes of liuing creatures that Senaga doth. In the midst of this riuer standeth the Isle of Elephants, so called, in regarde of<note place="margin">The isle of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants.</note> great numbers of those beasts. The riuer Zaire beginneth out of the same lake from whence Nilus springeth: this being one of the greatest riuers of all Africa, and vtterly vnknowne vnto ancient writers, containeth at the mouth eight and twentie miles in bredth, hauing a very safe harbour for ships to ride in: also there are many and great Islands in the chanell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and sundrie riuers do fall thereinto, the principall whereof are Vumba, Barbela, Coanza, and Lelunda: in briefe, this riuer Zaire running through<note place="margin">These two ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Cuama and Magnice (according to Philippo Piga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetta) spring both out of the great lake and are not bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of one riuer.</note> the kingdome of Congo, disgorgeth it selfe into the maine Ethiopian sea. Out of the same lake, which is the very fountaine of Nilus, springeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notable and famous riuer, which after a long race toward the south and east, is diuided into two branches: the northerly branch, which is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great (for it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> fixe great riuers thereinto, and is nauigable for the space of seuen hundred miles) being properly called Cuama, and the other branch more southerly, which is verie great also, being named Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich or Magnice, or Rio del spirito santo.</p>
   <p>The promontories, capes, or headlands of Africa be verie many, the most<note place="margin">The promonto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or capes of Africa.</note> famous and principal wherof are, The cape of Buena esperança, or good hope, Cabo verde, and Cabo de los corrientes. The cape of Buena esperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ça<note place="margin">Cabo de buena esperanza.</note> or good hope is the extreame southerly point of all Africa, being a most renowmed and dangerous promontorie, which in the yeere one thousand foure hundred nintie seuen was the second time discouered by Vasco da Gama at the commandement of Don Emanuel king of Portugal: this cape the mariners were woont to cal the lion of the Ocean, and the tempestuous cape, by reason of the ruffling and roring of the windes, which they found there for the most part very boisterons: for the sea thereabout is exceeding rough, by reason of the continual fury of the windes; neither will any naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatours touch vpon the cape, except they be enforced by meere necessitie. Cabo verde or The greene head-land, is esteemed by some to be the same<note place="margin">Cabo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> which <hi>Ptolemey</hi> calleth <hi>Promontorium Arsinarium,</hi> &amp; is compassed on either
<pb n="6" facs="10"/>
side by the riuers of Senega and Gambra. Cabo de los corrientes, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise<note place="margin">Cabo de los cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientes.</note> called the cape of San Sebastian, stretcheth foorth it selfe right ouer against the south ende of the great Isle of Madagascar: it is a cape well knowne, by reason it is so dangerous to double, which the Moores durst not passe for a very long time.</p>
   <p>And heere as concerning the strange beasts, fishes, serpents, trees, plants, and roots of Africa, as likewise touching the diseases, whereto the African people are most subiect; and the varietie of languages (excepting the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daean, Egyptian, Turkish, Italian, and Spanish toongs) which are now and haue beene of ancient times spoken in Africa; I refer the Reader to the first and last bookes of <hi>Iohn Leo,</hi> and to other places, where they are at large and purposely intreated of.</p>
   <p>Moreouer this part of the worlde is inhabited especially by fiue princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall<note place="margin">The inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Africa.</note> nations, to wit, by the people called Cafri or Cafates, that is to say out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawes, or lawlesse, by the Abassins, the Egyptians, the Arabians, and the Africans or Moores, properly so called; which last are of two kinds, namely<note place="margin">The diuersitie of religions in Africa.</note> white or tawnie Moores, and Negros or blacke Moores. Of all which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions some are Gentiles which worship Idols; others of the sect of Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met; some others Christians; and some Iewish in religion; the greatest part of which people are thought to be descended from <hi>Cham</hi> the cursed son of <hi>Noah;</hi> except some Arabians of the linage of <hi>Sem,</hi> which afterward passed into Africa. Now the Arabians inhabiting Africa are diuided into many seuerall kinds, possessing diuers and sundrie habitations and regions; for some dwell neere the sea shore, which retaine the name of Arabians; but others inhabiting the inland, are called Baduini. There bee likewise infinite swarmes of Arabians, which with their wiues and children, leade a vagrant and roguish life in the deserts, vsing tents in stead of houses: these are notable theeues, and very troublesome both to their neighbour-inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and also to merchants: for which cause trauellers and merchants dare not passe ouer the African deserts alone, but onely in Carouans, which are great companies of merchants riding, and transporting their goods vpon their camels and asses: who go very strong, and in great numbers, for feare of the said theeuish Arabians.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ptolemey</hi> in his fourth booke of Geography diuideth Africa into twelue<note place="margin">The ancient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision of Africa by Ptolemey; and a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with the moderne names.</note> regions or prouinces: namely, Mauritania Tingitana, Mauritania Caesari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ensis, Numidia, Africa propria, Cyrenaica, Marmarica, Libya propria, AEgyptus superior, AEgyptus inferior, Libya interior, AEthiopia sub AEgypto, &amp; AEthiopia interior.</p>
   <p>Mauritania Tingitana, the most rich and beautifull couutrey of Africa,<note place="margin">Mauritania Tingitana, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all one with the kingdomes of Maroco and Fez.</note> so named of the citie Tingis, which we at this day call Tanger, was some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times also (as <hi>Plinie</hi> witnesseth) called Borgundiana: moreouer others haue called it by the names of Mauritania Sitiphensis, Hispania Transfretana, and Hispania Tingitana: but <hi>Solinus</hi> termeth the same Mauritania inferior. The inhabitants were of old named by the Graecians Maurusij, and by the
<pb n="7" facs="10"/>
Romaines Mauri, but the Spaniards at this present terme them Alarabes. In this part of Africa are now contained two stately kingdomes, namely the kingdome of Maroco, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the kingdome of Fez; both which are enuironed with the mountaines of Atlas, the Ocean and the Mediterran seas, and to the east with the riuer of Muluia.</p>
   <p>Mauritania Caesariensis, named according to the citie of Caesaria,<note place="margin">Mauritania Caesariensis cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Tremizen, and Aiger.</note> which was so called after the name of <hi>Claudius Caesar,</hi> at this present bearing the name of Tiguident or Tegdemt, which worde in the Arabian toong signifieth ancient; was by <hi>Victor Vticensis,</hi> termed Mauritania maior; by <hi>Strabo</hi> Massilia, and Massaesilia, and the inhabitants thereof by <hi>Plinie</hi> Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saesuli. At this present it containeth the kingdome of Tremizen, as <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias Niger,</hi> and <hi>Giraua</hi> are of opinion.</p>
   <p>Numidia the ancient, called in the time of <hi>Ptolomey,</hi> The new, but by<note place="margin">Numidia the ancient, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Bugia, Constantina, Bona, Mezzab, &amp;c.</note> the Greekes (as <hi>Plinie</hi> testifieth) Metagonitis, and the inhabitants thereof Numidae, and Nomades; is that region which lieth betweene The great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and the riuer Megerada, ouer which countrey king <hi>Masinissa</hi> bare rule. It containeth now (as I coniecture) the prouinces of Bugia, Constantina, Bona, and Mezzab. Howbeit at this present we vnderstande by Numidia that region which lieth betweene the mountaines of Atlas and the Libyan deserts, called by <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> and <hi>Marmolius</hi> Biledulgerid, or the lande of Dates, bicause this is the onely region for plentie of Dates, in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica.</p>
   <p>Africa propria, situate vpon the Mediterran sea, betweene the regions<note place="margin">Africa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> all one with the kingdome of Tunis.</note> of old Numidia, and the Cyrene, is called by <hi>Plinie</hi> Zeugitania, who diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it into the ancient and the new. At this present it is the kingdome of Tunis, for it containeth Byzacium, which by <hi>Strabo</hi> is accounted a part of Africa propria. The head of this prouince in times past was Carthage, whereof at this present there are nothing but ruines extant.</p>
   <p>Cyrene, or Cyrenaica, by <hi>Plinie</hi> called Pentapolis, and by the Hebrews<note place="margin">Cyrene now called Mesrata.</note> Lebahim, is esteemed by <hi>Giraua</hi> to be at this present called Corene, and by <hi>Andrew Theuet,</hi> Assadib: but <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> and <hi>Marmolius</hi> name it Mesrata.</p>
   <p>Marmarica is called by <hi>Plinie</hi> Mareotis, and Libya: howbeit at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent<note place="margin">Marmarica comprehended in the desert of Barcha.</note> the desert of Barcha, described by <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> in his sixt booke, containeth a great part of Cyrenaica, and all Marmarica.</p>
   <p>But Libya propria, retaineth till this present the name of Libya, and is<note place="margin">Libya propria, called Sarra.</note> that part which the Arabians call Sarra, which worde signifieth a desert.</p>
   <p>Both the ancient Ethiopias are now possessed by the Abassins, vnder<note place="margin">AEthiopia, now called Abassia.</note> the dominion of <hi>Prete Ianni.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Egypt retaineth euen till this day, the ancient name.</p>
   <p>The best moderne diuision of Africa, for these our times is to adde vnto the foure general partes, Barbaria, Numidia, Libya, and the land of Negros, set downe by Iohn Leo, three other generall partes to wit, Egypt; the inner or the vpper Ethiopia, containing Troglodytica, Nubia, and the empire of Prete Ianni; and the lower, or the extreme Ethiopia, stretching from the
<pb n="8" facs="11"/>
said empire along the sea-coast, and through the Inland euen to the Cape of Buena Esperança.</p>
   <p>Thus much of Africa in generall. Now it remaineth that we briefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe in particular all the principall maine landes, and islands, (vndescribed by <hi>Iohn Leo</hi>) which thereto belong, or adioyne; beginning first with the Red sea one of the chiefe limites of Africa, and from thence shaping our course along the easterne or farthest quarters thereof, through the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Prete Ianni,</hi> the lande of Zanguebar, the empires of Mohenemuge, and Monomotapa, and the region of Cafraria: and then, hauing doubled the cape of Buena esperança, range we along the westerne partes by the kingdomes of Angola, Congo, Anzichi, Benin, Ghinea, and by the capes of Sierra Leona, Capo verde, and the castle of Arguin, till we haue brought our selues to finish our course, vpon the most southwesterne partes of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie, from whence our author <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> beginneth his.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>