<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108677_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19310</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5724</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108677</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The copies of certaine discourses, which were extorted from diuers, as their friends desired them, or their aduersaries driue them to purge themselues of the most greeuous crimes of schisme, sedition, rebellion, faction, and such like, most vniustly laid against them for no subscribing to the late authoritie at the first sending thereof into England : in which discourses are also many things discouered concerning the proceedings in this matter abroad</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walker, James, Heirs of, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 186, that is 182, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He differences and disagreements are such, which in these fewe yeares last past haue bred, and daily grow to more and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in that kind, to so great a disgust of all sincere Catholickes, not onely here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land but also in the principall, if not in all the parts of Christendome, whither the worthie fame of their memorable acts for the resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their natiue Country vnto the Catholicke faith hath come, that it is high time to giue them some taste of these matters, who are so disgusted, by laying before them the true cause, and grounds of this lamentable dissention, and to discouer how colourably the common enemie of God, and his Church, hath proceeded to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance first of Gods Priests, then to the mutual dislike of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes among themselues, and of such Priests as against whom by wrong informations they are violently led, and let not to vse both tongue and penne in most vngratefull manner.</p>
   <p>Some, being asked by others what might be the cause of so great a strife among the Priestes, haue simply answered that the cause is, for that the Priests being but secular men will not humble themselues, or be directed or gouerned by the Iesuites, who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious; but what truth soeuer is in this cause, of all other it must not be giuen, for such a subiection, euen in the eares of those who desire it, soundeth so absurdly, that they endeuour rather to haue it, then to heare of it, and both M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> in his Letters to the Cardi. <hi>Caietan</hi> dated the 10. of Ianuary 1596. and F. <hi>Parsons</hi> in his Letters against M. Doctor <hi>Bish:</hi> and M. <hi>Ch:</hi> dated the 9. of October 1599. labour to put this conceit out of mens minds, how euidently soeuer the practise in <hi>Wisbitch</hi> to make Fa. <hi>Weston</hi> the Iesuite superiour ouer the secular Priests (who then were in
<pb facs="3"/> durance for the Catholicke faith: pursued both by the knowne, and couert Iesuites, and all other their fauourites doth proue it, as also a Libell giuen abroad by the Authour thereof himselfe, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish others to beware of such Priests (and by no meanes to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dealing with them in spirituall matters, euen to the disturbing of them out of their places of residence) as vnfit guides for soules, who had not a dependance of the Iesuites. And not long since another of their fauourites letted not to say, that those Priests who are not vnder the Iesuites gouernment are no better then the Ministers; Many more proofes may be made hereof out of the speeches of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other their fauourites, who giue counsell to all that are afflicted in these turmoyles to submit themselues to the Iesuites.</p>
   <p>Other some, (who perceiue well, that, if this should be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be the true cause of so scandalous a schisme in Gods church, it would redound to the eternall disgrace, &amp; infamie of such, as, by whom they hauing conceiued some foolish hope of preferment, they had rather that they should indeed beare the sway, &amp; haue the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Cleargie (although it were vnderhand) then be said either to seeke it, or to haue it) giue out that the cause of this diuision among the Priests is, for that some Priests mooued either with ambitiō, or desire of contradiction, will not subiect themselues vnto their lawfull superiour appointed by his holinesse, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in authoritie ouer them by his Breue sent into England for that purpose: and these haue from time to time both written, and maintained in most iniurious manner (to possesse the more perfectly such as are too readie to thinke no calumniation too greeuous euen against those who haue best deserued of them) that these Priests are schismatickes, seditious, rebellious, &amp;c. euen to the diuiding for this cause of parents and their children, men and their wiues, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and sisters, and whole housholds, while the one retaining that reuerend respect of their long knowne, and tried ghostly fathers, for learning, wisedome, and vertue, is assailed by the other with these most wicked suggestions, and false calumniations, and forced either to liue a discontented life, or to break friendship; and (against their owne consciences) make semblance at the least that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hardly of such as they very well perswade themselues wil not
<pb facs="3"/> commit so great offence against God, and his Church, in whose de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence they haue spent many yeares, and remaine still resolute to shead their dearest bloud.</p>
   <p>That therefore no errour be hereafter in any man, who will not too much affect ignorance in such things as concerne not onely his particular good but the Common cause of God, &amp; his Church (which whiles the Cleargie liueth at some variance in an euill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Countrey, cannot doubtlesse but be very greatly preiudiced therby) it is thought expedient, yea necessarie, that the cause of this dissentiō be with truth, and sinceritie declared, &amp; made knowne to the world, that our actions and the reasons thereof being weighed with equall ballances, truth may take place, the offerers of the wrong may be discouered, the vniustly afflicted may be relieued, and that ease (at the least by these meanes) may be procured, which would not come of so long sufferance.</p>
   <p>The strife, and dissention at this day too great, and scandalous in England, is maintained by the Arch-priest, the Iesuites, &amp; their adherents, against those Priests who did forbeare to subiect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnto the Arch-priest constituted in authoritie ouer all the Seminary Priests in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> by a Cardinall, who was Protector of the English Colledge at <hi>Rome,</hi> and afterwards honoured with the title of Protector of <hi>England,</hi> for the which forbearing to subiect themselues at the first making knowne of this authoritie, the Priests were accused of schisme, sedition, faction, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, &amp;c. All which calumniations were forgiuen by the Priests so grieuously iniuried, and a peace made to the great comfort of all Catholiques, when his holinesse Breue was presented vnto them, but this peace was soone after broken by the meanes of the Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, who reuiued the same calumniations against the Priests, and by the Arch-priest, who did not onely auerre the assertions of the Iesuites, but published also that he had receiued a resolution from the mother Citie (to vse his tearmes) which avowed that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusers of the authoritie (noting by this phrase the Priests who did forbeare for a time vpon causes seeming iust to them to accept thereof) were Schismatickes. So that the cause of this diuision now in England, is not for any resistance in the Priests against the
<pb facs="4"/> superioritie, as many forward and euill taught people perswade themselues, &amp; cry out against the priests, that they are disobedient. But the cause of this diuision is, for that the Priests will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that in the time of their forbearance to subscribe to the authoritie (which was no longer then vntill they sawe the Breue) they were factious, seditious, rebellious, Schismatickes, enormiously disobedient, in continuall mortall sinne, practising their function in irregularitie, and pretending to absolue from sinne without facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or iurisdiction meete therevnto, worse then South-sayers and Idolaters, &amp;c. If therefore sufficient reasons may be giuen why the Priests did forbeare to subiect themselues before they sawe any Letters from his holinesse concerning this authoritie, it will both appeare how greatly they haue bene iniuried both by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priest, Iesuites, and their euill nurtured children, and how necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie this course of publishing in this sort, is for the purging of the other Priests from those slaunderous speeches; and here by the way do we aske of those pious Catholiques, (for so they must be tearmed howsoeuer they deserue it,) when they charge, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade themselues that they choake the Priests with disobedience, what it is, that they meane by this disobedience, if they meane ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that the Priests do not acknowledge M. <hi>Black.</hi> for their Arch-priest and superiour, they may if it so please them correct this their vnderstanding, and from henceforth either beleeue that euery man dooth acknowledge him, or else name who doth not, and let him in particular be called in question for it: for this generall prattle that they are disobedient is so vnsauourie a shift, vnlesse they could discend to particulars, that a man with litle honestie would quickly perceiue how it doth taint his breath:</p>
   <p>If by disobedience in the Priests they do meane the not yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or conforming their vnderstanding to the Arch-priest his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, they exact this obedience to the Arch-priest either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that he is learned, or because that he is a superiour, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these respects conuince any such matter, as that the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to be so conformable should bring with it schisme, sedition, fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, rebellion, &amp;c. Not the first, which is in regard of his learning. For although that many in England for modestie sake onely make
<pb facs="4"/> no comparisons with him for his learning, yet without offence we may say that there are many beyond the seas farre his betters, and much more learned, who haue decided this question for vs against him, so that the conceit only of being an Arch-priest, or in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is left for them to iustifie these most iniurions calumniations against vs. If then they exact this obedience in Priests to the Arch-priest, in respect that he is a superiour, and because that he is a superiour they imagine that euerie man who will not thinke as he thinketh, and do what he commaundeth is a Schismaticke, a rebell, factious, seditious, &amp;c. These who are so ignorant must be taught, and such as are contented at this time to make shewe of so grosse ignorance, must be put in mind that authoritie is not an infallible rule of truth in all who haue authoritie, and consequently that no man is bound in all things to beleeue or execute what eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man in authoritie ouer him shall put vpon him. In how many things not onely Arch priests but their superiours also the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, and other of higher degree haue done amisse, and swar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the truth? and who vpon earth is warranted from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring but one, and not he in all things? how absurdly then should this point be vrged that the Priests are Schismatickes, rebellious, &amp;c. for not conforming themselues in their vnderstanding to an Archpriest? And if the simpler sort of Catholiques cannot vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand this reason sufficiently grounded vpon too many examples re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in all Ecclesiasticall Histories, we would demaund of them, when they are commaunded to doo that by such as are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie vpon their alleageance, which in conscience they cannot doo, whether they be rebellious, factious, seditious, &amp;c. in not obeying this commaundement? or by what reason they may in not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing resolue their consciences, that they are not rebellious, &amp;c?</p>
   <p>Doubtlesse either they must confesse that they are rebellious, &amp;c. in not obeying the commaundment of those who are in authoritie, or else that it is not a sufficient proofe of rebellion that men do not in all things as others in authoritie commaund them, and to runne for refuge to cases, and particulars, is to flie touch for (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before spoken of this particular case which is in question a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs) we presse now onely this point, that authoritie is not so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible
<pb facs="5"/> a rule of truth in all to whom it is most it stly deriued, as those must be condemned as factious, rebellious, sediticus, schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, &amp;c. who will not conferme their vnderstandings to their conceits, who are in authoritie because they are in authoritie.</p>
   <p>These points, and those which hereafter will be touched, wee doo not set downe as men that would make sheepe iudges of their pastours, but as men desirous that their bretheren, and children, would not be so violently carried as they are, both against dutie, and charitie, but suspend their iudgements in these matters, and so beare themselues towards all, as they may hereafter make a good answere for their behauiour towards them, who haue after so deare a rate sought to saue their soules, and now request that their long sufferance be no preiudice vnto them, nor warrant to loosse tongues to enlarge themselues with contumelious speeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them whose cause the discourses following wil both conuince all, who are desirous not to be misled in a matter of so great conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that it is iust, and that they haue also iust cause to publish the same for the better instruction of such as with whom they may not be suffered or admitted to conferre about it, yet without touch of any more then the matter it selfe, and occasions ministred doo most necessarily require.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all true hartie affection.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>