<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. EDWARD MEEDE one of the assistants of the most vvorthy companie of Merchants Aduenturers residing at Ham∣borough.</title>
           <author>Loe, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108789_Fr8_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16690</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. EDWARD MEEDE one of the assistants of the most vvorthy companie of Merchants Aduenturers residing at Ham∣borough.</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Songs of Sion : Set for the ioy of gods deere ones, vvho sitt here by the brookes of this vvorlds Babel, &amp; vveepe vvhen they thinke on Hierusalem vvhich is on highe. By W.L</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Hamburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 164, 100 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="83"/>
   <pb facs="83"/>
   <head>To his much esteemed good frend Mr. EDWARD MEEDE one of the assistants of the most vvorthy companie of Merchants Aduenturers residing at Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough.</head>
   <q>Grace in this vvorld, and ioy in the other.</q>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL happines in the lord Iesus. I present vnto you a part of Ieremies Lamentations meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrased. You may see herein my true hart vnto you all. In the midst of lamentable discōtents I tuned my soule, tongue, &amp;
<pb facs="84"/>
pen to the land of god. And the rather in these lamentations for that they sorted some vvhat to my retired meditations. One tyme, or other all men are not as they vvould be. It is the condition of gods children. Happie is that man that can vse gods scourge to his amen dement. The great modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of all things knovves his children fittest to be made palmes, to be spread vvith burthens, &amp; vvaights, &amp; not to be Oliues. That so vve might more thinke of our victorie, then of our rest. It is enoughe for vs that vve shall once triumph in heauen, &amp; rest for all. To this holy rest, and eternall tranquillity god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giude
<pb facs="84"/>
vs all, into vvhose blessed keeping I recommend you in Christ sauing mercies. And rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours much deuoted.
W. LOE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>