<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108778_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06143</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16630</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108778</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The stratagems of Ierusalem : vvith the martiall lavves and militarie discipline, as well of the Iewes, as of the Gentiles. By Lodowick LLoyd Esquier, one of her Maiesties serieants at armes</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 352, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lphonsus <hi>king of</hi> Cicile <hi>(gentle Reader) was euer wont to say,</hi> Optimos consiliarios esse mortuos, <hi>meaning wise and profitable bookes, both at home and abroad.</hi> Lucullus <hi>one of the greatest captaines among the Romaines, and</hi> Philopomē <hi>of no lesse fame among the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; the one by reading</hi> Euangelus <hi>bookes, the other by reading</hi> Xenophon, <hi>became excellent souldiers. In so much that</hi> Cicero <hi>wondred that</hi> Epaminondas <hi>being such a singular Philosopher, should become so famous a Captaine. A great staine in</hi> M. Corilianus <hi>and in</hi> C. Marius, <hi>(though otherwise stout and valiant) not to be learned.</hi> Caesars <hi>Commentaries are at this time as much esteemed among the Turkes, as</hi> Homers <hi>Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ads were in auntient time among the Grecians. If these Polymar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies and Campmaisters confesse, that by holding a penne in the one hand, do profit as much, as by holding a sword in the other, or rather more; If</hi> Fabius <hi>weakned</hi> Hanibal <hi>more by delayes, then</hi> Marcellus <hi>did by the sword; If</hi> Fabritius <hi>wearied</hi> Pirrhus <hi>more by counsell, then all</hi> Rome <hi>could do by their warres, then it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly said, that</hi> Plura auspicijs &amp; concilijs, quam telis &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus geruntur. <hi>So that sometimes that saying of</hi> Cicero <hi>is true,</hi> Cedantarma togae; <hi>an other time the saying of</hi> Lysander <hi>is as true,</hi> Sileant leges inter arma. <hi>So all Empires ought to be,</hi> Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>olùm armis decorata, verumetiam legibus ornata. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Alexander Seuerus <hi>vsed both the sword and the penne, as well in decreeing of his lawes at home, as in mannaging of his warres abroad,</hi> Consilijs togae, &amp; militiae literatos adhibere. <hi>I speak not of such bookes which</hi> Plato <hi>compareth</hi> Adonijs hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, <hi>fresh and full of sauour in the morning, and withered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed at night, like the Elephants of</hi> India <hi>at their first sight in</hi> Asia, <hi>were so wondred at, that</hi> Antiochus <hi>the great, hauing but two, named the one</hi> Aiax, <hi>the other</hi> Patroclus, <hi>the names of two Princes: but when these Elephants became so common in</hi> Rome
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>and in</hi> Asia, <hi>that they were in euery Cōsuls triumph, they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but</hi> Boues Lucanias; <hi>a great change frō the names of Greeke Princes, to bee named oxen of</hi> Lucania. <hi>Bookes are no otherwise; for in auntient time, when bookes were yet rare, they were fellowes and companions with Kings &amp; Princes in courts, it so seemed by</hi> Alexander <hi>the great, who could not sleepe before he laid</hi> Homer <hi>with his dagger vnder his pillow; and by</hi> Scypio Affrican, <hi>who would not frō</hi> Rome <hi>to</hi> Carthage, <hi>without either</hi> Panetius <hi>or</hi> Polybius <hi>in his company: and now bookes being common, are so little regarded, rather bought for their golden tytles which the Printer giueth them for his sale, then for the matter therein by the Author written for the Revder, much like to</hi> Mithridates <hi>sword, whose scabbard was farre more precious and richer without, then the blade within. Of such bookes</hi> Plato <hi>speaketh,</hi> Qui subitò &amp; vno die nati, celerimè pereunt, <hi>therfore seldome seene in sight are most in request. The Ebaine tree which</hi> Pompey <hi>the great brought in his triumph into</hi> Rome, <hi>was more wondred &amp; gazed vpon, then all the braue shewes of the triumph besides: So fewe wise words out of a wise mans mouth, are more esteemed then heapes of wordes out of an vnwise mouth, like the Abderites Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, more desirous to heare fewe words out of</hi> Zeno <hi>the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers mouth, then of all the Athenians besides: and therfore</hi> Pau. Aemilius, <hi>after he had subdued the king and kingdome of</hi> Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia, <hi>wrote no more to the Senators, but</hi> Victus est Perseus. Caesar, <hi>after he had conquered king</hi> Pharnaces, <hi>wrote no more words, but</hi> Veni, vidi, vici: <hi>Like the Lacedemonians, whose wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and speeches were so short and briefe, that they would answer either Embassadors, friends, or foes, by writing or by mouth, in two or three words. And so with the like fewe words, I referre my selfe to the gentle disposition of the reader, rather to excuse my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in curtesie, then to accuse my goodwill wrongfully.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Lodowick Lloid.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>