<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worthy Company and whole body of No∣ble Souldiers, seruing in the Fift Cautionarie or Trayned Band of Midlesex, otherwise called Captayne Perts Company.</title>
           <author>Cooke, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108654_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19255</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5668</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worthy Company and whole body of No∣ble Souldiers, seruing in the Fift Cautionarie or Trayned Band of Midlesex, otherwise called Captayne Perts Company.</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The character of vvarre, or The image of martiall discipline : contayning many vsefull directions for musters &amp; armes, and the very first principles in discipline, the ground postures, all the military motions now vsed ... By Edvvard Cooke</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the worthy Company and whole body of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Souldiers, seruing in the Fift Cautionarie or Trayned Band of <hi>Midlesex,</hi> otherwise called Captayne <hi>Perts</hi> Company.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here a generall voyce warrants an approbation (worthie Gentlemen and Souldiers) there euery seruice is a Duty. The truth of it concernes &amp; inuites mee to write a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Epistle vnto you, and therein to extoll your worth: And none will discommend me for it, that either imitates your vertues, or would be praysed (as you) for worth. Your worth Implyes your rare parts: your rare part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (though many) may bee Epitomized in Foure.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> Your pronesse of mind to beare Armes. <hi>2.</hi> Your actiuenesse in all Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary motions. <hi>3.</hi> Your Subiugated wills to obey your Officers. <hi>4.</hi> Your Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and Pythian like affection one to another.</p>
   <p>The three first are rare, but the fourth and last is the most rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent; For as a Diamond fairely set in Gold, it giues luster to all the rest, and makes me stile you <hi>Philonida</hi> or <hi>Philonis,</hi> a bande of friends, or true friendship, or indeed the <hi>Holy band.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plutarch</hi> telleth of an holy band errected by one <hi>Gorgidas,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Pelopidas.</note> which did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist of three Hundred chosen men, entertayned by the state, &amp; kept within the Castle of <hi>Cadmea,</hi> called the Townes band, (as you the Kinges band:) This band was neuer broken nor ouerthrowne before the battaile of <hi>Chae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronea,</hi> where they were all slaine, found lincked together with cordes of silke arme in arme, Pikes sticking in their brests.<note place="margin">Philip King of Macedon. Father to Alexander the great.</note> King <hi>Philip</hi> their enemie shedding teares for them, and causing them to bee buried together, who in death would not be parted.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus the louing Holy Band,</l>
      <l>Fell by the <hi>Macedonians</hi> hand.</l>
      <l>Each one dying for his Frend,</l>
      <l>Keeping Friendship to the end.</l>
      <l>From whose ashes doth arise,</l>
      <l>You that them doth Sympathize.</l>
      <l>Neuer to dissolue together,</l>
      <l>Nor like God to liue for euer,</l>
      <l>For one by one, be sure to die,</l>
      <l>Time takes away, time will supply.</l>
      <l>And as he brought you to the Wombe,</l>
      <l>So backe hee leads you to your Tombe.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in life and death, <hi>Edward Cooke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>