<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Dering, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108150_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20303</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108150</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Dering, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sparing restraint, of many lauishe vntruthes, which M. Doctor Harding dothe chalenge, in the first article of my Lorde of Sarisburies replie. By Edward Dering student in Diuinitie. With an answere vnto that long, and vncourteous epistle, entituled to M. Juel, and set before M. Hardings Reioinder</title>
                 <author>Dering, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 114, 126, 121-216 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I first peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed this Reioinder of master Hardings, good Christian Reader, and savve in vvhat sort he made answere to M. Iuels Replie, I vvas grieued bothe for his own sake, that so many good giftes should be so yll applied, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for thy sake, least per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture his deceitful talk should beguile thee. I sawe on the one side, the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many, very daungerously bent to the loue of that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. On the other side much wordly wisdome, and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, countenaunced with suche a singulare boldnesse, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie, that without the especiall working of almighty God, I saw but litle hope of their further libertie, whose hart was set to receiue bondage. I coulde not be ignoraunt of the common prouerb, which I had heard so often, that <hi>fair words do make fooles faine,</hi> and I sawe againe, the subtile kinde of wryting, the sugred words, and entising speaches, which the enimie did vse to call away the simple vnto their destruction. These euils, the more perillous they were, so I thought it appertained vnto all good men, by what meanes possible to seke the spedier reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. And therefore in the great businesse, which that good Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop had in hande, whose happy Sermon did first so much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the enimie, I thought it some parte of my duetie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the gift that God had giuen me, so to make aunswere vnto the subtile aduersarie, and helpe to confirme in Gods truthe suche our simple brethren, as were falling away. Vpon
<pb facs="5"/>
this occasion I first toke vpon me to meddle with this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioinder. And when in reading it, I founde the whole nothing worthy answer, I did chuse only so farre to touche it, as I might bothe make a sufficient discharge of all suche blame, as was laid vpon maister Iuel, and shewe forthe an open, and vndoubted proofe of the residue of maister Hardings labour. Then I toke vpon me the aunswer of his long Epistle, written to M. Iuell, wherein he spareth nothing, saue only truthe, to allure his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the defence of those .225. vntruthes, whereby he would discredite Gods true religion. By this meanes, I did trust, that some would quench their longing thirst, to drinke of that gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cuppe, full of poison, and spirituall whoredomes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the whole grounde of their religion, to be nothing else but quarels, and wranglings, would at last runne forthe of their vngodly synagoges, and most frowarde assemblies. This labor I had finished more than .xij. monthes since, with so little dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that it made wiser men to consider better of it, whose wisdome was also a longer stay vnto me, least either my true meaning might run in blame for want of consideration, or my vnripe writing, might giue occasion to the enimie of triumph. But afterwarde remembring the good councell of <hi>Plutarche,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. So I, after some continuaunce of time, read ouer againe mine owne doing, in which as I could haue wished something altered, if I had sought the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of learning, so I sawe nothing but truthe maintained, and that in suche sort, as maister Harding might not wel contemne it. Then knowing assuredly, that bothe the defence of truthe might edifie the learned, and the manner of my wryting mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster grace vnto the godly Reader, I would no longer suppresse that, which being set abroade, might be fruitful. And vpon this aduise I deliuered it vnto the Printer: but after perusing it, I espied in the Printing many faultes, which the indifferent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, will not lay vpō me. Only for my discharge I thought good in this Epistle to admonishe thee of some, that by them thou mightest knowe whome to blame for the rest. In the .38. leafe
<pb facs="6"/>
for the house of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, thou shalt finde printed the churche of Rome, and straight after, modest, for immodest. In the .40. leafe, such language, for such laughing. In the .46. leaf, the same hath made vs free, for the sonne hath made vs free. In the .53. leafe, way for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay, fol. 64. corner it, for couer it. fol. 65. is not yet, for, is yet. In the .96. leafe, thou shalt find king Ionathas, yet good re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>der, I wrote king Iosaphat. If that fault had ben mine, I wold thē haue alowed M. Harding, naming the holy captain Iosue, for the Prophet Ose. fo. 98. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. fo. 100. expresse, for represse. fol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>od. alone hereof, for, in earth aboue hir. fol. 102. but you haue, for, but your churche hath fol. 104. cansabo, for, cantabo. fol. 111. Antonius, for, Antoninus. And after thou shalt finde <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, destruction, for distinction, could easily, for could not easily. These and suche other faultes escaped in the printing of my boke, as well in the wordes, as in the pointing, how many so euer thou shalt ascribe vnto me, so many iniuries thou shalt doe me. He is a simple scholer that can not write truely, and the pointing is not so difficult, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth any great learning, for other things what so euer shalbe founde blame worthy, the fault is mine owne, and wherein so<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the enimy shall finde his fault, I doubt not but I shall by Gods grace be able to defend it. The force of truth is such, that though the patrone be simple, yet she will defend hir self, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially suche truth, as hath made hir selfe so manifest. The truthe of God that standeth vpon a hill, and may be seene of all men, the truth, that shineth as a light in a darke place, and as the day starre, arising in our heartes, that truthe, whose glorious beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath darkned the painted, and deceiueable lokes of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whore of Babilon. It is now no mastery, sith we know God, to know him, that lifteth vp himself against God, sith we know Christ to know Antichrist, sith we know Peter, to know Peters forged successoure. And for as much as to this issue al our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie is come, that what right, or authoritie so euer the Pope chalengeth, he maketh his whole claime from Peter, and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists
<pb facs="6"/>
themselues will defende him no further, but so farre as he succedeth Peter, I will speake a little of Peters bishoprike of Rome, so farre as the scriptures shall be my warrant. Consider thou of it, good christian Reader, that shall be said, and if thou see, that all the glorying of Peters being at Rome, is but a fasing out of an impudent he, then iudge what is their other religion. First, here I must forwarne thee, that as a lie can not long agree with it selfe, so in all this matter thou shalt hardly finde in all pointes two popishe chronicles agree togither. So that what so euer I wryte, as touching the exacte computation of yeres, there must needes be many against me. Therefore in that I will not striue, only I will wryte that which is certaine, and shall haue as I said, either some warrant of scripture, or shall be agreed on, by the consent of all ages. Our sauioure Christ was crucified for our sinnes, the .18. yeare of Tyberius, as by all histories it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest. Peter is said to be put to deathe in Rome, the last yeare of Nero, so Peter liued after Christ, vnder Tyberius .v. yeare, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula 4. yeare, Claudius .13. yeare, Nero. 13 yeare. In all .36. yeares and odde monthes according to the raigne of the saide Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roures, in these .36. yeares and odde moneths, they vvryte of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thus. He vvas bishop ▪4. yeares in the East partes .7. yeares at Antioche, and .25. yeares at Rome, vvhere at last he died. Heere this fable doeth almost bevvray it selfe, suche hasty enstallings, and so many translatings out of one bishopprike into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth not vvell agree vvith oure sauiours vvordes, that they should haue affliction in the vvorlde. But let vs searche the scriptures, and trie hovve these Bishopprikes vvil stande. After that our Sauioure is ascended, they goe into Ierusalem all the Apostles togither, they choose Mathie the Apostle.<note place="margin">Act. 1.12. Act. 2.4.</note> After fiftye dayes they receiue the holy Ghost, Peter conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth many.</p>
   <p>After certaine dayes Peter,<note place="margin">Act. 3.1.</note> and Iohn goe vppe in to the Temple, they heale the lame, they are put in prisone, they are forbidden to preache anye more in the name of Iesus,
<pb facs="7"/>
then they returne vnto the other Apostles, and tary many daies togither,<note place="margin">Act. 4.18. Act. 5.12.</note> working many miracles amōg the people, in so much that the Cities round about resorted daily to Ierusalem, to haue their sick, and diseased healed. Then again, the Apostles are put in prison, and God deliuereth thē, and many dayes they preach in the temple, and in euery house. After this came a great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution against the Church at Ierusalem, in so much, that they were all dispearsed sauing the Apostles.<note place="margin">Act. 8.1.</note> Then at the laste after many dayes, Peter is sent out of Ierusalem into Samaria, where he preacheth in diuers townes about. Thus farre good Reader, thou seest plainly Peter is no bishop, nor yet in any speciall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, when the other Apostles sende him out to preache. Then he returneth againe to Ierusalem, and this is one yeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of our sauioure Christ, as the histories do all agree in reporting the conuersion of S. Paule, which was nowe done, as appeareth. Act. 9. This is the yeare of our Lord .35. In the yere of our Lord .38. He dwelleth in Ierusalem. Gal. 1.18. Likewise in the yere of our Lorde .46. he is imprisoned at Ierusalē. Act. 12.2. Againe in the yeare of our Lord .48. he is at the councel holden in Ierusalem. Act. 15.7. from that day forward, he giueth his faith vnto Paule, and Barnabas, that he will be an Apostle, not to the Romaines, but to the Iewes. Gal. 2.9. vvhich truely he accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hed euen vntill his death, and doubtlesse neuer came at Rome. Now christian reader, seing the scripture lieth thus, that Peters aboade in Ierusalem, after the conuersion of S. Paule <hi>Anno Domini</hi> .35. is recorded .iij. seuerall times. And after the last time a couenaunt made, that he woulde continue among the Iewes. If I shall proue vnto thee, that these seuerall times are rightly numbred, according to the yeare of the Lorde, that is, that the first time was the .38 yeare, the seconde time, the .46. yeare, the third time, the .48. yeare, and then in the meane while betwene the .35. yeare, and the .38. likewise the .38. and the .46. and betwene the .46. and .48. that Peter was not in Rome, last of all, that he was true of his promise, and after the .48. yeare, came not at Rome, then I trust thou wilt confesse with me, that Peter was
<pb facs="7"/>
neuer .25. yeares Bishop of Rome. But that all poperie, as it is in it selfe nothing but lies, so it is grounded wholly, and altogither vpon lies. First it is agreed vpon by all, &amp; the thing is plaine in it self, Paule was conuerted the yere of our Lord .35. Thē Paule himself writeth thus.<note place="margin">Galat. 1.18. Act. 9.26.</note> After three yeres I came to Ierusalē to see Peter, and abode in his house .xv. dayes, so this was the .38. yere of our Lord, when Peter is first in Ierusalē. When he was after im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned at Ierusalem, Act. 12.2. that it was the .46. yeare of our Lorde, it is proued thus. The countreis about▪ that is, Tyre,<note place="margin">Act. 12.20. <hi>Suetonius in Claudio. Euse. Beda. Orosius. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> and Sidon, were then nourished with the kings prouision. But that prouision Claudius made, in the great famine▪ the .4. yere of his raigne, which was the yeare of our Lord .46. Againe immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, the scripture mēcioneth <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 12.23.</note> the death of Herode. But He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode was made king in the first yeare of Caligula, and raigned 7. yeare, so he died in the .4. yeare of Claudius. And consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as is said, the .46. yeare of our Lorde. Peter being now in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son at Ierusalem, and thus the seconde time, that Peter is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned to be in Ierusalem, is the .46. yeare of Christ. Afterward, when the Apostles helde the councell in Ierusalem,<note place="margin">Other number these .14. yeres from his firste going to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem, and so this councell is holden▪ An. 51.</note> that it was the .48. yeare of our Lord, it is proued by S. Paule, who after he had mentioned his conuersion, and his first going to Ierusalem, whereof we spake before, he saith thus. <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2.1.</note> Then after .14. yeres, I went vp again to Ierusalem. So it was the .48. yeare of our Lord, this being .14. yeare after his conuersion, and he conuerted in the .35. of our Lorde, and thus it is proued, that in the yeares of our Lord .35.38.46.48. Peter was in Ierusalē. Now it resteth to proue, that in the meane space Peter came not to Rome. That he was not at Rome betwene the .35. and the .38. yeare, I haue this profe. In the yeare of our Lorde .37. Pilate wrote his letter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vnto Tiberius the Emperor of Christ, and of his doctrine,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eus. li.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. <hi>Tert. in apol. Orosius. Nauclerus. fol.</hi> 512.</note> and how the Iewes accompted him a God, whereby the Emperoure was so moued, that he wold nedes make Christ a God in Rome▪ If Peter had bene in Rome, Pilates letters had not ben necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Emperor should haue had better instruction. Thus in those three yeares Peter was not in Rome. Betwene the .38. yere,
<pb facs="8"/>
and the .46. yeare they say, suche is their impudencie, that Peter was Bishop all the while at Antioche. If it be so, then by their owne confession he was not at Rome. But the scripture is plain he was neither at Antioche, nor yet at Rome. And howe these 7. yeares are passed, marke, and thou shalt see. In the beginning of these .7. yeares, Peter goeth forth a preaching. First into all Iury, Galile, and Samaria, which wold require some cōtinuance. Afterward he goeth vp to the saints at Lidda,<note place="margin">Act. 9.32.</note> and there tarieth. From thence he goeth to Ioppe, and there tarieth <hi>dies multos,</hi> a long while.<note place="margin">Act. 9.39.</note> From thence he goth to Caesarea, and ther couerted Cornelius,<note place="margin">Act. 10.24.</note> the first gentile that euer he conuerted, as is plain by the scriptures, then he abideth certain dayes at Caesarea, all this well nigh .400. miles from Antioche: and now for profe he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no hast to Antioche,<note place="margin">Act. 11.2.</note> he commeth home againe to Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, where he is againe ioyned with the Apostles. And now the Apostle heare word, that certaine gentiles at Antioche are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, not by Peter, but by the disciples, that fled when Steuen was stoned.<note place="margin">Act. 11.22.</note> Act. 7.60. &amp; 8.1. Well did the holy ghost here name them that preached this while at Antioche, or else here had ben some coloure for Peters bishoprike. But marke further, when the Apostles heare this, to confirme the gentiles, they send to Antioche. But vvhome sende they? Peter? Sure they vvoulde haue done, had he then bene their bishop, but Peter abideth still in Ierusalem, and Barnabas is sent to Antioche, where he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth, after goth in to Tarsus to Paule, from thēce they come againe bothe to Antioche, and there tary afterwarde one whole yeare. About this time saith the scripture, Peter was put in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,<note place="margin">Act. 12.2.</note> which was as is proued, the yeare of our Lord .46. And that he continued in Ierusalem euer since Barnabas was sent to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche, we haue this coniecture. When he was deliuered out of prison, and knockt at Maries dores, Rhoade the maide knewe him by his voice.<note place="margin">Act. 12.15.</note> And so well, that the Disciples said she was madde, or else it was Peters angell. Yet were the thing neuer so incredible, she said she was sure it was euen he. This perfecte knowledge of a mannes voyce, required some continuaunce of
<pb facs="8"/>
acquaintaunce. And thus we are come to the .7. yeare of his bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprike of Antioche, in which time he yet neuer came at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche. Nowe the yeare of our Lord .46. the .4. of Claudius, he goeth from Antioche to Rome, and there is bishop .25. yeares, 2. months .8. dayes, from the .16. of Ianuary, to the .24 of March. Suche accompt I trow they make, that tell vs how many mile it is to heauen. But be it so, he is gone out of the prisone in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem .2000. mile of to Rome to be made bishop. If the story of dame Ioane were so incredible as this, maister Harding vvith some countenaunce might haue written against it. But let vs go foreward.<note place="margin">Act. 15.7. <hi>Orosius. lib.</hi> 7 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Suetonius. Nauclerus.</hi>
      </note> In the yeare of our Lorde .48. notwithstanding this posting to Rome, he is yet at Ierusalem. <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> And from hēceforth that he ment not to goe to Rome, but kepe his promise that he would continue among the Iewes, we haue this profe. First his othe where Iames, Peter, and Iohn doe sweare vnto Paule, and Barnabas, that they would execute their Apostleships among the Iewes. Which sure Peter woulde not haue done, if he had thought to haue gone to Rome, and all the Papists in the world shall neuer be able to ansvver it, iangle hovv they vvil, that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vvas bishop of Rome. He vvas not, he ment it not, he kept his promisse. Paule calleth him the Apostle of circumcision.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.11. Gal. 2.7. 1. Peter. 1.1. Iacob. 1.1. 1. Ioh. 2.24.</note> He vvas aftervvarde among the Ievves at Antioche, he vvry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth▪ his Epistle to the Ievves, that vvere straungers, and scatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red abroade in Asia, euen as Iames dothe to the tvvelue Tribes scattered among the nations, and Iohn to them that had heard and seene from the beginning, vvhich vvere the Ievves. Thus did those Apostles minde their promise, though vve talke of bishopprikes, vve knovve not vvhat. But bicause there are yet three and twenty yeares behinde, let vs as vve may, examine them by the scriptures. In the Actes vve read,<note place="margin">Act. 18.2. <hi>Orosius. lib.</hi> 7 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Suetonius. Nauclerus, &amp; alij.</hi>
      </note> that Priscilla and Aquila, and all the residue of the Ievves vvere banished out of Rome. But this vvas done the .9. yeare of Claudius. <hi>Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> .51. When now Peter should haue bene more than .5. yeare bishop in Rome. Thus yll may this fable agree vvith the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God. But let vs examine it further.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>About six yeares after this, and the beginning of the raigne of Nero, Paule wryteth his Epistle to the Romaines, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, for that he then caried vp to Ierusalem, for the pore saints there abiding, suche distribution as they of Macedonia and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia had gathered,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.26.</note> which was a little before Paules last going to Ierusalem, as most writers agree, in the last yeare of Claudius. And for profe it was so, now al things are quiet at Rome, Paule saluteth Priscilla, and Aquila, which in the .9. of Claudius were bothe banished, and the Actes doe specifie certaine yeares after, in which Paule and they were togither. So now being at Rome againe, it agreeth wel, that the Epistle to the Romains, was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten about the beginning of the raigne of Nero, and the yeare of our Lorde .56. at which time Peter was not at Rome, as may be proued aboue all gesses, and coniectures, out of the worde of God. First he saluteth diuers by name, and yet he speaketh not of Peter,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> a sure profe that Peter was not at Rome. Againe, he sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteth Andronicus, and Iunia, with this especial note, which are notable among the Apostles,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.7.</note> and were in Christ afore me. How muche more occasion had Paule, thus to salute and commende Peter, whome he calleth other where a piller of the Church, and who was not only before Paule,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> but before all men, sauing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew his brother, called to be a disciple. Nothing may be here answered, but that only, which is true, Peter was not at Rome. If these reasons seme not strong inoughe, then good Reader, loke in the .15. to the Romaines, thou shalt haue an other, which by no meanes may be shifted off. Thus he wryteth, I enforced my self to preache the gosple, not where Christ was named, least I should haue built vpon an other mannes foundation, but as it is vvritten,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> to vvhome he vvas not spoken of, they shall see him, and they that heard not, shall vnderstande him. Then he addeth, therefore also I haue bene oft let to come vnto you, by which words it is manifest, they had but weake maintenaunce of their faith, and the true Disciples had no long continuaunce among them. But how could this be, if Peter were .25. yeare, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop there. Again, he saluteth the houshold of Narcissus, which
<pb facs="9"/>
Narcissus saith, Ambrose vvas <hi>Presbiter eius ecclesiae,</hi> a chiefe ruler in that churche. and hovv coulde Paule here haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Peter, being <hi>Archpresbiter,</hi> the chiefe of all rulers, and Pope himselfe? Thus are vve past .xj. yeare of this Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprike, and yet vve can not once finde S. Peter in his dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse. In the yeare of our Lord .58. and the seconde of Nero, Paule commeth to Rome, and then Peter is not at Rome,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eusebius in chronico.</hi> Act. 28.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> as appeareth by this saying of the Scripture, vvhere the chiefe of the Ievves in Rome speake thus vnto Paule. We vvill heare of thee vvhat thou thinkest, for as concerning this secte, vve knovve that euery vvhere it is spoken againste. Then vvhen Paule had preached vnto them, and some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued, and some beleued not. The text saith, vvhen he had said these, the Ievves departed, and had great reasoning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them selues. Is it possible that Peter should now haue bene thirtene yeare bishop, and yet the chiefe of the Ievves that vvere there vvhen Paule came, had scarce any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of Christ▪ They may beleue it, that vvill nedes be deceiued. Tvvo yeare after this, vntill the yeare of our Lorde 60. the fourthe of Nero, Paule abideth in Rome. All vvhich while, vndoubtedly Peter came not once there, as may plain appeare, if thou reade the Epistles, vvhich Paule vvrote in Rome. To the Galathians he speaketh muche of Peter, and of his conuersation vvith him, about tvventy yeares paste, but of his present being at Rome, not one vvorde, and yet he speaketh of him to this purpose, to get the more credite vnto himselfe, vvhy then doeth he not name him, as novve present vvith him? In like case, vvryting to the Philippians,<note place="margin">Philip. 1.2.</note> he beginneth his Epistle thus, Paule and Timothie, vvhy coulde he not heere, haue begon Paule and Peter? Nay what folly vvas it to bring Peters testimonie many yeares past, vvhich novv might be doubted of, vvhen he might haue had his present, and most certaine vvitnesse, vvith subscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ovvne hande, to confirme his doctrine? Againe,
<pb facs="10"/>
he vvryteth thus vnto the Philippians, that many brethren in the Lord vvere boldned through his bandes,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.14.</note> and durste frankely speake the worde, if bandes would haue made them faithfull, no doubt Peter had long before, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, surely he would not haue shronke neither for chaines, nor prisones. It is his owne doctrine, that heere vnto we are called,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 2.21.</note> he coulde not so sone haue forgotten his owne good councell. Againe, Paule wryteth, he had no man like minded as Timothy was,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.20.</note> how coulde this be, if Peter had bene there? Againe he wryteth, he had only A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristarchus his prisone felow,<note place="margin">Col. 4.10.11</note> sure Peter would haue bene in prisone too, if he had bene in Rome. Againe, Marke, and Iustus,<note place="margin">Phil. 23.</note> are onely my felow workers, and shall we thinke that Peter was now bishop, yet would not helpe Paule in preaching? Read ouer all Paules Epistles, written in Rome, and if the spirite of truthe be within thee, thou wilt say Peter was not in Rome, yet now he shoulde haue bene euen in the floure of his bishoprike. Nowe are there on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lefte ten yeares behinde, in which likewise it shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, whether Peter were in Rome. At the latter ende of this ten yeare, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> .7d. Neronis .14. Paule commeth againe to Rome, and is againe imprisonned, whence he wryteth his seconde Epistle to Timothie, as Ierome, and Eusebius, and diuers other doe thinke. Then Peter is not in Rome. Only Luke is vvith me, saith S. Paule,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.11.</note> if this be true, vvhere then vvas Peter? Shall vve thynke he vvoulde not once see Paule a prisonner? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, at my first aunswering, no man assisted me, but all forsoke me.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.16.</note>
   </p>
   <p>O vnthankefull vvretches, and deseruing yll of Peter, that vvoulde novve thinke Peter vvere Bishoppe. But heere are nowe nine yeares, in the meane season, in vvhich it is sone proued, Peter coulde be no bishop. Paule reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that he had escaped out of the hands of Nero.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.17.</note> But what
<pb facs="10"/>
needed he, if that Peter could set quietly bishop? Seneca wryteth secretely epistles vnto Paule,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Seneca.</hi>
      </note> and Paule vnto Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca, but neuer a worde of Peter. Nero made proclamation that no man shoulde speake either to Christian, or to Iewe, and howe coulde then Peter be bishop?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Orosius lib.</hi> 7 <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> Nero when he had set the Citie on fire in the .9. yeare of his raigne, to auoid the enuye of so great a mischiefe, he layde all the fault vpon the Christians, whereof Tacitus, that wicked heathen, wryteth thus.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cornel. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus. lib.</hi> 15.</note>
      <hi>Repressa in praes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ns exitiabilis supersticio rursus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</hi> That wicked superstition, that was now well repressed, sprang vp againe. But is it like if Peter had bene then bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, that christianitie shoulde haue bene so quenched, that no man did scarce remember it? But be it that all this were true, let Peter become vnfaithfull, let him forget to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse Christ, and feede his flocke, were he neuer so vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet sure he coulde not be then bishop of Rome. For in the .10. yeare of his raigne,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sueton. in Nerone. Euseb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>Egesip. lib.</hi> 4.</note> Nero made suche great persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Christians, that in no place they coulde be sure, but euery where were drawne forthe vnto moste shamefull deathes, and this persecution continued .4. yeares without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termission, and how vvas Peter then a bishop? They had beastes skinnes put vpon them, and then were weryed with dogges, they laide them on heapes, and burnt them to giue light in the night time, they hong them vp quicke vpon gibbets: they practised all kinde of exquisite crueltye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, and yet for all this shall we thinke that Peter vvas bishop?<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.14.</note> I leaue here to speake of Peters ovvne epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, the last written a little before his death, what time this persecution shoulde haue bene in the greatest rage, yet Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doeth not so muche as once mention any suche thing. The former was writē about the .12. yere of Claudius, and by expresse words dated from Babilon, which thing bicause it is a most euidēt token, that Peter was thē no bishop of Rome,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note>
      <pb facs="11"/>
Therfore they make this glose vpon it. From Babylon, that is from Rome, and vvhat a miserable shift is this, in defence of Peters bishoprike, to confesse Rome to be Babylon? But Rome, as it is, it shal be Babylon, and their religion, as it is, it shall be the purple vvhore, and the Pope as he is, he shall be Antichrist, rather than they vvill lose this succession of Peter. And heere to make the fable perfect, they shut it vp vvith tvvo especiall lies.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eusebius. Hieronimus. Aegesippus Ambr. Epi. li.</hi> 5. <hi>ad aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium.</hi> Act. 7.58. <hi>In Epist. ad Gal. cap.</hi> 1.</note> The one, that Paule and Peter bothe died in one day. The other, that Christ met Peter flying avvay, and bad him goe back, and suffer death. As touching the first, vve reade of Paule vvhen he vvas conuerted, he vvas a yong man, and vvhen he vvent to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem to see Peter, Athanasius saith, he vvent for reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence▪ that he bare to Peters age. So it seemeth Peter vvas gray headed, vvhē Paule vvas but young. <note n="*" place="margin">Philip. 9.</note> About .25. yeres after Paule vvryteth to Philemon. Though I be, as I am, euen Paule an olde man. Then vvhat vvas Peter at these yeares? Yet Paule liueth after this ten yeare, and then wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of hym selfe,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.6.</note> that the tyme of his resolution is at hande. Paule had novv finished euen his naturall course, a very probable coniecture, that he outliued Peter. But this other vntruthe that vve speake of, is aboue all coniecture shamelesse, and vnreasonable. They saye that Peter the night before he shoulde suffer, fledde avvay, and as he vvas going, Christ met him, vvhome vvhen he had seene, Peter sayd vnto him, <hi>Domine, quò vadis?</hi> Maister, vvhether goest thou?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Egesip. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> Then christ made aunswere, <hi>Romam iterum cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifigi,</hi> to Rome that I may be crucified againe. Then Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perceiued that Christ spake of him, and so he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and vvas crucified, as if Peter him selfe had neuer taught vs, that the heauens must containe, and kepe Christ, vntill the time that all things be restored, vvhiche shall not be accomplished vntill the last day,<note place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> and thus endeth the fable of Peters bishoprike in Rome.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>Novv good christian Reader, thou consider of it, as the truthe shall moue thee, and vvay the Pope, and Papistry, vvhat it is. Searche the scriptures saith▪ our sauior Christ. For they doe beare vvitnesse of me.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.39.</note> But searche the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vvhile thou vvilt, thou canst not finde one line for the Popes supremacie, no title for proofe of Peters bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prike in Rome. A certaine argument, the Pope is not of Christ. And as this head, and vvell spring of all this ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, I meane the Pope him selfe, hath no vvarrant in the vvorde of God: so his religion, that it may be like him selfe, is altogether contrary, and beside the vvorde of God. What should I here recite all particulares? Searche the scriptures, thou shalt not finde neither Masse nor Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, Diriges, Trentals, Dispensations, Iubileis, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Pardones, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lgrimage, Holy water, Holy bread, Crucifixe, Rodes, Banners, Tapers, Sensors, Paxes, Pixes, Canopies, Copes Corporase, Vestments, Albes, Stoales, Tunicles, Saccaring, Eleuation, Altare, Altareclothes, Superaltaries, Howseling, Shriuing, Aneling, Dispeling, Creping, Halovving of Bels, Halovving of Churches, Halovving of Fountes, Monethes mindes, Lent, Vigill, Aduent, Praying to saintes, praying for the deade, praying in a straunge tongue, none other of the xxv. Articles, mencioned by maister Iuell. And vvhat shoulde I speake of all, that are almoste infinite. Reade their Portuise, and reade the Bible, thou shalt finde no leafe of agreement. And this none can denye, vvho so euer is most frovvardly bent. What resteth then, if vve loue God, and his holy vvorde, but that vve consider our vvayes, and see vvhether vve vvalke as he hathe taught vs. There is no heauen, but his dvvelling place, no vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto it but by his cōmaundements, and his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes no vvhere to be founde, but in the Scriptures, vvhich he hath left vs.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>Next vnto Gods glory, we haue nothing so precious, as the sauegarde of our owne soules. And where shall we finde the saluation of our soules, but in the vvorde of God? God graunt vnto thee his holy spirite, that thou mayest heare his worde, and keepe the same, to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his will, and the saluation of thine owne soule. Amen.</p>
   <closer>Farewell, <dateline>from Christes colledge in Cambridge, <date>the .iiij. of April. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1568.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lorde.</hi> Edward Dering.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="12"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>