<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right vvorshipfull Syr William Fitzwilliam Knight, late Lorde deputie of Irelande: A. Anderson the minister of Christes ho∣ly Gospell, vvisheth Christ our Lorde, vvith his vvhole merites.</title>
           <author>Anderson, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108500_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19265</idno>
           <idno type="STC">568</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108500</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right vvorshipfull Syr William Fitzwilliam Knight, late Lorde deputie of Irelande: A. Anderson the minister of Christes ho∣ly Gospell, vvisheth Christ our Lorde, vvith his vvhole merites.</title>
                 <author>Anderson, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie sermon, preached on Newe yeeres day last : before Sir William Fitzwilliam knight, late lord deputie of Irelande, Sir Iames Harrington knight, their ladyes and children, vvith many others, at Burghley in Rutlande. By the minister of God Anthony Anderson. Hereto is added a very profitable forme of prayer, good for all such as passe the seas: by the same author framed, and vsed in his aduentured iourney</title>
                 <author>Anderson, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <head>To the right vvorshipfull Syr William Fitzwilliam Knight, late Lorde deputie of Irelande: <hi>A. Anderson the minister of Christes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Gospell, vvisheth Christ our Lorde, vvith his vvhole merites.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>All vppon me (sayth God) in the day of thy trouble, and I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer thee. Greater troubles with lesse comfortes than in the raging Seas, can not be founde, as those with Dauid must confesse which occupie their busines in greate waters. This daungerous Iourney, as among many others ye are in the Lordes name to aduenture, so vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe this preparatiue to your godly hart, and by and with the same in assured hope of Gods assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce for his Christ, approche his mercy seate. The hast we haue, and gaping hope for Wester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly winds, will not permit long leysure, to proyue this sodayne frame. Take it (Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) as it is, and accept the good will of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, vse it at your neede to the Lordes prayse, and your present comfort, which is my harty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire. And I shall dayly pray the Lorde for you, and vs, that we may speedely imbarke, and safely arriue in Englande through Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes ayde, the master of our ship. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At <hi>Holme Patricke</hi> in Irelande. <date>
            <hi>17.</hi> October. <hi>1575.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships in <hi>Dom. A. Anderson.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>