<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Moffett, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108519_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19179</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5590</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108519</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Moffett, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true history of the ciuill vvarres of France, betweene the French King Henry the 4. and the Leaguers : Gathered from the yere of our Lord 1585. vntill this present October. 1591. By Antony Colynet</title>
                 <author>Colynet, Antony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 549, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Vlly</hi> (the glorie of the ancient <hi>Rome)</hi> defineth the historie to be a witnesse of time, and a remembrance of things that are past; this is to say somewhat, but not enough. For it is a witnesse and record of the execution of Gods iustice in reuenging the corrupt iudgements, vncleane affections, and wicked deedes of men, and of Gods good will and fatherly goodnes in defending, deliuering, and rewarding the iust. Therefore (Christian Reader) I haue to warne thee of three things; of the vse, order, and locution of this historie: desiring thee to reade this, not onely to delight thine affection in seeing this man doo prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously and commended for his prowesse and vertue, and another dispraised ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the desert of his actions; but specially to consider the presence of God in gouerning the one, and prospering him, in doing profitable things for the defence of a iust cause and his countrey: and the iudgement of God, which according to the threatnings of his law, doth leade the wicked to punishment: if not at all times and after all ill actions, yet most commonly and at length, alwaies doth make him swallow downe the dregges of his wrath. Feare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and keepe thy selfe within the bounds of that vocation, which the lawe of God hath prescribed thee.</p>
   <p>The greatest part of this Historie is translated out of French, which was set foorth concerning these affayres of the holy League, encreased much out of the seedes of actions, dispersed in the declarations, edicts, proscriptions, apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, aduertisements, agreements, articles and letters written by the Kings <hi>Henry</hi> the iij. and iiij. now raigning, and other noble men acquainted with the publique affayres and estate.</p>
   <p>The latter part of the Historie, to wit, from the death of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, is a gathering of such euents as haue been published from time to time. And as for the distressing of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the horrible famine there, I haue for the most part followed the report of <hi>Pedro Corneio</hi> a Spanyard, which was then in the citie during the siege thereof, which doth report it after a more incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible sort then I dare lay downe.</p>
   <p>Of such things which I doo suspect, I doo note the vncertaintie thereof by
<pb facs="5"/>
the word of report, following therein that famous Historiographer of our time <hi>Iohn Sleyden.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue written this Historie in forme of Annales, reducing the actions of euery seuerall yeare into a sundrie booke, saue onely the first, which is a colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the secret practises of many yeres, to bring that state to that confusion which we see it now. The new Popish Kalender hath brought some diuersitie in the date of dayes, moneths and yeares, some following one Kalender, and some another: yet I haue reduced it to the old so farre as I could do it.</p>
   <p>Forasmuch as the rebellion of the holy League is the greatest conspiracie that euer was heard of against all Christian Kings and Princes, threatning all of bondage and subuersion, and first put in vre in the kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> as most fit to receaue the same, by reason of the dissentions long cōtinued there, wrought by the vilest men and meanes that euer were heard of, hauing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted &amp; atchieued most haynous &amp; outragious murthers, I haue thought good to decke the parties with titles and ornaments fit for such deedes, to wit, with sharpe words to expresse more effectually the greatnes of the offences, protesting not to touch the noble families of Christendome, whom I reuerence, but the degenerating of them, who hauing put aside the robes of true Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, are become slaues of all treacheries and rebellions, and haue clothed them selues with dishonour and infamie: to the end that the Christian reader may by the signification of grieuous Epithetes, comprehend the greatnes of such transgressions as doo boyle in such men, and learne to auoyde the societie of all damned congregations of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>