<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTVOVS gen∣tlewoman Mrs. Dorothy Kemp, wife to the Right Worshipfull Mr. Robert Kemp, Esquire, one of his Maiesties Iu∣stices of Peace in the County of Northfolk.</title>
           <author>Levett, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108514_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05403</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15555</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTVOVS gen∣tlewoman Mrs. Dorothy Kemp, wife to the Right Worshipfull Mr. Robert Kemp, Esquire, one of his Maiesties Iu∣stices of Peace in the County of Northfolk.</title>
                 <author>Levett, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ordering of bees: or, The true history of managing them from time to time, with their hony and waxe, shewing their nature and breed : As also what trees, plants, and hearbs are good for them, and namely what are hurtfull: together with the extraordinary profit arising from them. Set forth in a dialogue, resolving all doubts whatsoever. By the late unparalell'd experience of Iohn Levett, Gent</title>
                 <author>Levett, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 4</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 71, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTVOVS gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman M<seg rend="sup">rs.</seg>
      <hi>Dorothy Kemp,</hi> wife to the Right Worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>Robert Kemp,</hi> Esquire, one of his Maiesties Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of Peace in the County of <hi>Northfolk.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost vertuous and kinde, J here present unto your hands and view, this Treatise not great, of a subiect in seeming small, indeed full of greatnesse and glory. For howsoever the body of this little creature, while she is under sayle on her airy voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, can scarce be apprehended of sense; yet the admirable power and manifold wisdome of the Creator, manifested in this his working work, cannot bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by reason, no not by the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious
<pb facs="3"/>inquisitors into her busie industry. This therefore hath in many ages busied many of the most learned of Natures Secretaries, to observe the nature, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, policy, thrift, and exquisite perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this little Flie, in all affayres of war or peace, at home or abroad: and yet have they all beene rather brought to height of admiration, than made fit for full expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the wisdome which (surpassing their owne wisdome) they have found in the Bee. Among others, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Booke, Father to my selfe and it, was a scholler of this schoole, and hat thus written of their orders and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering; which he not living to publish, J have presumed to set forth under your Name, as the heire of that love and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which he bare to the common good, and your selfe; whom in regard of birth, qualities, and fortunes, as gentle, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="3"/>and the most worthy wife of a most worthy husband, he alwayes highly estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. J hope therefore, that (to be silent of my selfe) either of your own generous disposition, or your love to the deceased Author, or your charity to this posthume Orphling, you will most heartily accept what I most heartily dedicate, together with my selfe, unto you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all duty, IOHN LEVETT.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="4"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>