<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>S. Purcas.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108514_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05403</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15555</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>S. Purcas.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ordering of bees: or, The true history of managing them from time to time, with their hony and waxe, shewing their nature and breed : As also what trees, plants, and hearbs are good for them, and namely what are hurtfull: together with the extraordinary profit arising from them. Set forth in a dialogue, resolving all doubts whatsoever. By the late unparalell'd experience of Iohn Levett, Gent</title>
                 <author>Levett, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 4</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 71, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>S. Purcas.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>VNskild am I to usher forth thy Book,</l>
      <l>Or blaze thy selfe with termes of commendation,</l>
      <l>(Nor busie Bees such idle court' sies brook,</l>
      <l>Nor can I rules queint affected fashion.)</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thy selfe, thy selfe enough, enough thy Booke,</l>
      <l>Thy Book commends, and I, my <hi>Levett,</hi> leave it,</l>
      <l>Here in small Bees, Gods greatnesse first I looke,</l>
      <l>And then thy selfe though dead to live yet.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Industrious Fly, fly forth, and sound him farre,</l>
      <l>Which here sounds thee, thy nature, art, thrift, keeping,</l>
      <l>Much can he prayse thy peace, and much thy warre,</l>
      <l>Modell of policy, a sweet good seeking:</l>
      <l>And in those lazy Drones thy sting fix sure,</l>
      <l>Which nor their own, nor others paynes can dure.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>