<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers.</title>
           <author>Cowell, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108959_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19476</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5900</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108959</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers.</title>
                 <author>Cowell, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The interpreter: or Booke containing the signification of vvords : wherein is set foorth the true meaning of all, or the most part of such words and termes, as are mentioned in the lawe vvriters, or statutes of this victorious and renowned kingdome, requiring any exposition or interpretation. ... Collected by Iohn Cowell</title>
                 <author>Cowell, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>584 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Readers, I heere offer my selfe to your censures, vvith no other desire, then by you to be admonished of my faults. For though I doe professe the amplifying of their vvorkes, that haue gone before me in this kinde, and haue both gathered at home, and brought from abroade some ornaments for the better embellishing of our English lavves: yet am <hi>I</hi> neither so vaine, as to denie mine imperfections, nor so passionate, as to be offended at your charitable reformation. Nay, my true ende is the advauncement of knovvledge; and therefore haue <hi>I</hi> published this poore vvorke, not onely to impart the good thereof to those young ones that vvant it: but also to dravve from the learned the supply of my defects: and so by degrees, if not my selfe to finish this modell, yet at the least, by the heate of emulation to incense some skilfuller architect thereunto. Yea, <hi>I</hi> shall thinke my paines sufficiently recompensed, if they may be found but vvorthy to stirre vp one learned man to amend mine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
   <p>The Ciuilians of other nations, haue by their mutuall industries raised this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of worke in their profession, to an inexpected excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie. I haue seene many of them that haue bestowed very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and commendable paines therin and lastly one <hi>Caluinus</hi> a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> like a laborious Bee, hath gathered from all the former, the best iuyce of their flowers, and made vp a hiue full of delectable honie. And by this example would I gladly incite the le ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our common lawes and antiquities of England, yet to lend their aduice to the gayning of some comfortable lights &amp; prospects toward the beautifying of this auncient palace, that hitherto hath bene accoumpted (howsoeuer substantiall) yet but darke and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly.</p>
   <p>Whosoeuer will charge these my trauiles with many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sights,
<pb facs="4"/>
he shall neede no solemne paines to prooue them. For I will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily confesse them. And, vpon my view taken of this booke sithence the impression, I dare assure them that shall obserue most faults therein, that I by gleaning after him, will gather as many omitted by him, as he shall shew committed by me. But I learned long si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence out of famous <hi>Tullie;</hi> that as no mans errours ought to be folowed, because he sayeth some things well: so that which a man saith well, is not to be reiected, because he hath some errours. No man, no booke is voide of imperfections. And therefore reprehend who will, in Gods name: that is, with svveetnes, and vvithout re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche. So shall he reape hartie thankes at my hands: and by true imitation of the most iudicious that euer vvrote, more soundly helpe on this pointe of learning to perfection in a fevve monethes, then I by tossing and tumbling my bookes at home, could possibly haue done in many yeares. Experience hath taught me this in mine Institutes lately set forth: by publishing vvhereof I haue gained the iudicious obseruations of diuers learned gentlemen vpon them, vvhich by keeping them priuate I could neuer haue procured. By vvhich meanes <hi>I</hi> hope one day to commend them to you againe in a more exact puritie, and so leaue them to future times for such acceptance, as it shall please God to giue them.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>I</hi> haue in some tovvardnes a tract <hi>(de regulis iuris)</hi> vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my intent is, by collating the cases of both lavves, to shevve, that they both be raised of one foundation, and differ more in lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and termes then in substance, and therefore vvere they redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to one methode (as they easily might) to be attained (in a maner) vvith all one paines. But my time imparted to these studies, being but stolne from mine emploiments of greater necessitie, <hi>I</hi> cannot make the hast <hi>I</hi> desire, or perhaps that the discourse may deserue. VVherefore vntill my leisure may serue to performe that, <hi>I</hi> intreate you louingly to accept this.</p>
   <p>One thing <hi>I</hi> haue done in this booke, vvhereof, because it may seeme straunge to some, <hi>I</hi> thinke to yeld my reason: and that is the inserting not onely of vvords belonging to the art of the lavve, but
<pb facs="4"/>
of any other also, that <hi>I</hi> thought obscure, of vvhat sort soeuer; as Fish, Cloth, Spices, Drugs, Furres, and such like. For in this <hi>I</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv the example of our Ciuilians, that haue thought it their part to expound any thing they could meete with in their vvalke. And in deede a Lavvyer professeth true Philosophy, and therefore should not be ignorant (if it vvere possible) of either beastes, foules, or creeping things, nor of the trees from the Cedar in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> to the Hyssop that springeth out of the vvall. And therefore, if <hi>I</hi> haue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther omitted any hard vvord vvithin my circuit, or set it dovvne not expounded; <hi>I</hi> giue you good leaue to impute the one to my negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, the other to mine ignorance: and so cōmend these my paines to your best profit, and you vnto God.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Nouember. 3. 1607.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>IO. COVVELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>