<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVELY Honorable, and right VVorship∣full Knight, Sir THO. SMITH, Gouer∣nour of the East India, Muscouia, Summer Ilands, and French Companies, &amp;c. All increase of Grace, Health and Happinesse in this life, and Glorie in that which is to come.</title>
           <author>Lesk, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108492_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05341</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15493</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108492</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVELY Honorable, and right VVorship∣full Knight, Sir THO. SMITH, Gouer∣nour of the East India, Muscouia, Summer Ilands, and French Companies, &amp;c. All increase of Grace, Health and Happinesse in this life, and Glorie in that which is to come.</title>
                 <author>Lesk, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached aboard of the Globe the 18. of May, anno 1617 : At an anchor by the Cape of Good Hope, in the Bay of Souldania, 34. degrees to the southward of the æquinoctiall line. By William Lesk, minister of Gods Word. Entertained by the Honourable Companie of Marchants trading into East India, for the instruction and comfort of the fleet, by them sent forth for those easterne parts anno, 1614</title>
                 <author>Lesk, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 45, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVELY Honorable, and right VVorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Knight, Sir</hi> THO. SMITH, <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of the East <hi>India, Muscouia, Summer Ilands,</hi> and <hi>French Companies, &amp;c.</hi> All increase of Grace, Health <hi>and</hi> Happinesse <hi>in this life, and Glorie in that</hi> which is to come.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>OSEPH</hi> (Honourable Sir) in the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and great goodnesse of Gods all-ruling prouidence, being by <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> deliuered from the violence and oppression of his mightie, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious enemies, throughout the whole course of his life thereafter, testified his thankfulnesse vnto the great God of Heauen, for so comfortable a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, by his effectuall and earnest endeauours,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.33, 34, 35, 36. &amp; 47.11, 12.</note> making both for the aduancement of Gods glorie, and good of the Common-wealth wherein he liued: as his wise, graue, and discreete counsell for prouision against the famine to come, and charitable feeding of the Lords chosen, sufficiently witnesse: there needeth no application: for it is a great deale better knowne, then that by my penne
<pb facs="3"/>the fame thereof can be encreased, how seriously (the successe still answering the zeale and greatnesse of your endeuours) since the first time it pleased our gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne to cast his eye vpon your singular and rare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, you haue taken to heart this holy taske. Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therefore the wise and discreete carriage of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Embassage vnto the Emperour of Muscouia, by his Maiestie imposed and laid vpon you, your more then ordinarie care of increasing the Trade of Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, beneficiall vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>l, but especially vnto Ilanders, whereof our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies themselues being Iudges, wee are inferio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> vnto none; your great and manifold aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es vnto farre distant and remote Countries, for animating and encouraging of others vnto the like attempts, your bountifull expence and charges vpon new Discoueries, your liberall maintaining of men skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Mathematikes, and other Sciences, making for the direction of Sea-faring men, in conducting their shippes into whatsoeuer parts of the world, and, which both in Policie and Pietie exceeds all, your Christian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseration and fauourable acceptance indifferently of all poore distressed men, in whom sparkles of Ingenuitie, and ripenesse of Iudgement, whereby in time the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth may be benefited, are in any competent measure to be seene: whence it comes to passe, that many, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise should haue lyen buried in the pit of obliuion, for want of preferment, forced to betake themselues vnto the basest and most seruile imployments, liue now in some eminencie and places of note in their Countries, being helpefull rather then chargeable vnto others: all which making rather for posteritie, then present gaine,
<pb facs="3"/>(for what benefit can your gray haires expect by Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Discoueries, and other Attempts of that or the like nature?) affoord sufficient matter of a right large and ample Discourse, being a subiect well worthie and deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the applause and commendation of a learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vnto whom (although in dutie as farre obliged as any) leauing the exact performance of so great &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie an employment, I shall at this time content my selfe with a briefe remembrance of the reason mouing me to publish these slender Meditations vnder the couert and shade of your protection, I meane your religious care, in furnishing the Ships and Factories vnder your gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with painefull, learned, and conscionable Preachers and disposers of the Mysteries of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whereby God is glorified in the assemblies of your seruants, and they themselues, although (the supply of their necessities so requiring) for a season depriued of the benefit and comfort of their Countrey, liue as at home in regard of spirituall foode: In which respect, as in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, all that loue the prosperitie of Sion, are obliged, and become debtors vnto your deuotion: so more particularly, those vnto whom the propagation of Gods worship, after a speciall manner, is committed: but of all, most especially we, who in this kind haue beene eye-witnesses of your care, executioners of your zeale, and obiects of your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and great fauours, for Christ and the Gospels sake, conferred and bestowed vpon vs. The due consideration whereof, makes me an humble suiter, that according to your wonted respect, and reuerence of the meanest ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of this nature, you will be pleased to safegard and protect from the slanderous and carping tongues of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="4"/>Atheists, this small Treatise, that vnder your name of all good and godly men iustly honoured, comming into the publike view of the world, God in some measure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may be glorified, his people edified, and others of your qualitie and condition, as by many other means, so by this small exercise, vnderstanding the religious course of your gouernment, may thereby be incited and stirred vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the like proceedings: according to that of our Sauiour, <hi>Let your light so shine before men,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 5.15.</note>
      <hi>that they may see your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heauen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all humble dutie to be commanded, <hi>WILLIAM LESK.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>