<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godlie readers, and e∣specially to them amongst whom this author and my selfe ex∣ercise our function.</title>
           <author>Conham, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108401_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1095</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godlie readers, and e∣specially to them amongst whom this author and my selfe ex∣ercise our function.</title>
                 <author>Conham, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very fruitfull exposition of the Commaundements by way of questions and answeres for greater plainnesse : together with an application of euery one to the soule and conscience of man, profitable for all, and especially for them that (beeing not otherwise furnished) are yet desirous both to see themselues, and to deliuer to others some larger speech of euery point that is but briefly named in the shorter catechismes. By Geruase Babington</title>
                 <author>Babington, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 514, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>To the godlie readers, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially to them amongst whom this author and my selfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise our function.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleased God (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to vse my ministerie, not in one, but in moe places in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nner, still to succeede the author of this treatise, to water what hee hath planted, to labour in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aruest, whereof he cast the seede, to seede, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urther to bring on those, of whom he was the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall father, and by the immortall seede of gods word first begat them; and still to enter vpon his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>abours, and goe forwarde with his beginninges: Alwaies to my great helpe, and comfort (God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nowing otherwise my wantes and weakenesse) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he easilier to wade there, where he had broken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he yee, the plainlier to goe on, and leade others, where he had beaten the path, and more readilie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o builde vpon, and reare vp, where he had layed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he foundation, and squared the frame, and with lesse paines to keepe agoing that which hee had moued, and set agoing. God hauing dealt thus mercifully with me in my ministerie, and by the hande of this author thus holpen me; I thought my selfe in duetie bound, in respect of this course which God hath taken with me, (and especially by his meanes) to giue to thee some testimonie of this his worke, for thy further profit, &amp; withall to him some witnesse of my good will. Supposing my selfe in respect of the former cause, as fitte to doe
<pb facs="22"/>
this as another, &amp; knowing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> effect &amp; hauing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> profit of these his labors, and daily reaping it, being, and abiding in the place where this seed was cast, I thought I ought to doe as willingly and as readily as anie other. If for no other cause, yet to commende this especially to them, to bring foorth further fruite among whome it was first sowen, and in whose heartes I doubt not, but it tooke roote nowe long since. An especiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatiō of this worke, if I would take that way, might be drawen from the workeman of it most plentifully, from his stocke, and kindred, educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and such like; which because it is rare fruite on such trees, to some may make it seeme the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but I passe ouer these shewes and outwarde leafes to decke it with, it hauing ynough in it selfe to commend it, least if I should long speake of this colour, and grace, I should speake the lesse of him, or of the thing it selfe, minding not to speake much of either, &amp; but litle in all. And as I passe the stocke from whence this graft was taken, so will I not stand to shewe you where it was ingrafted &amp; planted, in what vniuersitie, in what Colledge, what roote he toke, what sufficient time he grew, howe he spred there, and with what liking, which would make this fruite to many not without cause to realish the better. But to come to that which commeth nearer to the bringing forth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of this worke, when hee was first planted by a fellowshippe in that famous Colledge of the holy, and vndiuided Trinitie, in Cambridge, wholly, or most especially consecrated to the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of him, and his knowledge, whose name it
<pb facs="22"/>
beareth: so straight he toke himselfe to that studie whereby he might be most seruiceable to gods Church, and some triall first had of his guiftes, as it were aduowed himselfe a man to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord, to serue in his tabernacle: Not long after, that betimes he might begin to be profitable &amp; be profitable long; God touching his heart, he toke on him the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie &amp; so mercifully God dealt with him, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> with all he placed him in one certaine Charge, not far from his Colledge; that he might haue where to sowe, be still at hande to sowe, and knowe both what, and how to sowe, and to his comfort see the growing vp, and fruit of it. Nowe hauing there painefully laboured by the space almost of two yeares, and seene the effect of that promise, with what measure ye mete,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Mark.</hi> 24.</note> shall be measured to you againe, and vnto them that haue shall more bee giuen, that though he cast in with full hande, and euer a zelous heart to doe good, in a continued course; yet God so blessed, that the haruest ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounded his labour, and exceeded his hope; and that litle towne was a candle light, set on a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesticke, and a tower vpon the toppe of a hill. When God to his comfort had thus encouraged him in his lawe, he by great meanes calleth him from this litle towne (where he had no pastorall charge) to a greater charge, and in respect of the change, and dignitie of the place whither he was called, it was as it were from <hi>Tecon</hi> to <hi>Bethel,</hi> from preaching in some vplandish, and countery towne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the wildernesse of <hi>Iudea,</hi> to <hi>Herods</hi> court, or as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ndeede in many respectes, it well may be sayde, by a <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> vnto his house. When he had
<pb facs="23"/>
there continued nowe a whole yeare and more, to the good reformation, and great benefitte of that most honorable familie; it pleased God, that his <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> leauing as it were <hi>Nazareth,</hi> went and dwelt for a time in <hi>Capernaum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 4.13.14.</note> which is neare the sea, in the borders of <hi>Zabulon,</hi> and <hi>Nepthalin,</hi> beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> in <hi>Gallilie</hi> of the Gentilles, out of the borders of <hi>Palestina.</hi> I hope I may without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence allude vnto that place, in all pointes it so fitly answereth: where a while abiding, by his meanes, God wrought, that the people which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in comparison sate in darkenesse sawe great light, and to them which sate in the region &amp; sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of death, light was risen vp. Of this place, and this people, he hauing yet further cōpassion, they beeing as sheepe without a shepheard, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in the mountaines, and the haruest there great, and the labourers fewe; the Lorde moued his heart, to remaine there, and wrought this in the heart of his most honorable Lorde; himselfe to forgoe him, and leaue him there, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther increase of God his Church, and for the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der loue he bare, and good he would to this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; where what paines hath beene taken, &amp; good hath beene done, it is by more witnessed than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> neede to make relation▪ and this worke, and some others of this authors, since that time come forth giue open testimony, though I hould my tongue I would not haue saide thus much of the man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the places themselues, of which I haue spoke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> were not readie to say and set downe more tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I haue saide; and this haue I saide that God in him may be glorified, they among whom he liueth fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="23"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im thankefull: and to admonish him what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eedinges these beginninges require. The worke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> selfe, might manie waies beside be commended, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he matter, and principall grounde of it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>awe of God, brought from the highest heauen, giuen by God himselfe to his seruant <hi>Moses,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hunders and lightninges,<note place="margin">19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> and the sounde of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rumpe exceeding loude, on mount <hi>Sinay,</hi> the mountaine all on smoke; the Lorde discending vpon it in fire &amp;c. and all the mount trembling exceedingly, giuen to all the Israell of God, aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ayning to all men, conteining infinite blessinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or the hearers, and doers of it, and innumerable &amp; intollerable curses, &amp; plagues, for the breaker <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hereof, either by negligence or contempt. This principall, not laide vpon with any borrowed col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ours to hide the grounde: but the workemanship and ingrauing of it, is out of the matter it selfe, so that still the grounde, and marble thereof may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and dealt with all in this manner fitlie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering to the subiect matter, deliuered as it were in thunder, with a spirite as hotte as fire, zealous with iudgment, setting an edge by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued strength euen vpon this rasier. The place also, and persons, where, and for whome, this worke was both made, and vttered, may adde much grace, and strength vnto it. In a most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable familie, and for it, and with good liking, and profitte there: and commonly men like that the better, which liketh them well, and that which profiteth such profiteth manie. If it wette the mountaines, it will water the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: and if it bee sweete oyntment for the
<pb facs="24"/>
heade, it cannot be but acceptable to the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of the partes, and to the borders of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The dewe from <hi>Hermon,</hi> and the mountaines of <hi>Sion,</hi> trickleth downe sweeteli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vppon the vallies about. And if this make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> profitable to others, because deliuered heere▪ then must it be most profitable to this family it selfe, for which it was made, and first for it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and nowe is by me especially to it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. It is fruite of your owne grounde, the voice of your owne sheephearde, the sounde of your proper trumpet, and therefore you must both knowe it, and like it the better, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be warned the sooner. It is a lesson, which alreadie you haue learned, and therefore in it may and must be more readie than others. It is not nowe first commended to you, but againe recommended to your eyes, which heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene sent by your eares, to your mindes, and to your heartes, by a great vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, and zeale of spirite, wherewith this author aboundeth. Which although so much, and with such life, and mouing, will not nowe altogether appeare in this writing, as when it was with the liuely voyce, and earnest spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite deliuered, because that GOD promiseth to that, the more especiall blessing, yet shall you easily see, that it is a worke comming out of the same shoppe; a streame flowing from the same fountaine; a print stamped, with the same seale; and sparckles flying out of the same flame. Which the more they shall inflame you, which ought most to inflame you, you hauing beene
<pb facs="24"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>readie with them set on fire, the more they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>all heate others, and by your example be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ofitable to all, which is that the author wisheth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d I his welwiller heartily pray for, to him who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the able worker of it: to whose especiall grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> good reader) in reading this worke, to direct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ee, I commende thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lorde Iesu, <hi>Abraham Conham.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>