<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108119_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19056</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5471a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108119</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Chronographia : A description of time, from the beginning of the vvorld, vnto the yeare of our Lord, 137. Diuided into six periodes. Wherein the seueral histories, both of the Old and new Testament are briefly comprised, and placed in their due order of yeares. Collected ou of sundrie authors, but for the greatest part, abridged and translated out of Laurentius Codomannus his Annales sacræ scripturæ</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 87, 13 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>IT was not my meaning (Gentle reader) whē I first published this litle treatise, so soone again to haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed it: but after some more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of time, and with more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberatiō to haue performed my promise of perfecting the same: yet when I saw the first impression so suddenly dispersed, and a greater number required: I was contēt once againe to let it passe the presse, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that extreme &amp; last hand which my desire was to haue put into it. But because I durst not so far abuse thy patiēce, as in nothing to increase the former edition: it may please
<pb facs="3"/> thee to vnderstand, that I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken care in good part, to better and to amend the same, for thy benefite. For besides the correction, inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and addition of many necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; profitable things, I haue now also set downe in a maner the whole Historie of the Gospel, from point to point, as I could collect the same out of the Euangelists. Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing also after the iudgement of the best Chronographers of our age, the yeare and time wherein euerie thing was done. Further I haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished the whole booke into six periodes of yeares, as I thought would fitliest serue for helpe of thy memorie, and to auoid confusion &amp; tediousnesse in so great varietie. Moreouer, I haue added vnto this edition an Index of the names of all
<pb facs="3"/> the Patriarches, Iudges, Kings, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Priests, Emperors, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Countries, Citties, Persons, Bookes &amp;c. which though perhaps it may seeme to some in so small a volume altogither superfluous: yet I perswade my selfe thou shalt finde it in vse both pleasant and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto thee. For the things which alreadie I haue admonished thee of in my former preface, I thinke not necessarie now againe to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee with thē. Onely thou maist vnderstād, that the principall causes of that difference which is betwene myne Author and Functius with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in accounting the yeres of the world, by his adding to their nūber almost 180. yeares; are these three, First that Codomanus taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the yeares expreslie
<pb facs="4"/> mentioned in the storie of Iudges: Secondly that according to S. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Actes 7. he setteth the death of Tharah before that peregrination of Abrahā, which he being 75. yeres old, vndertooke at the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of God Gē. 12. And thirdly that he beginneth the yeares of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians raigne, mētioned in the books of the Machabees, immediatly after the death of Alexander the great. VVherein because his meaning was not to preiudicate the opinion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but simply to expresse his own iudgemēt; it ought not to be to any an occasion of offence. If it shal mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thee that I haue taken so manie things out of the Apocrypha and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writers, besides the bookes of the Canonicall scriptures: it may please thee to vnderstand, that fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="4"/> it done by mine Author, onely to cōtinue the Historie, &amp; for other cōplemēt, I could not conueniently neglect the same. Holding firmely neuerthelesse, that knowne and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie differēce in authority, which is betweene the sacred monuments of the spirit of God, and the fraile &amp; doubtfull writings of men. If anie further thing haue escaped the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gēce of the Printer, in so many num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of so great difference, I pray thee gentle Reader friendlie to correct what thou findest to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse. And so I bid thee most hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly farewel in the Lord. This eigth of Iune. Anno. Dom. 1590.</p>
   <q>Y. W. Signifieth the yeare of the world. Y. C. The yeare of Christ. b. borne. d. died.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>