<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE CHARACTER of the famous Odcombian, or ra∣ther Polytopian, Thomas the CORYATE, Traueller, and Gen∣tleman-Author of these Quin∣que-mestriall Cru∣dities.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108718_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19383</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5810</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE CHARACTER of the famous Odcombian, or ra∣ther Polytopian, Thomas the CORYATE, Traueller, and Gen∣tleman-Author of these Quin∣que-mestriall Cru∣dities.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Odcombian banquet: dished foorth by Thomas the Coriat, and serued in by a number of noble wits in prayse of his Crudities and Crambe too. Asinus portans mysteria</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introductory_encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE CHARACTER of the famous <hi>Odcombian,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Polytopian, Thomas the</hi> CORYATE, Traueller, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman-Author <hi>of these</hi> Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que-mestriall Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</head>
   <argument>
      <p>Done by a charitable friend, that thinkes it necessary by this time, you should vnderstand the <hi>Maker,</hi> as well as the <hi>Worke.</hi>
      </p>
   </argument>
   <p>HE is an Engine, wholly consisting of Extremes, a Head, Fingers, and Toes. For what his industrious Toes haue trode, his readie Fingers haue written, his subtill head dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. He was set a going for <hi>Venice</hi> the fourteenth of <hi>May, Anno</hi> 1608. and returned home (ofhimselfe) the third of October following, being wound vp for fiue moneths, or thereabouts: his paises two for one. Since, by vertue of those weights he hath beene conueniently able to visite Towne and Country, Fayres and Mercats, to all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> a <hi>Spectacle</hi> gratefull aboue that of <hi>Nineueh,</hi> or the citty of <hi>Norwich;</hi> and hee is now


<pb facs="5"/>
become the better <hi>Motion,</hi> by hauing this his Booke his <hi>Interpreter:</hi> which yet hath exprest his purse more then him, as wee the rest of his Commenders haue done, so vnmercifully charging the Presse with his <hi>prayse.</hi> But to that Gale, he sets vp all sayles. Hee will beare paper (which is cloth) enough. Hee hath euer since the first design of printing hereof, bin <hi>à Deliciis</hi> to the Court; but serued there in his owne cloathes, and at his owne costs; where hee hath not bin costiue of acquaintance to any, from the <hi>Palatine</hi> to the <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beian;</hi> which popularity of his (it is thought by some of his <hi>Odcombians</hi>) may hurt him. But he free from all other <hi>Symptomes</hi> of aspiring, wil easily outcarry that; it beeing a motly and no perfect ambition: the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, because when hee should haue beene taken vp for the place (though he hastily preuented it with a tender of himselfe) he conditioned to haue no office of charge, or neerenesse cast vpon him, as the <hi>Remora</hi> of his future trauell; for to that hee is irrecouerably addicted. The word <hi>Trauaile</hi> affects him in a Waine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oxe, or Packe-horse. A Carrier will carrie him from any company that hath not beene abroade, because he is a <hi>Species</hi> of a Traueller. But a <hi>Dutch-post</hi> doth rauish him. The meere <hi>Superscription</hi> of a letter from <hi>Zurich</hi> settes him vp like a top: <hi>Basil</hi> or <hi>Heidelberg</hi> makes him spinne. And at seeing the word <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> or <hi>Venice,</hi> though but on the title of a booke, he is readie to break doubler, cracke elbowes, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow the roome with his murmure.</p>
   <p>He is a mad <hi>Greek,</hi> no lesse then a merrie: and will buy his <note n="*" place="margin">J mean when he trauelled. A thing that I know he scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to do since he same home.</note> Egges, his Puddings, his Ginger-bread, yea cobble his Shooes in the <hi>Atticke Dialect:</hi> and would


<pb facs="5"/>
make it a matter of Conscience to speake other, were hee trusted alone in a roome with an <hi>Andiron</hi> of State. The greatest <hi>Politicke</hi> that aduances into <hi>Paules</hi> hee will quitte, to go talke with the <hi>Grecian</hi> that begges there; such is his humilitie; and doth grieue inwardly he was not borne that Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for that <note n="*" place="margin">Not to beg, but to talke Greeke the better with the naturall Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</note> purpose. You shall perceiue a veine or threed of <hi>Greeke</hi> runne through his whole discourse, and another of <hi>Latine,</hi> but that is the courser. Hee is a great and bold <hi>Carpenter</hi> of words, or (to expresse him in one like his owne) a <hi>Logodaedale:</hi> which <hi>voice</hi> when hee heares, 'tis doubtfull whether he will more loue at the first, or enuy after, that it was not his owne. All his <hi>Phrase</hi> is the same with his manners and hauiour, such as if they were studied to make <hi>Mourners</hi> merrie: but the bodie of his discourse able to breake <hi>Impostumes,</hi> remooue the <hi>stone,</hi> open the passage from the <hi>Bladder,</hi> and vndo the very knots of the <hi>Gout;</hi> to cure euen where <hi>Physicke</hi> hath turnd her backe, and <hi>Nature</hi> hung downe her head for shame; Beeing not onely the <hi>Antidote</hi> to resist sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but the <hi>Preseruatiue</hi> to keepe you in mirth, a <hi>life and a day.</hi> A man might vndo the <hi>Colledge</hi> that would practise with onely <hi>him.</hi> And there is no man but to enioy his companie, would neglect any thing but businesse. It is thought hee liues more by letting <note n="(a)" place="margin">I meane the foreparts, not the binder.</note> out of ayre, then drawing in; and feared, his belly will exhibite a Bill in <hi>Chauncerie</hi> against his Mouth for talking away his meales. Hee is alwayes <hi>Tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Maior</hi> of the companie, and if euer the perpetuall motion be to be hoped for, it is from thence. He will aske, <hi>How do you? Where you haue beene? How is it? If


<pb facs="6"/>
you haue trauelled? How you like his booke?</hi> with, <hi>what newes?</hi> and bee guilty of a thousand such courteous impertinences in an houre, rather then want the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity of vexing you. To conclude this ample Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller in some bounds, you shall best know him by this: he is frequent at all sorts of free tables, where though he might sit as a Guest, he will rather be ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in as a Dish, and is loth to haue anything of himselfe kept cold against the next day. To giue the <hi>Non vltra</hi> of him in a word, hee is so <hi>Substantiue</hi> an <hi>Author</hi> as will stand by himselfe without the neede of his <hi>Booke</hi> to be ioyned with him.</p>
   <trailer>
      <hi>Here endeth the</hi> Character, <hi>attended with a</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterisme Acrostich.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>