<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROLOGVE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108590_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15716</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108590</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROLOGVE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Scotlands vvelcome to her native sonne, and soveraigne lord, King Charles : wherein is also contained, the maner of his coronation, and convocation of Parliament; the whole grievances, and abuses of the common-wealth of this kingdome, with diverse other relations, never heretofore published. Worthy to be by all the nobles and gentry perused; and to be layd vp in the hearts, and chests of the whole commouns, whose interests may best claime it, either in meane, or maner, from which their priuiledges, and fortunes are drawne, as from the loadstar of true direction. By William Lithgovv, the bonaventure, of Europe, Asia, and Africa</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue_to_poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PROLOGVE TO THE READER.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hilst SCOTLANDS <hi>Welcome,</hi> sends its substant show</l>
   <l>To Mighty CHARLES, as bund duetie owe;</l>
   <l>To whom sweet songs, and hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie plaints it brings,</l>
   <l>Mixt so, and framd, discovring serious things:</l>
   <l>Yet some blind judgements may condemne my <hi>Muse,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For touching that, which they them selues abuse:</l>
   <l>But if it gall, their stinking sores, long wounded,</l>
   <l>A tush for base despight, from such hate grounded:</l>
   <l>Whose guilt may plead, and tell their conscience thus,</l>
   <l>Shrewd faults find eyes, and <hi>Tyme</hi> must punish vs;</l>
   <l>Which if one age ago, this <hi>Land</hi> had beene</l>
   <l>Check'd of such faults, might now haue beene fund cleane.</l>
   <l>As for the <hi>Critick,</hi> or the carping Slaue,</l>
   <l>Goe hang himselfe, I care not for a knaue:</l>
   <l>Whilst for the <hi>Commoun-wealth,</hi> I stand to plead,</l>
   <l>To show <hi>Oppressours</hi> tyranny and greed:</l>
   <l>And eu'ry grievous vyce, this Land affords,</l>
   <l>Where I affect more matter, than coynd words,</l>
   <l>Brayne-wrested straines, <hi>AEnigmatick</hi> stile,</l>
   <l>Or epitomizd <hi>Epilogues</hi> the while:</l>
   <l>Although I dyving could, and soaring fetch▪</l>
   <l>My top-wingd flight, too high, for vulgar reach:</l>
   <l>Whilst I meanewhile, haue more paynes to be plaine,</l>
   <l>Than to be curious, in the highest strayne.</l>
   <l>For what this worke affoords, lyf-burning <hi>Taper!</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I had no <hi>Bookes</hi> to read, when pennd, but Paper:</l>
   <l>With <hi>Ink▪</hi> and <hi>Pen,</hi> my <hi>Chamber</hi>-garnish bare,</l>
   <l>Warme <hi>Bed,</hi> and <hi>Boord,</hi> none other <hi>Book</hi> was there:</l>
   <l>But <hi>Memory, Invention, Experience</hi> great,</l>
   <l>Whereon my labours, build their solid Seat:</l>
   <l>Which if it bee not well done, goe and mend it,</l>
   <l>For with the same condition, I Thee send it:</l>
   <l>But stop, O stay! its harder to invent,</l>
   <l>Then adding invention, to whats here meant▪</l>
   <l>This <hi>Web</hi> then see, of welcome I it Warp,</l>
   <l>Whiles playne and prolixe, sometymes breef, and sharp;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, vnsadled, spurring on I goe,</l>
   <l>And neither spares my friend, nor hurtes my foe,</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut smoothly twixt two strugling shoares I runne,</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lat-sandy <hi>Scilla, Charibdin</hi> rocks to shunne:</l>
   <l>For twixt like two, the golden meane may rest,</l>
   <l>Nether too bitter, nor too sweet is best:</l>
   <l>Which justly I set downe, and purpose lyke,</l>
   <l>Vpon the <hi>Annill,</hi> of the Trueth I stryke:</l>
   <l>And if I erre in one jote, I requyre,</l>
   <l>Let mee goe headlong to deaths fatall fyre.</l>
   <l>Say, if he come this yeare, say he come not,</l>
   <l>Yet tyme shall praise mee, for a louing SCOT.</l>
   <l>Which being doubtfull, precisely, how, and when,</l>
   <l>I reddy made this worke, form <hi>Presse,</hi> from <hi>Pen:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Yet not to vent my Bookes, nor haue them sould,</l>
   <l>Before myne eyes, his comming in behould:</l>
   <l>To whome the first I owe, to be presented,</l>
   <l>For onely, to him onely, its invented:</l>
   <l>Which when it is devulgd, I dare expect,</l>
   <l>From the judicious <hi>Lector,</hi> kynd respect.</l>
   <l>Then read, misconster not, but wysely looke,</l>
   <l>If reason be, the <hi>Mistrisse</hi> of my <hi>Booke,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And if I finger, what thou fayne wouldst touch,</l>
   <l>O! thank mee, and be pleasd; whylst I avouch,</l>
   <l>The commoun sorrowes, of this groaning Land,</l>
   <l>Which I lay open, to thyne open hand:</l>
   <l>Then ponder, and peruse it, thou shalst fynd,</l>
   <l>The <hi>Sole Idea,</hi> of thy Countreyes Mynd.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thyne, as Thou art Myne,</hi>
WILLIAM LITHGOVV.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Non vita haec ducenda est, quae corpore &amp; spiritu continetur,
&amp; illa inquam, illa vita est, quae viget memoriâ saeculorum
omnium, quam posteritas alit, quam ipsa aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas
semper intuetur.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>