<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authour to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108006_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5343</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authour to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Henoch Clapham his demaundes and answeres touching the pestilence : methodically handled, as his time and meanes could permit</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Authour to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THE last great <hi>Pest-time</hi> (I speak of the Great plague in
<hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> for otherwise, it is now the greatest Pest-time in the
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and throughout his Highnes Dominions) it pleased God to give me
affection and strength to continue &amp; hold out my Ministerie to the end,
publikelie teaching, and privately comforting the Lords poore flocke abyding in
the Citie of <hi>London</hi> (as occasion here and there, night and day was
administred) what time the Citie was much infirmed for Civill governement, and
well-nigh emptied of due ecclesiasticall cure.</p>
   <p>Satan<note n="“" place="margin">Revel. 12. 10.</note>
      <hi>The
accuser of our brethren,</hi> maligning the happy successe of my labors, he
gets som vnwise Spirits to bruite abroad, that <hi>Clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> taught <hi>The
plague not to be infectious,</hi> and that <hi>All that dyed of the plague were
damned, as dying without faith.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The first accusation came readily to the present Lo. Bb. of
London, but the second (it seemeth) not so. For about som 34. wekes after my
first Cōmitment, the said Lo. BB. and Sir <hi>Edward Stanhope</hi> in Court
did publikely affirme, that they had not heard of that bruite before: what time
I my selfe then first vttered it in their court, that so then in the face of
all by-standers it might be checked, so well as other slaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, forged only
for obscuring myne innocency.</p>
   <p>The BB. beleeving the first tale, he (without sending for me, or
tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with me) caused me to be taken (euen presently vpō a Sermons ending,
wherin I had opposed to such insensible reportes) and so was conveyed to
the<note n="*" place="margin">Anno Do: 1603. Novemb.
 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>4</note> Clinck prison. Passing by
some inter-currentes (which in som other my writings are layde downe) he at the
eleven weekes end convented me, thē signifying that I had bene imprisoned for
teaching, <hi>That the plague was not inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ctious;</hi> as also for publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing <hi>An Epistle concerning the
Pestilence;</hi> and that in contempt of the booke of <hi>Orders</hi> for the
Wednesdayes fast, authorized by the King. To both I answered
<hi>Negatiuely,</hi> if so by <hi>Plague</hi> they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood not that stroke
of the Angel termed of the Holy-Ghost <hi>Deber;</hi> but that which grew from
corruption of the Creature. Well to the Gate house prison I was sent, and to my
booke and the contentes, I should answere in another place.</p>
   <p>To passe by the second Convention, it being to no other end then
the former, the weeke before the Archb. death, I was called to
<hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</hi> There, after assurauce had of certaine Articles their
compasse, I <pb facs="3"/> tooke my othe to answer truly to them. The next Monday
at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisters office I did so. The answere was sent to the BB. of Londō.
He seeing it made not to his purpose, did not convent me, but (without all
adoe) he let me ly in prison still as afore. My wordes nor writings prevayling
any whitt, I complayned to the King on<note n="“" place="margin">1604.</note>
      <hi>Easter monday,</hi> who appointed the same to be conveyed to the BB.
<hi>And he thereto to giue in his answer.</hi> Hearing nothing more of that of
7. weekes, I on the day of Pentecost insuing, complayned to his
<hi>Highnes</hi> againe. Thereto, Sir <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> in his Maiesties
name subscribeth thus. 
<q>The Kings Maiesty hath eftsoones referred this petitiō to the
 Lord Bishop of London, who is required by his Highnes calling other of the
 Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commission vnto him, withall convenient expedition and according to the Law,
 to proceede to iudgement, either with or against the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as his cause
 shall deserue; that his Highnes may not further bee importuned herein. So farre
 the Kings commaund.</q>
   </p>
   <p>To the Bishop I sent it, but hearing nothing from him, a fortnight
after, I sent to the King againe. About a week after, I was convented. And
after much talke to no purpose, the Bishop concluded thus: <hi>you may doe this
at least; the Doctrines being put downe as supposed to be taught of you, you
may subscribe herein, I was truely or not truly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood.</hi> I answered,
let that be done, and I shall doe what I ought. Doctor <hi>Stanhope</hi> then
said, Maister Deanes of Westminster &amp; Pawles are appointed to that, who (at
their convenient leasure) will send for you. So the Court broke vp. This was
the eleventh of Iuly last; and then the first time also of excepting at the
doctrine of <hi>Faithes appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending deliverance from the plague,</hi> taught
in the foresaid <hi>Epistle.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Being thus left to the two Deanes, I writt to them sundry times
for speedy proceeding. One of them sent my messenger to the other, backward and
forward. At the Monethes end, Doctor <hi>Androes</hi> sends me word, that he
had put the matter from him. And so he never sent for me, according to the
Courtes Depute.</p>
   <p>Passing by inconvenient repeates, about three weekes after, I was
sent for to the Registers office. Coming thither, his man lets me see Doctor
<hi>Androes</hi> his moneths worke. And what was it? <hi>A flat
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation,</hi> and nothing answerable to that which the Court (in myne
hearing) appointed as afore. So much I signified to the Bishop, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to the
<hi>Doctor,</hi> But other answer since I could haue none but this: put in
bondes so to protest, <hi>When and Where we</hi> shall appoint, and so 
<pb facs="3"/> departe prison. So my cause at the penning hereof standeth.</p>
   <p>The severall pointes, for the which I am thus handled, in the
se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Discourse I do treat of, by way of <hi>Quere</hi> and
<hi>Response;</hi> that is by way of Question and Answere. Wherein my cause is
vnsound, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; wherein Orthodoxall, accept: and so farre be Gods instrument
for my Good.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Art thou a Magistrate?</head>
      <p>Then hearken what <hi>Salomon</hi> saith: <hi>Deliver them that
 are drawen to death;</hi>
         <note place="margin">Prover. 24. 11. 12.</note>
         <hi>and
 wilt thou not preserue them that are ledd to be slaine? If thou say, Behold, we
 knew not of it, he that Pondereth the heartes, doth he not vnderstand it? And
 he that keepeth thy Soule, knoweth hee it not? Will not he also recompence
 every man according to his workes?</hi> Thus let the Magistrate take heede how
 he pleades ignorance, and wincketh at the fall of the innocent. For such a
 looking through the fingers, may fill the earth with innocent blood, till it
 roare again for heavens iudgement. And so not only such, but also the whole
 lande shall fare the worse for iniustice.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Art thou a Minister?</head>
      <p>Then heare what <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> say:<note place="margin">Leuit. 5. 1.</note>
         <hi>And if any haue sinned, namely, by hearing
 the voyce of an othe, and he can be a witnesse, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath seene or
 knowen of it, he do not vtter it, he shall beare his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie.</hi>
         <note place="margin">Prou. 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
         <hi>Open thy mouth for the dombe in the cause of all the children of
 destruction.</hi> Some of you are reported to say that Clapham hath a good
 cause, but it is to be doubted, if so he haue sufficient learning to defend it.
 That I haue, I haue: God make me faithfull in that I haue. But thou that art
 able to giue in thy Testimonie, art bound also to do it. If thou wilt not be a
 Procter for Christ in his members, one of the two Theeues executed with lesus,
 shall turne Preacher, &amp; giue in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fficient evidence, to thy condemnation.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>To the People.</head>
      <p>Also Brethren, I beseech you for our Lorde Iesus sake and for
 the loue of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Rom. 15. 30. &amp;c.</note> that ye
 would striue with me by prayers vnto the Lord for me, that I may be deliuered
 from the disobedient, and that my seruice (which I haue yet to do) may be
 accepted of the Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: that I may come forth to his people with ioy, by
 the will of God, and may with you be refreshed. Thus the God of peace be with
 you all, Amen.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Yours, <hi>Henoch Clapham.</hi>
         </signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>