<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The aunswere of my Lordes the Estates generall, made to the former decla∣ration.</title>
           <author>Houfflin, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108223_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68316</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15207.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108223</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The aunswere of my Lordes the Estates generall, made to the former decla∣ration.</title>
                 <author>Houfflin, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The apologie or defence, of the most noble Prince William, by the grace of God, Prince of Orange, Countie of Nassau, of Catzenellenboghen, Dietz, Vianden, &amp;c. Burgmaister of Antwerp, and Vicou [n] t of Bezanson, Baron of Breda, Diest, Grimberg, of Arlay, Nozeroy, &amp;c. Lord of Chastel-bellin, &amp;c. Lieutenaunt generall in the lowe Countries, and Gouernour of Brabant, Holland, Zeelande, Vtrecht and Frise, &amp; Admiral. &amp;c. Against the proclamation and edict, published by the King of Spaine, by which he proscribeth the saide lorde prince, whereby shall appeare the sclaunders, and false accusations, conteined in the said proscription, which is annexed to the end of this apologie. Presented to my lords the Estates generall of the lowe Countrie. Together with the said proclamation or proscription. Printed in French and in all other languages</title>
                 <author>Loyseleur, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Delft</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="reply">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The aunswere of my Lordes the Estates</hi> generall, made to the former decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
   <p>THE Estates generall, hauing not many dayes since, seene and read a certaine Proscription, published by the enemies, against your Excellencies person, by which they charge the same with hainous crimes, indeuouring to make it odious, (as though by vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes, and indirect wayes, it had vsurped the place and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, wherein it is sett and established) and to deliuer your saide Excellencies person ouer for a parie, and to take from it the honor thereof: hauing in like sorte seene and viewed, a defence sett out by your Excellencie, against the said Proscription, finde, by the trueth of that which hath passed in these countries, and which is knowen and manifest also, to euerie one of them, in respect of themselues, that the saide crimes, faultes and reproches, haue vniustlie bin laide vpon the same. And as concerning the offices, as well of Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt generall, as of the particular gouernementes, they affirme that his excellencie, yea euen then, when he was lawfully elected &amp; chosen, did not accept them, but at our instant request, in which also he hath continued at our intreaties, and that with the sounde contentment and satisfaction, of the whole countrie: and the saide Estates doo yet againe beseeche him, that it would please him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein, promising him all ayde and assistance, without sparing anie of the meanes they haue, and also to yeelde vnto him readie and willing obedience. And because they knowe, the faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, that your Excellencie hath yeelded to these countries, and those also which they hope, in time yet hereafter to come, you will performe: they offer vnto him, for the assurance of his person, to maintaine a companie of horsemen for the sauegarde thereof, besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching him to accept it on the behalfe, and at the offer of those persons, which thinke themselues much bound to the preseruation
<pb facs="5"/> thereof. And so much as toucheth the said Estates (who think them selues also charged by the said Proscription) they minde shortly in like sorte to iustifie them selues, so farre forth as they shall thinke it conuenient. So concluded in the assemblie of my Lordes the Estates generall, in the towne of Delft, the xvij. day of December. In the yeere of our Lorde, 1580.</p>
   <closer>
      <hi>By the expresse determination of the said Eslates.</hi>
      <signed>Signed I. Houfflin.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>