<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108833_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5837</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108833</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The infallible true and assured vvitch: or, The second edition, of The tryall of witch-craft : Shewing the right and true methode of the discouerie: with a confutation of erroneous vvayes, carefully reuiewed and more fully cleared and augmented. By Iohn Cotta, Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Cotta, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Higgenbotham, Richard 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 155, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="87"/>
   <head>The Errata.</head>
   <p>BY the Authors distance and remotenesse from the presse, and by the vnauoidable countermaund of his presence thorow the then indesinent vrgence of his calling fixing him else-where: these errours following (before they could be knowne vnto him) had ouer-runne his power of their reuocation. Of those errours which common sense and euery vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar scholership may easily and tacitly vnto it selfe in reading rectifie, he he doth ease the Reader in this place, namely, of slight take orthographics, of some senselesse discontinuations, of requisite continuations of some syllables, words, lines, and sentencies, the legges and feete of some verses out of Poets cited beyond their due measure, line and length extended within the prose, the dislocating of some commaes, prickes, and full points. Those errours only which doe more materially exact their reformation (for that they doe manifestly hood-winke the sense, and ouer-cloude the clee<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er sight and vnderstanding) he hath hither summoned.</p>
   <p>In the subscription of the Dedicatorie Epistle vnto the Iudges in the first Edition, reade dutious for deuotious. In the Pris<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ters preface vnto the Reader in the second edition, Chap. 7. fig. 4. and thence line 4, reade, to be esteemed Watches, not, to be esteemed. Witches, Page 12. line 13. reade in for is page 13. line 9. reade likewise when, for likewise. page 13. line 18. adde as much incourage. page 26. line 25. reade from the Diuell also, for from the Diuels; al<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o. page 42. line 33. reade enumeration. page 43. line 12. read for any man. page 43. line 26. reade For he that is. page 45. line 12. reade abiect for obiect. pag. 40. line 2. reade or pretence. pag. 51 line 32. reade from the Friets. pag 52. line 33. reade aerem for verem. pag. 2. line 33. read confessionibus for confessio, and responsa for response. page 60. line 32. and 33. reade and Church and betweene, for Church. And betweene, page 61. line 1. reade at ceremonies a comma not a full po<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt, and which not. Which page 62. line 25 reade conniue for conuince. pag. 66. line 24. reade in Physike for curation not in Physike For curation. pag 68. line the last. reade of an infinite. page 74. line 8. reade were, for where. pag. 76. line 6. reade Practisers. pag. 79. line 26. reade nature. The impossibilitie. pag. 88. line 5. reade effected for affected. pag 88. line 4. reade mediately for immediately. pag. 90. line 8. reade nature. Whether. p. 104. line 13. reade proceede to. pag. 106. line 13. reade awaketh. pag 107. lin. 1. read against any other. pag. 130. line 32. reade false as ordinarie. pag. 149. line 15. 16. reade, himselfe. In the Diuels truth behold, not himselfe in the Diuels truth behold.</p>
   <pb facs="88"/>
   <pb facs="88"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>