<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Epilogue.</title>
           <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108006_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5343</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Epilogue.</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Henoch Clapham his demaundes and answeres touching the pestilence : methodically handled, as his time and meanes could permit</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <head>Epilogue.</head>
   <p>EQuall is that Pentameter, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Euery forced
busines, is grievous.</hi> Almost a yeare is passed, at the penning hereof. So
long forbearance, was much and onerous; specially in so even a cause. If my
Aduersaries scorpions, haue by lashing enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this Cry, and thou thereby
bettered, <hi>Deo gratias,</hi> giue God the prayse, who out of a flint can
fetch fier; and of stones, rayse vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Abraham. Meane tyme, be
assured, it had beene more ease for me, not to haue beene so vrged. But though
I were slaine, I must (with <hi>Iob</hi>) hold fast myne innocencie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="30" facs="16"/> Innocency; By how much the more it is
innoeencie, by so much the more I should (by silence) haue borne false witnes
against God, his Church, and myne owne soule. But if it bee remembred, what
horride reportes, were scattered abroad of me, both touching <hi>Fact,</hi> and
matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> notwithstanding all orderly suites, and
protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, subscriptorie, and iuramentall; yea, against the tendering
Royal purpose, of our Soueraigne: to the possessing of Magistrates eares with
vntruthes, to the perverting of Ministers, and people; for ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all against
me, and so the sword of Gods holy Angell (<note n="“" place="margin">Never ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
 this sick nes so migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily and vniversally in England, as now it doth</note>
yet vn-sheathed) gainst all; damming vp the course of my Ministerie, cutting of
my bodies liberty; propounding my life to daunger; brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the heart of my
family, consumed the substance I had payne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully earned: to the gladding of
fooes, sadding of friends, procuring murmurations, &amp;c. and al for praying,
preaching, visiting, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, to all sortes, pestilenced: when almost
none els would; if all this be layd to heart, am I Iron, that I should not
feele; or am I lead, that I should not sound? Nay is it reasonable (though I
bee therefore cōmitted close prisoner, yea, should dy the death) but I should
speak, and write, for clearing of myne innocencie?</p>
   <p>Wherein I haue fayled (and who is it, that in nothing sinneth not)
thou that art stronger, helpe to sustayne me: at least, simpathize so my
estate, as I may be helped, by thy feeling and harty prayers. And so with
reference of my cause to the iudgement of God, his Church in England, Scotland,
France, Ireland, and wheresoeuer, I end. This 18. of September, 1604.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The Lord most vnworthy HENOCH
 CLAPHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>