<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TWO MOST VERTVOVS, and wel-learned young Gentlemen. Mr. FRANCIS STEWART, Master of Mourray. And to Mr. IOHN STEWART Sonne to the DVKE of LENNOX his GRACE.</title>
           <author>C., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108067_Bo1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5393</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108067</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TWO MOST VERTVOVS, and wel-learned young Gentlemen. Mr. FRANCIS STEWART, Master of Mourray. And to Mr. IOHN STEWART Sonne to the DVKE of LENNOX his GRACE.</title>
                 <author>C., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hērō-paideia, or The institvtion of a yovng noble man : by James Cleland</title>
                 <author>Cleland, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 1-246, 251-271, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="162" facs="91"/>
   <head>TO THE TWO MOST VERTVOVS, <hi>and wel-learned young Gentlemen.</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. FRANCIS STEWART, Master of Mourray. <hi>And to</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN STEWART Sonne to the DVKE of LENNOX his GRACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Sirs</hi> whom to can this part of Institution, having Vertue for chiefe Obiect, so rightly appertaine, as to either of you two, who are no lesse vertuous, then learned? VVhy then will some saie, should I ioine two so worthie Gentlemen in one so vnworthie a dedication? But why rather thinke they, that I should separate thē, who are no waies nearer vnited in kind, thē alwaies euer in kindnes? So if I were but to name the one, surely I should intend the other: but intending this dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to two, I could not but name both. Adioine then, I exhorte you, these my meane practises vnto those good grounds of vertuous speculations yee haue both so happily laid, and continue in your study of Philosophy (as <hi>Cicero</hi> said in great commendation of <hi>Cato</hi> the second) <hi>non ita disputandi causâ, sed ita viuendi.</hi> In so doing you shall shine in vertue like the two <hi>Cherubims</hi> placed respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue mutuallie on the top of the propitiatorie, and shall shew your selues not mere and ordinary agents, but that ye are worthy patternes propounded vnto others Imitation.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>To both your worships humbly devoted I. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>