<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE CONFERENCE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108682_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12208</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5742.9</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE CONFERENCE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The copie of a leter, vvryten by a Master of Arte of Cambrige, to his friend in London : concerning some talke past of late betvven tvvo vvorshipful and graue men, about the present state, and some procedinges of the Erle of Leycester and his friendes in England. Conceyued, spoken and publyshed, vvyth most earnest protestation of al duetyful good vvyl and affection, tovvardes her most excellent Ma. and the realm, for vvhose good onely it is made common to many</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 199, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="3" facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE OF</hi> THE CONFERENCE.</head>
   <p>
      <label>SCHOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAR.</label>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot long before the last Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masse, I vvas requested by a letter from a verye vvorshypfull and graue gentleman, vvhose sonne vvas then my pupyle in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, to repaire vvyth my said scholar, to a certain house of his neare London, and ther to passe ouer the holie dayes in his companie: for that it vvas determyned that in Hyllarye ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> folovving, his said sonne should be placed in some Inne of Chauncerie, to folovv the studie of the common lavv, and so to leaue the vniuersitie. This request vvas grateful vnto me both in respect of the tyme, as also of the mater, but especialie of the companie. For that, as I loue much the yong gentleman, my pupile, for his tovvardlines in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, learning, and vertue: so much more do I reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his father, for the riper possession of the same ornamētes, &amp; for his great vvisdom, experience, and graue iudgement in affaires of the vvorld that do occurre: but namlie touching our ovvn countrie, vvherin truelie I do not remember to haue heard anie man in my lyfe, discourse more substantialie, indifferentlie, &amp; vvyth lesse passion, more loue and fidelitie then I haue heard him: VVhich vvas the cause that I toke singular delite to be in his cōpanie, &amp; refused no occasion to enioie the same. VVhich also he perceiuing, dealt more openlie &amp; confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vvith me, then vvith many other of his friendes, as by the relation folovving may vvell apeare.</p>
   <pb n="4" facs="4"/>
   <p>VVhen I came to the forsaid house by London, I found ther among other friendes, an auncient man that professed the lavv, and vvas come from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don<note place="margin">The per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons and place of this con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference.</note> to kepe his Christmasse in that place, vvyth vvhom at diuers former tymes I had bene vvel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, for that he haunted much the companie of the said gentleman my friend, and vvas much trusted and vsed by him in maters of his profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and not a litle beloued also for his good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation, notvvythstanding some difference in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion betvven vs. For albeit, this lavvyer vvas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to be a Papist, yet vvas it vvyth such modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reseruation of his duetie tovvardes his Prince and countrie, and proceedinges of the same: as he seemed alvvaies to giue ful satisfaction in this point to vs that vvere of contrarie opinion.</p>
   <p>Nether did he let to protest often tymes vvith<note place="margin">A Tempe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rat Papist</note> great affection, that as he had manie friends and kinsfolke of cōtrarie religion to him self: so did he loue them neuer the lesse for their different consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but leauing that to God, vvas desirous to do them anie friendship or seruice that he could, vvith al affection, zeale, and fidelitie. Neither vvas he vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or obstinat in his opinion, and much lesse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochful in speech (as manie of them be) but vvas content to heare vvhat soeuer vve should say to the contrarie (as often vve did:) and to read anie boke also that vve delyuered hym, for hys in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</p>
   <p>VVhich temperat behauiour, induced this gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man &amp; me, to affect the more his companie, &amp; to discourse as freelie vvyth him in al occurrentes, as if he had bene of our ovvn religion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>