<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108377_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15351.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108377</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The relection of a conference touching the reall presence. Or a bachelours censure of a masters apologie for Doctour Featlie. By L.I. B. of Art, of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Lechmere, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 377, 388-393, 396-600, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="26"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now more thē a yeere, COVRTEOVS READER, since first I saw the <hi>Sacrilege</hi> of M. Featlie, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he hath adioyned a <hi>Conference</hi> or Disputation had in Paris long agoe with my Lord of Chalcedon. This Conference being short I presently read it ouer, and liked so well some fragmēts of my Lords Answer which the Minister hath imparted, that I desired to see the whole: but could not then get a coppie.</p>
   <p>Hauing lighted now at leingth on a Latine one, and liking it excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well, I haue thought good to translate it, and impart it vnto others by the print: partly because it is not easilie found by such as do seeke after it, the Conference being past
<pb n="3" facs="26"/>
almost twenty yeeres agoe; and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly also because the Minister (who would seeme to haue a Coppie) doth cite imperfectlie my Lords answers, putting words or peeces together at his pleasure, and sometimes adding: and obscuring the sence which in the Relation it selfe I find to be distinct and cleere.</p>
   <p>He hath also striuen to make good his former Arguments; &amp; inuoluing them in a new discourse, hath thrust in, heere &amp; there, what he thought good: wherefore for their sakes that are vnlearned, I will, as oft as there is cause, adde a note; and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the new maske of words, will let the Reader see, that after all his <hi>washing, those Ethiopians haue not changed their complexion:</hi> and that now this <hi>second</hi> time of their comming on his Errand, they neede not any other Answer then that was giuen them before.</p>
   <p>In one of his Epistles before the booke I mentioned, he demands to see another <hi>leap;</hi> which may be shewed
<pb n="4" facs="27"/>
him in good time, meane while you may be pleased to measure this, which the minister would not haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne himselfe to chronicle, had he not thought it to be extraordinarie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>