<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE SACRED MAIESTIE OF MY SOVERAIGNE LORD AND MASTER, King CHARLES.</title>
           <author>King, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108022_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14334</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14965</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108022</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE SACRED MAIESTIE OF MY SOVERAIGNE LORD AND MASTER, King CHARLES.</title>
                 <author>King, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition vpon the Lords prayer : Deliuered in certaine sermons, in the cathedrall church of S. Paul. By Henry King Archdeacon of Colchester, and residentiary of the same church</title>
                 <author>King, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Partridge, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 365, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE SACRED MAIESTIE OF MY SOVERAIGNE LORD AND MASTER, King CHARLES.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Gracious Sir;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I haue had two Masters, I neuer had but one Patron. When by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Blessed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my first Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Master, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what was done to disproue that (since con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed)
<pb facs="3"/> scandall, touching my Fathers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolt from his Religion, I then addressed my selfe to Your Princely protection, which You so liberally afforded, that my emboldned Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty afterwards instructed me to presume vpon Your Goodnesse in the like kinde. I confesse, this weake testimony of my seruice in Gods Church, tooke life from the Example of Your Glorious Fathers worke (I meane that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Meditation</hi> of <hi>His</hi> vpon <hi>this Prayer</hi>) and my purpose was to haue dedicated it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him, as an humble acknowledgement of the many gracious encouragements which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from his owne mouth, in the times of my Attendance on Him. But though my Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose dyed with Him, my Obligation did not. That liues in You, whose vouchsafed fauour both deriu'd and increased it, by assuming mee to Your Seruice, when the consideration of mine owne inabilitie, and the losse of my Master made mee content to lose my relation to the Court. Then, Gracious Sir, since it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally descends on you by Two Titles, both as His Executor, and My Master, bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed once more to enlarge the bounty of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation,
<pb facs="3"/> and to receiue this Tribute from his hand who is ambitious of nothing, but leaue to weare Your Cognisance, and to write Your Name in the Front of his labours. This affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Goodnesse and my gratitude will sucessiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prompt Deuotion, by making it my daily practice to pray for the addition of all Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings vpon your Royall selfe, with that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Loyalty which fits</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humbly deuoted Seruant, HENRY KING.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>