<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108881_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5882</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108881</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A modest and reasonable examination, of some things in vse in the Church of England, sundrie times heretofore misliked : and now lately, in a booke called the (Plea of the innocent:) and an assertion for true and Christian church policy, made for a full satisfaction to al those, that are of iudgement, and not possessed with a preiudice against this present church gouernment, wherein the principall poynts are fully, and peaceably aunswered, which seeme to bee offensiue in the ecclesiasticall state of this kingdome. The contentes whereof are set downe in the page following. By William Couell, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Covell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 215, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the immoderate desire of reformation in some men had not extended it selfe further than eyther Religion or reason would wel permit, and especially at that time when thankfulnesse exacted from vs all something like a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath for that blessed Rest continued to this Church by the meanes of our dread Souereigne this cause and some others not yet published had with their vnworthy authors slept in a long and a charitable silence, and whereas the miraculous blessings bestowed and continued vpon this land could no otherwise rightly be vnderstood, than the true effectes of that Church which was planted in it (seeing as S. <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Haec est charitas expectanda, haec est charitas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior imperio, si fides tuta sit qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> seruat imperium. Ambrose. ep.</hi> 31. <hi>ad Valentinianū.</hi> The Assertion for Church policie.</note>
      <hi>That is Charitie to be expected, that is Charitie greater than the Empire, if that faith bee inuiolate which preserueth the Empire.</hi>) I thought it vnfit to let these men vnderstand that the peace of this Church was litle beholding to their paines, who in the middest of an vniuersall ioy soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a seditious Alarum to a second warre which as it could be no lesse than inconsiderate Zeale in some of the Tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> to drawe their swords against their Reuerend Religious Fathers as if with <hi>Aaron</hi> they had beene guiltie of erecting a Golden Calfe; so we hope, in the opinion of the most seuere, our defence shall neither be thought needlesse, nor out of season; wherein peraduenture our labour is of lesse vse, because we encounter in particular men of no greate authoritie in this Church, whom our directions were first to haue answered in another manner, but finding that to follow their steps had beene onely but to tread often in the same pathes which were wearisome in themselues and could haue brought little aduantage to this publike cause, we rather resolued (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the approbation of authoritie to giue allowance) to defend a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, weighty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ighteous and publike <hi>Church gouernment,</hi> than onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue and confute some particular obscure, and priuate men; for accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing gaineth not that admittance in the eares of indifferent Readers, which defending doth, and herein I may safely protest I looked at no other scope in the labour and cost of this vnpleasing imployment than the discharge of my particular dutie, and the performance of that seruice which I owed vnto this Church, &amp; yet if I had known which I vnderstand since that some more of Master <hi>Hookers</hi> works had bene recouered from the iniurie of men and time once againe to speake in the defence of this truth, I woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> most willingly haue obserued the praecept of the Sonne of <hi>Sirach: Thou that art yong speake if need be, and yet scarcely when thou art twice asked:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 32.</note> for the same things (but who is able to speake the same things that he did?) being spoken by diuers are not the same, and for my selfe if any man thinke this defence a presumption, I may boldly say as <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>u</hi> did,<note place="margin">Iob. 32.</note>
      <hi>Behold I did wait vpon the words of the auncient and hearkened to their knowledge.</hi> But seeing wee are children of that Church whose pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie was enuied and peace hindered by the aduersaries of this cause, wee could not but let them vnderstand that the voyces of Angels, of
<pb facs="5"/>
men and of time and all against them; and if wee were in the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of them (as they bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st of number) but like the children of <hi>Ruben</hi> and the children of <hi>Gad,</hi> and the Tribe of <hi>Manasses</hi> in respect of all Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell besides, yet if they will needes send vs a message by <hi>Phyneas</hi> the sonne of <hi>Eleazar</hi> and ten Princes with him saying:<note place="margin">Iosua. 22.16.17.</note>
      <hi>What transgression is this that ye haue transgressed against the God of Israell to turne away this day from the Lord in that ye haue built you an Altar for to rebell this day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord? Haue wee too little for the wickednesse of</hi> Peor <hi>whereof wee are not cleansed this day though a plague came vpon the congregation of the Lord</hi>? Wee must aunswere them as they did: <hi>The Lord God of Gods, the Lord God of Gods he knoweth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vers. 22.</note>
      <hi>and</hi> Israell <hi>himselfe shall know, if by rebellion or by transgression against the Lord we haue done it, saue thou vs not this day. If wee haue built vs an Altar to returne away from the Lord eyther to offer burnt offerings or meat offerings, or to offer peace offerings thereon, let the Lord himselfe require it. And if wee haue not rather done it for feare of this thing, &amp;c. vnto vers.</hi> 30. Wee hope they will giue vs leaue if their Zeale make them iealous of any thing vsed or admitted in our Church, <hi>to tell them that these are witnesses betwixt them and vs. &amp;c.</hi> Betweene our forefathers, and our generations after vs to execute the seruice of the Lord before him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apud Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos non qui pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, sed qui facit contumelians miser est. Hier. Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t qui pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. In bona consc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiateneo, quis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis volens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>it fame meae, nolens addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> merced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> meae. Ne aestimet quis plus ponderis esse in alienoconuitio quam in testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> suo. Ambrose.</hi>
      </note> in our Lyturgie, in our prayers, in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and that neither their children, nor the children of any Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Church should say to our children in time to come, <hi>Yee haue no part in the Lord</hi>: and if for all this they cease not the heape reproaches vpon that Church, whose absolute gouernment they ought with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to imbrace, and with loue to honour, we must tell them as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> doth that amongest Christiās <hi>not he that suffereth, but he that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth reproach is wretched.</hi> Wherein surely of all that euer laboured in this cause, he endured most, &amp; with most patience, whom vertue crownd with much Honour in this life, and according to his owne propheticall word (ouercame whilest he suffered) and now triumpheth. And for my selfe (Gentle Reader) I resolue humbly to endure whatsoeuer it pleaseth the vsuall impatience of their furie to lay vpon mee, saying with Saint <hi>Austen,</hi> In a good conscience I speake it, <hi>Hee that willingly doth detract from my good name vnwillingly doth add to my reward.</hi> For I lay with Saint <hi>Ambrose, Let no man thinke that there is more weight in the slaunder of another, than in the testimonie of his owne conscience.</hi> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>