<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue to the Ingenious READER.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108593_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05601</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15717</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108593</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue to the Ingenious READER.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true and experimentall discourse, upon the beginning, proceeding, and victorious event of this last siege of Breda : With the antiquity and annexing of it, to the house of Nassaw, and the many alterations it hath suffered by armes, and armies, within these threescore yeares. Together with the prudent plots, projects, and policies of warre: the assailants and defendants matchlesse man-hood, in managing martiall affaires: the misery and manner of souldiers living, their pinching want, and fatall accidents: strange weapons and instruments used by both parties in severall conflicts. Lastly, their concluded articles, with the circumstances and ordering of the siege and victory. Being pleasant to peruse, and profitable to observe. Written by him who was an eye witnesse of the siege. William Lithgow</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue to the <hi>Ingenious READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Iudicious Lector:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou mayst admire to see my fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Quill come unto such a low flight, as the <hi>Belgian</hi> Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:<note place="margin">His booke of nineteene years travailes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by <hi>3.</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral voyages.</note> which formerly slighted (in the late and large Discourse of my long and fastidious Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes) this Westerne World: but made a step from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Rome:</hi> Nay, scarce of <hi>Rome</hi> it selfe, would my pen peruse any paines, till my face sighted <hi>Greece,</hi> and Easterne <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> Whence there my feete footing pedestrially many <hi>Regions</hi> in <hi>Asia,</hi> and thence consequently <hi>Voyaging</hi> in <hi>Affrica,</hi> by two severall turnes and Returnes. It is a wonder (I say) to behold my Remote Labours, fall now upon <hi>Breda</hi> in <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,</hi> our neighbour soile, divided from us only (as it were) by a Channel of the Sea. And yet reason fortifieth my intention, since now inability of body, restraineth me from any further lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching abroad, and my preteriat daies of long worne time, being stricken in age, retroverteth
<pb facs="3"/>
the ancient <hi>Proverbe</hi> backwards upon my selfe: To wit, <hi>That young men have wide eies abroad, and old men narrow eies at home:</hi> VVhich now I begin reciprocally to countercambiat, being of both sayings participant. But vnderstand me bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">A comparison betweene Gyants and Dwarfes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orded by Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; Virgil.</note> were not <hi>Conopas</hi> and <hi>Molon</hi> two little <hi>Dwarfes,</hi> as much Renowned in <hi>Pliny</hi> for their smalnesse, as those two huge and monsterous <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants Cyclops</hi> and <hi>Enceladus</hi> rest famous in <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil</hi> for their bignes. And why may not a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine produce a Mole-hill: for although, perhaps, this present matter seeme to thee as a Flie sitting upon an <hi>Elephants</hi> back, in comparison of those my rarer Relations formerly exhibited to the wide desirous World: yet now the time, the sight, the place, the subject, and the accidents about <hi>Breda,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he sight of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>reda incited <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he Author to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erforme this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orke.</note> command me, and have commanded me to leave a stampe of their Protractures to this present Age, and succeeding times. Which thou shalt not peruse like to flashing <hi>Currants,</hi> lying surmises, blind-folded Gazetoes, feined by Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticke imaginations, or frivolous reports of fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doubts. No, no, but receive and read this Worke from my owne occular experience, whereof I was a daily <hi>Testator.</hi> And it also besides, being grounded upon the soundest judgements of the best Officers there, but indeed more narrowly searched by me from the common souldiers,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>perience excelleth farre all flying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</note> who daily and nightly were incident unto the Tragicall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of the subject it selfe, from whom as from a fountaine, I have drawne the Christall truth of this Relation, so much as concerned their passive
<pb facs="3"/>
proofe and Knowledge, the rest and best relyeth upon my selfe.</p>
   <p>Neverthelesse <hi>(Gentle Reader)</hi> if this fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar stile seeme not to thee so accurate and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, as I have done heretofore in other Workes, impute the fault thereof to a disordered Leaguer, my miserable lying on cold straw, in straw huts, and unshifted apparrell, to the clangor of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, the ratling of Pikes, the hurling of shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Muskets,<note place="margin">The distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of an Army, to a pen-man▪</note> the clamour of tongues, the soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Trumpets, and the noise of Drums: where, when, and whilst I was in writing this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall Discourse, distempered my quietnes. Yet howsoever that turbulent time, crossed my Pilgrimagious paines, I have made it plaine to the ignorant, and intelligible to the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and withall to satisfie the apprehension of any curious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. And so I rest, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thee, as I leave my selfe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>To be thine, as thou art mine,</hi> William Lithgow.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>