<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my well beloued brother, health and increase of knowledge.</title>
           <author>Bradshaw, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108276_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108276</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my well beloued brother, health and increase of knowledge.</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The shepherds starre : now of late seene, and at this hower to be obserued merueilous orient in the East: which bringeth glad tydings to all that may behold her brightnes, hauing the foure elements with the foure capitall vertures in her, which makes her elementall and a vanquishor of all earthly humors. Described by a gentleman late of the right worthie and honorable the Lord Burgh, his companie &amp; retinue in the Briell in North-holland</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To my well beloued brother, health and increase of knowledge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rother, I haue made bolde to publish the booke which you left me to my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vse. I was moued thereunto by your friends, and my fauourets heere in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. The matter is adiudged by some of learning, not to be vnworthie of the light. I meane not that light which you meant, when you gaue it mee to commit it to Vulcane. But I haue saued it, and it shall saue you: if not from vniust vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of backbyting wordes: yet from iust occasion of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thoughtes. Manie will say, that an English booke of loue, is like a Marchpane, of which one may soone scale the walles, and leap into the Castle: for there is no foode in it to stay a hungrie stomack, nor substance in pleasures to peruse a learned Censure. Tis true, the argument of fond loue is feeble: because the subiect of the matter is but an abiect. And the Genus of the thing will decay, where the species is onely faire without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther qualities. But your scope is such you aime at, that you could not speake lesse of it, nor well say more. Sith the manner was as truely inacted, as the matter is duely reported. And seeing in al demaunds, there is but foure things to be knowen, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. You may easily resolue any one that shall carpe, with all these foure: For the strictnes of the intention, shall excuse the dulnes of the inuention. So I commit you to your delightes of those colde countries. From the Court at Greenewich, vpon Saint Georges day 1591 Aprill. 23.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your brother to commaund: <hi>Alexander Bradshaw.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>