<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR, WI∣sheth to all Merchants, health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108815_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14600</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16784</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108815</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR, WI∣sheth to all Merchants, health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The merchants new-royall-exchaunge : framed at Roan, and brought ouer to be set vp in England. Or, A law-booke for English merchants</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_statement">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR, <hi>WI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth to all</hi> Merchants, <hi>health.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Merchants, the King our soueraigne Lorde (in whose bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, Iustice and Right, liue in safe protection) knowing what Priuiledges, not onely He, and his Predecessors, but also all the Romane Emperours, haue graunted vnto you, in regard of the Trade of Merchandize, and the order of Exchange, both of gold and siluer: hauing made you thereof absolute Iudges, for the ease of all other Iudges, who in such cases can doe nothing, without calling you to be Arbitrators. For the better administration therfore, of Iustice to his subiects, in all such cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which in times past were reserued to your vnderstandings: And for that
<pb facs="14"/>you may perceiue your authoritie and iurisdiction, not to be a new thing, or of late deuised, (but first founded by the Greekes, from whom the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines haue taken their groundes, I haue thought good, for your more ease, brieflie to comprehend and to set downe in writing (although not all) yet at the least a good part of your power and authoritie; And to shew you in a manner the Kings pleasure, how you may proceed and keepe your auncient Priuiledges, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting of your authoritie, you may speedily proceed, to iudge of all such differences, as doe appertaine to your knowledge. Desiring you, to take this in good part, &amp; to defend the same against all those, that will enuie, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly me; but your selues.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>