<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE
to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108196_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04988</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15137</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE
to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Catholicke apologie against the libels, declarations, advices, and consvltations made, written, and published by those of the League, perturbers of the quiet estate of the realme of France : Who are risen since the decease of the late Monsier, the Kings onely brother. B E.D.L.I.C</title>
                 <author>Belloy, Pierre de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aggas, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 99, 90-139 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE
to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Christian and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Frenchman, neuer
was there offered bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
meanes then at this
time to discouer and
smel out the subtelties
of our enemies, &amp; with
what money Sathan vsually paieth his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
whē we see some of thē so blinded,
that beeing vppon the poynt of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction,
they promise to themselues all
assuraunce, still coueting to conceale their
abhominable wickednesse, with sleights,
shiftes and lyes. Neuerthelesse, when they
do most hide themselues they are foonest
spied. For, to say the trueth, what goodlier
or more apparant pretēce could the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbers
of the quiet of our Fraunce take
holde of, then Religion and the reliefe of
the people: but as the enemie of trueth
hath allured thē vnto him by lyes, so hath
<pb facs="3"/>
hee for their repaste left them no other
foode vpon his Table, and yet doth that
also faile them, when they make it an vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
messe, and trueth remaineth Mistresse.
According hereto, the lyes and horrible
slaūders, that to this day haue bene spued
foorth against the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> &amp; the
Lord Prince of <hi>Condie,</hi> by certaine straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
enemies to this Crowne &amp; the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Progenie, vnder the pretence of zeale
of Religion doth ouerthrowe them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
cōtinually they haue sought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade
our souraigne Lord the King and
all the French Nation, that these Princes
were his euill seruaunts, Rebels, and diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient
persons, enemies to his Estate, in
the preseruation and encrease whereof,
they haue greater interest then any other
worldly person next vnto his Maiestie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
whom they haue the honor very nerely
to appertaine. As also in truth, we are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely
to giue GOD thankes, especially, in
that after so many false and slaunderous
inductions made vnto the most Christian
Maiestie against these two Princes, his
good kinsmen and most faithfull subiects
and seruants (by whose reliefe this feeble,
weake and pale Realme hath oftentimes
<pb facs="3"/>
escaped falling) it hath pleased him to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
the Kings eyes, &amp; to let him perceiue
that all the illusions vnto him presented,
tended only to the ouerthrow of himself,
his Crowne and Estate, in offering hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
to his viewe one thing in liewe of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
For herevpon his Maiestie smelling
out the causes of passed mischiefe, hath fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
in earnest done as the good Phisitiō,
who whē he seeth his Patient pale, weake,
faint, and grieuously sicke, beginneth his
cure with bringing him to his bed, &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging
him frō all painfull toyle, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
him to take some rest: euen so our
King, casting his eyes vpō his poore realm
afflicted with ciuill warres which so long
haue bene kindled vnder a false and slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous
pretence, to the end to begin the
cure, hath first sought to set it in peace,
that after some time of rest he might haue
better opportunitie to heale the rest of
the causes of the disease, &amp; to put from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
him those who vnder his authoritie
had by their false &amp; wicked perswasiōs so
hardly entreated it. Which when his euill
Councellors perceiued, &amp; seeing that they
could no longer goe forward in the same
path, they haue sought with open play to
<pb facs="4"/>
compasse that which so lōg they had craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely
practised, &amp; now haue plainly shewed
that it was the State &amp; Crowne that they
leueled at, procuring the writing of diuers
Libels aduices and consultations of their
suffragās, to the end not only to diminish
and blemish the King of <hi>Nauarres</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
&amp; lawfull succession, if it should
please God to worke his will of the Kings
Maiestie without leauing any issue Male,
but also to aduaūce their own false, slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous
and supposed titles and pretēces.
Howbeit, although the said Lord King of
<hi>Nauarre</hi> neede not yet to pleade his cause
or presently to aunswere all these sleights
and counsailes of the wicked, in respect of
the sufficient terme &amp; small likelihood of
occasion euer to put the same in executiō,
cōsidering the King is (thāks be to God)
yong, in health, &amp; in good disposition, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the small interest that in my
opinion the sayd Lord King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi>
pretendeth to any such successiō, as being
a Prince both wise &amp; circumspect, &amp; such
a one as hath not so smal forecast but that
he knoweth vndoubtedly, that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
wealth, reliefe, good hap &amp; contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
that may redound to him cōsisteth in
<pb facs="4"/>
the prosperitie, health, &amp; long and happie
life of the King his Lord, to the ende per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually
to be vnder him the same that he
is, to liue vnder his liking &amp; in his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
wherby &amp; vnder the fauour wherof
he shalbe not only preserued from the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiraties
which his enemies worke against
him, but also, which is more, if it please
God to encrease him, he shal alwaies be by
the King fauoured &amp; aduanced, vnto whō
he hath the honor to be the first Prince of
his bloud. Neuerthelesse, how euer it be, I
do not thinke that any man at this day cā
with reason and iudgement conceiue any
bad or sinister opinion of the sayde Lorde
King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> though he lay open his
iust causes, sith those that haue no right,
and for whō there can be no likelihood at
all, are so impudent, rash, &amp; vndiscreete, as
to bring to the barre a matter wherevpon
euen their most affectionate seruāts durst
not before haue thought: which to saye
the trueth, is one of the cōsideratiōs that
moued me to set hand to the pen, to the
aunswering of such diffamatorie Lybelles,
discourses, aduices, &amp; cōsultatiōs, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
this yeere haue come to my hands: and
I protest that I haue done it without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="5"/>
cōmaundemēt or commission of the
sayd Lord King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> vnto whom I
neuer had the honor to approach, neither
is it of any affectiō or desire to aduaunce
the Religiō that he professeth, sith my self
am and all my life time haue bene a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,
and liued vnder the authoritie of
the Apostolicke Romish Church: But the
onely cause hath bene that being borne a
Frenchman, I haue thought it my duetie
to vphold the rightful cause of the French
Princes, vnto whome, after his soueraigne
Maiestie, &amp; for whose seruice, we are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
bounde and holden to procure all
honor, wealth, &amp; prosperitie, to maintain
and defend them from slaūders and such
deceipts as Sathan would stirre vp against
their excellēcie &amp; greatnesse: besides that
euery mā may perceiue that these Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
are kindled to the vtter ruine, losse &amp;
fubuertion of this miserable Realm, so as
the loue of my Countrey, Christian piety,
and that compassiō that I take in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
my fellow Citizens and my self with
them in daunger to consume our selues in
that fire that by those ciuill warres, which
vnder this cursed and detestable pretence
are like to bee kindled, will seaze vpon al
<pb facs="5"/>
degrees, haue beene to mee as a spurre to
hasten my penne to aunswere these dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
writings, fearing least the people
should suffer themselues to be won there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
&amp; so might withstād y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> truth &amp; equitie
if euer occasiō to debate thereof were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred,
or that these pretēders should pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poūd
or bring this cōtrouersie in questiō.</p>
   <p>I doe therefore most humbly desire the
French &amp; Catholike Reader (laying a way
al passions) to cal to mind first the bond &amp;
commaundement wherein by God he is
bound to the King and the Princes of his
bloud according to the order and natural
succession by the Lawes of this Crowne.
Secondly, the loue of his Countrey, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
wee all are men, all Christians, all
Frenchmen, and al louers of our selues, &amp;
that if we should stoope vnder the yoke of
these tyrāts that would bring vs into sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection
and abuze vs with lyes, falshoodes
and forged titles, they would afterward
beare vs the like minde, and their faith as
tainted &amp; corrupt as by corruption, fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
and vntrueth, they had abused our
simplicitie, and suborned &amp; withdrawne
vs from the obedience of our true and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
Lords. For, in asmuch as they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riders
<pb facs="6"/>
riders and contemners of God, in whose
name they haue dared to begin, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured
that the most abhominable fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
that euer was, might be made manifest
to all, it can not be that wee should looke
for any other thing of thē, but that hope
that they haue conceiued to entreate and
handle vs after the Turkish manner, with a
more detestable &amp; daungerous inquisitiō
then that which now raigneth vnder the
Spanish tyrannie. Let therefore euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
diligently aud faithfully employ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
to serue our King and the Princes of
his bloud, whose cause we ought euē with
the price and venture of our liues to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
to the end the state of this Realme
being assured, at the least our childrē may
liue peaceably vnder the obediēce of their
naturall Lords, who by that meanes shall
haue the greater occasion to cherrish and
entreate them well as they haue done vs,
remembring that with the grace of God
by our fidelitie &amp; loyaltie they haue bene
preserued in that greatnesse and dignitie
wherein the diuine goodnes hath suffered
them to bee borne in this Realme to the
glorie of the King of Kings, to whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
it be and remaine euerlastingly. So be it.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>