<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The iudgement of a godly learned man touching this matter, sent mee in a Letter.</title>
           <author>C., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108097_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04901</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15040</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The iudgement of a godly learned man touching this matter, sent mee in a Letter.</title>
                 <author>C., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutation of monstrous and horrible heresies, taught by H.N. and embraced of a number, who call themselues the Familie of Loue : by I. Knewstub. Seene and allowed, according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Knewstubs, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sergier, Richard 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 94, 28 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The iudgement of a godly learned</hi> man touching this matter, sent mee in a Letter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I did first heare that you had taken in hand a confutation of the heresie, or rather of the heape of heresies, which some yeeres past comming out of Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land arriued in Englande, and receiued in many places secret, but dangerous and yet too too safe entertainment: I did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare an euil, then hope for a good issue of that your godly labour. For considering first the dark and deceauing words, the new phrases, and blasphemous allegoryes wherwith the Family of Loue, fill their bookes, which speaches may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded thus if they will, and otherwise if they liste, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with euery change of person in that family as he is more or lesse vrged, or able to answere, or as may most deceiue or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde a mischief: Secondarily noting that they deny princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and groundes of Religion, scorning the ground of all grounds, the most holy Scriptures of God, &amp; that in the most holy poyntes touching the person and offices of Christ Iesus, our iustification and sanctification: thirdly finding that they haue a double hart &amp; a chaungeable tounge, renouncing and recanting before Magistrates, and vpon their commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the world that they maintained, and are resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued notwithstanding to maintaine still in sworne obedience to <hi>H.N.</hi> according to the like practise of counterfaiting Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, who make shew of religion hauing sworne hearts to the Pope, whose dispensation either they haue, or trust in some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling reliques and ceremonyes from Rome: for these cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses I thought it some danger to lay open suche blasphemyes, such escapes of an euill and erronious conscience, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning long agoe in the ancient heretiques, the <hi>Priscilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistes, Montanists, Pelagians, Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists &amp;c.</hi> and hauing been long time buried in the botome of
<pb facs="17"/>
Hell, are not thence to be raked any more. Also I thought it almost impossible to meet with such an inconstant and slippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry serpent, that hath so obscure wordes now to hide, and now to conuay her poyson, thereby to auoyde the wholesome reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by the worde, and iust punishment by the magistrate. But, my good brother, these my doubts grew from the eye I had to their will and way: finding the Serpent so subtile to charme others, &amp; yet him selfe to shut his care so against the trueth, that he will not heare the voyce of the charmer, charme hee neuer so wisely: and that it is as hard to finde out his way, as the way of a Ship that hath sayled through the sea.</p>
   <p>For afterwarde considering that Antichrist did bring (as he thought) to perfection the mystery of iniquitie in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king force of Satan, in all powers and signes and lying woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and in all deceit of vnrighteousnesse, as S. Paul prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied, &amp; we in these last ages, haue clerely seene: and that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding God hath already, almost altogither consumed that man of sin with the spirit of his mouth, which is his word preached in the Gospel. I acknowledge with praise to God the father in Iesus Christ for that sword of the spirit, that two edged swoord, that it is able either to heale, or to wounde to death all aduersary power, be it either in al impietie of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, or in all corruption of maners. Yea if <hi>H.N.</hi> were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all his sinne, and washed from all corruption: If he in deede were, as he is in the fancie of his familie an angell from heauen, or by an other transubstantiation more then an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changell, or that which they affirme and I dare not write: yet teaching otherwise then we haue receiued from the holy Prophets and Apostles, he is to be holden accurssed, and his Gospell of the kingdom with all other his doctrine to be had in abhomination. They that pray, are thus to pray against such heresies: they that write, are so, vpon occasion to write, and Magistrates are in a zeale of Gods house to put on that minde, that the holy trueth may bee exalted, and all heresies rooted out to the glory of GOD, and the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
<pb facs="17"/>
of his Churche from those damnable waies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many, not esteeming nor seeking the trueth, are sooner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, then they can feare destruction. Therfore you haue doone wel in the Lord, drawing out that sworde of the worde of God, to make a separation betweene thought and thought, betweene practise and practise, betweene secret &amp; open paths of errour and contempt, betwene ioynts and marrow, betwene soule and spirit, that all the outgoings &amp; escapes and dennes wherein these heresies either lye in waite and worke against the trueth, or hide themselues from discouery, may be disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and the bright face of the trueth appeare to the great glory of God, ouerthrowing of al error, cōuerting those of that family of Loue, whom he hath loued and in mercie will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, deliuering their eyes from blindenesse and feete frō fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: and to stay those that might, for want of the voice of the trumpet, sodenly fal into the enemies hand, to be caried away into the miserable captiuitie of those heresies, and to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death that followeth thē as their iust reward. Also the Magistrate by such a manifest discouery of those blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies against God, against his Christ, against his worde, shall more &amp; more see into the great danger of their horrible sect, and find necessary cause to ioyne with the worde to cut it off, lest in the end they with their brethrē the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themselues asmuch against the holy and necessary autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritte of magistrates, as they doe already against God and his word, by whome Princes raigne &amp; receiue their blessed peace and safetie. Against which Magistrates this practise they haue vsed and still doe vse, abusing their holy place of Iustice: they recant in woordes, without recantation in heart (as I noted before) holding it for a rule, that they ought not to destroy the Temple of GOD (whiche is say they in a grosse and absurde interpretation) our body: and therefore we will not be brought to persecution and death. Making a rule against the rule of Christ, and against the most won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull practise thereof in him selfe, and his holy Martyres:
<pb facs="18"/>
who loosing their life heere haue found it in heauen: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their bodies burnt to ashes in hope they looke for the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful resurrection of the same bodyes at the comming of Iesus Christ. Therfore, my very good brother, I thanke God for your labours praying his maiestie to blesse them, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders may see and repent their offence: that others yet free, may remaine by such instruction free for euer from those and such heresies: and may be more &amp; more armed against error with the trueth, and comforted therein to their saluation.</p>
   <p>Praying also that God would continue with increase that spirit of zeale and wisdome in the heart of our most excellent soueraine the Queene &amp; other in authoritie vnder her, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse those fantasticall and erronious spirits, being indeed the true succession of those ancient <hi>Catharists</hi> &amp; <hi>Puritans,</hi> who thought themselues not to sinne, but actually to bee possessed with absolute holinesse and purenesse. For so those thinke of themselues, and plainly affirme it of their illuminate elders. But howsoeuer they seduce some goodly and zealous men &amp; women of honest and godly conuersation, placing them at the porch of their Synagogue, to make a shewe of holinesse, and to stand there as baites and stalles to deceiue others: yet alas who can without blushing vtter the shame that is committed in the inwarde roomes, and as it were in the heart of that Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Satan. These are the things I haue thought tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the booke, and a testimonie of my greate ioy touching the same. And besides the good I haue already noted this confutation shal testifie to all ages at large that the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed gouernment of our gratious soueraigne the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie suffereth neither Papists nor other heretiques to goe vncōfuted or vnpunished, howsoeuer first in great abundance of singular clemencie it pleaseth her to seeke their saluation &amp; draw on their effectuall conuersation. Which blessed fruite of that singular clemencie the Lord God graunt in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, and a perfect peace to this Church for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours assuredly in the Lorde <hi>W. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>