<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108369_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05186</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15320</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108369</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of ghostes and spirites walking by nyght : and of strange noyses, crackes, and sundry forewarnynges, whiche commonly happen before the death of menne, great slaughters, [and] alterations of kyngdomes. One booke, written by Lewes Lauaterus of Tigurine. And translated into Englyshe by R.H</title>
                 <author>Lavater, Ludwig</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Watkins, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 220 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eyng desirous (gentle Reader) to exercise my self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> with some translation, at vacant tymes, and seeyng, that since the Gospel hath benne preached, this one question, touchyng the appearyng of spirites and soules departed, hath not ben much handled amongst vs, and therefore many, otherwise wel affected in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, vtterly ignoraunt herein, I thought it not amisse to take in hande some good and learned treatise con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter. VVherin as many haue both lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, paynfully, &amp; religiously traueyled: so amongst others, none in my iudgement hath more handsomely and eloquently, with more iudgement and better me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode discoursed the same, then <hi>Lewes Lauaterus,</hi> minister of Tigurine. Others haue handled it in dede wel, but yet <hi>nihil ad nostrum hunc,</hi> beyng eyther to short, or to long, or to darke, or to doubtful, or otherwyse so confused, that they leaue the reader more in suspēce in the end, then they founde hym in the begynnyng. As for mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Lauaterus</hi> his discretion herein, I wyll no otherwise commend it, then to desire the reader to view, &amp; iudge hym selfe. For thus much at the first syght he shal see: A cleare methode, with a familier and easie style, the matter throughly handled <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> on both sides, so that nothyng seemeth to be wantyng, nor any thyng redoundyng. And if it be true that Horace saith, <hi>omne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ulit punctum, qui miscuit vtile dulci,</hi> that is, He wynneth the price, that ioyneth pleasure with profite: I thinke this author may also in this respect be pronounced <hi>victor,</hi> &amp; adiudged to the best game. For he so intreateth this serious and terrible matter of spitites, that he now and then insertyng some strange story of Monkes, Priestes,
<pb facs="2"/>
Fryers, &amp; such like counterfeyts, doth both very lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly display their falsehood, and also not a litle recreate his reader: and yet in the ende he so aptly concludeth to the purpose, that his hystories seeme not idle tales, or impertinent vagaries, but very truethes, naturally falling vnder the compasse of his matter. And howe profitable this his work is, those may best iudge, which are most ignorant in this question, some thinking eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry small motion and noyse to be spirites, and some so fondely perswaded that there are no spirites, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better enfourmed herein by this author, I suppose wyl confesse his worke to haue done them some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: if knowledge be profitable, and ignorance discom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modious. And agayne, those which beyng hytherto borne in hande that mens soules returne agayne on earth, crauyng helpe of the lyuyng, and haue spent much of their substance on idle Monkes &amp; Fryers, to relieue them, wyll confesse the lyke. For when they shall see they haue ben falsly taught, &amp; that they were not the soules of men whiche appeared, but eyther falsehood of Monkes, or illusions of deuyls, franticke imaginations, or some other friuolous &amp; vaine perswa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sions, they wil thinke it profitable to haue knowen the trueth, aswel to auoyde error hereafter, as to saue their money from such greedy caterpillers. Some also whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be otherwise well trayned vp in religion, and yet not knowyng what to thynke of these matters, wil not iudge their labour euyl imployed, nor the worke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, wherby thei may be brought out of doubt, and knowe certainly what to beleue. There be many also, euen nowe a dayes, which are haunted and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with spirites, and knowe not howe to vse them selues, who when they shall learne howe a Christian
<pb facs="3"/>
man ought to gouerne hym selfe, beyng vexed with euyl spirites, wyl thynke it a very profitable poynt of doctrine, that shal teache them to direct them selues. Profitable therefore it is, and shalbe, no doubt, vnto many, and disprofitable vnto none, except perchaunce vnto popishe Monkes and Priestes, who are like here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to lose a great part of their gaynes, which somtimes they gathered together in great abundance, by their deceiptfull doctrine of the appearyng of dead mens soules. But this their wicked and deuyllishe doctrine, together with all the patches and appendices therto belongyng, he so notably teareth and cutteth in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that I am well assured they shal neuer be hable to cobble and cloute them vp agayne. And this doth he with suche a moderation of breuitie and tediousnes, that I may rightly say: He hath sayde well, and not to much, and written truely, and not to litle.</p>
   <p>Nowe as touchyng my translation, although I haue not made hym speake with like grace in Englishe, as he doth in Latine: yet haue I nor changed his meanyng, nor altered his matter, endeuouring my selfe rather to make thee vnderstande what thou readest, then to smoothe and pollishe it with fine and picked wordes, which I graunt others myght haue done more exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitely, and perchaunce I my selfe also somewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yf I would haue made therof a study and labour, and not a recreatiō &amp; exercise. But howsoeuer I haue done herein, verily good reader, I trust thou wylt take it in good part, which is al that I esteeme: yf any man shal mislike therof, let hym amende it. I trust it be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to testifie my good wil to do thee good, and to let thee vnderstande the authors meanyng.</p>
   <closer>Fare well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>