<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108762_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06134</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16619</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108762</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The consent of time : disciphering the errors of the Grecians in their Olympiads, the vncertaine computation of the Romanes in their penteterydes and building of Rome, of the Persians in their accompt of Cyrus, and of the vanities of the Gentiles in fables of antiquities, disagreeing with the Hebrewes, and with the sacred histories in consent of time. VVherein is also set downe the beginning, continuance, succession, and ouerthrowes of kings, kingdomes, states, and gouernments. By Lodovvik Lloid Esquire</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 722, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thinke my labour well bestowed, my rewarde sufficient, if my trauaile and good will be herein of the reader accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I accuse my selfe of some rashnesse to wade into those strong streames that haue caried the best learned to a labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth of errors, who in seeking consent of time by vncerteine computations of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> haue missed the square and perfect frame of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the streight and perfect line from <hi>Adam</hi> vnto <hi>Christ,</hi> without the which all prophane writers most grosly erre: for can any true accompt of time be made by the <hi>Romanes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, either from the building of their Citie which was from yeere to yeere, or by the censure of <hi>Lustrum,</hi> which the <hi>Grecians</hi> call <hi>Penteterides,</hi> which was from fiue yeere to fiue <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> yeere, or by the computation of their Indictions, which was from fifteene yeere to fifteene yeere, when neither the time of the building of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of appointing of <hi>Lustrum,</hi> or of the instituting of the indictions, are not yet knowen or agreed vpon? In like maner the olde <hi>Grecians</hi> from the time of <hi>Ninus,</hi> from the destruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> and last from the <hi>Olympiads</hi> so erred and became so fabulous in histories, and since frō their <hi>Olympiads,</hi> that <hi>Greece</hi> it selfe is called <hi>Grecia mendax:</hi> for the <hi>Olympiads</hi> is the generall cause of all errors, euen in the best learned: for <hi>Xenophon,</hi> who florished in the chiefe time of the <hi>Olympiads,</hi> yet <hi>fallax in his accusatur.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The like grosse error is in the computation of the <hi>Persians</hi> of the time of <hi>Cyrus.</hi> To speake of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> accompt from the one flowing of <hi>Nilus</hi> vnto another, from one <hi>Dynastia</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another: during which time they say, 340. kings reigned from the first <hi>Pharao</hi> called <hi>Amasis,</hi> vnto the last <hi>Amasis</hi> named also <hi>Pharao,</hi> farre from any true consent of time, it were super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous: by this meanes <hi>Hellanicus</hi> accused <hi>Acusilaus, Acusilaus Ephorus, Ephorus Timaeus, Timaeus Herodot,</hi> and <hi>Herodot</hi> accused <hi>Hesiodus.</hi> In briefe one so accused another, that all erred in
<pb facs="4"/>
consent of time, and that by reason of their false cōputation, without looking to the succession of the Patriarches, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuances of Iudges, reignes of kings, and without respect of the Iubilees which the <hi>Hebrues</hi> so obserued, that they coulde not erre: which if <hi>Plinie, Halicarnassaeus, Polybius, Diodorus,</hi> and the rest had obserued, they had not so disagreed, in a hundred, two hundred, three hundred, foure hundred yeeres, more or lesse from the sacred histories.</p>
   <p>Had they looked to the histories of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> they had found howe to auoide many inconueniences: for prophane writers of the <hi>Assyrian, Chaldean, Egyptian,</hi> and <hi>Persian</hi> histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries can not but erre, for that they wrote long after the time of these kingdomes. I haue therefore for the more assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of sound warrant answered the time with the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie of the Church, and haue withall followed the best authorities both in sacred and in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane histories, as farre as my simple iudgement can reache.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Lodowik Lloid.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>