<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL AFFLICTED CONSCIENCES VVHICH GRONE FOR SALVATION AND VVRASTLE VNDER THE crosse for the kingdome of Christ, grace peace and victorie in the Lorde Iesu our Sauiour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108973_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06492</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16965</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108973</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL AFFLICTED CONSCIENCES VVHICH GRONE FOR SALVATION AND VVRASTLE VNDER THE crosse for the kingdome of Christ, grace peace and victorie in the Lorde Iesu our Sauiour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie of M. Doctor Martin Luther vpon the Epistle of S. Paul to the Galathians : first collected and gathered vvord by vvord out of his preaching, and novv out of Latine faithfully translated into English for the vnlearned. Wherein is set forth most excellently th glorious riches of Gods grace</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 208, 211-282 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO ALL AFFLICTED CONSCIENCES VVHICH GRONE FOR SALVATION AND VVRASTLE VNDER THE crosse for the kingdome of Christ, grace peace and victorie in the Lorde Iesu our Sauiour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N fewe wordes to declare what is to be sayd for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of this worke, although in fewe wordes all can not be expressed that may be said, yet briefly to signifie that may suffice, this much we thought good to certifie thee, godly reader: that amongest many other godly english bookes in these our daies printed and translated, thou shalt finde but fewe, wherein either thy time shall seeme better bestowed, or thy labour better recompensed to the profite of thy soule, or wherein thou mayest see the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and veine of S. Paule more liuely represented to thee, then in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent reading of this present commentary vpon the epistle of S. Paule to the Galathians. In which, as in a myrrour or glasse, or rather as S. Stephen in the heauens being opened, thou mayst see and behold the admirable glory of the Lord and all the riches of heauen, thy saluation freely and onely by faith in Christe, his loue and grace toward thee so opened, thy victory and conquest in him so proued, the wrath of God so pacified, his lawe satisfied, the full kingdome of life set open, death, hell and hell gates, be they neuer so stronge, with all the power of sinne, flesh and the world vanquished, thy conscience discharged, all feares and terrours remoued, thy spirituall man so refreshed and set at libertie, that either thy heart must be heuier then lead, or the reading hereof will lift thee vppe aboue thy selfe, and giue thee to knowe that of Christe Iesu, that thy selfe shalt say thou neuer knewest before, though before thou knewest him right well.</p>
   <p>Such spiritual comfort, such heauenly doctrine, such experience and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of conscience herein is contained, such triumphing ouer Sathan and al his power infernall, such contempt of the lawe compared with the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, such an holy pride and exaltation of the beleuinge man (whom here he maketh a person diuine, the Sonne of God, the heire of the whole earth,
<pb facs="4"/>
conquerour of the world, of sinne of death and the deuill) with such phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and speeches of high cōtemplation, of Christ, of grace, of iustificatiō and of faith (which faith, saith he, transfigureth a man into Christ, and coupleth him more nere vnto Christ then the husband is coupled to his wife, and maketh a man more then a man), with such other mighty voices, full of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall glory and maiestie, as the like hath not bene vsed lightly of any wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter since the Apostles time, neither durst he euer haue vsed the same him selfe, had not greate experience and exercise of conscience by inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictes and profound agonies framed him thereunto, and ministred to him both this knowledge of spirite and boldenes of speech.</p>
   <p>And this commonly is the working and proceeding of Godes vocation, euer to worke thinges by the contrary: of infidelitie to make faith, of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to make riches, in misery to shew mercye, to turne sorrowe to solace, mourning to mirth, from afflictions to aduaunce to glory, from hell to bring to heauen from death to life, from darkenes to light, from thraldome to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie,<note place="margin">Samuul. 1. Esay. 41. 1. Cor. 1.</note> in wildernes to geue waters, the barren to make frutefull, of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that be not to make thinges to be, briefely to make all thinges of nought. Thus began God first to worke, thus he proceeded, thus he continueth, and so will to the worldes ende. The firste seede of promise next to Eue, was geuen to Sara: yet in what case was Eue before she had the promise? And in vvhat barrennes and despaire vvas Sara before she enioyed her welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Isaac? The like is to be said of the two mothers of two most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent children Samuel &amp; Iohn Baptiste, and yet what griefes &amp; sorrowes past ouer their heartes, being both past all hope in nature, before the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God did worke? Howe longe did Iacob the Patriarke serue in mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thraldome for his Rachel? In what excellent glorye was Ioseph ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted? yet what suffered he before of his brethren, and how longe imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? In what and howe longe seruitude were the sonnes of Israell before Moses was sent vnto them? and afterward in what distresse were they cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed on euery side whē the sea was forced to geue them place? After that againe, what an excellent land was promised and geuen vnto them, flowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with milke and hony? but how were they scourged before in the desert, and yet neither had they the lande, but their children? To ouerpasse many thinges here by the way, what an excellent worke was it of God to set vppe Dauid in his kingedome? Also what excellent promises were geuen to his throne? Yet how hardly escaped he with life? howe did the Lord mortifie and frame him to his hand before he placed him in quiet? Infinite it were to recite all. Briefely, in all the works of God this is vsuall to be seene, that he worketh euermore most excellent thinges by instrumentes most humble,
<pb facs="4"/>
and which seeme most furdest of. Which of al the Apostles did euer thinke, when Christ was so humbled and crucified vppon the tree, that they should euer see him againe? although he foretold them of his rising before: in so muche that Thomas did scarsely beleeue when he with his eies sawe him. What man would euer haue thought that Paule in the raging heate of his persecuting spirite would haue turned from a persecuter to such a profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor? from such infidelitie to such a faith? in so much that Ananias woulde scarsely beleue the Lord when he tolde him. Such is the omnipotencie of the Lorde our God, euer working lightly by the contrarye, especially when he hath any excellent thinge to worke to his own glory.</p>
   <p>After like sorte may we esteeme also of Martine Luther, who being firste a frear, in what blindnes, superstition and darkenes, in what dreames and dregges of munkishe idolatrye he was drowned, his historie declareth, witnes recordeth, and this booke also partly doth specifie. Whose religion was all in popish ceremonies, his zeale without knowledge, vnderstanding no other iustification but in workes of the law and merites of his owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge, onely beleuing the historie (as many doe) of Christes death and resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, but not knowing the power and strength thereof. After he had thus continued a longe space, more pharisaicall and zealous in these monkish waies then the common sorte of that order, at length it so pleased almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to beginne with this man: first to touch his conscience with some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse and feelinge of sinne, his mind with feares and misdoutes, whereby he was driuen to seeke further: So that by searching, seekinge, conferring, and by reading of S. Paule, some sparckles of better knowledge beganne by litle and litle to appeare, which after in time grew vp to greater encrease. But here it happened to him as commonlye it doth to all good Christians: The more that the true knowledge of Christe in him encreased, the more Sathan the enemy stirred with his fiery dartes, with doubtes and obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with false terrours and subtill assaultes, seeking by all meanes possible howe to oppresse the inward soule which would faine take his rest in Christe. In these spirituall conflictes and inward wrastlings, how greuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he was encumbred, fighting against incredulitie, errour and desperation, maruelous it is to consider: In so much, that three dayes and three nightes together he lay vppon his bedde without meate, drinke or any fleepe, like a deade man (as some of him doe write) labouringe in soule and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite vppon a certaine place of S. Paule in the third chapiter to the Rom. which was: <hi>Ad ostendendam iustitiam suā:</hi> that is, <hi>to shevv his iustice,</hi> thinking Christ to be sent to no other end but to shewe forth Gods iustice as an executor of the law, till at length, being aunswered and satisfied by
<pb facs="5"/>
the Lord touching the right meaninge of those wordes, signifying the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of God to be executed vppon his Sonne to saue vs from the stroke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he immediatly vppon the same started vp from his bedde, so confirmed in faith, as nothing afterward could appall him: Besides other manifold and greeuous tentations (which I speake not of) of all sortes and kindes, except onely of auarice, with the which vice onely he was neuer once tempted nor touched, as of him is writen by them that were conuersant with him.</p>
   <p>In this meane while, during these conflictes and exercises of M. Luther, which notwithstanding did him no hurt, but rather turned to his more furtherance in spirituall knowledge, Pope Leo the .x. sent a Iubiley with his pardons abroade through all Christian realmes and dominions, wherby he gathered together innumerable riches and treasure. The colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors wherof promised to euery one that would put ten shillinges in the box, licence to eate whitemeat and flesh in lent, and power to deliuer what soule he woulde out of purgatorye, and moreouer full pardon from all his sinnes, were they neuer so heynous. But if it were but one iote lesse then .x. shillings, they preached that it would profite him nothing. The abomination wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was so horrible, that when no other man durst speake, yet Luther could not of conscience holde his peace, but drawing out certaine articles, desired gently to dispute the matter, writing withall a most humble admonition to the Pope, submitting him selfe in most lowely wise to his censure and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the Pope thinkinge great scorne to be controlled of such a frear, tooke the matter so hoate, that he with all his Cardinals, with all the rable of Monkes and Frears, Bishops and Archbishops, Colleges and vniuersities, Kinges and Princes, with the Emperour also himselfe, were all vppon him. If the omnipotent prouidence of the Lord from aboue had not sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, what was it for one poore frear to haue endured all these sharpe assaultes of Sathan, all the violence of the whole world, hauinge no lesse then the soone, the moone and seuen starres (as they say) against him? being hated of men, impugned of deuilles, reiected of nations, by solemne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty condemned, distressed with infirmities, and with all maner of tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tried and proued. And yet for all these tentations such was his life, that (as Erasmus writing to Cardinall Wolsey affirmeth) none of all his enemies could euer charge him with any note of iust reprehension. Againe, such were his allegations out of the scripture, that Roffensis writing to Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, confesseth himselfe to be astonied at them.</p>
   <p>And thus much by way of preface touching the conflictes and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises of this man. Which we thought good to insinuate to the Christian reader for sundry purposes: First to note the mercifull clemencie of Christe
<pb facs="5"/>
our Sauiour in calling so superstitious and idolatrous a frear so graciously to such a light of his gospell, his grace in iustifying him, his might in preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him, his helpe in cōforting him, his glory in prospering him, one against so many, and so prospering him, that the whole kingedom of the Pope had no power either to withstand him, or to maintaine it selfe: Secondly for this respect also and purpose, that the reader considering the meruelous working of the Lord in this man, may the better credite the doctrine which he teacheth. And though his doctrine as touching a litle circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the sacrament can not be throughly defended, yet neither is that any greate maruell in him, who being occupied in weightier pointes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, had no leisure to trauell in the searching out of this matter, neither ought it to be any preiudice to all the rest which he taught so soundly of the weightier principles and groundes of Christes Gospell and our iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation onely by faith in Christ. And yet in the same matter of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not withstanding that he altereth somewhat from Zuinglius, stic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to nere to the letter: yet he ioyneth not so with the Papist,<note place="margin">Hereof reade more in the Apologie of the church of England, and in the booke of monuments fol. 992. Col. 2.</note> that he leaueth there any transubstantiation or idolatrie. Wherefore the matter being no greater then so, nor directly against any article of our crede, let not vs be so nice, for one litle wart to cast away the whole body. It were doutlesse to be wished, that in good teachers and preachers of Christ, there were no defect or imperfection. But he that can abide nothing with his blemish, let him, if he can, name any Doctor or writer (the scripture onely except) greke or latin, old or new, either beyond the Alpes or on this side the Alpes, or him selfe also, what so euer he be, which hath not erred in some sentence or in some exposition of holy scripture. But if he can not so doe, then let him learne by him selfe to beare with other, to take the best and leaue the worst (although there is no such matter in this booke to be feared, forasmuch as we hauing a respect to the simple haue purposely spū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out and omitted such stumbling places, being but few, which might offend) and to geue God thankes for any thing that is good, and namely for this which he hath geuen to vs by Luther, in opening to vs his grace, mercy and good will in his Sonne so excellently through the preaching of this man: who if he had not taught the difference betwene the lawe and the gospell, and set out to vs our iustification, victory and libertie by faith onely in Christ so plainely, so plentifully and so assuredly as he hath done, who euer durst haue bene so bold to open his mouth in such wordes, or so confidently to stand in this doctrine of faith and grace? For if there haue bene since the time of Luther, and be yet some, which openly defend that workes be necessary to saluation, where he before so mightely hath taught
<pb facs="6"/>
the contrary: what then would these haue done if Luther had not bene? who also did forewarne vs of the same, prophesying that after his time this doctrine of iustification would be almost extinguished in the church, as in certaine places experience beginneth partely to proue.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, so much as the Lord shall geue vs grace, let vs hold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly the comfortable doctrine of faith and iustification, &amp; not lose that the Lord so freely hath geuen, calling vppon the Lord with all obedience and diligence, to geue vs grace with S. Paule, not to refuse the grace whiche he bestoweth vppon vs, nor to be offended with this ioyfull do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as many be. And therefore as our duty was for our part to set it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, so our counsell is no lesse to euery studious reader thereof, to pray for grace, rightly to vnderstād that he readeth. For els, vnlesse the special grace of Christ doe helpe, hard it is to flesh and blood to comprehend this mysticall doctrine of faith onely. So straūge it is to carnall reason, so darke to the world, so many enemies it hath, that except the spirite of God from aboue doe reueale it, learning can not reach it, wisedome is offended, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is astonied, deuilles doe not knowe it, men doe persecute it. Briefely, as there is no way to life so easie, so is there none so hard: Easie to whom it is geuen from aboue: hard to the carnall sense not yet enspired. The igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce whereof is the roote of all errours, sectes and diuisions, not onely in all christendome, but also in the whole world. The Iewe thinketh to be saued by his Moses lawe, the Turke by his Alcoran, the philosopher by his morall vertues. Besides these, commeth an other sort of people, not so ill as the Iewe, nor so hethen as the philosopher, but hauing some part of both, which refuse not vtterly the name of Christ, but with Christ doe ioyne partely the law of Moses, partely the morall and naturall discipline of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy, and partely their owne ceremonies and traditions, to make a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect way to heauen. And these here in this commentary are called papists, of the Pope their author, being diuided within themselues more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an hundreth diuers sectes, orders and professions of Cardinales, Frears, Monkes, Nunnes, Priestes, Heremites, and other votaries. All which seeme to springe vp of no other cause but onely vppon ignorance of this doctrine. And no meruell: For take away this doctrine of iustification by faith onely in Christ, and leaue a man to his owne inuentions, what ende will there be of newe deuises? Such a perilous thing is it to erre in the first fundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whereuppon the higher ye build, the greater is the fall. And yet such builders are not without their proppes to hold vppe their workemanship of workes against this doctrine of iustifying faith, pretending for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence the testimonie of S. Iames, where he seemeth to attribute iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="6"/>
to workes and not to faith onely.</p>
   <p>Touching which matter of iustification, for as much as in the sequele of this treatise the author hath discoursed vpon the same at large, it shall not be much needefull to vse many wordes at this present. This briefely may suffice by way of preface, in a word or two to aduertise the christian reader, who so taketh in hand with profite and iudgement to reade this booke, that in him two things are specially to be required: First to reade it wholy togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not by peeces and partes here and there, but to take it in order as it lyeth, conferring one place with an other, wherby to vnderstand the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the right meaning of the writer, howe and in what sense he excludeth good workes, and howe not: howe he neglecteth the law, and how he mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the lawe. For, as in case of iustifying before God, the free promise of the gospell admitteth no condition, but faith onely in Christ Iesu: so in case of dutifull obedience, Luther here excludeth no good works, but rather ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horteth thereunto, and that in many places. Thus times and cases discret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly must be distincted.</p>
   <p>The second thing to be required is, that in reading hereof, he that seketh to take frute hereby, doe bring such a mind with him to the reading, as the author him selfe did to the preaching therof: that is, he had neede to haue his senses exercised somewhat in such spirituall conflictes, and to be well humbled before with the feare of God and inward repentance, or els he shal hardly conceaue the excellent swetenes either of this writer or any other. For albeit most true it is, that no greater comfort to the soule of man can be found in any booke next to the holy scripture, then in this commentary of M. Luther: so this comforte hath litle place, but onely where the conscience being in heauines hath neede of the phisicions hand. The other, who feele thēselues whole &amp; are not touched in soule with any sorowe, as they litle care for these bookes, so haue they litle vnderstandinge of this doctrine when they reade it. And this is the cause in my mind, why the Pope &amp; his papistes haue so litle feeling &amp; liking of Luthers doctrine, and all because they commonly are neuer greatly vexed in spirite with any deepe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but rather deride them that be beaten downe with such conflictes and tētations of Sathan, as they did by Luther, whom because God suffered to to be tried and exercised with the buffets of the enemie, they say there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he learned his diuinitie of the Deuill. But how he learned his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, let vs heare what he him selfe in this booke, fol. 197. &amp; 198. cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth in these wordes, saying: <q>Vnlesse we had bē exercised with violēce and craftie assaultes by tirannes &amp; heretikes; and in our heart with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and fiery dartes of the deuill, Paule had bene to vs no lesse obscure,
<pb facs="7"/>
then he was in times past to the whole world and yet is to this day to our aduersaries the papistes, the Anabaptistes and other our aduersaries: And therefore the gifte of knowledge of the scripture and our studies through such inward and outward conflictes, open vnto vs the minde of Paule and of all the Scriptures &amp;c.</q>
   </p>
   <p>But let these ignorant papistes who so euer they be, tast a litle the same or like as Luther did, and then see what they will say. Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience geueth demonstration. For howe many of them doe we see, for all their auricular confession, which puffeth them vp in false securitie, but at length, when they lie at the point of death, where death on the one side and Gods iustice on the other side is before their eies, for the most part ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they despaire, or ells leauing all other helpes, they onely sticke to faith and the blood of Christ Iesus, and in very deede many of them are glad to die Lutherans how so euer they hated Luther before. And what shall we say then of this doctrine of Luther? If the papistes them selues be glad to die in it, why are they vnwilling to liue in it? And if it be true at one time, how can alteration of time make that false which is once true?</p>
   <p>And therefore where these men so stoutely wihstand this doctrine of iustification by faith onely, they are much deceaued. And where they alledge S. Iames for them, that is soone aunswered if we rightly discerne the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of S. Iames and of S. Paule: Of whom the one speaketh of mans righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes or iustification onely before men, which is a demonstration of a true faith or a true beleuer before man, rather then the working of true iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation before god. And so is it true which S. Iames saith, how that faith without workes doth not iustifie: whose purpose is, not to shewe vs what maketh a iust man before God, but onely to declare the necessary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of good workes in him that by faith is iustified. The other spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of righteousnes or iustification, not before men, but onely before God: meaning not to exclude good workes from true faith, that they should not be done: but to teach vs wherin the true stay and hope of our saluation ought to be fixed, that is, in faith onely. And so is it true likewise that S. Paule saith, that faith onely without workes doth iustifie.</p>
   <p>The which proposition of S. Paule the better to vnderstand and to ioine it with S. Iames, here is to be noted for the satisfying of the cauilling ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersary, that the proposition is to be taken full and whole, as S. Paule doth meane it, so that with the right subiect we ioyne the right predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, as the Scholemen terme it: that is, so that faith of Christ in iustify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, euer haue relation to the true penitent and lamenting sinner. And so is the article most true, that faith onely without workes doth iustifie.
<pb facs="7"/>
But whom doth it iustifie? the worldlīg? the licentious ruffen? the volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Epicure? the carnall gospeller? Paule meaneth no such thing, but onely the mourning and labouring soule, the greeued conscience, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting heart, the mending sinner: And in him the proposition is true, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of S. Paule:<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note>
      <hi>Credenti in eū qui iustificat impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, fides eius imputatur ad iustitiam:</hi> that is, <hi>to him that beleueth in him vvhich iustifieth the vngodly, his faith is counted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes.</hi> Contrarywise, let faith haue relation to the obstinate and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rebel, who contrary to conscience continueth and deliteth in sinne, and in him it is true likewise that S. Iames saith: <hi>&amp; non ex fide tantum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iac. 2.</note> that is, <hi>and not by faith onely,</hi> meaning therby that faith auaileth not to iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but onely in such persons as haue a good will and purpose to amend their liues: Not that repentance and turning from iniquitie doth saue them: but that faith in Christ worketh iustification in none but onely in such as heartely repent and are willing to amend. So that:<note place="margin">Mar. 1.</note>
      <hi>Credite E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelio, beleue the gospell,</hi> hath euer: <hi>agite poenitentiam,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note>
      <hi>repent and amend</hi> going withall. Not that repentance saueth any malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor from the law, but onely sheweth the person whom faith in Christ onely doth saue and iustifie.</p>
   <p>But of this enough, and more then greatly needed, especially seeing the booke it selfe here following will satisfie the reader at large in all such doutes to this matter appertaining. And thus ceasing to trouble thee, gentle reader, with any longer preface, as we commend this good worke to thy godly studies, so we commend both thee and thy studies to the grace of Christ Iesu the Sōne of God, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely wishing and crauing of his maiestie, that thou mayest take no lesse profite and consolation by reading hereof, then our purpose was to doe thee good in setting the same forth to thy comfort and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, which the Lord graunt, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>