<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND TRVELIE RELIGIOVS, Sr ALEXANDER GORDON Of Clunie, Knight, Grace, Mercie, and Peace, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108810_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06199</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108810</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND TRVELIE RELIGIOVS, Sr ALEXANDER GORDON Of Clunie, Knight, Grace, Mercie, and Peace, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cum bono Deo : Raine from the clouds, vpon a choicke angel: or, A returned answere, to that common quæritur of our adversaries, VVhere was your church before Luther? Digested into several meditations, according to the difference of points. Extorted off the author, for stilling the vncessant, and no lesse clamorous coassation of some patmicke frogges, against the lawfulness of our calling</title>
                 <author>Logie, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>77, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND TRVELIE RELIGIOVS, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>ALEXANDER GORDON</hi> Of Clunie, Knight, <hi>Grace, Mercie, and Peace, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I haue dared, out of the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie (as vvee learne novv abusiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to speake) to emprunt your Worships Name to this little vnpolished piece of mine vnworthie workmanship; as justlie fearing to disjoyne in my Dedication, whom GOD hath so happilie conjoyned in so tender and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affection: which your Worship shall giue as the trueth beareth, not to anie itching desire on my part to put hand to the penne, as if <hi>in boc mustaceo quaererem laureolam;</hi> Nay, as who am more than loath and vnwilling of my selfe, to giue ought foorth to the publicke view, out of a consciousnesse of my weaknesse, whereof I am not the least ashamed to giue open signification; besides diverse others more than just reasons and respects best knowne to my selfe: But to the inopportune importunitie of the Adversarie, enforcing this taske vpon mee, and expressing it of mee, how nilling so ever: As
<pb facs="3"/>semblablie to that due regard had by mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rueth, (whereof it beseemeth everie Gregarie Christian in common to bee charie) though not the least heere endangered of it selfe, and in it selfe; yet turning quaestionarie with some of the blacker note amongst vs, as the easier, so as yet (blessed bee GOD for it) the best prey of our compassing Adversaries; to whom wee envye not much these their so well accomplished Proselytes. Certes, I haue not subserved here my humor in this my Dedication, neither yet <hi>sub manu demum hic mibi natum consilium,</hi> as the triviall adage hath: But to speake sadlie, &amp; no lesse sincerelie, without the least assentation, as which proves not much compatible with my naturall, if I durst glose my selfe, not without right putation and due pondering of the matter, haue I recoursed with these my barelie &amp; nakedlie delineated, and vnfilled vp as yet lineaments, to the <hi>Zoar</hi> of your Worships Name; that shrouded and sheltered vnder the shadowing winges of the same, they may finde the better harbouring at home, and receiue as the safer conduct, so the frier passage abroad: as who truelie here finde my selfe, as emboldened on everie hand, so necessitated on everie side; whether from that your Worships respectfull regard to all, and reverend eftimation of all of my Coate; or from that your Worships sincere loue to the Trueth, (for the which wee haue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to praise GOD, and pray for the happie and long continuance thereof, with a daylie increase, because of this so thicke apostating Generation) from whence the meanest indevours of anie in this kynde cannot but finde most gracious acceptance, and heartie wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, at your Worships hands. Expecting and expeting your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships charitable construction, to the better part of those my simpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or rude and homelie labours; and so bolde, as familiar vsage of your Worships Name, in full acquytall, of these whatsoever my paines, I most humbly take my leaue: this one thing intreating, what is wanting heere in the effect or worke it selfe, your Worship would bee pleased, out of that your <hi>Persian</hi> mynde to arcesse and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it from the workmans praepondering affection; and here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all most heartilie wishing your Worship the comble of all true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, here and hence.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships in all obsequiousnesse, most humblie devoted,</hi> ANDREW LOGIE, <hi>Arch-Deane of</hi> ABERDENE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>