<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108576_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03089</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108576</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent treatise teaching howe to cure the French-pockes : with all other diseases arising and growing thereof, and in a manner all other sicknesses. Dravvne out of the bookes of that learned doctor and prince of phisitians, Theophrastus Paracelsus. Compiled by the learned Phillippus Hermanus, phisition and chirurgion. And now put into English by Iohn Hester in the spagiricall arte, practitioner</title>
                 <author>Paracelsus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 63, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>IN this Booke I haue taken vpon me (gentle Reader) to describe the ground and the original of the disease called the Pockes, and therewithall to correct the abuses which haue hetherto been vsed in the curing thereof, as namelie in fumigation, washing, annointing, opening of tumours and such like, and (the abuses beeing corrected) I meane to shew (God willing) how they may be vsed without anie perrill to the Patient, and further to teach you a rare waie (with Lignum Guaiacum, commonly called Pockwood) how to care your Patiēts going about their busines, after a more better and perfect manner then heeretofore hath beene taught, wherby you may minister helpe and comfort to the forsaken and comfortles Patient, and may be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which both you promise to him, and he expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at your hand, that is to say the recouery of his former health, for which he so greatly longeth. But there are many now adaies, which take cures in hand, which neither know the disease, nor the manner of curing of it, &amp; yet they dare promise health to the Patient: these men goe to work with their Patients as the blind man doth with the Crow, at all aduentures, for they minister that to the disease, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth nothing at all to it, and so in steed of health, they giue the Patient his bane. For redresse whereof, and that you may the better take heed of such, I haue therfore writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this little Booke, which dooth teach you perfectly to cure the aforesaid disease without any danger, so that the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent after that he is cured, shall be more healthfull in all his body thē he was before such time as he first got this disease, but for your better vnderstanding of that which is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, I wish you with dilligence to read that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And so fare yee well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>