<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108781_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06140</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16624</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108781</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrimage of princes, penned out of sundry Greeke and Latine aucthours, by Lodovvicke Lloid Gent</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jones, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 188, 185-218, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <l>
      <hi>C</hi> Call on God, vvith CICERO craue, thy countrie good to vvish.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>H</hi> Haue PHOCION learned Greke in mind that ioyed of Athēs blisse.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>R</hi> Remember CAESARS saying in Rome, ech day to vvinne a friende:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>I</hi> In vvorde and deede most DAMON like, that vvill endure the ende.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>S</hi> Seeke vvith care, serue vvith faith, think PLATOES saying on earth</l>
   <l>
      <hi>T</hi> To serue thy God, thy Prince, thy soyle, did nature poynt thy birth.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>O</hi> Offende no man, deserue due prayse, the poore doe not denie:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>F</hi> Forget not PHILIPS Page that sayd, O PHILIP thou must die.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>O</hi> Obay the lavves, hurt no man, hate not the siely Groome:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>R</hi> Right so in Englande shalt thou haue, as POMPE had in Rome.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>O</hi> Of CVRTIVS fayth, of CODRVS care, of Roman SCIPIO think:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>S</hi> Shun subtill SINONS savvcie sleyght, flee cursed CACVS linke.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>H</hi> Hat' on eche vice, eche vertue loue, thy state vvith CHILO knovve▪</l>
   <l>
      <hi>A</hi> Auoyd raging vvrath vvith paciēce mild, PERIANDER teacheth so.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>T</hi> Time doth BIAS vvise affirme, to make most men offende:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>T</hi> Time SOLON sayth doth trie al things, and time doth iudge the end.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>O</hi> Order must vvith measu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e rule, ech state sayth PYTTACVS playne:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>N</hi> Nothing must abounde to much CLEOBVLVS biddes agayne.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>V</hi> Vertue buildes hir blasing bovver, in sacred breast to breede:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>S</hi> Such prayse as shall aduaunce your fame, if sages sayings you reade.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>