<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull, my singular good Vn∣cle, Richard Lewkenor, Sergeant at the Law.</title>
           <author>Lewkenor, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108534_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108534</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull, my singular good Vn∣cle, Richard Lewkenor, Sergeant at the Law.</title>
                 <author>Lewkenor, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse not altogether vnprofitable, nor vnpleasant for such as are desirous to know the situation and customes of forraine cities without trauelling to see them : Containing a discourse of all those citties wherein doe flourish at this day priuiledged vniuersities. Written by Samuel Leuukenor Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Lewkenor, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Hooper, Humphrey.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 76 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, my singular good Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, Richard Lewkenor, Sergeant</hi> at the Law.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Emperour <hi>Claudius</hi> made an inuiolable decree, that whatsoeuer bondman in <hi>Rome,</hi> being manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and set free from seruilitie, if he neglecting the loue and bountie of his friend that did enfranchise him, requited him at any time with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindnes, he should be againe reduced to his former bonde and slauish condition. Whereby most euidently appeareth, that this inhumaine and barbarous vice ingratitude, hath beene euen of wicked men in all ages detested and abhorred: but to the vertuous and best disposed persons, hath it euer beene so extreamely odious, that they haue left to their posterity innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable multitude of examples, for the rooting out of so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sagious a pestilence from all societies: VVherefore to cleare my selfe from all suspition of any guilte or faultines herein, which you (my singular good Vnckle) most iustlie may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue against me, for letting slip so many proffered occasions, and deferring so much time before I present some essentiall
<pb facs="3"/>
testimony of my dearest loue, and most dutifull affection to your Worshippe: hauing run into so deepe adebt, for many &amp; those no meane curtisies receyued at your bandes, I haue at last, I fear, too and atiously attempted to straine the small &amp; slender talent, which I haue to pleade my cause in this behalfe, most humbly beseeching you now to shew your accustomed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity in pardoning the defectes, wherewith these my simple labours are disgraced and blemished through my owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulnes, and want of learning, which of it selfe will easilie appear, in laying open to your iudicial &amp; cleare seeing view, a learned subiect in so naked cloathing, I meane a worhy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise in so disioynted, harsh, and vnpolished a stile: howbeit I most humbly beseech you not to measure the earnest zeale &amp; dutifull affection I beare you by this simple testimony, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I goe about to shew it, but rather vouchsafe to know how greatly I am ashamed, that my abilitie can afforde no better meanes, nor my inuention, as yet bring forth a better present, fit to be offered vp to so learned a sur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay. But yet if it please you to allow of this my simple trauel, such as it is, and thinke it worthy of your patronage: I most faithfully do promise hereafter to imploy the vttermost of my endeuours in amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this faulie, and shall from henceforth the better bee enocuraged to assay some matter of greater moment, and more worthy of your protection. Vouchsafe therefore gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously to accept these my gatheringes and gleaninges out of other mens haruestes, a worke though not greatly profitable, yet pleasant and pithie, which I haue garnished with sondrie excel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent histories, and I dare boldly promise that you looking thereon at some idle howers for your recreation, shall finde therin some pleasur &amp; content, the rather because no man to my knowledge hath euer assayed the same before, &amp; for that
<pb facs="3"/>
many of these vniuersities &amp; cities are by me truly described, I hauing beene thereof in my trauelles <hi>oculatus testis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Almighty God, who hath hetherto many yeares most louingly and liberally endued you with a plentifull and happie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, blesse and prolong your daies, that wee all to the exceeding comforte of our name and Family, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in you the happie consummation of old age, before you shall be summoned to the euerlasting ioyes of the celestiall paradise.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worshippes dutifull and most affectionately louing Nephew, Samuell Lewkenor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>