<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOVR TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108288_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04260</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14379</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108288</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOVR TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>His Maiesties poeticall exercises at vacant houres</title>
                 <author>James, I., King of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>124 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOVR TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eceaue heere beloued Reader, a short Poetique discourse, which I haue se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and translated, from amongst the rest of the works of <hi>Dv'BARTAS:</hi> as a viue mirror of this last and most decreeped age. Heere shalt thou see clearlie, as in a glasse, the miseries of this wauering world: to wit, the cursed nature of mankinde, and the heauie plagues of God. And speciallie heere maye thou learne not to flatter thy selfe, in cloaking thy odious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with the delectable coulour of vertue: an errour, allace, ouer common in this hypocriticall age, not onlie in particular men of all degrees: but euen generallie in rankes, estates, and offices. But that this Treatise may seeme the les obscure vnto thee, I haue insert before the same, the Authours Praeface and Exord of the whole woorke, that thereby thou may rightlie conceaue the comming in of this portion thereof. And in case thou finde aswel in this work, as in my <hi>LEPANTO</hi> following, many incorrect errours, both in the dytement and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography, I must pray thee to accept this my reasonable excuse, which is this. Thou considers, I doubt not, that vpon the one part, I composed these things in my verie
<pb facs="3"/> young and tender yeares: wherein nature, (except shee were a monster) can admit no perfection. And nowe on the other parte, being of riper yeares, my burden is so great and continuall, without anie intermission, that when my ingyne and age could, my affaires and fasherie will not permit mee, to re-mark the wrong orthography committed by the copiars of my vnlegible and ragged hand, far les to amend my proper errours: Yea scarslie but at stollen moments, haue I the leasure to blenk vpon any paper, and yet not that, with free and vnuexed spirit. Alwaies, rough and vnpolished as they are, I offer them vnto thee: Which beeing well accepted, will moue mee to hast the presenting vnto thee, of my <hi>APO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALYPS,</hi> and also such nomber of the <hi>PSALMES</hi> as I haue perfited: &amp; incourage mee to the ending out of the rest. And thus (beloued Reader) recommending these my labours to thy freindlie acceptation: I bid thee hartelie Fare-well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>