<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1528</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108645_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00007</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10002</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108645</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Cronycles of Englonde : with the dedes of popes and emperours, and also the descripcyon of Englonde</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Worde, Wynkyn de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1528</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, c lxiii, 22 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb n="i" facs="7"/>
   <head>The prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N so moche y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is necessary to all creatures of chrysten rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion / or of fals religyon or gen tyles &amp; machomytes to knowe theyr prynce or pryces y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> regne vpon them / &amp; them to obey. So it is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modyous to knowe theyr noble actes &amp; dedes / &amp; the circūstaūce of theyr lyues. Therfore in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere of our lorde. M .cccc .lxxxiij. the .xxij. yere of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> regne of kynge Edward the fourth at saynt Albons / so that all men may know y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> actes namely of our noble kynges of englonde / is com pyled togyder this boke / &amp; more ouer is trāslated out of latyn in to englysshe / fro the begȳnynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde / the lignage of Chryst from Adā tyll it be comen to Da uid / &amp; fro Dauid / the kynges of israel &amp; of iewes / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hye by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>s;shops in theyr dayes with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iudges &amp; {pro}phetes. The .iiij. prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypall realines of the worlde / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say Babylon / Perce / Grece / &amp; Rome / &amp; all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> emperours of Rome &amp; popes by ordre / &amp; theyr names: &amp; many a notable fader: w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> certayne of theyr actes / as more playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ensueth. And here ben rehersed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> auctours y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> trāslated these cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycles specially. Geffray Nūmoth mon ke in his boke of Brute / saynt Bede in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> actes of englonde. Also Bede in his boke of tymes. Gyldas in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> actes of Britayn. Willyam Malinesbury mōke in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> actes of kynges of englond &amp; bysshops. Cassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der{us} of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> actes of emperours &amp; bysshops Saynt Austin de ci. dei. Cit{us} Liuius de gestis romano{rum}. Martyn penitency ary to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pope in his cronycles of emperours &amp; bysshops / &amp; namely Theobaldus car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tusiensis cōteynynge in his boke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse of all notable faders / fro y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde vnto our tyme / w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the notable actes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. ¶ In this new trāslacyon are cōteyned many notable &amp; meruaylous thinges / &amp; those ben alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by auctoryte of many famous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euery man may knowe how these cronycles bē ordred / ye shal vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this boke is deuyded in to .vij. partes. Of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche the fyrst parte con teyneth from Adam tyll Brute came in to Britayne. The seconde parte cōteyneth frō Brute came fyrst in to englonde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cite of Rome was buylded by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul{us}. The thyrde parte cōteyneth syth Rome was buylded vnto Chryst was borne of our lady virgyn Marye. The fourth parte frō thens vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> comynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saxons in to englonde: The .v. parte from thens vnto the comyng of danes. The .vj. parte frō thens vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> comynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> normans. The .v. parte fro y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans vnto our tyme / which is vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> regne of kyng Edwarde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fourth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. yere / whose noble cronycles by custome may not be seen. ¶ And so in euery part of these .vij. partyes be shewed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moost and necessary actes of all the kynges of englonde / &amp; theyr names wryten aboue in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> margent / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euery man may fynde them soone. And afore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kynges of eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>londes actes ben wryten / there is wry-ten y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lignage of Chryst frō Adam tyll y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> chryst was borne of our lady w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the hye bysshops &amp; iudges y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> were in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tyme &amp; certayne of theyr actes necessary tyll it be comen where Chryst was borne &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that chryst was borne &amp; Peter was pope of Rome / is shewed by ordre y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> popes &amp; emperours of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me afore &amp; after / with certayne of theyr actes breuyately / &amp; many other dyuets thynges &amp; meruayles in those mennes dayes fallynge. And it is shewed euery thȳge in his place / how many yere it fei after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> begynnynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde / &amp; how lōge afore y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Chryst was borne / &amp; whan y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> I come to Chryst was borne / thā it is wrytē how lōge any thynge fell after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Natyuite of Chryst. And this is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordre of this boke / &amp; of thynges spoken of.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
ANd as to men desyryng to haue a very knowlege of these crony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles or of ony other / it is necessary to kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we .vj. thynges. ¶ The fyrst is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> states of thynges / &amp; those bē two. One is fro y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> begynnynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde vnto Chryst / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche is called the state of deuiacyon. The seconde is frō Chryst to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ende of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde / the whiche is called the state of reconstliacyon. ¶ The secōde thynge is the diuysyon of tymes / &amp; those ben thre. One is afore the lawe of Moyses / &amp; an other is vnder the lawe of Moyses / an other is vnder the lawe of grace after Chryst dyed. ¶ The thyrde is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of kyngdomes. And as for that ye must knowe / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> though there were foure prȳcipal kyngdomes / that is to saye / of Babilon / of Persees / of Grekes / &amp; of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maynes. Neuerthelesse as to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> course of the worlde / &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordre of holy scripture / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fyrst gouernyng was vnder faders / frō Adam vnto Moyses. The secōde vnder iudges / from Moyses vnto Saul. The thyrde vnder kȳges from Saul vnto zō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>robabel. The fourth vnder bisshops / frō zorobabel vnto Chryst. ¶ The fourth is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dyuersite of lawes / &amp; those were fyue. The fyrst was y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lawe of nature / &amp; that was comyn to all men. The secōde is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lawe or custome of gentyles / whan y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der kynge Nyno began y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp false goddes. The thyrde is vnder the lawe wryten rose the lawe of iewes / whan circūcysyon deuyded y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iewes frō other peple. The fourth is vnder chryst rose y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lawe of christen men / whan fayth and grace of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramentes enformed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyfe of men. The fyfth is vnder Macho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met rose the lawe of sarasyns &amp; turkes. ¶ The fyfth is the noblenesse or vnno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes in dedes. And as to these / it is to knowe that .vij. persones ben redde / of whome the dedes many tymes are had in mynde in hystoryes. That is to wyte of a prynce in his realme / of a knyght in batayle / of a iudge in his place / of a bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop in the clergye / of a polytyke man in the people / of an husbond man in the hous / &amp; of an abbot in his chirche. And of these are wryten many tymes / the laudes of good men / and the punysshe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the cursed men. ¶ The syxth is the true countynge of the yeres. And to that / it is to be knowen y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there were viij. maner of nombrynge or countynge of the yeres. Thre after the Hebrewes. Thre after the Grekes. One of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayns. And one now is after the chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten men. The Hebrewes thre maner of wyse begynneth theyr yere. After the Hebrewes there is the yere vsuall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge at Ianuary / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche they vse in couenauntes and bargeyns ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng. And the yere leyfull begynnynge at Marche / the whiche they vse in theyr cerymonyes. And the yere Emergens from Maye begynnynge / whan they wente from Egypte / they vse in theyr cronycles &amp; calculacyons. ¶ The Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes nōbreth theyr yeres thre maner of wyse. Fyrst to the glory &amp; Ioye of theyr victory coūteth theyr yeres from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struccyon of Troye. The fyrst / y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> second / the thyrde / and the fourth. <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr> ¶ Than after the chyualry began at the hyll of Olympus they notyfyed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeres after the same Olimpiadū. And what Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piades is / ye shall knowe after in the boke. The thyrde whan they began to haue lordshyp of all the worlde they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed theyr yeres these maner of wyse. In the yere of the regne of Grekes / the fourth / the .x. the .xv. <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr> as it is open in the boke of Machabeo{rum}. ¶ Than after the Romayns gouernynge the worlde / coūted &amp; nōbred theyr yeres (ab vrbe con dita). ¶ The last of all chrystē men coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth theyr yeres from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Incarnacyon of Chryst. And bycause we bē chrystē men
<pb n="ii" facs="8"/>
we vse moost to nombre / from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the worlde vnto Chryst was borne. And fro Chryst was borne vnto our tyme. And this ordre is obserued &amp; kepte in all the boke / of euery thynge in his place / as is sayd before.</p>
   <trailer>¶ Explicit prologus.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>