<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108610_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19208</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5618</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French iubile: or, The ioy and thanksgiuing of all France, to God and their king, for the death of the Marquise d'Ancre. Translated out of the French copie printed at Paris</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onest and well affected Reader, for thy greater contentment, I am bold to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent thee with this Iubile of the whole French Nation vpon the death of the Marquise <hi>de'Ancre:</hi> this ioy hath been manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted on all hands, by all sorts and degrees. The King to shew how acceptable the seruice of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier <hi>de Vitry</hi> was to him in this execution, hath made him thereupon Marshall of <hi>France,</hi> in the place of the Marquise <hi>d'Ancre:</hi> And Mounsier <hi>d'Hailler,</hi> who accompanied <hi>d'Vitry</hi> in that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath hee caused to be sworne Captaine of his Guard; and many other of the ancient Officers of the Crowne hath he restored to their places, abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely taking the gouernment to himselfe: and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing (as he saith) all childish sports to his brother, he hath caused to be set at liberty those little Birds, wherein hee formerly delighted, that so they may haue their libertie as well as himselfe. The Princes (vpon it) are some of them returned to Court, and others expected daily, euery one laying downe
<pb facs="3"/>Armes presently, and amongst others the Duke <hi>d'Mayen</hi> presented the King with the keyes of <hi>Soy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> a towne which he had fortified.</p>
   <p>The generall and extraordinary reioycing of the common people cannot be sufficiently expressed; but because I list not to trouble thee (good Reader) with vncertaine and slender reports, I referre thee for the full manifestation of their generall ioy to the discourse following; intreating thee to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded of my honest fidelitie and care in these pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lications, for J assure thee J am not desirous to shew my selfe both false and foolish in Print. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>