<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Jones, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108579_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05583</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108579</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Jones, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sixe bookes of politickes or ciuil doctrine, written in Latine by Iustus Lipsius: which doe especially concerne principalitie. Done into English by William Iones Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Lipsius, Justus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Aggas, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 205, 106-107, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I may well doubt how this my
first labour shall be accepted of, or gaine credit
with thee and I did long hang in suspence, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
I should as an abortise, burie it, or as a dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
cherish it. The first sure had best pleasèd
me, if therein I should not haue displeased o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
and bene commanded by the power they haue ouer me, and
perswaded by their learned reasons, not onely to nourish it, but
to bring it vp to full growth and strength: assuring me, there
would be as much pleasure, and profit taken therein in publicke,
as I had taken paines therewith in priuate. And although I
had at the beginning, great reasons to disswade me from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise
(as a matter ouer-difficult, the same hauing bene attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted
by two or three, and perished, with one, in the bud, with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
in the blossome, and with the third, being no sooner ripe,
but foorthwith it was rotten.) Neuerthelesse, I was still, vnder
this assurance, prouoked to go forward, and did euery day, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
more force, and in the end, by the warmth and heate, of a
fauourable sunne, brought it to the best perfection I could, and
the change of the soile would giue me leaue. In which estate I do
freely offer it vnto thee: desiring thee, not sinisterly to interpret,
if there be any thing not agreeing to thy minde, but friendly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend,
that thou shalt find amisse. And before thou do pronoūce
full sentence against me, I beseech thee with a sound iudgement to
enter into consideration of the sence, and substance of the author,
and not of euery particular word: (albeit euen therein likewise
(as neare as the matter would giue me leaue) I haue sought to
satisfie thee.</p>
   <p>Touching the substance of the booke, it contàineth matter of
pollicie, and especially concerneth the establishment of Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
It is deuided into sixe seuerall bookes, in the foure former, he
<pb facs="5"/>
sheweth what the Prince should be, what vertues he is especially
to be endued withall, how he should make choise of good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellers,
and officers: and to be short, after what sort he should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue,
and establish him selfe in time of peace.</p>
   <p>The fifth booke setteth downe, in what maner he should begin,
vndertake, and execute, foraine warre: how the same should be
finished, and peace established thereby, which is the true ende of
warre. A worke so necessarie for Captains, and those that serue
their prince in the field, that in many things it surpasseth all those
discourses of warre, I could yet come to the sight of. In the sixth
booke, he treateth of ciuill warre.</p>
   <p>Concerning the order I haue kept in this worke, I haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
at all dissented from the Author (though at the first blush
the contrarie may appeare.) For whereas he hath distinguished
the sentences, and it may seeme I haue not: yet are they (in my
opinion) as well seuered by this marke *, as if they were farther
distant the one from the other.</p>
   <p>Another thing (I feare) will be obiected against me, that I
haue not rightly pointed my distinctions. Whereunto I answer,
that if you looke into the Author, you shall find his meaning, and
my distinctions to agree. For albeit he hath set a <hi>periodes</hi> (.) in
the end of many sentences, yet doth not the full sence end there, but
still hang, and continue, as <hi>Lipsius</hi> him selfe confesseth in these
words: <hi>Nec enim sinis semper sententiae in fine clausulae, sed
pendet ea semper, &amp; haeret.</hi> I haue followed these vsuall points:
(,) : (.)</p>
   <p>And whereas I was perswaded by some, to leaue out the quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
of the seuerall Authors, and the notes of the margent; I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
not to their perswasion for two respects. The one, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
it might be thought, I had bene a corrupt, and faithlesse trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator,
and that I durst not set my worke to the touch. The other,
that the said marginall notes, do giue great light to the worke, &amp;
serue to explaine many matters therein: besides they haue this
singularitie in them (which I haue not seene in any other) that
they do entertaine one another, as if they were a continued speech:
which if you reade them by them selues, you shall soone finde out.
Moreouer, if any be pleased to confer, some one sentence of mine,
<pb facs="5"/>
or more, with the originall, by the quotacion of the Authors, the
same may be more easily found, and he the better satisfied, of my
paines, and diligence in this labour, or what fault I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
therein.</p>
   <p>Lastly, whereas I haue sometimes changed the tense, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles
the person: I say, the discourse could not else be well
knit together: and herein I haue especially in the whole worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded
the pluralitie of Gods (which all Christians detest) and
the Author could not but mention, his sentences being taken alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
from prophane writers. And as concerning some thing left
out in the third Chapter of the second Booke, it was a thing done
of set purpose; for some important cause, which I meane not here
to vtter.</p>
   <p>Thus I haue (gentle Reader) giuen thee some taste of this
notable discourse; which I desire may be well disgested by thee,
the which I do leaue to thy fauourable perusing: yet before thou
enter any further therein, I pray thee with thy pen to correct those
faults, which haue passed the presse, which by reason of my dayly
attendance at my Lords are grown to a greater number, then
either my desire or the Printers was they should. And
so I wish thee many happie, and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
yeares.</p>
   <p>At my house at Newington Buts, the first
of Ianuarie. 1594.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy friend to vse,
VVilliam Iones.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>