<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108317_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20531</idno>
           <idno type="STC">694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108317</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Anwick his meditations vpon Gods monarchie and the deuill his kingdome : And of the knowledge that man in this life may obtaine of the almightie, eternal, and most glorious godhed: with other thinges not only worth the reading but also the marking and the retayning</title>
                 <author>Anwick, I.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dewes, Garrat</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 117, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or a while after the Gospell was freely preached in England there were but two sortes of people not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> knowen, those were Papistes and Protestantes, which diuersitie of names were deuised to put different <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> true Christians and false. Because all that were once vnder the Popes vsurped auctoririe, were called Christians without distinction, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h neither in the manners of their life, nor in the matter of their beleefe they deserued so honorable a title. But the loosenes of the times sithence hath bene such, for want of correction of manners, that there are now diuerse sectes, wherof I wil touch one especially, a third sort which are of no religion, named Atheistes. A people without God hauing no feeling of God, nor knowledge of their owne horrible state. * Neither here nor cold; neither feeling their<note place="margin">Reuel. 3. 15</note> owne misery nor regarding their owne shame. Of which wicked sort the nomber is now greatter in diuers landes then both of Papistes and Protestantes. And they are so much worse and more pestiferous then the Papistes, as they faine to bee of all religions, as occasion and company may serue their turne. And yet indeede are of no religion at all.</p>
   <p>But because the Papistes religion is more pleasing vnto the carnall sences of man, then the strait rules of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell▪ There is no doubt but they will ioyne with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes against the Protestantes when any stirre happeneth for religion: Which God forbid if it bee his holv will.</p>
   <p>Therefore if such monsterous cloudes of Satans sleightes did not presently hang ouer our heads, and therewithall such stinking mistes of horrible iniquity enclose vs round aboute: euen readie to choake all our sences. (Satan therby endeuouring to seperate vs from God and his holy woord) it might seeme too too curious a question to aske: is there a
<pb facs="4"/> God or no? Seing that ther hath not bin nether yet is heard of so tude a Nation vnder the Sun, that hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n euery age imagined to themselues one thing or other, of whom to craue helpe, and woorship for a God.</p>
   <p>Sauing this pestiferous kind of Deuils incarnat these A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theistes * who are the fooles that Dauid speaketh of, that say<note place="margin">Psal. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Ephes. 2</note> in their hartes there is no God. * They are without Christ, they are aliantes from the common weal of Israel, they are straungers from the couenant, they haue no hope because they think there is no God: and vnlesse order were taken &amp; put in vre for correction of manners, they would shortly become so brutish as to vtter it in speech.</p>
   <p>Therfore seing this generation of vipero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Atheistes that say in their hartes there is no God: do daily increase by the pestileut pollicy of Satan their father, it is now most neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary in this daungerous time, to declare vnto thē, that they shall finde at last an almightie and euerlasting God, euen he that is the onely Monarch of Heauen earth, and Hel as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<note place="margin">Reuel. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Scriptures teach: which if they beleeue not, the labor is lost on them. For without fayth it is impossible to please God.</p>
   <p>Therefore they that will come to God, must first beleeue that God is: and that hee is a most bountifull rewarder of them that seeke him, and to all others a consuming fire.</p>
   <p>It is the want of correction of manners that encourageth the wicked to do almost what they list. The Papistes hope<note place="margin">Papistes</note> that they shal yet haue a day for their purpose. And to that ende there haue bin great nombers of papisticall bokes frō beyond the Sea, brought into the Realme, whereof though a few were taken, no doubt very many haue bin distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among their sect. Their confederacie must needes bee great, for they haue had a long and a quiet time to consult, and lay their plot togither with manie and sondry mighty f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>endes, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>The Atheistes and all other erronious sectes are careles,
<pb facs="5"/> setting their part at hazarde: for it is all one to them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion which end goe forward, so they may bee quiet by dissimulation, But the Protestantes of this realm<note place="margin">Protestants</note> of all degrees, I meane such as are true Christians indeede, (which are percel of Christ his litle flocke dispersed and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>west in nomber) they waite in fearful patience what God is about to doe. Some of them not well resolued in this sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Sonne of God, * Many are called, and fewe are<note place="margin">Mat 29. 16. Luc. 12. 49.</note> chosen. For they are greatly amased to see the true feruent zeale of Gods holy seruice, (euen the fyre that the Sonne of God brought into the World, and wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed that it should burne in mens hartes) to bee now almost quenched, or at the least the substance wherein it should woorke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that there resteth but only embers raked in the ashes.</p>
   <p>And therefore seeing men regard not to maintaine that fyre of true zeale which the Lord himselfe willed to burne in mens hartes. There are great likelihodes by many conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, that God will shortly kindle the fyre of disturbance, and in the end consume his enemies. For euen now the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of God speaketh vnto the diuers states, as hee did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the congregations of the Laodicians, saying: * let him that hath an eare heare what the spirit sayth vnto the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches A men the true &amp; faithful witnes, euen the beginning of the Creatures of God, sayth these thinges: I know your woorkes that yee are neither cold nor hote, I would yee wer cold or hote: so then because yee are lukewarme end neither cold nor hote, I will spew you out of my mouth: because ye say, I am ritch and encreased with goods and need nothing, and you know not that yee are wretched, miserable, poore, blind, and naked.</p>
   <p>Therefore I counsell you to buy of mee Gold tried in the fyre, that yee may bee ritch, and white raiment that yee may bee clothed that your filthy nakednes do not appeare. And annoint your eies with eie salue that yee may see. As many as I loue I rebuke and chasten, be feruent therefore,
<pb facs="5"/> and repent saith the Lord.</p>
   <p>Behold I stand at the dore and knocke, if any man heare my voice and open the dore: I will come in vnto him, and suppe with him, and hee with mee: To him that ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth will I graunt to sit with mee in my throne, as I haue ouercome and sitte with my Father in his throne.</p>
   <p>By this let them that haue eares heare what the Spirite saieth to the congregations. They are monstrous may med bodies, that want eares to heare the woord of God, and yet haue eares doing their office in hearing all other thinges.</p>
   <p>Now where the fault lyeth of this wauering zeale, this dulnes in hearing, this lukewarmnes in following, this slow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in beleeuing and exercising the word of God, or who deserueth the blame thereof I leaue that in question.</p>
   <p>For to be an accuser of crimes is perillous, namely wher the Iudges want vpright hearing, there it is not only a lost labor and thankles office: but also obtaineth vnwoorthy blame and hatred for good wil.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding I say an accusation may bee made in Christian charity for the amendment of such as walke inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatly, whereupon I say (proue it as I can) that euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is bound by duty to bee an eie and an eare to the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate to declare vnto him in christian charitie the enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which he seeth among the people, because he can see no further then a mā except god do inspire som mā with more vertue that way thē cōmonly is in men. Therfore whē falts be told the magistrats for charity sake &amp; duty to god, those persons haue discharged the duty of good Christians: And then if the maiestrates do not trie out the truth &amp; execute iustice, the sinne is vpon him. Therfore in praier I humbly beseech the almighty God for his dear sons sake to send his holy Spirite into the hartes of all, that euen from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est that sittes in the roiall throne, vnto the lowest and sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest in whole kingdoms &amp; dominions, that euery one may remember, that the ende of their creation both in body &amp; soule is to glorify God.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>And therfore let euery one that desireth saluatiō endeuour now themselues to walke vprightly and deale truly, hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stly and faithfullie in their vocation: &amp; pray hartily to God in this time of vrgent necessity, that the feruent zeale of Gods most sacred seruice, according to his owne word may be surelie engrafted in the hartes of all, and most chiefly in Princes, counsellers, Nobilitie magistrates and officers. That the same true zeale, and the vertue thereof may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from them by degrees in good example into the harts of the commons, euen to the poorest and basest subiectes. That all with one found minde may praise the holy and dreadfull name of Iehoua; the most glorious, almighty, and eternall God; the onely Monarch of Heauen and Earth, &amp; that in the name of Christ Iesus, for whose sake our praiers are pleasant and acceptable vnto him, for otherwise he can not abide nor brooke them.</p>
   <p>As King Dauid was moued and sollicited doubtles by holy motions which were in him the woorke of the holy<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7. 1 Chron. 17 &amp; 22.</note> Ghost, to build a Temple vnto the mighty God of Israell, which when hee had purposed to doe, and prepared much costly stuffe for the building: Nathan the Prophet warned him to the contrary, God would not haue it of his dooing▪ And why? Euen because of his bloody handes. Therefore hee commaunded to leaue it to his son Salomon: by whose innocent handes, God would haue that most famous and glorious figure wrought, before Satan should corrupt his vnderstanding &amp; leade him captiue for a time: as afterward hee did in most shamefull wife: as in the 11. of 2. booke of Kinges. Euen so I by like motions from time to time, haue bin and am continually sollicited to meditate vppon Gods Monarchie; and the Deuils Kingdome: But whether the Lord worke in mee to the end I may rightly frame and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, and time to finish the same to the benefite of his Church, because of my bloudy handes and sinnes of my youth, the Lord Iesus knoweth and not I.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Yet through his grace woorking in mee (for my selfe I can not thinke a good thought) I haue gatherd togeather good and sound stuffe, for some other that labor in Gods vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, to frame the same or like peece of woorke.</p>
   <p>Men ought to examine al doctrines by the word of God and chiefly consider what is spoken or written, and not so much regarde the speaker or writer. For it is a grosse error to thinke, and more blockish to bee spoken: That the true interpretation of holy Scriptures should rest onely in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ole men. Whereas wee finde by daily experience, that many of them are enemies to the glad tidinge, of Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>Now if any man obiect or take exceptions against the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctority of the bookes called Apocripha, out of which I haue heare and there alledged somewhat, I answere thus, that in all pointes wherein they doe agree with the Canonicall Scriptures, they are in my opinion to bee preferred to all other mens writinges, Doctors what or who soeuer: which canonicall Scriptures God hath most miraculously preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued euen in the handes of the enemies of the truth therein contayned: And that in the daungerous tymes of darke ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and cruel persecution, and albeit Satan woorking in some of the enemies, haue sought and endeuoured to corrupt some part thereof by false translations and wicked gloses. Yet notwithstanding God hath euermore appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted some by working of his holy Spirite to restrayne the wicked from vtter currupting and destroying them: And likewise haue wrought in some of his elect in all ages, to preserue some true copies therof vndefiled with their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked leuin, euen through all the ages of Papistes and other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies▪ The holy, glorious and dreadful name of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Iehoua the onely Monarch of Heauen and Earth be euer more praised and magnifyed, for that and all other bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites done vnto mankinde in general, but especially for his mercies in Christ Iesus on his elect only.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>