<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable his verie good Lorde, George Earle of Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet, Aton and Vescie, &amp;c. E. A. wisheth all increase of honour and true felicitie.</title>
           <author>A., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108246_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05074</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108246</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable his verie good Lorde, George Earle of Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet, Aton and Vescie, &amp;c. E. A. wisheth all increase of honour and true felicitie.</title>
                 <author>A., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The politicke and militarie discourses of the Lord de La Nouue : VVhereunto are adioyned certaine obseruations of the same author, of things happened during the three late ciuill warres of France. With a true declaration of manie particulars touching the same. All faithfully translated out of the French by E.A</title>
                 <author>La Noue, François de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Orwin, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Aggas, Edward</distributor>
                            <distributor>Aggas, Edward</distributor>
                            <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 284, 283-446, 445-458, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> his verie good Lorde, George Earle of <hi>Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet,</hi> Aton and Vescie, &amp;c. E. A. wisheth all increase of honour and true felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>NTIGONVS being asked whom he thought to bee the worthiest Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in his time, answered, Pirrhus if he were of more yeres, not daring to pronounce him absolutelie the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiest vntill he had experience to match with his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: euen so if it were demaunded at this daie who iustlie deserued the name of a politike &amp; expert Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptaine, I think (without preiudice to anie other) that the Lord de la Noüe, the author of this present trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, whose wise gouernment in time of peace being no lesse commendable than his long seruice in time of warres to the Church of God hath bene profitable, is not in silence to be ouer-passed. Howbeit least I should (right Honorable and my verie good Lord) seeme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to blemish than amplifie the vertues of so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a man through the basenesse of my stile and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polished phrase, I leaue the same to bee notefied by those whose great knowledge and ripe iudgement I
<pb facs="3"/>
doe iustlie preferre many degrees before mine owne, being the rather thereto induced by the like example of Menedemus the Lacedemonian, who was wont to saie that the qualitie and condition of the praiser ought to be as well regarded as that of the praised. Insinuating thereby that it was vnfit verie for anie man to commend the thing wherein his iudgement might fayl, or his education be therto not answerable. In as much therefore as his owne works may in some measure make manifest what is to bee thought of his person, I doe present them to your Honors view and patronage in this our vulgar tongue faithfullie and trulie translated out of the French, desiring though not deseruing like fauourable acceptation, as I had good meaning to offer the same. For therein I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perswaded the indifferent and not curious reader shall finde matter sufficient for the reestablishing of a ruinous common weale, if it be put in practise: wise counsaile for maintenance thereof: and lastly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued documents requisite whether in ciuill or forraine warres, which albeit they were written perticulerlie to releeue and restore the declining estate of the realm of France, are also in my opiniō not vnnecessary for ours or any other that may fal into the like, if God who is the protector and guider of all Realmes shoulde not continue among vs vnity and godly peace. A work no doubt worthy the writer, and yet at the first
<pb facs="3"/>
published without his priuitie or allowance, being col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and disgested into one volume out of a heape of papers cast aside by the industrie &amp; paines of the L. of Fresnes, whom, as himself reporteth, the miserie of the time and troubles of his owne natiue Countrie, enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as a banished man to keepe companie with the said Lord de la Noüe during his captiuitie in a forraine land, dedicated to that excellent Prince &amp; patterne of pietie Henrie of Burbon King of Nauarre, thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough whose roiall patrimonie together with the iust desert of the author himselfe it hath receiued friendly entertainment among the better sorte of the French Nation: as I doubt not but it shall finde the like heere among vs English men, being shrouded vnder the couert of your L. honorable protectiō, to the which I commit the same: thus crauing pardon for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse most humblie I take my leaue of your Lordship, to whom I wish long life with all encrease of honour.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble and heartie well willer,
E. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>