<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108344_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18690</idno>
           <idno type="STC">52</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108344</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mirrour of Popish subtilties : discouering sundry wretched and miserable euasions and shifts which a secret cauilling Papist in the behalfe of one Paul Spence priest, yet liuing and lately prisoner in the castle of Worcester, hath gathered out of Sanders, Bellarmine, an others, for the auoyding and discrediting of sundrie allegations of scriptures and fathers, against the doctrine of the Church of Rome, concerning sacraments, the sacrifice of the masse, transubstantiation, iustification, &amp;c. Written by Rob. Abbot, minister of the word of God in the citie of Worcester. The contents see in the next page after the preface to the reader. Perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 25, 28-155, 158-173, 178-226 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be deemed, good Christian Reader, that in publishing this Pamphlet I neither bethought my selfe of my selfe nor of these times. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching my selfe I must acknowledge, that by reason of many defectes, I should haue bene discouraged from giuing any thing forth to the common view and censure of the world. Especially these times being such and so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant in learning and knowledge, as that it may seeme great pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption in any man, to attempt the diuulging of any writing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is not either for wit or learning, somewhat more then may be expected of euery common and ordinary man. Moreouer these matters of controuersy betwixt the Church of Rome and vs, haue bene so throughly sifted and debated to the full by diuers men of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular learning and iudgement in this age, that for such as I am, to say any thing after them, may seeme no other a matter then for Pan to pipe after Apollo his musicke, and for an vnlearned Atturney to plead a cause after the pleading and debating of most learned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell. But yet the necessary regard of procuring due estimation to the trueth against the aduersaries secrete disgracinges, hath mooued me to doe that in this behalfe which otherwise I could not haue thought conuenient. Neither haue I iudged the conscience of mine owne slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse and inhability a sufficient reason to stay me here-from, the case standing as it doth, because I know that as in the bodily fight it is necessary for the winning of the field, that not onely the Captaines and best experienced souldiours, do vse their strength, but also those that in experience and ablenesse are farre inferior vnto them, so in
<pb facs="5"/> this spirituall warfare and contending against the aduersaries of the Gospell of Christ, not onely they that are of supreame excellency of learning and giftes, but also they which are but as it were of the first order, must as occasion serueth vse that ablenesse which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them to iustifie the cause of the Gospell, and to cleere it from those mistes of falsehood and errour, wherewith the aduersaries labour to ouercast it, and to hide it from being seene. And although these matters haue bene already very sufficiently disputed of, yet because it fareth with bookes as it doth with newes, that whilest they are new &amp; fresh they are regarded and sought after, but after a while they are in a maner buried, so that if the aduersary stirre again, though he bring nothing but that that was confuted before, yet he is thought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answered, except some speciall answere be returned to him, therefore beside the commoditie which ariseth by the diuerse handling of the same matters, seruing much for the more easie conceiuing and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing thereof, as <seg rend="sup">t</seg> S. <hi>Austen</hi> noteth, it is in this respect also verie<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> August. de bap cont. Donat. lib. 2. cap 1.</note> behouefull and necessary for the Church of God, that the same points be againe and againe discussed, and truth from time against new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries a new defended, though in respect of the matter it selfe, there needeth not be any thing further sayd, then that which by diuers hath bene sayd already. Therefore it shall not seeme vnreasonable that I though not worthy, whose name should go forth into this publicke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, yet being occasioned thereto, should after the labours of so many learned men, employ my small talent to the confuting of such vaine gloses and shifts as an aduersary hath vsed against my selfe to darken the truth layd open and manifest before his eyes. But for thy better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, gentle Reader, and more full satisfaction as touching the necessitie of this my doing, I will briefly declare the originall &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of the whole matter.</p>
   <p>There was in the Castle of <hi>VVorcester,</hi> a Priest named <hi>Paule Spence,</hi> not of the Seminary, but begotten to his order as I suppose, in the ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of Queene <hi>Mary.</hi> Vpon motion sundry times made vnto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, I went vnto him to haue some speech with him concerning his
<pb facs="5"/> profession. The particulars of our speech either then or after, I will not report, least I should seem partial either for my self or against him. The conclusion of my speech at that time, was to wish him that hee would at some conuenient times resort to my studie, that by the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of my bookes I might, as occasion serued, shew him those pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and testimonies which I should alleage to him. He promised that he would▪ so that I would procure him licence. I procured it of my L. the Bishop lately deceased. I came to him againe, and after some speech I required the performance of his promise. He shewed himselfe too &amp; fro in the matter, and in the end gaue me plaine answere that he was resolued, and so he knew I was also, and therfore that it was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for him so to doe. I departed from him. The next newes that I heard, was a report giuen foorth that I had bene with him at the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and that hee had stopped my mouth that I had nothing to say to him. This is the accustomed maner of these men, who are all so ranke of learning, that the veriest asse of them if he do but once braie, is able to astonish and confound any aduersary be he neuer so learned. I went to him againe, and vrged him as before. He answered me in the same maner. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> length hee was perswaded by another man and came to mee. I reasoned with him of sundry matters. Being in speech as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Transubstantiation, I shewed him a saying of Cyprian: <note n="b" place="margin">Cypr. lib. 2. ep. 3.</note>
      <hi>We find that it was wine which Christ called his blood.</hi> But Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an saith withall, <hi>That the cup was mixed which the Lord offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> He left the matter in hand, and began to demaund of mee what I thought of the mixture of the cup, I answered him nothing of mine owne opinion, but told him that Chrysostom called it <note n="c" place="margin">Chrysost. in Mat. ho. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3.</note>
      <hi>A pernicious heresie.</hi> He required me and I shewed him the place. But returning to the former point, I shewed him the words of Gelasius where he saith, that in the Sacraments of the bodie and blood of Christ, <note n="d" place="margin">Gelas. cont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uty. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor.</note>
      <hi>There ceaseth not to bee the substance or nature of bread and wine.</hi> These two latter places haue bene the occasion of all this writing. He sent to me within two or three daies after for my bookes, to peruse the places, that wheras he could not presently answer any thing by spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch, he might do somewhat by w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ting. I receiued his answere, and replied
<pb facs="6"/> to the same againe by writing; yet not intending, because it stood not with my businesse otherwise, to goe any further in this course, but only for some aduertisement and instruction to him which I sawe hee nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and to giue him occasion of further conference by speech, as I mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him in the end. This happened neare the beginning of Lent, in the yeare 1590. Towards Whitsuntide next following, when I thought he had bene quiet and would haue medled no more, he sent me an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere againe written at large to my reply. But the answere in truth was none of his owne doing, as is manifest partly by his owne confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by that he shewed himselfe a straunger in his owne answeres, when afterward in speech he was vpbraided with some of them by my selfe: partly by the muttering report of his owne fellowes, vaunting that though he were able to say litle, yet some had the matter in hand that were able to say inough. He himself indeed was not, nor is of able<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to doe it, as all men know that haue any knowledge of him. He was neuer of any Vniuersitie, and both professed and shewed himself in speech vtterly ignorant of Logicke, wherof his deputie <hi>Answ.</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth great skill. I omit some other matters that I might mention for proofe hereof. But thus I was vnwares drawne from <hi>P. Spence,</hi> to tontrouersie and disputation with some other secret friend of his, who for his learning might take vppon him to bee a defender of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish falshood. I addressed my selfe to a confutation of this answer, and thought to haue sent the same to M. Spence in writing; but before I had fully perfected it, which was in Iuly or August following, he was by occasion of some infirmitie as was pretended, set free from his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment vpon suerties, and so continueth till this time, neither could I by such meanes as I vsed, bring him foorth to receiue that which I had written. Hereupon haue I bene traduced by the faction as a man conquered and ouercome, as if I taught openly, that which in dealing priuately with an aduersary I am not able to defend. For the auoyding of this scandall, I was diuerse times motioned to publish the whole matter, but for some speciall reasons did forbeare. It laie by me almost a whole yeare, before I would resolue so to do. At the length, for the satisfying of such as might bee desirous to bee satisfied in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe,
<pb facs="6"/> and that foolish men might haue no further occasion of their vaine imaginations and speeches, I tooke it in hand as my great businesse otherwise would permit, to peruse it againe, and to adde some things for answere to Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, as touching some points for which the Answ. referreth me to him, whose workes I had not at the first penning heereof, and so I haue presumed, Christian Reader, to offer it vnto thy consideration. I haue termed the whole discourse in respect of the principall purpose and argument of it, <hi>A Mirror of Popish subtilties,</hi> as wherein thou maist in part behold the vanitie &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednesse of those answeres wherein these men account so great subtiltie and acutenesse of wit and learning, as if the same being giuen, there were nothing more to be saide against them. In the publishing heereof, I haue thought good to obserue this order. First I haue set downe the aboue named places of <hi>Chrysostome</hi> and <hi>Gelasius.</hi> Secondly, M. <hi>Spence</hi> his Answere to those two places. Thirdly, my reply to that answere. Fourthly, the latter answere to my reply, with a confutation thereof, from point to point, and a defense of the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and authorities vsed in the said reply. Reade all, and then iudge of the truth. I protest, I haue made conscience to write nothing but the truth: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath any vaine curiositie led me to the publishing hereof, but only the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of iustifying the truth, and that namely to those of the Citie and Countie of <hi>VVorcester,</hi> whom my labours do most neerely and properly concerne. If thou canst reape any frute or benefit by it, I shalbe heartily glad thereof, and let vs both giue glorie vnto God. If any see the truth herein, and yet will malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously kicke against it, I passe by him with those words of the Apostle; <note n="e" place="margin">Apoc. 22 11.</note>
      <hi>He that is filthie, let him be filthie still.</hi> It is our part to propose the truth: it is God onely that can giue men hearts to assent vnto it, and <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 11. 1▪</note>
      <hi>VVisedome shalbe iustified of her children.</hi> The God of all wisedome and knowledge, enlighten vs more and more to the vnderstanding of his true religion; subdue the pride and rebellion of our hearts, that we may vnfainedly yeeld vnto it, and giue vs constancie and perseuerance to continue in the same vnto the end, that in our ende we may attaine to the endlesse fruition of his kingdome and glorie, through Iesus Christ our Lord.</p>
   <closer>Amen.
<signed>Rob. Abbot.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>