<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108235_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03635</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1376</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108235</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dolorous discourse, of a most terrible and bloudy battel, fought in Barbarie, the fowrth day of August, last past. 1578 : VVherein were slaine, two kings, (but as most men say) three, besyde many other famous personages: with a great number of captains, and other souldiers that were slaine on both sides. VVhereunto is also annexed, a note of the names of diuerse that were taken prisoners at the same time</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> great reason, (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader,) that the auncient Poets in old time; fained <hi>Phaeton</hi> to fal from heauen, and to be drowned in the deapth of the Sea: because not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his calling, he woulde of a prowde ambicious minde, presume to take vppon him the gouernement of his Father <hi>Phaebus</hi> Chariot, being a thing farre beyond his skil to compas. For surely there is not in the whole world, a more pestilent euil, or a thing that breedeth so much mischife, as doth the cankred and most accursed vice of ambition, which not onely worketh the ruine of the partye therewith pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessed: but often times causeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of many mighty Monark<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e vtter ouerthrovv of whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes and common weales.</p>
   <p>Wherewith the words of <hi>Cornelius <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
            <desc>…</desc>
         </gap>rus</hi> do verry aptly agree, who saith that after the desier of principallytie had longe continued in the mindes of men vndiscouered: when Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>an to enlarge their Limittes, and to make their dominions greater: when they began to conquer kingdomes, and enuying the felicitie of common weales, desired the confusion and vtter ouerthrowe one of another. Then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan this ambition first of all to breake out, which as (Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> saieth) pleaseth and delighteth euery man, and yet is there nothinge that doth more cruelly crucifie or breede more vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes, then it doth.</p>
   <p>For from whence springeth bloody warres so much, as from this roote of Ambition.</p>
   <p>What causeth so manye to endure the extremitie of the coulde Winter nightes, by lying abroade in the open
<pb facs="3"/> Feeldes without any harbour, and to abide the heate of the whot Sommer season being clogged with the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of their vnweldye armoure: but onelye ambicion?</p>
   <p>Is it ought els but this greedy ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that maketh men to trauell so many intemperate countryes, and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately to runne into so many doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full daingers as they do?</p>
   <p>In conclusion, there is nothing that more breaketh the bandes of beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, abateth the obedience of childrē towardes their Parentes: the loue of Parentes, towardes their Children: the dutye of subiectes, towardes their Princes, and the care of Countryes commoditye, from al men, as doth this abominable vice of ambicion.</p>
   <p>Whereof dyuers historyes aswell of auncient time, as examples daylye shewed amongst vs, is a most perfect testimony.</p>
   <p>By the greedye ambition of <hi>Scilla Marius, Carbo, Cinna, Pompeius,</hi> and <hi>Caesar,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> there were more slaine amongst the <hi>Romaines,</hi> then in conquering to them the kingdome of the whole world.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Silla</hi> condempned &amp; caused to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted 80000. <hi>Romaines,</hi> besydes many <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore that were slaine in the ciuil wars, betweene him and both the <hi>Marius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Also <hi>Pompeius</hi> and <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> the one suffring no peere, the other no su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, by their insasiable ambition, caused innumerable people to be slaine betweene them, and subuerted the best and most renowmed publique weale, in the whole world: and finally, enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little time to reioyce them in theyr vnlawfull desires, <hi>Pompeius</hi> shamefullye flyinge, had his head stroken off, by the commaundement of <hi>Ptolome</hi> Kinge of <hi>Egipt:</hi> vnto whom as to his frende he fled for succour, and <hi>Caesar</hi> that was the vanquisher, was shortlye after cruellye murdred in the Senate, with daggers, by them whom he best trusted, and most specially fauowred.</p>
   <p>It would require much time, and a
<pb facs="4"/> verye large volume, to make mencion of all those that heretofore, by coueting to encrease their credit and estimation in the worlde, and to aduaunce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to high dignities, haue brought both themselues and their countryes to extreame daunger.</p>
   <p>But I will leaue heere to rehearse any more of such antiquitye, and shew a more liuely &amp; lamentable example, of three renowmed Princes: who not longe since by their ambicious desires, did not onely procure their owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death: but also the destruction of many thousandes of their people, in the maintenaunce of their vniust quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, as by that which followeth shall more manifestly appeare.</p>
   <p>But before I proceede to the matter, I haue here thought good, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders better instruction, breflye to discribe the country of <hi>Barbary,</hi> and the customes thereof.</p>
   <p>(∵)</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>