<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Exhortation to the Planter and Graffer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108874_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19451</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5874</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108874</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Exhortation to the Planter and Graffer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The country-mans recreation, or The art of planting, graffing, and gardening : in three bookes. The first declaring divers wayes of planting, and graffing ... also how to cleanse your grafts and cions, how to helpe barren and sicke trees, how to kill wormes and vermin and to preserve and keepe fruit, how to plant and proyne your vines, and to gather and presse your grape ... how to make your cider and perry ... The second treateth of the hop-garden, with necessary instructions for the making and the maintenance thereof ... Whereunto is added, the expert gardener, containing divers necessary and rare secrets belonging to that art</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hearne (Herne, Heron), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young, Michael</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 127, 1, 2, 54 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_gardener">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>An Exhortation to the Planter and Graffer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Egard alwayes before ye doe intend to plant or graffe, it shall be meete to have good experience in things meet for this Art, as in knowing the natures of all fruites and the differences of Climates, which be contrary in every Land: also to understand the East and West winds, with Aspects and Starres, to the end ye may begin no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that the Wind or Raine may oppresse, that your labour be not lost, and to marke also and consider the dispositions of the Elements that present yeare, for all yeares be not of like operation, nor yer after one sort; the Summer and Winter doe not beare one face on the Earth, nor the Spring-time alwayes raine, or Autumne alwayes moist▪ of this none have understanding, without a good and lively marking Spirit, few or none without learning may discerne of the varieties and qualities of the earth, and what he doth aske or refuse. Therefore it shall be good to have understanding of the Ground where ye doe plant either Orchard or Garden with fruit, first it behoveth to make a sure Defence, to the end that not onely rude Persons and Children may be kept ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, but all kind of hurtfull Cattle endamaging your Plants or Trees, as Oxen, Kine, Calves, Horses, Hogs, and Sheepe, as the rubbing of sheepe doth greatly burne the sap, and often doth kill young Trees and Plants, and where they are broken or bruised with Cattell, it is doubtfull to grow after. It shall be good also to Set, Plant, or Graffe Trees all of like nature and strength together, that the great and high trees may not overcome the low and weake, for when they be not like of height, they grow no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ripe not your fruit so well at one time, but the one before the other. That earth which is good for Vines, is good also for other fruit.</p>
   <p>Ye must dig your holes a yeare before ye Plant, that the earth may bee the better seasoned, mortified and waxe tender, both by Raine in Winter,
<pb facs="3"/> and heate on Summer, that thereby your Plants may take root the sooner, if ye will make your holes and plant both in a yeare: at the least ye ought to make your holes two moneths before ye plant, and as soone as they be made, then it shall be good to burn straw or such l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke therein, to mak the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ground warme. The further ye make them asunder, the better your trees shall beare. Make your holes like unto a furnace, that is, more straight in the mouth then beneath, whereby the rootes may have the more roome, and by straightnesse of the mouth, the lesse rainer cold shall enter by in Winter, and so lesse heate to the roote in Summer.</p>
   <p>Looke also that the earth ye put to the rootes, be neither wet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> laid in water: they doe commonly leave a good space betwixt every tree, for the hanging boughes, for being nigh together, ye cannot set rootes, nor sow nothing so well under your trees, nor they wil not beare fruit so well Some loveth forty foote, some thirty betweene every tree: your Plants ought to be greater then the handle of a shovell, and the lesser the better. See they be straight without knots or knobs, having a long straight grain or barke, which shall the sooner be apt to take Graffes, and when ye set branches or boughes of old trees, choose the straightest branch thereof, and those trees which have borne yearely good fruit before, take of those which be on the Sunny-side, sooner than those that grow in the cover or shadow, and when ye take up or alter your Plants, ye shall note to what your plant is subject, and so let them be set againe, but those which have growne in dry Grounds, let them be set in moyst Grounds, your Plants ought to be cut of three foot long. If ye will set two or three Plants toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a hole, ye must take heed the roote of one touch not another, for then the one will perish and rot the other, or dye by Wormes of other Vermen, and when yon have placed your Plants in the earth, it shall be good to strike downe to the bottome of every hole, two short stakes as great as your arme, on either side your hole one, and let them appeare but a little above the earth that ye may thereby in Summer give water unto the rootes if need be. Your young Plants and rooted Trees are commonly set in Autumne, from the first unto the fifteenth of <hi>October,</hi> yet some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is, better after <hi>Alhallontide</hi> untill <hi>Christmas,</hi> then in the Spring, because the earth will dye too soone after, and also to set Plants without root after <hi>Michaelmasse,</hi> that they may be the better mollified and gather roote against the Spring, whereof ye shall find heereafter more at larger Thus much have I thought meete to declare unto the Planters, Graffers, and Gardeners, whereby they may the better avoyd the occasions and dangers of Planting, Graffing, and Gardening, which may come often times through ignorance.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>