<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of Loue. The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108443_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19058</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5473</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108443</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of Loue. The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A table of humane passions : With their causes and effects. Written by ye Reuerend Father in God F.N. Coeffeteau, Bishop of Dardania, councellor to ye French King in his Councels of Estate, suffrage and administrator generall of ye Bishopricke of Metz. Translated into English by Edw. Grimeston Sergiant at Armes</title>
                 <author>Coeffeteau, Nicolas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 684 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="78" facs="64"/>
   <head>Of <hi>Loue.</hi> The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Ancient sayd, that to expell Youth out of our townes, were to cut off the Spring time of the yeare. But we may maintaine with no lesse truth, that to banish <hi>Loue</hi> from a ciuill life, and the conuersation of men, were not only to depriue the <hi>yeare</hi> of her goodliest sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but also as it were to pull the Sunne out of the firmament, and to fill the whole world with horror and confusion. For
<pb n="79" facs="64"/>
what is there in this life, bee it amidst honors and glory, in riches and treasures, yea in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleasures, that can giue a full and sound content vnto man, without the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the sweetenes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to friends? Wherefore an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Philosopher</hi> said, that if any one were raised aboue the heauens, from whence he might behold all the wonders of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and of the world, and see with amazement the reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, periods, order, diuersity, &amp; beauty of the Planets and Stars, and had no friend to whom hee might impart this admiration; all these things in steed of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of ioy, would become dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing and importune to his thoughts. For as colours which are the most exquisite orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>nature,</hi> how liuely and
<pb n="80" facs="65"/>
glistring so euer they be, wil not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>āding be darkned &amp; giue no pleasure to our eies, if they were not enlightned, and as it were inspired by the light which discouers vnto vs the singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and perfections: so what wealth or honor soeuer we enioy in this life, we cannot tast the sweetnes therof but in represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto our selues the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which comes to thē we loue, and whom we thinke haue an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual <hi>Passion</hi> on our behalfe. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paminondas</hi> gloried to haue won <hi>2</hi> battels, his Father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being yet liuing; as if the ioy that those persons conceiued which were so neere to him, had made his victories more stately, &amp; increased the glory &amp; pompe of his triumphs. In like manner there is no man liuing, which in the cours of his prosperities doth
<pb n="81" facs="65"/>
not feel as it were an increase of happinesse, when as he imagines that his friends are spectators &amp; partakers of his felicity. And moreouer what can be sweeter to our thoughts then the image of a true &amp; constant <hi>loue,</hi> which we are assured our frend doth beare vs? What happinesse to haue a friend to whom we may safely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our hart, and trust him with our most important secrets, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apprehēsion of his cōscience, or any doubt of his fidelity? What content to haue a friend whose discourse sweetens our <hi>cares</hi>? whose counsells disperse our feares? whose conuersation charmes our griefs? whose circū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection assures our fortunes, &amp; whose only pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sence fils vs with ioy and content? Seeing then <hi>loue</hi> is a <hi>Passion</hi> which doth produce such sweete and ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb n="82" facs="66"/>
contents in the society of men, we will endeauour to shew what his beginning is, wherein his essence consists, to what Persons it extends, and what the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects bee.</p>
   <div n="1" type="chapter">
      <pb n="83" facs="66"/>
      <head>Of the beginning of Loue. CHAP. 1.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of men to refer the noblest effects to the most excellent causes; many considering the dignity of <hi>loue,</hi> haue imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that this <hi>Passion</hi> came from a particular impression, which God makes in our <hi>Soules,</hi> inspiring into them with the <hi>nature,</hi> the affections which transport them, and which makes them seeke the
<pb n="84" facs="67"/>
obiects which are pleasing vnto them. The which they striue to proue by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the naturall inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he hath giuen to other Creatures. Wee see, say they, that God as the Author of <hi>nature,</hi> hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into light things an inclination to rise vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to seeke the place of their rest, by reason whereof the fire doth alway send his flame towards <hi>heauen.</hi> And in like manner hee hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in heauy things a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination which makes them tend to the <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>: so as stones, marbles, and such like, do alwayes bend downeward, &amp; do not hang in the aire, but with violence and contrary to their incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. In the same manner,
<pb n="85" facs="67"/>
say they, God hath ingrafted in man a certain inclination to those things which haue some beames of beauty or bounty, so as when these ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects come to incounter his eyes or minde, he is rauished, and then presently there is framed in his heart an ardent desire to seeke and pursue them. They confirme this opinion by the diuerse incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which shine in the life of men from their birth. For wee see some loue pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting naturally, others take delight in Geometry, some are passionatly affected to the Liberall Arts, others im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Mechanicks; some loue Hunting, others burne with a desire of Play; some are borne to War; &amp; others are inclined to Mildnes and
<pb n="86" facs="68"/>
peace; some haue no content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but in solitarinesse; and others cannot liue without the mannaging of affaires. And whence, say they, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed these so different incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, but from the author of <hi>nature?</hi> The which they confirme againe by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of things which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen often in the loue which men beare one vnto another; for that it will sometimes fall out, that by a certaine simpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of mindes, wee shall loue at the first incounter a man whom we haue neuer before seene nor knowne. So as it seemes, this affection doth not then disclose it selfe in our soules, taking forme so suddenly and sweetly, but it is rather quickned and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the presence of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,
<pb n="87" facs="68"/>
which makes vs to see that which we loue instantly without delay, for that wee knew him not, finding him so conformable to our humors and inclination. The which hath made some presuppose, that the beames of their eyes, which loue incountering with the beames which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the obiect which inflames them, makes so sweete a mixture, as their vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is as it were the fulnesse of al the delights which may be tasted in this life: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise at the first incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wee shall haue a distast of some other person whom we had neuer seene before: Doth not this proue (say they) that it is nature which frames in vs this <hi>Passion</hi>? and so they conclude, that it cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="88" facs="69"/>
but from the Author of <hi>nature:</hi> others prefer the cause of <hi>loue</hi> to the <hi>Planets, Starres,</hi> and constellations, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suppose that the reason why <hi>Achilles</hi> loued <hi>Patroclus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Hephestion,</hi> and the Queene of the <hi>Amazons, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>; And to come to moderne examples, that <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth loued the Marshall of <hi>Rais,</hi> that <hi>Henry</hi> the third loued the Dukes of <hi>Ioyeuse,</hi> and <hi>Espernon,</hi> and <hi>Monsier de Termes</hi>; that <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth loued the Duke of <hi>Suilly</hi>; and that the King now gloriously reigning loues the Duke of <hi>Luines</hi> and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; are all effects of the as<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pects of the <hi>Planets,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered at the natiuities of these Princes and Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Others seeke the cause
<pb n="89" facs="69"/>
in the Parents, as if they which bring vs into the world, with our being did transfer and infuse into vs their <hi>Passions.</hi> Others refer it to the good or bad educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we receiue, according to which wee frame our desires and affections. The <hi>Platoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> imagine that wee must seeke it in the degrees of the harmony which is found in <hi>Soules</hi>; which they beleeue are compounded as of a consort and proportion of numbers, the which incountering e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually in two persons, incites them to loue one another. But this is very mystical, and requires a spirit accustomed to the imaginations of <hi>Plato.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>To come then to the point, it is certaine that God hath infused into our soules the
<pb n="90" facs="70"/>
seedes of loue, seeing that he hath giuen vs the powers which are capable. It is also certaine that the influence of the Planets may cōtribute to this <hi>Passion</hi>; for that it resides in the <hi>concupiscible appetite,</hi> the which is a sensitiue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and depends of the body, ouer whose motions the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets haue a kind of power. It is also visible, that nurture &amp; education, &amp; sometimes the inclinations which our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents haue ingrafted in vs, may haue a share in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our affections. But to speake according to the rules of <hi>Philosophy,</hi> wee must say precisely and absolutely, that the bounty of things, whether they bee found in them, or that wee imagine them to be, is the Spring, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
<pb n="91" facs="70"/>
and mouing cause of the loue wee beare them. For God the Author of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who hath created all things in number, weight, &amp; measure, hath also imparted to all Creatures, inclinations and motions necessary to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto their ends. So hee hath infused into his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding an inclination which makes him passionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to seeke the truth, and to imbrace it when hee hath found it. And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hee hath ingrafted in the wil a desire and loue of good, which is the only obiect which may moue it and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame it to pursue it. And as colours are the obiect of the sight, which drawe it by a certaine attraction, which growes from a naturall sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy
<pb n="92" facs="71"/>
which is betwixt them, like vnto that which is betwixt our vnderstanding and truth, betwixt the eye and colours; and betwixt the hearing and sounds. Hence it growes that there is so strict a cōnexion betwixt the will and the good, as the will cannot loue any thing which hath not a shew of good. So as if it bee at any time decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and imbraceth the <hi>euill,</hi> it is vnder a veile and shew of <hi>good,</hi> which is imployed to abuse it; and the like may bee sayd of the <hi>sensitiue appetite,</hi> which in its motions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the same instincts that the will doth. But when as wee say, that the good is the obiect of our <hi>will</hi> and <hi>loue,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this <hi>good</hi> wee compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that which is faire, for
<pb n="93" facs="71"/>
that goodly things haue an equall power with those things that bee good, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our <hi>wills</hi>: as also beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and bounty in effect are all one, and differ not but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our imagination. The which the <hi>Platonicians</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate by excellent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, calling <hi>loue</hi> simply a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of beauty. Yea to shew that beauty is louely of it selfe, as well as bounty, they adde that beauty which shines in the body, is as it were a beame or image of the infinite beauty which is in God; wherefore we admire it and loue it passionatly, when it presents it selfe vnto our eyes; and then, say they, the beauty of the body is also an image of the beauty of the mind: for that the internall
<pb n="94" facs="72"/>
perfections ingender the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, as the lustre of preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous stones &amp; pearles growes from the perfect mixture of the foure Elemēts which are found in their constitution, as flowers and leaues of trees borrow their beauty from the roote; and as in beasts the good interior constitution is the cause of the beauty which appeares in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. So then wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the external beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the body proceeds from the internall bounty of the mind, so as bounty seemes to bee the roote of beauty, and beauty the flower of that bounty which shines in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And therefore hee that containes himselfe within his bounds and in the innocency of <hi>loue,</hi> seeing the beauty of
<pb n="95" facs="72"/>
the body, imagines (as it is true) that this pleasing obiect is a beame of the infinit and immense beauty, whereof the essence of God is as it were the center, from whence shee deriues and takes her begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and consequently, that it is as it were a sience of the interior beauty which shines in the soule, from whence the body hath taken life. Thus the <hi>Platonicians</hi> proue that beauty as well as bounty makes an impression in our wills, and proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably inflames our desires, &amp; begets affections and <hi>Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which makes vs to seeke it. But leauing all other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to proue this assertion, wee will content our selues with the saying of <hi>Aristotle</hi>; That to demaund why wee
<pb n="96" facs="73"/>
loue beautifull things, were a question fit for a blind man, for that the eyes feele and know how powerfull the charmes are to make an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression in the <hi>Soule.</hi> By this which wee haue spoken it is easie to bee gathered, that loue hath for obiect and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cause the bounty and beauty of things, which by the sweetnes of the beames they cast forth, make so pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull an impression in our soules, as they remaine as it were rauished or rather char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with so pleasant a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre; so as to ascend vnto the Spring &amp; fountaine, we must eleuate our selues to that great and immortal Essence, which is as it were a notion of all the graces, of all the beauties and of all the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="97" facs="73"/>
which are infused into al the creatures. We must, I say, raise vp our selues to that infinite and most happy Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, which is as it were the center, from whence all the perfections which represent themselues so goodly vnto our eyes, and so pleasing vnto our sense, borrow their lustre and take their beginning. And in this manner wee shall tie our affections to an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect worthy of the generosity of their motions, which should alwayes imitate the nature of fire, which remaines vnwillingly in the earth, and striues continually to mount towards heauen.</p>
      <p>Finally, wee must remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>Loue</hi> is deuided into fiue branches, and that there are fiue kinds which differ
<pb n="98" facs="74"/>
much one from another: for there is a loue of naturall things, there is a loue of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; there is a loue of men; there is a loue of Angells; and there is a loue of God. The <hi>Loue</hi> of naturall things is nothing else but the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which things destitute of knowledge haue to vnite themselues vnto their ends, and to attaine the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their nature; to which sence an Ancient sayd, that the loue of the bodies was nothing else but the weight wherewith they are ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, bee it that the weight keepes them downe, or that the lightnes raiseth them vp on high: for God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted these inclinations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all naturall things, to the end they may attaine to
<pb n="99" facs="74"/>
their perfections, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue them when they haue once gotten them. The loue of creatures is nothing else but a vehement impression made in their sences, surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with things which they conceiue to be pleasing. This <hi>Passion</hi> is many times blind, importune, obstinate, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solent, and is common to men, &amp; brute beastes, which suffers themselues to bee transported with the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a dishonest pleasure.</p>
      <p>Humaine <hi>Loue</hi> is a <hi>Passion</hi> which should follow the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>reason,</hi> and which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guided by the light of the soule shold only imbrace the true good, to make it perfect: for containing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe within these bounds, it should no more be a violent
<pb n="100" facs="75"/>
&amp; furious passion, which filles the world daily with so many miseries by her exorbitant and strang disorders. The <hi>Loue</hi> of Angells flies yet high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for that those happy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits enlightned with a more excellent light, and illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a more pure &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect splendour, loue the soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Good more ardently then all the creatures, and by a reflux of this great <hi>Loue</hi> take an incredible care of the affaires of men; and being neuer wearied in the seruice they do them by the cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, assist them, &amp; procure their safety, with constancy, and ioy full of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement and wonder. The <hi>Loue</hi> of God enters not into comparison with any other, for that as there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="101" facs="75"/>
betwixt things fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and infinite, his moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being infinite, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare with another lustre, and shew themselues with a greater endeauor towards that he loues, then the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can doe. From this spring flow the admirable beauties which shine in the heauens, in the Starres, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, Elements, in bodies both simple and compound, and in great, meane, and small things; all which do feele the effects of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the perfect assistance of his prouidence. From this spring proceedes the care which hee hath of men, the graces which he imparts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, the good desires wherewith hee doth inspire them, and the meanes which
<pb n="102" facs="76"/>
hee offers them to raise them vp to the height of his glory, and to make them enioy the felicity of Angells. But we will not treate of this kind of <hi>loue,</hi> whereof wee had rather feele the flames then describe the perfection. Neither will wee discourse of that of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, which wee may better admire then set forth: wee will not in like sort busie our selfe with that of naturall things or of creatures, which is too base for our subiect, but wee will represent the <hi>Loue</hi> which is a humaine <hi>Passion,</hi> whereof morall <hi>Philosophy</hi> teacheth vs to discourse, and whose essence we meane now to set downe.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="chapter">
      <pb n="103" facs="76"/>
      <head>Wherein the Essence of Loue <hi>doth consist.</hi> CHAP. 2.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in other sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects we dovsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ascend vnto the knowledge of the cause by the search of the effects, so in this matter to attaine vnto an exact knowledge of the nature of <hi>Loue,</hi> we must first vnderstand what it is to <hi>loue,</hi> to the end the branch may discouer the nature of the roote. <hi>Loue</hi> then is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, but, <hi>To will good to some one, not for our owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate interest, but for the loue of himselfe; procuring with all our
<pb n="104" facs="77"/>
power what we thinke may bee profitable for him, or may giue him content.</hi> Whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, there are foure things to be considered in <hi>Loue.</hi> The first is, that wee be carefull of his good whom we <hi>Loue</hi>; the which growes, for that <hi>loue</hi> vnites the <hi>wills</hi> perfectly, and makes vs esteeme the good which befalls him we loue, as our owne particular: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ancients sayd, that <hi>Loue</hi> was one soule in two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. The which it seems that <hi>Alexander</hi> would giue <hi>Darius</hi> mother to vnderstand, when he sayd that <hi>Hephestion</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Alexāder</hi>: For he vsed this speech in regard of the great affection hee bare him, the which was such as he held him another himself, so as he would haue him a partaker of
<pb n="105" facs="77"/>
all his honors &amp; glory. After this manner then wee should desire to our friends the same honors, the same glory, and all other felicities which we wish for our own proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. And when they succeed, wee must reioyce as if wee our selues enioyed them, seeing that all things are common among friends.</p>
      <p>But secondly we must wish al this good to those we loue for their ownesakes, and not for any priuate interest of our owne, or for any profite wee expect to reape by them; for the <hi>Epicures</hi> opinion (who wil haue men loue for profit, or pleasure) is infamous, and makes <hi>Loue</hi> either mercenary or of small continuance. Wee must then remember that there are three kinds of
<pb n="106" facs="78"/>
friendship; that is to say, <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, profitable,</hi> and <hi>pleasing.</hi> Betwixt the which there is this difference, that the two last kinds are no true affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but rather shadowes of <hi>Loue</hi>; whereas the first, that is to say, <hi>honest friendship,</hi> which hath vertue for her obiect, is solid and true, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer it is constant and of long continuance; whereas the profitable and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing last little, and are dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon the first alteration which happens in the subiect whereunto they are tied. As for example, they that loue only for profit, continue no longer in this affection, then they whom they loue, may be beneficiall vnto them; the which ceasing, they renounce the duties of friendship
<pb n="107" facs="78"/>
which they had formerly shewed; for that the cause ceasing, the effect of necessity must cease. Hence it growes that the friendships of Court are so inconstant and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, for that Courtiers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e their affections to those which are in fauour, &amp; haue some kind of credit, to the end it may bee an entry, for them to offices in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state. But if there happen any alteration in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune by a disgrace with the Prince, and that they see them vnable, and incapable to assist them, they presently abandon them, and make no more account of them then of an image ouerthrowne; yea they would haue men thinke that they neuer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued them. So in <hi>Tiberius</hi>
         <pb n="108" facs="79"/>
time, <hi>Seianus</hi> possessing his maister absolutely, &amp; recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the fauor of this Prince with full sailes, so as all the honors, all the dignities, and all the offices of the Estate, depended of the inclination he had to those that courted him; all the world adored him, the people and Senate erected statues vnto him, hee was publiquely praised, his house was neuer empty, all the Orders went to consult with him as with an oracle, or rather as the soule of the Empire. But as soone as his fauour began to shake, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently hee saw the affections of such as had so shamefully flattered him, decay and die; and when it was wholly falne, there followed so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s a change in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb n="109" facs="79"/>
of the Court and people, as after they had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily massacred him, they drew his body through the streete into the riuer of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> his statues were beaten downe, all his kinsfolkes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted, his memory detest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the name of <hi>Seianus</hi> was held in execration to all the world. But this is the ordinary course in Court, whereas Fortune is alwayes adored.</p>
      <p>As the affections which depend vpon profite decay as soone as the profite cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, in like manner that friendship which is suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only by pleasure, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues no longer then the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of pleasure indureth. For they that loue in considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of beauty, when as age or
<pb n="110" facs="80"/>
infirmities makes it to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and decay, their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is gone, and they esteeme no more that which they had formerly honored. So as there is no true nor solid friendship but that which is grounded vpon vertue and honesty. The rest hauing inconstant and wandring ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, are also inconstant and mutable, and the interest and pleasures ceasing, they die: whereas honest loue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding vnto it selfe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and durable obiect, knowes no change. They that Loue in this sort wish all good to him they loue, for his owne sake, and not for their priuate interest. The third thing wee must consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in <hi>Loue</hi> is, that wee are bound to imploy all our
<pb n="111" facs="80"/>
meanes to procure good to them wee loue. For as the Sunne should not deserue the name of Sunne if it gaue not light to the whole world, so wee cannot esteeme him a true friend which doth not imploy himselfe with all his power and meanes to bind him whom he makes professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to loue. And this admits no limitation nor bounds, for there is not any thing which <hi>Loue</hi> will not make him do that loues perfectly, euen to contemne his owne life for the safety of him hee loues. It is true, that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect friend should wish that he to whom he hath ingaged his affection, should haue all things happy and prosperous in the course of his life, that hee be neuer shaken with any
<pb n="112" facs="81"/>
storme, and that hee neuer feele any crosses of fortune; but as the condition of man is fraile and exposed to a thousand calamities, if it chance that hee fall into any infirmity, he must participate of his paine. If a tempest carries him through the waues of the sea, hee must hoist saile to follow him; yea if the billowes ouerset his ship, he must seeke him in this shipwracke. If Tyrants seaze vpon him, if they cast him into prison &amp; loade him with chaines, hee must offer his owne body to free his bonds; and if they send him to execution, he must present his head to redeeme his friends. If hee see him assaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his enemies, who seeke to murther him, he must pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="113" facs="81"/>
himselfe to beare their blowes. And if he see him in the throat of lions, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to the rage of wild beasts, hee must hazard himselfe to free him from danger; and if he die, he must in like manner abhorre life. <hi>Hee that loues perfectly,</hi> sayd <hi>Plato</hi> by the mouth of <hi>Phedro, will rather abandon himselfe to death, then expose that he loues to dangers. And there is no man so faint hearted, whom Loue doth not fill with courage and inflame with a force, to make him in this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect equall to the most generous soules. For that which</hi> Homer <hi>saith, that the Worthies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired with a diuine force and furie, is more truely verified in those that loue, whō loue hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten inspired with a diuine fury, which hath made them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
<pb n="114" facs="82"/>
death, to preserue the life of those they haue loued.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The last thing that is to be considered in <hi>Loue,</hi> is that we wish vnto our friends; the things which we thinke true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are good for them, that is to say, that we desire for them the things that are iust, and that are adorned with all the circumstances of vertue. In regard whereof hee spake wisely, which answered his friend, who would haue him forsweare himselfe, that hee was a friend euen vnto the altars, hauing no intent to serue his friend against his conscience. In this case then <hi>Loue</hi> admits bounds &amp; limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and it were to abuse the name, to bind him that loues, to commit vniust things in fauour of them to
<pb n="115" facs="82"/>
whom he wisheth well. So when as <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Burbon</hi> (to reuēge his priuate discōtent) abandoned <hi>France</hi> and his King, and imbraced the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Spaine</hi> &amp; the Emperour, the Princes &amp; Noblemen his friends, (whereof he had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Court) did not hold themselues bound to follow him, and to make themselues confederates of his despight and rebellion. So as these words which are at this day in the mouth of many, that they are ready to turne Turkes for their friends, yea and to follow them into hell, is the speech rather of a fury, then the discourse of men transported with true <hi>Loue:</hi> for <hi>Loue</hi> must cōtaine it selfe within the bounds of iustice, honesty, and vertue, and not
<pb n="116" facs="83"/>
make vs do any thing which may breed vs shame. And moreouer, they that make these impious protestations, haue them more in their mouthes then in their harts; and I know not how they can make them without blush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. By al this which we haue sayd, it is easie to gather wherein the essence of <hi>Loue</hi> doth properly consist, the which we may define in this manner.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Loue is a wellwishing, which we testifie with all our power to those, to whom we haue an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, procuring them for their owne sakes, all the good we think may giue them content.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which hee is a friend that loues, and is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally beloued; for <hi>loue</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were a torch which
<pb n="117" facs="83"/>
lightens another, friends must beleeue that affections are reciprocall, and that as they loue, so they are belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; wherein they must not shew themselues vnpleasing or importune, to sound the hearts one of another, which will bewray a diffidence and distruct: But content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with the true signes of <hi>loue,</hi> which their friends shew them. These signes of true <hi>Loue</hi> are reduced to three principall heads. The first is, that friends reioyce &amp; grieue for the same things: wherfore <hi>Homer</hi> describing <hi>Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nōs</hi> affliction, when as he was forced to sacrifice his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Iyhigenia,</hi> he represents al his friends accompanying him to this sacrifice, with mournefull countenances &amp;
<pb n="118" facs="84"/>
full of sorrow; and at <hi>Rome,</hi> when as any one was accused and brought in question for his life, al his friends changed their robes with him, to shew that they did participate with his affliction. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is, for that sorrow and ioy are the markes of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of that wee haue in the <hi>soule,</hi> which reioyceth or afflicts it selfe, as the obiects which present themselues are pleasing or distastfull. And for this reason, sorrow and ioy discouer the inclination we haue to any one.</p>
      <p>The second is, that friends share equally betwixt them the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>euill.</hi> They say that there are images of wax, vpon the which inchanters deliuer such powerfull spells, as being made to represent
<pb n="119" facs="84"/>
any person, as soone as they are wronged, the body of him for whom they were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioned, feeles paine. In this sort there is such a bond of affection betwixt friends as the harme which happens to the one, afflicts the other, and fills him with bitternesse, so as many times we haue seene true friends die with sorrow, for the losse of their friend. Yea, prophane histories are full of Persons which haue slaine themselues, for that they would not suruiue them whom they haue loued dearely. In like manner the prosperity of friends passeth from one to another, so as the tryumphs of <hi>Alexander</hi> are the cōtentments of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion,</hi> and the glory of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi> is the ioy of <hi>Alexander.</hi>
         <pb n="120" facs="85"/>
The third is, that they which loue should haue the same friends, and the same ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. They say the Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant or Loadstone doth not only make an impression vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iron which it drawes, but doth also impart his vertue by his touching; so as the iron which it hath toucht, drawes other iron vnto it, and makes as it were a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued chaine. In the same manner, a friend brings his friends to him he loues, and he reciprocally imparts vnto him his friends; whereof there is framed a common bond, which makes them ready to succor one another, as if they were members of one body.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="chapter">
      <pb n="121" facs="85"/>
      <head>To what Persons <hi>Loue</hi> extends. CHAP. 3.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough that <hi>loue</hi> hath for his generall obiect the bounty and beauty which shines in those things which present them selues vnto our eyes and soules; yet there are diuerse particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations, and diuerse beames, which excite this <hi>Passion</hi> and fashion it in the hearts of men. <hi>Aristotle</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers fifteene causes, the which are also diuided into other branches, whereof we will treate as briefely as wee
<pb n="122" facs="86"/>
may, taking only that which shall belong vnto our sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. First, sayth he, men <hi>loue</hi> them which do them good, or whom they thinke haue a will to do it, or to their friends. In truth there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that more bindes the hearts of men, and induceth them more to <hi>loue</hi> then bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits. For euen bruite beasts feele the good which they receiue from men, and there is no creature so wild, whom good vsage doth not make gentle and tame. They that gouerne Lyons feare not their rage, but play about them without any apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of their fury, for that this generous Creature knowes him that hath a care to feede him. By continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all feeding they bring Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants
<pb n="123" facs="86"/>
to do what seruice they desire. And wee must not obiect against it, that it hath beene a common com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in the mouth of men in all ages, that most of the benefits that are bestowed in the world are lost, for that they fall vpon vngratefull soules, who do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themselues in any sort bound. For (as an Ancient hath obserued) this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes not from the nature of the benefits, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise haue a particular vertue to draw the affection and to charme the will: but most commonly the fault proceeds from our selues, for that wee either erre in our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, doing good to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy persons: or we distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it ill, if we take away the
<pb n="124" facs="87"/>
grace. For wee must not think that our benefites bind a friend, if we suffer our selues to be too much courted, if we make him to languish in the pursuite, or if we do it with a kind of vnwillingnesse; for by these meanes wee take away all the merrit and bond of the benefit, for that no man will thinke himselfe behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for that which hee hath purchased so dearely: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Ancient called bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of that nature, a loafe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with stones, which no man can vse. Men therefore thinke themselues bound to those from whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue benefits, whether they be great and worthy to bee acknowledged, in regard of their greae shew and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence; or that they which
<pb n="125" facs="87"/>
are the authors, bestow them freely without importunity, and with a singular demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of <hi>Loue</hi>; or that such as giue, haue made a sit choice of time to bind them, assisting them when as they or their friends had extreame neede, and when as they thinke that for their owne sakes they haue bound them by these benefits.</p>
      <p>They also <hi>Loue</hi> the friends of their friends, and such as haue any conformity with them in the subiect of their affection, and that <hi>Loue</hi> those whom they <hi>Loue,</hi> and who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so make profession to be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their enemy. The reason is, that reputing their friends good as their owne, they beleeue, that the good which is done vnto their
<pb n="126" facs="88"/>
friends extends vnto them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>selues, and that they do par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate wholy thereof. In regard whereof they <hi>loue</hi> the spring and fountaine. And contrariwise they beleeue, that the auersion and distast they haue of their enemies is a token of the <hi>loue</hi> they beare them. They also <hi>loue</hi> those that succour them with their meanes, or bind them with the hazard of their liues. For first of all, men loue bountifull friends passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onatly, imagining that they are borne for the good of mankind. As for the second, men <hi>loue</hi> great courages, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magining that they are sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of their liues; &amp; that they will neuer suffer wrong to bee done vnto the weake and feeble. They also loue
<pb n="127" facs="88"/>
such as they hold to bee iust, and resemble not the <hi>Harpeys</hi> or rauening birds, which liue of spoyle, but content themselues with their owne fortunes, committing no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, nor offering violence to any. And in this rancke they put labourers and handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts men, to whom all the world seemes to beare an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, in regard of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of their profession. They also put in the same rancke, temperate persons, in whom they see some great modesty to shine, which shew that their soules are not inclined to any kind of iniustice. They againe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme those that leade a peaceable life, which haue no curiosity, and which pry not into the liues of other men,
<pb n="128" facs="89"/>
but content themselues to order, &amp; gouerne those that are submitted to their care and charge, presupposing that such as containe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues within these bounds, thinke not of any iniustice or wickednesse. Men also <hi>Loue</hi> famous persons, who by their vertue haue attained to an eminent glory, and an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary reputation, bee it generally in the world, or only among good men, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong such as they haue in admiration, or by whom they themselues are admired; and they especially make great shew of their affection, when as they presume, that these Persons in all their dignity and greatnes disdaine them not, but are wel pleased with the testimonies of their <hi>Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi>;
<pb n="129" facs="89"/>
so wee haue seene peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple runne by whole troupes from all the corners of the world, to see conquerours &amp; such as did triumph; men of holy life, and Persons indued with rare knowledge or wisedome, aboue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sort of men. The reason is, for that vertue, generosity, sanctity, and eminent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, are not only louely things of themselues, and which haue powerfull allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to cause them to bee affected and admired in the subiects where they reside, but also men beleeue there is a kind of glory to bee admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the fauour of such il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious persons, whose glory seemes to communicate with those that haue the honor to come neere them. But men
<pb n="130" facs="90"/>
         <hi>Loue</hi> particularly these fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and vertuous Persons, when as they discouer, that they disdaine not the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>Loue</hi> of those, which make shew to honor them with <hi>Passions</hi>; for it is a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their moderatiō &amp; of the bounty of their nature, not to be puft vp with the glorious aduantages which they haue gottē aboue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary sort of men. They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>Loue</hi> such as are of a sweete conuersation, and that haue a milde and pleasing humor, that is to say, they <hi>Loue</hi> those that are not fantasticall, and of a troublesome and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune behauiour. They also <hi>Loue</hi> such as reproue them not odiously of their faults, they loue those whom they see enemies of contention,
<pb n="131" facs="90"/>
and which make shew, that they haue not a desire to bee superior in al disputes which rise in companies; but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōmodate themselues wisely and moderately to that which is contested. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is, for that these wayward spirits, they that are licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their answeres, and such as will alwayes in their arguments haue the vpper hand, seeme to bee borne to contradict and controule the opinions of the whole world: the which is a signe of the alienation of wills, and dissenting from others; which makes them to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: whereas contrariwise they <hi>Loue</hi> such as haue none of these bad humours, and which accomodate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in company, without
<pb n="132" facs="91"/>
making any shew to bee selfe conceited. Moreouer men haue as it were a naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to <hi>Loue</hi> those which haue a quicknes and grace in their incounters, or to iest pleasantly, but withall can indure to heare a witty returne: hence it comes that in Court, buffoones and iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, which haue biting and <hi>Satiricall</hi> spirits, are so much esteemed; and yet many times these people, bite pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Persons too sensibly and indiscreetly, and draw vpon them the iust wrath of those whom they haue licentiously offended. In the meane time the reasons why they <hi>Loue</hi> such as are sudden in their incounters and sharpe in their ieasts, is, for that it seemes this quicknesse, &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinesse
<pb n="133" facs="91"/>
to incounter, proceeds from the subtilty and force of their spirits. And then we are inclined to heare men euil spoken of; wherefore we <hi>Loue</hi> them that do it with a good grace. And for that we <hi>Loue</hi> particularly such as take liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty to iest at others, &amp; are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be iested withall; that proceedes, for that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that such as will indure that which they themselues practise to others, haue no bad intent nor any bitternes in their hearts, but are carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to these incounters, more through a quicknesse of wit, then by any spleene. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer they loue such, as seeme to make great esteeme of the good partes and qualities which they beleeue they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy. Wherefore wee suffer
<pb n="134" facs="92"/>
our selues to be surprized by flatterers, who insinuate into our fauours, couer our defects, &amp; seeme to admire our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This misery happēs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to such as distrust themselues, and who feare to want those vertues which they desire to attaine vnto. For this distrust b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the praises which they giue them, they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues bound to such as bring this support vnto their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
      <p>They also loue those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons which affect neatnesse in all things, who take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to carry a pleasing countenance, and to attire themselues properly: for that this neatnesse and hansome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is as it were a signe of the desire they haue to insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate
<pb n="135" facs="92"/>
themselues into the hearts, and to gaine the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of men, who f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r this cause think thēselues boūd to loue them: they in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner loue them, that lay not their faults before them to shame them, nor reproche them with the benefits wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue bound them. The reason is, for that both the one and the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to our disgrace; and it seemes, that such as enter into these reproaches, will make vs contemptible, either by discouering our defects, or in accusing vs of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. They also loue such as remember not iniuries past, which are not obstinately bent to reuenge, and who are alwaies ready to pardon such as haue offended them.
<pb n="136" facs="93"/>
Wherefore the <hi>Romaines</hi> did wōderfully admire the first of the <hi>Caesars,</hi> for that he forgat nothing but iniuries, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance whereof he held vnworthy the greatnesse of his courage. Wherefore when as this Prince had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againe the statues of <hi>Pompey, Cicero</hi> (that great or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of the <hi>Romaine</hi> Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) pronounced to his commendatiō, that in erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the statues of <hi>Pompey,</hi> he had assured his owne, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wonne the <hi>Loue</hi> of the whole world, by this act o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> humanity, which hee shewed to his enemy opprest with misery. The reason of this <hi>Loue</hi> which men beare to those which forget iniuries in this manner, is, for that they presume when they haue
<pb n="137" facs="93"/>
offended them, they will shew themselues in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to them, as they haue done to others.</p>
      <p>They also loue such as are not il tongued or detractors, which obserue not their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, nor those of their friends, but only regard their vertues, either to admire them, or to frame themselues after their example. For that these things are the offices of good men, and of persons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with singular integrity, and great probity. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, they <hi>loue</hi> such as resist them not when they are in choler, or that importune them not in the middest of their most serious imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for that they which take pleasure in these oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions and importunities,
<pb n="138" facs="94"/>
seeme to <hi>loue</hi> contention, and to be enemies to all society. They also <hi>loue</hi> those that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire them, which haue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that they are vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and make shew that they take delight in their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, and are officious vnto them: But principally, when they make shew of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and liking in those things wherein they would haue their industry admired. As for example, a man that loues <hi>Philosophy,</hi> takes delight to heare his profession prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: he that takes delight in Armes, hath a singulat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to heare his exercise commended: wherefore both the one and the other <hi>loue</hi> those tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> giue glorious te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes their profession. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb n="139" facs="94"/>
all, they haue an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to loue their like, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing which nature teacheth vs dayly, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance ingenders <hi>Loue,</hi> not onely among men, but also among other creatures: for euery creature loues his like: <hi>Tygers</hi> &amp; <hi>Panthers</hi> troop together with beasts of their owne kind: And birds of one fether fly willingly together; such power hath resemblāce to vnite affectiōs: the which we must beleue is more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful in man, who can haue no sweeter conuersatiō thē with his like. The reasō why euery man loues his like, is, for that mā louing passionatly aboue other things, loues conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently any thing that hath any corresponcy with him; so as respecting him whom
<pb n="140" facs="95"/>
he loues as another himselfe, hee cannot but bee inflamed with this consideration. The <hi>Platonicians</hi> had another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, the which in my opinion concurres with this. <hi>Loue,</hi> say they, makes an impression in the soule of him that <hi>loues,</hi> of the Image and forme of the thing beloued. But man lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth not onely his being, and his true and reall forme, but also his imaginary forme; as appeares by pictures, and looking-glasses, in which we behold with content our portraicts &amp; formes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is a certaine <hi>Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for the thing beloued, in whose soule he doth contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate his forme which <hi>Loue</hi> hath ingrauen. After this manner, resemblance bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Loue,</hi> and vnites the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb n="141" facs="95"/>
of men. The truth hereof appeares, for that men do commonly <hi>loue</hi> those, that are allyed vnto them in neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of blood, so as Kinsmen doe commonly loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: or by some confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of humours and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, which maketh me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy men <hi>loue</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of their like, and Iouiall spirits delight in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of them that are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant: Or by some commerce of profession, which maketh <hi>Philosophers</hi> to loue <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi>; and <hi>Painters</hi> delight in <hi>Painters</hi>: Or some equality of age, which makes young men delight in the company of youth, and olde men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse with them that are graue: Or some coherence of manners, which makes good
<pb n="142" facs="96"/>
men loue the vertuous, and the wicked seeke after such as are wickedly affected. But notwithstanding that which we haue said, that cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly men of one profession loue one another, must bee vnderstood according to the true nature of things, for by occasion and accident, this cōformity of professions may ingender hatred and enuy, that is to say, when as they of one trade and profession, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of their art and labour, hinder one another: as for example, when as a tradsman hauing gotten some reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth hinder the profit of his companions, then iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie riseth amongst them, according to the saying of an Ancient, <hi>The Potter enuies the Potter.</hi> The <hi>Philosophers</hi> giue
<pb n="143" facs="96"/>
an excellent reason hereof: He that loues, say they, loues himselfe more deerely then all other things besides: for that he is vnited to himselfe by Essence and Nature, whereas hee is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to him that he loues, but by some accidentall and externall forme. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if this conformity cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth his priuate good, and be preiudiciall vnto him, hee findes himselfe more strictly tied vnto himselfe, then to his like: wherefore seeing his losse concurring with his <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> he whom hee loued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an obstacle to his desire, he growes odious vnto him, as opposite to his good.</p>
      <p>Men doe also loue those that aspire to the same ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and dignities, at the least
<pb n="144" facs="97"/>
when they may attaine vnto them, and enioy them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without any obstacle or wrong one vnto another. For competency causing an hinderance, as it did in the pursuit of the Consulate at <hi>Rome,</hi> it happeneth (as wee haue said of men of the same profession) that it excites en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and hatred: Wherefore in the <hi>loue</hi> of women they can endure no corriuals, for that with honesty they cannot be enioyed by two. They also loue those with whom they haue any familiarity, which is not scrupulous, hauing free liberty without apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of disdaine, to doe and say things in their presence which they would not act or speake before the world. As for example, they affect those
<pb n="145" facs="97"/>
before whom they may free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discourse of their <hi>loues,</hi> of their pursuites, and of their other <hi>Passions.</hi> But wee must remēber that there are some things which are dishonest of themselues, the which a good man may neither do, or speak before the world, or before his friends. But there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which are shameful on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the opiniō of the world, and not according to the truth of things: and these a good man, vsing an honest fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with his friends, may doe and speake in their presence, although he would not doe it in publike before the world: like vnto King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesilaus,</hi> being in priuate with his children, playd with them with a fatherly liberty, but beeing surprized by one,
<pb n="146" facs="98"/>
who knew not how farre the <hi>loue</hi> of a father might extend, he was discontented.</p>
      <p>Men also testifie, that they loue those before whom they are ashamed to doe or say those things which are of themselues shamefull or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest; wherein wee may say, that the <hi>Persians</hi> gaue good testimony of their <hi>loue</hi> to their wiues, when as they caused them to retire from their banquets, being vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that their eies shold be spectators of their excesse, &amp; admitting none but their Concubines. For this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and reuerence which they gaue them, was a signe of true <hi>Loue,</hi> for that wee are ashamed to commit any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Act before them wee affect. They also willingly
<pb n="147" facs="98"/>
imbrace such as they haue seene faithfull, and constant in their affections, and who loue equally both present &amp; absent. For which conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration they desire to insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate themselues into their friendship which testifie their <hi>loue</hi> vnto the dead, who adorne their Tombes, erect Statues, and make other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents for them, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue their memory among men. They also affect such as abandon not their friends in the crosses and iniuries of fortune, whereof wee haue a worthy example in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pithias,</hi> whereof the one beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to die, by the tyrant <hi>Dionisius,</hi> and desiring some respite, to goe and settle the affaires of his house, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion
<pb n="148" facs="99"/>
yeelded himselfe a pledge for his returne, with this condition, that if hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned not backe within the prefixed time, hee should vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the rigour of the same sentence: but the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man presenting himselfe at the day appointed, the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant was so rapt with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to see the faith which he had vnto his friend, in a matter of that importance, and of so great danger, that in stead of putting him to death, he coniured these two perfect friends, to accept of him as a third man in their friendship. Behold how the most sauage and vntamed spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are forced to loue those, that shew an vnuiolable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy in their affectiōs. Men doe also loue such as they see
<pb n="149" facs="99"/>
full of freedome, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dissimulation towards them. In which ranke they nūber such as make no scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to discouer their errors vnto them, and who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them freely with their priuate <hi>passions</hi>: For, as wee haue shewed before, we blush not to say or doe in priuate with our friends, that which we would not doe publickely before the world. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as he that is ashamed to doe any thing before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, shewes that hee loues him not perfectly; so he that hath not this apprehension, giues a manifest testimony that he hath a full confidence in his friendship: wherefore, wee loue such as make shewe to rely vpon vs, euen disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering their imperfections
<pb n="150" facs="100"/>
vnto vs. Againe, they affect those whose authority is not fearefull vnto them, &amp; whose power they thinke they shall haue no cause to apprehend: for no man euer loued him whom he feared seruilely; and herein Tyrants abuse them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, thinking to se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>le their Authority by the terror of Armes, and the terror of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment: yea, they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes detested the furious words of him that said, I care not to be hated, so I may bee feared. It were good among bruit beasts, but men must be managed and gouerned by mildenesse. And they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly embrace such as they may trust; and whose power is not fearefull vnto them. Behold the persons to whom the <hi>Loue</hi> of men doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="151" facs="100"/>
extend.</p>
      <p>In the meane time the true means to purchase <hi>Loue,</hi> is to bind those whose friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship we affect, by all sorts of benefites and good offices. And to this end they must do good before it be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or that they bee forced to discouer their wants vnto vs: for that were to put them on the racke, to make them confesse our magnificence &amp; bounty. Moreouer he must be carefull neuer to reproach the fauours which hee hath done them, nor proclaime them to others, with a vanity which seems to turne to their contempt. He that obserues this mean in the benefits and fauours which hee bestowes, seemes to haue propounded vnto himselfe, the onely good
<pb n="152" facs="101"/>
of him whom he hath bound, without any other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar interest: In regard where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is also bound to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and <hi>Loue</hi> his free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and bounty.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="chapter">
      <head>Of the Effects of <hi>Loue.</hi> CHAP. 4.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Ancient <hi>Romanes</hi> obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the one side, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, victories, triumphes, and glory, which <hi>Caesar</hi> by his valour had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased to their Empire; and on the other side weighing the ruines, miseries, massa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, and slaughters, which he had caused in their Estate,
<pb n="153" facs="101"/>
they were wont to say, that it was difficult to iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his birth had bene more fortunate or fatall to their Common wealth. Euen so it is hard to say, whether that <hi>Loue</hi> causeth more good or euill in the world. It is true, when as this <hi>Passion</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines it selfe within the bounds of honesty, it is a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spring and fountaine of all good things in the life of men. It is also true, that the author of nature hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in vs the first moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and beames; and it is true, that it is borne with vs, that it increaseth with vs, &amp; that it doth alwayes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany vs, so as it cannot subsist without vs, nor we <hi>Loue</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. It is an immutable law, which men haue not
<pb n="154" facs="102"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>nd out, <hi>lawgiuers</hi> haue not prescribed; neither doth it depend vpon the examples or customes of nations, but was grauen, as we may say, by the hands of nature in our <hi>Soules.</hi> But when like a wild and vntamed beast it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes the bounds of reason, there is no misery which it brings not into the world, nor any disorder which it causeth not in our liues. It is as it were a fatall source, from whence flow all kinds of horror, vncleanenes, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, incests, sacriledges, quarrells, warres, treasons, murders, parricides, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and violences; besides the particular torments it giues vnto the soules of such as giue themselues to be sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, filling them with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies,
<pb n="155" facs="102"/>
iealousies, cares, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholies, terrors, yea and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; drawing them many times to despaire, and to do things whereat heauen and earth blush and are ashamed: wherein it is the more to bee feared, for that as the first heauen by his motion doth violently draw whatsoeuer is beneath it, so <hi>Loue</hi> prescribes a law to our other desires, &amp; to all our other <hi>Passions</hi>; so as we may tearme it the key and beginning of our tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ghts, of our words, of our actions, and of whatsoeuer wee do in this life: So it makes the first impression in our soules, where it excites the desire of that which we resolue to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue; &amp; then it fortifies this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire by hope, which inflames vs to the pursuite of that
<pb n="156" facs="103"/>
we desire; and if there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare any obstacle, it imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>Choller,</hi> and hath no rest vntill it hath vanquished and surmounted all lets, wherein she settles her cōtentment &amp; rest. And as the thunder breakes whatsoeuer resists it, so this furious <hi>Passion,</hi> being once inflamed, striues to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw whatsoeuer opposes it selfe against her rage and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Yet as the winds fill the sailes of Pyrats shippes, but are not the cause of the murthers and thefts which they commit at sea; But all these miseries proceed from the bad inclination and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetousnesse of these infamous Pyrats: So although that <hi>Loue</hi> bee an assistant in many villanies which men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, yet it proceedes not
<pb n="157" facs="103"/>
from the malice of this <hi>Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> which contrariwise is framed to bring all good to the society of men; but it growes from the liberty and excesse of men, who peruert the vse of all things, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the causes of their feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, into instruments of their misery. Let vs then see what bee the proper ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of <hi>Loue,</hi> not staying at those which rise from the meere malice of men. We will reduce them to three or foure heads, the explanation whereof will giue sufficient light to the rest of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
      <p>The first effect they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to <hi>Loue,</hi> is, that it hath an vniting vertue, by meanes whereof it causeth him that loueth to aspire to vnite him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
<pb n="158" facs="104"/>
to the thing beloued: whereunto we may refer the fable of <hi>Androgenes,</hi> where of <hi>Plato</hi> doth so much triumph; but we must swallow so many fopperies, before wee shall come to the mysteries of this fiction, as it were better to passe it ouer in silence, then to spend time to explicate it. So it is that prophane and vnchast <hi>Loue</hi> seekes the vnion of bodies, which is found e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen among brute beasts, and for this reason may be called brutish, if it bee not sought with an honest intent by a lawfull marriage. But chast and honest <hi>Loue</hi> seekes the vnion of affections and wills, and exceeds not that which is decent and vertuous. They which <hi>loue,</hi> sayd <hi>Aristophanes,</hi> would passionately desire to
<pb n="159" facs="104"/>
be trāsformed, &amp; chāged one into another, &amp; of two bodies to become one. But for that this transformation cannot be without the destruction of their being, they striue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence this defect, by a ciuil and honest vnion, which tēds not to the ruine of their nature, but contents their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; that is to say, they conuerse continually toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, entertaine their <hi>Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and are as little absent as may bee one from another: Moreouer they haue the same <hi>thoughts,</hi> the same desires, the same affections, the same wils, the same delights, &amp; the same distastes, &amp; seeme to be but one soule in two bodies. So as that which is pleasing to him that loueth, is in like manner to the party belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="160" facs="105"/>
what he affects the other imbraceth; and what hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects the other flies, and doth abhorre. So as their willes being thus strictly vnited, all their actions and carriages conspire to the same end, and propound vnto themselues the same obiect. For when as we haue graft the sience of one tree vpō another stocke, the fruits which grow follow the nature of the graft, and sauor nothing of the stocke: so the will of the louer, being transported into that of the party beloued, takes the tincture, and doth not any thing but what is conforme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his desires and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But whence comes the power which this <hi>Passion</hi> hath, thus to vnite the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects where it worketh? This
<pb n="161" facs="105"/>
cannot well bee explicated without the aide of <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</hi> First of all, <hi>Loue,</hi> say the <hi>Philosophers,</hi> is a desire to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the good wee propound vnto our selues, as proper for our content, and capable to make vs in some sort better by the fruition. But this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying &amp; participation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee effected but by vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the obiect to our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the same good we propound vnto our selues; wherefore it is of the Essence of <hi>Loue</hi> that it produceth this vnion. Hence it proceeds, that the presence of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beloued is so deare and pretious vnto vs, and that we feele our selues filled with content, when as we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy him to entertaine our thoughts, to taste the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="162" facs="106"/>
of his company, and to discouer our <hi>Passions</hi>: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his absence and separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on giues vs a thousand tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and afflicts vs with a thousand sorrowes and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, which wee would redeeme with our liues. Wherefore when as death doth take violently from vs those whom wee loue deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by this meanes hath condemned vs as it were to a perpetuall absence, we striue to ease our griefe, and swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our losse, by transporting our selues often to the places where we were accustomed to see thē, representing vnto our selues their portracts and images, reading ouer their letters, &amp; stil handling al the gages and monuments they left vs of their affection.
<pb n="163" facs="106"/>
Sometimes the same gages and the same momuments of their affection displease vs, and wee do so abhorre them, as wee cannot indure to see them, nor handle them, but this growes from the griefe of their absence, for that we then represent them as infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible signes of our losse, which they figure vnto vs as irreparable; by reason where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of their pictures fill vs with bitternes. But on the other side when as the same things seeme vnto vs to supply the presence, wee <hi>Loue</hi> them dearely, and cannot bee wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to entertaine our selues with those thoughts. And if amidst all this we can inuent any thing that may serue to preserue the memory more liuely in our soules, wee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb n="164" facs="107"/>
the inuention, and are wonderfully pleased with this art. Wherein doubtlesse <hi>Artimesia</hi> Queene of <hi>Caria,</hi> shewed an act of wonderfull <hi>Passion</hi> towards her husband <hi>Mausolus.</hi> For death hauing taken him away, this desolate Princesse not knowing how to pull the thornes of her sorrow out ofher soule, she caused his body to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ashes, and mingled them in her drinke, meaning to make her body a liuing tombe, whereas the reliques of her deare husband might rest, from whom shee could not endure to liue separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
      <p>The most subtile <hi>Philosophers</hi> giue a second reason of this vnion which ariseth frō <hi>Loue. Loue</hi> (say they) hath her feate
<pb n="165" facs="107"/>
in the <hi>Will</hi> (they doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it as a <hi>Passion</hi> onely, which riseth in the sences, but also as a quality which in the end becomes spirituall;) but there is this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the vnderstanding and <hi>Will</hi>: the vnderstanding goes not out of it selfe to ioyne with his obiect, but rather he drawes the obiect vnto him, whereof the Image is framed to produce his action, like vnto a seale which prints its forme in the waxe. But the <hi>Will</hi> being toucht with the <hi>Loue</hi> of her obiect, suffers it selfe to bee drawne to his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; and going out of it selfe, vnites it selfe vnto him to take his forme; like vnto the waxe which receiues im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of the seale. So as by this reason, <hi>Loue</hi> is thoght
<pb n="166" facs="108"/>
to cause the vnion of him that loueth with the party beloued; for that his will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uished by his <hi>loue,</hi> hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Passion</hi> but to see her self vnited vnto her. But these meditations are too nice for our subiect.</p>
      <p>The second effect they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to <hi>Loue,</hi> and which is as it were, a branch and bud of the first, is, that it causeth the soule of him that loues, to bee more where it loues, then where it liues, and that reciprocally the soule of the party beloued, is more with the louer then with his owne body. The reason is; for that the soules of such as loue, are perpetually attentiue to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the image of that they loue, and haue no other thoght nor greater pleasure,
<pb n="167" facs="108"/>
then that they receiue by this sweete entertainment: By reason whereof the soule making shew of a more exact presence, where it doth most frequently worke, it followes thereby that it is more with the party beloued, then in its owne body.</p>
      <p>But let vs heare the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Platonicians</hi> vpon this point: The soule, say they, which is toucht to the quicke with <hi>Loue,</hi> dying in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s owne body, findes life in that it loues. And when this <hi>Loue</hi> is reciprocall, it dies but once, wheras it reuiues twice. For he that loues dyes truly, when as <hi>Loue</hi> makes him neg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lect and forget the causes of his life, to thinke wholly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the party beloued; but hee recouers his life doubly
<pb n="168" facs="109"/>
when as he sees himselfe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced and entertained by the party beloued; and that he finds in his armes his deer Image; which hee preserues more carefully then his own life. Who will not then, say they, hold this death happy, which is recompenced by two such sweete liues? But this discourse of the <hi>Platoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> presupposeth an equall correspōdency in <hi>Loue,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that this <hi>Passion</hi> is full of despaire, &amp; leaues nothing in our soules but importune and troublesome thornes. Wherfore the Ancients said, that to make <hi>Loue</hi> grow, shee had neede of a brother. But wee haue treated sufficiently of this Subiect.</p>
      <p>They attribute other ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb n="169" facs="109"/>
to <hi>Loue,</hi> that is to say, languishings, extasies, and amazements; but that <hi>Loue</hi> must bee very violent which doth produce them. And moreouer wee may consider these extasies, and rauish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ments which may happen in a violent <hi>Loue,</hi> after two sorts. First, we may obserue them as a true alienation of the sences, which ariseth, for that the spirit and will of him that loueth, being who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed in the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and enioying of the thing beloued, suffereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to bee so transported with this content, as the soule remaines as it were quencht and without moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The which may also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a more powerfull cause, that is to say, either
<pb n="170" facs="110"/>
from God or from euill spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which somtimes stirre vp these rauishments and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary extasies. Secondly we may consider these exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies &amp; rauishments, as a kind of madnes, which transports them that <hi>Loue,</hi> and makes them to commit many fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; wherefore an Ancient sayd, that <hi>Iupiter</hi> himselfe could not be wise and loue at one instant. These extasies and rauishments produce sometimes prodigious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in their soules that are afflicted with this <hi>Passion.</hi> For that his soule that loues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, is perpetually imploy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed in the contemplation of the party beloued, and hath no other thoughts but of his merit, the heate abandoning the parts, and retiring into
<pb n="171" facs="110"/>
the braine, leaues the whole body in great distempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which corrupting and consuming the whole bloud, makes the face grow pale &amp; wanne, causeth the trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the heart, breeds strange convulsions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires the spirits in such sort, as he seemes rather an image of death, then a liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. These accidents are followed with passionate and heart-breaking sighes; as it appeared in young <hi>Antiochus</hi> at the sight of <hi>Stratonice</hi>: Or when as they only make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her, as if the spirit were eased and free from a heauy burthen, and receiued content by this thought or presence. Teares in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fly to succor this afflicted soule, for that the heate
<pb n="172" facs="111"/>
which is mounted vp to the braine, causeth the humor to dissolue and discharge it selfe by the eyes. But this poore soule thus agitated, hath no certaine consistence, but flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting betwixt hope and feare, she sometimes giues signes of ioy, sometimes markes of sorrow; she is sometime fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen and congealed, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times all on fire: she goes, she comes, without any stay or rest, and doth many things which shew that shee is as it were incensed. For she pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clames the merit and glory of that she loues, and giues extraordinary commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are the signes of her rauishment. Suddenly changing her humor, shee makes her griefe and discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ascend vp into heauen,
<pb n="173" facs="111"/>
shee accuseth the innocent Starres, she complaines of destiny and fortune, and blames that which she loues; and suddenly returning to herselfe, shee condemnes her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe of wrong. Then she powres forth her spleene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such as she thinks haue crost her rest and hindred her content, so as she suffers cruel tormēts in this agitatiō. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times euen in the heat of his <hi>Passion,</hi> the party toucht with <hi>loue</hi> can indure no lōger discourse; his words are short &amp; scarce intelligible, for that the soule being thus tied to the obiect which it loues, it cannot giue it self the leasure to speake of any other thing. And that which is full of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miratiō, this <hi>Passion</hi> doth so chāge &amp; trāsform men, as it
<pb n="174" facs="112"/>
makes the wisest to commit great follies; it humbles the grauest to seruices vnworthy of their rancke, it makes the most glorious to become humble and meeke, the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to be profuse and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and cowards to shew themselues hardy and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. But for that some of these effects exceed the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of a morall <hi>Passion,</hi> we will leaue them to discourse particularly of <hi>Iealousie,</hi> vpon which subiects there are great controuersies and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, that is to say, whether it bee one of the effects of <hi>Loue,</hi> as the <hi>Vulgar</hi> sort imagine; or whether it be rather the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>Loue,</hi> as others presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; but we will referre the discourse to the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="chapter">
      <pb n="175" facs="112"/>
      <head>Of <hi>Iealousie,</hi> whether it be an Effect and signe of <hi>Loue.</hi> CHAP. 5.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Vulgar</hi> sort thinke, that as the Sun runnes not his course without light, so <hi>Loue</hi> cannot bee without <hi>Iealousie</hi>; and they adde, that as lightning is an infallible signe of Thunder, which breakes forth, so <hi>Iealousie</hi> is a certaine signe of <hi>Loue,</hi> which desires to shew it selfe power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. But they that haue a more exact and particular
<pb n="176" facs="113"/>
knowledge of <hi>Humane Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> maintaine, that as the Sunne beeing come to the South (which is the point of the perfection of his light) casts no shadow, but spreads his beames all pure vpon the earth; so a true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue is not subiect to the inclinations of <hi>Iealousie.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And they say moreouer, that this vniust <hi>Passion</hi> is no more a signe of <hi>Loue,</hi> then stormes and tempests are shewes of faire weather; this opinion is more probable: for to begin with the proofs, how can Iealousie subsist and remaine with <hi>Loue,</hi> vnlesse we will ouerthrow the Lawes of Nature, which suffer not two contraries to subsist in one subiect? Is there any thing more contrary to <hi>Loue</hi> then
<pb n="177" facs="113"/>
         <hi>Iealousie?</hi> Can the world see a greater Antipathy, then that which is obserued in these two qualities, whereof the one doth participate with the condition of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and the other is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Idea</hi> of perfection? <hi>Loue</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites the <hi>wils,</hi> and makes that the desires of them that loue, striue to take, as it were, the same tincture, to the end they may resemble one another. And contrariwise, what doth so much distract the <hi>Wills,</hi> and diuide the hearts, as <hi>Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie? Loue</hi> binds vs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret fauourably of all the actions of the party belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and to take in good part that which we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue she hath done with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: whereas <hi>Iealousie</hi> makes bad interpretations, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="178" facs="114"/>
of her actions, but euen of her very thoughts? Is there any innocency that can bee sheltred from the outrages of this inhumane fury? If the party beloued hath any ioy, it then presupposeth a riuall; if she be pensiue, they are sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions of contempt: if shee speakes to another, it is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity; if she haue wit, they apprehend practises; if shee be aduised, they imagine sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties; if she be plaine, they call it simplicity; if shee bee well spoken, it is affected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; if she be courteous, it is with a designe. So as <hi>Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie</hi> is like vnto those coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit glasses, which neuer represent the true proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the face: and what more sinister iudgements could the most cruell enemy
<pb n="179" facs="114"/>
in the world giue of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beloued? But not content thus to blemish the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perfections of that shee seemes to loue, she seekes to depriue it of the sweetest content in this life, which is by communicatiō with men of honor and merit, who doe not visite her but for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme they make of her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: So as many times to please an importune, who is himselfe a great burthen to them that suffer him, shee must forbeare all good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. What iustice can force a soule well bred, to indure this brutish rigot? <hi>Loue</hi> is a liuely fountaine of ioy and contentment, which bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth all cares and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; but <hi>Iealousie,</hi> what is it else but a nursery of grief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="180" facs="115"/>
and waywardnesse, whereas wee see thornes of despaire and rage, to grow vp among the sweetest and most plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing flowers that Nature can produce? How then can any man beleeue that these two contrary <hi>Passions</hi> can subsist in one subiect? If they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose heereunto experience, and the testimony of many persons worthy of credite, which protest that they haue loued sincerely, and yet were neuer without <hi>Iealousie</hi>; and will thereby inferre, that at the least, <hi>Iealousie</hi> is a signe of loue; which is the second thing we must incounter, to satisfie that which hath bene formerly propounded: it suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth to answer, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for respect we yeelde to those personages what
<pb n="581" facs="115"/>
they publish of their <hi>Passions</hi>: yet as one Swallow makes no Spring, so that which hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pens to particulars, cannot prescribe a law to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. But to containe our selues within the bounds of our first proposition, we say, that these persons are much deceiued in this subiect: and their error growes, for that they cannot giue proper names to things, for that of a respectiue feare competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with loue, whereof it is full, they make an vniust <hi>Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie,</hi> with the which <hi>Loue</hi> can no more subsist, then wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with fire. They that loue intirely, are in truth, full of respect to the party beloued; honor her with all the passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their soules, fight for her honor, and hold it a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
<pb n="182" facs="116"/>
to offend her. But these are not the effects of <hi>Iealousie,</hi> which contrariwise violates the honour which is due to the party beloued, and by a prodigious manner to blind the world, will haue her fauour by wronging her, treading her merits vnder foote. We must then put a difference betwixt a respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue feare, which always doth accompany those that loue perfectly, and <hi>Iealousie</hi> which is neuer found but with an imperfect <hi>passion,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not iudge of the perfections of the party beloued. They which know that these things are diuerse, and as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote one from another, as the earth is from heauen, wil easily passe on this side, and yeelde, that <hi>Iealousie</hi> is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="183" facs="116"/>
competible with <hi>Loue,</hi> nor is any signe thereof. Yet if wee shall yeelde any thing to the opinion of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> we may freely confesse, that <hi>Iealousie,</hi> in truth is a signe of <hi>Loue,</hi> but as the feuer is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of life. It is vnque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionable, that a feuer is a signe of life, seeing the dead are not susceptible of this bad quality. But as a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer shewing that there are some reliques of life in the patient that is tormented, accompanies him to his graue; so <hi>Iealousie</hi> is I know not what signe of <hi>Loue,</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they which loue not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue any <hi>Iealousie.</hi> But it is certaine, that if wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell it not, it will in the end ruine <hi>Loue,</hi> like vnto a thicke smoake which smothers the
<pb n="184" facs="117"/>
brightest flame. This is all we can yeelde vnto the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi> so as according to this opinion which we haue held the most probable, <hi>Iealousie</hi> is to <hi>Loue</hi> as thicke mists are to flowers, haile to haruest, stormes to fruites, and poison to our liues.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>