<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>L., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108230_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04995</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15144</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108230</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>L., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archeion, or, A discourse vpon the high courts of iustice in England : Composed by William Lambard, of Lincolnes Inne, Gent</title>
                 <author>Lambarde, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Frere (Fryer), Daniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 276 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Corruptio unius est generatio alterius.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR had not this late <hi>aspersion</hi> tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>pietie</hi> I owe to so worthie an <hi>Ancestor</hi> (as I dare say) the <hi>Kingdome</hi> would acknowledge; truly I should not have given my least <hi>assent</hi> to have advanced this to light,
<pb facs="5"/> (which too lately was, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my privitie, or liking.) But the crying <hi>Errors</hi> (arising from the <hi>untimely publication</hi>) call upon me, to <hi>vindicate</hi> him from that <hi>wrong</hi> (if any such can be) and my selfe from an imputed <hi>Apathie.</hi> But why doe I call them <hi>wrongs,</hi> and <hi>aspersions?</hi> since that sweet <hi>Odour</hi> hee hath left, cannot by their false <hi>ingredients</hi> be so <hi>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phisticated,</hi> but may by the <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious</hi> bee easily smelt out. And for those that delight meerely in <hi>superficials,</hi> neither weighing the <hi>sense,</hi> or <hi>defects,</hi> but swallow the <hi>Errours</hi> for <hi>Errataes;</hi> such as these it hath
<pb facs="5"/> alreadie passed. Others are to be expected, of meere <hi>active soules;</hi> and of these, some that will passe <hi>sentence</hi> (upon the Booke) before it come to <hi>judgement:</hi> I shall <hi>assigne</hi> them the <hi>Character,</hi> heeretofore occasioned upon this verie <hi>Worke;</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Fooles will contend, without the cause discerning,</l>
         <l>And argue most, of what they have no learning.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>I have too much digressed: seeing my <hi>desires</hi> are to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired,</hi> for <hi>injuries</hi> past; not to labour to prevent I know
<pb facs="6"/> not what, to come: Grant me the <hi>first,</hi> and I shall <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale</hi> the <hi>other</hi> to thy <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and thinke, I have well tendred my <hi>dutie</hi> I owe to my <hi>Parents,</hi> and <hi>Countrey.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>