<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108976_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19487</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108976</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of a Christian man : VVherein is plainelie shewed out of the VVord of God, what manner of man a true Christian is in all his conuersation, both inward, and outward. ... By M. William Covvper, minister of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Cowper, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 284, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatise presents vnto thee a liuely image of a Christian man, as he is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neate in the word by him who best knowes him, that is, by the Spirit of God that begets him: wherein it shall be euident, that albeit now in the world, there be nothing rifer then the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian name, yet is there nothing rarer then the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian man. Concerning which, a singular craft of Sathan comes to be discouered; for when the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian name, which had the beginning in Antiochia came first vp in the world, Sathan did what he could by false calumnies and bloudy persecution to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse it. This sect, as witnesses S. <hi>Luke</hi> euery where<note place="margin">Act. 8. 22. Act 6. Act. 16. Act. 17.</note> was spoken against, and Christians were accused to be blasphemers of God, troublers of Cities, yea trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the whole world: worshippers of the Sunne, and of an Asses head, eaters of mens flesh, seditious, and vile abusers of their bodies, and what euer else might make them odious to the ignorant multitude. By the Iewes they were called in contempt <hi>Nazari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> by <hi>Iulian</hi> scornfully they were termed <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>lilaeans;</hi> by <hi>Ulpian</hi> vnder <hi>Seuerus impostores,</hi> as if they had beene coggers and deceiuers; by <hi>Demetrian</hi> whom <hi>Cyprian</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
confuted, procurers of all the plagues of God that came vpon the world. Yea, so farre in their ignorant malice did they proceede, that it was counted a capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall crime for any man to call himselfe a Christian. A most vnreasonable thing indeede, seeing as <hi>Tertullian</hi> reasons in his <hi>Apologet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>{que}</hi> written in defence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians. <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> nominis nullus est rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tertull. Apologet.</note>
   </p>
   <p>But now Sathan hath changed his course: for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that doe what he can, Christianity flourishes like vnto the Palme tree, which growes the more, the more it is prest downe, hee labours subtilly to staine and obscure the glory of that holy profession, which before by cruelty hee could not ouerthrow: for now the Christian name is become common, and men of most licentious life are brought vnder the couering thereof; by which policie of Sathan, men are put into this false opinion, that it is an easie thing to be a Christian, and that a man may liue as hee likes, and be a Christian good enough also: whereof it is come to passe, that the Church is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished, with such a number of bastards, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Christians, as this day we may see with griefe of heart, some Atheists, some Apostates, some adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, many murtherers, most part blasphemers: <hi>qui Christianum nomen ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>dicium habent, non ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. de Temp. 215.</note> And vnder this generall opinion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity liueth now many a one miserably deceiued, <hi>impugnant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s eum quem praedicant,</hi> either persecuting<note place="margin">Gregor. mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. lib. 1.</note> the sonne of God by damnable doctrine, or else by their workes denying him, while they professe that they know him; turning the grace of God into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnesse; hauing a name, that they are aliue, but in truth are dead.</p>
   <p>It is certainly a great pitie to see so many of <hi>Adams</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
sonnes, in word condemners of their Fathers Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasie; yet indeed imitators of his folly, hiding their nakednesse with a garment of Fig-tree leaues; not perceiuing how by so doing, they come neere to the likenesse of that Tree, which had faire leaues, but no fruit, and therefore was once accursed by Iesus Christ, that it might stand a perpetuall example of that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full curse, which these men may looke for at his hands, who haue a shew of godlinesse, but hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the power thereof, and are outwardly like vnto painted Scpulchres, beautifull to the eye of man, but in his sight who searches the heart, are full of rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and all filthinesse; whereas indeede they should be the Temples of the liuing God, far more glorious and beautiful within then without. <hi>Iacobs</hi> heart vnder <hi>Esau</hi> his garment, were farre more seemely for them who say they are <hi>Iacobs</hi> brethren, then to haue <hi>Iacobs</hi> voice onely, that is, a tongue to speake well, and yet the prophane heart with the rough and cruell hands of <hi>Esau,</hi> which sort of disguised Christians may look not for such a fauorable successe of their dissembling with God as <hi>Iacob</hi> found with <hi>Isaac.</hi> For he being but a man, was deceiued through ignorance, but men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themselues, if they thinke that in this manner God can be mocked, what euer shape men turn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues into, the Lord can discern the Israelite in whom there is no guile, and though <hi>Simon Magus</hi> would seeme so religious, as to redeeme the graces of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with the losse of his money, yet can the Spirit of God paint him out in his colours, and giue him his owne name, <hi>Thy heart is not vpright in the sight of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Such is the power of godlinesse, that euen they who loue not the substance thereof, are forced often times to lurk vnder the shadow of it: and such again
<pb facs="9"/>
is the shame of sinne, that they who loue to commit it, yet doe not loue to seeme committers of it, <hi>hi sunt</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ber. in Cant. ser. 66.</note>
      <hi>qui boni videri, non esse mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> non videri, sed esse volunt,</hi> these are they who will seeme good, and not be so, will not seeme euill, and yet will be so To these we may speake as <hi>Chrysostome</hi> did to the like in his time. <hi>Dic hypocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>a, si bonum est bonum esse, cur non vis esse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Chrisost. in Math.</note>
      <hi>quod vis apparere, quod autem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>urpe est apparere, turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us est esse?</hi> Tel me hypocrite, if it be a good thing to be good, why wilt thou not be that which thou wouldst appeare to be, for that which is a shame for a man to appeare to be, is it not much more shame for him to be it indeede? <hi>aut ergo esto quod appares, aut appare, quod es,</hi> either else therefore be such, as thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearest, or then appeare such as thou art.</p>
   <p>It were happy for these men, if they could learne in time to examine themselues according to that word, by which one day they will be iudged, for not euery one that saith Lord, Lord, will enter into the kingdome of God, <hi>He is not a Iew, that is one without,</hi> neither hath <hi>euery one receiued an ointment from that holy one:</hi> but he who is a Christian indeede, <hi>sicut par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeps</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ber. in <hi>Cant.</hi> ser. 15.</note>
      <hi>est nominis, it a &amp; haereditatis,</hi> with the name of Christ, the oyle of grace from Christ is also commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to him, by which with Christ he is pertaker of the inheritance. <hi>Qui vero Christum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>se non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. de Temp. ser. 17</note>
      <hi>Christianus dici non potest,</hi> but hee that hath not Christ liuing in him by his spirit, cannot be called a Christian. It is a notable saying of <hi>Basile, quid inquit est Christianimus?</hi> what said hee is Christianity? <hi>si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudo</hi>
      <note place="margin">Basil. hexa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> hom. 10.</note>
      <hi>Dei quoad eius capax est Natura humana,</hi> a similitude and conformity with God, so farre forth, as the nature of man is capable thereof.</p>
   <p>Seeing then it is the doing, not the speaking of
<pb facs="9"/>
righteousnesse, must proue vs to be the children of God, <hi>For if wee say wee haue fellowship with God, and walke in darknes, we lie, and do not truly,</hi> and <hi>if any man be in Christ Iesus he must become a new creature,</hi> let vs studie to proue our new generation by our new man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, conforming our selues to the rule of a Christian conuersation. A patterne and example whereof I haue gathered out of holy Scripture, and proposed vnto thee, wherein thou shalt see first how the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian who by his first birth was borne a Naturall man, by his second becomes a Christian, with such other things as with his new birth he receiues to make him a new man. Secondly, what is the disposition of his inward man, by which hee walkes with God. And thirdly, the disposition of his outward man, by which he walkes among men, and that in all the points of his conuersation both inward and outward. Euery one whereof as ye haue them set downe particularly in seuerall Chapters, so doth euery Chapter consist of these foure things. First, Gods precept to the Christian: secondly, the Christians prayer to God: thirdly, his practise of both: and these three haue you set downe in words of holy Scripture alanerly. The fourth is, in the end of euery Chapter some ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations teaching vs how to make our owne profit of the words of God. This is the order I haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued here: for the Christian, because hee knowes that he is bound to liue to the Lord, and not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, doth in all his waies set before him the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of his God. And next, because hee knowes his owne Naturall inability to fulfill these commandements, he turneth all the precepts of God into prayers, the vse whereof I hope in all the parts of thy life, shall not be vnprofitable for thee. And
<pb facs="10"/>
last of all, hee liues in a continuall practise of those du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ties of godlinesse which God in his word hath commanded him, and he himselfe doth pray for.</p>
   <p>Now in the end I haue onely to obuiate two sorts of men: by the one it is surmized that I haue plowed with the Heifer of another, specially of <hi>Cashmannus,</hi> who hath written before me, <hi>de nouo homine:</hi> by the other it may be obiected that I haue presented an imperfect image of a Christian, and haue left out ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things which profitably might haue beene poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out concerning him. For the first, as I giue thanks to God for the labours of that worthy man: so if I had borrowed any thing from him, I would neuer thinke shame to confesse it: <hi>nam ingenui pudoris est, vt ait</hi> Plinius, <hi>fateri per quos profecerimus, &amp; haec quasi merces authori iure optimo pensitanda est, ne fures esse videamur:</hi> but the truth is, that many yeares before he came in this Country, this <hi>Anatomie</hi> was drawne and portraited, as now you see it. As for the second I humbly confesse it, <hi>Malim tamen aliquid agendo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorem àme doctrinam, &amp; sapientiam desiderari, quam nihil agendo prudentior, doctior{que} iudicari.</hi> It was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable policy of these Indian Philosophers, called <hi>Gymnosophista, qui à suis discipulis, seuerius otis, quàm negoti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> rationem exigendam esse arbitrabantar.</hi> What I haue done in this little labour, is a part of my nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation with that one talent I haue receiued from the Lord, and which hee hath charged me to put to the vttermost profit. And therefore had I rather by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of some good, lay open my infirmities to the censure of men, then to hide by idlenesse my talent in the earth, and so to incurre the indignation of my Maister. I know my selfe I haue not done what I should, nay, not what by the grace of God I could,
<pb facs="10"/>
yet that which in regard of my daily labour in the worke of the Ministerie I might.</p>
   <p>Accept therefore from me, this image of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian in a Christian manner; apply it to thy selfe and looke what similitude or dissimilitude thou findest betweene thee and it. Doe as <hi>Elizeus</hi> did to the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes sonne, when he raised him from death to life, he stretched himselfe ouer the childe, hee put his mouth on the childes mouth, his eyes on his eyes, his hands on his hands, and therewithall he ioyned prayer, and the childe reuiued: so compare thou thy selfe with this ensample; thy minde, thy will, thy affections, thy words, thy actions with these of the new man: where thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>indest a conformity, giue thanks to God for the beginning of the worke of his grace in thee: where not, pray to God further to quicken thee, that thou mayest grow in an holy simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude and conformity with him, to the glory of his holy name, and thy euerlasting comfort in Christ Iesus, to whom be praise, glory, and honour for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus
M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. VVILLIAM COWPER Minister at Perth.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>