<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGGT HONOVRABLE, my singular good Lord and Master, EDWARD, Earle of Dorset, Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene, Councellour of Estate to his Majesty, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</title>
           <author>Rutter, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108694_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19346</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5770</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108694</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGGT HONOVRABLE, my singular good Lord and Master, EDWARD, Earle of Dorset, Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene, Councellour of Estate to his Majesty, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Rutter, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Cid : a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their Majesties at court, and on the Cock-pit stage in Drury-lane by the servants to both their Majesties</title>
                 <author>Corneille, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walkley, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGGT HONOVRABLE, my singular good Lord and Master, EDWARD, Earle of <hi>Dorset,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene, Councellour of Estate to his Majesty, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O give your Lordship a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my readinesse to obey you, I no sooner was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by you to translate this Poem than I went about it. And certainly your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands gave life to the worke, which else despaire of performance, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>deration to whom it must be presented, would ave stifled in its first birth. For how could I <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ope any thing from mine owne sufficiencie, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eing little exercised in the French tongue, and
<pb facs="3"/>
finding such a contumacy in their phrase to our manner of speaking; or how should I not feare such a Judge as your Lordship, who are not onley a perfect understander, but an exact speaker of both languages. So that what w<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> with much labour compasse, is your daily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise. For if that which <hi>Augustus</hi> attributed to <hi>Vinicius,</hi> that he had <hi>Solus ingenium in numerato,</hi> can snit with any man, it does with your Lordship, whose wit we have so often seene ready told out, and fit for any emanation: and with which you have justly purchased every mans wonder and astonishment. It was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aptly and truly said by a noble man of your owne ranke and order, that when you spoke in any businesse you imposed oblivion on what was said before you, and silence on any man that should speake after you. It behooves me then (since I must feare your judgement) to flie to that sweetnesse of your disposition (the temper of your vertues) with which you use to receive the offers that come from a gratefull heart. Un lesse I should presume to thinke that your Lord ship cannot without delight survey the person of D. <hi>Roderigo</hi> in this play, with whom you life has held some proportion, for like him yo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> have ever preferr'd your honour to your affe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctions, and your King and Countrey to an thing besides: which you did not so much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="3"/>
the place you are in requires it, but out of an in-bred affection delivered to you from your Ancestors, who with their happy counsailes have no lesse confirm'd this kingdome than D. <hi>Diego</hi> is here said by his armes to have sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported <hi>Castile.</hi> In fine, my Lord, I hope you will looke with more content upon this Peece, when you shall reade there some places of my Lords your sonnes translation, from whose at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, if I have borrowed this time, I must account it upon your Lordships setvice, from whom I have received all I have, which is the glory to be esteemed,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
      <signed>Your honours most faithfull most obedient servant.
RUTTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>