<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>K., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108024_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68300</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14969.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108024</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>K., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the 25. of Nouember. 1621 : Vpon occasion of that false and scandalous report (lately printed) touching the supposed apostasie of the right Reuerend Father in God, Iohn King, late Lord Bishop of London. By Henry King, his eldest sonne. Whereunto is annexed the examination, and answere of Thomas Preston, p. taken before my Lords Grace of Canterbury, touching this scandall. Published by authority</title>
                 <author>King, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 77, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="43"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow little I affect to be in Print, needs no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie to any, who either know already it was the desire of some my most Honourable friends, whose intreaties were commands to me, or but consider the subiect which first set me a worke, a</hi> Slandered and traduced Father: <hi>vnto whom duty and necessity vrged me to doe this right. And I cleerely professe, if a true relation of his end may doe him right, I haue faithfully performed it, and haue giuen the world so iust an account of Him,</hi> tanquàm Ephemeridem Deo traditurus, <hi>as if I should haue made my conscience last shrift to God. Whether I haue vprightly stewarded his honour, and my owne faith, I leaue to the strict iudgement of any, who are able to distinguish colours, and discerne</hi> Truth <hi>from</hi> Imposture: <hi>being confident, as innocence can make a man, that none are able to disallow the reckoning.</hi> Si veredicam, Deus testis; si mentiar, Deus Vindex. <hi>As therefore the acquitting of His integrity was the prime mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue which entred me into this Quarrell, so now the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my owne fidelity was a secondary motiue for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of it. First, that they might not thinke by false al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arms and the confused outcries of</hi> Report, <hi>to beare downe a good cause, or so easily to triumph in their supposed victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as if none durst affront them; I thought good, in the meane time, thus on the sudden to checke the rumour, till haply some more deliberate pen (which they shall not long, or vainely expect) may quite race it out. And though this byrth of mine were more hastily formed, I hope it will not be vntimely, for</hi> Truth neuer knew abortion; <hi>but, like a starre newly risen to discouery, hath its being of old, though the obseruation was but late and moderne. Secondly, to let
<pb facs="43"/>
those calumnious tongues, who gaue out my Reuolt also as well as my Fathers (both true alike) know, I haue not yet so doted on their part, or dis-affected my owne, as to leaue my</hi> Countrey, <hi>or</hi> Religion; <hi>nor, I thinke, euer shall, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my vnderstanding, wits, and aboue all, the Grace of God leaue me: or their perswasions haue the same power ouer me, as</hi> Mercuries <hi>had ouer</hi> Sosias, <hi>that they can make me beleeue</hi> Ego non sum Ego, <hi>I am not the</hi> Son <hi>of such a</hi> Father. <hi>And what in this case, on my owne behalfe, I write, is likewise auowed on behalfe of my second brother,</hi> IOHN KING, <hi>entred into the same orders as my selfe; who also had his share in this lewd imputation, as well as my selfe: for we are not more brothers in nature, then (by Gods mercy) in this resolution. Thirdly, to take the liberty of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and explicating some remarkeable</hi> circumstances, <hi>which better become a Margin then a speech. Lastly, that though the</hi> slander <hi>hath hitherto got the start, the</hi> Detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>might, at last be set in a course to ouertake it. Which taske,</hi> Sermo transiens, <hi>a Sermon pronounced, could not so thorowly effect, except it were also</hi> Sermo in scriptis, <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. A course no way improper, for</hi> scriptor praedicare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci potest; <note place="margin">Gerson de laude script consider. 1</note>
      <hi>A</hi> Writer <hi>is in some sort a</hi> Preacher; Certè si lingua silet, manus praedicat, &amp; fructuosiùs aliquandò, quantò Scriptura venit ad plures vberior quàm transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens sermo; <hi>though his</hi> tongue <hi>be silent, his</hi> Pen <hi>preaches: and a</hi> Sermon <hi>preached from the</hi> Presse, <hi>sometimes edifies so much the more then from the</hi> Pulpit, <hi>by how much the Report is carried further. So that the audience which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was but</hi> Parochiall, <hi>or at most</hi> Prouinciall, <hi>may by this meanes grow more</hi> Generall <hi>and (as it were)</hi> Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menicall.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And now hauing committed it to the view of all men, I will not preiudicate, or doubtfully forestall the beliefe of any. I make no question but all will rest satisfied, except those wayward dispositions, who are resolued afore-hand not to be satisfied at all:</hi> Non persuadebis etiamsi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaseris; <hi>hauing banished all reason from them without
<pb facs="44"/>
hope of repeale. Such, though vnwillingly, I must leaue to their owne hardened obstinacy,</hi>—Stultos iubeo esse li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentèr, <hi>and suffer</hi> fooles <hi>gladly that will be so against my consent. If they can yet flatter themselues with any aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, this fiction may affoord them, I shall not enuie them that Paradise, into which their fond imagination hath put them. I rather pitty the poore shifts they are driuen to, for the keeping of their weather-beaten Cause a-float. All the harme I wish them is, that they would leaue off this thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare trade of</hi> Calumny, <hi>especially towards the</hi> Dead, <hi>grow better acquainted with speaking and writing the</hi> Truth, <hi>and not conuersing with her at such a distance, as now they doe. Or if they will needs be</hi> Architecti menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum, <hi>still hammering</hi> vntruths; <hi>I would aduize them to lay probable foundations, and chuse such</hi> Materials <hi>as are more malleable, and (in the worlds esteeme) not so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for them to worke vpon as He they haue heere se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. For euery wood will not make a</hi> Mercury; <hi>nor is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good man a fit mould to cast Them a</hi> Conuert <hi>in.</hi> Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. K.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>