<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108337_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05115</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15251</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108337</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Via regia ad geometriam. The vvay to geometry : Being necessary and usefull, for astronomers. Geographers. Land-meaters. Sea-men. Engineres. Architecks. Carpenters. Paynters. Carvers, &amp;c. Written in Latine by Peter Ramus, and now translated and much enlarged by the learned Mr. William Bedvvell</title>
                 <author>Ramus, Petrus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 299, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>FRiendly Reader, that which is here set forth to thy view, is a Translation out of <hi>Ramus.</hi> Formerly indeed Translated by one M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Hood,</hi> but never before set forth with the Demonstrations and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agrammes, which being cut before the Authors death, and the Worke it selfe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, the Coppie I having in mine hands, never had thought for the promulgation of it, but that it should have died with its Author, considering no small prejudice usually attends the printing of dead mens Workes, and wee see the times, the world is now all eare and tongue, the most given with the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> to little else than to heare and tell newes: And if <hi>Apelles</hi> that skilfull Artist alwayes found somewhat to be amended in those Pictures which he had most curiously drawne; surely much in this Worke might have beene amended if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour had lived to refine it, but in that it was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the first draught, and that he was prevented by death of a second view, though perused by others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Presse; I was ever unwilling to the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but that I was often and much solicited with
<pb facs="6"/>
iteration of strong importunity, and so in the end o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ruled: perswading me from time to time unto it, and that it being finished by the Authour, it was farre better to be published, though with some errours and escapes, than to be onely moths-meat, and so utterly lost. I would have thee, Courteous Reader know, that it is no conceit of the worth of the thing that I should expose the name and credit of the Authour to a publike censure; yet I durst be bold to say, had he lived to have fitted it, and corrected the Presse, the worke would have pointed out the workeman. For I may say, without vaine ostentation, he was a man of worth and note, and there was not that kinde of learning in which he had not some knowledge, but especially for the Easterne tongues, those deepe and profound Studies, in the judgement of the learned, which knew him well, he hath not left his fellow behind him; as his Workes also in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuscript now extant in the publike Library of the famous Vniversity of Cambridge; do testifie no lesse; for him then being so grave and learned a Divine to meddle with a worke of this nature, he gives thee a reason in his owne following Preface for his principall end and intent of taking this Worke in hand, was not for the deepe and Iudiciall, but for the shallowest skull, the good and profit of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler sort, who as it was in the Latine, were able to get little or no benifite from it. Therefore consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the worth of the Authour, and his intent in the Worke. Reade it favourably, and if the faults be not too great, cover them with the mantle of love,
<pb facs="6"/>
and judge charitably offences unwillingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and doe according to the termes of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as thou wouldest be done unto, but it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saying, as <hi>Printers</hi> get Copies for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, so Readers often buy and reade for their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; and there is no worke so exactly done that can escape the malevolous disposition of some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting spirits, to whom I say, as one well, <hi>Facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t unicuivis nostrum aliena curiosè observare: quam proproia negotia rectè agere.</hi> It is a great deale more easie to carpe at other mens doings, than to give better of his owne. And as <hi>Arist. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>; omnibus placere difficilimum est.</hi> But wherefore, Gentle Reader, should I make any doubt of thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie, and favourable acceptance; for surely there can be nothing more contrary to equitie, than to speake evill of those that have taken paines to doe good, a Pagan would hardly doe this, much lesse I hope any good Christian. Read then, and if by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thou reapest any profit, I have my desire, if not, the fault shall be thine owne, reading haply more to judge and censure, than for any good and benefit which otherwise may be received from it; let but the same mind towards thine owne good possesse thee in reading it, as did the Author in writing it, and there shall be no neede to doubt of thy profit by it.</p>
   <byline>
      <hi>Thine in the common bond of love,</hi> IOHN CLERKE.</byline>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>