<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the indifferent Reader.</title>
           <author>K., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108042_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68294</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14906</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108042</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the indifferent Reader.</title>
                 <author>K., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pallas armata, or Militarie instructions for the learned: and all generous spirits, who affect the profession of armes. The first part· Containing the exercise of infanterie, as well antient, as moderne: wherein are clearelie set downe all the postures and motions, belonging to battallions of foote</title>
                 <author>Kellie, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro, Heirs of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 121, that is 130 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the indifferent Reader.</head>
   <p>NOBLE, worthie, and courteous Reader: although I haue set out this Treatise, principally for the use of my Fellow-Lawers, coting the chiefe instructions and termes of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> (the best Masters of the Arte Militarie) in their owne Idiome; yet I haue had a care to put the same pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages in our language for the use and profite of those who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand not the Greeke tongue, and haue set downe a plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of all the Motiones of Infantery, with a demonstration of them in figures, so that I thinke they shall be facile and perspicuous to the meanest capacitie, whereby I hope the Noble and worthy-minded Reader shall be allured, not only to a further vnderstanding of Martiall exercise, but also animated to put the samine precepis in practise for the well and seruice of his Country. For I hope, hee is not ignorant of the worth and dignitie of the Arte Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie: and how much It, and the professours thereof, haue euer beene esteemed in the World.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
         <hi>Plutar. in Lycurgo.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Lycurgus</hi> in his Lawes did Ordaine, that no Epitaphe should bee made, nor no mans Name remembred vpon his Tombe, except of him who had beene a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, esteeming them only worthy of memorie. When the seuerall Prouinces of <hi>Grecia</hi> sent their Ambassadoures to
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <hi>Plutar. in Pelopida.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Artarxer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes,</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> be preferred <hi>Pelopidas</hi> &amp; the <hi>Theban</hi> friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to the rest, because hee heard they were the best Souldiers, &amp; best practised in the faites of Armes: not respecting the wealth &amp; power of the <hi>Athenians, Spartans,</hi> &amp; other Cities. <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedone</hi> King of a poore Country, by exactly learning the Exercise of Armes, &amp; practising a new militarie discipline inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as some say) by himselfe, did not only frie his Kingdome from the oppression of the <hi>Poeonians</hi> &amp; <hi>Illirians,</hi> but also subiected the most goodly rich Prouinces and Cities of <hi>Grecia</hi> to his Crowne; So that making a preparation against the <hi>Persians,</hi> he died, and left his young Sonne <hi>Alexander</hi> successour of his Kingdome, and of his Designes, who beeing carefullie instructed by his Father in the discipline of Armes, and surpassing him farre in martiall valour, <hi>Vt Telamonem Aiax vt Pelea vicit Achilles,</hi> did not only execute his Fathers designes against <hi>Darius,</hi> by overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in two great Battells, but also in a shorte time did ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and subdue the most populous Kingdomes of <hi>Asia;</hi> And by
<pb facs="7"/>terrour of Armes, made all the World to tremble at his Name. The <hi>Romans</hi> rose from nothing to bee Masters of the World, by no other meanes, but a continuall Exercise of Armes: and when through lazinesse, they left off their use, they were ouer runne, by the barbarous <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals:</hi> And in the time of their Imperiall Governement, how many were there, vvho by Militarie vertue, did rise from a meane Birth and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Supreame Honours, yea, to Sway the Imperiall Scepter? As <hi>Severus, Pertinax, Valerius, Aurelianus, Maximinus,</hi> &amp; many other, whom ye shall finde in Historie. The <hi>Suyzers,</hi> a basse me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicke Nation, of little account, beeing provocked by <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> to take Armes against their will, like Oxen ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of their owne strength, hath euer since continued in that course, &amp; hath gained such credite &amp; reputation amongst Christian Princes, that the mightiest of them are glad to buy their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe at a great price. Our Neighbours the States of the vnited Belgick Provinces, latelie were reputed, a dull, poore, lazie people, But by taking Armes, and maintaining the professours of Armes, they haue not only vindicate themselues from subiection to a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and powerfull Master, and gained Libertie, (which if it were not in our Age would seeme incredible) But haue come to such a height of wealth, and power, that they are extreamely redoubted by their Enemies, and respected by their Friendes. Hence it was, that our Heroicke King <hi>ROBERT</hi> the First of most famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, left in His Testament, that our <hi>Scots</hi> should neuer make a long Peace with <hi>Englād:</hi> knowing well, that the Exercise of Armes was the onely meanes to maintaine our Credite, Honour, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and that the desuetude thereof was the losse of all. Since then the benefite of the Arte Militarie is such, that the poore haue growne rich, the weake strong, the vile and abiect, valorous and of good Fame: Since it is the onelie meanes to Conserue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Libertie of a Nation, I hope there are no worthie and Generous mindes, but will apply themselues to Militarie exercise, and take Armes, if not for other ends, yet for defence of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Libertie of their Countrie, now when it is in danger: And I hope they will spend their Blood before they suffer this our Antient and Noble Kingdome, which hauing euer beene <hi>Externi immunis Domini,</hi> out-braues the rest of the Nations of the World, with <hi>Nunquam victa;</hi> now to be subiected, and to fall in the hands of any forraigne vsurper. A well gouerned Common-wealth in time
<pb facs="8"/>of Peace, will prepare for Warre, knowing the course of the world, to bee still subiect to change and alteration (resembling the eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and flowing of the Sea.) &amp; constant in nothing but inconstancie; yea, a vvell Setled Minde in time of Prosperitie vvill prepare for Aduersitie, <hi>Metuens alteram sortem:</hi> How much more ought vve, now, vvhen the Time of Peace is gone, and the Dayes of Warre come vpon vs, vvhen a fearefull Invasion is threatned by a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and powerfull Enemie; Now to rouse vp our Spirites, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for Resistance: Shall vvee bee still slougishlie secure, and lye in a lavish senslesnesse, without making any addresse for Defence: Where is the Antient Vigour of our Scottish Blood? Where are those, vvho not onely at Home, defended their Libertie against forraigne Hostilitie, limiting the proude <hi>Roman</hi> Triumphes at our Borders, &amp; repressing the Furie of the <hi>Goathes, Danes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vandals,</hi> But also assisted their Friendes, and Allyes abroad? vvhere are those, vvithout vvhom, <hi>Nulla unquam Francis Fulsit victoria castris?</hi> Those (I say) vvho put Crownes vpon Kings their distressed Friends heades: Those (I say) vvho at the Conquest of <hi>Italie,</hi> vvere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the first in acquiring, and last in surrandring, vvhen ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse Portoune brought necessitie, (although that assistance bee now by them, ingratfullie buried in oblivion:) Where are all those Braue Spirits now in this Age? Now (I say) vvhen not our Friends &amp; Allyes stand in neede of our helpe: But the Daughter of our King, the Sister of our Deare Sacred SOVERAIGNE, is in extreame distresse: The true and liuelie Image of his owne Goodnesse, &amp; Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiousnesse, A Princesse, although suppressed by Fortune yet of Her selfe vvorthie, to whom the World should ascribe, and on whom the Heauens should bestow, the highest Degree of Glorie, and Felicitie, that Humane condition is capable of: Whose Worth no Lynes can expresse, nor Fame duelie report of, Beeing endued with all Royall Graces and Vertues, and cheifelie with an Invincible Fortitude of Minde, in the midst of Her Calamities, farre aboue the Condition of her Sexe: Shee is by the consent of all; The Flower of Princes, The Grace of Queenes, and The Queene of Graces, The Delight of the World, the Glorie of Her Sexe, yea, by confession of Her owne Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, The Iewell of <hi>Europe;</hi> A Princesse whose rare Vertues are so infinite and eminent, vvhose Maiesticall Cariage is so sweete and so Gratious, that I dare avouch, Neuer Eye did see Her, whose Heart did not admire and adore Her. And vvhen Her so many Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Children partake Her Calamities, But aboue the rest, That most
<pb facs="8"/>Hopefull Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> Her first Borne: A Plant, out of vvhich all Heroicke Vertues doe budde; Adornde vvith all Princelie Qualities, of a singular activitie in all exercises of bodie becoming His Highnesse, Of an Admirable Iudgement and Vnderstanding in all Noble Sciences, farre aboue His Age; Hee is of so rare Hopes, and such exquisite Perfections, that I cannot remember Him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Admiration: I wish my Penne were as able to expresse Their due praises, as my Sword shalbe reddie to Redresse their Wrongs: Can a true hearted Brittaine liue in Securitie, and thinke of the Distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, of those Princes? Can a Minde anie wayes affected to Grace, &amp; Vertue, not be commoued to see the very Temple of Vertue defaced? Can neither the duetie which vvee owe to those afflicted Princes, nor the Safetie of our owne Countrie, moue vs to tak Armes? Shall vvee bee still slow in advancing the affaires of the Magnanimous and Invincible KING of <hi>Denmarke:</hi> a Prince, vvho for his Royall Courage, His Incomparable Valour, His Compleetnesse in all Martiall Vertues is to bee paralelled vvith the Greatest Kings and Princes, and Brauest Generalls that euer liued: who hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured His Life, His Crowne, His Posteritie, for our Quarrell, our Safety, and Restitution of these distressed Princes: who by His onelie power with-holdeth the Enemies Forces from falling vpon vs: Shall vve then be still insensible of our owne Danger, and of the Obligation which wee owe to this Most Valorous KING? Shall vvee contribute nothing to the furtherance of those levyes, vvhich our Most Sacred <hi>SOVERAIGNE,</hi> out of the Duetifull respect vvhich hee ought to Him, and the tender Loue which Hee caries to His Deare Sister, and the Earnest Care vvhich Hee hath of oursafetie, hes granted vnto Him: O let it never bee said! and let the aversnesse of sundrie from this Service bee amended, that they may eschew the note of Disloyalty to their King and Countrie, and of ill affected mindes to these Princes: I can not likewise, but remember with due Praises those two Worthie and Generous minded Noble-Men, vvho haue left their Ladies, their Children, their estate in this Countrie, and with extreame diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and great charges, haue lifted their Regiments, and haue consecrated their Fortunes, Blood, and lifes, for the Service of their King, their Countrie, and those afflicted Princes, vnder the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that Most Valorous CHRISTIAN Generall: and also all those Worthie Gentle-men, who haue accompanied them in this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as vvell Officers, as priuate Souldiers: And likewise all
<pb facs="9"/>other Noble-Men, Gentle-men, and well affected Subiects, who haue bent their whole power to further and advance those Levies: What praise is due vnto their merit? and with what Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought they to bee extolled? Let their Fame liue for euer, and the Sinceritie of their mindes bee knowne to all those who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terressed in our Querrell. The example of those Braue Spirits (No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and worthie Reader) I hope will allure You, either to follow them, that yee may bee partaker of their Honour, (for I assure You that our Countrie-men, both with that Magnanimous KING, and with all other Princes and States for their Militarie Valour are more respected, than other Nations:) or at least to Dedicate your selues to a daylie vnderstanding and exercise of Armes at home, that yee may bee able and readie to doe Service to your Countrie in time of Danger. I speake not to Base vulgar mindes, whom I know, no perswasions, nor examples will allure to follow Honour, who beeing naturallie repugnant to all Grace and Vertue, and beeing vnprofitable burdens to the Earth, make themselues to bee estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnworthie of life: But to You, whose Noble Mindes breathes after all Honourable and Vertoues Designes, who carie an vpright and vvell affected heart to your Countrie, who are alwayes readie to purchesse her Quietnesse by painefull Industrie, her Honour with effusion of Your Blood, her Safetie with lose of your lyfes: It is You, vvhom I exhort, It is You, vvhom I affectionatelie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and to whom I will ever approue my Selfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most duetifull Servant, <hi>T. K.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>