<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of England, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108780_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06131</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16616</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108780</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of England, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe conference of diuers lawes : diuided into certaine regiments. By Lodowick LLoyd Esquier, one of her Maiesties serieants at armes</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 143, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by the grace of God, Queene of <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Knew not how most gratious Queene, to make my most boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den &amp; dutifull seruice known vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie; But as <hi>Dauids</hi> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts ventured theyr liues through the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of their enemies to fetch water from the well of <hi>Bethelem,</hi> to please their Lord and Maister; So my selfe thought it my dutie to trauell into some farre countries in no daunger, but of your Maiesties displeasure, by presenting some straunge Iewels among so many, as might dislike your Highnesse, which should scorch mee more then the Sunne did <hi>Ionas</hi> when his gourd was off; and terrifie me more, then the countenance of <hi>Moses</hi> terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="3"/>
the Iewes without his vaile on. But your Maiestie, which forget nothing but iniuries, will the sooner forgiue mee my ouermuch boldnesse, the rather for that I present your highnesse, but with Iewels, &amp; such as far excell the Iewels on <hi>Aarons</hi> garment, the onely pearles which ought to be bought with al the wealth we haue, the Iewels which we ought to seeke with all the studie and trauell wee can; the onely <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> which should shine bright on a Princes breast, which the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> ware as tablets about their necks, as frontlets on their foreheads, and gardes on their garments, which Iewels many other kings sought and mist. <hi>Licurgus</hi> sought these Iewels for the Lacedemonians at <hi>Delphos, Mena</hi> sought them of <hi>Mercurius</hi> for <hi>Egipt, Numa</hi> of the Nymph <hi>Egeria</hi> for the Romanes, &amp; <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leucus</hi> of <hi>Minerua</hi> for the Locreās. Of these Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els also I brought the best Pearles I could finde among them vnto your Maiestie, in hope of your wonted gracious fauour to accept these Iewels for their owne sake, as <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted water of the riuer <hi>Cyrus,</hi> for <hi>Cyrus</hi> sake.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties most bounden and obedient seruant,</hi> Lodowick LLoyd.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>