<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108276_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108276</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The shepherds starre : now of late seene, and at this hower to be obserued merueilous orient in the East: which bringeth glad tydings to all that may behold her brightnes, hauing the foure elements with the foure capitall vertures in her, which makes her elementall and a vanquishor of all earthly humors. Described by a gentleman late of the right worthie and honorable the Lord Burgh, his companie &amp; retinue in the Briell in North-holland</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, I knowe no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to mooue mee to write vnto you, sith I cannot remoue you from your preiudiciall opinion. It is peculiar to euerie one, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of a booke so singular, as that no most exquisit worke can satisfie the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest expectation in his desire of reading. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reason is, because euerie Readers emulous and couetous minde, hopeth to finde once a booke made all by the figure <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.<note place="margin">Cicero 3. de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator. illustris ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>planatio rerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que quasigetan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur sub aspectum pene subiectio.</note> Aboue all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: And so longeth to finde a writer, that can set downe his matter as well as his heart can thinke. This shall neuer be God wot. For, first the simple may, I confesse, be pleased soonest with that which they vnderstande least, but admyre most. But what a fond pleasing were this? Yet tis so. For <hi>Iris</hi> is fained to be <hi>Thaumantis filia.</hi> The Raynbowe is the daughter of Admiration. The coulours please much, because they are little perceiued, and least of all coulours knowen what they are. The Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond is onely rare, because it deceiueth the eye with newe varietie, such as the sight is not still ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of: Marke it when you will. For the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to please them, I will not presume to speake howe, because I cannot. Onely this I protest: There is not a letter in this sillie Pamphlet, that by my placing is set there, to displease any one, or to
<pb facs="7"/> please manie. Only this: Let the wisest giue their verdicts, and the rest holde their tongues. If I fall by the one, I wil be sure for euer hereafter to stand by the other: and so displease neither with any more Toyes. In hast on Saint Georges day. <hi>Aprill.</hi> 23.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>