<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108444_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19060</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5475</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A refutation of M. Ioseph Hall his apologeticall discourse, for the marriage of ecclesiasticall persons : directed vnto M. Iohn VVhiting. In which is demonstrated the marriages of bishops, priests &amp;c. to want all warrant of Scriptures or antiquity: and the freedome for such marriages, so often in the sayd discourse vrged, mentioned, and challenged to be a meere fiction. Written at the request of an English Protestant, by C.E. a Catholike priest</title>
                 <author>Coffin, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 376, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS according to the order set downe in the ensuing <hi>Letter,</hi> I had determined to adde another Paragraffe to the former three, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning <hi>A detection of M.</hi> Halls <hi>errours, and ouersights in writing,</hi> I found in the pursuit therof so aboundant matter, as I could not comprize it all within the narrow bounds of a Paragraffe; and increasing so much vnder my hands, I resolued at length to set it out a part, at amounting to more then what I haue already writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in answere of this <hi>Letter</hi> to <hi>M Whiting,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one entier Controuersy, might perhaps better be set out alone thē conio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ned with other points nothing at all incident to that matter, as are the other doctrinall Errours, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, Mistakings, Impostures, and other fraudulent, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and malicious behauiour which I am forced to detect, and wherwith all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>apsodyes of his Epistles that contey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> any disputable question are fraught to the full.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>Another cause heerof was, for that a Gentleman la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely come out of England, gaue me notice of other bookes of the same Authour, which I had not yet seene, and of one entituled, <hi>The peace of Rome,</hi> on which in particuler dependeth very much of that which I haue written in the <hi>Detection,</hi> especially in refuting that most shameles as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion,<note place="margin">Decad. 3. Epist 5.</note> that <hi>Bellarmin acknowledgeth vnder his owne hand two hundred thirty and seauen Contrarietyes of doctrine amongst Catholiks:</hi> which is nothing els but 237. lyes in one assertion, if he meane as he must do, of points that belong to sayth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and not of matter vndecided and meerly disputable in Schooles. And yet further (which to one not acquainted with the forhead of Heretikes may seeme incredible) he auoucheth, <hi>the dissensions of Protestāts to be only in cerimonyes of the Catholiks in substance: theirs in one or two points, ours in all.</hi> Againe, <hi>ours is in the whole cloath, theirs only in the skirts &amp;c.</hi> with more to the same effect. All which, or at least the chiefest part, I meane the disagreement of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks in fundamentall points, are as I suppose discussed in that worke, and I cannot so well refute his words in generall, vntill I see his speciall prooses that are made against our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the proper subiect of euery particuler dissension.</p>
   <p>Only heere to his generall charge, I returne also in generall this answere: That neither he, nor all of his Sect set togeather can make this good: and in case he be so bold in his <hi>Peace,</hi> as he hath beene in his other VVritings, we shall find store of most impudent vntruths (for lying and detraction if it be for the aduancement of the Ghospell seem with this Man to be meritorious works) and those deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with such audacity, as if they were most certaine and vncontrollable truthes: of which kind there be many disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ered in the refutation of this <hi>Letter,</hi> but the number that
<pb facs="3"/> remaine is without comparison greater: which when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, togeather with his eminent ignorance, I cannot but greatly admire the scarcity of learned men in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that could find no better Doctours to send to <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t Conference,</hi> to conclude the peace between the <hi>skirt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrangling-Brethren</hi> then <hi>M.</hi> Hall, no more to be cōpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with learned men, then a Pedlar with Merchants, a Pettifogger with Lawyers, a meer Pedanticall Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian with graue and learned Deuines.</p>
   <p>VVere the matter in Controuersy to be concluded with outfacing of lyes; <hi>M. Hall</hi> might sit for Arbiter and Iudge of the whole Assembly, &amp; (vnles they be too shameles) ouerbeare them all. Of a mayne multitude which already I haue set downe in the <hi>Detection, I</hi> will touch one heer, and that only to discharge and cleare my selfe from that wherof I accuse him, I meane of detraction, and defaming his person Let this then passe for an example which so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently he writeth in his <hi>Quo vadis,</hi> or <hi>Censure of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note>
      <hi>Trauell:</hi> where though he say that, <hi>A discreet man will be ashamed to subscribe his name to that whereof he may be afterwards conuinced,</hi> yet<note place="margin">Pag. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> so indiscretly doth he deale, as he blusheth not to write in these wordes: <hi>What packets fly abroad of their</hi> Indian wonders? <hi>Euen</hi> Cardinall Bellarmine <hi>can come in as an auoucher of these cosenages, who dares auerre, that his fellow</hi> Xauier <hi>had not only hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the deafe, dumbe, and blind, but raysed the dead; whiles his brother</hi> Acosta <hi>after many yeares spent in those parts, can pul him by the sleeue, and tell him in his eare so loud, that all the world may heare him,</hi> Prodigia nulla producimus, ne{que} verò est opus <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So <hi>M.</hi> Hall.</p>
   <p>And I appeale to all the Ministers of <hi>Dort,</hi> whether they euer heard a more impudent vntruth. For first <hi>Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> was neuer in the East Indyes at all nor <hi>Xauier</hi> in the VVest: and how then would <hi>Acosta</hi> spend many years in those parts where <hi>Xauier</hi> had liued? This is one lye, and that so long a one, as it reacheth as far as it is from the East to the VVest, or from the <hi>Artick</hi> to the <hi>Antartick</hi> Pole. Againe so far is <hi>Acosta</hi> from <hi>pulling Bellarmine by the sleeue,</hi> or disauowing the miracles of <hi>Xauier,</hi> as in this very worke he doth both acknowledge &amp; confesse them for true. For thus he writeth: <hi>Conuertamus oculos in</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 2. 10.</note>
      <hi>saeculi nostri hominem, B. Magistrum Francis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi>
      <q>
         <hi>virum Apostolicae vitae &amp;c.</hi> Let vs cast our eyes vpon a man of our age, on B. Maister Francis (Xauier) a man of an Apostolicall life, of whome so many &amp; so great miracles are recorded by many, and those approued wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,</q> as there are scant recounted more or greater (vnles it be of the Apostles) of any. VVhat haue M. <hi>Gaspar</hi>
      <q>
         <hi>(Berzaeus)</hi> &amp; other not a few of his Cōpanions done in the East Indies? How much haue they aduanced the glory of Gods power in conuerting that people by their miraculous workes? So far <hi>Acosta.</hi>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Out of whose wordes deliuered in so plaine, &amp; honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable tearmes of this Blessed Man <hi>Francis Xauier,</hi> the Reader may see whether he were a fit witnes to be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced against the miracles of the sayd Father: whether he <hi>pull Bellarmine by the sleeue, and cry so loud in his eare, that all the world may heare him,</hi> or rather whether <hi>M. Hall</hi> do not most lewdly lye, and maliciously abuse his Reader in applyirg that to <hi>Xauerius</hi> which <hi>Acosta</hi> spake only of himselfe, and others then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing with him in <hi>Perù, Brasil, Mexico,</hi> and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning coasts, and assigneth the causes of their not working miracle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, as I shall more fully declare when I shall come to handle this in the <hi>Ditection.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And euen now there is come to my handes a booke
<pb facs="4"/> written by one <hi>Collins</hi> in defence of Doctor <hi>Andrews.</hi> If <hi>Spenser</hi> the Poet were liuing, he might very well make another <hi>Collins Slowt</hi> vpon his slowterly discourse, so loose &amp; loathsome, as will weary the most patient Reader, and withall so ignorant, railatiue, and lying, as I wonder that it was permitted by priuiledge to come to the Presse, &amp; was not suppressed with his other which he wrot against the Reuerend Father <hi>Andraeas Eudemon-Ioannes.</hi> He is fortunate in the choice of his Aduersaryes, for be singles out such as are singular; but in the combat he is weake, simple, and a meere pratler: this he shall better heare from him whome it concernes, then I shall need now to declare. Only this I must note in him, that————<hi>Et Platanus Platanis, Alno{que} assibilat Alnus.</hi> One egg is not more like another, then are these Ministers in lying, For this seely fellow in his Epistle to his Maiesty (of all others which euer I saw written to a Prince the most beggarly) thus writeth of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He in his deuoutest Meditations of all others, his booke <q>last set forth <hi>de aeterna Felicitate</hi> (sayth M. <hi>Collins</hi>) will not excuse Kings from being murthered <hi>de iure</hi> (not only <hi>de facto</hi>) only he passes it ouer as a <hi>casus omissus,</hi> happily because auouched in his other Volums more perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily. So he▪ Insinuating that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alloweth the</q> murthering of Kings, not only <hi>de facto,</hi> but also <hi>de iure:</hi> for what other sense can his words beare, <hi>that he wil not excuse Kings from being murdered de iure?</hi> And againe when afterwards he sayth, <hi>The Cardinall not content with a death</hi> de facto, <hi>implyes that they may be slaine</hi> de iure <hi>too,</hi> but that it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue it? which is so far from the Cardinalls meaning, as he insinuateth the quite contrary. For hauing compared the Saints in heauen with Kings on earth, he commeth after to shew wherein the Saints do excell them: and putteth
<pb facs="5"/> this for one point, that earthly Kings are subiect to many calamityes, from which the Saints are exempted: and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the difference in these wordes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Deni{que} potest etiam Rex subditos vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, carcere, exilio, flagris, morte mulctare: sed potest etiam Rex (de facto loquor, non de iure) vinciri, carceri mancipari, exilio, vulneribus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 1. c. 5.</note>
      <hi>morte mulctari. Id verum esse probauit Iulius Caesar, Caius, Nero, Galba, Vitellius, Domiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus &amp;c.</hi> To conclude, a King may also punish his Subiects with fetters, prison, banishment, whippings, and death: but the King also may be fettered (I speake <hi>de facto,</hi> not <hi>de iure</hi>) may be committed to prison, may be punished with banishment, wounds, and death. This did <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> find to be true, this <hi>Caius, Nero, Galba, Vitellius, Domitian &amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> And let any heere iudge whether the Cardinall speaking <hi>de facto</hi> and not <hi>de iure,</hi> do not graunt the one, and deny the other? Graunt I say that such facts haue fallen out (and may vpon the wicked disposition of the people fall out againe) but not that they were lawfully done. VVhich is further confirmed by the other examples which he doth produce, of which som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> were good Princes, as <hi>Gordian, Gratian, Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the second, and others. Some also Saints, as <hi>S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of <hi>England, S. Sigismund</hi> of <hi>Burgundy, S. Wenceslaus</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>S. Canutus</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke.</hi> And is it possible to conceaue that the Cardinall should affirme all these to haue beene lawfully murthered? And in case he had so imagined, why then did he interpose that negatiue exception, <hi>de facto loquor, non de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> I speake of the facts which haue fallen out (for certaine it is the forenamed Princes to haue beene slaine) but not of the lawfullnes of their killing? VVas it not, trow you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse the Kings, and accuse the murtherers? For if he would
<pb facs="5"/> haue implyed the contrary, or approued it as lawfull, he would neuer haue spoken in this phrase of speach, but either haue concealed these words, or expressed his mind in other.</p>
   <p>And it cannot but moue laughter to see, how this man geeth about to proue the immortality of Kings, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> for saying only, that Kings <hi>de facto</hi> may be slaine, telling his Maiesty most son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly, <hi>that the Scripture leads vs to speake of Kings &amp; Princes in another strayne, as if they, that ought not to be violated by any mortall hand, could not dye at all.</hi> So this grosse flattering Parasite. But where I pray you are those straynes? Sure I am he must strayne hard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he find any such on our Bibles. He alleadgeth the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Dauid,</hi> speaking of the death of <hi>Saul, How was he slaine, as if he had not beene annoynted with oyle?</hi> But doth this shew that <hi>de facto</hi> Kings cannot be slaine? or rather doth it not shew the contrary? For heere you haue <hi>Saul</hi> a King, and yet <hi>de facto</hi> slaine, which is as much as the Cardinall doth affirme. But to this M. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> very learnedly (<hi>scilicet!</hi>) replyes, that Kings dye not as Kings but as men (quatenus homines non qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>enus Principes) and so graunteth that Kings as men may be killed, but not as Kings. By which reason I will deny that any Minister, Cobler, Tinker, or Tapster may be killed, or dye at all. Or though some of these degrees come to be promoted to the gallowes, yet are they hanged as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, not as Ministers, not as Coblers, not as Tinkers, not as Tapsters: for els all Ministers, Coblers, Tinkers, &amp; Tapsters should be hanged, which were as you know a very pittifull case. And the like happeneth although they dye in their beds, for they do not dye because they are Ministers, Coblers, Tinkers, &amp; Tapsters, which are accidentall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes, but for that they are mortall men, and subiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>But I leaue him to his learned Aduersary, who yet as I perswade myselfe, if he read any one Chapter in him, will be more moued to contemne his writings then to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere them. And indeed he should to much iniure himselfe in case he should seriously go about to refute such an idle froth of indigested fully, or encounter with so base and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling an Aduersary, whose pride, ignorance, &amp; rusticity are such, as the one maketh him to reiect, the other not to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the truth, and the last to forget all modesty, or good method in writing. <hi>S. Bernard</hi> speaking of Heretikes truely sayd: <hi>Nec rationibus conuincuntur, quia</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bernard. serm. 66. in Cantic.</note>
      <hi>non intelligunt; nec auctoritatibus corrigūtur, quia non recipiunt; nec flectuntur suasionibus, quia subuersi sunt.</hi> Such Ministers as <hi>M. Hall,</hi> M. <hi>Collins</hi> and the like, are not conuinced by reasons, because they vnderstand them not; nor amended by authorityes▪ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they regard them not; nor moued by persuasions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are subuerted. So he. And were it not for others of more indifferent iudgment, we should surcease from all labour of further writing: but their saluation we ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly thirst, howsoeuer we distrust of these Ministers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime. And so much heereof. Now let vs come to the <hi>Letter</hi> it selfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>