<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Q.L. to the gentle reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108240_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05034</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15178</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108240</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Q.L. to the gentle reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The minde and iudgement of maister Frau [n] ces Lambert of Auenna of the wyll of man : declarynge and prouynge howe and after what sorte it is captyue and bonde, and not free: taken out of hys commentaries vpon Osee the Prophete, wherin vpo [n] the. iiii. chapter of the sayd prophet, he most godly, plainlye and learnedly, entreateth and writeth of the same, as hereafter euide [n] tly shal appere. Newelye tra [n] slated into Englishe by N.L. Anno Do. M.D.xlviii. the xviii. day of Dece [m] bre</title>
                 <author>Lambert, Franz</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, ii-lxxii, lxiii-lxiiii leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb n="ii" facs="5"/>
   <head>Q.L. to the gentle reader.</head>
   <p>HEre in this worke (moost gentle reader) thou hast set before thyne eyes the wil of man so playnely, so liuely that no Appelles coulde with al his craft in a table with his colours set furth the phisiouomie of anye man lyke. Thou dost perceiue and behold him in this boke, as he is in his owne propernature and kynde, altogether nakid, altogether mysera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, wretched, and bound. Not that there by thou shouldest thynke thy self more at liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie to offend bycause thy wyl is bound and captiue: or elles that thou cast not chose but offend: but that rather thyne owne weke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and pouerte being known, thou sholdest knowledge▪ prayse and glorifie the myghtie and infinit power and strength of the Lord, with the aboundaunt and plentifull fulnes of ryches in al goodnes, to whom only eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good gyft, and euery perfect gifte from heauen aboue, from the father of lyght is to be attributed &amp; ascribed as witnesseth Ia .i. Thou must be also in this case lyke a man, which through long sicknes is so feble and weeke, and brought so low: that he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to stand without a staffe, fearynge to set his foote to the ground least he shoulde fall doune, not able to ryse agayne of hymselfe without the helpe of another. This mā get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="6"/>
to him a staffe to stande vp or to go by: or els he leueth on another mās arme which is stronger than he: and so goth furth by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and lytel euer fearing to fal. So doyng thou shalt not fal, nay though thou dost stō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, or trippest a litle with thi fote, that is the carnalconcupiscēce of the flesh, yet shalt thou not fal to the ground: the spirite of the Lord is so strong, that he wyll holde the vp. But if thy staffe be weake or rotten: or that man whom thou dost trust, be not altogether thy frynd: thou canst not chose but fall and that miserably to thine vtter confusion, with out another takyng compassion and pitie on the of his goodnes wyll come and take the vp. Lykewise is thy doyng whē thou dost trust and put thy confidence in thyne owne meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in thyne owne workes, in thyne owne strength, in thyne owne wit and power: thē is thy fall moost greatest, when the truste of thyne owne power semeth moost strongest, and when thou art most inflamed wyth the loue of thy selfe, that is of thyne owne dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and workes, which are altogether flesh if they be not wroughte, by the spirite of the Lord, the which spirite of the Lorde being in the, the Lord doeth make althy wayes godly &amp; straight be fore his eyes, so that thi sinne is not imputed to the, nor thou art not fleshly,
<pb n="iii" facs="6"/>
yea, though the fleshe hath some pryckyng in the. For to the iust man the lawe is not made as witnesseth Paul: that man I saye whose iustice is Christes iustice, which alre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in his hert hath done al that thing which the law requireth not of hymself but by the power of the spirit of the Lord which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wil in hym. What hast thou (saith Paull) that thou hast not receiued: if thou hast receiued, wherfore, art thou proud of it as thoughe thou hast not receiued it but as it were thyne owne of thy self: For asmuch then as al godlines is receiued: we must cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sider &amp; cōfesse, that ther is a geuer in whose hande and power it dothe rest, whether he wil geue it yea or nay, so that we must say, not vnto vs Lord, not to vs. but to thi name be glory &amp; prayse. What worke dyd Paull worke to optayne the fauoure of the Lorde, When he was most strongest in persecutiō and sheddyng of the christian bloud? soden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly he was taken from hym selfe (that is to say) the Lord alterid him of his owne good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and mere mercy his cruel affectiōs, and in the steade of the spirite of persecution: he put in hym the spirite of mekenes, the spirit of loue, of preaching his glory, of preaching Iesu Christ crucified, and in the steade of a persecutour of Christ, he became a sufferer
<pb facs="7"/>
for Christ. When Peter was most stronge to fyght wyth dente of sworde as appered by his bolde and manly deades and great crakes, how sodenly became he in the stead of a defēder, a denier? And wher as he wold dye with Christ, he would not so much as once knowe hym, nay he denied him vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Who did subdue the naughtie spirite of Paul when he was in his most rage &amp; fury agaynst the preachers of Christes glory? Was it ani other, thā the power of the lord vnder whose fete all thynges are made sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect: yea, from the reasonable to the vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, as oxen and sheepe. At the whiche tyme of persecution, Paull was in durate because he had not in hym the spirite of the Lord, and therefore he coulde not chose but with al extremitie persecute the lord as far as the fleshe woulde geue hym leaue. The flesh alway as Paul wytnesseth resystyng and strinyng agaynst the spirit. The cause then why that Paull had not the spirite of the Lord, was only the pleasure of the Lord whiche taketh mercye on whom it pleaseth him selfe. Paul myndyng nothing lesse thā to be called, it pleased the Lorde to cal hym frō dishonour to honor, to the setting furth of his glory. Paull for this tyme of perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution was indurate none otherwyse than
<pb n="iiij" facs="7"/>
was Pharao in the persecution of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Israel. If it had pleased the Lord to haue taken Paull as he dyd take Pharao, the one shulde haue perished as well as the other. Yf the Lord had lefte Peter in his de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niall and styll to hym selfe, if he had not loked on hym wyth the eye of fauoure, it had ben euyll with hym, as it was with Pharao. But to declare that all men are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and God only true as the prophet saith The Lord toke the spirit of stedfastnes and knowledgyng of God from hym: leauyng hym to hymselfe, to fraylenes, to the verye counsel and motion of the flesh, which flesh had rather lyue a whyle and dye for euer, than to suffre a smal temporal death and al way after to lyue. Therfore, if any manne do fall, let not hym dispayre, for the Lorde is merciful. It is not the fall whiche decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth induration, it is the contempte of the Lord, when thou dost delyght in thy synne not fearyng the Lordes iudgement, that is a fearful token of induration. What canst thou tel whether the Lorde wyl take the in this tyme of thy wyckednes and vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes yea or nay? as he dyd Pharao in the mydest of hys madnes? If he so doo what shall become of the? Thou caust not denye but that he may, if it please hym so to doo.
<pb facs="8"/>
Thou hast a good cause therfore alway to fear and mystrust thy wayes, for thou arte altogether of thy selfe, fleshe, thou canst do nothyng of thy selfe but synne. And lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse as the trust of the mercy of God pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mysed for Christes sake, whiche foloweth streyghtway the hatred of vyce and synne with ful intent and purpose to liue after the wyll of the father, is a certayn token of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and of the fauour of God, wherin so long as thou doste remayne and continue thou art sure that thou art of the ryght fort Euen so the loue to lyue vngodly, to wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in all kynde of vyce, and to lye styll in impuritie of lyfe, declareth to the that for that same season thou art nothing ells than the chyld of wrath, curssed of God, indurat as was Pharao. This is a good cause to make the to be alway in feare, to make the suspect thyne owne selfe, and begyn to hate synne, the deuyl, and the fleshe with al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscence, then the spirit of God beginneth to worke his worke in the, to crucifie thi spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual enemy in the and to subdue them in the. Then hath the Lord put a new his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into the, which before he dyd plucke frō the, leauyng the to thyne owne stynckynge affections and carnal cōcupiscences. What caused the proud heady and obstinate Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises
<pb n="v" facs="8"/>
that thei would not beleue in Christe, for al the myracles that he wrought? Thei beleued not in him, saith Christ in Ihon .xii. that the saiyng of Esay the prophet mighte be fulfilled, whych he spake. Lord, who shal beleue our saiyng, and to whō is the arme of the Lorde declared. Therfore coulde not they beleue because Esay sayth agayne, he hath blynded their eyes and hardened their hertes that they shuld not se with their eies and least they shuld vnderstand with their hertes. et c. So because they were blynded the could not se. What thing can moue and styrre vs to the loue of God, what thynge can setfurth the glory of God and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: more thā the perfit knowledge of this article whiche maketh hym a whole God, which setteth hym in his owne seat a highe which declareth him to be authoure &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of al goodnes, he that doth both begyn and maketh an ende? Whych article I saye setteth mā in his owne place here in erth, na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turally geuen to the earth, to al curruption both bodely and gostly disposed to doo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng of himself that is good. What thing to man is more necessary thē that doctryne whych teacheth hym howe he shall knowe when he is the sōne of God and of the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen sort, that he may pray the Lorde to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
<pb facs="9"/>
his spirit in him, wherbi he shal know which way he is the sonne of the deuil &amp; of out cast furth of the fauour of God. Ther is nothing more necessary thā this. I wold wysh and desyre wyth all my hert that all men would reade this boke with a godlye desyre and entente, not to contention, and mayntenaunce of their lewde lyfe whose dampnation is iust▪ but to know God how strong he is, howe myghtie a prynce he is howe good and mercyfull he is, on whose mercy all thyng dependeth, and to knowe mā, howe weake and how myserable he is that he can do nothynge of hymselfe, that he is the instrument of God to al goodnes and the instrument of the deuyll in al vyce and synne. The euyl and most iustly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned personnes come to this boke, to fetche a lycense of synne to make their lyfe more lycentious, more dissolute, to make them selfe more bolde in all kynde of vyce most like to the spider &amp; venemous worme which from the swete flowers doo drawe and sucke furthe venym and poyson. The vertuous and godlye disposed, meane no thyng lesse, they do gather hence all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Here fynde they a brydle to plucke in their vicious affections. Here fynd they the swete libertie of God and bondage of the
<pb n="vi" facs="9"/>
deuel. Here do they learne their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and theyr saluation by Christ The flesh taketh al thyng fleshly and lyke itself. But therfore the faythful may not be depriued of theyr foode and sustenaūce. Let vs therfore pray the Lorde to put in vs hys spirit: that it may be our guyde to al godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vertue, that we be none occation of slaūder to his worde, but that al our actes, dedes and alwrytinges, teachyng, reading and communicatiōs maye bee to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, to the settyng furth of his glory, to whom be honour and praise for euer and euer wythout ende. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>