<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable and his verie good Lorde, Henrie Earle of Darbie, Lord Stanley and Strange, Lord of Man, and of the Isles adioy∣ning, and Knight of the most no∣ble Order of the Garter, Oliuer Carter wisheth continuance of health, with increase of honor.</title>
           <author>Carter, Oliver</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108169_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18055</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4697</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108169</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable and his verie good Lorde, Henrie Earle of Darbie, Lord Stanley and Strange, Lord of Man, and of the Isles adioy∣ning, and Knight of the most no∣ble Order of the Garter, Oliuer Carter wisheth continuance of health, with increase of honor.</title>
                 <author>Carter, Oliver</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere made by Oliuer Carter, Bacheler of Diuinitie: unto certaine popish questions and demaundes</title>
                 <author>Carter, Oliver</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>19, 82 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right Honourable</hi> and his verie good Lorde, Henrie <hi>Earle of Darbie, Lord Stanley and Strange,</hi> Lord of Man, and of the Isles adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Knight of the most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Order of the Garter, Oliuer Carter wisheth continuance of health, with increase of honor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) the brittle and fraile state of mans life, beeing sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto manifold miseries by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclinatiō, but also in continual daunger and ieopardie, through the assaultes of Sathan, &amp; sinister practi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses of his vngodly mēbers: I thinke it the part of all the childrē of God, so much the more to imploye all their trauell, both for the reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="3"/> of these decayed affections in man, &amp; also for the suppressing and beating downe (by all meanes pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible) all wicked &amp; sinfull attempts, whereby Gods glorie may be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. And although I amongest manie am most vnmeete, both for want of knowledge, and lacke of experience, to take anie such enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise in hande: yet for satisfying the expectation of a godlie learned friend, as also for the comfort of my poore neighbours, (whome I perceiue to bee ouer much seduced (the more it is to bee lamented) by these and such like Popish deuises: and thereby not so willing to yeeld their dutifull and loyall submission to God and to their most Noble, vertuous, and godlie Soueraigne) as most especiallie for the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods honour and increase of Christes kingdome. If his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie wisedome thinke good, to
<pb facs="3"/> worke by such simple meanes: I haue thought good (at the least) to bestowe my labour, referring the successe thereof, wholie and onelie vnto God. I am giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande, and I do partlie know it for trueth, that these Interrogations &amp; Questions (inuented by some pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist) be secretlie spredde abroad in sundrie places. And albeit I doe certainlie knowe, what great care and paines godlie Magistrates for their partes do take, to aduance and extoll the true seruice and worship of God, to further the free passage of his most holie woord and Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to suppresse the rage of such as do obstinatelie and stubburnlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the trueth: yet notwithstanding there be not onelie close and secret enimies, which wander abroad in corners, seducing the simple by wicked doctrine, sedicious &amp; trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous libells, and false tales, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating
<pb facs="4"/> their mindes by all meanes, from true religion vnto superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but also the rabble of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishe merchantes with their mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wares, do so increase and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie, that vnlesse redresse bee had in time, I do feare least great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience and mischiefe will ensue thereof. For partlie by these Popish whisperers, and partlie for lacke of true and faithfull Teachers, shippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke is made of the Gospell of Christ. I do not wishe their punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but desire their reformation: for my conscience beareth me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, howe earnestlie for my part, I haue laboured to reduce them, where I haue had charge, from the grosse errours in exercising that small talent, which GOD of his goodnesse hath bestowed vpon me, and what inward loue I doe beare vnto them, if I were able to doe them good. Neuerthelesse, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="4"/> but lament their miserable state, perceiuing in thē such a readinesse to imbrace euerie fonde idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous tradition inuented by man, to accept the aduise and counsell of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ignorāt, &amp; lurking rebellious priest, to persist in their old doating customes, and heathenishe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: and such slacknesse, or rather dulnesse, to receiue the vndoubted trueth of Gods most holie worde, whiche is the verie pathwaye to Christes eternal kingdome, and the power of God vnto saluation to all that beleeue. But it is not my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to make anie long discourse of these matters: Onlie I beseech your Honor to pardon my bolde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise, in presenting this litle An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere vnto you, and to accept my good will herein, in good part. So you shall not onelie incourage me, (if the like occasion bee offered) to take greater paynes hereafter: but
<pb facs="5"/> also binde mee daily to pray vnto GOD for your Honor, that all your actions may tende to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie of GOD, and to the discharging of that office and function, which God hath called you vnto: which God graunt, for his mercie sake: To whom bee all prayse, dominion, and power, now and for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors Oliuer Carter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>