<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
TO THE TRUELY Noble the Ladie, Theophila Cooke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108695_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5771</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108695</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
TO THE TRUELY Noble the Ladie, Theophila Cooke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the Cid</title>
                 <author>Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Browne (Broun), Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="2"/>
TO THE TRUELY Noble the Ladie, <hi>Theophila Cooke.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I had no obligation to your Ladiship, which might challenge my endevours of honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you, a fitter or a happier name could not protect this piece, (whose subject is the preferring of Dutie, and respects before Love, as the former did Honour and courage:) which I therefore offer to
<pb facs="3"/>
your Ladiship; because in them there is none better studied than your selfe, in whom I have observ'd from the strength of Vertue, such a serenity as conducts your mind to the performance of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is fit and decent in humane life. And I remember I had the Honour to heare your Ladiship discourse of this subject, when you concluded that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Lover should submit his desires to his Mistresses advancement: which made mee wish that our French Author had spoken with those Graces here in this, with which your Ladiship then did. But since it pleased his Majesty to thinke it worth the translating, and commanded it to be put into my hands, I will not censure it, though I believe, if that may carry the place which is free from defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, without excellence before that which is here and there exceeding faire, and as much blemished, I think this may deserve it, which is rather not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted to then much extold. Whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it be, I beseech your Ladiship to let it
<pb facs="3"/>
passe under your name, lest I be thought indiscreet in placing it else-where, or unmindfull of what I owe you, though this be the least part of that returne which is meant to you from</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most humble and obedient Servant,
ERUTTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>