<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOVR to the gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>Gibbons, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108929_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06450</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108929</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOVR to the gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gibbons, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A spiritual doctrine : conteining a rule to liue vvel, vvith diuers praiers and meditations. Abridged by the Reuerend Father Levvis de Granada of the holie order of preachers. And deuided into sixe treatises, as is to be seene after the prefaces. Nevvlie translated out of Spanish into English</title>
                 <author>Luis, de Granada</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 208, 229-397, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOVR to the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath seemed good to me, Gentle Reader, to let thee vnderstand in the beginning of this little booke, that som yeeres past, a vvorthie and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Gentleman of our nation, had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon to translate out of Spainish into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, the Memoriall, and other spirituall bookes, of that famous and Religious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Levvis de Granada,</hi> of S. Dominicks order. Of all vvhich, som haue ben put in print, som others, I knovv not vppon vvhat occasion, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> not yet com forth. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the cause maie be, certeine it is that in the meane time, the same Religious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being verie desirous, that all sort of men should take the profit of such spirituall vvoorkes, as he vvith so greate paines had vttered to the vvoorld, for theire soules good, and auancement in the seruice of
<pb facs="5"/>God, did, not long before his death, dravve out an Abridgment of his forsaid bookes, moued therunto for the reasons, vvhich he him self hath set dovvne in his preface to the Reader, as it goeth heere in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this little volume. VVhich vvoork, vvhen I had read and perused the same, liked me so much, that I resolued vvith mie self to put it in English, esteeming that as all the other spirituall vvoorks of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout father, ar of greate comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, to all the seruants of Almightie God, so this vvould be of no lesse furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in spirite, to such as vvould endeuour to vse the same. Especiallie considering, that all that is conteined in this little booke, is matter apperteining rather to practise of deuotion, and to kendle our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the loue of our svveete Sauiour, then to frame greate discourses, and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate our vnderstanding; albeit this part be also to be found heere, as much as it maketh to the benifit of the other, and standeth vvith the briefenes, vvhich the Author novv pretended.</p>
   <p>This being so, it remaineth Gentel Reader, vvhoesoeuer, and of vvhatsoeuer Religion thou be, that thou endeuour to peruse this booke, to the end, for vvhich
<pb facs="5"/>it vvas first vvriten, and is novv translated into English, that is to thine ovvne good and saluation. VVhich thing thou shalt easilie perfourme, if thou procure, as neere as God shall aforde thee grace, to reade and vveigh that vvhich is heere conteined, vvith a reposed and quiet spirite, vvith a meeke and humble spirite, vvith a spirite of patience and long animitie, vvith a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite altogether determined and resolued, to seeke sincerelie and purelie, not so much thine ovvne interest &amp; contentment, as the honour and glorie of God, and to knovv his good vvill and pleasure, and vvith all thy povver to put the same in execution. Neither must thou be ouercurious, or hastie to passe on in reading the contents thereof, but rather endeuour to staie thie self som space of time, in considering vvith much attention that, vvhich thou hast read, and by this consideration to stirre vp, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thy vvill and affection, to practise &amp; excute that, vvhich thou shalt vnderstand to be the best pleasure of almightie God, and most profitable to thine ovvne salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This is that vvhich thou must doe, if thou pretend to take anie comfort or commoditie, by reading of spirituall and deuout bookes.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Novv then, deare Reader, hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els vvhereof to admonish thee, I vvil end this mie preface, and remitte thee to the Author him self of this little vvoorke, desiring thee, for mie small paines besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved in the translation, to be mindfull of me in thie praiers. Christ IESVS direct thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan <date>the <hi>25.</hi> of March, <hi>1599.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thy hartie vvellvviller and seruant in Christ IESVS. Rich. Gibbons.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>