<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108433_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05289</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15432</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108433</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Speculum belli sacri: Or The looking-glasse of the holy war : wherein is discovered: the evill of war. The good of warr. The guide of war. In the last of these I give a scantling of the Christian tackticks, from the levying of the souldier, to the founding of the retrait; together with a modell of the carryage, both of conquerour and conquered. I haue applyed the generall rules warranted by the Word, to the particular necessity of our present times</title>
                 <author>Leighton, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 316 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>Errata.</head>
   <p>LET me intreat thee (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ourreous Reader) to bear with errours from the presse, as some literall faults, defects of Accents, or Points, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing, or wanting of a word. Three Greek words in the Margine hath likewise faults in them. In the Epistle to the Reader, pag. 2. line 1. for <hi>treatise,</hi> reade <hi>this treatise:</hi> Pag. 49, Marg. for <hi>alumoniam,</hi> reade, <hi>alimoniam: Ibid.</hi> for <hi>virtus</hi> reade <hi>victus:</hi> pag. 87, l. <hi>ult.</hi> for <hi>that like,</hi> r. <hi>that it is like:</hi> pag. 159, l. 13, for <hi>ebary,</hi> r. <hi>chair:</hi> pag. 186. l, 20, for <hi>for,</hi> r. <hi>far: Ibid.</hi> l. 32, for 1180, r. 11800: pag. 208. l. 18, for <hi>the better,</hi> r. <hi>to the better.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="169"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>