<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right honourable the Lorde Vidam Chartres, Prince of Chabanoys. Peter Droet Phisition sendeth gréeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108183_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20865</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7241</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108183</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right honourable the Lorde Vidam Chartres, Prince of Chabanoys. Peter Droet Phisition sendeth gréeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A new counsell against the pestilence : declaring what kinde of disease it is, of what cause it procedeth, the signes and tokens thereof: with the order of curing the same</title>
                 <author>Drouet, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right honourable the Lorde Vidam Chartres, Prince of Chabanoys. Peter Droet <hi>Phisition sendeth gréeting.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O many are your benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon mee, (Right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Patrone, where by you would haue me bounden vnto you all the dayes of my life, both in bestowing parte of your goods vpō mee, and in imparting the rare gyftes of your minde: that if I would indeuour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the same in wordes, truely I were not able▪ And first to let passe the giftes of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune wherewith you haue sufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaced my wealth, I would willingly reherse the countreyes which I haue traueyled with you: and what secrets of nature I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by your means &amp; industrie: what ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions you haue proposed vnto me and other professours of Phisick, drawne out of the deepest secrets and bowels of nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at both they &amp; I being astonied: haue won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at your singular learning, and merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at your sharpnes of wit, yea, I myselfe remember how ofte I haue reade ouer the workes of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> only to be
<pb facs="4"/>
able to satissie your demaundes, who woulde dispute with more sharpnesse of witte then is accustomablye vsed in our publique schooles, whereby you haue so pricked mee forward that whatsoeuer excellencie is in me in the knowledg of Phisick, which I would haue to be taken as spoken without brag, I acknowledg that I haue receiued it by your meanes only. For by the helpe of you, and your wisdome, I haue had conference with the best learned Phisitions both in England, Germanie, and many other places: and for your sake I haue learned many thinges of them concerning the secrets of our facultie, and found them to bee true by practice and experience, whereby I am able to cure many kindes of diseases. Amonge all which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets▪ I haue gathered together manye rare and verie effectuall remedies against the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer quartaine, against the infectious Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to breake the stone, and against cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten other stubburne diseases, neuer set forth in the writinges of any Phisitions as far as I doe knowe. VVhich when I had imparted vnto certen well learned Phisitions, my friendes and acquaintance, I regarded them somuch that by oftē requesting of me, they obtayned, that I should setfoorth into
<pb facs="4"/>
light such speciall remedies as I had gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red against the plague, to the commoditie of the miserable estate of mankind. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (Right honourable <hi>Mecoenas</hi> and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone) though I bee mindfull of your good turnes on me bestowed, wherwith you haue bounde me and all mine to be at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente for euer: notwithstanding since it is the parte of an honest and liberall heart to desire to be more beholden to him to whom he is much beholden, I would thus much request of you, that this bookegoing forth vnder the salfconduct of your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable name, and being alreadie approued by your singular learning, and presuming on your aucthoritie, may come abrode into mens handes, whereby the posteritie maye wonder at you, and worthely praise you for being not onely a prince of warre, but a student also of liberall sciences. Fare you well From my studie, the iiij. of the Ides of Iune. 1572.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>