<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR HENRY NORTH, HIGH SHE∣riffe of the County of Suffolk, together withthe rest of his Maiesties Iustice of peace in that County.</title>
           <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108664_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19288</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5698</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR HENRY NORTH, HIGH SHE∣riffe of the County of Suffolk, together withthe rest of his Maiesties Iustice of peace in that County.</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The cry and reuenge of blood : Expressing the nature and haynousnesse of wilfull murther. Exemplified in a most lamentable history thereof, committed at Halsworth in High Suffolk, and lately conuicted at Bury assize, 1620</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wright, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 63, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR HENRY NORTH, HIGH SHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> together <hi>withthe rest of his Maiesties Iustice of peace</hi> in that County.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull: It fell out by Gods good prouidence, that at the last Assize at <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> I was an eare-witnesse of the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of the most strange and cruell Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that euer I read of: The Detection whereof, together with the most fayre and honourable car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the businesse, did so affect me: that I could not think my time better spent, then in taking notes of such speciall Passages as fell out therein. Which howsoeuer I then onely entended for my priuate vse, yet considering, that such wonderful works of God, are to be declared to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity: and being solicited by some Worthies of the Shire to that end: I thought it good to condiscend to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests with the soonest, the rather to preuent such flying and suspitious pamphlets, wherewith the world in such cases, is too much abused: and so informe the world in the right vse of such strange occurrents. Wherein if your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships shall find ought that may reuiue in your memory, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o
<pb facs="4"/>
wonderfull a discouery, and shall stirre vp your affections to magnifie the prouidence of God herein: As I shall haue herein what I principally desire, so shall I not faile to take any other good occasion, to testifie my thankefulnesse vnto your Worships, as God shall offer the same: to whose gracious protection I doe most hartily commend you all,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Resting in him, Your Worships poore remembrancer at the Throne of Grace.
THO. COOPER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>