<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
To the Right Honourable Sir William Webbe Knight, Lord Mayor of Lon∣don, and to the right Worshipfull the Aldermen of the same Cittie his brethren.</title>
           <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108793_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68409</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16767</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108793</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
To the Right Honourable Sir William Webbe Knight, Lord Mayor of Lon∣don, and to the right Worshipfull the Aldermen of the same Cittie his brethren.</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A profitable and necessarie discourse, for the meeting with the bad garbelling of spices, vsed in these dayes : And against the combination of the vvorkemen of that office, contrarie vnto common good. Composed by diuers grocers of London, wherein are handled such principall matters, as followeth in the table, before the booke</title>
                 <author>Grocers' Company (London, England)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bourne, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 87, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="2"/>
To the Right Honourable Sir William Webbe Knight, Lord Mayor of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and to the right Worshipfull the Aldermen of the same Cittie his brethren.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecause the complaintes of sundrye of the retayling grocers of Londō, to the cheefe officers the gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and to the first menne of that society, against the fact of bad gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling of spices, betvveene them and the Marchantes, hath in lieu of reformation taught manye indigneties and vvrought som indignation tovvards the cōplaināts. Therefore no councell vvas better (that despaire of remedie amongst them, could then conceiue or bring forth) then to flie to your moste godly vvisedome for suche helps therein, as do beare an <hi>Anologie</hi> and proportion correspōdent to the mischiefs and diseases in the fact of garbling. Or if that doo faile to follovv the saieng of the Poet <hi>Musaeus,</hi> the vvhich is thus set forth:
<q>
         <l>It is good sometime to sound in open street</l>
         <l>The wicked works which men do thinke to hide.</l>
      </q>
      <pb facs="3"/>
meaning that by publishing of some smal pamphlet touching the same, suche good maye ensue, either the vvorkemanne to grovv better, or the buier to be more vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser, in the office of garbling (a matter right Honorable and vvorshipfull, full of rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to breake open a discourse, vvherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a man may more easilie enter, then find the vvaie out againe.) But since that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie and povver (vvhich vvorketh by operation) to redresse these defectes, is as yet lefte, only in them vvhich are the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of them, vve meane in the Garbeller and vvorkemen. Our vvit is such (vvhich ought to vvork vvith councell and discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to allovv and aduance this smal trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise vnder your Honors fauor and protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the effect vvherof is to shevve the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses doone in that office, vvith the right vse and motion therof: vvherin your vvis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Honor may be pleased, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse our boldnesse vnder this defense, that in great inconueniences, great Officers haue not despised the meanest voices. Then shall our duties to the cōmonvvelth be out of daunger, and the same aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="3"/>
by your vvonted affection, to vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer concerneth common good, &amp; by this our labour. In the vvhich affection vve beseech the Creator of all thinges, to assist your Lordship and vvorships vvith his holy spirit, and to giue you the same for councel and conduction in the seruice of hir Maiestie, this Cittie, and to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and your posteritie for euer heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Grocers Hall in London.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most humble the Retailors
Grocers. London.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>