<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Letter to a friend.</title>
           <author>Niccols, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108006_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5343</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Letter to a friend.</title>
                 <author>Niccols, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Henoch Clapham his demaundes and answeres touching the pestilence : methodically handled, as his time and meanes could permit</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb n="31" facs="16"/>
   <head>A Letter to a friend.</head>
   <p>YOu desire to heare by what Law, I was committed, and so am still
continued in prison? I protest, in the presence of God, I know not, by what
Law, all this is done, There is a Law, that toucheth som, concerning iudgement
and doctrine of the Pestilence. It is layd downe in the booke called the
<hi>Queenes Orders</hi> for the Pestilence: I speake of our late sweet
Soveraigne, now gone vnto God. The same booke since (as I take it) was
published last pest-tyme, in his Maiesties name, and this is it
<hi>verbatim.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <p>
         <hi>Order</hi> 16. Item if there be any person, Ecclesiasticall or
Lay, that should hold, and publish any opinions, (as in som places report is
made) that it is a vayne thing, to forbeare, to resorte to the infected: or
that it is not charitable, to forbid the same; pretending that no person shall
dy, but at their time prefixed, such persons shall not only be reprehended, but
by order of the Bishop, (If they bee Ecclesiasticall,) shalbe forbidden to
preach: and being Lay, shalbe also enioyned to forbeare, to vtter such
daungerous opinions, vpon payne of imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which shalbe executed, if
they shall perseuere in that errour. And yet it shall appeare manifestly, by
these Orders, that according to Christian charitie, no persons of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
degree, shalbe left without succour and relief.</p>
   </q>
   <p>Admitt now, I had bene coulpable, of such doctrine: my punishment
should not haue bene imprisonment, but som in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, <pb n="32" facs="17"/>
      <hi>to preach.</hi> But, as may appeare, by all my writings, I am cleared from
all such imputation: and so no Law (that yet I can heare of) in this matter,
violated of me. His Maiestie commaunded, I should be proceeded withall; <hi>By
the Law,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, that there was a Law to cleare me, or condemne me:
and yet (as you heare) I am kept still in bondes, only vpon my L. of London
commaund, (not vpon any Law Civill, or Ecclesiasticall, once spoken of) others
of the <hi>Hy-Commission</hi> vnited with him therein, who (I suppose) dare
not, easilie, be in any thing, vnto him, repugnant: and he having imprisoned
me, before he truely vnderstood the cause, doeth thus goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to make good
his imprisonmēt, by wincking at the truth of the cause, seeming to plague me
for the contrary.</p>
   <p>This may suffice, for your question; wherewith I end, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring
Your harty prayers vnto God, for my good: To whose saving mercies also, I
referre you and your Studies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours HE. CL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>