<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable, and most vertuous Lady, Anne, Countesse of War∣wicke.</title>
           <author>Bell, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108948_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06524</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16996</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108948</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable, and most vertuous Lady, Anne, Countesse of War∣wicke.</title>
                 <author>Bell, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise, touching the libertie of a Christian. Written in Latin by Doctor Martine Luther. And translated into English by Iames Bell</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 92, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honourable, and most vertuous Lady, <hi>Anne,</hi> Countesse of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had finished this simple Translation for the behoofe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettered, some of my welwillers conceiuing well of the matter, were very desirous that I should present the same to some noble personage: others challenging more knowledge in Courtly affaires, perswaded the contrary, being of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that though it might in some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect seeme plausible enough, yet the present being but simple, could not deserue to be aduanced to Court, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to place of estate. And although I supposed, and partly knew, that the opinion of the later was but weake in
<pb facs="3"/>
iudgement: yet loe, it made so much the longer stay in deliberation, by how much I was abashed in conceit, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of my rudenesse, and vnaptnesse, to satisfie the learned, &amp; Courtly eares. Neuerthelesse, hauing clothed my Stranger in English attyre (whom I call a Stranger, in respect of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, who was the first Author therof.) And well knowing the Court, to the great fame and honour thereof, by the space of many yeares now passed, to haue bin the rescue of all Strangers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed, I could not but beleeue, that in the Court, this Stranger so godly, so zealous, so learned, should be both ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily accepted, and gently entertained: and encouraged by this well knowne experience, I yeelded my selfe to the first perswasion, and finding by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall report (Madame) the noble orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and gifts, I speake not onely of
<pb facs="3"/>
nature, but of godlinesse, wisedome, and zeale, ioyned with singular milde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and benignity, being the fruits of grace amongst the rest especially, to shine in your sacred breast, I was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by emboldned to proceede, and aboue all others, to presume vpon your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable patience, and to present to your honour this my poore Stranger: In whose commendation I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme, that there was neuer any a more trusty seruant to his Master: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any of more vndaunted courage in his Masters cause: neuer any that aduentured, or durst aduenture far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: neuer any that vsed more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie, magnanimity, and force, in battering the fortresses of the enemy: neuer any that pierced deeper, preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led further, and procured larger, for the safety of poore Christians, so many hundred yeares oppressed, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned,
<pb facs="4"/>
impouerished, yoked, and chained in miserable captiuitie, through the monstrous outrage of that execrable Nimrod of Rome, amongst many of whose exployts, albeit there cannot any one bee found, that is not able to replenish the Spirituall and true Christian man, with such, and so great ioy, as can not with my penne be expressed, yet in my simple iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this one little treatise of his, which I haue now aboue all others se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to translate, doth farre excell and surmount in ghostly consolation, wherein are entreated no vaine, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish, or trifling toyes, but sweet, dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, serious, weighty, and matters of great importance, namely, the pure faith of a true Christian man, the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnion and marriage of the most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable Bridegrome IESV Christ, to the poore miserable abiect and
<pb facs="4"/>
wretched Soule, the well ordering of christian life, and the gladsome chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian freedome and liberty. Euen such a one is this my Stranger, whom, if it may please your Honour to vouchsafe vnto your honourable patronage, I shall not onely accompt my selfe most happy in my ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, but also (acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging your honourable courtesie in full satisfaction of mine English cost, such as it is employed) yeeld my selfe doubly bounden &amp; indebted to your Honour in any thing which my penne may endeauour, or trauell may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. The holy ghost, the Author of all goodnesse, &amp; ghostly consolation, replenish your heart with the most ioyfull freedome of his grace, to the comfort of all such as trauell in the building of Gods holy temple.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours most humble at commandement, <hi>IAMES BELL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>