<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108604_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19207</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5615</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108604</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvelspring of wittie conceites : containing, a methode, asvvell to speake, as to endight (aptly and eloquently of sundrie matters: as (also) see great varietie of pithy sentences, vertuous sayings, and right morall instructions ... Out of Italian, by W. Phist. student)</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 27, 29-94, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Authors Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Conceites</hi> or <hi>Deuices</hi> of our mindes expressed, either with <hi>Pen,</hi> or by <hi>Speaking,</hi> do tende to this ende, namely, that they may <hi>Perswade:</hi> And to <hi>Perswade,</hi> is as much, as that one man should make others beleeue, that our talke, or the thing whereof we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, is either <hi>True</hi> or <hi>False,</hi> and our <hi>Reasonings</hi> or <hi>Speeches,</hi> be either <hi>publique,</hi> or <hi>priuat: Publique,</hi> are those that are vsed vniuersally to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people, &amp; also, to those that gouerne y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people: <hi>Priuat,</hi> bée sutch as are vsed with <hi>Priuat</hi> Persons, which bée assembled together, and they be of thrée sortes: for they bée ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Thinges present,</hi> of <hi>Thinges passed,</hi> or of <hi>Thinges to come: Present,</hi> do comprehende <hi>Vertues,</hi> which are praised, or on the contrarie side <hi>Vices,</hi> which be blamed: <hi>Thinges past,</hi> as <hi>Manslaughters, Rapines,</hi> and all the offences and debates, which are brought into iudgemēt, in which consist to <hi>Accuse</hi> and <hi>Defende: Thinges to come,</hi> are those, in which we haue néede: first, of <hi>Counsell,</hi> afterwarde, <hi>of Election,</hi> or making choice. The first kinde, is called <hi>Demonstratiue:</hi> the second, <hi>Iudiciall:</hi> the third, <hi>Deliberatiue:</hi> all which (notwithstanding) that they do chiefly respect publicke persons, yet they be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily vsed toward priuat persons, the which do many times giue counsell amongst themselues, doo <hi>Accuse,</hi> doo <hi>Prayse</hi> and <hi>Reprooue.</hi> Other sortes of reasoning, as to <hi>Reioyce,</hi> to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile,</hi> to <hi>Complaine,</hi> and all others bee reduced vnder some of the three aforenamed kindes, &amp; haue for their ende to <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade,</hi> the which is sometimes brought to passe with reasons either <hi>Probable</hi> or <hi>Apparent,</hi> and sometimes with moouing mens affections: which things be principally giuē by nature,
<pb facs="4"/>and afterward ruled and fitted out with that wonderfull or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which is shewed vs by <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and by other, both aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and late excellēt Wryters, who through their rule and order obserued, haue been the occasiō that the fruites of many Authors shall liue for euer: out of whome I haue taken some part of these <hi>Conceites</hi> or <hi>Deuices,</hi> which I haue vnderstoode to be most learned, most méete, and proper to applye vnto all kindes and manners of <hi>Speaking,</hi> or of <hi>Writing</hi> familiarly, and those that were most briefe, déeming that in the <hi>qualitie,</hi> and not in the <hi>Quantitie</hi> of wordes, and of <hi>Sense,</hi> doth consist the <hi>Elegancie</hi> of a commendable <hi>Speech,</hi> or <hi>Writing:</hi> and that heerby we may, in what <hi>Reasoning</hi> soeuer it be, or in <hi>writing,</hi> receiue light of <hi>Inuentiō,</hi> and with such <hi>Eloquēce</hi> adorne our matter, as shall containe fit <hi>Numbers,</hi> comely <hi>Figures, Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phores, Similitudes, Sentences, Aucthoritie,</hi> and <hi>Examples:</hi> as those do shew foorth that I haue here placed in order: and to make serue with fewe, and with many, according, as shall be most conuenient, either in <hi>Writing,</hi> or in <hi>Speaking:</hi> &amp; because one discours of <hi>Wordes,</hi> &amp; one <hi>Letter</hi> or <hi>Epistle</hi> shall not haue occasion to weaue together all these <hi>common places,</hi> it shall be expedient that they be of iudgement, and haue regard how to apply euery Sentence in his due place, according as <hi>Time</hi> and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Matter</hi> doth require, they which shall go about to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate any thing herein. Those <hi>Sentences,</hi> which I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of <hi>Auncient</hi> and famous <hi>Authors,</hi> their names (for the most part) are coted in the Margent: others which haue béene partly the inuention of late Writers &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mine owne I haue not coted. Thus wishing for a frenedly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, in recompence of my frée goodwill, I cease.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell in the Lorde.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>