<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108989_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19493</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5919.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108989</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three heauenly treatises vpon the eight chapter to the Romanes : Viz. 1 Heauen opened. 2 The right way to eternall glory. 3 The glorification of a Christian. VVherein the counsaile of God concerning mans saluation is so manifested, that all men may see the Ancient of dayes, the Iudge of the World, in his generall iustice court, absoluing the Christian from sinne and death. Which is the first benefit wee haue by our lord Iesus Christ. Written by Mr. William Cowper, minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Cowper, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Knight, Clement.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ferbrand (Firebrand, Forbrand), William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 216, 4, 217-398, 6, 399-457, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2+ letters">
      <desc>••…</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="83"/>
   <p>the welfare of your Highnesse royall children, the terrour of
your enimies, and common benefite of all your Maiesties well
affected subiects. A good so much the more carefully to bee
keept, because Sathan out of all doubt spitefully doth enuie it,
as being the very fountaine, out of which doth flow that great
and common good, both of your royall posteritie, and loyall peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
the aspect of your Highnesse fauourable countenances loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
in loue one of you to another, and both of your maiesties in
coniunct compassion to your people, sweeter than the influence
of the vndiuided <hi>Pleiades,</hi> bringing to Church and common
wealth, vnder your happy raigne a flourishing spring of innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
blessings. We doe therefore blesse the Lord who hath
confirmed your royall hearts, and set it in the foremost of your
godly cares, how to keep and increase this holy and happy band
of loue which keepeth you both. For the continuance whereof,
as after my weake measure, I stand vp a dayly supplicant vnto
the Lord, among others your Highnesse loyall subiects, so doe I
humbly craue that your Highnesse impute it not to me for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption,
that I haue conioyned your maiesties in the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
of this small propine of the first fruits of my labors, whom
I doe wish for euer to be conioyned in the communion of al good
present, and to come: but that rather according to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
wonted fauour and clemencie toward me, your maiestie
would graciously accept it, as a testimonie of my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
and vnfained affection toward your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
name and honour in this life, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
welfare in the life to come.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
and dayly Oratour
<hi>William Cowper,</hi>
Minister at <hi>Perth.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>