<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108980_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5915</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108980</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Bishop of Gallovvay his dikaiologie : contayning a iust defence of his former apologie. Against the iniust imputations of Mr. Dauid Hume</title>
                 <author>Cowper, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 183, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO
THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I was on my iourney from
<hi>LONDON</hi> homeward, in
the Moneth of <hi>May</hi> last, I
was ouertaken not farre from
<hi>Darnetoune,</hi> by our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man,
M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Dauid Hume,</hi>
Goodman of <hi>Gods-croft.</hi>
After we had saluted one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
we fell incontinent to a conference of Church-gouernment:
hee excused himselfe, that his leasure
serued him not at that time to stay in our companie,
his vrgent affaires forcing him to post before, but hee
promised to send mee his doubts in writing, and I
promised him (if it pleased the Lord) an answere. The
point I tooke in hand to proue, was, that no substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
point of Discipline was changed in our Church.
For, Ecclesiasticke Synods vsed before, are retained
still, the censures of Admonition, Suspension, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication;
yea, the Admission and Deposition of
<pb facs="3"/>
Pastors, or what euer else pertaynes to the matter of
Discipline; these are not remoued but rectified and
roborated: in that the power to moderate and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
these censures, is not left free to euery one, but
restored againe to the Bishop, to be vsed with aduise
of his Brethren: thus keepe wee still the same Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
but more orderly vsed.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> dined at <hi>Darneroune,</hi> and parted in louing
manner, with all brotherly kindnes: we ouertooke him
againe at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> where not finding his former hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie,
I maruelled what it could be, or from whom
it c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me, that so small a change of the soile; should
make so great a change of the affection; for in the one
hee was most kinde, where with reason he might haue
beene more strange; and in the other most strange,
where of dutie hee both might and should haue beene
more kindly. Since that time I fore-gathered not with
him, and I expected nothing, but kindnesse from him,
and that the question should haue beene quietly and
peaceably disputed by writing among our selues, till
now that he hath begunne the publike warre. He had
sent me some missiue Letters written by him to some
others, crauing resolution of his doubts concerning
Church gouernment. And as I was dispatching an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere
to him, I was forced to plead for my Conscience
by <hi>APOLOGIE</hi> against a lying Libeller, which here
<hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Dauid</hi> against all dutie and reason hath publicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
impugned. First, because I stood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ound by promise
to giue an answere to himselfe, and reason would hee
should haue expected it: yea doubtlesse he had gotten
<pb facs="3"/>
it long ere now, in more quiet and louing manner, if
he had not interrupted me. Secondly, I had written
nothing against <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Dauid,</hi> I touched him not in my
<hi>Apologie,</hi> and no other way gaue I him any cause to
write against mee. Thirdly, hee being a priuate man,
it cannot be but a great Presumption to condemne by
publike writing a Church-gouernment established by
Law and that without knowledge (if himselfe be true)
for he professeth to seeke instruction concerning it,
yea, without eyther calling or lawfull commission.
Fourthly, before euer he sent this Refutation of this
<hi>Apologie</hi> to me, or had discharged with me, he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished
sundry Copies of it to be seene and read of others,
which in our Prouerbe we call <hi>Treason vnder trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
Fiftly, his whole Admonitorie Treatise is full
of Inuectiues <hi>in personam,</hi> without regard of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie,
yea, of that feare of God which becommeth a
Christian, bringing nothing, or else very little <hi>ad
propositum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus hath <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Dauid</hi> kept no faire warre with
mee, but hath very farre ouer-seene himselfe, and
wronged mee, which that the indifferent may know,
I haue here published his <hi>Admonition</hi> in his owne
words and mine answeres. I haue omitted no materiall
thing in it; onely words of needlesse repetition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
hee abounds. If hee had contented himselfe to iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
the Libeller, in tramping my Name, my Conscience,
my Ministrie vnder his feete, it had beene a proofe of
my patience great enough. But where without reason
or truth, he will beare downe a common cause, and
<pb facs="4"/>
increase offences in the hearts of simple people, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
of conscience suffer it vnanswered: specially, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
vnder pretence of impugning mee, hee directly
impugneth it. If my heart in this had reproued mee
of my wayes, I might haue lurked in secret, and past
ouer the Libeller, and him also with silence; but an
honest conscience feareth not the light, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth
in it. Onely I craue of the modest minded
Christian, that if my speeches in the <hi>Answere</hi> at any
time be sharper then becommeth, it be imputed to
humane infirmitie, whereunto the loue of the cause,
and knowledge of mine owne innocencie hath carryed
mee, not want of loue toward him or others. It is no
pleasure to mee to offend any man: if any such haue
escaped mee, I will not excuse my selfe in that which
the wise, godly, and indifferent Reader shall thinke
may iustly be reprehended.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
W. B. of <hi>Galleway.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>