<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE QVEENE,
MOTHER OF OVR
KING, AND REGENT OF
FRANCE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108850_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19436</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5862</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108850</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE QVEENE,
MOTHER OF OVR
KING, AND REGENT OF
FRANCE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hellish and horribble councell, practised and vsed by the Iesuites, (in their priuate consultations) when they would haue a man to murther a king : According to those damnable instructions, giuen (by them) to that bloody villaine Francis Rauilliacke, who murdered Henr the fourth, the late French king. Sent to the Queene Regent, in answere of that impudent pamphlet, published by Peter Cotton Iesuite, in defence of the Iesuites, and their doctrine; which also is hereunto annexed. Translated out of French</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bushell, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE QVEENE,
MOTHER OF OVR
KING, AND REGENT OF
FRANCE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> combate of spirits is so
iealous, as there is not any kind
of errour, how cleare and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
so euer it be, but it shall
finde a defender, rather then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
way to yeeld or giue place to
truth: because opinion, in such
mindes as pride will neuer permit, to humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
vnder the victorious arme of the strongest wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stler,
beares them out (with no meane courage) in all
apparant and impudent shame. The Iesuites doe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
giue sufficient testimony, whose doctrine, both iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
and defending the killing of Princes, they dare
yet put on such shamelesse vizardes; as, to perswade
your Highnesse, that they are no such men, neither
doe deserue any such taxation.</p>
   <p>Vpon this our late lamentable disaster in France, by
such a bloudy, fatall, and parricide hand, as hath bereft
<pb facs="3"/>
vs of the most remarkable King, that euer this flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing
Kingdome enioyed; the Iesuites, to excuse
their hellish harts, and palpable bloudy intentions
(hauing beene so highly fauoured from you, as to
haue the buriall of the Kinges hart, at the College of
<hi>La Flesche</hi>) haue published a little pamphlet, called;
<hi>A dedicatorie Letter, of the doctrine of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
Iesuites, conformable to the decrees in the
Councell of Constance;</hi> directing it also to your
Maiesty, that you might remaine fully assured, of their
harmelesse innocency and honest inclination.</p>
   <p>But, as it becommeth any true harted French-man,
(so much as in him lyeth) to discouer truth from false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
and verity from lying; I haue sent vnto your
sacred view, the same booke of <hi>Peter Cottons,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
altering or adding thereunto any the very least
sillable. And when your Highnesse shall haue read it
ouer, that you would be pleased, to reade likewise a
much shorter discourse following, to giue you a true
tast of the Iesuites doctrine, and whereby you may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
them in their kinde. So may you rest fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded,
how neare their hollow harts and equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
soules doe agree together, and how studious they
are, in imploying their paines and vttermost endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,
to nurse vp such villaines as must become the
murderers of Kinges.</p>
   <p>Withall, if it might please you, but to remember
him, to whom (that monster of men) <hi>Rauilliack,</hi> that
robde you of your richest iewell, and vs of our dearest
Lord; had shewne the fatall instrument, wherewith
<pb facs="3"/>
he did the deede, and the man commending the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
workemanship of the knife, seeing withall, that he
kept it curiously, and made no vse thereof in his fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;
was answered by the said <hi>Rauilliack: That
that fayre knife, was to performe a faire deede, yea,
that it was to kill a King.</hi> Which wordes, whether he
vnderstood not, or guiltily concealed them, he paied
the price of his life for: And with that, as also these
other serious considerations, I humbly intreate your
Highnesse, to take an intire apprehension of
these dangerous men, how smooth so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<hi>Cottons</hi> discourse shall
appeare vnto you.
({inverted ⁂})</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>