<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Iohan Bale to the readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108451_Bo1_4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05300</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15445</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108451</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Iohan Bale to the readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The laboryouse iourney [and] serche of Iohan Leylande, for Englandes antiquitees : geuen of hym as a newe yeares gyfte to Kynge Henry the viij. in the. xxxvij. yeare of his reygne, with declaracyons enlarged: by Iohan Bale</title>
                 <author>Leland, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bale, John, Bishop</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 <publisher>Foster, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>¶Iohan Bale to the readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N occasyō (me thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth) is offered me here, to exhybit som part of my studious labours to the vse of my brethrē, I wold I were as able to geue them the whole contentes therof, as I coulde fynde in my harte to do it out of hande frely. Sens I returned home agayne from Germany, where as I both collected, and emprented my symple worke, <hi>de Scriptoribus Britannicis</hi> I haue for the full correccyon and fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther augmentacyon of the same, peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed many libraries both in Cambridge and Oxforde. In the famouse cytye of London, is but one knowne library, so
<pb facs="52"/>
farre as I can learne, whyche also by fauer I haue seane ouer. But alas for pytie, that it shoulde be reported of so noble a cytie, to haue but one lybrary, and that to be so slendre a thing as it is The tyme hath bene, whan it hath had a great nombre of the noblest libraries in all Christendome, their destenecyon at this daye, of men godly mynded, is muche to be lamēted. Though the acte were most cōmendable, to suppresse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dysgysed sectes of the Romyshe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, and so to bannyshe them hens, yet can not the sufferaunce of this so heauy a ruine of Englandes noble mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>numentes, be so iudged of men wyse &amp; learned, but alas, farre otherwyse.</p>
   <p>Their temples for the more parte, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> their other buyldynges, remayne yet styll, vnbroken, Alac whie myghte not theyr libraries as wele haue remained to the commen wealth of learnynge, vndestroyed? Among the stacyoners &amp; boke bynders, I found many notable Antiquitees, of whom I wrote out the tytles, tymes, and begynnynges, that we myghte at the leaste shewe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb facs="52"/>
of them, though we haue not as now, their whole workes to shewe. Yf the byshop of Romes lawes, decrees decretals, extrauagantes, clemētines and other suche dregges of the deuyll, yea yf Heytesburyes <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>phlsmes, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyryes vniuersals, Aristotles olde so gyckes and Dunse &amp; dyuynyte, wyth such other lowsy legerdemaynes, and frutes of the bottomlesse pytte, had lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of our libraries, and so becomē couerynges for bokes comminge from the forē nacyons, we might wele haue ben therwith contented. But to put our auncient Chronicles, our noble hysto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, our learned cōmentaryes &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melyes vpō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scriptures, to so homely an office of subieccyon &amp; vtter contēpte we haue both greatly dishonoured our nacyon, and also shewed our selues ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry wycked to our posteryte.</p>
   <p>Now lete me returne to my labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse serche for olde and new wryters. I haue bene also at Norwyche, oure seconde cytie of name, and there all the library monumētes, and turned to the vse of their grossers, candelmakers
<pb facs="53"/>
sope sellers, and other worldly occupy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, so studyouse haue we ben there for a cōmen wealth, and so careful of good lernyng, o negligence most vnfryndly to our nacion. I woulde haue bene sory to haue vttered so obscure a facte, had not the vngentilnesse of the thing requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red it, to the warnyng of them whiche shall come after, for doyng the lyke to the hinderaūce of the realme. As much haue I saued both there &amp; in certē other places of Northfolke and Southfolke cōcerning the authors names &amp; tytles of their workes, as I could, &amp; as much wold I haue done through our y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole realm, yf I had bene able to haue borne the charges, as I am not. Wherfor my dere cō<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rey men, such as are zelouse to their nacion &amp; desirouse of good know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> residue shall accept at thys tyme, my good wil for my facte. These are the notable writers, whose names I haue gathered, &amp; whose manifold fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of doctrine I am redy to shew, yf y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord make me of power to perfourme it besides y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diligēt recogniciō &amp; increace<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes of my first labors.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>