<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honourable Lord Willyam Cobham, lord Warden of the cinque Portes: Thomas Tymme wisheth Nestors yeares, increase of honor, with preseruation of desired health.</title>
           <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108281_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16696</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3601</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108281</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honourable Lord Willyam Cobham, lord Warden of the cinque Portes: Thomas Tymme wisheth Nestors yeares, increase of honor, with preseruation of desired health.</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes from Niniue to Englande, brought by the prophete Ionas : vvhich newes in plainlye published in the godly and learned exposition of Maister Iohn Brentius folovving, translated out of Latine into Englishe by Thomas Tymme minister</title>
                 <author>Brenz, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 81 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honourable <hi>Lord Willyam Cobham, lord</hi> Warden of the cinque Portes: Thomas Tymme wisheth Nestors yeares, increase of honor, with preseruation of desired health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE CVRTEOVS BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, the noble vertue, but speciallye the godlye zeale (Right honourable) which fame and report cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefieth me to be in you, hath kindled such an earnest af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in me, that my rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and base state stayeth mee nothing at all, to dedicate this simple worke vnto you. For I know that Nobilitie, gratefully accepteth at others hands slender giftes, and of small reputation, according to their habilitie that offer the same.</p>
   <p>Artaxerxes, his good acceptation of a handfull of running water, made mee thus bolde, to offer this Pamphlet to your honour as a token of my good will: hoping that as he thought no disdain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the one, so you wil not take scorne of the other. Let me craue therefore this one thing, at your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours handes, that the basenesse of my translation of the learned Brentius procure not you, to refuse
<pb facs="3"/> the patronage and defence of my slender woorke. Which as I know vndoubtedly shall neuer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruayle your worthinesse: so do I assuredly hope that it may be a proofe of my good will, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The worthy Prophete IONAS, deserueth a worthie personage to be his defence and garde, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst scoffing Lucian, and fretting Momus.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, if your honor refuse not, but vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe, to take the same vpon you (as I perswade my selfe you will, weying the giuers intent, and seing that these are partly the first fruites of his trauaile) you shall not onely purchase immortall prayse of others: but I also shall be incouraged, and anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to greater, and waightyer attemptes: which I shall no sooner atchieue, but you shall be a witnes of my indeuours, and a rampire to my exploytes.</p>
   <p>Thus hauing boldly required your honors assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and tediously molested your eares with cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstaunces, leauing now at length to abuse your friendly pacience, I end: wishing to your honor the increase of Nobilitie, with a most happie estate, and after this lyfe, the gladsome ioyes of the euerlasting lyfe to come.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Beneficium dando accepit, qui digno dedit.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble Orator Thomas Tymme.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>