<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Of the Table and Catalogues heerin contained of degrees.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108078_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18994</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5411</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Of the Table and Catalogues heerin contained of degrees.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triall of bastardie : that part of the second part of policie, or maner of gouernement of the realme of England: so termed, spirituall, or ecclesiasticall. Annexed at the end of this treatise, touching the prohibition of marriage, a table of the Leuitical, English, an positiue canon catalogues, their concordance and difference. By William Clerke</title>
                 <author>Clerke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 82, 22 pages, 3 folded charts, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="52"/>
   <pb facs="52"/>
   <head>¶ Of the Table and Catalogues heerin contained of degrees.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onferring these Catalogues in the table that ensueth together, that is to say, the English and Canonicall with the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitical, some persons there shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare within the Leuiticall names and degrees; some without the Leuiticall names, but in the degrees; others there shall appeare without the Leuiticall names and degrees; the due consideration whereof is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>First of the ascendents and descendentes, such no doubt, though they exceed the Leuiticall names and degrees, yet they be prohibited infinitelie to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in so much that <hi>Adam</hi> if he had liued to this day, could not haue married againe.</p>
   <p>The second consideration, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Collaterals, such (with the Leuitical in name and degree) no man doubteth of their prohibition; otherwise, that is to say, If they differ but in name, <hi>Communi cōsensu &amp; iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio putantur in Leuitico prohiberi,</hi> thou art (for example) expresly in the Leuiticall forbidden to marrie thy brothers wife, thy wiues sister is not mentioned there in name, otherwise than thus, <hi>viz.</hi> Thou shalt not take a wife with hir sister (during hir life) to vexe hir in vncouering hir shame vpon hir; but thy brothers
<pb facs="53"/>
wife neuerthelesse comprehendeth hir degree, and whom equally thereforethou art prohibited to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that is to say, as with thy brothers wife, so with thy wiues sister, this vnderstand of the residue in this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>viz.</hi> Mothers brothers wife, wiues fathers sister, &amp;c. For the third, that is to say, such collaterals as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed both the name and degree Leuitical, doe also exceed this prohibition, <hi>i.</hi> they may marrie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out question or scruple, consideration had of such collaterals as doe sauour so of the ascendent and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent lines, that they be parents, or <hi>in loco paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> the one to the other, such be in names collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, because we haue no other tearms to cal them by, <hi>Plures enim sunt res quàm vocabula,</hi> such is the scarsity of our speech, that more things there be, than wee haue names to call them by; such be thy brothers line, so neere thine own as may be, we must not call them descendents, for confounding of lines, nor yet allow them that laterall libertie to make them out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward degrees, <hi>Laterall</hi> they be tearmed or <hi>Collaterall à latere,</hi> as much in effect as sideward of the side wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they be placed, as by the figure it may appeare and other descriptions in the treatise: but so neer they be the side, that they warme it, and be warmed by it, side by side, and bloud by bloud; and yet we must call them Collaterals, and yet I exhort thee beware of them, they be not forbidden expreslie, and by name by the law, the Leuiticall law I meane, no more thou shalt finde it forbidden expresly to marrie with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other persons of thy kinred besides, thou wilt not therfore say it is lawful, god forbid thou shouldst. This I haue red in the works of learned men, it is for
<pb facs="53"/>
bidden by the right of nature, it is forbidden, by the law that is written in euerie mans heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, it is forbidden by loue and charitie, the which we haue handled in this treatise before, it is forbidden by title and right of nigh kinred: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, many great things shalt thou finde, if thou loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest about thee, not forbidden expresly by the law that <hi>Moses</hi> made, and yet the same be forbidden by a certaine plaine expresse commaundement of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and consequently by the law of God: for what commaunded <hi>Moses</hi> from the Lord, as lawfull to be done, that was not expedient? Shall we seeke a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition then by name, for euerie person, and do the thing (if we finde it not) that is neither expedient nor honest? God forbid. I finde it written of <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose,</hi> that he affirmed plainlie, The lawe of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth that brothers children should marry, and yet I cannot finde it there expresly; the occasion grew by one <hi>Patern,</hi> that had a sonne by one woman, and a daughter by another, which daughter had a daughter, whom <hi>Patern</hi> would haue married to his sonne, the maidens halfe vncle, wherein consulting with <hi>Ambrose</hi> in this case, receiued this aunswere; I neither thinke nor iudge, saith <hi>S. Ambrose,</hi> that your bishop an holy man doth so much as looke after my sentence and iudgement in this matter, for if he had, he would haue written to me of it, and in somuch that he writeth not, he sheweth plainly that he iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this no matter to be doubted on: for what doubt may there be in this case, whether thy sonne and thy daughters daughter, or thy neece by thine owne daughter may marry together, seeing the law of God
<pb facs="54"/>
forbiddeth, that thy son should marrie with thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers daughter. And what (faith the same author) is moresolemne, accustomed, or more reuerentlie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, than the charitable kisse betweene vncle and neece, which he oweth to hir of duety, as to his daughter, &amp; she to him as to hir father? shalt thou then go &amp; make this innocent kisse of loue and charity, in which is none offence nor suspitiō of euil, to be suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, whilst thou intēdest such a mariage? as if he shuld say, Wilt thou betray (as <hi>Iudas</hi> did his maister) the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly law of nature, &amp; take away from thy dear pledges or children so deuout &amp; religious (a sacrament) he tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it, but a token of pure and naturall loue, as also he doth, wee may terme it stil.</p>
   <p>And touching the furthest distant of the persons we haue mentioned last, <hi>viz.</hi> Brothers children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in a maner, they be brothers and sisters, cōming all of one parent, grandfather grandmother, or both; but the second stocke of the tree, or figure of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanguinitie, in this treatise before, if it were for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, yet for the reuerence that they owe to the same parēts, <hi>Theodos</hi> the Emperour would haue them abstain from marriage the one with the other. But to leaue the Emperours law, there is a law of this land, (the Lord preserue it and the life of the same) this we haue touched in the diuision of this table hereafter; but there is a law, and this we haue touched too, the Lord write it in our minds and in our hearts, that he may be our God, and we may be his people.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>