<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Myles Couerdale vnto the Christian Reader, moste hartelye wysheth the continuall encrease of heauenlye taste and spirituall swetnesse, in the same assured saluation which commeth onely through Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108888_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19465</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5886</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108888</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Myles Couerdale vnto the Christian Reader, moste hartelye wysheth the continuall encrease of heauenlye taste and spirituall swetnesse, in the same assured saluation which commeth onely through Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certain most godly, fruitful, and comfortable letters of such true saintes and holy martyrs of God, as in the late bloodye persecution here within this realme, gaue their lyues for the defence of Christes holy gospel : written in the tyme of theyr affliction and cruell imprysonment</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rogers (ap—Rogers), Owen.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 46, 49-689, 5 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Myles Couerdale vnto the</hi> Christian Reader, moste hartelye wysheth the continuall encrease of heauenlye taste and spirituall swetnesse, in the same assured saluation which commeth onely through Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He more nigh that mens wordes &amp; workes approch vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most wholesome sayinges &amp; fruitful doings of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> old auncient Saincts &amp; chosē childrē of god (which loued not only to heare his word, but also to liue therafter) the more worthy are they to be estemed, embraced, &amp; followed. And therfore as we heare &amp; read of many godly, both mē &amp; wemen, whose cōuersatiō in old time was beautifyed w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> syngular giftes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy ghost (according as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribeth thē in the .xi. chap. to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hebrues) so haue we iust cause to reioyce, that we haue bene familiar &amp; acquainted w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> some of those, which walked in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> trade of their fotestep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which cause, it doth vs good to read and heare, not the lying legendes of fayned, false, counterfayted, and popish canonized saincts, neither y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> triflyng toyes &amp; forged fables of corrupted writers: but such true, holy, &amp; approued histories, monuments, orations, epistles &amp; letters, as do set forth vnto vs y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> blessed behauiour of gods deare seruaūtes. It doth vs good (I say) by such comfortable remēbraunce, conceaued by their notable writinges, to be conuersaunt with them, at the least in spirite.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> writing to one <hi>Nitia,</hi> and hauyng occasion to speake of letters or epystles, maketh mention of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Authour named <hi>Turpilius,</hi> whose woordes,
<pb facs="3"/>
(sayeth he) are these: a letter or epistle, is the thyng alone y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> maketh men present which are absent. For among those that are absent, what is so presente, as to heare and talke with those whom thou louest? Also, that noble Clarke <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasmus Roterodame,</hi> cōmendyng the booke of the Epistles or letters which <hi>S. Augustine</hi> dyd write, sayeth thus: by some of <hi>Augustines</hi> bokes we may perceaue, what maner of man he was being an infant in Christ. By other some, we may knowe what maner a one he was being a young man, and what he was being an olde man. But by thys onely booke (meaning the booke of the Epistles or letters) thou shalt knowe whole <hi>Augustyne</hi> altogether. And why doth <hi>S. Hierome</hi> or <hi>Erasmus</hi> saye thus? No doubt, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that in such writynges, as in a cleare glasse, we maye see and beholde, not onely what plentifull furniture and store of heauenly grace, wisedome, knowledge, vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, fayth, loue, hope, zeale, pacience, mekenes, obedience, with the worthy fruites thereof, almighty god had bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the same his most deare children: but also what a fatherlye care he euer hadde vnto them: how his mightye hand defended them: howe hys prouidence kept watch and warde ouer them: howe hys louyng eye loked vnto them: howe hys gracious eare heard their prayers: how he was alwaye myndfull of them, neuer forgat them, neither fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, nor forsoke them: how the armes of his mercye were streytched oute to embrace them, when soeuer they faythfullye tourned vnto hym: howe valiaunte also and stronge in spirite, howe ioyfull vnder the crosse, howe quyet and cheerefull in trouble he made them: what victorye of their enemyes, what deliueraunce oute of bondes and captiuitie, what health from sicknes, what recouerye from plagues, what plentye from scarcenesse: to bee shorte, what helpe at all nede and necessity he gaue and bestowed vpon them.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>By such lyke mounmentes also and writynges, it is manifest and playne, how the same deare children of God in their time behaued themselues, aswel towards hym, as also towardes their frendes and foes: yea what the verye thoughts of their hartes were, when they prayed (as their maner was incessantlye to doe) when they confessed their sinnes, &amp; complained vnto god: when they gaue thankes: when they were persecuted and troubled: when they were by the hand of god visited: when they felte, not onelye the horrour of death, the griefe of synne, &amp; the burthen of gods displeasure by reason of the same: but also the swete tast of hys great mercy &amp; eternal comfort through Iesus Christ, in theyr conscience. Of the which thinges, lyke as we may euidently perceiue rich and plentiful experience in the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uēly treasurie of that most excellēt boke which we cōmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cal Dauids Psalter: so hath not god nowe in our days, left hymselfe without witnesses: yea no more, then he dyd in other ages before vs: but of his aboundante goodnes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when the late persecutiō was most cruel, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies rage most extreme, he hath raised vp such zelous men &amp; women as (by the wonderful operation of hys holy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) of weake were made so valeant &amp; strong in him (aswel against all idolatry, superstitiō, false doctrine and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted religion, as against their own old blemishes &amp; sinnes) that they haue turned to flight, and cōfounded the whole rable of suche malicious papists, as were the persecutors and murtherers of them.</p>
   <p>Wherby they that list not stil to be blind, may plainlye behold and see, not onely the terrible iudgementes of God ouer &amp; against the wicked, but also his wonderful doinges mixt wit mercy in and towardes hys chosen: vnto whom, as vnto them that loue him, he causeth al things to worke for the best. So that with him, by the heauēly light of sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast faith, they see lyfe euen in death: w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> him, euen in heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="4"/>
&amp; sorrow, they faile not of ioy &amp; comfort: wyth hym e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in pouerty, affliction and trouble, they neither perish nor are forsaken. How els could they be so patiēt, so quiet of minde, so cherefull and merye in aduersitie and straite captiuitie: some beyng throwne into dungeons, vgsome holes, darke, lothesome and stinking corners: other some lying in fetters and chaynes, and loaded wyth so many i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons that they could scarcely styrre: some tied in the stocks wyth their heeles vpwarde: some hauyng their legges in the stockes &amp; their neckes chayned to the walle wyth gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets of iron: some both handes and legges in the stockes at once: sometimes both hands in, and both legges out: some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right hand with the left leg, or the left hand with the right legge fastened in the stockes wyth manicles and fetters, hauyng neither stoole nor stone to sitte on, to ease their wofull bodies withall:<note place="margin">These engines are called Skeuingtons giues, the forme &amp; maner wherof you shall see in the boke of Martyrs. Fol. 1651.</note> some standing in most painful engines of iron with their bodies doubled: some whypped &amp; scourged, beatē with roddes, &amp; buffeted with fistes: some hauing their handes burned with a cādel to trie their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or force thē to relente: some hunger pyned &amp; most mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serably famished. Al these torments &amp; many moe, euē such as cruel Phalaris could not deuise worse,<note place="margin">If these vnmerciful monsters had the reward of their ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny that Phalarts had, yet shuld they not haue so muche as they haue iustly deserued.</note> wer practised by the papists, the stout sturdy souldiours of Satan, thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityng in variety of tiranny and torments, vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Saints of god, as it is ful wel &amp; too well knowen, &amp; as many can testify which are yet aliue, and haue felte some smart ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Yea &amp; furthermore, so extremely were these deare ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes of god delt withal, that although they were moste desirous by their pen and writing, to edify their brethren, other poore lambes of Christ, &amp; one to comfort an other in him, yet were they so narowly watched and straitly kepte from al necessary helpes, as paper, inke, bokes &amp; such lyke, that great maruail it is how they could be able to write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of these or other so excellent &amp; worthy letters. For
<pb facs="4"/>
so hardly were they vsed (as I said afore) for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most part y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they could not end their letters begon:<note place="margin">Notwithstandyng al this cruel dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, they wrote verye manye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and fruitfull letters moe: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of sundry are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this boke which shall God willing, be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed hereafter, if they in whose handes they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, wil bring them to light.</note> sometime for lacke of ease, being so fettered with chaines, &amp; otherwise handled as you haue heard: sometime for lacke of light, when they could neither see to write wel, nor to reade their letters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: &amp; somtyme through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hasty cōming in of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kepers or officers, who left no corner nor bedstraw vnsearched: yea somtime they were put to so hard shiftes, that lyke as for lacke of pennes they were fayne to write with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lead of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> windowes: so for want of inke they toke their own blood, (as yet it remaineth to be sene) and yet somtime they were faine to teare &amp; rent what they had writtē at the hasty cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> officers.</p>
   <p>Thus, thus vnkindly, thus churlishly, thus cruelly &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally were euē they entreated &amp; handled, whose most notable &amp; godly writings are here set forth in thys booke. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which, &amp; such other monumēts, great cause haue we to praise god: which he himself hath preserued &amp; broughte to light, no dout by his sīguler great prouidēce, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> herby we beīg taught to haue his mighty mercy &amp; merciful working y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more in reuerēt &amp; thākful regard, might not onely consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what heauēly strēgth &amp; rich possessiō of cōstant faythe, of ardent zeale, of quiet patience, of peace &amp; ioy in the holy ghost, he vseth to arme thē, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> can find in their harts to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor al vngodlines both of doctrine &amp; life: but also to ioine w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thē our selues in such sort, that loking to Iesus our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, abiding y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> crosse &amp; despising y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shame, as they did for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ioy y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was set before thē, may w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> much quietnes of a good consciēce, end this our short course, to his glory, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of his church, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōfusion of Satan, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hinderaunce of al false doctrine, &amp; to our own eternal cōfort in the same our lord &amp; alone Sauiour Iesus Christ. To whō wyth the father and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy ghost be all honour, al glory, al thankes and all praise, world without ende. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>