<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE SIR George Barne Knight, Lord Maior of the Citie of London; and the right worshipfull the Aldermen his Brethren and assistants, peace and ioie in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Lightfoote, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108556_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05463</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15595</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108556</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE SIR George Barne Knight, Lord Maior of the Citie of London; and the right worshipfull the Aldermen his Brethren and assistants, peace and ioie in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Lightfoote, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The complaint of England : Wherein it is clearely prooued that the practises of traitrous papists against the state of this realme, and the person of her Maiestie, are in diuinitie vnlawfull, odious in nature, and ridiculous in pollicie. In the which they are reprooued of wilfull blindnes, in that they see not the filthines of the Romish gouernment: and conuinced of desperate madnesse, in that they feare not the mischiefe of Spanish inuasion: the former whereof is exemplified by the Popes practises both here in England, and abroad in other countries: the later by the Spaniards outrages, in his exactions raised vpon Naples, and his tyrannies executed in the Indies. Lastly the necessitie, equitie, and benefits of the late proceeding in iustice are set downe; with a friendly warning to seditious papists for their amendment; and an effectuall consolation to faithfull subiectes for their incouragement. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Lightfoot, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE SIR <hi>George Barne Knight, Lord Maior of the</hi> Citie of London; and the right worshipfull the <hi>Aldermen his Brethren and assistants,</hi> peace and ioie in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an <hi>axiome</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in philosophie, and a truth apparant in dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie experience, that small forces firmly vnited and cōpacted in one, grow to bee mightie in continuance of time: whereas matters of far greater moment being separated either by casuall diuision, or wilfull discord, are easily ruinated, and sodainly brought to confusion. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Nature in all her actions intending <hi>vnitie,</hi> buildeth her whole frame vpon the groundworke of sweete harmonie, and musicall concent: tempering the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in each seuerall body with such indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb facs="3"/>proportion, that albeit some one ouerrule the rest, yet it is not permitted to ouerthrow them: but they all by a secret <hi>sympathie</hi> &amp; mutual agreement, indeuour to support the one the others burden. But whensoeuer this <hi>vnisone</hi> is interrupted by iarring of the parts, then is Nature by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence rackt out of her course, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on insueth the subuersion of the whole. Seeing then <hi>vnitie</hi> is the marke whereat Nature aimeth, and the verie meane to preserue her woorkes: and seeing such thinges of all others doe chiefly promise perpetuitie, as draw neerest to the rule of Nature; it is an vndoubted consequent that those common wealthes haue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test likelihood of prosperitie, &amp; least cause of decaie, wherein concord is nourished, and dissension suppressed. Mitigation of punishment is a dangerous imboldening of malicious aduersaries; and obstinate purposes, vnles they be timely preuented by politike foresight, and restrained by speciall penaltie, are often times too late
<pb facs="3"/>repented, when in the end they burst out into vnlawfull practises, to the distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of publike <hi>vnitie</hi> and the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of common confusion. Therefore as the maintenance of <hi>vnitie</hi> is an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that conserueth the state: so is exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of iustice the golden piller that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth <hi>vnitie.</hi> The which prop so long as it shall stand in force (but it must stand in force so long as <hi>England</hi> will desire to rest in safetie) I hope the Traitrous intents of <hi>Englands</hi> and English enemies shall be vtterly frustrate, neither shall they haue so great cause to triumph for their victories, as she hath now iust reason to complaine of their trecheries. For by the cutting off, of putrified members the whole bodie maie be deliuered from perill: and by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding odious iarres, amiable <hi>vnitie</hi> may be retained. But if their hidden rancour be suffered inwardly to fester, and further to disperse it selfe, then it is greatly to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red least the contagion thereof breede a fouler maladie, then can bee cured with
<pb facs="4"/>an ordinarie plaister. In respect whereof your honors &amp; worships trauailes ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and seuerally imploied in these dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous times, as they argue a studious zeale and affectionate deuotion towards your naturall Prince and countrie: so doe they merit all titles of singular commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. The renowne of diuers your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors is with capitall letters so inregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred in the booke of <hi>Fame,</hi> that neither the darkesome vaile of <hi>Obliuion</hi> can ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shadow it, nor the forked sting of <hi>detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at anie time cancell it. In imitation of whose worthines if yee shall constantly proceede, as ye haue alreadie laudably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, it will appeere that vertue yet stoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not for age, and that common care is not brought a sleepe by priuate profit. This argument might minister ample matter of true discourse: but least my words should be wrested beyond the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of my thoughts, &amp; so attainted with suspicion of flatterie, I wrap that vp in si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence which I might very wel vtter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="4"/>anie impeachment of insinuation; omitting your industrious care for sifting out recusants, your diligent search for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of factions, your watchfull regard for appeasing of mutinies, your charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prouision for relieuing of Orphanes, with diuers other matters of importance greatlie behoofefull to the state of this Realme, &amp; properly incident to the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of good Magistrates. And seeing these are the daies wherein treason is coloured with religion &amp; malice armed with poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, I haue in this treatise detected the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Traitors, and vsed dissuasions by manifesting the dangers annexed to their proceedings. The which for that it is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the person of <hi>England</hi> whome yee haue oft assisted in extremities, I haue published vnder your L. and W. patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and offer the same to your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whom th'almightie protect with his power, and guide with his grace.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your L. and VV. at commaund,</hi> William Lightfoote.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>