<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Translator to the
Reader.</title>
           <author>Hartwell, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108820_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06339</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16805</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108820</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Translator to the
Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hartwell, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A report of the kingdome of Congo, a region of Africa : And of the countries that border rounde about the same. 1. Wherein is also shewed, that the two zones torrida &amp; frigida, are not onely habitable, but inhabited, and very temperate, contrary to the opinion of the old philosophers. 2. That the blacke colour which is in the skinnes of the Ethiopians and Negroes &amp;c. proceedeth not from the sunne. 3. And that the Riuer Nilus springeth not out of the mountains of the Moone, as hath been heretofore beleeued: together with the true cause of the rising and increasing thereof. 4. Besides the description of diuers plants, fishes and beastes, that are found in those countries. Drawen out of the writinges and discourses of Odoardo Lopez a Portingall, by Philippo Pigafetta. Translated out of Italian by Abraham Hartwell</title>
                 <author>Lopes, Duarte</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 217, 3 pages, 2 folded plates, illustrations (woodcut), maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>❧ The Translator to the
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Finde it true, that <hi>Sophocles</hi> writeth
in his <hi>Whipp-bearer Aiax,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:
Labor labori laborem
adfert, <hi>that is to say, Labour doth
breede labour vpon labour.</hi> For
after that the translation of the Booke,
contayning the Warres betweene the
<hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Persians</hi> written by <hi>Iohn-Thomas Minadoi</hi>
was published, diuers of my friends haue earnestly moued me
to be still doing somewhat, and to help our <hi>English Nation,</hi>
that they might knowe and vnderstand many things, which
are common in other languages, but vtterly concealed from
this poore <hi>Island.</hi> I haue aunswered some of these my friends
to their good satisfaction, and told them, that the weakenesse
of my body would not suffer me to sit long, that the houres of
my leasure were not many, vnlesse I should vnduetifully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraude
those to whome I am most beholden and bounden, of
that duty and attendance which I owe vnto them: and
lastly, that I had no great pleasure to learne or informe my
selfe of the state of other <hi>Nations,</hi> because I do not as yet suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
know the Estate of mine owne <hi>Countrey.</hi> Whereof
(I am verily perswaded) I may iustly auouch that which <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysses</hi>
protested of his <hi>Ithaca:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.
<hi>Then which poore Countrey
can I neuer see any sweeter.</hi> Among others that made


<pb facs="6"/>
these <hi>Motions</hi> vnto me,<note place="margin">M. R. Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luyt.</note> one there was, who being a curious
and a diligent searcher and obseruer of Forreine aduentures
and aduenturers, as by his good paines appeareth, came vnto
me to the house of a graue and learned <hi>Prelate</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. H. Castel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note>
where I lay in my returne out of <hi>Norffolke,</hi> and there made
the like request vnto me, and I the like answere vnto him.
But it would not satisfie him: for he sayd it was an answere
answerelesse, and it should not serue my turne. And presently
presented me with this <hi>Portingall Pilgrime</hi> lately come to
him out of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Congo,</hi> and apparrelled in an
<hi>Italian vesture:</hi> intreating me very earnestly, that I would
take him with me, and make him <hi>English:</hi> for he could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
many pleasant matters that he sawe in his <hi>pilgrimage,</hi>
which are indeed vncouth and almost incredible to this part
of <hi>Europe.</hi> When I sawe there was no remedie, I yeelded,
and euen (as the Poet saith) <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer.</note> I brought
him away with mee. But within two houres conference, I
found him nibling at two most honourable Gentlemen of
<hi>England,</hi> whome in plaine tearmes he called <hi>Pirates:</hi> so
that I had much adoo to hold my hands from renting of him
into many mo peeces, then his <hi>Cosen Lopez</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi>
was quartered. Yet <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>My second wits</hi>
stayed me, and aduised me, that I should peruse all his <hi>Report,</hi>
before I would proceede to execution: which in deede I did.
And, because I sawe that in all the rest of his behauiour hee
conteyned himselfe very well and honestly, and that he vsed
this lewd speech, not altogether <hi>exanimo,</hi> but rather <hi>ex vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio
gentis,</hi> of the now-inueterate hatred, which the <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi>
and <hi>Portingall</hi> beare against our <hi>Nation,</hi> I was so
bold as to pardon him, and so taught him to speake the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
toung.</hi> In which language, if you will vouchsafe to heare
him, hee will tell you many notable obseruations of diuers


<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Countreys</hi> and <hi>peoples</hi> inhabiting in <hi>Africa,</hi> whose
Names haue scarse been mentioned in <hi>England.</hi> As namely,
the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Congo,</hi> with all the <hi>Prouinces</hi> thereof,
the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Angola,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Loango,</hi>
the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Anzichi,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Mata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi>
the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Buttua,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Sofala,</hi>
the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Mozambiche,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loa,</hi>
the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Mombaza,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linde,</hi>
with the three great <hi>Empyres</hi> of <hi>Monomotapa,</hi> of
<hi>Moenemugi,</hi> and of <hi>Prete-Gianni.</hi> He will tell you the
seuerall <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Customes,</hi> the <hi>Climates</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratures,</hi>
the <hi>Commodities</hi> and <hi>Traffiques,</hi> of all these
<hi>Kingdomes.</hi> He will tell you the sundry kinds of <hi>Cattell,
Fishes</hi> and <hi>Fowles, strange Beasts,</hi> and <hi>Monstrous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi>
that are to be found therein: For <hi>Africa</hi> was alwayes
noted to be a fruitfull Mother of such fearefull and terrible
<hi>Creatures.</hi> He will tell you of great <hi>Lakes,</hi> that deserue the
name of <hi>Seas:</hi> and huge <hi>Mountaynes</hi> of diuers sorts, as for
example, <hi>Mountaines scorched with heat, Mountaines</hi>
of <hi>Snow</hi> proceeding of colde, <hi>Mountaynes</hi> of the <hi>Sunne,
Mountaynes</hi> of the <hi>Moone, Mountaynes</hi> of <hi>Christall,
Mountaynes</hi> of <hi>Iron, Mountaynes</hi> of <hi>Siluer,</hi> and <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes</hi>
of <hi>Golde.</hi> And lastly, he will tell you the <hi>Originall
Spring</hi> of <hi>Nilus,</hi> and the true cause of the yerely increase
thereof. In any of these poynts, if his Mouth shall happen to
runne ouer (as I hope, much it doth not) you must needes
beare with him, for he will challenge the priuilege of the
<hi>English</hi> Prouerbe, <hi>A Traueller may lye by authoritie,</hi>
and the old <hi>Greeke Agnomination,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<hi>Euery Pilgrime is not a Sooth-sayer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But to leaue this long <hi>Allegorie,</hi> which indeede is meant
of this Booke, and to come seriously and briefly to certaine


<pb facs="7"/>
faults, that some Readers may peraduenture finde therein, I
will do my best indeuor to satisfie them in such obiections as
may be made. And first, they will except perhaps against the
<hi>Methode</hi> of the <hi>Author,</hi> because he keepeth no continuate
<hi>Order</hi> in this <hi>Report,</hi> but leapeth from one <hi>Matter</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
without any coherence, like <hi>Marots Poeme,</hi> called <hi>Du
Coqual' Asne:</hi> and so maketh a <hi>Hotchpot</hi> of it. But herein
<hi>Pigafetta</hi> is not greatly to be blamed, who gathering this
<hi>Report</hi> out of the tumultuarie Papers of <hi>Lopez,</hi> and from
his vnpremeditated speeches, vttered by mouth at seuerall
times, could not so well reduce it into so exact a forme and
<hi>Methode,</hi> as curious wits do require. He is rather to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,
that hauing so rude and vndigested a <hi>Chaos</hi> to
worke vpon, he could frame so handsome a little world of it as
this is. If happily it be further vrged, that the Translator
should haue taken paines to cast him in a new <hi>Mould,</hi> and to
make his members hang proportionably one vpon another:
I must answere, that I neither do, nor euer did like of that
kinde of course. I was alwayes of this opinion (and therein I
do still dwell) that <hi>Authors</hi> should be published in the same
<hi>Order,</hi> in the same <hi>Termes,</hi> &amp; in the same <hi>Stile</hi> which they
themselues vsed. For how know I, what moued them to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
this <hi>Order</hi> or that <hi>Order,</hi> and to make choyce of one
word rather then of another? peraduenture the reason of
their so doing might proue to be so strong, as I doubt it would
not easily be ouerthrowne.<note place="margin">Style.</note> And touching <hi>Style,</hi> some are
so scrupulous and so nice, that they cannot abide to haue old
and auncient Writers to be published in <hi>Latin,</hi> vnlesse they
do imitate one of the <hi>Triumuiri</hi> of the <hi>Latin</hi> toung, <hi>Cicero,
Caesar</hi> or <hi>Salust.</hi> If all men should be of that humour, we
should be bereaued both of singular <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> and antique
<hi>Historie,</hi> which haue been written by men of no great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,


<pb facs="8"/>
as <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Friers,</hi> whome (though they were
very simple and meane, yet) it pleased God in the times of
ignorance, to vse as meanes to preserue vnto vs those <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents</hi>
of <hi>Antiquitie.</hi> And therefore I could wish, that
they might be published in their owne <hi>Style,</hi> and (as it were)
in <hi>Puris Naturalibus,</hi> yea though they write false <hi>Latin,</hi>
as some of them do. On the other side, some of our <hi>Critikes</hi>
are so <hi>Criticall</hi> and so audacious, that when they publish any
of the foresayd <hi>Triumuiri,</hi> or any other <hi>Classicall Author,</hi>
they will transpose, and omit, and foyst into the <hi>Text</hi> many
words and many <hi>conceytes,</hi> whereof the <hi>Author</hi> neuer
dreamed, as <hi>Eustathius</hi> and <hi>Seruius</hi> haue done vpon <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>
and <hi>Virgill.</hi> But if algates some <hi>Enthusiasme</hi> haue
come vpon our <hi>Critikes,</hi> that hath reuealed vnto them <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam
ex antro Trophonij,</hi> the certaintie of the <hi>Authors</hi>
writing and meaning, to be such as they haue confidently set
downe, let me be bold to intreate them, that they would muster
their conceytes in the <hi>Margine</hi> (if the <hi>Margine</hi> will hold
them: as I doubt it will not in this <hi>Hypercriticall</hi> world)
or else that they would reiect them (as some of them haue
done) to the later end of their publications, vnder the title of
<hi>Corrections, Castigations, Emendations, Animaduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
Variae Lectiones,</hi> or such like, <hi>Vt suo quisque v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur
iudicio &amp; sensu abundet,</hi> That euery man may vse
his owne iudgment, and abound in his owne sense. But <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta
Glossa quae corrumpit Textum. Cursed be that
Glosse that corrupteth the Text.</hi> And sory I am, that
some of our later <hi>Diuines</hi> haue erred in this point, euen in
translating the <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Another exception may be taken against the <hi>Paradoxes</hi>
that are maintayned in this <hi>Treatise,</hi> As namely, contrary
to the opinion of the old world, and of the auncient <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,


<pb facs="8"/>
That the two Zones, Torrida, and Frigida, are
both habitable and inhabited.</hi> But hereunto if the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi>
reasons here alleaged do not sufficiently answere, I do
referre them, that will not yeeld therein, to the excellent
Treatise of <hi>Iosephus a-Costa, de Natura Noui Orbis,</hi>
printed this last yeare, and composed by him in <hi>Anno</hi> 1584.
in which <hi>Theologicall</hi> and <hi>Philosophicall</hi> worke, he doth
at large both by good reasons and also by his owne experience
proue this his position to be true. And therefore I protest vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you, it was one of the chiefe <hi>Motiues,</hi> which moued me to
translate this <hi>Report,</hi> to the end it might be more publikely
knowen, that it was not the single fancie of one man, touching
the temperature of these two <hi>Zones,</hi> but also of diuers others
that by their owne trauell haue tryed the certayntie thereof:
among whome, this <hi>Lopez</hi> was one, who deliuered this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi>
in <hi>Anno</hi> 1588, being foure yeares after the <hi>Treatise</hi>
made by <hi>Iosephus-a-Costa.</hi> And I do not doubt, but that
within few yeares you shall haue it confirmed by many others
that are and haue been trauellers, who haue not as yet publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
their knowledge and trials in this behalfe. In the meane
time we do great iniurie to them that haue been alreadie so
desirous to acquaint vs with their labours, and to make vs
know as much as they know vpon their credites and honesties:
when in stead of shewing our selues thankefull vnto them for
the same, we skoffe and mocke at them, and confidently sweare
that they are lyers, and opposite to all auncient <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</hi>
But in a word, I will answere herein with an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Rhetoric▪ lib. 2.</note>
which <hi>Aristotle</hi> vseth, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. i. <hi>Siquidem in vsu est hominibus,
mentiri id quod credibile: existimare oportet &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium,
Incredibilia multa hominibus, contingere


<pb facs="9"/>
vera:</hi> which for the better vnderstanding I must paraphrase
in <hi>English:</hi> If it be an vsuall thing among men, that when
a thing is reported, which is very credible and like to be true,
yet afterwards it falleth out to be a starke lye: Then must we
needes thinke on the contrary, That many Reports or things
which are incredible, do in the end fall out to be true. In
which case, as <hi>Credulitie</hi> leaneth a little to <hi>Foolerie,</hi> so
<hi>Incredulitie</hi> smelleth somewhat of <hi>Atheisme.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Another Paradox is, <hi>That the heate of the Sunne
is not the cause of Whitenesse or Blacknesse in the
Skinnes of men.</hi> This <hi>Position</hi> in the <hi>Negatiue</hi> he may
safely defend against all <hi>Philosophers,</hi> by vertue of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
that he hath vouched in this <hi>Report,</hi> which in deede do
vtterly ouerthrow their <hi>Affirmatiue.</hi> But because neither
any auncient Writer before this age, nor he himselfe, hath
euer been able to declare the true cause of these colours in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
bodies, very honestly and modestly he leaueth it vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided,
and referreth it to some secret of Nature, which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
hath been knowne to God alone, and neuer as yet reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
to man. And therefore I do wish, that some sound <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
Philosopher,</hi> such as <hi>Fernelius</hi> that wrote <hi>De abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
rerum causis,</hi> or as <hi>Leuinus Lemnius de Occultis
Naturae miraculis,</hi> or as <hi>Franciscus Valesius de Sacra
Philosophia,</hi> would enter into the <hi>Closet</hi> of <hi>Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
to finde out the true <hi>Naturall</hi> cause thereof. In the
meane while I hold still with my <hi>Author</hi> in the <hi>Negatiue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The third <hi>Paradoxe</hi> touching the <hi>Amazones</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in this booke, I do not see, why it should be counted a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox</hi>
to beleeue, that there is such a <hi>Nation,</hi> considering
how many <hi>Authors</hi> both <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> both <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers</hi>
and <hi>Cosmographers,</hi> both <hi>Diuine</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,</hi>
haue acknowledged that <hi>Nation,</hi> and the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
wherein it inhabited. But our new Writers say, that
a little after <hi>King Alexanders</hi> death it was vtterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne
and quite extinguished. What? <hi>Vsque ad vnam?</hi>
not one of them left aliue? Certainely that depopulation must
needes proceede, either from the peculiar visitation of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties
owne hand, or else it was the strangest slaughter that
euer was heard of, that of a whole <hi>Nation,</hi> being so populous
as that was, there should not remaine some few, that escaped.
But yet suppose that some <hi>Hypsiphile,</hi> or <hi>Penthesilea,</hi> or
<hi>Thalestris,</hi> or some such other, did wisely conueigh hir selfe
away, <hi>cum Dijs Penatibus, cum Matre, &amp; cum filia,</hi>
and being guided by some happie <hi>Venus,</hi> arriued in a farre
remote <hi>Region,</hi> and there obserued the customes and fashions
of their owne <hi>Natiue Countrey:</hi> Might not these three,
together with some other women that were desirous of Rule
and gouernment, and allured by them to be of their <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi>
might not they (I say) in processe of time, (for it is a long
time since <hi>Alexander</hi> died) breede a <hi>New Nation</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazones,</hi>
although we neuer heard, in what <hi>Climate</hi> they
remained? Yea it may be for any thing that I know, this latter
generation might growe againe to be so populous, that they
could send foorth <hi>Colonies</hi> from them into other places, and
so plant themselues in diuers <hi>Countreys.</hi> For I heare that
there are of them about <hi>Guiana,</hi> and heere in this <hi>Report</hi>
I reade that some of them serue in the warres of the <hi>King</hi> of
<hi>Monomotapa.</hi> And I hope that in good time, some good
<hi>Guianian</hi> will make good proofe to our <hi>England,</hi> that there
are at this day both <hi>Amazones,</hi> and <hi>Headlesse men.</hi> And
thus much for the <hi>Paradoxes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The last exception which may be made against this booke,
is the discourse of the <hi>Conuersion</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of
<hi>Congo</hi> to <hi>Christianitie,</hi> which is amplified, and set out with


<pb facs="10"/>
such <hi>Miracles</hi> and <hi>Superstitious Vanities,</hi> as though it
had been plotted of purpose for the glorie and aduancement
of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Adherents:</hi> Wherein, because it doth
concerne matter of <hi>Religion,</hi> I will deale more warily and
seriously to satisfie my <hi>Reader.</hi> True it is that the <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi>
of <hi>Congo</hi> were all <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> vntill
they entertayned Traffike with the <hi>Portingales:</hi> Among
whome, one <hi>Massing Priest</hi> became a meanes to conferre with
a <hi>Noble Man</hi> of <hi>Congo</hi> concerning <hi>Christianitie,</hi> who
taking liking thereof, as being a <hi>Man</hi> of good inclination and
disposition, was very desirous to be further instructed. The
<hi>Priest</hi> being wise, tooke oportunitie to make way for his
<hi>Countreymens</hi> traffike, and also for planting of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Faith</hi> in that <hi>Region,</hi> It may be in hope to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
and aduanced in a new established <hi>Church,</hi> as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
our trauelling <hi>Priests</hi> vse to do, that wanting mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
or being vpon some occasion discontented at home,
do leape ouer sea into forreine partes, not for the desier which
they haue to gaine <hi>Christian Soules,</hi> or to preach the <hi>Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,</hi>
but to procure to themselues either dignities or wealth.
But I do not say that this <hi>Priest</hi> was such a one: for I neither
haue reason nor authoritie so to say. For he sent ouer into
<hi>Portingall</hi> for some fellowes to helpe him, who being come
into <hi>Congo,</hi> laboured so much, that in time the <hi>King</hi> and
his people consented to become <hi>Christians.</hi> Then did the
<hi>Portingall-Priests</hi> bestirre themselues nimbly in <hi>Baptising</hi>
the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Queene,</hi> the <hi>Lordes,</hi> and the <hi>Commons.</hi>
They built <hi>Churches,</hi> they erected <hi>Altars,</hi> they set vp <hi>Cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi>
and at last brought in a <hi>Bishop.</hi> And all this was done
(I must needes confesse) with all pompe and solemnitie, after
the <hi>Romish</hi> maner, which in deede is so plausible, as it is able
to allure any simple Man or Woman, euen with the very sight


<pb facs="10"/>
thereof. Yet will I not denie, but that these <hi>Priests</hi> had a good
intent, and for my part I do beleeue that they were in <hi>bona
fide,</hi> because they conuerted a great part of the <hi>People,</hi> not
to <hi>Poperie,</hi> but to <hi>Christianitie,</hi> the true foundation of all
<hi>Religion.</hi> And this <hi>Action,</hi> which tendeth to the glory of
<hi>God,</hi> and may be a notable example to the <hi>World,</hi> of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the like, shall it be concealed and not committed to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie,
because it was performed by <hi>Popish Priests</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish
meanes?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philip. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> God forbid. <hi>S. Paule</hi> maketh mention of
diuers that preached <hi>Christ, Some of enuie and strife,
and not purely,</hi> and <hi>Some of loue and good will.
What then? Yet Christ is preached, whether it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
pretence, or sincerely, and therein do I ioy.</hi> So these
Men are not to be regarded, whether they preached <hi>Christ</hi>
for vaineglory, and for maintenance of <hi>Poperie,</hi> or of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
minde: but certaine it is, that <hi>Christ</hi> was preached by
them,<note place="margin">Marke. 9.</note> and therein ought we to ioy. In <hi>Marke</hi> and in <hi>Luke,
S. Iohn</hi> saith to <hi>Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luke. 9.</note>
      <hi>Maister, we sawe one casting
out Deuils in thy Name, but we forbad him, because
he followeth not with vs. Forbid him not</hi> (saith Christ)
<hi>for he that is not against vs, is with vs.</hi> If we see a <hi>Turke,</hi>
or a <hi>Iewe,</hi> or a <hi>Papist,</hi> vpon what pretence soeuer, seeke to
drawe any to <hi>Christ,</hi> or to driue the <hi>Deuill</hi> of <hi>Ignorance</hi>
out of any, let him alone, forbid him not, mislike him not,
for in that point hee is not against vs, nay peraduenture hee
may become one of vs.<note place="margin">Numb. 11.</note> In the <hi>booke of Nombers,</hi> word
was brought to <hi>Moses,</hi> that <hi>Eldad and Medad prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied
in the hoast. And Iosua sayd, My Lord Moses
forbid them. But Moses sayd, Enuiest thou for my
sake? Would God that all the Lords people were
Prophets.</hi> And are we angrie, or shall we finde fault, that
the <hi>Portingall Priests</hi> being <hi>Papists,</hi> should be reported to


<pb facs="11"/>
haue conuerted the <hi>Realme</hi> of <hi>Congo</hi> to the profession of
<hi>Christian Religion?</hi> Shall we enuie them in their well
doing? I for my part do earnestly wish with all my hart, that
not onely <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> but also all <hi>Sectaries,</hi>
and <hi>Presbyter-Iohns men</hi> would ioyne all together both
by word and good example of life to conuert the <hi>Turkes,</hi> the
<hi>Iewes,</hi> the <hi>Heathens,</hi> the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and the <hi>Infidels</hi> that
know not <hi>God,</hi> but liue still in darknesse, and in the shadow
of <hi>Death.</hi> What a singular commendation would it be vnto
vs, if it might be left in <hi>Record,</hi> that we were the first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerters
of such a <hi>Nation,</hi> and such a people, and first brought
them to the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> and the true profession of his
glorious <hi>Gospell?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus I haue (gentle <hi>Reader)</hi> laboured to satisfie such
scruples, as may arise in thy minde touching this <hi>Treatise:</hi>
which if it shall breede either profit or delight vnto thee,
I shall reioyce to my selfe: If not, I shall be sorie that
I haue employed my precious time so idly.
Farewell in <hi>Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Abraham Hartwell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>