<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVL AND
MY MVCH HONOVRED
good friend Sir Tho. Sauyle, sonne to the
noble and worthy Patriot Sir Iohn Sauyle
of Houly in Yorkshire.</title>
           <author>Cooke, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108652_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19251</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5664</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108652</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVL AND
MY MVCH HONOVRED
good friend Sir Tho. Sauyle, sonne to the
noble and worthy Patriot Sir Iohn Sauyle
of Houly in Yorkshire.</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Yet more vvorke for a Masse-priest</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheffard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 42, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVL AND
MY MVCH HONOVRED
good friend Sir Tho. Sauyle, sonne to the
noble and worthy Patriot Sir Iohn Sauyle
of Houly in Yorkshire.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Booke hath been printed and
reprinted, yet without my name,
though not without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of many that it was mine,
who now do father it. Its reported
there is an Answer made, or in
making to it. Some tell me, they
haue seene it in print: some tell
me, it is but yet in writing. The truth is, I hitherto can
learne no certainty: but time will trie the truth. Perhaps
both the reports are like that whereof I am certified by
the Printer, viz. That the Author of <hi>More worke for a
Masse-priest</hi> is turned Romane Catholicke. A lie, as
shamelesse as that which is spread farre and neare of that
worthy last Lord Bishop of London his reconcilement to
Rome. For discouering whereof, I haue added some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
tending to the further shame of Popery, to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="3"/>
Impressions: which I make bold to dedicate vnto
you, as to the worthiest of my friends, next vnto the most
reuerend Father in God <hi>Tobias</hi> the Lord Archbishop of
York his Grace, and your noble father. To them, I owe
my selfe, and more: to you, I owe much for kindnesses
already receiued, and liue in hope to be further indebted
hereafter, euen in respect of the care which, I doubt not,
but you will haue of the common good of the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
and especially of the Parish wherein I liue. For I trust,
that as in time you are to succeed your father in faire and
large possessions; so presently you will shew your selfe to
be his sonne, in succeeding him in doing iustice. Whereof
you haue giuen some proofe already, (though yet you haue
but liued a small time amongst vs) gaining much credit
vnto your selfe thereby, and putting the country in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
of great things, when it shall please God your
priuate occasions will suffer you to settle your selfe among
vs. Which I pray may be shortly. And so with remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
of my humble dutie and seruice, I commend this
little Pamphlet vnto you, and you to the gracious bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of God, resting alwayes</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worsh. at cōm.
Alexander Cooke.</signed>
      <dateline>Leeds in York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,
<date>April 4.
1622.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>