<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the christian Reader encrease of those especiall grates, which may moste further his comfort in Christ.</title>
           <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108342_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21655</idno>
           <idno type="STC">796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the christian Reader encrease of those especiall grates, which may moste further his comfort in Christ.</title>
                 <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exhortation of Salomon. By H.A</title>
                 <author>H. A. (Henry Arthington)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the christian Reader encrease</hi> of those especiall grates, which may moste further his comfort <hi>in Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eelooued in him, who looued vs moste dearely when wee were all lost: Jf you call to remembrance what I haue published in my pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiefull Seduction, you shall finde from page 53. to the latter end of page 55. That J make mention of two sortes of people, whome Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan very groslie seduceth: The one by alluring them to professe poperie or some false Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The other to polute the true profession, by a prophane and loose conuersation: of which number are all carnall Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, promising in that place, that I will proclaime open warre against bothe and all other aduersaries whilst I liue. Since which time (and yet during my moste iust restreint) I tooke occasion to peruse the holy Bible, to arme mee more strongly against all such enemies: and comming by course vnto the notable speaches of <hi>Dauid,</hi> (which is the main ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of this discourse following) considering the same to contein ma<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter of fit instruction against all papists and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane persons, and withall reuoluing my minde what necessarie doctrine I had once heard a Preacher of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel to produce publiquely out of the sāe. I did foorthwith pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare to indite and write what good matter I could conceiue
<pb facs="5"/>
and gather out of the same, and so (by Gods helpe) did fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish without direction from any Person or any other meanes (saue my weake memorie and the booke of God du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of my imprisonment) the which for some cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses (as a byrd vnfligge) hath hetherto lyen by mee, as vnfit to flie abroade.</p>
   <p>But now by the prouidence of the Almightie is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be published for the vse of such as shall bee willing to heare or read the same, wherin the Lord knoweth &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth witnes (that I seeke not my selfe) but his honour onely who hath preserued mee, and their edification whome I haue offended any kinde of way: Jn which respect, J hope the courteous Reader will be are with the style (though for want of art or eloquēce it seeme but harsh) for I professe not learning, but plain dealing in all my indeuours, to profit ther by the simpler sorte, which if by perusing thou shalt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then haue I gotten my first request. The second is this, That as thou shalt feele it to chaunge thy minde and lyfe, to refourme either in any good measure, thou wilt not forget to giue God his due, the only prayse of all, because from him alone all good gifts proceede <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17.</p>
   <p>Namely for his extraordinarie fauour still extended towards mee, in moouing all my good Creditors in London, to whome I stand deeply exdetted by suretieship, not only to remit mee all interests with charges, and to take their principalles onely at my handes after two shillings in the pound yearely till they bee satisfied, (If I liue so long:) But which is more, and so much as may be admyred of all men, wheras one of my creditors (vnt whome only I was a suretie, would not be pacified with his principall interest and charges at my hands, after the former rate for princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palls only but either would haue it after twentie pound <hi>per Annum,</hi> or els my bodie shoulde lye in prison. The which extremitie rather then my good creditors would suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to incurre: they haue all condiscended to rebate so
<pb facs="5"/>
much yearly of their due, to supply my want and satisfie his minde, whome mercie would not mooue (the Lord lay it not vnto his charge) neither forget to recompence their kindenes, that are so willing to extend mercie, as they haue learned of their heauenly father. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.35.36.</p>
   <p>To conclude I beseech thee (good Reader) to pray for mee the Lords vnwoorthiest seruant, that as my late fall, did bring to iust grief and offence to many: so my vprysing by dayly signes and tokens of true repentance, may bring double ioy to all the redeemed that shall either heare or see the same. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy vnfeigned wel-willer.</hi> Henry Arthington.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>