<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Publisher to the Reader.</title>
           <author>R., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108558_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05467</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15599</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108558</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Publisher to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A worke of the Beast or A relation of a most vnchristian censure, executed vpon Iohn Lilburne, (novv prisoner in the fleet) the 18 of Aprill 1638 : With the heavenly speech vttered by him at the time of his fuffering [sic] . Uery vsefull for these times both for the encouragement of the godly to suffer, and for the terrour and shame of the Lords adversaries</title>
                 <author>Lilburne, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>‘Richt Right’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Publisher to the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Tender hearted Reader.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>OF The wicked it is truely said in <hi>Iob.</hi> their <hi>Light shalbee Put out:</hi> Now wee see, in a <hi>Candle,</hi> beeing almost extinguished, that after it hath glimmered a while, it rayseth some few blazing flashes, and soe suddenly vanisheth.</p>
   <p>To speake what I thinke, my minde gives me, that the Lord is now vpon extinguishing the bloody Prelates out of our Land. For whereas they have not, in some late yeares shewed the cruelty which they did before, but now increase in persecution; me thinkes this is a cleere fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going signe, that (like a <hi>snuffe</hi> in the <hi>socket</hi>) their end and ruine is at hand.</p>
   <p>I write this, to have thee the more patient, contented, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when thou either hearest, seest, or readest of their barbarous crueltie; besure their condemnation sleepeth not, but when their wickednes is full, I say when they haue once filled up the measure of their iniquity the which I trust they haue allmost don) then will the Lord send back these <hi>locusts</hi> to the <hi>Bottomlesse pitt,</hi> from whence they came.</p>
   <p>In the meane time feare not their faces, but stand in the trueth, and let Gods house and his ordinances bee deare to thy soule, And know, that as the Lord gaue strength to this his Servant to suffer joyfully for Christs cause; soe he will to thee and me and all others of his saints, if he count us worthy to be called thereto.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine if thou be Christs, and a hater of the English Popish Prelates. <hi>F. R.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>