<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>C., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108516_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19175</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5587</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108516</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>C., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The palinod of Iohn Colvill : wherein he doth penitently recant his former proud offences, specially that treasonable discourse lately made by him against the vndoubted and indeniable title of his dread soueraigne Lord, King Iames the sixt, vnto the crowne of England, after decease of her Maiesty present</title>
                 <author>Colville, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charteris, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>BEhold heere (gentle Reader) a strange spectacle of a man tormented vvith the rack of his ovvne conscience, vvho as he vvas not affrayed to spevv out of his knovvledge and vvilfullie, the gall and venome of a malitious heart, against his sacred Prince, of vvhom he had in most bountifull manner recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedmanie Princelie favors, so novv doth he not stick resolutelie to proclaime before the heavens and the earth, that he is forced to eat vp that same filthie vomit, and to speak more bitterlie a thousand folde against himself, then anie man else could: and so much the more, as he vvas more privie to the faults, and angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes of his ovvn soule, then any others could be. The vvork I haue published as it came to my hands, vvithout adding any thing ther to, or diminishing ought therfrom, or altering any part therof pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming that the same should neither be offensiue to his Maiestie, for vvhose privat satisfaction it vvas first penned, or displeasing to M. Iohn Coluill the authour therof: vvhom thou mayest as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure thy self vpon the credite both of honorable and honest persons to haue purposelie vvritten and signed the same vvith his ovvne hand &amp; most humblie vpon his knees, in the presence of the Erles of Argyle &amp; Craufurd to haue deliuered it to the L. Archbishop of Glasgovv, his Maiest. Ambassadour in France, most earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly craving, that his Lordship (vvithout any intercession for him) vvould only vouchsafe to present it to his Maiesties vievv, not in any hope that in reason he could conceiue of any favour or par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don from his highnesse thereby, but rather to disbur then his ovvn fraughted conscience, pressed dovvn vvith a vvaight of sorrovv, heauier than the mountain Aethna. Which reasonable petition vvhat stonie heart could denie to him, vvho seemes to think no shame to be a sufficient reuenge taken of himself, vvho vvith so</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>high a hand, had reuyled the annointed of the Lord▪ &amp; doth novv by this, as vvith a loud trumpet proclaime to all subiects,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>Discite Iustitiam moniti. &amp;c.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And trulie (good Reader) notvvithstanding hypocrisie is of all sinnes the moste close and secrete, and most hardlie remooued, and that (as he doth confesse of himself) that he hath had a most subtile and vndiscernable vaile of it: yet remember the common saying, that the man runnes far vvho neuer returnes, and that in charity vve are to conceyue and hope his repentance to be vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vvhich vve may boldly and confidētly affirme, if to this good beginning he shall add of his feruent zeale, to beare testimonie to the truth, a plaine and perfite discouerie of all manner of plots &amp; treacheries, intended against the Kings Maiesty, by himself or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to his knovvledge, vvhich the great King of Kings vvould neuer haue to be concealed: &amp; lykevvise of all manner of persons subiects or aliens, vvho hath either of malice to his Maiesty, or loue to himself, bene contriuers, entysers, prouokers, counsellers, adoers, or assisters to any such mischeuous enterprises, as directly or indirectly could subuert, or anie vvise harme his Maiesties Royall person, croun, title, honour, state, or dignity, and by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence might dravv vvith them the confusion and ruine both of the Kirk and Common vveale. To vvhich, no doubt, all his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest friends vvill earnestlie incite him, and his conscience (if it be sinceare) vvill prick him, and for vvhich all good and religious persons vvill highlie commend him, seing heerby God shall be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, his Maiesties safetie and honour continued, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie preserued, and the Kirk fully satisfied in his harty conuersion and repentance. </hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Farevvell. <signed>A. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>