<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY LO∣uing Country-men, but espe∣cially to the Merchants of London.</title>
           <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108815_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14600</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16784</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108815</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY LO∣uing Country-men, but espe∣cially to the Merchants of London.</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The merchants new-royall-exchaunge : framed at Roan, and brought ouer to be set vp in England. Or, A law-booke for English merchants</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Country-men, but <hi>espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Merchants of London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Olde is the Merchaunts Cape of <hi>Buon Esperanze,</hi> he sailes about the world onely to recouer it: for Riches is the brightest star, whose heighth, Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke takes, to direct it selfe by. Yet doth this Tree of Enter-course bring foorth other sweete and delectable fruites: It is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether planted in the garden of the <hi>Hesperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> onely to beare golden Apples: No: It carries other frutages, almost as faire: For the vertue of Comerce, is to discouer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: the pleasure of it, to be familiar with Nations: the exercise of it, to get politique experience: the benefit double: for both the forrein &amp; the free-borne are crowned with wealth by it: the black Indian, &amp; the white Englishman, sill their purses by one &amp; the
<pb facs="3"/>same bargaine. So that the Straunger (how much Salt-water soeuer parts him and vs) is a husband-man in our owne Country: hee reapes the fruites of our earth as plenteously and as freely as wee our selues: Is acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the blessings of our Land, and tastes them as we do. And though he cares not to vnderstand our Language, yet is he curious to vnderstand our Ladings: looking rather into the bottomes of our Shippes, than on the brauery of our Parlours. And this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse which hee deriues from vs, we doe backe againe reduce from him: So that it is but a neighbourly borrowing and lending betweene Kingdomes. And all these good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Triumphes are brought in by Traffick, Merchants being the chiefe and Maister-workmē that giue thē beautie &amp; Illustratiō. To speake in praise of whose dignitie, were idlely to extoll that, whose worthines none can call in question. Sure it is, that all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales florish where they prosper, and wither where they are pluckt vp: Insomuch that Kings haue bin, &amp; at this day are of the Societie, the greatest number of their houres being spent in the exercise of Merchandize.</p>
   <p>The affection therefore which I carry to all you (my deare Country-men that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse this Art of Negotiatiō:) together with an Ardor and zeale to see the Merchants of this Kingdome, grow vp into a liuely Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb facs="3"/>Bodie, as they do now in <hi>France</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Dominions: haue giuen me a boldnes and willingnes to entertaine this labour. It is a <hi>New,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Royall-English-Exchange,</hi> which I would build for you: The Moddell of it, I confesse, I founde drawne to my hand in <hi>France,</hi> you all are acquainted with it: Set then all your hands to the Frame, and helpe to reare it vp in England. Cast not your eyes on the rough pieces which I haue hewē out, but on the purpose, for which they are thus wrought vpon. And albeit perhaps, my ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norāce &amp; vnpractised familiaritie with these French phrases, which here speak their Law in broken English, may make you cast aside this booke in the reading, yet doe not cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the matter. Admit that in turning ouer the leaues, you should finde no other stuffe then this, that the French King (imitating therein, the Greeks and auncient Romanes) hath iustituted such a Burse or Guild-house, for Merchants: and ordained three such Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, &amp;c. Why euen this should be enough to intice you (whō it concernes) to buy this paper-commoditie: and hauing founde this measure of <hi>Hercules</hi> his foot only, not to cease til you haue got so much cunning, as to draw out the whole symetrical proportiō of all his body. You haue many helpes to do it: you haue the voices not only of forren Christian Kinges speaking in your behalfe, But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of our owne most gracious and godly
<pb facs="4"/>Soueraign. The penne (with which he hath not many yeares since, signed such like Royall Priuiledges, for the benefit of his Countrey <hi>Scotlande,</hi> and the Merchaunts thereof,) holds yet ynck enough in it, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow the like Princely grace vpon you the Merchants of England. Be humble petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to his Maiestie for it. It is no Innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: It is no vpstart attempt: other Realmes haue broken the yee: follow you their steps, that a way may lye smooth before you.</p>
   <p>There are many Spurres, that (if they were clapt to your sides) would make you to keep company in this beaten path. They whose money-bags are shrunke together by reason of that Siluer Consumption, which tedious Lawe-suites haue brought them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, can rise vp as sittest Orators to perswade you to this enterprise. The wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of many a sometimes-wealthy Citizen, (who hauing scapte shipwracke on the seas, hath notwithstanding bin cast away on the land, by intangling his estate in the nettes of the Lawe) may with his cryes awaken you, to preuent the like future mischiefes, that (without prouidence) may fall vppon your selues. Be wise therefore: A medicine is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, and (by the tryall of other Cities that haue taken the phisicke) approued to be so wholesome, that it cannot choose but doe
<pb facs="4"/>London much good. Do but entertaine (for a taste) these considerations: Of what fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are all your controuersies? Flow not all your variances frō the troubled head of your Accounts? Are not your suites (which now and then many yeares cannot weare out) drawne from your bargaines and barterings when they be not perfectly wrought? What hands therfore may better vntye those knots than your owne among whome they are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened? Who are fitter to conduct you out of those windings &amp; turning-Mazes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the whole estates of many wealthy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants are often-times halfe-lost, than your selues, that haue best experience in those causes, by reason of your daily and hourely treading in those pathes?</p>
   <p>Suruey therefore all the roomes of this beautifull French building: yet I do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne you, neither thinke I it conuenient, that you purchase the same, in all respects as it is to be seene standing heere: but by this patterne, you may easily fashion such ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, more apt for your selues, and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the condition of our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
   <p>Do but study this Merchants <hi>Law-Booke,</hi> with <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      </hi> same carefulnes that you peruse your Debitor &amp; Creditor, and you shal not need so often to goe to Law. It is a learning will
<pb facs="5"/>much aduance you and your posterities, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it therefore. And thus wishing safe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors to your Shippes when they are foorth, and to your Soules the land of heauen, when they are bound thither, I bid you farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>