<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IL∣LVSTRIOVS PRINCE, ESME, Duke of Lenox, Earle of March and Darnley: Lord of AVBIGNY Torbolton Methuen: Baron of Settrington, &amp;c. Knight of the Noble Order of the GARTER.</title>
           <author>Cleland, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108068_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18977</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5396</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108068</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IL∣LVSTRIOVS PRINCE, ESME, Duke of Lenox, Earle of March and Darnley: Lord of AVBIGNY Torbolton Methuen: Baron of Settrington, &amp;c. Knight of the Noble Order of the GARTER.</title>
                 <author>Cleland, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A monument of mortalitie : vpon the death and funerals, of the gracious prince, Lodovick, late Duke of Richmond and Lenox: Earle of New-castle, and Darnley, &amp;c. ... By Iames Cleland Doctor in Diuinitie and domestick chaplaine to his Grace</title>
                 <author>Cleland, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rounthwait, Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE IL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVSTRIOVS PRINCE, ESME, Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> Earle of March and Darnley: Lord of AVBIGNY Torbolton Methuen: <hi>Baron of</hi> Settrington, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Knight of the Noble Order of the GARTER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honourable LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oe here <hi>A Monument</hi> of mans <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> erected in haste, to represent the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Funerals,</hi> of my good Lord, your Noble Brother; whose heroicke <hi>LIFE</hi> requires more lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb facs="3"/> to build <hi>A MAVSOLE</hi> to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Memorie. Meane time J offer vnto your <hi>Grace,</hi> these mournefull Spoiles, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Trophees, as most proper and due vnto you; his Successour and Jnheritour; in assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance you will accept them fauourably, and with your gracious aspect, giue them, a speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-power, as the Sunnes reflection did on the Image of <hi>Memnon.</hi> The Ghostly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of his Effigie I know, cannot affright your <hi>Grace,</hi> who is ready and prepared at all howers for Death; nor (I hope) will the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentation of it, renew your griefe, as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephs</hi> particoloured Coate, caused sorow to his father <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Caesars</hi> shirt to <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purnia:</hi> But that you will looke and behold in it as <hi>a Mirror</hi> to see your <hi>Fate,</hi> as your <hi>Fortune;</hi> and so esteeme me for euer one of</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Aprill 20. 1624.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Graces Most humbly Deuoted in all dutifull obseruance, IAMES CLELAND.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>