<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>VVYLLYAM TVR∣NER VNTO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108032_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14057</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24363</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108032</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>VVYLLYAM TVR∣NER VNTO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A new dialogue vvherin is conteyned the examinatio [n] of the messe : and of that kynde of priesthode, whych is ordeined to saye messe: and to offer vp for remyssyon of synne, the body and bloud of Christe agayne</title>
                 <author>Turner, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hill (Hyll), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>VVYLLYAM TVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NER VNTO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGHE IT BE not belōgyng vnto my</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessyō to dispute of maters of diuinite, whyche am a Phisitian: yet extreme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessite requirīg I am cōpelled to do in thys kynde of war, as coblers, shoma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers, masons, carpēters, &amp; al other mē of handy occupations are compelled to doo, when theyr cytie is beseged, to take wepens in theyr handes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come warriers, whych haue had lytle or no experiēce of war before, when as theyr cytie is beseged. Whych: yf that (when a cyty is beseged) euery mā that is a faythfull citizen oughte to do the beste that he can, to defende hys cytye, and to ouercū the enemies of the same: who wyll blame me, which am no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor of diuinitie, when as the cyty of God, whereof I am a sworne Citizen,
<pb facs="3"/> is beseged, wyth so great hostes of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyshe warriers: yf I play in this tyme of nede, the diuine warryer, to defēde the forsayd cyty, and endeuore my selfe to ouercome the enemyes of the same. The enemies of our city, ar they, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che take by violēce away y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godly and necessarie ordinaūces of our cyty and would by force thurst into our cyty, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of theyr awn makīg, cōttary vnto the lawes of our lawmaker which buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded our city, &amp; dyed for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> liberty of the same. Suche enemyes, ar the Byshop of Rome, and all Popyshe Prelates and preistes, whyche mangle and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe, yea, rob and many wayes deface the mooste comfortable cōmon seale of our saluation and redemptiō: the holy Sacramēt of Christes body &amp; bloude, and in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stede of the same, set in a mere mannes inuention, a certayne Popish playe, whych they call the meritorius Messe, bearyng vs in hande that, that they can doo wyth it as muche as our redemer Christ coulde do w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hys most
<pb facs="3"/> blessed passiō, which thyng I iudge to be greatly to the dyshonour of Christ, that is that our most cōfortable cōmō seal of our lybertie, and redemption, should be māgled and robbed, and for the moste parte of the hole yere, taken from vs, and that the worke of a man should be made equall with the worke of our Lorde and lawmaker whych is both God and mā: I could do no lesse, but wryte thys booke, to defende the blessed ordynaunce of our Lorde and redemer, and wrastle a lytle wyth the wycked mannes ordynaūces, to helpe to dryue them out of the churche oure cytie, and to restore the ordynaunce of our sauyour into the church agayn. I know that many wyll be offended, and take it very greuously, that I shoulde wryts of thys matter, and I loke for none other, but some shal cal me knaue and heretyke for my laboure taken in thys matter. Some wyll there be also of Sathans syde, whyche neuer can be satiate wyth bloud, whych wyll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre
<pb facs="4"/> to haue my bloude, as dyuers in Englande, at thys daye, yet lyuynge haue done, God forgiue them. And the same, yf that theyr crueltyes were not repressed and holden downe wyth the hyer powers, whych ar manteyners of al truth and honesty, would not leaue alyue in thys realme one of my iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vse ether to wryte or to preach agaynst such mānes inuencions, as at thys tyme, I do wryte agaynst: but I care not for these horsleches, trustynge that he that hath so ofte delyuered me frō the handes of myne enemies, wyll either saue me from them at this tyme also, or elles, yf it be hys pleasure that I shal lose my lyfe for his names sake, I shall be sure to fynde it agayn. But yf there be any man that of a conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce had agaynste me and thynke that I holde any false opinions in thys boke or any other booke and woulde haue the amendement of me and not my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction yf they be learned, let them wryte agaynste me, and I shal answer
<pb facs="4"/> them or elles yf I can not, recante it that I haue wrytten. In the meane season I woulde desyre the vnlearned whyche erre by reason of ignoraunce and not of malyce, that they woulde cease from raylynge agaynste me, tyll that theyr chefe champions haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed my booke, and haue perceyued that I wyll not recante. Thys would I also requyre of learned mē yf it coul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be obteyned. I answered wythin these seuen yeres a certayne learned man of Englande and confuted as well as I could, hys boke but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto all honestie and learnyng, perceyuynge that he was not able to answere to my booke, in euery booke that he wrote afterwardes agaynst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men rayled and scoffed agaynste me by name. Should learned mē play suche partes in a chrysten kingdom? I thinke that it were mete that he that is learned &amp; opēly in wrytīg or in pulpit speaketh agaīst any mā shuld ether be
<pb facs="5"/> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to confute hys opinions that he rayleth agaynst, or elles should be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled openly to cry hym mercy, whom he hathe sklaundered. Yf thys were brought to passe, we shold haue fewer raylers in Englande then we haue.</p>
   <p>Therfore haue I sette my name vnto thys boke that yf thou thynke that I haue wrytten herein, any thynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst God or hys word, thou mayest knowe to whome thou shouldeste wryte. Almyghty God graunte to the ignorante, knowlege, and to them that haue knowledge, to lyue thereafter. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>