<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>O THE RIGHT Honorable, Sir Henry Mountague, Lord Chiefe Iustice of England, and his thrice honoured Lady, all encrease of honour and true happinesse.</title>
           <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108664_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19288</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5698</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>O THE RIGHT Honorable, Sir Henry Mountague, Lord Chiefe Iustice of England, and his thrice honoured Lady, all encrease of honour and true happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The cry and reuenge of blood : Expressing the nature and haynousnesse of wilfull murther. Exemplified in a most lamentable history thereof, committed at Halsworth in High Suffolk, and lately conuicted at Bury assize, 1620</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wright, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 63, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>O THE RIGHT Honorable, Sir <hi>Henry Mountague,</hi> Lord Chiefe Iustice of England, and his thrice <hi>honoured Lady, all encrease of honour</hi> and true happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing it hath pleased your good Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to giue life to this poore Infant, by that gratious breath of yours, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you prepared the guitlie deseruedly to their death: Pardon (I beseech you) my boldnes in committing it to bee fostered vnder your Honorable Patronage, who already haue a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the better part thereof. Long haue I bene desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to approue my selfe vnto your honour, in what poore measure I haue bene able: not only in respect of many fauors vndeseruedly receiued from your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Lady in my former afflictions: but especially in regard of your Lordships gratious clemencie, in releasing a poore distressed neighbour, at my request: whose follie by how much the more it prouoked your honours iust displeasure, by so much the greater was your benignitie in remitting his offence. And
<pb facs="3"/>
therefore, obseruing your meekenes extended to so vndeseruing, I haue bene the rather emboldned to put my selfe, and these poore labours vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert thereof, that so the Church of God may more warrantablie entertaine, and make better vse of this discouerie, being commended vnto them vnder such iustifiable protection: and the Countrie may more earnestlie pray for yours honours happie returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, for the full discouery and censure of what yet lies hidden, concerning this most hellish and execrable murther. Among whom my selfe also vnfaynedly wait Gods holy prouidence herein: and shal not cease to cōmend your honour in my best de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions vnto the God of Iustice, to continue your Lordship in all health and happines, not only to the finishing of this worke, so worthily proceeded in hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, but also to the perfiting of your saluation, in his feare, in a full discharge of this great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable calling hee hath placed you in. And so I commend your honour with your gratious Ladie to the grace of God.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my house in White-crosse streete <date>this 24. of <hi>August.</hi> 1620.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Resting in the Lord at your Honours, and the Churches seruice.
THO. COOPER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>