<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108929_Bo1_4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06450</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108929</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A spiritual doctrine : conteining a rule to liue vvel, vvith diuers praiers and meditations. Abridged by the Reuerend Father Levvis de Granada of the holie order of preachers. And deuided into sixe treatises, as is to be seene after the prefaces. Nevvlie translated out of Spanish into English</title>
                 <author>Luis, de Granada</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 208, 229-397, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT the treatise that heere ensueth, serue princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallie for such, as begin to serue God in Religion, yet neuertheles al the contents thereof, se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e as vvel alsoe for al those, that trulie and vvith al theire hart giue them selues to the seruice of our Lord, as in the beginning of this booke vvas mentioned. But that vvhich ought heere to be aduertised is, that <hi>the end of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian life,</hi> to vvhich ar ordeined al Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundments and counsels, and al statutes &amp; voues of Religion, <hi>is,</hi> as th' Apostle saieth, <hi>Charitie.</hi> VVhich although it be so, yet doe vve not, in the beginning of this treatise, straite vvaies speake of this end, but of that, vvhich apperteineth to him, vvhoe
<pb n="255" facs="129"/>taketh vppon him to instruct a nouice, nevvlie com out of the vvorld, vvith such inclinations and vvicked customs, as he bringeth from the same. For he that hath this office, must cheefelie at end to destroye and mortifie such euil habites, and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and to plant in theire place al those vertues that be contrarie to them.</p>
   <p>For euen as the Carpenter, vvhich preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to furnish the timber, for building of a palace of som great lord, first of al cutteth avvaie the barks of such trees, as be brought from the vvoode, &amp; then doth savve, square, and polish them, vntill they be fit for his purpose; so likevvise the good maister of nouices, and he that desireth to becom the temple and dvvelling place of God, must vnderstand, that first he must cast out of his soule, al the vvicked and peruerse customs vvhich he bringeth from the vvorld, and then must adorne and beutifie the same, vvith the vvoorks of vertues. And this thing vvhich is the end of him that bringeth vp a nouice, is also a meanes to obteine the true end of the lavve, vvhich is Charitie, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath ben saied. For vvhen the passions be once mortified, and vertues planted in theire place; Charitie remaineth as the ladie and Queene of a man: for as our sovvle is a
<pb n="256" facs="130"/>spiritual substance, so is she a frind of spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things. Neuertheles the affections of this life dravve her dovvnevvards, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her from flying vp to heauen, vvhere she hath her neast.</p>
   <p>Heerehence it is, that as a stone, vvhich by force of som other thing is holden in a higher place, then his nature requireth, as soone as the impediments, that held it, be taken avvay, straite vvais falleth dovvne to the center, vvhich is his natural place: in like manner, vvhen the disordred passions of oure soule be once mortified and subdued, vvhich she hath to the things of this vvorld, she sudainlie, being holpen vvith the grace of God, lifteth her self vp to heauen, vvhich is the proper place of her abode.</p>
   <p>This is then the reason, vvherefore so greate account is made heere of the morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of our passions, because these be the chaines, vvhich hold our soule bound, &amp; hinder her from flying vpvvards. Vertues also be necessarie together vvith this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, because they be the instruments, vvhich Charitie vseth in alther vvoorks; no othervvise then our sovvle vseth her faculties, and naturall povvers in all her functions.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>