<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE CONTEY∣NING THE ARGVMENT OF THIS TREATISE, VVITH THE CAVSES mouyng the Author to wryte the same.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108494_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05354</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15507</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108494</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE CONTEY∣NING THE ARGVMENT OF THIS TREATISE, VVITH THE CAVSES mouyng the Author to wryte the same.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise tovvching the right, title, and interest of the most excellent Princess Marie, Queene of Scotland, and of the most noble king Iames, her Graces sonne, to the succession of the croune of England : VVherein is conteined asvvell a genealogie of the competitors pretending title to the same croune: as a resolution of their obiections. Compiled and published before in latin, and after in Englishe, by the right reuerend father in God, Iohn Lesley, Byshop of Rosse. VVith an exhortation to the English and Scottish nations, for vniting of them selues in a true league of amitie</title>
                 <author>Leslie, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Loyselet (L’Oiselet), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 1, 13-71 leaves, folded plates (woodcut), genealogical table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>A PREFACE CONTEY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING THE ARGVMENT OF THIS TREATISE, VVITH THE CAVSES mouyng the Author to wryte the same.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE deepe prouidence of Almightie God, who of nothinge created all thinges, most euidently in this poynt showeth it selfe, that by his power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable he hath not onlye created all thinges, but by the same power, hath also endewed euery liuyng creature, with a speciall guyft &amp; grace to continue, to renewe, and to preserue; eache his owne kynde. But in this consideration, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man kynde, amonge and aboue all earthly thinges, hath a pearlesse prerogatiue of witt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: wherewith he onlye is of God graciously in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued and adourned.<note place="margin">Man by the guyft of vvitt &amp; reasō hath a greate fresight of thinges to come.</note> For by theese excellent guiftes and graces of witt and reason, he doeth not onlye prouide for his present necessitie and sauegarde (as doe naturally, after their sort, all brute beastes, and euery other thinge voide of reason) but also, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnantlie discoursinge from cause to cause, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie applyeng their seuerall courses &amp; euentes, he gayneth a greate foresight of the daungers and perilles that many yeres after may happen, either to him selfe, or to his Countrey: and then by diligence and carefull prouision doeth inuent some apt and meete remedies, for the eschewinge of suche mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, as might outragyously afterward occurre. And the greater the fear is of more imminent mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief: so muche more care, and speedier diligence is vsed to preuent and cutt of the same.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="10" facs="10"/>And it is most certaine, by the confession of all the world, that this care (whiche I speake of) ought principally to be imployed of euerie man (as opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie serueth) to this ende, that therby the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Prince may be kept whole and sound: the publik weal of his countrey assured: and the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peace &amp; tranquillitie of bothe preserued.<note place="margin">Subiects ought to loue their kinge, and to knovv the heyr apparent to the Croune.</note> For the obteining whereof, as there are many braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of policie to be desired: so one special parte is for subiectes, louinglye and reuerentlye to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and obedientlie to serue their Soueraigne, which for the time hath the rule and gouernement: the next, to foreknowe to whome they owe their alleageāce, after the deceasse of their present prince and Gouernour. VVhiche being once certain, and assuredly knowen, procureth (when tyme doeth come) readie and seruiceable obedience, with great comfort in the mean while, and afterwarde vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal reast and quietnesse of all good Subiectes: as on the contrary part, throughe discord, variance, and diuersitie of mindes and opinions, about a Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sour, the matter groweth to faction: and from factiō bursteth out to plain and open hostilitie: wherevpō foloweth passing great perilles, and oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable alterations and subuersions of the plublick state.</p>
   <p>For the better auoyding of suche and lyke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences (albeit at the beginning Princes rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned, not by descent of blood and succession,<note place="margin">VVhy all the vvorld, almost, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth suc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cession of princes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than election.</note> but by choyse and election of the worthiest) the world was for the most part constreyned to reiect and abandon election: and so oftentimes in stead of a better and woorthier, to take for their Gouernour, some certain issue &amp; ofspring of one family, though otherwyse perhappes not so mete. VVhich defecte is so supplied, partly by the greate benefit of the
<pb facs="11"/>
good reast and quyetnesse that the people vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally enioye by this course of succession: and partly by the industrie and trauail of graue and sage perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, whose counseil Princes doe vse in their affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: that the whole world, in a manner, these many thousand yeres, hath embrased successiō by blood, rather than by election.</p>
   <p>And all politike Princes wanting issue of their own bodies to succede them, haue euer had a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care &amp; foresight (for auoyding of ciuil dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that the people allwayes myght knowe the true and certain heyr apparent of the Croune: spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when there appeared any lykelyhode of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of opinions, or factions to ensue, about the true and laufull succession in gouernement.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The care of English kinges to haue the successour to be knovvn.</note>This care and foresight doeth manifestly appear to haue bene not only in manye Princes of forain Countreis, but also in the kynges of England, aswell before, as after the Conquest: namely in S. Edward, kyng of England, that holie Confessour, by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and appoynting Edgar Atheling, his nephews fonne,<note place="margin">Flores hist. anno <hi>1057</hi>
      </note> to be his heyre: as also in kynge Richard the first: who, before he interprised his Iourney to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,<note place="margin">Richard Chanon of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ī Londō</note> assembled his Nobilitie and Commons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and by their consentes declared Arthure, sonne of his brother, Duke of Britain, to be his next heir and Successour of the Croune. Of whiche Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thure,<note place="margin">flores hist. anno <hi>1190</hi> Poli. l. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> as also of the sayd Edgar Atheling, we will speake more hereafter.</p>
   <p>This care also had king Richard the second, what time by authoritie of Parlament he declared for heir apparent of the Croune, the Lord Edmond Mortymer, that Maried Philip daughter and heyr of his vnkle Leonell,<note place="margin">Polid. l. <hi>20.</hi>
      </note> duke of Clarence. And (to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend to later times) the late kyng Henry the eight shewed (as it is knowen) his prudence and zelous
<pb n="11" facs="11"/>
care in this behalfe, before his last voyage in to Fraunce.</p>
   <p>And nowe, if almightie God should (as we be all, bothe prince and others, subiecte to mortall chaunces) once bereaue the Realme of England of their present Queene: the hartes and mindes of men being no better, nor more firmely setled and stayed towardes the expectation of a certain succession, than they seme now to be: then woe &amp; alas, it woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth my very hart, euen once to thinke vpon the imminent, and almost ineuitable perilles of that noble Realme, being lyke to be ouerwhelmed with the raiging, &amp; roaring waues, &amp; stormes of mutuall discorde, and to be consumed with the terrible fire of ciuil dissention.</p>
   <p>The feare whereof is the more, by reason that already in these later yeres, some flames of this horrible fire haue sparkled and flushed abroad: &amp; some part of the rage of those fluddes haue beaten vpon the Englishe shores: I mean the hote conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hath there bene sturred in so many places, and among so many persones: Of bookes also di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersed abroode, so many wayes fashioned &amp; fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as either depraued affection peruersely lusted, or zelous defense of truthe sincerely moued men.</p>
   <p>Seing therfore, that there is iust cause of fear, and of great daunger lykely to happen, by this va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of mennes myndes and opinions, so diuersely affected, aswell of the meaner sort of menne, as of greate personages: I take it to be the parte of euery naturall Englishe man, &amp; of suche as fauoure them, to labour and trauaile (eache man for his possibilitie, and for suche talent as God hath gyuen hym) that this so imminent a mischiefe may be in conuenient time preuented.</p>
   <p>VVe see what, witt, policye, paynes, and charges
<pb facs="12"/>
men employe, with dammes, weares, and all kynde of ingenious deuises, to prouide, that the sea or other riuers doe not ouerflowe or burst the bankes, in suche places, as are most subiecte to suche daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. VVe knowe also, what politike prouision is made, in many good Cities and townes, that no daungerous fires do aryse through negligence: and that the furie therof (if any happen) may speedilye be repressed with diligence. VVherein Augustus the Emperour, among other his famours actes, is woorthely commended &amp; honored, for appointing in Rome an ordinary wache of seuen companies in seuerall places, to preuent suche mischiefes, as come by fyre: being hereunto induced, by reason that the Citie was set on fire in seuen seuerall places in one daye. And shall not then euery man, for his part and vocation, haue a vigilant care and respect to extinguishe and quenche fuche a fyre alreadye bursten owt, as may (if the matter be not wyselye looked vnto) subuert, distroy and consume, not one Citie onlye, but also a whole Realme &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye?</p>
   <p>VVhiche to suppresse, one ready and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouse waye (as I thinke) is, that the Countrey men &amp; people of that nation may throughly vnderstand and knowe, from time to time, in what persone the right of succession of the Croune of that Realme doeth stande and remayne. For now, many men, partly through ignorance of the sayd right &amp; title, &amp; partly through sinister persuasion of some lewd pamphlets (whereunto they haue too lightly giuen credit) are seduced and caried away quite from the right opinion and good meaning, whiche once they had conceiued, and from the reuerence and duetie, that they other wyse woulde, and shoulde haue.</p>
   <p>VVhiche corruption of Iudgement and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="12" facs="12"/>
I doe hartely wishe to be plucked out of the hartes and mindes of men: and shall in this Treatise, doe my best indeuoure, with moste strong reasons and prooses, to remoue the same: not presuminge vpon my selfe, that I am better able than all others this to doe: but vpon duety and zeal to open a waye fot the knoulege of trueth, whiche by so many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct meanes is restreined, obscured, and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tde: after reading and vewing of suche bookes, and the argumentes therof, as haue bene set forth by the aduersaires to the contrarie, (whiles I was in England, Ambassador for my most gratiouse So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne ladye, the Quene of Scotland) I attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted this woork, not vnrequested of some noble personages, then of great accompte: nor without the aduise, counsail, and Iudgement of some, verie skillfull in the customes, lawes, and statutes of that Realme. VVherein I verily hope to showe suche good matter, for euident demōstration of the truth, as semeth to me sufficient to satisfie euery honest and indifferent persone: and able to persuade all such as are not obstinatly bent to their own partiall affections, or not gyuen ouer to some sinister mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and factiouse dealing.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>