<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST CHRISTIAN KING OF FRANCE AND PO∣LONIA, HENRIE the third of that name.</title>
           <author>Primaudaye, Peter de la</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108252_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05094</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15233</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST CHRISTIAN KING OF FRANCE AND PO∣LONIA, HENRIE the third of that name.</title>
                 <author>Primaudaye, Peter de la</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French academie : wherin is discoursed the institution of maners, and whatsoeuer els concerneth the good and happie life of all estates and callings, by preceptes of doctrine, and examples of the liues of ancient sages and famous men: by Peter de la Primaudaye Esquire Lord of the said place, and of Barree, one of the ordinarie gentlemen of the Kings Chamber: dedicated to the most Christian King Henrie the third, and newly translated into English by T.B</title>
                 <author>La Primaudaye, Pierre de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 659, 670-769, 768-812, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST CHRISTIAN KING OF FRANCE AND PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LONIA, HENRIE the third <hi>of that name.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, if we credit the saying of <hi>Plato,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths begin then to be happy, when Kings exercise Philosophie, and Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers raigne. The wise man speaking more d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uinely, exhorteth kings to loue and to seeke after wisdome, that they may raigne vpon earth rightcously, and in heauen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally. And truly from wisedome and philosophie, as from a liuely fountaine, floweth the gift of gouerning by good lawes and good example, of defending by prowesse, and of nourishing by wisedome and prouidence, which are the bands of all perfection requisite in an excellent and absolute prince, that desireth to gouerne his kingdome according to pietie and iustice. These three great and excellent gifts depending of God, as euerie other grace doth, one of those meanes whereby he vseth most commonly to inrich them that haue the raines of worldly gouernment in their hand, is to imprint in their harts a loue and desire of learning and sciences. But bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they cannot so perfectly vnderstand them, by reason of their great and burden some charge, as priuate men may, who quietly enioying the fruit and benefit of their kings labors, addict themselues to no other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, their maiesties are so much the more pricked forward to loue, to inquire after, and to honor such their subiects, as are best able to set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies those vertuous and learned instructions that are drawen out of the fountains of arts and disciplines. This mooued <hi>Antigonus king</hi> of Macedonia to write thus to <hi>Zeno</hi> the philosopher: <hi>I am assured that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell thee in the goods and fauour of fortune, and in the renowne of such things, but I know withall, that thou art far aboue me, and goest beyond me in that true felicitie, which consisteth in the knowledge and discipline of studies. Therefore I desire ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly that thou wouldest come vnto me: wherein I pray thee denie me not, that I may enioie thy conuersation and companie, as well for mine owne profit, as for the profit of all the Macedonians my subjects. For he that instructeth a prince, doth also profit as many as are vnder his charge.</hi> This selfsame loue of knowledge was the cause, that all the festiuall ornaments of that great louer of vertue <hi>Ptolomie Philadelphus</hi> king of Egypt, were graue questions as well of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic
<pb facs="9"/>
as of phlosophic, which he propounded to be handled and concluded by those learned men, whom he ordinarily maintained in his traine. Sir, the example of these two noble kings shining wholy in you, who greatly loue and fauour learning, and the professors thereof, and open the gate of that holie and vertuous discipline, which was so much cherished by ancient men, that they might daily be instructed the better in the dutie of their charges, doth promise to your good subjects and vassals, that by the grace of God they shall see vnder your raigne, the euill of those sini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster effects defaced, which haue issued from these long troubles and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill wars. Whereof all men haue conceiued a more certaine hope, bicause they see, that you labor with a holie zeale and good affection, to restore pietie and iustice to their former strength and beautie, which were in a maner buried in France: and that you haue gloriously crowned that worke, which that great king <hi>Francis</hi> your grandfather did happily begin, to the end that arts and sciences might flourish in this kingdome. The diner of that prince of famous memorie, was a second table of <hi>Salomon,</hi> vnto which resorted from euerie nation such as were best learned, that they might reape profit and instruction. Yours, Sir, being compassed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with those, who in your presence daily discourse of, and heare dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed many graue and goodly matters, seemeth to be a schoole erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to teach men that are born to vertue. And for my selfe, hauing so good hap during the assemblie of your Estates at Blois, as to be made partaker of the fruit gathered thereof, it came in my mind to offer vnto your Maiestie a dish of diuers fruits, which I gathered in a Platonicall garden or orchard, otherwise called an ACADEMIE, where I was not long since with certaine yoong Gentlemen of Aniou my companions, discoursing togither of the institution in good maners, and of the means how all estates and conditions may liue well and happily. And although a thousand thoughts came then into my mind to hinder my purpose, as the small authoritie, which youth may or ought to haue in counsell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst ancient men: the greatnes of the matter subject, propounded to be handled by yeeres of so small experience: the forgetfulnes of the best foundations of their discourses, which for want of a rich and happie memorie might be in me: my iudgement not sound ynough, and my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession vnfit to set them downe in good order: briefly, the consideration of your naturall disposition and rare vertue, and of the learning which you receiue both by reading good authors, and by your familiar commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with learned and great personages that are neere about your Maiestie (whereby I seemed to oppose the light of an obscure day, full of clouds and darknes, to the bright beames of a very cleere shining sunne, and to take in hand, as we say, to teach <hi>Minerua)</hi> I say all these reasons being but of too great waight to make me change my opinon, yet calling to mind manie goodlie and graue sentences taken out of sundry Greeke and Latine Philosophers, as also the woorthie examples of the liues of ancient Sages and famous men, wherewith these discourses were inri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, which might in delighting your noble mind renew your memorie
<pb facs="10"/>
with those notable sayings in the praise of vertue and dispraise of vice, which you alwaies loued to heave: and considering also that the bounty of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> that great Monarke of the Persians was reuiued in you, who receiued with a cheerfull countenance a present of water of a poore laborer, when he had no need of it, thinking it to be as great an act of magnanimitie to take in good part, and to receiue cheerfully small pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents offered with a hartie and good affection, as to giue great things li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally, I ouercame whatsoeuer would haue staied me in mine enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise. For I assured my selfe thus much of your bountifull &amp; roiall great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (which I craue in most humble maner) that you would measure the gift and offer of this my small labor, not according to the desert thereof, or by the person of one of your basest seruants and subjects, who presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in vnto you, but according to the excellencie of those things, which you shall see handled in this Academie, and according to the seruiceable and most affectionate desire, wherewith I dedicate and consecrate both goods and life to your seruice. I beseeth God, Sir, to preserue your Maiestie in great prosperitie, increase of honor, and continuance of a long and happie life. At Barre in the moneth of Februarie, 1577.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most humble and most obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient seruant and subject,
Peter de la Primaudaye.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>