<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108377_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15351.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108377</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The relection of a conference touching the reall presence. Or a bachelours censure of a masters apologie for Doctour Featlie. By L.I. B. of Art, of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Lechmere, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 377, 388-393, 396-600, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was (when I liued in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and I think it is still) the custome for him who defends in Deuinitie, to make first a <hi>Supposition,</hi> wherein such as come to heare that exercise, may see the <hi>State of the Questiō</hi> which is to be disputed. By this meanes the <hi>Defendant</hi> laies his Cause open to a faire tryall; and diuers Auditors not yet perfect in the knowledge of such matters, are better inabled to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand and vnderstanding to iudge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and his <hi>Opponent</hi> that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to perswade the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
   <p>I was thinking to conceaue my Preface in that manner, like a <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position;</hi> &amp; it had beene to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
<pb facs="3"/>
considering that some may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to see this Booke or <hi>Conference,</hi> who being catechized by Puritās, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knew the true <hi>State of the Question</hi> betwixt vs and them in the point of the <hi>Reall Presence.</hi> But those with whō I am to deale, will not permitt such a discourse; excepting, that it is against I know not what lawe.</p>
   <p>My intention is not to write a Booke of the <hi>Blessed Sacrament:</hi> that Argument deserues a better pen; and is excellentlie treated by diuers wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Catholike Deuines: but to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the iust honour of the defenders of it, traduced &amp; scornefullie jeered by a <hi>Precisian,</hi> on the behalf and by the consent of Doctour <hi>Featlie.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se nicenes shall not hinder me from doing that which doth confessedlie appertaine to the <hi>Sustentants</hi> part.</p>
   <p>And yet I meane withall, to keepe my self punctuallie to the matter, without running out into new; for that were to make the busines infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: or, bringing Arguments for our <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net;</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
for they with whō I deale would then report that I chang parts, and pretending to be a <hi>Defendant</hi> come a <hi>Disputant.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Doctor Featlie in a Challeng of his,<note place="margin">In his Challēg to M. Fisher.</note> resembles a Controuertist to a <hi>Sawier,</hi> who, till he hath gonne thorough, keepes himself to the same line: and imputes vnto his Aduersarie that he neuer pierced into the heart of any Controuersie. Whereas himself (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Featlie I meane) was the man that moued the <hi>sawe</hi> out of the line; and ranne into an other distinct matter, when he was not able to giue satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the former, which had beene the Cōtrouersie betwixt thē 2. Their disputation was, of a <hi>Catalogue of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> in all ages; and he, leauing that, challengeth his Aduersarie to dispute of <hi>Communion in both kinds.</hi> Which is a way to runne ouer Controuersies; but not to make an end of Controuersies. Logicians nūber it amongst the faults of a Disputant. It is a tacite yeelding of the cause.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>I haue taken (a Ministers impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie made me,) the <hi>Sawe</hi> into my hands; and am, if we regard the Controuersie, vpon the vpper side: my Aduersaries (being still in errour) be in the pit. The lines, Featlie drew: they be his Arguments; deliberatlie chosen, by him, for the best; these, which I am to meddle in. If they do not leaue pulling, wee shall in time come to the heart of this Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie. So they keepe themselues to their owne <hi>lines.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The matter of the Conference was, <hi>not Transubstantiation, but the Reall presence onlie. So my Lord of Chalcedon</hi> did expresse<note n="a." place="margin">Supra pag. <hi>7.</hi>
      </note> himself; and Master Featlie to the same purpose, <hi>Doctor Smith,</hi> saith<note n="b." place="margin">D. Feat in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. pag. 288.</note> he, <hi>distinguishing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt the Questions of Reall presence and Transubstantiation, determined the point in Question to be this, whether the bodie and blood of Christ were trulie and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiallie in the Sacrament vnder the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of bread and wine?</hi> My Lord Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the affirmatiue: <hi>videlicet,</hi> that it is
<pb facs="4"/>
there <hi>trulie</hi> and <hi>substantiallie:</hi> that is to say, <hi>according to the substāce of the thing.</hi> Master Featlie vndertooke the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, <hi>videlicet</hi> that it is not there tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and substantiallie,<note n="c." place="margin">Feat. pag. 289</note>
      <hi>not according to the substance of our Sauiours naturall bodie</hi> and blood.</p>
   <p>The words of <hi>Institution,</hi> which Feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie did obiect, be these, <hi>This is my bodie;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matt. 26</note>
      <hi>this is my blood &amp;c.</hi> which wordes he saies, must needes be taken in a sence that makes against the <hi>Reall presence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In this <hi>proposition</hi> or enunciation, <hi>Hoc est corpus meum, this is my bodie;</hi> (It is the like of the other wordes, <hi>Hic est sanguis meus, this is my blood</hi>) there is to be considered, the <hi>subiect;</hi> the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate,</hi> or attribute; the <hi>determination</hi> of the predicate; and the <hi>copula</hi> or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of idētitie. Four things, in the four words. The Subiect is, <hi>Hoc;</hi> the Predicate is <hi>Corpus;</hi> the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, <hi>Meum;</hi> the <hi>copula,</hi> the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be <hi>Est.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Subiect or first word, <hi>Hoc;</hi> doth not of it self, import bread ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="5"/>
then <hi>bodie;</hi> or <hi>bodie,</hi> rather then bread, it is indifferent. <hi>Significat</hi> (saith the Doctour of the Schooles) <hi>substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in communi, sinc qualitate: id est, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma determinata. It signifieth a substance in common without the qualitie, that is, the determinate forme.</hi> Suppose a chalice before me, and that I point towards it, saying <hi>This is</hi>—I may, to make vp the proposition, say <hi>gold,</hi> or <hi>wine,</hi> or <hi>blood;</hi> without changing the first word <hi>This.</hi> If I adde, <hi>blood;</hi> it contracts and determines the subiect, <hi>This,</hi> (which before was vncontracted and vndetermined,) to one particular thing. if I saie <hi>wine,</hi> it contracts it to an other. if I saie gold, it is contracted to a third. <hi>This is blood. this is wine. this is gold.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The word <hi>Est</hi> is a <hi>verbe</hi> substantiue, that signifies identitie, or conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion; which connexion or identitie cannot be conceaued without the extreames identified or connected, which be the thinges signified by the <hi>subiect</hi> and the <hi>predicate.</hi> And the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
<pb facs="5"/>
of the <hi>subiect</hi> to the <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute,</hi> and the <hi>attribute</hi> to the <hi>subiect,</hi> be founded it it. Whence it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that it is not possible to know what the Subiect <hi>determinatlie relates vnto,</hi> (being of it self indetermined,) till the predicate or attribute be also knowne because vntill then, neither the <hi>terminus,</hi> nor the <hi>ratio fundandi</hi> (the connexion,) is knowne. The same <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be</hi> or <hi>copula,</hi> doth also <hi>consignifie the time</hi> for which the connexion is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised; which time presupposing the connexion, for it is the <hi>modus</hi> of it, (and may varie, the connexion perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, <hi>Petrus,</hi> est, fuit, erit, <hi>albus.</hi>) doth presuppose likewise both the extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. This is manifest, (to him that lookes well on it,) because it presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth the connexion; which conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion doth presuppose the saide ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames as before hath beene obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <hi>Ipsū Est</hi> (saith the<note n="d" place="bottom">Ipsa igitur secundum se dicta verba, nomina sunt, &amp; significant aliquid: constituit enim qui dicit, intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum; &amp; qui audit quiescit. Sed si est, vel non est, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum significat: neque enim signum est rei, esse vel non esse. Nec si hoc ipsum <hi>Est</hi> purum dixeris; ipsum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim nihil est. Consignificat autem compositionem quandam, quam sine compositis non est intelligere. <hi>Arist.</hi> 1. <hi>de Interp. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Vide Commentatorem, Ibidem.</hi>
      </note> Philosopher)
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>consignificat compositionem quandam, quam sine compositis non est intelligere. the word Est, Is, doth consignifie a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne composition, which cannot be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood without the things compounded.</hi> So then, by the intention of <hi>Art,</hi> the <hi>copula de praesenti</hi> doth signifie the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of the subiect and attribute<note n="e." place="bottom">Infra pag. <hi>484.</hi>
      </note> for <hi>that instant</hi> wherein both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames are so vttered, that both (not one onlie) may be conceaued.</p>
   <p>The word <hi>Corpus</hi> signifies a<note n="f." place="bottom">
         <hi>Vide</hi> S. <hi>Thom.</hi> de Ente &amp; Essent. c. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>bodie;</hi> &amp; by the word <hi>meum,</hi> it is determined to the speakers, our Sauiours, bodie. so likewise in the other forme, <hi>Hic est sanguis meus,</hi> the word <hi>sanguis</hi> signifies blood, and by <hi>meus,</hi> is determined to signifie our Sauiours. Moreouer, this
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>redicate corpus</hi> is heere taken pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erlie, and <hi>sanguis</hi> in like manner; as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he text it self preuenting the cauills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f Heretickes hath declared by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing to it that whereby it differs frō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ignes or meere figures: or, other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lood, or other bodies.<note n="g." place="margin">1. Cor 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and<note n="h." place="margin">Ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.<note n="i." place="margin">Luc. 22</note>
      <hi>This is my</hi> owne <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie,</hi> that verie <hi>bodie which is giuen, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en,</hi> sacrificed, crucificed, <hi>for you.</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his was, doubtles, his true, reall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.<note n="k," place="margin">Mat. 26.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. and<note n="l." place="margin">Ibidē.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and<note n="m." place="margin">Ibid.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. and<note n="n." place="margin">Luc. 22.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>This is my</hi> owne <hi>blood,</hi> the <hi>blood of the new testament:</hi> that blood which is <hi>shed for many, this</hi> thīg in the cup is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing <hi>shed for you.</hi> Which was blood properlie. The thing is so plaine, and so cleerelie expressed, that<note n="o" place="margin">Li. 10. c. 2.</note> Chamier the Caluinist, comming to the <hi>Quaeritur, Quid sit corpus meum, sanguis meus; what is</hi> that, <hi>my bodie, my blood?</hi> answers roundlie, <hi>Nos candidè
<pb facs="7"/>
&amp; liberè, ac libenter respondemus</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>interpretandum:</hi> it is litterallie▪ properlie, to be interpreted, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstood. So farre concerning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> parts of the Proposition, in seueral▪</p>
   <p>Now to reflect vpon it all toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther; vpon the whole Proposition▪ The veritie or falsitie of a propositiō▪ doth suppose the connexion and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tire <hi>essence,</hi> which essence includes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>subiect</hi> the <hi>predicate</hi> and the <hi>copula.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> properties, you know, do presuppos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the natures whose properties they be▪ Wherefore you bee not to looke fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the veritie of this Proposition when you haue heard only <hi>Hoc:</hi> that is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a proposition nor in, <hi>Hoc est:</hi> that is not yet the proposition. But when <hi>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> is vttered, <hi>Hoc est corpus meum:</hi> there is a proposition, and a true proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for he speakes it that cannot lie. In this <hi>proposition,</hi> the subiect <hi>Hoc,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates vnto the predicate <hi>Corpus,</hi> and the predicate <hi>Corpus</hi> relates vnto the subiect <hi>Hoc,</hi> the ground of which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall reference is the <hi>copula,</hi> or verbe <hi>Est.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>Whē your soule came into your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e, your <hi>matter</hi> had thereby a relation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o your <hi>forme</hi> (being of it self accordīg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o the substance, indifferent to that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r any other;) and your <hi>forme,</hi> a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>on to your <hi>matter,</hi> which reciprocall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>elation is founded in the <hi>vnion</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>onnexion, that is inuolued in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ubstance; and is antecedent to those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ccidentes, which be <hi>in alio genere.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut whilst you were yet <hi>in fieri,</hi> before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he generation was ended, the forsaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>lation of <hi>matter</hi> to your <hi>forme deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>inatlie,</hi> was not, it was to earlie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>oke for it before the <hi>terminus</hi> or the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tio fundandi</hi> were in being.</p>
   <p>And, as now, your <hi>matter</hi> being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uallie related to your <hi>forme,</hi> a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>pher may consider it (by way of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>raction) without that order, and <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ndum se,</hi> in which consideration, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>determined and indifferent to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rmes: so likewise in the Proposition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich wee speake of, <hi>Hoc est corpus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eum:</hi> though that <hi>Hoc,</hi> be there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rminatlie related to <hi>Corpus,</hi> in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="8"/>
aboue specified; yet, a Deuine ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> consider it (by way of abstractio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> without that order, and <hi>secundum s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in which consideration, it is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent to stand for, or relate vnto, <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> bodie, bread,</hi> or any thing els, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> might (by Gods omnipotent power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be in that forme, it signifying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> self, onlie, <hi>contentum sub hac visibili fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma; non specificādo qualitatem veluti sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stantialem;</hi> not determining particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larlie and <hi>in specie</hi> what that thing is as before was noted. Neither it is an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> great matter, whether this <hi>indetermi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation</hi> be declared by <hi>vagum,</hi> as som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> do: or by <hi>confusum,</hi> or <hi>commune,</hi> as o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers. They be but seueral waies of v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstanding the same thing, to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>indetermination</hi> of that pronoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> conceaued <hi>secundum se.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This is sufficient for the Reader a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this present, touching the words o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Institution,</hi> in which the Controuersi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> cheeflie doth consist. And by it, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> will be able to vnderstand those obie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctions which hereafter are brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/>
against the <hi>Supposition,</hi> and <hi>reference,</hi> of the word <hi>Hoc:</hi> the <hi>time,</hi> consigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed by the Verbe, <hi>est:</hi> and the like. As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lso, that vaine pretence of <hi>Tautologie</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o oft repeated by the Doctor, and his Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ogist. The subiect, <hi>Hoc,</hi> doth sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie (as I said) <hi>substantiam indeterminaté:</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he predicate <hi>corpus meum,</hi> signifies a particular kinde of substance; a mans bodie, our Sauiours bodie; <hi>speciem, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e qualitatem, determinat.</hi> so that, <hi>one</hi> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit answers in the mind, to the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, <hi>an other</hi> conceit or apprehension, farre more distinct and explicite, ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to the predicate, and therefore it is not (as the Doctor pretends) nuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to say <hi>This is my bodie.</hi> And had it beene indeed idle <hi>tautologie,</hi> it must of necessitie haue beene true (let the Doctor note this,) whosoeuer had spoken it, and said ouer a peece of bread, <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> which is farre other wise. Our Sauiour, being God, spake it: and it was verified, he could not lie. A Preist speakes it, and it is verified in vertue of the <hi>Institution</hi> of
<pb facs="9"/>
our Sauiour, who hath engaged his omnipotencie for the verification of it in that case. But you speake it, being no Preist, and it is false. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares further, that the proposition of the Preist is <hi>practick:</hi> able in it's kind, to inferre what it signifies, (which is an other point cauilled at by the Apologist:) and yours which is not able to do so, speculatiue onlie. Thus farre touching the words in Question. I come now to our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries construction and Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p>The Pamphlet which I am to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute, is written in behalf and Defence of Doctour Featlie, and dedicated by Waferer to his Lord of Couentrie: who seeme to be in two seuerall Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions touching the interpretation of the foresaid wordes: though both of thē would haue them figuratiue. His Lord, <hi>D. Morton</hi> (who comes thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring into the Controuersie, as if he would make vs <hi>for feare</hi> beleeue the Sacrament, whateuer God told vs, to
<pb facs="9"/>
be for substance, nothing els but ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers bread, and wine properlie,) puts the figure in the word <hi>est,</hi> which <hi>heere</hi> (saith he) <hi>hath the same sēce as, signifieth: as if Christ had said expreslie of the bread, This signifieth my bodie.</hi> So he, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. and Chamier, <hi>lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>intelligimus: vt sit positum, est, pro signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi> In which way, the wordes are thus to be interpreted: <hi>Hoc</hi> this thing: <hi>est,</hi> doth signifie; <hi>corpus meum,</hi> my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. A construction so absurd, that the very Authors are ashamed of it, and therefore couer it vnder metaphors &amp; clowdes of obscure speaches: that it appeare not to the Reader. <hi>D. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> pretence for it, is this, that the subiect is proper bread: which bread, saith he, doth <hi>signifie,</hi> but is not, the bodie. That it is bread, he perswades himself, because our Sauiour <hi>tooke bread,</hi> and the Fathers sometimes call it bread. Which is no good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: for, the<note n="a." place="margin">Greg. Nyss. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tec. c. 37. Ser. de Coen. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud. Cypr. Gaudent in exod. tr. 2 Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril. Hier. Catech. 4. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex Epist. ad Calos. Aug. Serm 28. de verb, Dom. lib. 2. con. aduers. leg. c. 9. Hier. Epist. ad Hedib q. 2 Ambros. Myst. init. c. 9. Chrysost. Hom. 83, in Mat. &amp; 24. in Pri. ad Cor.</note>
      <hi>Fathers</hi> when they speak of that, which is heere after consecration, expounde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,
<pb facs="10"/>
as you will see hereafter, (for Doctor Featlie doth obiect the same,) of bread which is <hi>changed,</hi> by the power of <hi>Omnipotēcie, not in shape, but in nature;</hi> of <hi>supersubstantiall, heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> not proper bread. in which sence our Sauiour calls his flesh, <hi>meate:</hi> and himself, <hi>bread: Ioh.</hi> 6. Whereupon whē they take the word properlie, they saie that it is <hi>not bread; not that which nature made, no sensible thing: but the flesh of Christ, the bodie which was crucified; the mediatour; the Lord of all.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neither doth it follow that it is bread properly, because he tooke such bread into his hands: for he <hi>chā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it</hi> by his omnipotence<note n="b." place="bottom">Panis omnipotentia Verbi factus est caro. Oblata con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertons in Veritatem propriae carnis. In illud <hi>(quod est immortale)</hi> transelementata corum quae apparent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura.</note>
      <hi>into flesh</hi> as they likewise teach vs. and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours words according to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<pb facs="10"/>
proper sence do<note n="c." place="bottom">
         <hi>D. Morton.</hi> Instit. of the Sacram. lib. 2. cap. 1. pag. 72.</note> confessedlie import as much: for they signifie that <hi>his bodie</hi> is now in <hi>that</hi> exteriour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, <hi>wherein</hi> before there was bread. Which doth inuolue a change. In a <hi>corporall</hi> feast, suppose a Prince ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes it, that which was bought aliue, is serued in before the guests,<note n="d." place="bottom">And consequentlie it is not rigorouslie spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, the <hi>same thing;</hi> though it be vulgarlie esteemed the same. <hi>Homo mortuus quanquam figurae for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam habet eandem, tamen homo non est, saies</hi> the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Part: Anim. c.</hi> 1. And elswhere he tels vs <hi>Homo mortuus, dicitur aequiuocé.</hi> Liuing and dead things haue not the same forme, and therefore, if you belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue him, be not the same things. <hi>Vide eundem lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Gener. t</hi> 23.</note> not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue. In this <hi>spirituall</hi> feast, exhibited by the Prince of heauen, that which was brought into the Church not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, is (he is the Creators Sonne and himself omnipotent that makes it,) presented to the communicants, his guests, aliue <hi>Influit oblatis vim vitae,</hi>
      <note place="margin">S. Cyril. Alex. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. ad Calos.</note>
      <hi>cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertens ea in veritatem propriae carnis. He doth flow in to the things offered the power of life, conuerting them into the
<pb facs="11"/>
veritie of his owne flesh.</hi> Neither was he long about it: but, said the word, &amp;<note n="e." place="bottom">Statim per <hi>verbum</hi> in corpus mutatur, vt dictum est à <hi>Verbo,</hi> hoc est corpus meum. <hi>S. Greg. Nyssen Orat. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech. c.</hi> 37.</note> suddainlie the thing was donne.</p>
   <p>Whereupon this ensued, that his bodie was at once in two places: In the one <hi>situallie,</hi> as other bodies are in the other <hi>sacramentallie,</hi> &amp; according to the manner of a spirit.</p>
   <p>This, as our greatest Aduersaries <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse,</hi> doth <hi>vnauoideablie follow</hi> vpō the natiue and <hi>proper sence</hi> of our <hi>Sauiours</hi> words. And Antiquitie so vnderstood and beleeued it, affirming that verie bodie which was crucified for our sinnes, to be vnder the<note n="f." place="bottom">S Aug. Conc 1. in Psal. 33. l. 9. Conf. c. 13. &amp; Serm. ad Neoph. apud Bed. in c. 10. ad Cor. In the 4. Argu. one place will be discussed. S. Chrys. Hom, 24. in Epist. ad Cor. S. Cyrill Catec. 4 S. Ansel. in c. 11 ad Cor.</note> forme or shape of bread: and that blood which
<pb facs="11"/>
issued out of our Sauiours side, the verie price of our Redemption, to be in<note n="g." place="bottom">S. Chrys. Hom. 24. in Epist. ad Cor. S. Aug. Epist. 162. Serm. ad Neoph. S. Leo Serm. 7. de ieiunio mens. sept.. S. Greg. mag. lib. 4. Dial c. 58. S. Cyrill. Catec 4.</note> the chalice; and thence powred into the mouthes of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants. They beleeued that the most precious bodie in heauen, was at the same<note n="h." place="bottom">S. Chrysost. l 3. de Sacerd. Hom. 24. in Epist. ad Cor. Hom. 17. in Epist. ad Heb. S. Greg. Nyss. Orat. Catech c 17. S. Cyrill. Alex. anathem. 11. in Conc Ephes &amp; lib. 11 in Ioan. c 27. Conc. Nicen. 1. in Act. Vatic. S. Cyrill. Hieros. catech 4.</note> time, in many places, heere on earth: that they had <hi>Iesus,</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, God and man, (he being at the same time in heauen,) heere in their<note n="i." place="bottom">S. Cyrill. Catech. myst. 5. S. Chrys. Hom. 24. ad Cor. lib. 3. de Sacerd. Hom. 46. in Ioan.</note> hands; and receaued him with their<note n="k." place="bottom">S. Aug. l. 2. con. Aduers. leg. c. 9. Tract. 59. in Ioan. Origen. Hom. 5. in diuersa S. Cyrill. Alex. lib. 10. in Ioan. c. 13 S. Cyrill. Hieros. Catech. 4. S. Leo. Serm. 7. de ieiunio mens. Sept.</note> mouth. The ground of which beleefe were the foresaid words and asseueration of our blessed Sauiour
<pb facs="12"/>
(to whose Authoritie they had sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their vnderstandings,) <hi>Take, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, this is my bodie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>They did not presume to dispute with Him, about the nature of quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, or substāce, or<note n="l." place="bottom">Or repute it absurd he should be in a <hi>mans bellie.</hi> VVhat is better, what purer, what more glorious thē the <hi>blessed Trinitie?</hi> and is not the <hi>blessed Trinitie</hi> in euerie place, and (now you stop your nose) in euerie thing? The bodie of our blessed <hi>Sauiour</hi> is immortall, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passible, and existeth in the Sacrament, according to the manner of a <hi>Spirit.</hi>
      </note> place: (they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re sure he knew these things better then they did,) or, by that little which man knowes or seemes to know, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine his Power &amp; Art: but ingenuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie honoured and willinglie heard Him, as the Master of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; <hi>in</hi>
      <note n="m." place="margin">Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loss. 2.</note>
      <hi>whom are hid all the treasures of wisedome and knowledge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To feare least the bodie, which is <hi>substantiallie</hi> indiuiduall, should be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted into two bodies by this <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
and superuenient manner of existencie, is a fault in the braine lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the name, rather then any signe of a good and sincere iudgment. It is in the Sacrament according to <hi>the manner of a Spirit</hi> as before hath beene obserued, and Spirits are not subiect to distraction by quantitie,<note place="margin">VVhen a man is behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is his <hi>soule</hi> cut in two?</note> though that happen (and whilst they are in it) to be diuided. One Angell is able to moue (&amp; so to be<note n="n." place="margin">Vide Caiet. Baun. Nazar. &amp;c. <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>p. q.</hi> 52. <hi>a.</hi> 2.</note> in) two bodies at once: &amp; though the bodies be distinct he still remaines the same. Neither is he continued by the continuitie of bodies, if those he moues (suppose two drops of water) become one. A Spirit in extended things is not extended; in continued things, not continued: in distinct things, not distinguished. He is in another order, far aboue. God, is neither multiplied in himself, by the great multitude of things wherein he is: nor by their quantitie extended. Were there at once many worlds, he would be in them all<note n="o" place="bottom">
         <hi>Saint Augustine had an apprehension that the soule of Martyrs were perchance, at once in diuers places.</hi> Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ista quaestio vires intelligentiae meae vincat, quemadmodum opitulentur Martyres iis quos per eos certum est adiuuari: Vtrum ipsi per seipsos assint vno tempore tam diuersis locis, &amp; tanta inter se lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginquitate discretis, siue vbi sunt eorum memoriae, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue praeter suas memorias vbicunque adesse senti untur: an ipsis in loco suis meritis conguo ab omni mortaliū conuersatione remotis, &amp;c. Res haec altior est quàm vt à me possit attingi, &amp; abstrusior quàm vt à me va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat persetutari: &amp; ideo quid horum duorum sit, an ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò fortassis vtrumque sit, &amp;c. <hi>S Augustin. lib. de cura pro mort. c.</hi> 16.</note> vndistracted.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>That it is the fault of men ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hastie and vndiscreetlie rash, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the <hi>supposition</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne <hi>Hoc,</hi> before the<note n="p." place="bottom">Neither doth <hi>Hoc,</hi> of it self determine <hi>that precise instant</hi> wherein it is vttered. The thing demonstrated may follow that instant or moment, when the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition is speculatiue, much more when it is practick and is cause of the thing signified. <hi>Nomen &amp; Pronomen secundum Grammaticos non consignificat tempus, sed Verbo id competit: quare demonstratio per se Pronominis abstrahit a tempore: scilicet &amp; quo prosertur Pronomen &amp; quo termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur totius orationis prolatio;</hi> saith, <hi>Soto,</hi> cited in the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,</hi> p. 501. In the Relation of S. F. pag. 80. there is a pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Scripture brought to shew that the thing demō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated, may follow the Pronoune <hi>Hoc, Hoc est praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum meum, vt &amp;c.</hi> There be diuers other examples of it in holie Scripture: whereof some are noted also by your Chamier <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>de Euchar. c.</hi> 21. <hi>Et hoc vobis signum, inuenietis infantem.</hi> Luc. 2. <hi>Hoc scientes, quod vetus homo.</hi> Rom. 6. <hi>Hoc est pactum meum— vt circumcidatur.</hi> Gen. 17. <hi>Haec sunt nomina —Ruben, Simeon,</hi> Exodi 1. And the Prophets otherwhile begin with <hi>Haec dicit Dominus.</hi> He adds that sometimes <hi>Hoc,</hi> and Hic, demonstrate things past, <hi>Hoc totum factum est.</hi> Matth. 1. and sometimes that which the eie cannot at all perceaue, <hi>Haec eo cogitante.</hi> Mat. 1. <hi>Falsum est,</hi> saies he, c. 18. <hi>etiam in Pronomine, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbioue demonstrandi requiri rem praesentem. Non enim est perpetuū.</hi> and, <hi>Omnia, tam praesentia quam praeterita, sensui sunt demonstrabilia: quia in sensibus aures sunt, quibus per verba nihil non demonstrari potest.</hi> To which purpose he citeth S. Aug. <hi>l</hi> 2. <hi>de Doct. Christ. c.</hi> 3.</note> predicate be knowne, it appeares by that I haue
<pb facs="13"/>
allready said about it. If it be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>secundum se</hi> (as it is before the rest is vttered) it is indetermined and he must make a new Dictionarie that will haue it in that acception to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>bread.</hi> Or, <hi>Hic,</hi> (in the other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,) determinatlie and <hi>ex vi sua,</hi> to signifie <hi>wine:</hi> into which new Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie should the same compilers put <hi>Haec,</hi> for <hi>meate,</hi> which it doth signifie as determinatlie of it self, the yong
<pb facs="14"/>
Schollers in <hi>Hic, Haec, Hoc,</hi> would ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a feast.</p>
   <p>If <hi>Hoc</hi> doth not, being taken <hi>secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum se,</hi> determinatlie signifie <hi>bread</hi> (as it is manifest it doth not,) then <hi>D. Mortōs</hi> whole building, without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re adoe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>D. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shers</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumēts for <hi>bread,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered by F. <hi>Mallon.</hi>
      </note> falls vnto the ground. Yet least it should not easilie enough be ruined this way, he doth another way himself vndetermine it, whilst he brings in an Armie of Witnesses to force his Reader to beleeue that the Sacrament is consecrated by <hi>prayer</hi> &amp; benedictiō distinct from these words <hi>(Hoc est &amp;c.)</hi> which he saith be not words of <hi>inuocation</hi> and prayer, but of <hi>declaration.</hi> It is in the <hi>second Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of his first booke, in his Challeng; where he saith, <hi>The Archbishop of Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarea cometh in, compassed about with a clowde of witnesses and reasons to proue that the consecration vsed by our Sauiour was performed by that blessing by prayer which preceded the pronouncing of those words Hoc est corpus meum.</hi> Were this so, the chiefest of his <hi>(D. Mortons)</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils,
<pb facs="14"/>
which is about the <hi>supposition</hi> of of the word <hi>Hoc,</hi> were cut of by it. When the water at <hi>Cana</hi> was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and wine standing vpon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, what cauill could then be raised against these words <hi>Hoc est vinum, This is wine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He thinks he gets the Cause, if he cā, out of the words of any of ours, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the contrarie to the common <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> of the Church. Which manner of disputing in him is notoriouslie<note n="q." place="bottom">If the Church-authoritie be ouerthrowne by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, it must be donne by a greater. The authoritie of priuate men, is far, yea infinitelie lesse: in regard of the Diuine Assistance which the Church, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, hath <hi>He shall teach you.</hi> Ioan. 14. &amp; 16. <hi>It has seemed good to the Holie Ghost and to vs.</hi> Act. 15.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient. The Writers themselues were still readie to retract whateuer could be found in their bookes any way repugnant vnto Church-doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: they knew <hi>they might mistake:</hi> and therefore submitted their writings &amp; opinions and iudgment to the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Censure of the Church,
<pb facs="15"/>
which <hi>they beleeued to be secured from errour,</hi> by the prouidence of the holy Ghost her Master.</p>
   <p>Should a man in the Schooles of Deuinitie step vp and say, <hi>The definitiō of the Councell of Trent,</hi> approued by the Church, <hi>is repugnant (in consequence at least) to the Opiniō of,</hi> suppose, <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Ergo the definition is false;</hi> He would be thought either to deride the Cardinall, or to want something which commonlie men haue. This I saie in generall, touching the <hi>manner:</hi> and for the <hi>matter,</hi> it is well knowne, the Cardinall (I meane the same of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) was able to defend, both, Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall <hi>tenets,</hi> and his owne priuate Answers and opinions, against a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Scholler then D. <hi>Morton.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Doctor Featlie, as it appeares by his Argumēt out of <hi>Tertullians</hi> words, puts the figure in the word <hi>Corpus:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Conferē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. and Prot. doct. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> a <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> for he would haue the words to run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thus, <hi>Hoc est figura corporis mei,</hi> which is the opinion of <hi>Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> fauored also by <hi>Caluin.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="15"/>
to this way, the words, <hi>Hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st corpus meum,</hi> are thus interpreted: <hi>Hoc,</hi> this thing, <hi>est</hi> is, <hi>corpus meum</hi> the figure of my bodie. Whence it will presentlie follow (if you consider the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ext well: <hi>this is my () which is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, deliuered, for you;</hi>) that the <hi>figure</hi> of our Sauiours bodie suffred <hi>for vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>His Arguments are in the <hi>Relatiō</hi> where you will see their Answers. Hee agrees with D. <hi>Morton</hi> in exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>the veritie of the bodie,</hi> and in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding <hi>Hoc,</hi> this bread; which is more then the word signifies. And the determination of it to bread pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie taken, is begd: as hath beene shewed before; and shall appeare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fullie hereafter in the Solution of his Obiections. Neither doth it <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatlie</hi> import or signifie a thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct from <hi>Corpus.</hi> If it did, it were false to say pointing at you, <hi>Hoc est corpus;</hi> because the proposition doth affirme <hi>Identitie</hi> betwixt the <hi>significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> of the two extreames, which <hi>Identi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
were not, if <hi>Hoc</hi> determinatlie sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified a thing distinct frō that which is signified by <hi>Corpus.</hi> And by the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me reason it appeares manifestlie that the extreames are not, <hi>ex vi terminorū, disparata.</hi> If they were, <hi>Hoc</hi> must im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a nature or thing distinct from that which <hi>Corpus</hi> doth import: which is not onlie against Theologie, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so against Logick and the generall notion of men that know <hi>Latine,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing that <hi>hoc,</hi> of it self, <hi>determines no nature.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I note heere further that both the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, D. <hi>Morton</hi> &amp; D. <hi>Featlie,</hi> do make the blessed Sacramēt to be in it self nothīg els but <hi>bread properlie,</hi> with a relation to grace, and to the bodie now in heauen (which relation being foūded in the institution, is <hi>rationis,</hi> in the mind onlie,) and consequentlie, how euer in words they repugne, they make it a meere <hi>signe</hi> or <hi>figure.</hi> This appeares by their interpretation of the wordes; <hi>Hoc</hi> this bread, <hi>est</hi>
      <note n="b." place="margin">D. Morton</note>
      <hi>doth</hi> signifie, <hi>Corpus meum</hi> my bodie, it <hi>doth
<pb facs="16"/>
signifie;</hi> there is all: or, <hi>Hoc</hi> this bread, <hi>est</hi> is, <hi>Corpus meum</hi> the<note n="c." place="margin">D. Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlie</note> figure of my bodie, <hi>the figure,</hi> not the substance, not the veritie. They tell you there is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, but if you aske what it is, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find it. <hi>Grace</hi> is not the Sacrament, but the<note n="d." place="bottom">This writing is the <hi>effect</hi> of my pen as the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall cause: but it is not my pen that still remaines a <hi>meere</hi> pen.</note> effect of it. Gods <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie,</hi> is not the Sacrament, nor any part of the Sacrament properlie. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his <hi>decree</hi> to giue vs grace whē wee receaue worthilie, the thing hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re meant by this word, Sacrament. Nor the <hi>faith</hi> and deuotion of the receauer: faith is not the Sacrament. Nor the bodie of our Sauiour <hi>in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> or <hi>on the Crosse.</hi> What then is it? Nothing but the signe: that is, <hi>bread</hi> properlie, with a dubble reference, one to the <hi>bodie</hi> or death of Christ; another, to <hi>grace,</hi> nothing els. This reallie is their <hi>tenet;</hi> though they be ashamed, many of thē, to professe it. Pretending a great feast, they serue in
<pb facs="17"/>
dishes; and in them the picture or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of meate; but the meate it self, the bodie, is, they saie, in heauen only, neuer neerer.</p>
   <p>The Catholiques interprete the words plainlie &amp; properlie, <hi>Hoc</hi> this, <hi>est,</hi> is, <hi>Corpus meum</hi> my bodie. In which sence it is <hi>confessed</hi> by our aduersaries themselues that they importe such a reall presence as wee beleeue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. So that, <hi>My Lord,</hi> sitting downe to defend, had this aduantage on his side, that the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth in plaine termes <hi>auouch</hi> his <hi>tenet.</hi> And <hi>M. Featlie</hi> on the contrarie, this disaduantage, that he was to dispute <hi>against the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per sence of holie Scripture.</hi> Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per sence, was, when Luther began,<note n="e." place="bottom">Hic error <hi>(so the Sacramentarians do stile it)</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud totius orbis Christianos inualuit. <hi>Bucer. lib. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. pag. 660.</hi> Missae abominatio omnes reges &amp; populos à summo vsque ad nouissimum sic inebriauit, vt &amp;c. <hi>Calu. l; 4. Instit. c. 18</hi>
      </note> generallie beleeued &amp; abbetted: &amp; that confessedlie for<note n="f." place="bottom">Libenter concedo Idolomaniam Pontificiam, cuius est verum sacrificium Missaticum, totum paene terrarum orbem inuasisse, praesertim superiore proxime millenario. <hi>Hutter, de sacrif. Misl. pag. 377.</hi>
      </note> many hundred
<pb facs="17"/>
yeeres together.<note n="g." place="bottom">Si verū est quod de Corpore Christi <hi>(he speakes to Berē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius)</hi> tu credis &amp; astruis, falsum est quod ab Ecclesia vbique gentium, de eadem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> creditur &amp; astruitur. Omnes enim qui Christianos se &amp; esse &amp; dici laetantur, veram Christi carnem verumque eius sanguinem, vtraque sumpta de Virgine in hoc Sacramento se percipere gloriantur. Interroga vniuer os qui Latinae linguae, nostrarum ne litterarum notitiam perceperūt, interroga Graecos, Armenios, seu cuiuslibet nationis quoscun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque Christianos homines vno ore hanc fidem se testan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur habere. <hi>Lanfran. Archiep. Cantuar. l. de Euchar con. Bereng. See the</hi> Censure. <hi>pag. 331.</hi>
      </note> All Natiōs as many as beleeued that our Sauiour hath true<note n="h." place="bottom">Those who following the errour of Eutiches, said the flesh of our Sauiour was <hi>turned into his Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> said consequentlie to their errour that heere was reallie present the bodie of the Diuinitie. <hi>Sacrificium panis carnis Christi, negant esse corpus Christi, sed diuinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis corpus esse dicunt.</hi> Euthym. in Panoplia. par. 2. ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 20. VVhence it appeares how vnskilfullie they be, by some brought for the <hi>Sacramentarian</hi> heresie.</note> flesh &amp; blood, haue beleeued it: &amp; amōgst them, our cuntry<note n="i." place="bottom">See the Prudentiall Ballance.</note> England. And Luther himself wrot a<note n="k." place="bottom">Defensio <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> verborum coenae.</note> booke in defence of it, telling the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,
<pb facs="18"/>
the text of Scripture is to<note n="m." place="bottom">In defens. verb. coenae. He is large in examining the places obiected out of <hi>S. Augustine, Tertullian, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Hilarius,</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus.</hi> Heereafter I shall haue occasion to bring some of his words touching the place of <hi>Tertullian</hi> which Featlie stands vpon: and as for <hi>Irenaeus</hi> whom Birckbeck doth alleage, he <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> plainelie that he held a reall presence of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours <hi>bodie</hi> to our <hi>bodies.</hi> Pugnabat (Irenaeus) contra Valentinum Haereticum, eiusque socios qui asserebant Christum non esse filium Dei, &amp; non fore resurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem carnis, nec corpus saluati, sed animam. Contra hoc scribit &amp; affirmat Irenaeus quod corpus etiam sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetur, &amp; quod resurrectio carnis futura sit, secundum Symbolum Apostolicum. Inter caetera autem hoc contra ipsos producit argumentum: Si corpus non sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatur, quid ergo cibatur corpore in coena? si ibi aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no cibo vescitur, vt in aeternum viuat necesse est. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feramus autem propria ipsius verba. Quemadmodum enim qui à terra panis percipiens vocationem Dei &amp;c. Luther. in Def. verb. coenae. p. 408. See the place, for he is verie large. Paulus dilucidè nos docet quid sit Dei vocare seu nominare, vbi ait, Deus vocat seu nominat ea quae non sunt, vt sint. Eodem modo Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus loquitur de Dei vocare seu nominare. Item Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses Gen. 1. testatur Deum per suum vocare seu nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare, quod est per verbum suum, omnia creare. Si tibi (Oecolampadium alloquitur) haec definitio non placet, age, praesta te Magistrum, &amp; nos doce quid aliud vocatio Dei esse possit, quando Deus vocat, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, appellat, nominat. Hoc verbum Dei est cum inquit Hoc est corpus meum, sicut in Genesi ait Fiat lux, &amp; fit lux. Deus est qui nominat seu vocat, &amp; quicquid nominat id illico praesto est, vt Psalm 33 testatur, dixit &amp; facta sunt. <hi>Ibidem.</hi> Item, Irenaeus ait. Quomodo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem rursus dicunt carnem in corruptionem deuenire, &amp; non percipere vitam, quae à corpore &amp; sanguine Domini alitur? Hic iterum audimus, corpus nostrum eo cibari corpore &amp; sanguine Domini, vt in aeternum viuat, &amp; non corrumpatur vt Haeretici somniabant. Irenaeus loquitur de corporali manducatione &amp; ciba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione corporis, &amp; tamen vult cibum illum esse corpus &amp; sanguinem Domini. <hi>Ibidem</hi> He brings there also the Sacramentarians <hi>Euasions,</hi> and refutes them out of Irenaeus words.</note> cleere &amp; plaine, in so much that it cā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<note n="l." place="bottom">Si quispiam mihi persuadere potuisset in sacramē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to praeter panē— verum ego captum me video, nulla euadendi via relicta: textus enim Euangelij <hi>nimis aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eus</hi> est &amp; potens. Epist. ad Argentin. habetur tomo 7. in Epist. Farrag.</note>
      <pb facs="18"/>
be auoided: &amp; auouching withall that it was the Fathers tenet. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise doth Melancthon,<note n="n." place="bottom">Melancth l. de Ver. Corp. Quid fiet in tentatione cum disputabit conscientia quam habuerit caussam dissentiendi à recepta sententia in Ecclesia▪ Tunc ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba ista, <hi>hoc est corpus meum▪</hi> fulmina erunt. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
      </note> Sequor, saith he, <hi>veteris ecclesiae sententiam quae affirmat adesse corpus in coena: ac iudico hanc habere Scripturae testimonium.</hi> I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="19"/>
the sentence of the auncient Church which affirmes the bodie to be presēt in the supper; &amp; I iudge it to haue the testimonie of Scripture.</p>
   <p>Those who stood on Featlies side, were such as by Apostacie had gonne out of the true Church.<note n="o." place="bottom">Archidiaconus Andegauensis. <hi>anno</hi> 1035. Docuit paruulos non esse baptizandos, teste <hi>Guit mundo</hi> eius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem temporis scriptore. Hanc autem Haeresim esse constat vniuersalis ecclesiae testimonio: idemque fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur Angli Protestantes.</note> Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, (who<note n="p." place="bottom">Malmesb. l. 3.</note> recanted;)<note n="q." place="bottom">Sacerdos &amp; Pastor de Lutterworth. anno 1371.</note> Wickleff,<note n="r," place="bottom">Archidiaconus VVittembergensis, &amp; Lutheri dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulus.</note> Carolstadius,<note n="s." place="bottom">Pastor Tigurinus.</note> Swinglius.<note n="t." place="bottom">Ex monacho Apostata.</note> Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colampadius, &amp;<note n="u." place="bottom">
         <p>Nouiodunensis. <hi>Deus adeo hunc Haereticum percussit, vt desperata salute, daemonibus inuocatis, iurans, execrans, &amp; blasphemans, miserrimè animam malignam exhalarit.</hi> Schlussel in Theol. Calu. fol. 72. idemque testatur Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Bolsecus in eius vita.</p>
         <p>That Luther, Caluin, Swinglius, Carolstadius, Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colampadius, had beene Papists, (as they speake) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they fell into their Heresies, is declared out of their owne authors in the booke <hi>de Auth. Prot. eccles. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
      </note> Caluin:<note n="x." place="bottom">See the <hi>Censure,</hi> pag. 274.</note> Iudas,
<pb facs="19"/>
and that great Apostata the<note n="y." place="bottom">See the <hi>Censure,</hi> pag. 274.</note> Deuil. I do not mention<note n="z." place="bottom">Touching this Bertrame reade the Plea for the Reall Presence, against Sir Humfrey Linde. by I. O.</note> Bertram, because he that makes any speach in him Caluinisticallie Protestāt in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, doth withall make him cōtradict himself, (it is the same of that<note n="a." place="bottom">Concerning this Homilie, and the Author, see the Prudentiall Balance l. 1. c, 19. in Odo, and Alfrick. &amp;c. 22. n. 4.</note> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie which is cited as Elfricks,) and thereby casts him of.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Iudge</hi> of Controuersies, is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Aduersaries themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, either the <hi>scripture,</hi> or the <hi>Spirit.</hi> If wee goe with the Controuersie to the Scripture, &amp; to our Sauiour speaking in it, the cause is ours; <hi>This is my bodie which is broken for you.</hi> Which <hi>words, if they be certainlie true in a proper and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall sence, then wee are to yeeld the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le
<pb facs="20"/>
cause [reall Presence,</hi> propitiatorie <hi>Sacrifice, and Adoration) saith</hi> D. <hi>Mortō, the</hi> last who wrot in England before Waferer of this subiect. <hi>I haue said oft, and now repeate the same againe, that the litterall sence or letter cannot be retained in these words of Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cited p. 293.</note>
      <hi>This is my bodie, without establishing the Papisticall tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation,</hi> saith <hi>Beza.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If we go with the Controuersie to the Spirit in <hi>the Church,</hi> we gaine the Cause too, for all knowne Churches in Luthers time did beleeue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it. If to the Spirit in <hi>the first Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes,</hi> Luther and his Disciples, the Cause is ours.</p>
   <p>If wee consider diligentlie the <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances</hi> of the text, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, my owne <hi>bodie,</hi> that which <hi>is deliuered, broken,</hi> crucified, <hi>for you:</hi> and of the blood in like manner, (<hi>vt supra pag.</hi> 11. wee are more and more confirmed in our <hi>tenet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If wee reade the <hi>Fathers,</hi> wee finde thē to be ours, the Lord of Plessis Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,
<pb facs="20"/>
had obiected out of them, by the help of his Ministers, what he could: but he is fullie answered by the worthie Cardinall Peron, in a iust to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of this subiect onlie, <hi>which booke he were to refute, that would laie claime to Antiquitie</hi> in behalf of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian Heresie.</p>
   <p>Moreouer that our <hi>tenet</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all presence of our Sauiours bodie vnder the signes, was the <hi>tenet</hi> of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, the Church tells vs, the Church I say; in Luthers daies, and before, a thousand yeers together: in which Church there haue beene innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble great Schollers, examining Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes, reading the Fathers, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and considering the text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; and this Church tells vs, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, their predecessors, taught them as they teach vs. Why should wee not beleeue them, &amp; in a matter so plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deliuered in the Scripture; rather then Daniel Featlie, or Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, or Iohn Caluin?</p>
   <p>If you will moue vs with Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="21"/>
bring <hi>greater</hi> Authoritie. If you will moue vs with Scripture, bring <hi>plainer</hi> Scripture; and more worlds o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlie, in plaine termes interpreting it, against vs. The Authoritie of one Deuine, of a Nation, will not serue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a world.</p>
   <p>The Doctour obiecteth S. Augus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; but, against S. Augustine: as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after will appeare. He obiecteth Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian and Origen; and, against Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, and Origen they, in this point, were not diuided from the world. But, had Origen, or Tertullian beene opposite in their opiniō, who so mad as to follow them, against so great an authoritie as the Church?</p>
   <p>To oppose a <hi>lesse</hi> Authoritie to a <hi>greater,</hi> &amp; thereby to think to winne the cause, is absurd. If Authoritie can moue, the greater it is the more it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</p>
   <p>To vrge against the <hi>Church,</hi> the words of any, in<note n="a." place="bottom">
         <hi>As, when a man speakes of the practicall</hi> dictio <hi>or</hi> vocatio, <hi>which is</hi> a making <hi>of the thing</hi> by saying it is or calling it <hi>by the name,</hi> (Ipse dixit &amp; facta sunt; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zare veni foras: Adolescens tibi dieo surge;) <hi>to interprete h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s words of a meere speculatiue</hi> dictio <hi>or</hi> vocatio. Qui est à terra panis, percipiens <hi>vocationem</hi> Dei, iam non communis panis est, sed Eucharistia, ex duabus rebus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stans, terrena &amp; coelesti. <hi>Irenaeus l 4 c 34. and l. 5. c 2.</hi> Quando ergo &amp; mixtus calix &amp; fractus panis percipit ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bū Dei <hi>fit</hi> Eucharistia &amp;c. <hi>The words are</hi> operatoria, <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall: as you will see more at large in the solution of the</hi> fift Arg p. <hi>479.</hi> &amp; seqq. S. <hi>Ierom vpon those words of S, Matth</hi> Surgens imperauit ventis—venti &amp; mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> obediunt ei. Ex hoc loco, <hi>saith he,</hi> intelligimus quod omnes creaturae sentiant creatorem. Quas enim increpauit, &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus imperauit, sentiunt, imperantem: non errore Haretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, qui omnia putant animantia, sed maiestate conditoris: quae apud nos insensibilia, illi sensibilia sunt. <hi>In c. 8. Matt.</hi>
      </note> another sence
<pb facs="21"/>
then they did vtter them; or to build an aduantage vpon a mistake in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<note n="b." place="bottom">
         <p>For example, what the word <hi>Hoc,</hi> doth preciselie demonstrate. S. <hi>Bonauenture</hi> did auouch the <hi>reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi> and <hi>transubstantiation,</hi> as all Schollers know; though he did expound <hi>Hoc,</hi> of bread. VVherefore your deduction from the like <hi>interpretation,</hi> (could you find it in one more auncient,) to <hi>the mans beleefe</hi> of a meere signe, would not hold. The <hi>sequele</hi> faild, in him, a Deuine. And you, though you know not perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture whether <hi>S. Peter</hi> when he said <hi>Tabitha rise,</hi> did addresse his speach to the dead bodie, calling that <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitha, (Conuersus ad corpus dixit, Tabitha surge,)</hi> or to the liue Person which vpon his word appeared; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it did in the beginning of the speach stand inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatlie: will graunt, notwithstanding, that in the end of the speach, there was not a dead corse, as in the beginning: but a liue woman, and this by vertue of his words instrumentallie, and principallie by the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods omnipotencie; which doth also worke heere, as the Fathers tell vs.</p>
         <p>In these propositions, <hi>Coeci vident: mortui resurgunt; qui in monumentis sunt audient votem &amp;c.</hi> there is (as the Deuines saie) <hi>sensus diuisus.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> nice point or subtilitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb facs="22"/>
with cōsēt in the mysterie<note n="c." place="bottom">The thing imported by our Sauiours words pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perlie vnderstood.</note> it self there might be diuersitie of opinions; is an euident signe of Hereticall perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie. The <hi>Church,</hi> by continuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise, doth profit in the knowledg of such matters. And, as now amongst the moderne Deuines, some do better interprete Gods word in obscure pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and deliuer the truth in more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate &amp; proper termes, then others:
<pb facs="22"/>
so was it, if wee beleeue the<note n="d." place="bottom">S. Aug. de Praed. Sanct. c. 14. Hier. Apol. adu. Ruff.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in the times primitiue; wherein some did speake of matters, by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants now beleeued, lesse<note n="e." place="bottom">Fieri potest vt— vel certe antequam in Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria quasi Daemonium meridianum Arius na ceretur, innocenter quaedam &amp; minus caute loquuti sunt, &amp; quae non possint peruersorum hominum calumniam declinare. <hi>S. Hier, Apol. aduers. Ruff. lib.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>warilie</hi> then others did.</p>
   <p>It is well knowne also, that the best Schollers and greatest Saincts were euer readie to submit themselues and their iudgment to the <hi>Iudgment</hi> of the Church: with whom the <hi>Spirit of truth</hi> remaines, to <hi>teach all</hi> truth, <hi>foreuer.</hi> Wherefore, if it should haue happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that any of them had been mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in this matter, (as S. Cyprian was in the point Baptisme,) he could not without open wrong be obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Church. Especiallie, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that, in that his <hi>generall submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> of his iudgment he virtuallie <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted</hi> whateuer should be found in his writings contrarie to any deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Hers.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="23"/>
      <note place="margin">S. Aug. l 5. de Bapt. c. 17. l. 2 c. 4.</note>You know S. Augustines Apologie for the Sainct but now mentioned, whose opinion he reiected because it was against the definition of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell. <hi>Neither do</hi> I <hi>preferre my owne opinion before his, but the iudgmēt or sentēce of the Holie Catholicke Church, all which he was not.</hi> and againe <hi>Neither durst wee affirme any such thing if wee were not well grounded vpon the most cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting or agreeable Authoritie of the Vniuersall Church, vnto which vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedlie he (S. Cyprian) would haue yeilded if as then, the truth of this Question, being cleered and declared, had beene establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by a Generall Councell.</hi> So far tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the state of the Controuersie Disputed in the Conference.</p>
   <p>The Apologist, who doth addresse himself against<note n="c." place="margin">Quā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora maiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferioris compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio, superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria est. <hi>S. Hier. ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. l.</hi> 1.</note> my Lord, is bitter: and without any cause giuen him. The title ouer euerie leafe is, <hi>An Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie for Doctor Featlie against the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Chalcedon.</hi> The <hi>Obiect</hi> of my <hi>Censure</hi> is this <hi>Apologie,</hi> which labours to discredit the Catholike <hi>Relation:</hi> &amp;
<pb facs="23"/>
doth many times misreport and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt it: which makes me represent it againe to the Reader entirelie. I shall haue much adoe whilst I blott out Waferers <hi>Errours</hi> to keepe my pen from touching him that lies amongst his lies and heresies. But, the field of combat is no place of complement. Flatterie, euer a fault, when it is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized to the disaduantage of Religiō becomes a crime.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>