<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MOST SACRED MAJESTIE, CHARLES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, King of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, DEFENDER of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Cant., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108350_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68328</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15307</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108350</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MOST SACRED MAJESTIE, CHARLES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, King of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, DEFENDER of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Cant., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A speech delivered in the Starr-Chamber, on Wednesday, the XIVth of Iune, MDCXXXVII : at the censure, of Iohn Bastwick, Henry Burton, &amp; William Prinn; concerning pretended innovations in the Church. By the most Reverend Father in God, VVilliam, L. Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace</title>
                 <author>Laud, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 77, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MOST SACRED MAJESTIE, CHARLES, <hi>BY THE GRACE OF</hi> GOD, <hi>King of</hi> Great Brittaine, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, DEFENDER <hi>of the</hi> Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Gracious, and Dread Soveraigne;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had no purpose to come in <hi>Print,</hi> but <hi>Your Majesty</hi> commaunds it, and <hi>I obey.</hi> Most sorry I am for the <hi>Occasion,</hi> that induced mee to speake, and that since hath moved You to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand mee to Print. Nor am J ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that many things, while they are
<pb facs="3"/>spoken and passe by the <hi>Eare</hi> but once, give great content; which when they come to the <hi>Eyes</hi> of men, and their often scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, may lye open to some <hi>exceptions.</hi> This may fall to my <hi>lot</hi> in this particular, and very easily, considering my many <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions,</hi> and the little time J could snatch from other <hi>Imployment</hi> to attend <hi>this.</hi> Yet choose J rather to <hi>obey Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty,</hi> than to <hi>sacrifice</hi> to mine owne <hi>priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and content.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Since then this <hi>Speech</hi> uttered in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> must now come to be more publike in <hi>Print;</hi> J humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire <hi>Your Sacred Maiesty</hi> to <hi>protect mee,</hi> and <hi>it,</hi> from the undeserved <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny</hi> of those men, <hi>whose mouthes are spears and arrowes, &amp; their Tongues a sharpe sword.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 57.4.</note> Psal. <hi>57.</hi> Though as the <hi>wiseman</hi> speakes, <hi>their foolish mouthes have already called for their owne
<pb facs="3"/>stripes, and their lippes</hi> (and pennes) <hi>been a snare for their soules,</hi> Prov. <hi>18.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prov. 18.6, 7</note>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Occasion</hi> which led mee to this <hi>Speech</hi> is knowne. There have of late beene divers <hi>Libells</hi> spread against the <hi>Prelates</hi> of this <hi>Church.</hi> And they have not beene more <hi>bitter,</hi> which is the <hi>shame</hi> of these <hi>raging waves,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Jude ver. 13.</note> than they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi>false,</hi> which is <hi>Our happiness.</hi> But I must humbly beseech <hi>Your Maiesty</hi> to consider, that 'tis not Wee onely, that is, the <hi>Bishops,</hi> that are strucke at, but through our sides, <hi>Your Majesty, Your Honor, Your Safety, Your Religion,</hi> is impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. For what <hi>safety</hi> can You expect, if You loose the hearts of Your <hi>people?</hi> And how can You retaine their <hi>hearts,</hi> if You change their <hi>Religion</hi> into <hi>superstition?</hi> And what <hi>Honour</hi> can You hope for, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Present, or derivative to <hi>Posterity</hi> if you attend your <hi>Government</hi> no better
<pb facs="4"/>then to suffer Your <hi>Prelates</hi> to put this <hi>change</hi> upon You? And what <hi>Majesty</hi> can any <hi>Prince</hi> retaine, if hee loose his <hi>Honour</hi> and his <hi>People?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>GOD</hi> be thanked 'Tis in all points o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise with You: For <hi>God</hi> hath blessed You with a <hi>Religious</hi> heart, &amp; not subject to <hi>change.</hi> And He hath filled You with <hi>Honor</hi> in the Eyes of Your <hi>People:</hi> And by their <hi>Love</hi> and dutifulnesse, He hath made You <hi>safe.</hi> So that Your <hi>Maiesty</hi> is upheld and Your <hi>Crowne</hi> flourishing in the Eyes of <hi>Christendome.</hi> And <hi>God</hi> forbid any <hi>Libellous</hi> blast at home from the <hi>Tongues</hi> or <hi>Pennes</hi> of a few, should <hi>shrivell</hi> up any growth of these.</p>
   <p>Wee have received, and daily doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from <hi>GOD,</hi> many and great <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings</hi> by <hi>You.</hi> And I hope they are not many that are <hi>unthankfull</hi> to <hi>You,</hi> or to <hi>God</hi> for You. And that there should bee
<pb facs="4"/>none in a <hi>Populous Nation,</hi> even <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to their owne <hi>happinesse,</hi> cannot bee expected. Yet J shall desire, even these to call themselves to an account, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that <hi>Blasphemy</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>slandering the footsteps of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi> are joined together, <hi>Psal.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi> 89. <hi>ver.</hi> 50. Wherewith thine E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies have blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Thee, and slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the footsteppes of thine Anointed.</note>
      <hi>89.</hi> For he that <hi>blasphemes God,</hi> will never sticke at the <hi>slander</hi> of his <hi>Prince;</hi> And he that gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>slander</hi> his <hi>Prince,</hi> will quickly ascend to the next <hi>highest,</hi> and <hi>Blaspheme God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But then, as J desire <hi>them</hi> to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, so I doe most humbly beseech <hi>your Maiesty</hi> to account with Your selfe too: And not to measure your <hi>peoples love</hi> by the unworthinesse of those few. For a <hi>loyall</hi> and obedient <hi>people</hi> You have, and such as will spare nor <hi>Livelyhood,</hi> nor
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Life</hi> to doe You <hi>service:</hi> And are joyed at the heart to see the <hi>Moderation</hi> of your <hi>Government</hi> and your <hi>constancy</hi> to maintaine <hi>Religion,</hi> and your <hi>Piety</hi> in <hi>Exampling</hi> it.</p>
   <p>And as <hi>I</hi> thus <hi>beseech You</hi> for Your <hi>People</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> so doe <hi>I particularly</hi> for the <hi>three Professions</hi> which have a little suffer'd in these <hi>three</hi> most Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Libellers Persons.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And first for <hi>my</hi> owne <hi>Profession,</hi> J humbly begge of <hi>your Majesty</hi> to thinke M. <hi>Burton</hi> hath not in this many fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and am heartily sorry hee would needs <hi>lead.</hi> The best is, <hi>your Majesty</hi> knows what made his <hi>Rancour</hi> swell; Jle say no more.</p>
   <p>And for the <hi>Law,</hi> J truly <hi>honor</hi> it with my heart, and believe <hi>Mr. Prynn</hi> may seeke all the <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> (and
<pb facs="5"/>with a <hi>Candle</hi> too if he will) and scarce find such a <hi>Malevolent</hi> as himselfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi> And because hee hath so frequently thrust mistaken <hi>Law</hi> into these <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> to wrong the <hi>Governours</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse your good and well-minded <hi>people,</hi> and makes <hi>Burton</hi> and <hi>Bastwicke</hi> utter <hi>Law</hi> which, <hi>God</hi> knowes, they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand not, (for J doubt his Pen is in all the <hi>Pamphlets,</hi>) J doe humbly in the <hi>Churches</hi> name desire of <hi>your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie,</hi> that it may bee <hi>resolved</hi> by all the <hi>Reverend Iudges of ENGLAND,</hi> and then <hi>published</hi> by <hi>your Majesty,</hi> That our keeping <hi>Courts,</hi> and issuing <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse</hi> in our owne <hi>Names,</hi> and the like <hi>Exceptions</hi> formerly taken, and now renewed, are not against the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the <hi>Realme,</hi> (as 'tis most certaine they
<pb facs="6"/>are not) That so the <hi>Church-Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> may goe on cheerefully in their <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and the peoples mindes be <hi>quieted</hi> by this assurance, that neither the <hi>Law,</hi> nor their <hi>Liberty,</hi> as <hi>Subjects,</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by infringed.</p>
   <p>And for <hi>Physicke,</hi> the <hi>Profession</hi> is <hi>honourable</hi> and safe; and I know the <hi>Professors</hi> of it will remember that <hi>Corpus humanum,</hi> mans body, is that, about which their Art is conversant, not <hi>Corpus Ecclesiasticum,</hi> or <hi>Politicum,</hi> the Body of the Church, State, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. <hi>Bastwick</hi> onely hath been bold that way. But the <hi>Proverbe</hi> in the <hi>Gospell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">S. Luke, 4.23.</note> in the fourth of S. <hi>Luke</hi> is all I'le say to him, <hi>Medice, cura teip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum,</hi> Physician heale thy selfe. And yet let me tell <hi>your Majestie,</hi> J believe hee hath gained more by making the
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Church</hi> a <hi>Patient,</hi> than by all the <hi>Patients</hi> hee ever had beside.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Sir,</hi> both <hi>my selfe,</hi> and my <hi>Brethren</hi> have been very <hi>coursely</hi> used by the <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>pennes</hi> of these men, yet shall J never give <hi>your Majestie</hi> any sower <hi>counsell;</hi> J shall rather magnifie <hi>your Clemencie,</hi> that proceeded with these <hi>Offenders</hi> in a <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Mercie</hi> as well as <hi>Iustice:</hi> Since (as the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Iudges</hi> then declared) you might have justly called the <hi>Offendors</hi> into another <hi>Court,</hi> and put them to it in a way that might have exacted their <hi>Lives,</hi> for their stirring (as much as in them lay) of <hi>mutinie</hi> and <hi>sedition.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Yet this J shall be bold to say, and <hi>your Majesty</hi> may consider of it in your Wisdom; That one way of <hi>Government</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>is not alwayes either <hi>fit</hi> or <hi>safe,</hi> when the <hi>Humors</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> are in a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Change.</hi> Especially, when such men as these shall worke uyon <hi>your people,</hi> and labour to infuse into them such ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant <hi>Principles,</hi> to introduce a <hi>Parity</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth. Et, si non satis suâ sponte insaniant, instigare,</hi> And to spur on such among them as are too sharpely set already: And by this meanes make and prepare all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages for the <hi>Roman party</hi> to scorne Ʋs, and pervert them.</p>
   <p>J pray <hi>God blesse Your Majestie, Your Royall Consort,</hi> and <hi>Your hopefull Posterity,</hi> That You may Live in <hi>happinesse;</hi> Govern with <hi>Wisdom;</hi> Support Your people by <hi>Iustice;</hi> Relieve them by <hi>Mercy;</hi> Defend them by <hi>power</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>and <hi>successe;</hi> And Guide them in the <hi>true Religion</hi> by Your Lawes and most <hi>Religious Example,</hi> all the long and lasting dayes of Your <hi>Life:</hi> Which are and shall be the daily <hi>prayers</hi> of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Sacred Majesties most loyall SUBIECT, <hi>AND,</hi> Most dutifull SERVANT, as most bound, <hi>W. Cant.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>