<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most noble and vertuous
Prince Christianus King of Denmarke, &amp;c. Lodowik
Lloids most humble Gratulation at his
comming to great Britane.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108763_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06133</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16618</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most noble and vertuous
Prince Christianus King of Denmarke, &amp;c. Lodowik
Lloids most humble Gratulation at his
comming to great Britane.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The choyce of ievvels. By Lodowik Lloid Esquier</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the most noble and vertuous
Prince Christianus King of Denmarke, &amp;c. Lodowik
Lloids most humble Gratulation at his
comming to great Britane.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho can passe in silence (most noble Prince)
the ioyes and triumphes of these Halcyons
dayes, wherein <hi>Christianus</hi> King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi>
leauing his Kingdome, his Queen,
his Court, forsaking his imperiall Sceptor
and his Subiects, renouncing all princely
dignities, as a Prince that had his soule diuided betweene
Great <hi>Britane</hi> and <hi>Denmarke,</hi> esteeming more the one
halfe in <hi>Britane,</hi> than the whole in <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>O loue! excelling all loue, and that in a King, which the
heauens cannot subdue, the earth forget, nor fortune ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe;
of whose eternall fame, fame dare not lye.</p>
   <p>Let <hi>Maro</hi> cease to commend his Troiane <hi>Aeneas:</hi> let
<hi>Homer</hi> blush to aduance the greatnesse of <hi>Achilles,</hi> which
disguised himselfe like a woman, lest hee should goe from
Greece to Phrygia. Let Greece not name <hi>Vlisses</hi> to faine
madnesse, lest he should depart from Ithaca, and his wife
<hi>Penelope</hi> to Ilion.</p>
   <p>But <hi>Christianus</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> whom neither mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
Queen, Crownes, or Kingdome, could keepe him from
great <hi>Britan:</hi> where his Maiestie may of right more reioyce
of his princely Progenie, than King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Hercules</hi>
stocke in Macedonia, or <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> of <hi>gens Iulia</hi> in
Rome, sith the line of <hi>Hercules</hi> expired in <hi>Alexander,</hi>
and the stemme of <hi>Aeneas</hi> in the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> so that
Romanes now may say, <hi>Fuimus Troes;</hi> and Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
say, <hi>Fuimus Herculani.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But <hi>Great Britane</hi> was then neuer so great vnder
<hi>Brutus</hi> the first King, as nowe vnder <hi>Iames</hi> the second
<pb facs="4"/>
King, whose continuance well nye three thousand yeres,
is now againe like the Eagle renewed and reuiued, to be by
Gods goodnesse continued as long by the second <hi>Brutus,</hi>
that babes in cradles may say, <hi>Iubilate Britanni.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Much beholden we are to God, if we forget not God, and
great cause haue we to loue, and to honour his Highnesse in
great <hi>Britane:</hi> if we looke but vnto the greatnesse of his
loue to <hi>England</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, and now with
greater at this present to King <hi>Iames,</hi> if we shuld be deafe,
and not heare of it, or be dumbe, and not speak of it, heauen
and earth would accuse vs of too much ingratitude, wood
and stones should condemne vs of too much forgetfulnesse.</p>
   <p>Sith neither <hi>Syracusa,</hi> with their conuoyes and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
to the Romanes at <hi>Thrasymenum,</hi> neither <hi>Tyre</hi>
nor <hi>Sydon,</hi> with their Caedars of Lybanon to <hi>Ierusalem,</hi>
were so forward as <hi>Denmark</hi> was of late to <hi>England;</hi> but
as <hi>Masinissa</hi> sayd of the Romanes, that there was one kind
of people vpon the earth, the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> and among
that one people one <hi>Scipio,</hi> to whom he fully deuoted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
as one whose soule rested in <hi>Scipioes</hi> bodie: the like
sayd <hi>Hyra</hi> King of <hi>Tyre,</hi> of <hi>Salomon</hi> King of <hi>Israel.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But neither <hi>Hyra</hi> with his Sydonians, was more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to <hi>Salomon</hi> King of Israel, nor <hi>Masinissa</hi> with his Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midians
more louing to <hi>Scipio</hi> the Romane Consul, than
<hi>Christianus</hi> King of Denmarke, was to <hi>Iames</hi> King of
great Britane, whom neither heauens, earth, nor seas, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Kingdomes nor Court, could keepe that louing King
from his loue, to come from <hi>Denmark</hi> as a crowned starre
of the North, to shine in <hi>England,</hi> and to come to celebrate
and to renew the name of great <hi>Britane,</hi> to see the Queene
his Sister, his Nephew, and the rest of the Kings children,
the sound and sacred anchor of three Kingdomes.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
O loue immortall! not to be wayed in ballance, not with
measure to be measured, not knitted with <hi>Gordius</hi> knot to
be cut by <hi>Alexanders</hi> sword, neither with <hi>Hercules</hi> knot to be vnknitted by <hi>Phoebus,</hi> sith all prophane Histories
cannot allow but eight onely of the like loue, but not eight
Kings, most seldome two. For to see a King out of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
is as strange, as to see the Sunne out of the skie.</p>
   <p>Let <hi>England</hi> bee of equall loue with <hi>Denmarke,</hi> sith
loue is recompensed with loue, iustly weyed in equall bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,
not with <hi>Philips</hi> siluer swords in <hi>Greece,</hi> not with
<hi>Artaxerxes</hi> golden Archers in <hi>Persia,</hi> but with <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi>
weapons, one minde, one heart, and one soule, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
weapons, the triumphes thereof haue their euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
tropheis.</p>
   <p>Among such, what needs such leagues, and couenants
to dippe our weapons in blood, as the Scythians did? or die
our clothes in blood, as the Armenians did? or to drinke
blood out of our armes, as the Medians and Lydians did?</p>
   <p>Sith the league between great <hi>Britane</hi> and <hi>Denmarke</hi>
is consecrated with inward blood of mutuall hearts, and
confirmed with the entrals and bowels of naturall Parents,
that two Sunnes may be sooner found to agree in the skie,
than these two Kings to disagree on earth.</p>
   <p>This God hath appointed, nature confirmed, fates al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed,
and fortune thereto agreed.</p>
   <p>Hence grow the cause of our publicke Iubilies, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
feasts, our dayly tropheis, and perpetuall triumphes;
that as the Romans loued and agreed with the Sabins, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
thanks to their God in the Feast <hi>Consualia:</hi> so the
Britanes with the Danes, yeelding thanks to their
God <hi>Iehouah</hi> in their Feasts <hi>Scaenopegia.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>