<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Explanation of the wordes of art contained in this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108340_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05137</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15267</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108340</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Explanation of the wordes of art contained in this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lathams falconry or The faulcons lure, and cure : in two bookes. The first, concerning the ordering and training vp of all hawkes in generall; especially the haggard faulcon gentle. The second, teaching approued medicines for the cure of all diseases in them. Gathered by long practice and experience, and published for the delight of noble mindes, and instruction of young faulconers in things pertaining to this princely art. By Symon Latham. Gent</title>
                 <author>Latham, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 147, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="glossary">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>An Explanation of the wordes of art contained in this Booke.</head>
   <list>
      <head>B</head>
      <label>BAthing</label>
      <item> is when you set your Hawke to the water, to wash or bath her selfe, either abroad or in the house.</item>
      <label>Batting,</label>
      <item> or to batte is when a Hawk fluttereth with her wings either from the pearch or the mans fist, stryuing as it were to flie away, or get liberty.</item>
      <label>Bousing</label>
      <item> is when a Hawke drinketh often, and seemes to be continually thirsty.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>C</head>
      <label>CReance</label>
      <item> is a fine small long line of strong and euen twound Packthreed, which is fastened to the Hawks leash, when she is first lured.</item>
      <label>Ceasing</label>
      <item> is when a Hawke taketh any thing into her foot, and gripeth or holdeth it fast.</item>
      <label>Checke or to kill, </label>
      <item>Checke is when Crowes, Rookes, Pies, or
<pb facs="9"/>
other birds comming in the view of the Hawke, shee forsaketh her naturall flight to flie at them.</item>
      <label>Casting,</label>
      <item> is any thing that you giue your Hawk to clense her gorge with, whether it be flannell, thrummes, feathers, or such like. To cast a <hi>Hawke,</hi> is to take her in your hands before the pini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of her wings, and to hold her from bating or striuing, when you administer any thing vnto her.</item>
      <label>Cadge,</label>
      <item> is taken for that on which Faulconers carry many <hi>Hawkes,</hi> together when they bring them to sell.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>D</head>
      <label>DRopping</label>
      <item>is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> muteth directly downeward, in seuerall drops, and ierketh it not longwaies from her.</item>
      <label>Disclosed,</label>
      <item> is when young <hi>Hawkes</hi> are newly hatch't, and as it were disclosed from their shels.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>E</head>
      <label>ERie</label>
      <item> is the nest or place where a <hi>Hawke</hi> buildeth and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vp her young ones, whether in woods, rockes, or any other places.</item>
      <label>Endew,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> digesteth her meat, not onely put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ouer from her gorge, but also cleansing her pannell.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>G</head>
      <label>GOrge,</label>
      <item> is that part of the <hi>Hawke</hi> which first receiueth the meat, and is called the Craw or crop in other fowles.</item>
      <label>Gurgiting,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> is stuft or sufforated with any thing, be it meat or otherwise.</item>
   </list>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <list>
      <head>I</head>
      <label>INke,</label>
      <item> whether it be of Partridge, fowle, doues, or any other pray, is the necke from the head to the body.</item>
      <label>Intermew'd</label>
      <item> is from the first exchaunge of a <hi>Hawkes</hi> coat, or from her first mewing, till shee come to bee a white <hi>Hawke.</hi>
      </item>
      <label>Iesses,</label>
      <item> are those short straps of leather, which are fastned to the <hi>Hawks</hi> legs, &amp; so to the lease by varuels, anlets, or such like.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>L</head>
      <label>LVer</label>
      <item> is that whereto Faulconers call their young <hi>Hawkes</hi> by casting it vp in the aire, being made of feathers and leather in such wise that in the motion it lookes not vnlike a fowle.</item>
      <label>Lease</label>
      <item> or leashe is a small long thong of leather, by which the Faulconer holdeth his <hi>Hawke</hi> fast, folding it many times about their fingers.</item>
      <label>Lice,</label>
      <item> are a small kind of white vermin, running amongst the feathers of the Hawke.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>M</head>
      <label>MVting</label>
      <item> is the excrements or order which comes from <hi>Hawkes,</hi> and containeth both dunge and vrine.</item>
      <label>A <hi>Make-hawke</hi>
      </label>
      <item>is an old staunche flying Hawke, which being inur'd to her flight, wil easily instruct a younger Hawk to be waining in her pray.</item>
      <label>Managing,</label>
      <item> is to handle any thing with cunning accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true nature thereof</item>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <label>Mew,</label>
      <item>is that place, whether it be abroad or in the house where you set downe your Hawke, during the time that shee raseth her feathers.</item>
      <label>Mites,</label>
      <item> are a kind of vermine smaller then Lice, and most about the heads and nares of Hawkes.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>P</head>
      <label>PLumming,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> ceaseth a fowle, and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the feathers from the body.</item>
      <label>Plummage</label>
      <item> are small downie feather which the Hawke takes, or are giuen her for casting.</item>
      <label>Pelt,</label>
      <item> is the dead body of any fowle howsoeuer dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</item>
      <label>Pill,</label>
      <item> and pelfe of a fowle, is that refuse and broken re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines which are left after the <hi>Hawke</hi> hath beene releiued.</item>
      <label>Plume</label>
      <item> is the generall colour or mixtures of feathers in a <hi>Hawke,</hi> which sheweth her constitution.</item>
      <label>Pearch,</label>
      <item> is any thing whereon you set your <hi>Hawke,</hi> when shee is from your fist.</item>
      <label>Pray,</label>
      <item> is any thing that a <hi>Hawke</hi> killeth, and feedeth her selfe thereupon.</item>
      <label>Pannell,</label>
      <item> is that part of the <hi>Hawke</hi> next to the fundament whither the <hi>Hawke</hi> disgesteth her meat from her body.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>Q</head>
      <label>QVarrie,</label>
      <item> is taken for the fowle which is flowne at, and slaine at any time, especially when young <hi>Hawkes</hi> are flowne thereunto.</item>
   </list>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <list>
      <head>R</head>
      <label>RVfter-hood</label>
      <item> is the first hood whieh a <hi>Hawke</hi> weareth, being large, wide, and open behind.</item>
      <label>Reclaiming</label>
      <item> is to tame, make gentle, or to bring a <hi>Hawke</hi> to familiaritie with the man.</item>
      <label>Raised in flesh,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> growes fat, or prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in flesh.</item>
      <label>Ramage</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> is wild, coy, or disdainfull to the man, and contrary to be reclaimed.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>S</head>
      <label>SLiming,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> muteth from her longwaies in one intire substance, and doth not drop any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</item>
      <label>Stooping,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> being vpon her wings at the height of her pitch, bendeth violentlie downe to strike the fowle or any other pray.</item>
      <label>Summ'd</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> hath all her feathers, and is fit either to be taken from the Crie or Mew.</item>
      <label>Setting downe,</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> is put into the Mew.</item>
      <label>Sore-hawke,</label>
      <item> is from the first taking of her from the eiry, till shee haue mewed her feathers.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>T</head>
      <label>TRussing</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawke</hi> raseth a fowle aloft, and so descendeth downe with it to the ground,</item>
   </list>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <list>
      <head>V</head>
      <label>VNsumm'd</label>
      <item> is when a <hi>Hawkes</hi> feathers are not come forth, or els not com'd home to their full length.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>VV</head>
      <label>VVEathering</label>
      <item> is when you set your <hi>Hawke</hi> abroad to take the aire, either by day or night, in the frost, or in the sunne, or at any other season.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>