<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108050_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18947</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5364</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108050</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Popes deadly wound : tending to resolue all men, in the chiefe and principall points now in controuersie betweene the papists and vs. Written by T.C. and published by Master Doctor Burges, now preacher to the English troopes in the Pallatinate</title>
                 <author>Clarke, Thomas, of Sutton Coldfield</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 200 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EE that vndertakes to commend another mans writings vnto the view and reading of men, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures his owne repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation therein, as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants doe their stocke in other mens ships. And there be two sorts of men, that doe and may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture more boldly then others, either goods or credit: First, such as haue so much to spare, as that the losse of their aduenture will not pinch them; or such as haue so little to aduenture, as no losse can hurt them much: Yet is there a middle sort that doe aduenture in hope of good returnes.</p>
   <p>J take my selfe a man not vtterly desperate, yet of poore estate, knowing nothing in my selfe that
<pb facs="3"/>might procure respect vnto another mans wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; vnlesse perhaps my acquaintance with many men of sundry places, the purchase of my trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some pilgrimage, or the louing fauour which God of his goodnesse hath giuen mee with many, far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my worth: But if I had more reputation in the Church of God and my Countrey then euer J shall haue, I would not feare to aduenture all mine owne praises in the praise of this little Booke, and the Author thereof.</p>
   <p>The Author thereof, Master <hi>Thomas Clarke,</hi> one of my parishoners in <hi>Sutton-Coldfield,</hi> I know to be a man of much grauity, piety, and honesty, &amp; for one of his sort to be admired for his vnwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried paines in reading such Authors as hee could, gathering out of them the pith of their discourses or disputes, and labouring to improue all, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the setling of his owne iudgement, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to the staying and satisfying of others popishly inclined, by conference or by writing: wherein also his successe hath exceeded the haruest of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other men, better languaged and more learned then be.</p>
   <p>Touching this his booke, it is true that onely the moulding of the Arguments against Popery is his
<pb facs="3"/>owne, fitter perhaps for the vulgar sort, then more exquisite pieces. The matter it selfe is to be found in the writings of our learned Countreymen, disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in large or many bookes, whereof some are not so easie to be had: But here is compiled and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted together in this popular forme, and in a stile (so farre as I can iudge) neither curious nor dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute, but well becomming the man and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
   <p>The end and ayme of this good man, I perswade my selfe to be honest and holy, not applause of men, nor gaine of money, but a true desire to informe his countreymen that cannot or will not heare often or reade much in the knowledge of the truth, which detayning or reclayming them from Popery, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them in true religion established in our Land, might yeeld them better Christians, better Subiects, better Neighbours.</p>
   <p>Many haue long called for this Booke vpon sight of some part of it, or report of others; these I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose will gladly reade it: such as neuer heard of it, or of the man, may please to make a tryall, whether or no they may finde in it, that which may refresh the memory of learned and diligent men in much breuity, or bring light vnto the ignorant with as
<pb facs="4"/>much perspicuity; which is, I confesse, my opinion of the Booke.</p>
   <p>God quicken vp our hearts to more zeale for the Gospell, and against popery, the zeale whereof in our aduersaries should prouoke vs to more zeale, or will condemne vs though it helpe not them; God also blesse this good old-Man that hath spent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe for common good, aad blesse all meanes that may any way aduance the Kingdome of our Lord Iesus, whether the scepter of Gouernement, the sword of Warre, the preaching of the Gospell, or Pen, or Print of wel-aduised and wel-affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. Farewell.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thine, to serue thee in the Lord, IOHN BVRGES Parson of</hi> Sutton-Coldfield, <hi>in Warwickshire, and now Preacher to the English troopes in the seruice of the KING of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>for the defence of the Pallatinate, vnder the command of S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> Horatio Veere <hi>Knight, Lord General.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>