<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An approbation of the historie ensuing, by me RICHARD HAKLVYT.</title>
           <author>Hakluyt, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108481_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05331</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15481</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108481</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An approbation of the historie ensuing, by me RICHARD HAKLVYT.</title>
                 <author>Hakluyt, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A geographical historie of Africa, written in Arabicke and Italian by Iohn Leo a More, borne in Granada, and brought vp in Barbarie. Wherein he hath at large described, not onely the qualities, situations, and true distances of the regions, cities, townes, mountaines, riuers, and other places throughout all the north and principall partes of Africa; but also the descents and families of their kings ... gathered partly out of his owne diligent obseruations, and partly out of the ancient records and chronicles of the Arabians and Mores. Before which, out of the best ancient and moderne writers, is prefixed a generall description of Africa, and also a particular treatise of all the maine lands and isles vndescribed by Iohn Leo. ... Translated and collected by Iohn Pory, lately of Goneuill and Caius College in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Leo, africanus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60, 420 pages, folded plates, map, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="sanction">
   <head>
      <hi>An approbation of the historie ensuing, by me</hi> RICHARD HAKLVYT.</head>
   <div type="part">
      <p>BEing mooued to publish mine opinion as touching this present Historie of <hi>Iohn Leo;</hi> I do hold and affirme it to be the verie best, the most particular, and methodicall, that euer was written, or at least that hath come to light, concerning the countries, peoples, and affaires of Africa. For which cause, and knowing well the suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of the translator, my selfe was the first and onely man that perswaded him to take it in hand. Wherein how diligently and faithfully he hath done his part, and how he hath enlarged and graced this Geographicall historie out of others, the best anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and moderne writers, by adding a description of all those African maine lands and isles, and other matters verie notable, which <hi>Iohn Leo</hi> himselfe hath omitted: I referre to the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all iudiciall and indifferent Readers.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Richard Hakluyt.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb n="58" facs="36"/>
      <p>VNto this approbation of master <hi>Richard Hakluyt,</hi> I holde it not altogither amisse to adioine the testimonies of certaine moderne writers, the most approoued and famous for their skill in Geographie and historie, which they haue also pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely set downe in commendation of this author of ours <hi>Iohn Leo.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>First therefore master <hi>Iohn Baptista Ramusius,</hi> Secretarie to the State of Venice, and a man of singular iudgement and diligence in these matters, in his epistle Dedicatorie before the third edition of his first volume of voia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, speaking of the manifold difficulties which he vnderwent to bring the important discourses therein, to light, writteth vnto learned <hi>Fracastorius</hi> in manner following.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Oltra che gli essemplari che mi son venute alle mani, &amp;c.</head>
      <p>MOreouer (saith he) those copies which haue come to my hands, haue beene extremely fowle and vncorrect; a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sufficient to discourage the minde of any man, though neuer so forward and resolute, were it not sustained by considering what vnspeakable delight these discourses will breed vnto all those that are studious in Geography; and most especially this of Africa written by <hi>Iohn Leo.</hi> Concerning which part of the world, euen till these our daies, we haue had no knowledge in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of any other authour, or at leastwise neuer any informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion so large, and of so vndoubted truth. But what do I heere speake of the delight which those that are learned and studious shall reape heereby? As though it were not a matter which will affoord also very much satisfaction vnto the greatest Lords and Princes? Whom it concerneth more then any other to know the secrets and particularities of this African part of the world, togither with the situations of all the regions, prouinces, and cities thereof, and the dependences, which the princes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple haue one towards another. For albeit they may haue some aduertisements &amp; instructions from others that haue personally trauailed these countries, &amp; may think their writings &amp; discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to be very large; yet am I well assured, that hauing once read this booke of <hi>Iohn Leo,</hi> and throughly considered the matters therein contained and declared, they will esteeme the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="59" facs="36"/>
of all others, in comparison of this, to be but briefe, vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and of little moment: so great will be the fruit which to their exceeding contentment, all readers shall reape heereby, &amp;c. Thus farre <hi>Ramusius.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>