<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the conscionable, and Ingenious Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108259_Bo1_3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14421</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15363</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108259</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the conscionable, and Ingenious Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A triumph of truth. Or Declaration of the doctrine concerning euangelicall counsayles; lately deliuered in Oxford by Humfrey Leech M. of Arts, &amp; minister. With relation of sondry occurrents, and particularly of D. King, the Vicechancellour, his exorbitant proceedings agains the sayd H.L. vpon his constant propugnation thereof. Also the peculiar motiues, ensuing therevpon, which perswaded him to renounce the faction of hereticall congregations, &amp; and to embrace the vnity of the Catholique Church</title>
                 <author>Leech, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 135, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="89" facs="54"/>
   <head>To the conscionable, and Ingenious Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>THOVGH</hi> the generall motiues vnto the <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion, are many, and vvaightie; yet the particular, vvhich issued out of this present businesse, vvere such, as cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced my vnderstanding, and svvayed my affection to approue, and embrace the same.</p>
   <p>ƲƲherefore <hi>(courteous Reader)</hi> aswel to procure thy good, as to iustify my selfe, and to satisfy others, J haue communicated them vnto thy vievv. For matter; they are the same novv, as vvhen J conceiued them in the beginning: for māner; they are brought forth in somevvhat a different shape.</p>
   <p>Thus much may suffice for thy instruction concerning these Motiues. Onely J may not forget to aduertise thee; that whereas through out their titles, J vse this perpetuall stile: <hi>The Protestantes &amp;c.</hi> (hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="90" facs="55"/> the most learned amongst them, differ in iudgement from the common sort: and in this respect, cannot be cōcluded in the generality of <hi>all</hi>) I haue not done this vvithout good consideration.</p>
   <p>For though the principall deuines in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> do vtterly distast the vayne opinions of <hi>D. King,</hi> and such like; yet, since by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique profession of the truth, they giue not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient notice vnto the vvorld of their <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> positions, J must inuolue them also in this cōmon accusation. And as they, against their knovvledge, do suffer a preiudice to fall vpon God his truth,<note place="margin">Corde cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ad iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiam; ore fit confessio ad salutem</note> they must likevvise, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their vvil, suffer an infamy to remaine vpon their ovvne persons.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>