<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his beloued Mother, I. K. sen∣deth greeting in the Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108651_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01136</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11248</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108651</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his beloued Mother, I. K. sen∣deth greeting in the Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at the christening of a certaine Iew : at London, by Iohn Foxe. Conteining an exposition of the xi. chapter of S. Paul to the Romanes. Translated out of Latine into English by Iames Bell</title>
                 <author>Foxe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>234 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="text">
   <pb facs="118"/>
   <head>To his beloued Mother, I. K. sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth greeting in the Lorde.</head>
   <p>THE desire that I haue to heare of your continuāce, which Christ Iesus in the day of this his battell which shortly shall end to the confusion of his proud enimies, neither by tong, neither yet by penne can I expresse, beloued Mother. Assuredly it is such that it vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth, and ouercommeth all remembrance &amp; solicitude, which the fleshe vseth to take for feeding and defence of herselfe. For in euery realme and nation God wil stirre vp some one or other to minister those thinges that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to this wretched life, and if men wil ceasse to doe their office, yet will hee sende his rauens: so that in euery place, perchance I may finde some fethers to my body. But alas where I shal finde children to be begotten vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by the worde of life, that can I not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently consider. And therfore the spiritual life of such as somtime boldly pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>essed Christ (god knoweth) is to my hearte more deare then all the glory, riches, and honour in the earth. And the falling backe of such men, as I heare dayly</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>