<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Chri∣stian Reader, conteyning godly exhortation.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108651_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01136</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11248</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108651</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Chri∣stian Reader, conteyning godly exhortation.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at the christening of a certaine Iew : at London, by Iohn Foxe. Conteining an exposition of the xi. chapter of S. Paul to the Romanes. Translated out of Latine into English by Iames Bell</title>
                 <author>Foxe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>234 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader, conteyning godly exhortation.</head>
   <p>FOrasmuch as the summe, &amp; absolute perfection of al our righteousnesse, consisteth in the onely faith and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Iesu Christ, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom al humane pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and puyssaunce is vneffectuall: without whome, no prouident policie preuayleth: ne yet any force, or actiuitie of naturall operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can bring any thing to passe: no honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ornament of vertue, no excellencie of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite learning, is auaylable: according to the testimonie of the Lord himselfe, <hi>Withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> me ye can do nothing:</hi> what ought we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> seely mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall wretches regard more entierly, then that by due proceeding; in dayly renewed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creases of this same faith, we not only cleaue fast to this Iesu Christ, the assured &amp; vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted chiefetaine &amp; Prince of life? And cōuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him into the very intrailes of our soules, we throughly possesse him, as fast enclosed in a certaine holy Oratorie: but also endeuour


<pb facs="4"/>
by all meanes possibly, to be most neerely ioyned vnto him, to be incorporate wholly in him, &amp; made members of his owne body? For performance wherof behoueth vs, aboue all other, to be guyded by his conduct and coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>el chiefely. <hi>Searche the Scriptures</hi> (sayth he) <hi>for they beare witnes of me.</hi> Which saying S. Peter the Apostle doeth verifie, aduertizing vs of the same faith: <hi>And we haue</hi> (sayeth he) <hi>a more s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re worde of the Prophetes, whereunto whiles yee take heede, as vnto a lyght that shineth in a darke place, ye doe well, vntill the dawne of the day appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, &amp; the day starre aryse in your hearts.</hi> Yea, the Lorde him selfe in an other place sendeth vs backe to the scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Law and the Prophets, as vnto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible preceptes, and rules of pure and true doctrine. And albeit I may not denye that testimonie of S. Paul to be most true, where he sayth, That faith is a gift of God, yssuing from his free mercy &amp; bountie: yet doth he not: thereby meanewhyles exclude other lawfull and ordinarie meanes, taught for the better attainement thereof. As where he say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Fayth commeth by hearing, &amp; hearing by the word of God.</hi> So that their error is so much the more blameworthy,<note place="margin">Fides impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita.</note> who contented with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, and confused faith (as they tearme it)


<pb facs="4"/>
be of opinion, that to the rude &amp; vnlettered people, sufficeth ynough to beleeue those things onely, that all other men do beleeue. But this common faith seemed not sufficient to the auncient fathers, in that purer age of the primitiue &amp; Apostolique Church: who though mistrusted not the lessons &amp; instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Apostles, yet were they also in this respect adiudged prayseworthy, because they did conferre the doctrine, which they receyued of the Apostles, with the bookes of the Law, and the prophets: which obseruatiō of the elders was of no smal importaunce, to procure credite to the establishment of faith. But the state of Christianitie is nowe come (I know not to what passe) that this Christian faith, which behoued to be most deepely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in the hearts of euery of vs, is either not so well garnyshed in manye of vs, as it ought to be: in others very faynt and feeble: and in some others skarse any resemblaunce at all appearing, which slender portion and sparkle of faith, be it neuer so small, as is not altogether to be reiected, so neyther is this wonderfull sluggishnes, and retcheles secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the men in our age, in any respect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable: of whome some ouergreedily busied


<pb facs="5"/>
in worldly affaires, some feeding their fansies vpon fonde delights, do either make no esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate at al, of that inestimable Iewel of faith, which only enricheth to the inheritaunce of eternall life, or at the least, are not so diligent searchers of the same, as they ought to be. To clime vnto honour, what attemptes and toyle do some vndertake? howe filthily do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers turmoyle them selues, in raking riches together? how dayntily some men besmeare them selues in perfumes, and pleasures? who because they knowe, they can not lyue here for euer, &amp; do determine to liue godly neuer, yeeld them selues wholly to liue delicately &amp; wantonly. To be aduaunced in Court, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spire to prelacie and ecclesiasticall dignitie, &amp; to be a magistrat ouer the multitude, who doth not accōpt it matter most honorable? who adiudgeth not that man to be most for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, that by hooke or crooke hath cratcht wonderfull possessions together? who thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not that man to be most happy, that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth most pleasurably? And what shal I say of those artes &amp; sciences, which procure gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lucre, &amp; estimation of the world? wherin whyles wee sweate and swinke all our lyues long, scarse one minute can bee spared, no


<pb facs="5"/>
thought employed to the things which lead vnto Christ. I speake not of them, who seme to sauour of no sappe of religion, nor are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with one drop of faith: who resembling rather Diagoristes and Protagoristes, then Christians, are so vtterly fallen from Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anisme, to Atheisme, that, measuring this life with the present pleasures thereof, they doe beleeue nothing holy, good, or worthy to be embraced, but those plausible workes &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of nature, wherewith our eyes &amp; senses are delyghted most. There is also an other crewe &amp; company, not much vnlike to these other, who perceyuing Christian religion as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulted, rackt, and rent in sonder (as they say) with sects, schismes and contrarieties of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, do persuade them selues that religion to be best, that will acquaint it selfe with no religion at all.</p>
   <p>What shall I say of them, wherof the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is exceeding great, who with full mouth do professe true religion it selfe, and will not deny, but that they do beleeue in Iesu Christ: but beyng demaunded, wherefore they doe beleeue in him: what the will of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Christ is: what Grace is: what &amp; how great promises are layde vp in stoare for vs


<pb facs="6"/>
in Christ: howe glorious the Maiestie &amp; roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie of Christes kingdome is: how inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the glorie of his riches be: what is the breadth, the length, the depth &amp; the heyght thereof: howe woonderfull the loue of his knowledge is: how great the force &amp; power of faith is: and vpon what principal pillers &amp; foundations it is buylded, they can render scarse any reason at all. For as much therfore as the infallible certeintie, &amp; true vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of these thinges can be attayned vnto rightly, from no where els, then from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly closets of sacred Scriptures: it shalbe very requisite and needefull, that euery of vs employ al our senses &amp; povvers of the mind, continually exercised in the same. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer Christian diuinitie is tossed, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyled to &amp; fro, with innumerable intricate entangled and wandering questions, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth faith one selfe same neuerthelesse both pure &amp; simple: and as it is but one, so ought all men necessarily be endued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wholly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> That is to say, that we all know Christ, that we repose all our ankerholde of affiaunce in Christ, &amp; that we imprint Christ in the bowels of our soule, as wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the mouth of God the father,


<pb facs="6"/>
seeing there is no name besides this name giuen vnder heauen, in whome the treasure &amp; hope of mans felicitie may safely shroude it selfe. Let Princes therefore learne to know this Christ: Let subiects attend vpon him: let auncient fathers take hold of him: Let yong men embrace him: Let the riche enlarge their treasury with this precious Iewel: &amp; let the poore seek their reliefe to be refreshed by him: who in deed cā els where by no meanes be found more easily, then in the very sacred wellspringes of the propheticall Scriptures: notwithstanding who so is desirous to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this ioyfull Iewel, must first of necessitie make earnest and diligent searche therfore. For this precious pearle is not allotted to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but vnto them, that vvill searche for it: nor doth this heauēly Manna feede any, but the hungry. The soule must be very thirstie, that must taste of this liquour that gusheth frō out the cōduyte pipes of eternal life. This gate is not opened to the lazy &amp; slouthfull droane, but vnto him that wil knocke. <hi>Knocke</hi> (sayth he) <hi>and it shalbe opened vnto you. Seeke, and ye shall finde.</hi> All persons without exception are graunted free accesse to the treasurie of this kingdome: It is layde open for all estates,


<pb facs="7"/>
but all catch it not, except such as scratche and offer force for it: for what (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeche you) is more forcible then fayth? what more mightie, if it be true faith, if it be liuely faith, yea if it be true Christian fayth? as that which displaying banner vnder his captaine Christ, doeth fight in heauen, and combat in the ayre, against the princes and powers of the ayre, against spiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses from aboue: doeth keepe continuall warres against infinite hazards in the earth, and in hell agaynst Beelzebub, agaynst the furies &amp; gates of the hells, yea against death fighteth for eternall life, against the Law for righteousnes, and against horror of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for freedome and peace.</p>
   <p>Therefore considering this faith is of such power and efficacie, yea so necessarie to be frequented in all the actions of mans lyfe: what remayneth from henceforth, but that all and euery of vs, crye out vnto the same Christ, and beseeche him to impart vnto vs, the true knowledge and vnderstanding of him selfe, to enlighten the glimmering sight of our dazeled fleshly eyes, with the most bryght and orient beames of this gladsome saith, and that he wil vouchsafe at length, to


<pb facs="7"/>
bring that to passe in vs, that he vsed some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with his Apostles, when as he discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them vpon the way, as they trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the holie Scriptures? For so we reade, <hi>And he, beganne at Moses, and at all the Prophets, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted vnto them in all the scriptures, the things which were written of him.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luke .24.</note> And immediately after, <hi>Then opened hee their vnderstanding, that they might know the Scriptures, &amp; said vnto them, Thus it is written.</hi> Whereby appeareth playnly, the duetie and office that is required in the expositours of the holy Scriptures: To witte, that omitting all superfluous circumlocutions, and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable quiddities of questions, they instruct the people in those principles, &amp; rules of the Scriptures chiefely, which auaile most to the nourishment and encrease of faith. In which kinde of argument, forasmuch as in this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon behoued me to frame my simple skill, according to the estate of the present mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and opportunitie of time, and that it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good to my friendes, to haue this litle treatise published in print, to the viewe of the common people, as not altogether vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the reading: I haue yeelded to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, that it myght be imprinted: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my meaning was at the first, to haue


<pb facs="8"/>
the same directed to the behoof of the Iewes chiefely, yet (I trust) it vvil not be altogether vnprofitable to the Christian readers. First, because it may so be, yea I feare me, may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so iustly be feared, lest amongst the nomber of thē, which say that they beleue in Christ, some happely vvil be found, in vvhose lippes onely this faith rolleth at large, and hath not yet pearced any deeper, nor taken roote in their heartes, nor are as yet so sufficiently learned, as (if matter come to tryall and proofe) they can render a true and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted reason of this their faith. Moreouer, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte that a man stande assured and stedfast in the certeintie of his faith, yet vvhat faith is there so sure, constant and vnuanqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>able, but may be made more stable and perfect? For if S. Paul did see sometime as in a darke ryddle: if the Apostles (notvvithstanding so many miracles vvrought in their sight) nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded yet the interpretation of Scriptures: if those vvhich receaued the vvoorde by the preaching of Paul,<note place="margin">Act .17.</note> did neuerthelesse cōferre his doctrine vvith the Scriptures, to see, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they agreed together<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as is recorded in the Actes of the Apostles: vvhat shoulde let vs to doe the like? that by this meanes, vve


<pb facs="8"/>
also myght encrease dayly, from fayth to faith. Finally for as much as our auncient &amp; deadly enemie doeth not more cruelly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne, nor more outragiously assaile any one thing, so much, as this our faith in Christ: surely I iudge this aboue all other most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite, that euery of vs haue especial regard, to be (as much as is possible) armed and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vvith this target of faith, that vve may couragiously encounter all attempts and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saults of the deuill: vvhereunto hovve auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable this litle Sermon vvill be, I knovv not: that let Christ our Lorde him selfe see vnto, and giue his mercifull ayde therein. I for my slender capacitie, haue perfourmed vvhat I vvas able, and as much as the Lorde graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me: vvhome I most heartily beseeche, to blesse and encrease thy holy studies (godly Reader) and to direct the same to the honour &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his name. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>