<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE 
Matrons and Mirrours of 
gratious Lady Anne Dutches of Sommerset, 
right honourable Lady Brigirt Countesse 
Bedford, the right vvorshipfull Misresse PHILIP PRY∣DEAVX,
Mistresse LVCE COTTN, and Mistresse
Mary VVatts, EPHRAIM PAGITT wisheth
the encrease of all spirituall graces meete
for this life, and a full assuraunce of
that honour whiche la∣steth
for euer.</title>
           <author>Wilson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108368_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE 
Matrons and Mirrours of 
gratious Lady Anne Dutches of Sommerset, 
right honourable Lady Brigirt Countesse 
Bedford, the right vvorshipfull Misresse PHILIP PRY∣DEAVX,
Mistresse LVCE COTTN, and Mistresse
Mary VVatts, EPHRAIM PAGITT wisheth
the encrease of all spirituall graces meete
for this life, and a full assuraunce of
that honour whiche la∣steth
for euer.</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The book of Ruth expounded in twenty eight sermons, by Levves Lauaterus of Tygurine, and by hym published in Latine, and now translated into Englishe by Ephraim Pagitt, a childe of eleuen yeares of age</title>
                 <author>Lavater, Ludwig</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 159, 159-163 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
Matrons and Mirrours of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
gratious Lady Anne Dutches of Sommerset, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
right honourable Lady Brigirt Countesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
Bedford, the right vvorshipfull Mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>resse PHILIP PRY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEAVX,
Mistresse LVCE COTT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>N, and Mistresse
Mary VVatts, EPHRAIM PAGITT wisheth
the encrease of all spirituall graces meete
for this life, and a full assuraunce of
that honour whiche la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth
for euer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue not that libertye (most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Ladies and graue Matrons) in
this my Epistle, to set foorth the
praises either of you, or of the work
which I haue labored to send vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you in Englishe: But a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced
as in an Apollogie, to defende my selfe, that
I a child of eleuen yeares of age haue dealt in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of religion, and presumed to dedicate the same to
you. For the first I aunswere, there is no age freed,
nor exempted from the knowledge of God, and the
setting forth of his glorye, so farre as he hath en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
them, but as children are asson<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> subiect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to
death as the olde, so must they learne to dye and to
yeeld accompt of that one talent which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> have
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ether they haue emploied it to the vse of God, who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it them, or no. Besides that I was emploied in
it, by the appointment of those my frends, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
of the interest they haue in me, the loue they
beare mee, the good they wish to come of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
to suche step-parents and children in lawe,
which vnderstand not Latine, that I could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
them.</p>
   <p>For the second, it is not presumption, that hath
made me to dedicate it vnto you (right Honourable
Ladies and worthy Gentlewomen) but a desire to
yeeld thankes for the comfort which I, my brother
&amp; Sisters (poore children) haue receiued by the
kindenes, which hath often come from you to vs &amp;
our parents in our necessities. Therefore I beseeche
your H. and Wor. in good part to take this booke
which I with all humilitie do heere offer vnto you,
humbly praying that you widowes will receiue into
<hi>England,</hi> these good widowes, <hi>Naomie</hi> &amp; <hi>Ruth,</hi>
come out of <hi>Moab,</hi> sent as excellent paterns of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
and godlynes, by the holy ghost to all christians,
described and lineated by the sermons of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
Minister, Maister <hi>Lauaterus</hi> of <hi>Tygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi>
Like will to like, widowes come to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes,
disdain thē not for their pouertye. Haue they
bene in trouble? so haue al you? Was <hi>Naomie</hi> a
soiourner in a straunge countrie, and lost there her
husband? so haue some of you. Did <hi>Ruth</hi> leaue her
countrie for religion? So haue some of you. Were
they disdayned, skoft and scorned at? so are you of
<pb facs="3"/>
the worlde for your zeale in religion, and loue to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
glorious gospell of Iesus Christ. Of the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>,
are you come of noble birth? are you of honorable
calling? so was <hi>Naomie</hi> of the royall and kingly
tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Ruth</hi> was maried to <hi>Boaz,</hi> a
man that sate in the gates of <hi>Iudah,</hi> iudged <hi>Israel,</hi>
and was great grandfather to <hi>Dauid</hi> the king, end
so from these good women came kinges and princes
to rule Gods people, and at length, the hope, ioy and
comfort of all mankinde, our Sauiour Christ accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the fleshe. Therefore Noble and Wor. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons,
I pray you take it in good part, that I haue
bene so bold to ioyne you of seuerall estates togeather
in this short Epistle: but because yee are all in one
estate of widdow-hode, in one course of religion, in
like regarde of the weale of vs and our parentes,
I was so bolde to knitte you together, entreating you
that my childishnes, which in this I haue shewed, your
wonted vertues may beare out toward your selues,
and as a vaile to couer from others, till God giue
me more knowledg and vnderstanding to amend it.
And I humbly pray the Lord to grant you as much
comfort in your own children, and in your sonnes and
daughters in law, as euer <hi>Naomie</hi> had in <hi>Ruth.</hi>
And as they had rest after their traueils, and
ioy after their sorrowes, so the Lord geue
you peace of consciences heere, and
after this pilgrimage that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
rest which neuer shal
be taken from you.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>