<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An introduction to the en∣suing verses.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108718_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19383</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5810</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An introduction to the en∣suing verses.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Odcombian banquet: dished foorth by Thomas the Coriat, and serued in by a number of noble wits in prayse of his Crudities and Crambe too. Asinus portans mysteria</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>An introduction to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing verses.</head>
   <p>I Here present vnto thee (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) the encomiasticke and panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick verses of some of the worthiest spirits of this Kingdome, composed by persons of eminent quality and marke, as well for dignity as excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of wit; such as haue vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to descend so low as to dignifie and illustrate my lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubrations without any demerit of theirs <note n="a" place="margin">Mistake mee not Reader. I referre this word to the word Lucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brations.</note> (I doe inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously confesse) with the singular fruits of their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant inuentions, which they haue expressed in the best and most learned languages of the world, two onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, which are the <note n="b" place="margin">Ironia.</note> Welch and Irish. But in that I exhibite vnto thy view such a great multitude of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, as no booke whatsoeuer printed in England these hundred yeeres had the like written in praise thereof; ascribe it not I intreate thee to any ambitious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of mee, as that I should craue to obtrude so many to the world in praise of my booke: For I can assure thee, I sollicited not halfe those worthy wights for these verses that I now divulge; a great part of them beeing sent vnto me voluntarily from diuers of my friends, frō whom I expected no such courtesie. At last when I saw the multitude of them to increase to so great a number,


<pb facs="10"/>
I resolued to put aboue a thousand of them into an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex expurgatorius,</hi> and to detaine them from the presse.</p>
   <p>Wherevpon the Princes Highnesse (who hath most graciously deigned to bee the <note n="c" place="margin">You shal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> the meaning of this word in a marginal note vpon the verses imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>
      <hi>Hyperaspist</hi> and <hi>Moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas</hi> of my booke) vnderstanding that I meant to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse so many, gaue me a strict and expresse comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to print all those verses which I had read to his Highnesse. Since then that ineuitable necessity hath beene imposed vpon mee, I haue heere communicated that copious rhapsody of poems to the world that my learned friends haue bountifully bestowed vpon mee; wherein many of them are disposed to glance at mee with their free and mery iests, for which I desire, thee (courteous Reader) to suspend thy censure of mee till thou hast read ouer my whole booke.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>