<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right vertu∣ous, &amp; most Honorable La∣dies, the Lady Sara Hastings, the Lady Theodosia Dudley, the Lady Mary Wing∣field, and the Lady Mary Dy-er.</title>
           <author>Olney, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108699_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19352</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5775</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108699</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right vertu∣ous, &amp; most Honorable La∣dies, the Lady Sara Hastings, the Lady Theodosia Dudley, the Lady Mary Wing∣field, and the Lady Mary Dy-er.</title>
                 <author>Olney, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essayes : By Sir William Corne-Waleys the younger, Knight</title>
                 <author>Cornwallis, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mattes, Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Mattes, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Read, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>584 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Right vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; most Honorable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the Lady Sara Hastings, the Lady Theodosia Dudley, the Lady Mary Wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, and the Lady Mary Dy-er.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIght Noble Ladyes.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Although I know that worthy Knight, the Author of thèse Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayes, hateth nothing more then comming in publick, yet many Copies of them being bestowed, by often transcription (as it many times hapneth) they might haue
<pb facs="5"/>
beene by a mercenary hand fowly corrupted and altered in sence, and both in his absence and mine, deliuered to some Printer, who to make present gaine, would haue published them vnpolished, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without any correction: to preuent which, hauing in my hands a perfect Copy, and being inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly priuate with his priuatest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, I thought it better to divulge them, then to aduenture that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard. To couer this presumption, I haue made your Ladiships part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the patronage, because I am sure howsoeuer he shall dislike the publishing, yet it shall please him that your Ladiships names are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in the forefront of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. I know also, that if himselfe could haue been perswaded to make
<pb facs="5"/>
them thus vulgar, out of his owne choise, to your Ladiships they had beene directed, of whose vertues I haue heard his owne tongue vtter such worthy praises, that I doubt not but his Heart (which alwayes agreeth with his tongue) and all his other powers, are, and shall euer be consecrated to your Ladiships seruice.</p>
   <p>The worke of it selfe being ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, it cannot but be gracious to your Ladiships: for in this back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Age (too much declining from Vertue,) who are more fit to protect and defend her then your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, who are so neerely allied to Vertue, that she hath chosen you for her Temple, therein inshrined her selfe, and in you onely desireth to be adored. Your Ladiships are
<pb facs="6"/>
neerely conioyned in blood, three of you being Sisters by nature, the fourth by Loue: but that coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is nothing so noble (although very noble) as that sweete combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of your spirits, which are all so deuoted to Good, that though there be a Quaternity of your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, yet those persons are so guided by those Angel-like spirits, that they make vp a delightfull harmony, a Soule-rauishing Musick, and a most pleasing and perfect Simpathy of Affections.</p>
   <p>If then your Ladiships shall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize these Essayes, what vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous tongues shall dare to infect them? If you like, who will dislike them? what you allowe, nothing but Enuie, Detraction, and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance wil disallow, whose infectious
<pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reaths shall bee so purified by the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>recious Balme of your Vertues, that all shall sodainlie dissolue into the sweet Aire of Applause. They are now (Honorable Ladies) your owne, being freelie giuen to your Ladiships by the true hearted Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their Author, and by the hands of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Ladiships most humbly deuoted</hi> Henry Olney.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>