<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honorables, &amp; puissant Barons, Robert Deuorex Earle of Essex, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, great Master of the Horse for her Highnes: And vnto Thomas Lord Burgh, Baron of Gayns-burgh, Lord Gouernour of the towne of Bryell, and the Fortes of Newmanton, &amp; Cleyborow in North-Holland for her Maiestie: health, &amp; increase of honour.</title>
           <author>Bradshaw, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108276_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108276</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honorables, &amp; puissant Barons, Robert Deuorex Earle of Essex, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, great Master of the Horse for her Highnes: And vnto Thomas Lord Burgh, Baron of Gayns-burgh, Lord Gouernour of the towne of Bryell, and the Fortes of Newmanton, &amp; Cleyborow in North-Holland for her Maiestie: health, &amp; increase of honour.</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The shepherds starre : now of late seene, and at this hower to be obserued merueilous orient in the East: which bringeth glad tydings to all that may behold her brightnes, hauing the foure elements with the foure capitall vertures in her, which makes her elementall and a vanquishor of all earthly humors. Described by a gentleman late of the right worthie and honorable the Lord Burgh, his companie &amp; retinue in the Briell in North-holland</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honorables, &amp; puissant Barons, <hi>Robert Deuorex</hi> Earle of Essex, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, great Master of <hi>the Horse for her Highnes: And vnto Thomas Lord</hi> Burgh, Baron of Gayns-burgh, Lord Gouernour of the towne of Bryell, and the Fortes of Newmanton, &amp; Cleyborow in North-Holland for her Maiestie: health, &amp; increase of honour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue read, I take it, right honorables, of <hi>Polycletus</hi> rule:<note place="margin">Polyclet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Regula.</note> A speeche applyed to those men, whose ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie many haue imitated, more haue enuied, but none haue attained. Those that haue imitated, haue been <hi>Socordes,</hi> and so vnworthie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they neuer trauailed to knowe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="3"/> of estate. Those that haue enuied, haue beene <hi>Vecordes</hi> base conceipts, and so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing because vnworthie. And those that haue not attained, are <hi>Excordes</hi> in pusillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and infirmitie of the mind. But there are yet another number <hi>Cordati Homines</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed men for wisedome, yet are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed for wealth. These enuie not any mans estate, but attribute vnto Fortune, the goods of Fortune: To the bodie, the goods of the bodie: to the minde, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the minde: and to <hi>Caesar,</hi> all things due vnto him. Such should wise men be, that what they are not thought worthie of by the worthiest; they should content them selues with, as well as the meanest. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I considering, that I cannot atchieue the knowledge which is worthie of your most honorable fauours, request, this may be worthie of your pacience. Wine which in base Dutch is called <hi>Drozen</hi> or <hi>Moder,</hi> is good for somewhat, it will make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound. So my wit may hereafter with your
<pb facs="3"/> present protections &amp; honourable allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance make a simple. But as there is of the yeare foure quarters: so is there of a mans knowledge, fouretimes. The Spring: the Summer: the Autumne: and Winter. The infancie, the youth: the middle age, (ripe iudgement:) and the olde age (right follie.) And because my knowledge is none, it cannot be termed any. Howbeit, for that I haue euer heard, my true honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord and maister, publish your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships excellent partes, which he recordeth often from his heart: I doe the rather presume of your Lordships clemencie in his absence. That I may approach with all this simplicitie vnto all that singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Who in witt beeing a Paterne to all men: may (where it wanteth) be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone to mee. I cannot be tedious in my writing. Woulde I had the like priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, not to be odious in my enditing. But so had I neede to bee in Arte <hi>Polycle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> in happe <hi>Polycrates:</hi> which because I
<pb facs="4"/> am not, I care not. Onely, I respect your Lordships true estimation, and I expect the Readers due consideration. I cease, not ceasing to remember your Lordships in my dayly wish for your long prosperitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honorable lordships bounden, and seruaunt to commaund: <hi>Thomas Bradshaw.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>