<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courte∣ous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108357_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05138</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15268.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108357</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courte∣ous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lathams new and second booke of falconrie : concerning the training vp of all hawkes that were vnmentioned in his first booke of the haggart faulcon and gerfaulcon, formerly printed; teaching approued medicines for all their diseases. By Symon Latham, Gent</title>
                 <author>Latham, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 148, 4 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="861" facs="459"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE. The names of the Interlocutors,</head>
   <stage>Asher, <hi>Happinesse:</hi> Amana, <hi>Trueth:</hi> Aram, <hi>Exaltation:</hi> Achitob, <hi>The brother of goodnesse.</hi>
   </stage>
   <sp>
      <speaker>ASER.</speaker>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not, good friends, but you rememember as well as my selfe, that when God of his great mercie endowed vs with grace in our tender yeares, to publish and set foorth in our Academie, that small portion of vnderstanding and knowledge which we had reaped out of the odoriferous vergiers of the morall Philosophy of ancient and wise men: touching the rules of liuing well, by following the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps and traces of vertue. And that therein we so much preuailed (yea and more then we either hoped or expected (that not only our country men of France, but strangers also participated with vs of our labors, and fauoured and esteemed of them so well, that they spared not the paines and charges to translate them, and to make them speake in their owne languages: which mooued and prouoked vs with gratification vnto them, to goe forward and to proceede further in our course. Whereby not long after, we manifested and made apparant the pursuite of our discourse, touching the Microcosmus or litle world, therein shewing and representing by a naturall history of man, the rarieties and excellences of the body and of the soule, and specially the immortality thereof. And not content to trauell so farre as therein to reduce vnto memory, and manifestly to declare and set downe the wonderfull testimonies of God, and of his prrouidence and iudgement, in the Anotamy and contemplation of the visible parts &amp; members of his chiefe work (Man) therby to conuince, and put to silence the Epicurian and the Atheist. We obliged our seluees so far, (for knowledge alwaies ingendreth a new and further desire to learne,) as at some other time (by the aide of God) to search and finde out the same things in the whole nature of this great visible world. And according to our desires, it pleased the diuine bounty, (who of his goodnes had giuen vs that commendable will and purpose) to perfect the same in vs by his heauenly blessing. In such manner that we presently published and set forth, the third book of our Academia intituled Microcosmus, or of heauen and earth. And not content therwith, aspiring higher then to the bounds and borders of the vniuersall world, we vowed to implore the supercelestiall fauour, that being better instructed and taught in the schole of eternal wisedome, and guided by his diuine light, we might also speake and discourse of the incomprehensible worke of God, touching the saluation of man, and so accomplishing our Academicall and Christian study, determined to rest from our labors. And to say the truth, what would it auaile or profit vs, to haue and attaine vnto the knowledge and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding of all humane and morall Philosophy, Logicke, Phisicke, Metaphisicke, and Mathematick, to know what belongeth to ciuill and politicke gouernment, and to be briefe, not to bee ignorant of any thing, which the liberall arts and sciences teach vs, therewith to content the curious minds of men, &amp; by that means to giue them a taest, &amp; to make thē enioy, some kind of transitory good in this life: and in the meane time to be altogether and wholy ignorant, or badly instructed, in the true and onely science of diuine Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy, whereat all the rest ought to aime, and whereof the finall end and purpose is, the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent good of the soule? That onely, and none other, is it, which teacheth vs to know God, his paternall will towards menkinde, and the rules of his law: that so we may liue holily heere on earth, and for euer happily in heauen. Therefore let vs boldly say, that without this spiritual wisedome, al learning &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is meere vanity and folly: and serueth to no other end, (as the great Doctor of the Gentiles saith) then as it were visibly, shewing vnto vs, the inuisible things of God, to make vs so much the more vnexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 20. 21</note> at the day of iudgement, for not hauing glorified him as we ought to doe.. Then seeing that we haue found the means, to pierce into the monumèts of the Philosophers, to shew that men ought, &amp; are creaetd to liue vertuously hereon earth, &amp; to reade the natural books of Theologie therin as it were to find out &amp; behold a shadow of the Deity, and to the glory therof, are enabled by argument to reason of the being of all creatures, why should not we assay to open that great booke of the life of the lambe which taketh away the sinnes of the world, therein to learne a more assured and perfecter lesson of the means how to liue hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pily, <note place="margin">Apoc. 21. 27. Iohn 1. 29.</note> &amp; of the knowledge which we ought to haue of God &amp; of his works, to glorifie him for our saluation.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <pb n="862" facs="460"/>
      <speaker>AMANA.</speaker>
      <p>It was not without great reason, and good cause that <hi>Postel</hi> a learned man, in a letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto vs, touching our discourse of <hi>Microcosmus,</hi> (the which is set downe and extant to bee read in the last edition of our Academie, together with our answer thereunto) congratulating vs in certen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable tearmes, therewith mixeth a kind of harsh censure: saying, I am hartily glad and reioyce, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing seene your writing and discourse of the naturall history of man, that you are so much obliged to the great king of heauen, that men may euidently see and behold the bright resplendant light of his diuine gifts in the forme of your Dialogues, and therby know the dignity of the holy language of Adam. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of your fained persons beare aitues, and that in shewing the dignity of the name of your ancestours, sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Primatu,</hi> you haue intitled your work, not the Common wealth or Theology, but the <hi>Primatus</hi>
         <note place="margin">Hacademiach sacred. primat</note> which in that tongue is called <hi>Hacademiach,</hi> that is to say, sacred or diuine Primate: but you must giue me leaue to tell you, as your true and perfect friend, that hauing omitted, and not spoken in some speciall Chapter, of the Church of God, (without the which there is no vnion) nor of the food and nourishment of the Spirit, tending to eternall life, without the which al is in vaine, you haue wholy left out, or at the least too slightly let slip and ouerpast, both the one and the other formal &amp; final causes, of that great workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, <hi>Man.</hi> Therfore my aduise &amp; counsel is (to the end that in your work, nothing may be omitted or found wanting,) that therin you would set down &amp; manifest those most diuine things, for that so accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishing an Hacademich doctrine, as a most Christian thing, &amp; an assured instruction of the truth, your writings may liue for euer, to the honour and glory of the eternall God, and the profite of mankinde.</p>
      <p>Our answer thereunto was grounded vpon these two points: that in our writing, wherein wee make a discourse of the workes of God, we haue proceeded according to the measure and abilitie of our spirits, and of our youthes: and that knowing, that the creation of all things, and the redemption of mankinde, are meanes to make vs acknowledge the Deitie and our saluation: we had begun for our instructions, to set domne the being of all creatures, specially of man, that afterward wee might speake of his happy being in the familie of Iesus Christ, when with longer and profounder study, wee should haue searched into and found out, the depth of the secrets which his holy word doth teach vs.</p>
      <p>To conclude, we are much beholding and obliged to the aduice of <hi>Postel,</hi> and also to all those that haue vouchsafed to honor and fauour vs so much, as to take the paines to read our books, yea and to our selues also, (as it is already shewed) for hauing past beyond our first bounds, &amp; of Academicke Phylosophers, to become Christian Philosophers: vntill that our Academic shall be a little Schole of Theologie. That the enterprise is too difficult, and ouerhigh for vs, we acknowledge it to be true, neither doe we affirme or beast that wee haue attained to the full perfection thereof. But to approach neere to excellent things, is alwayes commendable.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>ARAM.</speaker>
      <p>It is most certain, that the doctrine and examples of the writings and liues of auncient wise men, and famous Pagans, are of great force and efficacie in mens minds that are of generous education, to moue and stirre them with great delight, to an inward desire of resembling them, not onely in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of naturall things, but also in the practising of vertue. For that, man naturally desirous of present and immortal glory, perceiuing and beholding after so long a time, and many ages, by authentique meanes and memories, ancient Philosophers, and other famous persons, much honoured in their times, as it were to reuiue and liue againe, hee is thereby stirred vp and prouoked, to striue to make himselfe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the like praise and commendation, by following and imitating their steps. But as it is a good, most commendable, and an excellent beginning, to proceed and goe forward in a Christian vocation: so to stoppe there and goe no further, is as much as still to bee ignorant and miserable. How corrupt soeuer the nature of man is, yet it leaueth a certaine feeling in euerie particular mans conscience, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are as it were constrained, not onely to apprehend a Deitie, but also to discerne a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good and euil, and by that meanes are vnexcusable, if they follow not and practise piety &amp; vertue. And how much the more a man taketh paines, and endeuoureth himselfe to discouer &amp; contemplate (by the reasonable parts and faculties of the soule) things intelligible and worthy commendation, so much the more he maketh himselfe more vnderstanding, wise, and affected thereunto: to ioyne, frame and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion himselfe to those things and actions, whereunto they resemble. For it is most certaine, and cannot be otherwise, that in the fall of man, there did rest some sparkes of those graces, and of the diuine light, which he had receiued of his Creator; whereby he is still moued and prouoked, to enquire and seeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the truth, and to desire to be vnburthened, and freed from his owne proper and inherent corruption. But all these motions, both of the vnderstanding and the will, are so weake and inueloped with so great obscuritie, and pernicious passions, that they cannot produce nor bring forth any cleare or perfect thing, no not so much as to make any show or apparance thereof, in any part of humane nature, with out speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and diuine grace, but onely a ruinous disfigured shew of the guifts and graces by him first receiued, specially, touching things which concerne the saluation or happinesse of the soule. For as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> saith, <hi>That the light shined in darkenesse, but the darkenesse comprehended it not.</hi> And S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 5.</note>
         <pb n="862" facs="460"/>
that the Gentiles walked in the vanitie of their vnderstandings, hauing their thoughts obscured, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing strangers from the life of God, by their ignorance, and the blindnesse of their hearts. And because they became vaine in their imaginations, their foolish hearts being full of darknesse, they were destitute <note place="margin">Epes. 4. 17, 18</note> of vnderstanding. This in effect is the true and proper iudgement which may be made if men, and of <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 21, 22</note> all their Philosophie, vntill such time as being regenerated and illuminated by the spirit of God, they doe in Iesus Christ (the true Doctor of the soules of the faithfull) receiue those guifts and graces which onely make them vnderstanding and wise to saluation: which are most wisely and abundantly set downe and declared in the sacred Registers of the holy Scriptures. If then we wil take the pains earnestly to trauel like good Christians, out of this heauenly treasure, to draw a sound and solid instruction, hauing no other purpose nor intent, but onely for the glory of God, and to frame and bend our selues (and all those that wil vouchsafe to heare vs) to his holy and blessed will, we doe no lesse doubt of his grace, and of the sauour and good will of men, then we haue already found and felt in our first workes.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>ACHITOB.</speaker>
      <p>The name of a Christian is the most worthy name, that euer was giuen or attributed vnto man, infinitely surpassing all the glorie, that those men thought to merite and deserue, who among the Pagans were called Philosophers, or wise men. For this title of Christian, signifieth and betokeneth him, who by the knowledge, grace, and doctrine of Iesus Christ (God and man) knoweth the true and only God (Father, Sonne, and holy Ghost, cause, beginning, and end of all things) his iustice and his mercy; that enforceth and endeuoureth himselfe to be perfect, and repleat with holinesse, vertue, modestie, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes, constancie, and perseuerance, that with a certaine testimony of a good conscience, serueth God according to his will, and that of his meere grace and mercy confidently hopeth for eternall life and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: into the which most diuine knowledge and vnderstanding, neither the Grecian Phylosopher, the Egyptian Priest, the French Druyde, the Indian Gymnosophistus, the Romane Sibilla, nor the Mages of Persia, could euer penetrate: because they knewe not what that true Phylosophy is, which teacheth and openeth vnto vs so many great and wonderfull mysteries, that is, (the Law of God) written by the Prophets, and (the Gospel) written by the Apostles. Which was the cause, that all those Pagans and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, great personages, and men deepely learned and studious in diuers Arts, for the most part hauing a secret feeling of the felicitie of man, touching the tranquilitie of his soule, and taking great paines and much labour to attaine thereunto, and to teach and instruct others therein, were ignorant, and knew not the true and assured meanes how to enioy the same, neither yet could find out the originall fountaine from whence the same proceeded. That is the loue, mercie, and charitie of God towards mankinde, redeemed by the blood of his Sonne Iesus Christ, and purged from all his sinnes. Therefore, notwithstanding that the liues of diuers Philosophers, and others their Schollers and disciples, was learned and peaceable in some sort, and also cleared and freed from diuers vices and corruptions incident to the common sort of men, yet it resteth and consisteth in vs (if we be true Christian's) without comparison, to liue more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandingly, more happily, more contentedly, with more ioy and peace of conscience, and better purged from all impediments and vices then euer they did. To that end we haue many notable lessons, and a most certaine doctrine of the Registers of the holy Spirit (the Cannonicall Scriptures) Then let vs boldly peruse and turne ouer those sacred Rowles: from thence first to draw out certaine simple draughts, or smal proofes of Christian Philosophy; and if wee proceede so well and happily, that in the studie of his diuine wisedome wee finde in our soules and consciences an increase of spirituall graces, whereby wee may bee bold (&amp; what should we feare to vndertake in searching for, and setting forth the glory of God?) to speak of the high mysteries of Religion, wee will indeuour our selues in our Academie, to bring to open view, and to set foorth a greater matter of Theologie.</p>
      <p>In this booke therefore our intent and purpose shall be; first, onely and generally to frame and fashion the affections of the Soule to the loue of pietie, and to shew and set foorth the meanes how man should <note place="margin">The subiect of the dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>course in this booke.</note> walke in holinesse and vprightnesse of life and conuersation. Secondly, to represent vnto him Spirituall Meditations, which make a compleate happy life. In the first part of this Philosophie, wee will shew, how a Christian Philosopher before all other things, ought to purge and clense himselfe, of seuen princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall follies, which commonly doe as it were pursue and follow man, that is, how to know the Deitie as he ought to doe: not to esteeme of man more then of God; not to thinke that he shall liue alwaies in this world: to know why, and to what ende he liueth here on earth: not to iudge the happy or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy state of man by exterior signes: not to beleeue or giue credit to his enemies more then to his true and faithfull friends: and lastly, not to preswade with himselfe, or to presume that hee is wise. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently, wee will declare and teach him to consider of, seuen other singular things, requisite, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether necessarie and pertinent to a happy and godly life: that is, The Church, the Word of God, the Sacraments, Praier, reading of the holy Scriptures, Charitie, and Almes. Thirdly, wee will produce and declare, how a man ought to haue a great and speciall care, to clense and keepe his soule and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, cleane, vnspotted, and vndefiled from seuen deadly and pernious vices, that is, Couetousnesse,
<pb n="864" facs="461"/>
Ambition, excesse of Apparell and meates, Pleasures vnlawfull exercises, Euny, and Slander. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we will touch and point at seuen principall vocations, wherein all men are bound and obliged, to shew foorth and make knowne the fruits and effects of all this Christian Philosophie, to the glory of God, and for the good and benefit of mankinde; which vocations are, to be maried, to be a Father or a Mother, to be a Childe, to be a Magistrate, to be a Subiect, to be a Pastor, to be a slocke. Fiftly, we will speake of seuen considerate reasons and arguments tomooue and induce al Christians with great affection to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the meanes of a happy and godly life, set downe and declared in this Philosophie: which are, the authoritie of Iesus Christ, his Names, Holy, and Emanuel; fiue other titles belonging vnto him, his two names <hi>(Iesus Christ)</hi> that wee are all Strangers and Pilgrimes in this world: and to remember that the Kingdome of heauen is at hand. Not that wee will stretch the doctrine of so many notable points and matters so farre, as to take vpon vs seriously and fully to entreate of them, in all their seueall parts (for then we should be forced to make and compile many large volumes thereof) onely wee will content our selues, to set downe certaine briefe Summaries and generall points, whereunto euery true Christian ought to bend all his thoughts, words, and workes: speaking neuerthelesse, of all these things in such manner, that sufficiently, and by a certaine order, euery man shall be led, and addressed by the word of God, to the knowledge of godlinesse and Iustice, and to a true manner of life, well orderd and gouerned in all estates and conditions.</p>
      <p>Touching the second part, which shall properly belong to a contemplatiue life, it shall consist of seuen principall points, that is, Meditation of future happinesse: Knowledge of the meanes that assure and warrant this beatitude vnto Christians: The certaine way how to apply the signes and markes thereof vnto themselues: an assurance that they shall neuer fall from God: how they must be constant in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: to perseuer in their vocation without feare or fainting: and lastly to meditate and pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</p>
      <p>To conclude, we haue specially chosen the number of seuen, therein to comprehend and bound the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie of all our discourse, because the number is anciently and long since knowne to be full, perfect, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersall, and sufficient, to represent all things in perfection: and for that cause is oftentimes set downe and rehearsed in the holy Scriptures. Wherefore we hope, that all those that shall and will accompany vs in our vowes, by reading, vnderstanding, and practising of that which we shall set downe, both in the one and the other part of this our Philosophie, shall and may assuredly liue with vs, not onely Christian Philosophers, in name, but also in deed and in effect: and as it becommeth the true children of our Father which is in heauen, and that desire by the way and means which his Son tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and sheweth vnto vs, to enter into his kingdome. God grant vs all the grace so to do.</p>
   </sp>
   <closer>If I pray vnto God he will aide me.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>