<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in God, RICHARD, by divine pro∣uidence Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, Chancellor of the vniuersity of Oxford, and one of his Maiesties most hono∣rable priuie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Lever, Christopher</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108517_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05380</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15536</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108517</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in God, RICHARD, by divine pro∣uidence Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, Chancellor of the vniuersity of Oxford, and one of his Maiesties most hono∣rable priuie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Lever, Christopher</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Heauen and earth, religion and policy. Or, The maine difference betweene religion and policy. Written by C.L</title>
                 <author>Lever, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ballard, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 116, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER <hi>in God,</hi> RICHARD, <hi>by divine</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, Chancellor of the vniuersity of Oxford, and one of his Maiesties most hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuie Counsell.</head>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <opener>May it please your Grace:</opener>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Humbly present you this Tract of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Policy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I acknowledge the disproportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the matter and the manner I giue it. Yet because it is a seruice of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it may therefore please your Grace to accept it.</p>
         <p>The reason of my vndertaking it, is the duety of Christian conscience, which bindeth every man to some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb facs="3"/>
performance. And because God hath not yet beene pleased to giue me particular place of seruice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I might imploy his talent with more aduantage, I (therefore) endeauour my selfe in such trauell wherein God may receiue his part of honour, his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants their parts of profit, and my selfe the discharge of Christian duetie, all which respects are the lawes &amp; restricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of euery lawfull worke.</p>
         <p>The reason of dedication is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence your Grace doth merit from all them, who professe learning. In which number, though I be the meanest (in respect both of Nature and Fortune) yet beeing bound with others, I (like them) both declare and direct my selfe to your Grace in my labours of best per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</p>
         <p>Againe, the fitnes of your place with this argument, doth challenge the dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, because the execution of your high calling, is a continuall exercise of
<pb facs="3"/>
Religion and Religious Policy; the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and prouident armour whereby both Church and State are secured from vngodly practise: the which (as your Grace best knoweth) hath bin that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering gun-shot bent against the truth of Religion, and the peace of Christian States.</p>
         <p>For these respects I haue both writ, and giuen this trauell to your Grace, humbly acknowledging my duety, and the meanenesse of my deseruing.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>
               <hi>Your Graces In all duty and humble seruice,</hi> Christopher Leuer.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>