<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLE, AND GENEROVS WELL-WISHERS TO VERTVOVS ACTIONS, AND LEARNING: The Regent and Professours of the Musaeum Minervae, wish all honour and happinesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108163_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04956</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15099</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108163</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLE, AND GENEROVS WELL-WISHERS TO VERTVOVS ACTIONS, AND LEARNING: The Regent and Professours of the Musaeum Minervae, wish all honour and happinesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The constitutions of the Musaeum Minervæ</title>
                 <author>Musaeum Minervae (London, England)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Spencer, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 19, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLE, AND GENEROVS WELL-WISHERS TO VERTVOVS ACTIONS, AND LEARNING: The Regent and Professours of the <hi>Musaeum Minervae,</hi> wish all honour and happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owbeit publick actions and undertakings doe usually receive no Preface, it being needlesse to divulge that, which of it selfe will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to all mens Censures: neverthelesse new enterprises (how good, or iust soever they be) are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly subiect at least to suspicion, if not unto oblique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; which frequent experience, as well as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things hath manifested in this our new institution of an Academy here in <hi>England:</hi> Which though already it hath been iustified, and approved by the wisdomes of the Kings most sacred Maiestie, and many of the Lords of his Maiestie, most Honourable privy Councell, and confirmed by his Maiesties Letters patents: and these the
<pb facs="3"/>following Constitutions and Discipline thereof ratified under the hands and seales of the right Honourable, the Lord Keeper of the great seale of England, and the two Lord-Chief Justices. Yet for a further and more full satisfaction of all men, aswell ignorant detractours, as vertuous Favourers of this Designe, some remonstrance may not seem impertinent, but rather necessary to be print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and published for the better understanding of what hath been undertaken.</p>
   <p>Therefore for as much as we conceive, that it is not generally nor cleerly understood, what the nature of an Academy is: nor wherefore the institution of such a Colledge is here necessary, as well as in other great transmarine Cities: we have thought it requisite, for the bringing of vertue into action, and the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of liberall Arts into more frequent practise to show that such an institution is fit to be established here according to the laudable custome of other Nations: who even in the middle of their Ʋniversities have their Academies, as <hi>Rome, Bononia, Padua, Paris, Wittenberge,</hi> and other places: wherein our Aymes are directed to this end, that <hi>England</hi> may he as well furnished for the vertuous education, and discipline of her own Natives, as any other Nation of <hi>Europe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is sufficiently known, that the subiects of his Maiesties dominions, have naturally as noble mindes, and as able bodies as any Nation of the earth: and
<pb facs="3"/>therefore deserve all accommodations for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of them, either in speculation, or action. Neverthelesse such hath been the neglect, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valueing of our selves, and our own abilities, and overvalueing of forreigne teachers, that hitherto no such places for the education, and trayning up of our own young Nobilitie, and Gentrie, in the practise of arms, and arts have been instituted here in <hi>England,</hi> as are in <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> but that by a chargeable and sometimes an unfortunate experience, we to our own losse, and disgrace doe finde the noble and generous youth of this kingdome is sent beyond the seas, to learn such things at excessiverates, from strangers abroad, wherein they might be as well, and with lesse expence, and danger, instructed here at home.</p>
   <p>The experience not onely of the honour, but the gaine which other Nations reape by the confluence of our Nobilitie and Gentry to them, for instruction might be a sufficient au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>horitie, and warrant for the erection of such Academies, in the chiefest Cities of this kingdome, as are beyond the seas: were it not for some iealousies, and suspicions which the novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every publick action doth bring with it, as indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iduall concomitants: and therefore in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>r of this first institution of that nature, some short answeres are requisite to be given to some
<pb facs="4"/>places, whose foundations have so long and so honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably been confirmed.</p>
   <p>And for as much as we are to give reasons that the institution of an Academy is necessary amongst other noble qualities, and arts, (if taught, yet not practized in the Ʋniversities nor Innes of Court:) the scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Navigation, Riding, Fortification, Architec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Painting, and such like being most usefull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishments of a gentleman doe require a peculiar place and institution for them. And albeit many of them are taught in London, in dispersed places; yet it cannot but be iudged more convenient to reduce, and unite them in one certain place: likewise whereas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men teach them perfunctorily rather for gain then any other respect: it was held necessary to select cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain men who upon oath should undertake to see them learnedly and sufficiently taught: and in brief, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the Citie of London diverse strangers professe to teach sundry, or rather all the liberall arts and scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of which many have been found to be upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and triall egregiously ignorant, whereby our youth loose both their tyme, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ney: it could not but be thought most necessary for the benefit, and conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of all such vertuous disposed youths, as live about the Citie, as also for the honour of our nation: that such a house should be er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cted in which they might be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly taught to practise the aforesaid sciences and
<pb facs="4"/>qualities: and in a vertuous societie, have such gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and fitting recreations, as might divert them from the too much frequenting of places of expence, and of greater inconveniences.</p>
   <p>Now to let all men know that the intention of the erection of this Academy is as well for the prevention of inconveniences, and dangers; as for the positive benefit of our Gentrie: there is no understanding man, but may resent how many of our Noble men, and young gentlemen travell into forreigne countries before they have any language, or knowledge to make profit of their tyme abroad; they, not being any way able to get knowledge for want of language, nor lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for want of tyme: since going over so young, their yeares of licence commonly expire before they can obtain to sufficient ripenesse of understanding; which no nation is known to doe but the English: for what children of other nations come over to us before they are of able age, and ripenesse? To prevent which inconvenience we by this publick Act, give notice unto all men, that one great end of our institution is, to give language and instruction with other orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of travell unto our Gentlemen (if they shall stay some tyme in this Academy) before their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking any long iourneys into forreigne parts.</p>
   <p>Moreover whereas it is found by lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that Noblemen, and Gentlemen for want of an
<pb facs="5"/>Academy here, are as it were necessitated, to send their sonnes beyond the seas for education: where through change of Climat, and dyet, and for want of yeares of discretion, they become more subiect to sicknesses and immature death, then otherwise they might have been: we leave it to carefull prudent parents to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how necessary the institution of an Academy here in London is, in which especiall order may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the bringing up of young Gentlemen, untill both for yeares, and learning they may be fit as well to travell and make benefit of their tyme abroad, as to gain some knowledge how to prevent the dangers both of forreigne aire, and dyet.</p>
   <p>Now in the last place we humbly desire that it may not be imputed an affectation of singularitie, or of vain glory, that we publish these our Constitutions: for that divers have been desirous to see them, and more are ignorant whether we have any setled disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline or not: which because the institution is the first of this nature in this kingdome, it may seem more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable to be done, in this particular, rather then by any other Colledge in the Ʋniversities, whose formes of discipline are sufficiently known: And if this Designe, and the subsequent Constitutions may be so fortunate, as being seen and published to receive a condigne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation (albeit we the present members thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of us farre strucken in yeares are likely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb facs="5"/>little benefit to our selves, for all our great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours other then the reward of a good conscience) we cannot but hope since our institution, and colledge is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made capable by his Maiesties gracious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and letters patents of donation in land, as well as goods: that if not the present age, yet posteritie will afford some noble benefactours who by their boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to this foundation in upholding and continuing of what we have begun, will perpetuate their own ever honoured memory. And thus having upon the aforesaid reasons been induced to manifest our actions, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture intentions in this plain, and sincere manner, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the view of the world: we hope that our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours herein, will by all as favourably be interpreted, as they are by us true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and sincerely meant; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the glory of God, the honour of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and the publick good of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. {inverted ⁂}</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>