<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108823_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5823</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108823</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Conspiracie, for pretended reformation : viz. presbyteriall discipline. A treatise discouering the late designments and courses held for aduancement thereof, by William Hacket yeoman, Edmund Coppinger, and Henry Arthington Gent. out of others depositions and their owne letters, writings &amp; confessions vpon examination: together with some part of the life and conditions, and the two inditements, arraignment, and execution of the sayd Hacket: also an answere to the calumniations of such as affirme they were mad men: and a resemblance of this action vnto the like, happened heretofore in Germanie. Vltimo Septembris. 1591. Published now by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Cosin, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher, Deputies of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 36, 36-102, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN in the tyme of professing the
trueth of religion, such as pretend grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
sinceritie and zeale, doe fall into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticall
fansies and dangerous attempts:
then some doe thereupon stagger in the
doctrine, and are scandalized: some be
quite driuen backe: and others are caried
euen with open mouth to slander and to
reproch the very profession of the Gospell. The two first of which,
are of the weaker, but the last are of the wickeder sort. For these
are straight way ready to make comparisons betwixt the times,
and to declaime largely, concerning the sweete and golden quiet,
with agreement in iudgement, which they (erroneously) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue,
to haue continually accompanied the times of superstition
and blindnes.</p>
   <p>But though this were vniuersally true, which is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise:
yet both the one sort and the other, are dangerously decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
and transported into misdeeming by want of due considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
what is the very well-spring and occasion of such accidents
vnder the profession of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>For when <hi>Sathan</hi> the deceiuing enemie of mankind, had in
the times of <hi>Poperie</hi> by insensible and as it were obscure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
(vnder a colour of religion and deuotion) enuenomed once
the very fountaines of doctrine with many pestilent errours,
much superstition, and grosse <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> and had almost quite
dammed vp the light of the glorious Gospell: then was it no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,
though he here rested his labours, as being (in some sort) ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
vnto the maine ende of all his drifts and purposes. In so
much as this once atchieued, the rest were sufficiently able to goe
forward of themselues. For vpon corruptiō of faith &amp; doctrine,
must needes ensue either open corruption of life and conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
or at least corruption, masked vnder a vaile of hypocrisie: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="4"/>
he that walketh in darknes, knoweth not whither he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
and a corrupt tree cannot bring foorth good fruite. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
after the victorie gotten, that he might more deepely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
and surely retaine, whome he had caught, he thought it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite
(at some seasons) vpon these corruptions, to weaue a vaile
of pretended vnitie, and as it were to candie and sweeten them
ouer with the louely shewe of peace and agreement: which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse
being without Veritie, is nothing else, but a lewde
Conspiracie, and is rather a deadly sleepe wherewith men be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed,
then an vnitie of the spirite in the bond of peace.
For where all is subdued, what needes any further resistance?
And where a strong man keepes the house, all that he possesseth
are in quiet, till a stronger then he doe come to dispossesse him.</p>
   <p>But when as God taking compassion of his Church in the eies
of his mercie, had in these latter times made the day-starre to
shine againe in our hearts, no sooner did the beames of his Gospell
beginne to glimpse and breake foorth, but the old craftie serpent
(knowing his kingdome to be inuaded a fresh, and his time but
short) began in great wrath to rouse vp himselfe againe, and to
hammer ouer a new, all his long approued wicked experiments,
and to plant newe engines for the discredite and hinderance of
the passage and propagation of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>This he plotteth (besides many other meanes) by seducing
some that professe it, into sedition and errour: and so in their
persons he bringeth the profession it selfe into obloquie and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
with such, as afore did thinke hardly of it, or were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
it was the trueth. For by reason of his <hi>Angelicall</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
corrupted with <hi>Diabolicall</hi> malice, and by long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
euen of 5553. yeeres continuance, he is nowe become <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<hi>mille-artifex,</hi> his perfite crafts-master in infinite deuises
and subtilties. So that he doeth at sundry times very manifoldly
and variably suggest and plot, not onely seuerall and diuers, but
sometimes euen contrary opinions and actions, one to another;
howbeit all to one and the selfe same generall ende, <hi>of seducing
<pb facs="5"/>
mankinde.</hi> Therefore (amongst his infinite deceites for hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
of the Gospell, and of mans saluation by it) some whome he
cannot peruert in doctrine, he seeketh to attaint in life. Others
whome he cannot so easily seduce in their conuersation, he often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
soweth his cockle &amp; darnel of superstition, schisme, &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie
in their hearts, and so peruerteth them in iudgement, and
matter of religion. Some whom he cannot entangle by one sinne,
he tempteth to ouerthrowe by a sinne contrary vnto it. Others
whom he cannot snare by grosse and actual sinnes, he gets ground
of, by making them haue ouer great estimation of their owne
supposed vertues and puritie: so that they growe hereby both to
a conceite and selfe loue of themselues, and also to contemne and
condemne others with the <hi>Pharise,</hi> saying: <hi>Oh God, I thanke
thee, that I am not as other men are:</hi> or as the <hi>Prophet</hi>
speaketh touching such proud hypocrites, <hi>Depart from me, for
I am holier then thou.</hi> Others he draweth into errour by mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
of the true qualitie or cause of things, as when, not being
able to corrupt the general doctrine of the church, he perswadeth
Preachers most to insist vpon matters of meere circumstance, as
if they were of especial necessitie, and procureth the outward go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment
&amp; discipline to be obtruded &amp; beat vpō, for a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
point
of doctrine. So that matters of the substance of doctrine
&amp; faith in deede, do either wholly slippe by vntaught, or els are so
sleightly and ignorantly slubbered ouer by such Preachers, that
the common aduersarie the <hi>Papist,</hi> is thereby rather hardened
then conuinced in his opinions. Which practise may hereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
to be the very subtiltie of <hi>Sathan,</hi> for that such doe vse
farre more earnestnes and diligence to plant and bring in that
their <hi>discipline,</hi> then they doe for retaining of purity &amp; sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
of doctrine, and are lesse incensed and vehement against <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes,</hi>
then they are against such as impugne that fancie.</p>
   <p>Out of this head springs also that errour of some, who doe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
all disorder and personall faultes of men about execution
of lawes, vnto the lawes themselues, and vnto the verie pollicie
<pb facs="5"/>
of the Church: thereupon gathering with themselues, that the
plot of <hi>Discipline</hi> (if it might come in place) will surely serue
as a <hi>Mithridate</hi> and soueraigne salue, to heale (with short ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying)
all diseases and sores, both of Church &amp; Common wealth.
Certaine be so bewitched (in like sort) by a kind of admiration of
that, which is (in it selfe) most necessarie, as that in the meane
time they ouerslippe matters of no lesse importance in the life of
a Christian, because they thinke it sufficient, to be occupied onely
about the other.</p>
   <p>Hereupon it commeth, that sundry doe attribute so much to
the hearing of the word preached, that neither publike nor pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
reading of Scripture, workes of charitie, praying, nor pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
of that which is preached, is any whit almost regarded of
them. Whereby they are alwaies learning, but neuer come vnto
the knowledge of the trueth, as if the very worke wrought of
hearing alone could make them good and perfect Christians. So
that where in olde time there were certaine heretikes called <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
who did nothing but <hi>pray:</hi> so (not without cause) haue
some feared, left such persons would bring in an heresie of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
putting all religion in bare <hi>hearing</hi> of Sermons. Diuerse also
there are, who are so whetted against the abuse of things, that
the <hi>Seducer</hi> hereby taketh opportunitie, to drawe them to omit
euen the good and commendable vse of them. Such are those, that
because they will not seeme to confirme Gods trueth by humane
testimonie, doe therefore despise all light and helpe of good artes,
and learned Interpretors, and in steede of them, doe in their ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
nothing els, but blase out their own friuolous and vnsound
Collections, trifling out the time (without order and methode)
by an heape of earnest and resonant, but vndigested wordes,
vaine repetitions, <hi>tautologies</hi> and <hi>battologies,</hi> without any
substance of matter, to the great abuse of their auditorie, and of
that excellent worke. Many also are so afraide to fall into super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious
obseruation of daies, commanded for abstinence and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding
of most nutritiue diet, that at such times they doe vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="6"/>
most pamper their vile flesh, euen with a purposed and setled
contempt of good lawes, in that behalfe prouided. Neither will
this kinde of persons (for the most part) vse any priuate fasting,
for subduing the body, but must haue a whole side of a Countrey,
or an whole familie at least, knowe when they fast, and will not
sticke to ride out a dosen or twentie miles from home to fast with
others for companie (though without publike authoritie) there
to make ostentation of great humbling themselues, by abstaining
perhaps from one meale, howe plentifully and delicately soeuer
they do fare at suppers, or at their next meale. Likewise, to auoid
opinion of superstitious worship of the outward elements at Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
sundry doe refuse to kneele at the perception of it: and of
the contrary side doe fall to a prophane and swinish (at least out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward)
irreuerence of that high and excellent mysterie. Others
there are, who in auoiding superstition, are themselues become
litle lesse,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Rom. 1.</note> then superstitious. For albeit the holy Ghost condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
want of natural affection, as a sinne: yet such persons, when
their husbands, parents, or friends doe die, are so farre from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate
sorowe or mourning for them (lest happely they should
seeme to doe it superstitiously and excessiuely, as those doe, who
haue no hope) that on the contrary, they doe (euen with a kind of
superstitious singularitie) auoid all shew of sorow, as if it were a
matter vnlawful for any Christians, of their degree of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
And therefore they take vnto themselues at such times, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke,
Rose-marie branches, and other tokens of ioy and great so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.
Howbeit, the holy Ghost greatly commendeth the deuotion
of them,<note place="margin">Act. 8. 2.</note> who buried the Martyr S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> and made great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
for him. Of whose resurrection neuerthelesse vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
life, those mourners had as good assurāce, as any man now
can haue touching such, whom these do so pleasantly &amp; iocundly
tumble into the pit. Many also he deceaueth and drowneth in
sinne and impietie by some similitude and resemblance that it
hath vnto vertue and godlines, as, by making that which in
deede is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>will-worship,</hi> to seeme to be nothing els, but
<pb facs="6"/>
an earnest care to serue God: superstition to be taken for obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
deuotion: hypocrisie, for true sinceritie: a shewe of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
a mans selfe by a meale or twoes abstinence, and hanging
downe the head like a bull-rush, for true fasting, and subduing of
the flesh: calumniation, slander, and disdaine of others, for an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
of sinne: rancour and male contentment, for zeale of Gods.
glorie: schisme and diuision, for an auoiding of the workes of
darkenes and of pollution by them: seditious innouation, for law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
reformation: presumptuous expostulation in praier with
God, for feruencie of the spirite: bitter inuectiues against others
in praying, for desire of amendement in them, and to aduance
Gods glorie: ouer-weening conceites, for extraordinarie callings
and gifts: whot and bloodie panges of malice and crueltie, for
motions of Gods spirite and reuelation from him, with such like
a great many, moe them a good number. All these and such like,
are vsuall practises and sleights of <hi>Sathan,</hi> whereby euen in the
time of the Gospel, he cunningly inueigleth and slily entrappeth
many, to the danger of themselues, to the scandall and downe-fal
of others, and to the obloquie of true religion. <hi>It is necessarie</hi>
(saith Christ) <hi>that offences come: yet woe be to them, by
whome they come.</hi> And <hi>there must needes be heresies</hi>
(saith S. <hi>Paul) that such as be approoued, may be made
manifest.</hi> But of all the other, the last sort of them (being sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested
by <hi>Sathan,</hi> vnder the visard of vertue, godlines; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion)
are most pernicious and diuelish: and the poison of them
spreadeth and ranckleth furthest, to the disturbance and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill
both of Church and Common-wealth, because hereby the
<hi>Diuell</hi> transfourmeth himselfe into an <hi>Angell</hi> of light. For
as the most noble creature engendred, is most loathsome and
base in his corruption: so is the vntrue pretence and colour
of pietie and religion (thinges of themselues of chiefest price
and excellencie) the most daungerous snare and deadly dart,
that <hi>Sathan</hi> can shoote-foorth.<note place="margin">Macchiauel.</note> The prophane politique of
our age, coulde obserue, that shewe of pietie and religion
<pb facs="7"/>
was the readiest and surest way, to blinde and seduce a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.
If then this impe of his, could marke it, shall we doubt, but
that <hi>Sathan</hi> himselfe, the forger of all subtilties, can see it, and
accordingly also put it in practise? Yea, he hath put in vre this
most dangerous deuise, not onely in this action (whereof we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate)
done in our late sight and knowledge, by his seduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments
<hi>William Hacket, Edmund Coppinger,</hi> and
<hi>Henrie Arthington:</hi> but at sundry other times also, by other
his like factours, since the last renuing of the Gospell, begunne in
<hi>Germany,</hi> in our fathers daies. One or two of the most memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
of which examples recorded in historie, it shall not (I trust)
be amisse to compare with these late attempts and actions: both
that the one and the other may be better knowen, and auoided
hereafter, and that the efficacie of this strong illusion, may more
fruitfully be weighed and considered.</p>
   <p>In militarie instructions it is prescribed,<note place="margin">Polyaenus in Stratag.</note> not to vse a <hi>Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme</hi>
twise together in one age, for feare of ouer fresh remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
and thereby of preuention. Therefore <hi>Sathan</hi> an olde
Leader, might not in his great policie, so soone after, haue againe
assaied this practise so like (in most pointes) to the former in
<hi>Germany,</hi> had he not perfectly knowen (by experience) the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie
and rare working thereof, and therefore did repose in it,
an especiall confidence for raising of tumult, shedding of blood,
and ouerthrowe of states.</p>
   <p>But before I enter into that Comparison, it is requisite first
to make narration of this late <hi>Conspiracie,</hi> with the
circumstances thereof, as it was plotted and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
forward by them, so neere, as I could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme
my selfe therein, either by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions
of others, or from their
owne letters, writings, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall
confessions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>