<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VNCONSCIO∣NABLE
READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108005_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18914</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108005</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VNCONSCIO∣NABLE
READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chronological discourse touching, 1 The Church. 2 Christ. 3 Anti-Christ. 4 Gog &amp; Magog. &amp;c : The substaunce whereof, was collected about some 10. or 11. yeares since (as may be gathered by an epistle prefixed before a tractate, called, The visible Christian) but now digested into better order; and first published, by the author himselfe, H. Cl</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE VNCONSCIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NABLE
READER.</head>
   <p>ARt thou an <hi>Atheist,</hi> and so mockes all Religion? Then I leaue thee to
thunder and lightning, vvhereby some auncient Atheistes, haue
been forced to feare, and to acknovvledge a soueraigne diuine
povver ouer the Creature.</p>
   <p>Art thou of some Religion?<note place="margin">Iustin. <hi>the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storian affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,</hi> Condito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s Lupae vberib. alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s: sic omne illum populum Lupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum animos ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, inexplebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les sanguinis, at{que} imperij diuitiarum{que} auidos ac leiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos. Lib 38.<hi>Lactantius</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeth <hi>Lupa</hi> to haue been a vile Whore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, and thereof <hi>Lupanar. De vera rel lib.</hi> 1. c. 20.</note> VVhat, a flouting <hi>Papist?</hi> Then I
leaue thee to thy mother <hi>Rome:</hi> As the last <hi>Iericho</hi> by <hi>Hiel,</hi> so it vvas
founded in Blood, by such as had sucked the milke of a VVolfe (at least of a
vile Harlot) and it goes on in Blood, as vnable othervvise to be continued.
VVitnesse not onely many bloody massachres a broad, but many sanguiuolent
attempts (of late) heere at home. Specially, vve can not forget thy late
Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pouder treason; vvherevvith thou didest couet, to mingle vvith our
blood, the blood of thy Parents; yea, of men of thine ovvne Religion. Hovv
then should any Euangelicall vvriting, content thy Idolatrous iudgment?</p>
   <p>Art thou a <hi>Separist?</hi> One that no sooner hath crept out of the shell, but
labours to picke out the eyes of thy Mother? Looke for the curse of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
and to be rooted out, for a defiler of the nest thou vvast bred in▪ My Mothers
sonne can doe nothing that can content thee; for thou canst doe nothing, that
vvill long content thy selfe. I novv this is the true Discipline, anone that:
I novv some translation of the Bible may be brought into the Congregation,
i novv none but the liuely voyce of Gods spirit in the Teacher; that is, the
liuely voyce of his ovvne priuate fancie. I novv, the Minister may haue no set
kind of maintenance, I novv he may. I novv, the Apostate from that Church,
may vpon his returne, not be admitted into somuch as a Collecters roome,
(vvhom they call <hi>Deacon)</hi> anone he may. One-vvhile Psalmes may not be
songe in the Congregation, another vvhile they may. One yeare, it is as lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
for a man to preach in our Temples,<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>M. Greenvvod</hi> (neere his last cast, being come from the Fleet to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate) so affirmed, as George Knif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deliuered to me and others.</note> as for the Prophet of <hi>Iudah</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie
at <hi>Bethel;</hi> but next yeare, such an act must be tearmed <hi>Idolatrie</hi> and
<hi>Antichristianisme.</hi> In a vvord (for thy fooleries are infinite) thy ovvne
<hi>Apocryphall</hi> inuentions, must be held <hi>Canonicall;</hi> and I must not seeke to
content thee. VVere not a VVhirelygig in thy braine (as may appeare by thy
trundling from Country to Country, from shop to shop, pratling, inue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>iuing,
rayling) our vvritinges vvould be read more soberly, and iudged of more
conscionably.</p>
   <p>VVhatsoeuer vnconscionable Spirit thou bee, I turne my selfe from thee,
saying no more, then <hi>Michael</hi> did to <hi>Satan; The Lord reprooue thee.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>