<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the right Worshipfull
Sir Fraunces Drake, Knight, N. L. G. wish∣eth
all prosperitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108825_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68413</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16806</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108825</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the right Worshipfull
Sir Fraunces Drake, Knight, N. L. G. wish∣eth
all prosperitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the historie of the discouerie and conquest of the East Indias, enterprised by the Portingales, in their daungerous nauigations, in the time of King Don Iohn, the second of that name : VVhich historie conteineth much varietie of matter, very profitable for all nauigators, and not vnpleasaunt to the readers. Set foorth in the Portingale language, by Hernan Lopes de Castaneda. And now translated into English, by N.L. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Castanheda, Fer~nao Lopes de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 164 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧To the right Worshipfull
Sir Fraunces Drake, Knight, N. L. G. wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
all prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey haue an auncient custome in Persia
(the which is also obserued throughout
all Asia) that none will enterprise to visit
the king, noble man, or perticularly any
other person of countenance, but he cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
with him some thing to present him
with all worthy of thanks, the which is not onely done in
token of great humilitie &amp; obedience, but also of a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
loue &amp; friendly affection to their superiours &amp; wel
willers. So I (Right worshipfull following this Persian
president) hauing taken vpon me this simple translation
out of the Porti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gale tongue, into our English language,
am bold to present &amp; dedicate the same vnto you as a sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification
of my entire good will. The history conteineth
the discouerie and Conquest of the East Indias, made by
sundry worthy Captaines of the Portingales, in the time
of king Don Manuel, &amp; of the king Don Iohn the second
of that name, with the discription, not onely of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
but also of euery harbor apperteining to euery place
whervnto they came, &amp; of the great resistance they found
in the same, by reson wherof there was sundry great bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels
many times fought, &amp; likewise of the commodities &amp;
riches that euery of these places doth yeeld. And for that
I know your worship, with great perill &amp; daunger haue
past those monstrous &amp; bottomelesse seas, am therfore the
more encouraged to desire &amp; pray your worships patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
&amp; defence therof, requesting you with all to pardon
those imperfections, which I acknowledge to be very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb facs="3"/>
&amp; so much the more by reason of my long &amp; many
yeares continuaunce in foreine countries. Howbeit I hope
to haue truly obserued the literall sence &amp; full effect of
the history, as the Author setteth it forth, which if it may
please you to peruse &amp; accept in good part, I shalbe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
emboldened to proceede &amp; publish also the second &amp;
third booke, which I am assured will neither be vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
nor vnprofitable to the readers. Thus alwaies wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
your good worship such prosperous continuance and
like fortunate successe as God hath hetherto sent you in
your daungerous trauaile &amp; affayres, and as maye
euerye waye content your owne heartes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire,
doe euen so take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From
London <date>the fift of March.
1582.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>¶Your worships alwayes to commaund,
Nicholas Lichefield, Gentleman.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>