<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MASTER MIRTH VVAFERER In oxford; or Odiham, or els-vvhere; Quocumque sub axe; , More vvitt, and more grace.</title>
           <author>I., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108377_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15351.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108377</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MASTER MIRTH VVAFERER In oxford; or Odiham, or els-vvhere; Quocumque sub axe; , More vvitt, and more grace.</title>
                 <author>I., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The relection of a conference touching the reall presence. Or a bachelours censure of a masters apologie for Doctour Featlie. By L.I. B. of Art, of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Lechmere, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 377, 388-393, 396-600, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_his_opponent">
   <pb n="133" facs="91"/>
   <head>TO MASTER MIRTH VVAFERER In oxford; or Odiham, or els-vvhere; <hi>Quocumque sub axe;</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, More vvitt, and more grace.</head>
   <p>THere is a time (Sir) as I haue heard, to be merrie: and when better then in the companie of <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th?</hi> I am no good Musitian, yet, for this once, to beare a part with you (for recreations sake,) I will discant vpon your base, <hi>Apologie.</hi> And because I haue heard others more skilfull then your self, when I see that you are out, or sing such
<pb n="134" facs="92"/>
things as you should not, I will be, I say not, your<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor.</note>
      <hi>Cynthius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue reade your elegant <hi>Pamphlet</hi> ouer, and am thinking to tell others what I find in it. What hinders me? If they be good things, your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation will be the more; &amp; that, if I mistake not, is the thing whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch you did aime at when you made it: if they be not, the fault was yours to make them publike, and thereby to giue libertie to men, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout iniurie to your fame, to speake of them.</p>
   <p>He, they saie, that will not be laughed at, must not plaie the foole vpon stage; nor he publish his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes in print that will non endure a <hi>Censure.</hi>
      <note place="margin">VVaf <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</note> you were told before that your scriblings were childish, and full of errours. If after this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you would needs come out in print, you should haue blotted out the faultes (which had beene to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the coppie) and not haue added to your childishnes impudence; and obstinacie to your errours: whereby
<pb n="135" facs="92"/>
your case is now made notorious and inexcusable.</p>
   <p>Whilst the opinion of your wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes stood onlie on report, it might haue beene saide in your behalfe that fame doth not allwaies tell the truth; but if our iudgment of such a defect in you be made according to your true picture, (drawne by your owne self,) the issue of your braine, and image of your insufficiencie, your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inted and approued book, in this case (which is yours) the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logist himself knowes not how to make a good Apologie.</p>
   <p>The ground which a good name and fame doe stand vpon, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch is honours obiect or motiue, is worth and vertue. when we question a mans worth, we may consider him either absolutelie in all kinds, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiuelie to some particular waie of esteeme, that is, onlie in one kinde. That which you, in setting out this <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> aimed at, was to be thought a good <hi>Controuertist,</hi> a discreete <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour</hi> in matter of Religion, an acute
<pb n="136" facs="93"/>
      <hi>Apologist,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doque <hi>oportet</hi> vt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumeliā illatam repella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, <hi>maxime</hi> propter duo. Primò quidem propter bonum eius qui contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliam infert, vt vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacia repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur &amp; de cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianon attēter, secundū illud <hi>Prouerbiorum</hi> 26. <hi>Responde stulto iuxta stultitiam suam ne sibi sapiens videatur</hi> Alio modo propter bonum multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quorum profectus impeditur propter cōtumelias nobis illatas. Vnde Gregorius &amp;c. <hi>S. Tho.</hi> 2.2. <hi>q</hi> 72. <hi>a.</hi> 3.</note> and a good <hi>writer.</hi> In which kind, I tell you freelie <hi>Master Waferer,</hi> you haue defamed your self (if before you had any fame in this kind) &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faited your honour. This I will shew, without solliciting any in Oxford to come and testifie what they know, (twice, since I read your booke, I haue beene there, and neuer asked as much as what you were,) out of your owne mouth, vnder your owne hand, by your owne booke.</p>
   <p>A booke that comes abroad into the world, should haue nothing in it against <hi>faith</hi> or good <hi>manners;</hi> your booke offends in both. How it offēds in <hi>faith,</hi> and how deficient it is in all such learning as you haue vndertaken to shew, the <hi>Censure</hi> will note, it is more then can be saide in fewe words; yet this in generall. The whole scope of the booke is to maintaine an <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,</hi> against Gods Church, &amp; against our
<pb n="137" facs="93"/>
Blessed Sauiours expresse words; for the maintenance of which Heresie, you auouch many more;<note place="margin">VVaf: <hi>pag</hi> 88</note> and stile it a meere <hi>Sophisticall cauil</hi> (ô heauens!) to take Christ immediatlie on his word.</p>
   <p>For manners, Euerie one doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in a writer, then chieflie when he treates of Religion, Veracitie in elocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and tranquillitie of mind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his iudgment may be sincere and his words deserue credit. But your booke discouers in you great defect in both. it shewes you to be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with passion, whollie partiall, and much addicted to the vices of <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating</hi> and <hi>lying.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Censure will note part of your lyes, and calumnies. Here onlie I will put you in mind of your comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards my <hi>Lord of Chalcedon,</hi> and S. E. betwixt whom you saie <hi>you diuide your</hi> (bitter) <hi>language.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Your cariage towards my Lord (whom the greatest schollers in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glād do knowne to be a great scholler) is (giue me leaue to <hi>call a spade a spade</hi>) malapertlie insolent. You are a meere
<pb n="138" facs="94"/>
Punie, and he a Reuerend Prelat; yet you, <hi>Good Master Doctor take notice that—you must be kept ad idem. But by the Doctours leaue—. For shame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not—. not a word of this in answer to one who passeth, for a grandie.</hi> D. <hi>Smith laies downe a rule that — Rather saie I è cōtra. the cōparison of eating flesh in mummie deserues no other answer but mum: yet because it is a peece of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships wisdome it shall be sifted;</hi> Then, <hi>his Lordships singular imperfectiōs,</hi> &amp;, O <hi>most vnsufferable dotage;</hi> with other more bitter speaches, wherewith your Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan gaule seekes to dishonour his knowne worth. And for S. E. your anger scarce forbeares to annihilate him in matter of learning.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>He</hi> you saie, <hi>hath answered but stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meringlie and by roate. so poorlie as not worth confutation. if as fraudulent and fabulous as his relation is illiterate and slender, they haue neither truth nor hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie in them. simple, simple, simple, simple, simple, simple. Far belowe the answer of</hi> D. <hi>Featlie, a weaker pen may foile him. euerie boy can tell you. Your Sophistrie is
<pb n="139" facs="94"/>
slender and boyish. your verie</hi> A. B. C. <hi>of Logick will teach you. Onlie smile at some passages and they are answered. He must giue me leaue to answer with a smile. you doe wiselie to applie your self to the vnlearned, for they that can sift authors — we will pardon his doting. you close this sentēce verie saucilie. if you were not as good as cup-valiant. though you should teach the ignorant as seldome you do</hi> (now at least in his place I am to do so; but <hi>Mercurie</hi> is not made of euery <hi>stock.</hi> Pardon my interrupting of you, I was wearie in gathering tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se phrases out of your booke. Brieflie, that I may end, though you do not, you tell him, he is) <hi>shameles and foole-bardie. that there is in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> answer</hi> (that Reader, which thou hast but now seene,) <hi>insufficiencie and obstinacie. falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious dealing. the spirit of contradiction. bitternes. satyrs. inuectiues. jeeres. slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. detractions. lies. non-sence. calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> and what not? yet forsooth, <hi>if some lines may seeme to gall him</hi> I<hi>'le make</hi> (say you) <hi>no Apologie, because it can plead retaliation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="140" facs="95"/>Can it so Master Waferer? and are the holie Brethren vindicatiue, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? It seemes.</p>
   <q>Et Laeto sua bilis inest.</q>
   <p>I haue recited part of your language which you say you <hi>deuided betwixt them</hi> two; for you deale by <hi>retaile</hi> with them; with other Catholike Deuines you deale in grosse, calling their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>iugling Philosophie;</hi> their <hi>tenets, impious delusions;</hi> their pens, <hi>impudent,</hi> and their doctrine <hi>such as will not stick to license the lowdest lie, so it be aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to the cause of Rome.</hi> So you.</p>
   <p>There are some, the Philosopher tels, <hi>qui circa finem communem peruerse iudicant, who iudge vnto wardlie of the the common, highest end.</hi> You know their name. The Scripture saith there are an infinite companie of <hi>fooles,</hi> and, <hi>euerie one will be medling.</hi> you beginne to be <hi>wise in your owne conceit;</hi> I will <hi>answer</hi> or censure you, this once, least that egge prooue a cocatrice in your braine. my Censure shall be your glasse wherein you may examine both your
<pb n="141" facs="95"/>
learning and your manners, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</p>
   <p>I shall be thought by some, lesse wise, for appearing with you vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he stage; especiallie in the manner that I do; but, no matter; so I may do you, or any other, good. One said,<note place="margin">S. Paul.</note>
      <hi>to the weake I became as weak, that I might gaine the weak.</hi> and, <hi>I am made all things to all men, to gaine all to Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To deale with you, required no sad thoughts, or deep studdie: and there are <hi>Feriae Academicae;</hi> schollers haue their daies of recreation. <hi>Neque semper arcum.</hi> you came abroad, Master Waferer, as I suppose (a fit of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) to shew <hi>Mirth;</hi> and I, without offence may sometimes smile. <hi>congruit &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati ridere quia laetans:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tertull,</note>
      <hi>de suis aemulis lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere quia secura est.</hi> It appertained to the part I vndertook. <hi>Vbicumque dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus risus officium est.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Sickmens pills are lapt in sweete, some maladies be cured with musick. If mirth recouer you, I shall be glad I made you merrie. If vpon the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you grow penitent, I shall be
<pb n="142" facs="96"/>
glad I made you sorrie: <hi>Not that you were made sorrie, but that you sorrowed to repentance.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To others I shall giue warning to take heede of such Pāphlets as yours, made to spred errours. they be <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and vaine bablings</hi> that increase by degrees to more and more vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines. they partake in their kind the pestilent nature of serpents; and this, (yours Master Waferer,) which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth vp the head to hisse at the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church, and spits venom at the Defenders of it, is one. But I will cut it, into pieces; and with the segments will make a medicine to cure the swelling which another of the same kind <hi>(Featlies Conference)</hi> hath made in your head.</p>
   <p>This your Pamphlet, the gay coate of your Indiscretion, you haue laced vp and downe verie trimlie, with verses. <hi>Nunc oblita mihi tot carmina.</hi> It is longer since I was a child. Els, out of the ruines of that kind of learning I would hurle sometimes a piece, at the head of your Apologie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="143" facs="96"/>My quarrell, Master Waferer, is not with your person, but with your book. If I touch you it is by that <hi>medium:</hi> no other, put that of, I touch not you but some other that hath scribbled it. Whether you be the man, or not; I wish to you as to my self, and to all, that God in his mercie will please to amend what is amisse in vs; and make vs eternallie his seruants. This is the minde and prayer of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your frindlie Enemie and censuring Friend. <hi>L. I.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>