<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, the Lord Archbishop of Canterburie his Grace, Primate and Metropolitan of all England.</title>
           <author>Covell, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108881_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5882</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108881</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, the Lord Archbishop of Canterburie his Grace, Primate and Metropolitan of all England.</title>
                 <author>Covell, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A modest and reasonable examination, of some things in vse in the Church of England, sundrie times heretofore misliked : and now lately, in a booke called the (Plea of the innocent:) and an assertion for true and Christian church policy, made for a full satisfaction to al those, that are of iudgement, and not possessed with a preiudice against this present church gouernment, wherein the principall poynts are fully, and peaceably aunswered, which seeme to bee offensiue in the ecclesiasticall state of this kingdome. The contentes whereof are set downe in the page following. By William Couell, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Covell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 215, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="114"/>
   <pb facs="114"/>
   <head>To the most Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, the Lord Archbishop of Canterburie his Grace, Primate and Metropolitan of all England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat benefit (Right Reuerend) this Church hath receiued by your Graces meanes, (God bessing your Counsell vnder the gouernment of two great Princes) as this age present doth sensiblie perceiue, so the memorie thereof shalbe honorable in the time to come. For when the vertuons Gouernment of our late Souereigne, had banished from all parts of her Kingdome the Tyrannie and superstitiō of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> some men (fit instruments to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbe the peacefull happinesse of this Land) feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as it seemed of the dangers that might follow, and impatient of that forme of gouernment which mercy and wisedome had planted for the Churches safetie, laboured by meanes, ouer violent, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, to bring in (perhaps from the partiall loue to the orders of those Churches which comfortably refresht them in the time of banishment) a presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Discipline; both of them (notwithstanding) following a diuers shape of the Ecclesiasticall state in diuers times; the one in peace, the other in perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,
<pb facs="115"/>
neither of them both, doubtlesse, (circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances being weighed) either warranted by truth or answerable to these times; The one labouring, to ouerload vs, with an intollerable burden of humane traditions (polliticke inuentions to make an outward greatnesse whilst inwardly Religion must needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aile) the other to strippe her, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as the day wherein shee was first borne; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging her teachers, by robbing them of honour and maintenaunce; traducing that learning, wherein many of our Reuerend Fathers were equall to any in any part of the world besides, and in steade of these, making the Church to doe Pennance for her wontonnesse in the dayes of superstition, being left vnpitied, desolate, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and without honour; all their purposes tending to this end, to make vs had in dirision of all those that were rounde about vs; Thus these two enemies in our owne bosome, looking both of them with enuie at your happinesse, and with Ielosie at that fauour, which we might be suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to beare towards either of them; their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centions were not so violent to each other, as they both were cruell and daungerous to our peace; as if <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Manasses,</hi> had made a truce, and both of them concluded to deuour <hi>Iuda</hi>; At this time your Lordship (for lawes and authoritie had
<pb facs="115"/>
restrayned the one) vndertooke the defence of this Church Gouernment, against the other; wherein doubtlesse if your great wisedome and moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had not like another Athanasius, indured the furie and rage of this vnbridled multitude, Wee might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>stly haue feared, that disorder and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risme would haue tyrannously possest long since, the worthiest and most beautifull parts of our whole land. And as doubtlesse it was happie for the Church that you vndertooke by writing, the defence of this cause, (seeing no man could haue done it either better, or with lesse exception) so the day of your admission to the Sea of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> is, and was (in all likelihood) (next vnto our late Souereigne) the forciblest meanes, and the best se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, this Church then could hope for to procure her peace; neither can the Clergie of this land, but in dutie and thankefulnesse, offer vp continually, their Zealous and deuout prayers, for all blessings to come downe, and light, and rest vpon his sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Maiestie, and vpon his Royall posteritie to many thousand generations, for those Princely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, which his Highnesse extending to you, giueth, as vndoubted assurance to all vs, of the peace, prosperitie and happinesse, of this Church; I haue often with my selfe thought, that the greatest riches and most to be valued,
<pb facs="116"/>
which our late Souereigne left vnto his Princely Maiestie with the lawfull inheritance of this kingdome, was a learned and deuout Clergie; A wise and Religious Counsell; An Honorable, and Auncient Nobilitie; Valiant and discreet leaders; rich and louing Citizens; painfull and diligent husbandmen; In one word, a people not in any Vertue Inferour to any Nation of the earth; and for Loyaltie, and obedience (be it spoken without enuie) aboue them all; yet in the happinesse of all this, there haue not beene since wanting, which earnestly haue sought to ouerthrow the state of this Church; We know not their Intentions, the world seeth they are cunning to doe, and to speake euill; and whatsoeuer may seeme auaileable to further their cause, wanteth not the best aduantage, that any opportunitie can giue vnto them; in which respect it is all our duties, who desire the peace of this Church, &amp; prosperitie of the Commonwealth, no way to be wanting, to the reasonable, Iust, and honest defence of a good cause; In regard whereof, though by many degrees I am the vnworthiest of a great number, who haue, and are readie, to write in the defence of this Church (the aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in this cause hauing receiued the first &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Wounds from your pen) yet my care amongst the rest was, to imploy my labour, according to that
<pb facs="116"/>
abilitie which God hath giuen me, in the modest defence, of the Gouernment of this Church. Which hauing beene handled so often, and so learnedly heretofore, it ought not to seeme straunge to any, and I hope, will be pardoned at your hand, if wee gather but the gleanings after those, that plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully haue sown, and haue reaped before vs. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer my labour, and trauell hath beene in this, it is due vnto your Grace, whose manifold, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and vndeserued fauours, together with my priuate dutie, challengeth me &amp; my whole seruice, by a greater nearenesse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Leu. 23.11.</hi>
      </note> than that Law; <hi>yee shall bring a sheafe of the first fruites of your har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest vnto the Priest.</hi> Thus hartely desiring your Lordships Fauourable acceptance of this paines, how small soeuer, with my continuall prayers, for the long preseruation of your Graces health, and Honor, to the comfort of a great number, and the singular blessing of this Church, euen through the mercies of him, in whom we all liue, moue, and haue our being, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces in all Dutie. WILLIAM COVELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>