<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTVOVS LADY BRIDGET LYDDELL, My much Honoured Aunt:
Grace and peace be multiplied by Jesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Lockyer, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108798_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06161</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16652</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108798</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTVOVS LADY BRIDGET LYDDELL, My much Honoured Aunt:
Grace and peace be multiplied by Jesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Lockyer, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A divine discovery of sincerity : according to its proper and peculiar nature: very profitable for all sorts of persons to peruse. First preached, and now published, for the good of Gods Church in generall. By Nicholas Lockyer Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Lockyer, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 229, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTVOVS LADY BRIDGET LYDDELL, My much Honoured Aunt:
Grace and peace be multiplied by Jesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam: 'Tis Gods command to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and in him to us,
<hi>That we should walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and be perfect.</hi> Absolute
perfection God doth not there meane, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionall: which is, when we
desire and endeavour with <hi>David,</hi> to have all our waies conformed to
all Gods Statutes. Intentionall perfection, <pb facs="3"/>is no other but
sincere walking; and what this is, this tract now humbly presented to your
Ladyship, will plainely make knowne unto you. A sincere heart, <hi>is a
heart after Gods owne heart;</hi> which of all jewells which the Gentry, and
Nobility weare, is the most resplendent, in the breast and bosome to be
worne. The richest jeweller, Christ, proffers this pearle of great price,
<hi>without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or money-worth,</hi> and the multitude sleight it, as a
low prised thing, not worth the seeking after; but your Ladyship hath
otherwise learned Christ: Many things Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, may be convenient, but one is
necessarie; to wit, a sincere heart. The acquiring of this, is the worke
of our whole life: the setting forth of this, in its nature and lustre, is
the worke <pb facs="3"/>of Christs Ministers; the least, and
unworthiest of all which, is your Nephew, which hath in this tract, done
something to this effect; from which, if your Ladyship shall reape an
increase of good, to that sweete stocke you have, I shall humbly
blesse God. To whose blessing I commend your selfe and worthy
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; this worke, and the unworthy Authour,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your much obliged Nephew, NICHOLAS
LOCKYER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>