<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Noble-minded Gentlemen, and Heroicke Spirits in Court, Citie, and Countrey.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108584_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05594</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15711</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108584</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Noble-minded Gentlemen, and Heroicke Spirits in Court, Citie, and Countrey.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most delectable and true discourse, of an admired and painefull peregrination from Scotland, to the most famous kingdomes in Europe, Asia and Affricke : With the particular descriptions (more exactly set downe then hath beene heeretofore in English) of Italy, Sycilia, Dalmatia, Ilyria, Epire, Peloponnesus, Macedonia, Thessalia, and the whole continent of Greece, Creta, Rhodes, the Iles Cyclades ... and the chiefest countries of Asia Minor. From thence, to Cyprus, Phænicia, Syria ... and the sacred citie Ierusalem, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 126, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all Noble-minded Gentlemen, and Heroicke Spirits in Court, Citie, and Countrey.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, of these my double paines of a two-fold Pilgrimage: first, in my personall progresse, to these famous places; and next, a second Peregrination of minde, in reuiewing the same in the Map of my owne Memory. I haue, for thy more easie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, diuided them in sixe seuerall parts: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them therefore with the same loue that I offer them to thee, since they cost thee nothing but the Reading, how deere soeuer they are to mee. I could haue furnished this History with more new-coind Language, but I detest the ornament of such an ecclypsed shadow, that would obumbrate the beames of a glorious Subiect: Let other fantasticall braines dote, and prosecute the path of smooth inuented phrases, and new deuised diriuations; to soare aloft with the waxed feathers of flitghthered eloquence, wanting matter, which is the heart of the worke: I haue in my owne disposition, and for thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter satisfaction (Gentle Reader) set downe the same in the vulgar tongue of this Northerne Ile; Protesting, if
<pb facs="3"/>
(peraduenture) I finde thy kind acceptance, I shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to thy eyes, the second Lampe of this new light, which shall sh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w thee the distance of miles from place to place, and the valew of money in euery Kingdome, Dukedome, Republique, Territory, or Iland, wheresoeuer I haue beene; with the particular narration of the great Tributes and Charges a Trauellour must defray in such a voyage; which for the present I haue abridged, and partly omitted, for diuers weighty causes. As for these gnawing wormes, which carpe the merites of brauer Spirits, and contemne that vertue in others, that they cannot attaine vnto themselues, I craue they would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare their sinistruous censure, vntill such time, that by their owne industry, they atchieue the like attempts: Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing such like vomiters of venome no greater punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to be plagued with the experience of that which I sustained in my Trauailes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine as thou merites,</hi> W. Lithgow.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>