<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An admonition to the readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108033_Bo1_40_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04845</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14977</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108033</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An admonition to the readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectvres vpon Ionas : delivered at Yorke in the yeare of our Lorde 1594. By John Kinge: newlie corrected and amended</title>
                 <author>King, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 660, 2, 661-683, 3, 685-706, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>An admonition to the readers.</head>
   <p>IT may seeme strange, that I have vsed so lardge and impertinent a digression in behalfe of good learning. As after a longe orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on spent in the praise of Hercules, one asked, <hi>quis vituperavit?</hi> Who dispraised Hercules? So you may desire to know, vvho dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praised learning. Let it suffice you to vnderstand, that one of my fellow-labourers in this worke of the Lorde, whome neither I iudge in the freedome of his conscience for speaking what hee thought, neither can free from the community of erring with my selfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, because wee are all vnperfite in knowledge, vpon the best day of the seven, in the best place, and before not the meanest as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, handling the wordes of the Apostle, 1. Cor. 16.13. <hi>watch yee, stand fast in the faith</hi>; tooke occasion therevpon, to stande for the onelye <hi>worde of faith</hi> in sermons, with vehement exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="556" facs="286"/>
the histories of the Gentiles, Orators, Poets, &amp; other prophane knowledge. Wherein, let it be his commendation, that according to the warning of his text, he was diligent in his <hi>watch,</hi> and being iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the truth, suspected those for enemies which were not, and shewed his fidelity to the <hi>faith,</hi> though he went a litle too far, &amp; mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the iust measure of applying it. For mine owne part, I woulde have spared mine answer, especially in publicke, but that I perceived the speech to bee bent to some marke of a few that laboured in that calling, and the eares of the people dranke it in with earnest attēti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, because it was heartily spoken, and some were perplexed, others offended therewith, and learning was wounded, which not to have salved had beene a wrong, and the arrow flew from her side, &amp; glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon vs all without exception in that church, who in our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of teaching held no other course.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>