<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle of the aucthour. To the most adorned, and best deseruynge to be reueren∣ced of al that loue the know∣ledge of the Mathematicks. Abraham Ortelius of Andwarp.</title>
           <author>Lhuyd, Humfrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108126_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68397</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108126</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle of the aucthour. To the most adorned, and best deseruynge to be reueren∣ced of al that loue the know∣ledge of the Mathematicks. Abraham Ortelius of Andwarp.</title>
                 <author>Lhuyd, Humfrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The breuiary of Britayne : As this most noble, and renowmed iland, was of auncient time deuided into three kingdomes, England, Scotland and Wales. Contaynyng a learned discourse of the variable state, [and] alteration therof, vnder diuers, as wel natural: as forren princes, [and] conquerours. Together with the geographicall description of the same, such as nether by elder, nor later writers, the like hath been set foorth before. Writen in Latin by Humfrey Lhuyd of Denbigh, a Cambre Britayne, and lately Englished by Thomas Twyne, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Llwyd, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 96 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_dedication">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Epistle of the aucthour. To the most adorned, and</hi> best deseruynge to be reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>ced of al that loue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Mathematicks.</hi> Abraham Ortelius of <hi>Andwarp.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EARLY beloued <hi>Orte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> that day wherein I was cōstayned to depart from <hi>London:</hi> I recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your Description of ASIA ad before I came home to my house: I fell into a very perillous Feuer, which hath so torne this poore body of mine, these. x. continuall dayes: that I was brought into despayre of my life. But, my hope <hi>Iesus Christe,</hi> is layde vp in my bosome. Howbeit, neither the dayly shakynge of the continuall Feuer, with a double Tertian, neither the lookyng for present death, neither the vehement headache without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission: coulde put the remembrance of my <hi>Ortelius,</hi> out of my troubled brayne. Wherfore, I send vnto you my <hi>Wales,</hi> not beutifully set forth in all
<pb facs="19"/>
poinctes, yet truly depeinted, so be that certeyn notes be obserued, which I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered euen when I was redy to die.</p>
   <p>You shall also receaue the description of <hi>England,</hi> set forth as well with the auntient names: as those which are now vsed, and an other <hi>England</hi> also drawne forth perfectly enough. Besides certein fragmentes written with mine owne hande. Which, notwithstandynge that they be written foorth in a rude hande, and seeme to be imperfect: yet doubt not, they be well grounded by proofes, and authorities of auntient writers.</p>
   <p>Which, also (if God had spared me life) you should haue receaued in better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and in all respects perfect. Take therfore, this last remembrance of thy <hi>Humfrey,</hi> and for euer <hi>adieu,</hi> my deare friend <hi>Ortelius.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Denbigh,</hi> in <hi>Gwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedh,</hi> or <hi>Northwales,</hi>
         <date>the. xxx. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. 1568.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours both liuyng, and diyng:
Humfrey Lhuyd.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>