<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ELEGIA INTRODUCTO∣ria
in Lachrymas sequentes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108346_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05140</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15270</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108346</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ELEGIA INTRODUCTO∣ria
in Lachrymas sequentes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Phyala lachrymarum. Or A few friendly teares, shed over the dead body of Mr Nathaniel Weld Mr of Arts of Emanuel Colledge in Cambridge : who in the short journey of his life, died betwene the five and sixe and twentieth yeare of his youth, 1633. Together with sundry choyce meditations of mortalitie</title>
                 <author>Lathum, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 47, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="elegy">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>ELEGIA INTRODUCTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria
in Lachrymas sequentes.</head>
   <l>Scarce is (amongst a thousand dayes) one day</l>
   <l>So fortunate and luckie every way,</l>
   <l>But that in compasse of those twice twelve howres,</l>
   <l>Some one or other lucklesse chance devours:</l>
   <l>Or some of all from all in generall,</l>
   <l>Or all at once, from some in speciall;</l>
   <l>And every state one thing or other meet</l>
   <l>That mingles gall, and aloes with their sweet.</l>
   <l>Each where I heare complaint, and most lament</l>
   <l>On every side of losse and detriment;</l>
   <l>Husbands the wives, the wives their husbands losse,</l>
   <l>Parents their child, children their parents crosse;</l>
   <l>Brothers for sisters death are discontent,</l>
   <l>Sisters for brothers; these do those lament;</l>
   <l>Merchants their ships, shepheards do lose their sheep,</l>
   <l>Some waile the losse of what they cannot keepe.</l>
   <l>I none of these, but I have lost a friend;</l>
   <l>Time may all else, but not this losse amend:</l>
   <l>Which losse whoever suffer, understand</l>
   <l>What 'tis to be depriv'd of their right hand,</l>
   <l>To have a legge cut off, an eye put out,</l>
   <l>And live a creeple, to be led about;</l>
   <l>A maimed-uselesse man, at once bereft</l>
   <l>Of outward strength, and inward joy; so left</l>
   <l>A wandring Pilgrim in a land unknown,</l>
   <l>Injur'd of all, because belov'd of none:</l>
   <l>This leglesse, eyelesse, handlesse man am I,</l>
   <l>All these I lost, when he from mee did die.</l>
   <l>All yee that chance, (if any chance) to reed</l>
   <l>These sorry lines of mine; if yee indeed</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Of such like friend be sped, as I him vant</l>
   <l>(In this selfe-loving Age, (ah) very scant)</l>
   <l>Their patronage and mine I you commend,</l>
   <l>For yee can truly value such a friend.</l>
   <l>Your tender gentle hearts can entertaine</l>
   <l>A quicke impression of anothers paine,</l>
   <l>And nimbly can (at halfe a word) resent</l>
   <l>The weight and burden of their discontent:</l>
   <l>And passionate your loft compassion is,</l>
   <l>And tender unto all that is amisse.</l>
   <l>For love of that, which is to you most leefe</l>
   <l>Come all yee (as my seconds) to my griefe;</l>
   <l>Lend mee your teares, and sighs to furnish out</l>
   <l>The wofull worke which I am now about.</l>
   <l>And if such chance you ever doe mischance,</l>
   <l>(As God defend it should) in sovenance</l>
   <l>And faire requitall of your love, Ile pay</l>
   <l>You teares for teares, and sighs for your sighs; nay,</l>
   <l>(Unwilling, barely to repay your owne)</l>
   <l>Ile pay you interest of ten for one:</l>
   <l>And (till my briny braine be drayned dry)</l>
   <l>Will side with you, and mourne incessantly:</l>
   <l>(Ab) for your griefe will bring to memorie</l>
   <l>Mine owne unhappy griefe, and keepe my wound</l>
   <l>Still bleeding fresh, whilst ev'ry seeming sound,</l>
   <l>And each like word, (that even but relates</l>
   <l>And to his name alludes) insinuates,</l>
   <l>And will my heart with newes thereof informe,</l>
   <l>Still raising in my bosome a new storme;</l>
   <l>So shall your mone my mournfull mone augment,</l>
   <l>For full of harmony, a sweet consent</l>
   <l>Of sorrow is with sorrow, teares with teares,</l>
   <l>And griefe in parts the musicke higher reares;</l>
   <l>But now from you my conference must breake</l>
   <l>Whilst all my other mourners I do thus bespeake.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>