<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE MAGNANIMOVS AND ILLUSTRIOUS LORD, IAMES, EARLE OF MONTROSE, Lord GRAHAME, Baron of MURDOCK, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108580_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05590</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15709</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108580</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE MAGNANIMOVS AND ILLUSTRIOUS LORD, IAMES, EARLE OF MONTROSE, Lord GRAHAME, Baron of MURDOCK, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gushing teares of godly sorrovv : Containing, the causes, conditions, and remedies of sinne, depending mainly upon contrition and confession. And they seconded, with sacred and comfortable passages, under the mourning cannopie of teares, and repentance. By William Lithgovv</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Bryson, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lithgow, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE MAGNANIMOVS AND ILLUSTRIOUS LORD, IAMES, EARLE OF MONTROSE, Lord GRAHAME, Baron of MURDOCK, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Illustrious LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F gratefull duetie, may be reputed the childe of reason, then (doubtlesse) my choisest wishes, and best Affection, must here fall prostrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your auspicuous and friendlie face, fast chayned, in the


<pb facs="3"/>
fetters of obedience. Flatterie and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude I disdayne as hell: And to court your Lo: with elegant phrases, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as much as who would light a Candle, to light the Sunne: Your Noble and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicke Vertues light this Kingdome, and who can give them light: For, as the <hi>Auro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> of your honoured reputation, is become that <hi>Constantinopolitan Hyppodrome,</hi> to this our Northrene and virgine <hi>Albion;</hi> so lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, the same singularitie of worth, hath raised your auspicuous selfe, to be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numentall glorie of your famous, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Predecessours, iustly tearmed, THE SWORD OF SCOTLAND: Your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Summers day hath fullie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, the sacred Trophees of their match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse memorie; best befitting the generosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of your magnanimous minde. That as the GRAHAME, from long antiquitie, being the most ancient surname, of this unconquered Nation; so they, your old


<pb facs="3"/>
aged Ancestors, have left a lineall constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Valour and Worthinesse, to bee inherent in your most hopefull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonage, which God may long continue to you, your Race, and your Posteritie. My humble request, pleads the continuance of your favour, that as your late renowned Grand-father and Father, were unto mee both friendlie and favourable (proceeding from their great goodnesse, not my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts;) so expect I the same from your tender bountie, which hitherto beyond my merit, hath beene exceeding kyndlie manifested. For the which, my prayse and prayers, the two sisters of myne Oblation, rest solidlie ingenochiated at the feete of your conspicuous Clemencie. This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent worke in its secret Infancie, was both seene and perused by your Lo: but now enlarged, polished, and published: I have done my best, though not my uttermost: The discourse it selfe, runneth most on


<pb facs="4"/>
the causes, conditions, and remedies of sin, and they sharply linked in generalls and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: The whole substance of my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, sealing vp the happinesse of a sinners conversion to God, under the mourning Cannopie, of <hi>Teares,</hi> and <hi>Repentance.</hi> The lynes are plaine, yet pithie; and although the subject may carrie no loftie nor Poë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke style; yet themanner, the matter, the Man, and his Muse, are all, and only yours, and I left theirs, onlie to serve you, and your noble disposition. Accept therefore my good Lord, both the gift, and givers minde, with the same alacritie, as I offer them in Love and humilitie; which being shelterd under your pious and prudent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, shall enforce mee to remaine, as I vow ever to be, whilst I have being,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most obsequious and most obser vant Oratour, WILLIAM LITHGOVV.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>