<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable, Sir Francis VValsingham
Knight, principall Secretary to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, and one of hir highnesse most Honorable priuie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Nicholas, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108920_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06340</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16807</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108920</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable, Sir Francis VValsingham
Knight, principall Secretary to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, and one of hir highnesse most Honorable priuie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Nicholas, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pleasant historie of the conquest of the VVeast India, now called new Spayne : atchieued by the vvorthy prince Hernando Cortes Marques of the valley of Huaxacac, most delectable to reade: translated out of the Spanishe tongue, by T.N. Anno. 1578</title>
                 <author>López de Gómara, Francisco</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 405, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, Sir Francis VValsingham
<hi>Knight, principall Secretary to the</hi> Queenes most excellent Maiestie, <hi>and one of hir highnesse most Honorable priuie Counsell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hilest I abode (right Honorable) in the Isle of Palma, in affaires of merchandize for the vvorshipfull <hi>Thomas Locke</hi> deceased, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, time then permitted me, to haue cōference vvith auncient gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen vvhiche had serued in the Conquest of the vvest India, novve called nevve Spaine, vnder the princely Captaine <hi>Hernando Cortez.</hi> By vvhom as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vvitnesses at many of the actes herein contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I vvas credibly informed, that this delectable and vvorthy Historie is a most true and iust reporte of matter paste in effect: vvherefore I did the more vvillingly turne ouer and peruse the same, vvhiche is a Mirrour and an excellent president, for all such as shall take in hande to gouerne nevve Discoueries: for here they shall behold, hovv Glorie, Renovvne, and perfite Felicitie, is not gotten but vvith greate paines, trauaile, perill and daunger of life: here shall they see the vvisedome, curtesie, valour and pollicie of vvorthy Captaynes, yea and the faithfull hartes vvhiche they ought to beare vnto their Princes ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: here also is described, hovv to vse and correct the stubbern &amp; mutinous persons, &amp; in vvhat order <pb facs="3"/>to exalt the good, stoute and vertuous Souldiers, and chiefly, hovv to preserue and keepe that bevvtifull Dame <hi>Lady Victorie</hi> vvhē she is obtayned. And vvhere it vvas supposed, that the golden mettall had his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and place in the East and VVeast <hi>India,</hi> neare vnto the hote Zoane, (as moste learned vvriters helde opinion) it is novve approued by the vente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous trauellour and vvorthy captaine <hi>Martin Frobisher</hi> Esquire, yea and also through the greate paynes, procurement, and firste inuention of the vvorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Mychaell Locke</hi> Merchaunt, that the same golden mettall dothe also lie incorporate in the bovvelles of the Norvveast parties, enuironned vvith admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tovvers, Pillers and Pynacles, of Rockes, Stone, and Ise, possessed of a people bothe straunge, &amp; rare in shape, attire and lyuing, yea suche a Countrey and people, as all
<hi>Europe</hi> had forsaken and made no account of, excepte our moste gratious Queene and hir subiectes, vvhome vndoubtedly God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, not onely to be supreme Princesse ouer them, but also to be a meane that the name of Christ may be knovven vnto this Heathenish and Sauage generation.</p>
   <p>Not long since (right Honorable) I happened to trauayle from the famous Cittie of <hi>Tolledo</hi> in <hi>Spayne,</hi> tovvarde highe
<hi>Castile,</hi> and by fortune ouertooke an auncient Gentlemen, vvorshipfully accompanied, vnto vvhō I vvas so bold as to approch, beseching his vvorship to aduertise me of his iourney: vvho (after he had beheld my white head &amp; beard) ansvvered ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gentlely, that his intēt vvas to trauayle vnto the king <pb facs="3"/>of Spaynes Court, and vvelcomed me vnto his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. In shorte space that vve had iourneyed togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and communed of each other his Countrey, it pleased him to say as follovveth: My good friende, if you knevv my sute vnto the Kings maiestie, you vvould iudge that I vvere a mad man, and therefore to shorten oure vvay, I vvill declare my attempted sute vnto you. You shall vnderstande, that I am a Gentleman of lxx. yeares of age, and sometimes I serued in the ciuill vvarres of <hi>Pirru,</hi> vvhere I vvas vvounded in diuers parts of my body, and am novv thereby lame in one of my legges and shoulder. I haue neyther VVife nor childe, and at this presente (God be praised) I haue in the Contractation house in the Citie of <hi>Siuill,</hi> in golde and plate, the summe of thirtie thousande Duckates: and I haue also in <hi>Pirru</hi> in good lands and possessions, the yearely rente of tvvelue thousande Duckates, vvhiche rentes and readye money is sufficiente to mainteyne a poore Gentleman. But al this notvvithstanding, I do novv sue vnto the Kings Maiestie, to haue licence and authoritie to discouer and conquere a certayne parte of <hi>India,</hi> vvhyche adioyneth vvith <hi>Brazile,</hi> and is part of the Empire of <hi>Pirru,</hi> I pray you novve declare what you thinke of my sute. By my troth sir (quoth I) I trust your vvorship vvill pardon a rash and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine iudgemēt, which you now demand at my hād: yea truly (quoth he) say vvhat you list. Then (quoth I) my opiniō is, that you are not wel in your wit, for vvhat vvould you haue? vvil not reason suffice you? or else would you now in your old days be an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <pb facs="4"/>considering that your Sepulchre attendeth for you, Novve truly I thanke you (quoth he) for of youre iudgement are most men: but I say vnto you, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that all flesh must finish, I seeke for no quiet rest in this transitorie life: yea the vvise and Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctors do teach and admonish, that euery true Christian is borne, not for his ovvne priuate vvealth and pleasure, but rather to help and succoure others his poore breethren. Likevvise doe I consider the greate number of Gentlemen, yonger brethren, and other valiāt persons, vvho through vvant of liuing, do fall into many disorders. VVherefore to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish my dutie tovvard God and my Prince, and to releeue such poore Gentlemen, do I novv attempte this iourney, vvith the aduenture of my bodye and goodes, and for that purpose I haue in readinesse foure tall Shippes, vvell furnished in the porte of <hi>Saint Lucar de Barrameda,</hi> hoping assuredlye, that before the life depart from my body, to heare these valiante yong Gentlemen (vvhome novv I meane to haue in my company) say, oh happie day, vvhen olde
<hi>Zarate</hi> (for so is my name) broughte vs from penurie, yea and from a number of perils that vve vvere like to fall into. I hope also, that the royall estate of my Prince shall be by my paynes and poore seruice en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged: beleeue you me, this is the onely sumptuous Tumbe that I pretende to builde for my poore car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kas. But yet I knovv there are some, vnto vvhome I may compare the Bore that lyeth vvallovvyng in his Stye, vvho vvill not lette to saye, vvhat neede vve any other vvorld, honor, or Kingdomes? let vs
<pb facs="4"/>be contented vvith that vve haue: vvho may easily be aunsvvered, Sir glutton, your paunch is full, and little care you for the glory of God, honor of youre Prince, neyther the neede and necessitie of youre poore neyboures. VVith this conclusion the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ended his tale, the iudgement vvhereof I leaue to noble Gentlemen his peeres to be determined.</p>
   <p>And vvhere oure Captayne <hi>Hernando Cortez,</hi> of vvhose valiant actes this historie treateth, hathe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued immortal fame, euē so doubtlesse I hope, that vvithin this happie Realme is novv liuing a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vvhose zeale of trauayle and valiant begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings dothe prognosticate greate, maruellous, and happie successe: for perfection of honor and profite is not gotten in one daye, nor in one or tvvo voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as the true histories of the East and VVest Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests by Spanyardes and Portingalles do testifye. And calling to remembrance the greate zeale and good vvill vvhich your honor hath alvvayes exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to good and profitable attemptes, and especially in the proceedings of the nevv discouery, youre ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor hath not only vsed liberalitie in your aduētures, but also taken greate paynes in Courte, to aduance and further the voyage, a number I saye of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Marriners, and other artificers, shal haue great cause to pray for your honor. And vvhere I for my parte haue tasted of your honors goodnesse sundrye vvayes, I am novve most humbly to beseech youre honor to accept this poore gifte, the vvhiche I haue translated out of the Spanish tong, not decked vvith gallant couloures, nor yet fyled vvith pleasant phrase <pb facs="5"/>of Rhetorike, for these things are not for poore Marchant trauellers, but are reserued to learned VVriters: yet I trust the Author vvill pardon mee, bycause I haue gone as neere the sense of this Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as my cunning vvoulde reach vnto. I also craue, that it may please youre honor, vvhen your greate and vvaightie businesse vvill permitte, to beholde this vvorke, and that shall be for me an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente to take in hande the translation of the East
<hi>India,</hi> vvhiche is novve enioyed by the King of Portingall. Thus I ende, beseeching the Almighty to preserue your honorable estate. (?)</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honors most ready at commaundement Thomas Nicholas.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>