<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS LOVING PILGRIMAGIOVS POET,
WILLIAM LITHGOW.</title>
           <author>A., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108590_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15716</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108590</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS LOVING PILGRIMAGIOVS POET,
WILLIAM LITHGOW.</title>
                 <author>A., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Scotlands vvelcome to her native sonne, and soveraigne lord, King Charles : wherein is also contained, the maner of his coronation, and convocation of Parliament; the whole grievances, and abuses of the common-wealth of this kingdome, with diverse other relations, never heretofore published. Worthy to be by all the nobles and gentry perused; and to be layd vp in the hearts, and chests of the whole commouns, whose interests may best claime it, either in meane, or maner, from which their priuiledges, and fortunes are drawne, as from the loadstar of true direction. By William Lithgovv, the bonaventure, of Europe, Asia, and Africa</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS LOVING PILGRIMAGIOVS POET,
WILLIAM LITHGOW.</head>
   <l>CAN not thy Travells, blaze abroad thy worth?</l>
   <l>Which never yet did SCOT, the lyke set forth,</l>
   <l>Nor one in <hi>Europe,</hi> can with <hi>Thee</hi> compare,</l>
   <l>For thyne adventures, excellent, and rare,</l>
   <l>But that thou must, in adding fame, to fame,</l>
   <l>Thy matchles merits, in thy <hi>Muse</hi> proclayme:</l>
   <l>I can not call it Pryde, but vertue showne,</l>
   <l>From <hi>Thee,</hi> to vs, through this wyde <hi>Ile</hi> well knowne:</l>
   <l>But more an obligation, which thou ought.</l>
   <l>Vnto thy natiue <hi>Soyle;</hi> so headlong brought,</l>
   <l>In deep distresses, grieuances, and losse,</l>
   <l>Whilst sorrow, on sorrow, addes crosse, to crosse,</l>
   <l>Which thou rippst vp, vnto the very roote,</l>
   <l>Whence all these evills come, and springing sprout:</l>
   <l>Besydes this jouiall welcome, to our King,</l>
   <l>Which quicke <hi>Invention,</hi> now to light do'th bring:</l>
   <l>O! rare relations! worthy of regard!</l>
   <l>And from thy <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Soyle,</hi> deserve reward;</l>
   <l>But more for what, thou sufferd into <hi>Spaine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For CHRIST and Countrey, and thy late <hi>Sou'raigne:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Which if it be not weighd, in tyme I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare,</l>
   <l>That late repentance, shall buy pennance deare,</l>
   <l>Tymes haue their turnes, and ev'ry turne a Tyme,</l>
   <l>Men could not shift, without some changing <hi>Clyme;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For where neglect, claps merit on the face,</l>
   <l>The errour, not the object, reaps disgrace:</l>
   <l>Then pregnant <hi>Pilgrime,</hi> rest thou yet content,</l>
   <l>Hope still that Tyme, shall crowne thy braue intent,</l>
   <l>KINGS haue their mynds, and reason just demands,</l>
   <l>For Merit, can not fall, where judgement stands.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. A.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Virtus repulsae nescia sordidae</l>
         <l>Intaminatis fulget honoribus.</l>
      </q>
      <bibl>Horat.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>