<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his singular friend Mr. William Lithgow.</title>
           <author>Hannay, Patrick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108592_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05597</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15714</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108592</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his singular friend Mr. William Lithgow.</title>
                 <author>Hannay, Patrick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The totall discourse, of the rare adventures, and painefull peregrinations of long nineteene yeares travailes from Scotland, to the most famous kingdomes in Europe, Asia, and Affrica : Perfited by three deare bought voyages, in surveying of forty eight kingdomes ancient and modern; twenty one rei-publicks, ten absolute principalities, with two hundred islands. ... divided into three bookes: being newly corrected, and augmented in many severall places, with the addition of a table thereunto annexed of all the chiefe heads. Wherein is contayned an exact relation of the lawes, religions, policies and governments of all their princes, potentates and people. Together with the grievous tortures he suffered by the Inquisition of Malaga in Spaine ... And of his last and late returne from the Northern Isles, and other places adjacent. By William Lithgow</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 444, 447-514, 8 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To his singular friend Mr. William Lithgow.</head>
   <l>THe double travaile (<hi>Lithgow</hi>) thou hast tane,</l>
   <l>One of thy Feet, the other of thy Braine,</l>
   <l>Thee, with thy selfe; do make for to contend,</l>
   <l>Whether the Earth thou'st better pac'd or pend:</l>
   <l>Would <hi>Malagaes</hi> sweet liquor had thee crown'd,</l>
   <l>And not its trcachery; made thy ioynts unsound,</l>
   <l>For Christ, King, Country, what thou there indu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>'d,</l>
   <l>Not them alone, but therein all injur'd:</l>
   <l>Their tort'ring Rack, arresting of thy pace</l>
   <l>Hath barr'd our hope, of the worlds other face:</l>
   <l>Who is it sees this side so well exprest,</l>
   <l>That with desire, doth not long for the rest,</l>
   <l>Thy travail'd Countries so described be,</l>
   <l>As Readers thinke, they doe each Region see:</l>
   <l>Thy well compacted matter, ornat Stile,</l>
   <l>Doth them oft, in quicke sliding Time beguile,</l>
   <l>Like as a Maide, wandring in <hi>Floraes</hi> Bowers,</l>
   <l>Confin'd to small time, of few flitting howers,</l>
   <l>Rapt with delight, of her eye-pleasing treasure,</l>
   <l>Now culling this, now that Flower, takes such pleasure,</l>
   <l>That the strict time, whereto she was confin'd</l>
   <l>Is all expir'd: whiles she thought halfe behind,</l>
   <l>Or more remain'd. So each attracting Line</l>
   <l>Makes them forget the time, they do not tine:</l>
   <l>But since sweet future travaile is cut short,</l>
   <l>Yet loose no time, now with the <hi>Muses</hi> sport;</l>
   <l>That reading of Thee, after times may tell,</l>
   <l>In Travaile, Prose and Verse, thou didst excell.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Patrick Hannay.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>