<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle and curteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Lewkenor, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108534_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108534</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle and curteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lewkenor, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse not altogether vnprofitable, nor vnpleasant for such as are desirous to know the situation and customes of forraine cities without trauelling to see them : Containing a discourse of all those citties wherein doe flourish at this day priuiledged vniuersities. Written by Samuel Leuukenor Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Lewkenor, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Hooper, Humphrey.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 76 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the gentle and curteous <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had no sooner begun (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to take this taske in hand, but entring into a true and iudiciall consideration how weake &amp; slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my forces were to bring to any good perfection a work of so great moment and importance, I began immediately to faint &amp; fall vnder my burthen, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by perseuering therein, I should but set forth vnto the view of this captious age mine owne vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, and euer liue obnoxious to the malicious tongs of such barking mastifes, as thinke the reproofe of other mens labors to be the greatest parcell of their owne praises, though then themselues none are more ignorant. Notwithstanding, being at last earnestly entreated to finish what I had begun, and the same be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing finished, vehemently vrged to the publication thereof, by some friends of mine whome I am bound by dutie to obey, since of two euils wise men are wont to chuse the least, I thought it better to lay open to the world my follies, and discouer mine owne vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ignorance, then by curious and nice reiecting the aduised counsel, &amp; enforcing perswasions of my dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest &amp; nearest friends, to be touched or thought guilty
<pb facs="4"/>
of that fowle and of all good men detested vice ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
   <p>But least any one looking in this booke for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of our English Academies, and finding them placed in the latter end, shold by a misconstruction of my well meaning intention lay vnto my charge either negligence, or ignorance, or both, for not giuing vnto these two noble nurseries of the artes (whose resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent fame hath dilated it selfe to the vttermost con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of the earth) their due &amp; deserued places, I will for his satisfaction &amp; mine own excuse speake onely a word or two. I am not ignorant, that these vniuersities of our natiue country deserue for their degree &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse to be placed in the foremost ranke, and that in all <hi>Europe</hi> are not to be found more ancient, more magnificent, more plentifull, better accommodated, nor more in all kinds of learning flourishing vniuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But so great of late haue beene the controuersies, and so sharpe and bitter the contentions betweene the learned Doctors &amp; professors in either of these sacred, and most worthily renowned habitations of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: while they of eyther side with tooth and naile did labour to maintaine the prioritie of that place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had remained students, that I as one weakely armed, and fearing the encounter, not daring to des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the listes, was once determined plainely to giue ouer the fielde: for with what face shoulde I by any meanes presume (my learning being little, and my skill in the arte of antiquaries lesse) to interpose my poore opinion, among the stifly maintained allegations of so many graue &amp; learned men? I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="5"/>
was resolued rather to bee accused and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ignorance for leauing of them out, then by going about to giue superioritie vnto the one, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the displeasure of the other. But being againe aduised how great a maime &amp; blemish I should seeme to giue vnto this present treatise, if going about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate in one bodie the moderne vniuersities of our Christian world, I should cut off two of the most noble and principall limmes or members of the same: I haue at last (altering my first resolution) annexed them to the end thereof, in such manner, as neither of these vniuersities shall finde cause of discontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the curious reader depart (as I hope) well satisfied.</p>
   <p>Concerning the antiquities, priuiledges, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of colledges in the one and the other, I write nothing of mine owne inuention, what I haue found in <hi>M. Camdens</hi> Chorographicall description of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> concerning <hi>Oxforde,</hi> and other Chronicles, that haue I gathered and set downe, to <hi>Cambridge</hi> some thinges haue I added not of my self, but extracted out of certaine papers, printed in Paules Churchyearde, in the yeare of our Lorde, one thousand fiue hundred, seauenty two, and written by a learned Maister of that Vniuersity.</p>
   <p>Accept therefore (curteous Reader) in good part what here thou findest offered to thy view, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me not with thy frowne in my first attempt: the faultes that are herein escaped, if they proceede from the authors vnskilfulnes, forgiue them, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that he is one that hath more vsually beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb facs="5"/>
with the warlike sounde of martiall drums, then with the schooles and Lectures of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy: if committed by the Printer, amend them gentlie with thy penne, so shall I euer rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine to vse Samuell Lewhenor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>