<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Preface of D. Marten Luther.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108922_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06491</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16964</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108922</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Preface of D. Marten Luther.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chiefe and pryncypall articles of the Christen faythe : to holde againste the Pope, and al papistes, and the gates of hell, with other thre very profitable and necessary bokes the names or tyttels, whereof are conteyneth in the leafe next followynge. Made by Doctor Marten Luther. To the reader. In thys boke shal you fynde Christian reader the ryght probation of the righte olde catholyke Churche, and of the newe false Churche, whereby eyther of them is to be knowen. Reade and iudge</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lynne (Lin), Walter (Gualter, Wouter van)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>248 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Preface of D. Marten Luther.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Articles haue I compyled, &amp; for oure parte dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uered vp. Which also are receyued of oures and vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formely confessed, and concluded.</p>
   <p>That they shoulde (yf the Pope with hys adherentes, woulde ones be so hardy, withoute lyeng and dissimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, with earneste and trueth, to ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe an vnfayned free counsayll, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to hys duetye) be openly delyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vp, and the confession of our faith declared. But for as much as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myshe courte so terribly feareth a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Counsayll, and so shamefully abhorreth the light, that also thei, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the be of hys own syde, are put to dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>payre, as though he woulde neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde a free Counsayll, moche lesse ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe it hymself. Whereon, as reason re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth, <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/> they take occasion to be offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, &amp; moued to no smal encombraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce thereouer. As they that there by perceyue rightwell, that the Pope woulde rather see, the hole Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite caste awaye, and all soules dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, than he woulde suffre hym selfe, or hys, to be refourmed, and a measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to be sette vnto hys Tyranny.</p>
   <p>So haue I notwithstandynge wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led these Articles by open printe, to be brought to lyght to thintent, that yf I shoulde chaunce to dye, before anye Counsayl were kept (as doubteles I loke for none other) seynge these wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches so shamefully abhorring the light and eschewinge the daye, take suche intollerable paynes to delaye and hyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der a free counsayll. Vvhereby they that shall lyue and remayne after me may haue my witnes and confession to shewe, aboue and besydes that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessyon, whiche I dyd setfurth before, wherein also I haue persisted hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and wyl persiste by Goddes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/> For what should I say, vnto who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me shoulde I complayne. I am yet a lyue, I writte, preache, and reade day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, yet are there suche veninouse peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not onely amonge the aduersari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but also false bretheren, which fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to be of oure parte, that take vpon them, to interpretate my writtynges and teachynges directely against me. Euen before my face, that I may hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Although they knowe fulwel, that I teache otherwyse, and woulde colou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re their poison with my laboures, and seduce the people vnder my name, what wyll be done then after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath.</p>
   <p>Yea I shoulde by reason make aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to all thynges, whylest I am yet on lyue. Yea agayne, howe can I alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne stoppe all the mouthes of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll? Specially of suche (as they are all poysoned) as wyl not heare, nor marke what we do writte. But onely practyse with all diligence, howe they myght moost shame fully peruerie, &amp; infecte oure wordes, in all letters. Vnto suche to make aunswer. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte <pb facs="5"/> vnto the deuyl, or at the last vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to goddes indignation accordynge to theyr deseruynge. I remembre often the good gerson, which doubteth, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther men oughte to writte any good thyng openly, yf men do it not, then are there many soules lost, that might be preserued. But yf menne do it, so is the deuyll ready at hande with innu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merable euyll infected mouthes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che all thynges do infecte and peruer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se, so that the frute is kepte back, how be it, what they get by it, is openly sene. For sence the tyme, that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue so shamefully lyed agaynst vs, and woulde vpholde the people with lyes hath God neuertheles g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with hys busynes, and hath made their nōber styll to decreasse, and ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to increace, and hath put thē with theyr lyes to confusyon, and yet doth more and more.</p>
   <p>I must recyte a Story. There was sent hither to Vvittenberch, a certayn doctour out of Fraunce, which sayde opēly before vs: That hys kyng was surely certifyed, that by vs, there was <pb facs="5"/> no Churche, no Superiorite, no matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony, but wēt one amonge another ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke beastes, and that euery mā did what he woulde. Nowe iudge, howe shall they in the later daye before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt seate of Christ loke vpon vs, that haue by their writtinges infourmed the said kyng, &amp; also other Countryes suche rude and grosse lyes to be very true? Christ the Lorde &amp; iudg of vs all knoweth right well, that they lye, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue lyed, his iudgemēt must they heare agayne, that am I sure of, God cōuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te them that are to be conuerted, to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pētaunce. To the other it shall be said, Vvo and Alaes for euer more.</p>
   <p>And that I retourne agayne to my purpose, To see a right Counsayll I woulde truely be very glad, where by many matters might be redressed, and the people eased, Not that we haue nede of it. For oure Churches are nowe trough Goddes grace, with the syncere worde, and right vse of the Sacramentes, with knoweledge of all manner of States, and righte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, so illumined &amp; sette in order, that <pb facs="6"/> we for oure parte, care for no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayll, neyther do we loke or hope for any better reformation in these Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles by the Counsayll.</p>
   <p>But there see we in the Bysshop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rykes euery where, many Parysshes voyd and desolate, which myght cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se a mannes herte to breake. And yet neyther Bisshops nor Chanōs care ho we the pore people do lyue or dye, for the whiche Christe neuerthelesse suffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red death, and should not heare the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me speake with them as the right she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peherde with hys shepe. In so muche, that I am afrayde, and dredefull, least he let one day an Angelical Counsail passe ouer Doucheland, which might vtterlye destroye vs all, euen as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorre, seyng, we are so obstinate, morkyng, and gestyng with the Counsayll.</p>
   <p>Besydes these necessary Churche matters, are there also in the laye sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te innumerable great faultes, whiche had nede of redresse. There is discorde betwene Prynces, and States, Vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and couetousnes are broken in, euē <pb facs="6"/> as a mightye floude, and counted euen laufull and decent, wilfulnes, vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, presumption excesse in apparel, in eatynge, playeng, braggynge, with all manner of vngodlynes and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, disobedience of the subiectes, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and workemen, the inhaunsynge of al occupations and also of husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demen (and who can recyte it al) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue so preuayled, that with tenne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saylles and twenty Conuocations it wyl not be brought agayn to the right trade.</p>
   <p>Yf men woulde handle suche chiefe poyntes of the spirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall estates, whiche are against God, in the Counsayl, then shoulde they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ynough to do, euen all handes full, So that in the meane seasō, thei should forgette all children playes, and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshnes of long gownes, greate crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, broade gyrdels. Bysshoppes and Cardinalles hattes or staues, and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che other iugglynges. When fyrst we hadde executed the Commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ordinaunce of God, bothe in the spiritual and temporal estates, thē <pb facs="7"/> shoulde we fynde tyme ynough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme meates, garmentes, cronnes, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pes But when thei deuoure su<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che camelles, and in stede hereof wil see a moote, let the beame alone, and iudge the chippe, than myght we also well forbeare the counsayll.</p>
   <p>Therfore haue I set but fewe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. For as muche as we besydes that, haue of God so many commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes to do in the churche, in the superiorite, within the housse, that we can neuer be able to perfourme them. Vvho then? or what doth it auayll? to make besydes them many decrees and Statutes in the counsayl. Specially seyng these chiefe poyntes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God, are not regarded nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued. Euen as though he should set by oure iuglynge tromperies, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se we treade hys earnest commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vnder oure fete. But oure syn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes suppresse vs, and suffre not God, to be mercyfull vnto vs, neyther do we also repente, but will moreouer maynteyne and vpholde all abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/> O Lorde Iesu Christe, kepe thou Counsayll thy selfe, and delyuer thy people by thy gloryous commynge, It is done with the Pope and hys ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herētes. They wyll none of the: Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore helpe thou vs poore and misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whiche sygh vnto the, and seke the with earnest, accordyng to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, whiche thou haste geuen vs, through the holye Ghoste, which lyueth and reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, with the and thy father, praysed for euer and euer. AMEN.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>