<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE
GEORGE,
Marquesse of Buckingham, Lord
high Admirall, Viscount Villiers, Baron of
Whaddon, Maister of his MAIESTIES Horse, Knight
of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of
his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, one of his most honourable
Priuy-Councell, a Patron of good Letters, and a
Patterne of true Nobility. Grace and fa∣uour
be from Heauen by
CHRIST.</title>
           <author>Loe, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108813_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06196</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16691</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108813</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE
GEORGE,
Marquesse of Buckingham, Lord
high Admirall, Viscount Villiers, Baron of
Whaddon, Maister of his MAIESTIES Horse, Knight
of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of
his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, one of his most honourable
Priuy-Councell, a Patron of good Letters, and a
Patterne of true Nobility. Grace and fa∣uour
be from Heauen by
CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vox clamantis. Mark 1. 3 : A stil voice, to the three thrice-honourable estates of Parliament: and in them, to all the soules of this our nation, of what state or condition soeuer they be. By William Loe, Doctor of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Teage (Teague, Tege), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO
THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE
GEORGE,
Marquesse of Buckingham, Lord
high Admirall, Viscount Villiers, Baron of
Whaddon, Maister of his MAIESTIES Horse, Knight
of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of
his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, one of his most honourable
Priuy-Councell, a Patron of good Letters, and a
Patterne of true Nobility. Grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
be from Heauen by
CHRIST.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Noble, and most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
honoured LORD.
The true, and hearty Zeale,
which I owe vnto my God,
King, Church, and Country,
hath moued, and made me to
prostrate before the Three
thrice honourable Estates of
<hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
And in them to all the Cleriques, Courtiers, and
Commons within our Nation, euen from Sea to Sea, and
<pb facs="3"/>
from the Riuer to the Lands end, (being ledde hereunto
by the words of the Prophet prefixed) the still passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of this small Voyce, which hath laine suppressed
some yeares, by meanes of a certaine Great-one, (who
not long sithence was great, but now is not, so mutable
and nutable is the state of things on earth) taking of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
at some passages herein. Whose ouer-weening great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
and wilfulnesse, had then at the least shut me vp, if
not sent me (as there was great cause to suspect and feare)
not the way of all flesh in respect of the manner, but of
mortalitie) if some reuerend Fathers of the Church, the
blessed Beaue-Peeres of Diuinitie, had not stayed that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
fury against mee: But not long after, the hand of
Almightie God surprized that greatnes, clipped it, restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
it, that it might doe no more harme, &amp; so it remaines to
this day. Happy had it beene for that man, that hee had
then hearkened to that Voyce from God, deliuered by the
weake ministry of him, who neuer saw his face to this day,
that if it had pleased the Almightie, his soule might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
haue beene awakened out of that fearefull slumber,
wherein hee then lay, bewitched with the Circean Cups
of Ambition, Wantonnesse, and sensuall securitie. Then
had not his fingers, nor the hands of others, his Agents in
euill, dropped with the cruell bloud-guiltinesse, neyther
had their consciences beene tortured, and tormented with
the Hellish horrour of heart-bleeding wickednesse. What
I then spake in the accent, and action of a liuing man, to the
greatest Auditorie of this Land, I now present to publique
view, in the lesse effectual elements of a dead Letter: To no
other purpose (God is my record) but intending and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring
hereby the aduancement of Gods glory, some
good of his Church, and in all Estates a remembrance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
these present times, a manifestation of our happinesse
<pb facs="3"/>
vnder so Christian a King, whose heart detesteth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustice,
the maintenance of the truth then deliuered, and
that these palpable and pisculent imputations and aspersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of Faction, and Sedition, might in some sort be spun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
out, which it pleased that Great-one mentioned to cast
vpon me at that time in an honourable Assembly, and since
that time some others (strangely alienated both from our
Church and State) who haue endeuoured to be-sprinkle
me with the like, for that I vndertooke, and did reconcile,
and compose, by directions from his Maiesties owne mouth,
some differences in Ecclesiasticall discipline, happened into
a famous Fellowship, (to which I am much obliged) resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
in part beyond the Seas, whither I was not long si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence
sent by authority, allowance, and Recommendation
of his sacred Maiesty, and the most Reuerend Archbishop
of Canterbury. Which imployment and seruice, albeit it hath
in some part impayred, yea almost impouerished mee in my
poore personall eflate, and lost me some friends, whom I
thought had beene better minded, and may (in Gods good
time) bethinke themselues better: Yet, were either the one
abroad, or this seruice at home to be done againe; for the
vnfained loue I beare vnto the free passage of Gods glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Gospel, and to the present setled subsistants of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
of our Church, I would not onely (as a Merchant
Aduenturer) hazard my weake body, poore estate, and
liuelihood; but also would willingly (as a free Minister of
the Gospell) expose my selfe to all the Snibbes, Quippes,
Taunts, Reproaches, Disgraces, and Punishments, that any
wicked, and vngodly Great-one (little, or not at all affected
to God) should preuaile against mee in, that (at the least)
I might herein manifest to the World, my Willingnesse and
Indeauour to maintaine and make good (<hi>quantum in me</hi>)
the sacred freedome of the one, and the Christian Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
<pb facs="4"/>
of the other; both which, our Nation most comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
enioyeth vnder God, by the blessing of so Christian a
King as is our most gracious Soueraigne, vnder Christ
Iesus, the breath of all our nosthrils, my most dread Liege-Lord
and Master. Desiring all true honest English
hearts, which are not poysoned with preiudicate opinion of,
exotique niceties, and imitation of strangers, to iudge, if
there be any passage herein, that deserueth either manicles,
or menaces, or ought; but what becommeth a sober and a
true English-hearted Diuine. But be this little <hi>Hin</hi> of
mine either accepted or reiected (by such as care not how
the World goes, so they may atchieue their owne ends) I
passe not, so it may please your most noble Worth, that it
may shelter it selfe vnder your honourable protecting fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.
When I went ouer to that seruice mentioned beyond
the Seas, I made bold to present his Highnesse with a Tract
entit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>led, <hi>The Mystery of Mankind;</hi> and vpon my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,
I vowed <hi>This,</hi> to your Honour. It is the poore Mite
of him, that will euer remaine a Votary to God for you;
That the magnificence of Gods fauors, and the munificence
of his mercies may euer be multiplied vpon you, and vpon
all your godly endeuors; That so both you, and all you take
in hand, in discharge of your eminent places, may be sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
to the good of Gods Church, his Mai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stie, and the State,
to your owne soules safetie, and that you may be great in
the Kingdome of your heauenly Master, through the sauing
mercies and fauour of Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
in the seruice of
IESVS CHRIST,
<hi>William Loe.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="4"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>