<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, My honoured Kinseman, IAMES CHAMBERS, Doctor in Physicke, Physitian for his Maiesties Person in Or∣dinary, and for the Prince his Highnesse.</title>
           <author>Lesly, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108512_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05357</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15510</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108512</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, My honoured Kinseman, IAMES CHAMBERS, Doctor in Physicke, Physitian for his Maiesties Person in Or∣dinary, and for the Prince his Highnesse.</title>
                 <author>Lesly, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epithrene: or Voice of vveeping : bewailing the want of vveeping. A meditation</title>
                 <author>Lesly, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 322, 2 pages, folded table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, My honoured Kinseman, IAMES CHAMBERS, Doctor in Physicke, Physitian for his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Person in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and for the <hi>Prince</hi> his Highnesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the <hi>Lord in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> will adiudge those to bee wicked and slothfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.26</note> that improue not his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents: So in <hi>Mercie</hi> bee graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously
<pb facs="3"/>accepteth our Free-will offerings, aswell of Goates Haire and Rammes Skinnes,
<note place="margin">Exo. 25.34</note> as of Gold and Siluer, offered for building his <hi>Spiritual Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle;</hi> Who is well pleased, not so much with the Extention, as Intention of the Offering: And among the Gentiles, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<note place="margin">Suid in Voe <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> It was thought suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt, if poore men that were not able to sacrifice a <hi>liuing Bull,</hi> did but offer a <hi>Bull of Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>le.</hi> Vpon consideration of these, I presume that your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy &amp; Christian disposition, wil not disdaine to accept and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the inarticulate Voice of
<pb facs="3"/>this <hi>Abortive Infant,</hi> whose weake and warbling Notes cannot be more disliked by most censorious <hi>Criticisme</hi> or scorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Ignorance,</hi> than by his owne Author. Which if distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of my thoughts in other businesse, and passages of my Function, had suffered me ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to peruse, they might happily haue given a more distinct and lowder <hi>Echo.</hi> But the neuer-enough deplored Iniquities of the Times and place where I liue, enforced them to <hi>Aborti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and made me cry out with the Prophet, <hi>My bowels,
<note place="margin">Ier. 4.19.</note> my bowels, I am payned at my very heart, my heart ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="4"/>a noyse within mee, I cannot hold my peace:
<note place="margin">Ier. 20.9.</note> For the Word of the Lord was in my heart, as a burning fire shut vp in my bones,
<note place="margin">Psal. 69.10.</note> and I was weary with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, and I could not stay.</hi> But because when I wept and chastened my soule with Fasting, that was turned to my reproach;
<note place="margin">Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess. <hi>10.12.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Rideat me ista di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem, qui ista non sentit, &amp; ego dol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bo ridentem me;</hi> Let him that feeleth not these things, scorne me that say these things, and I will weepe for him that scorneth mee.</p>
   <p>How ever the tongue of most men be like <hi>Hanuns</hi> Rasors,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.4</note>
      <pb facs="4"/>still cutting off, and disfiguring the most holy intents. My hope is,
<note place="margin">Theed li. <hi>4.26.</hi>
      </note> that as <hi>Aphraates</hi> hauing spent the greatest part of his life in solitary Places, could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse his vnaccustomed walking once in the streets of <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia</hi> (for which he was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) by the example of a <hi>Maid</hi> that all her dayes had kept her selfe within her Fathers house, vntill the violence of a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Fire constrained her to bewray some <hi>Immodestie,</hi> to goe abroad, and give notice of the imminent danger: So now, my first stepping foorth vpon the Stage of the World from my <hi>retired Privacie,</hi> where <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<note place="margin">Plutarch. Hier de Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tando susp. Contub.</note>
      <pb facs="5"/>my day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Taske</hi> is, <hi>Praeterita mea plangere vitia, &amp; vitare prae. sentia)</hi> to warn wanton World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, delighting onely in the <hi>Sardonian laughter,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon their exorbitant enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities by holy weeping, may bee taken in good part; seeing, as sayeth the <hi>Schooleman,
<note place="margin">Aquin <hi>2.2 107. 1.2.</hi>
         </note> Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas est mensura actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> And my endeauour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from a will to doe good. Wherein if I seeme to haue stirred a course opposite to the liking of the <hi>Multitude,</hi> or that my <hi>Matter be Cynicall, and Methode Triuiall,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most approuing the <hi>Practicall
<pb facs="5"/>Phylosophy</hi> (which I dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime) of <hi>Heracli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> in his sullen humor; or that others,
<note place="margin">Erasm. in Adag.</note>
      <hi>In antro Trophonii vatici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes,</hi> should become irrisible: I haue resolued, and doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme it a part of my Felicitie vpon Earth, to be accounted a <hi>Stoicke</hi> of all the world, so I be a <hi>Peripateticke</hi> to Christ: For sensibly spake he, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly (mee thinkes) to our Times, who Weeping said, that though we commit no other sin,
<note place="margin">Hier in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. contr. Ruffin.</note>
      <hi>Certe verum tacuisse pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est,</hi> To conceale the Truth is Sinne.</p>
   <p>A sufficient <hi>Apologie</hi> for my bold adventure of publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="6"/>this <hi>Essay</hi> of my poore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, may be the <hi>Raritie</hi> or rather <hi>Nullitie</hi> of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe Tractats in this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">Bellarm de Gemit. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Bessas Heraclit. Christ.</note> Two onely <hi>Popish Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses,</hi> the one of <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> the other of <hi>Bessaeus,</hi> I meete with; In which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (without disparagement to their Learning) their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are fraught full of fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid, frothy, superfluous, and superstitious Speculations; I haue published this <hi>Embryo,</hi> though <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, hee may cost mee the publication of my <hi>Ignorance.</hi> As then no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of this wretched World, but zeale to promote <hi>Gods
<pb facs="6"/>glory, and Christs Gospell,</hi> moved mee to expose these, to the view of this censorious World: So in humble acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of your many kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses towards mee, They doe make mention of your <hi>Name</hi> in the <hi>Frontispice.</hi> Where be pleased (I beseech you) to accept my briefe and ingenuous <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession,</hi> that the <hi>Quotations, Quid cuius esset simpliciter confitentes,</hi> had these causes: <hi>1.</hi> To remove Imputations of <hi>Singularitie,</hi> and Phantasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call delight in going alone: <hi>2.</hi> To aduantage (I hope) the Truth; as Testimonies of very <hi>Heathens</hi> are inserted by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles:
<pb facs="7"/>3.
<note place="margin">Hieron. in Epitaph. Nep.</note> Hierome</hi> estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it a maine argument of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity in his Nepotian</hi> and worthy of imitation: <hi>4.</hi> To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide that <hi>forging Tricke of Iesuiticall Legerdemaine: 5.</hi> I know not better how to confirme what I alledge, then by acknowledging whence I had it. Therefore knowing mine owne defects (Let others <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cissus like</hi> content themselues with their own <hi>Conceptions</hi>) I doe so reverence and admire the rich <hi>Compositions</hi> of Ancient times, as that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but accord to them, that (in worthy examples) hold <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation better then Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>Vouchsafe then (deare Sir) Acceptance of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to this weake Watch▪ word, which feareth the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Weakenesse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Galen. de Nat facul. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) though lesse then of <hi>Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude:</hi> And therefore desireth not so much to expose my <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations</hi> to the World, as my <hi>Observance</hi> to you, for the fatherly care you ever had in cherishing my Labours, and encouraging my Studies. For which, I pray <hi>GOD,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long your Time with much comfort here, and crowne it with <hi>Eternity.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="8"/>Addimus his precibus Lachryma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> quo{que}, verba precāri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Perlegis, &amp; lachryma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> finge videre meas.</q>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most bounden Kinsman and devoted in the Lord, <hi>IOHN LESLY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>