<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE. Dedicated to the Right Honorable Sir Robert Cecil, Knight, one of her Majesties most Honourable Privie COVNCELL.</title>
           <author>Lambard, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108230_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04995</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15144</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108230</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE. Dedicated to the Right Honorable Sir Robert Cecil, Knight, one of her Majesties most Honourable Privie COVNCELL.</title>
                 <author>Lambard, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archeion, or, A discourse vpon the high courts of iustice in England : Composed by William Lambard, of Lincolnes Inne, Gent</title>
                 <author>Lambarde, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Frere (Fryer), Daniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 276 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE. Dedicated to the Right Honorable Sir <hi>Robert Cecil,</hi> Knight, one of her Majesties <hi>most Honourable Privie</hi> COVNCELL.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit, right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir; that my bounden Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards you, aswell for the singular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of my most Honorable Lord your Father, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="3"/> extended upon me, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so for that <hi>cheerefull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> which it hath pleased your Selfe to vouchsafe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, might have moved me with the first, to gratulate unto You, that Honourable place wherunto you are right worthily advanced: Yet that J may not onely bewray my ioy thereof in vanishing words, but testifie it also with some more stāding <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall</hi> that might remain: J have purposely spared to see your Honour, untill that
<pb facs="3"/> I might come accompanied with this Copie of mine <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheion,</hi> or <hi>Commentaries of the Courts of England;</hi> Whereof, some J penned sundrie yeeres sithence, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not long agoe, and the rest so lately, that your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may, if it please you, take the first view and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them; wherein if you shall finde either pleasure or profit, then shall I also both enioy the desire of my heart, and the expected fruit of my Travaile, And thus heartily
<pb facs="4"/> praying <hi>GOD</hi> to increase your Honor with your yeers, that as you bee already by Nature the Sonne; so you may at the length by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion become the very <hi>Heire</hi> of that renowned <hi>Nestor,</hi> and onely <hi>Atlas</hi> of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Countrie and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. I humbly pray you to pardon the escapes both of me and this Writer. From <hi>Lincolnes Inne</hi> this <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>October, 1591.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors to command,</hi>
         <lb/> Wil. Lambard.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>