<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most merciful and prudent Princesse, Elyzabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland Queene, Defender of the faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S108934_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06481</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16950</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S108934</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most merciful and prudent Princesse, Elyzabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland Queene, Defender of the faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A persuasion from papistrie : vvrytten chiefely to the obstinate, determined, and dysobedient English papists, who are herein named &amp; proued English enimies and extreme enimies to Englande. Which persuasion, all the Queenes Maiesties subiectes, fauoring the Pope or his religion, will reade or heare aduisedlye</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 192, 191-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most merciful and prudent Princesse, <hi>Elyzabeth,</hi> by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland Queene, Defender of the faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S heretofore (my moste gratious Soueraigne) I troubled your Highnesse (not without some trauell to my selfe) in a thing that was necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, reasonable, and commodious to many, and hurte to none: Euen so I haue now (not troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, but louingly) framed an earnest persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to suche of your subiects, as feare not God as they ought, regarde not hys worde as they shoulde, nor obey your Highnesse as they are bounde, naming them Englishe enimies (as I maye verye well) for Englishe friendes I am sure they are not: whych per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion is necessarie, reasonable, and very profitable for thē, &amp; not hurtfull to any. And as that which beefore I made to your Maiestie, was by your Grace onely to be aucthorized, for the greate releefe and succour of youre subiectes: So this that I haue nowe written to your subiectes, is to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and practised by them, to the great comfort and ioy (I hope) of your Highnesse. And though I haue penned it for them to performe: yet I haue dedicated it to your Grace to peruse. Beseeching youre Maiestie therein to pardon my boldenesse (or rather presumption) for thoughe it bee not so learnedly, so cunningly, and so finely framed, as is requisite for your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lēcie: yet it is so plainly, so truly, and so zealously done, as is meete for your subiects. Not doubting, but stedfastlye trusting, though al thereby be not allured from their errour, that many will be wonne to the truth: though it make not thē see, that wincke for the nonce, it wil cause thē to see, that wil open their eyes. And though it procure not the obstinate and determined Papistes, from being Englishe Enimies: yet it will enforce thousandes (I hope) of the simple seduced sorte, to become Englishe friendes (or rather friendes to <hi>England.</hi>) And thoughe there might seeme in mee, too muche boldenesse, to craue of your Maiestie, to reade this presently: yet I beseech your Highnesse to view and peruse it at your leysure conueniently. For as the reading thereof, I truste wil much profite them, to whom I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it: so your Graces reading of it, woulde not a little reioyce mee, to whome I dedicate it. And whereas I firmely beleeue, that God thereby wil be better honoured, the Gospel more embraced, Papistrie more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, your Maiestie better obeyed, your Highnesse of manye more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, your power more augmented, treason lesse practised, forraine foes more discouraged, your louing subiects more comforted, Englishe eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies more diminished, Englishe friendes more encreased, and this youre
<pb facs="3"/>
Realme of <hi>England</hi> the better strengthned: yet the onely thing that I craue therefore of your Grace, is, well to accept it, and in good parte to take it, Beseeching your Maiestie not to respect the meane estate of the person, but the meaning of the partie, not the cunning of the contriuer, but the intent of the writer, neither howe it is couched, but to what ende it is framed. And if there be any thing therein that shall mislike your Maiestie, I most humbly beseech you therefore to pardon me, protesting to God and your Grace, that I wrote the same, not purposely, but negligently: and not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, but ignorantly: Hoping besides, that the godly and wise will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue all things therein to the beste, and not wreast them to the worst. And as for other, that haue an ouerweening in their owne wittes, and that are rather curious carpers, than profitable doers, (whereof there are not a few) I doe not muche weigh, for it is impossible to write so circumspectly, to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie or please euery precise head. And therefore I haue chosen rather to write truth and goodnesse for fooles to mislike, than toyes and tryfles for the wise to deride: not ignoraunte, that there are moe finde-faultes than mende-faultes, and moe that are ready to detract other mens doings, than able to make the like of their owne: whereof some thinke they deserue more to be commended (so much they fancie their follie) for discommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that, in a minute of an houre, whyche the Writer with great study and paine for their greate profite, and the continuall commoditie of many thousandes hath beene a framing and finishing twoo or three yeares. And as a greate sorte for this will fauour me, and not hate mee: Euen so (I am sure) that some therefore will hate me moste spitefully, that rather oughte to loue me earnestly. Whose malice the better to withstande, I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen your Maiestie (as one that is beste able vnder God) to defende me. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whose protection, this may the more safely passe abroade, and thereby be the better accepted, the more desired, the gladlyer receyued, the more willingly perused, the more aduisedly scanned, the lesse detracted, and the better credited. And thus omitting any further to trouble your Highnesse, I, (as one of your most true and faithful subiects) vnfainedly and from the bottome of my heart, do beseeche God, to preserue you from perils, to shielde you from sorrow, to confound al your foes, to defend you from Traytours, to reueale their conspyracies, to frustrate theyr attemptes, and to protecte you in peace.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces moste dutifull and obedient subiecte <hi>THOMAS LVPTON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>