<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Philip Melancthon to the reder sendeth gretynge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1536</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109256_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22612</idno>
           <idno type="STC">908</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109256</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Philip Melancthon to the reder sendeth gretynge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The confessyon of the fayth of the Germaynes : exhibited to the most victorious Emperour Charles the. v. in the Councell or assemble holden at Augusta the yere of our Lorde. 153 [sic] . To which is added the apologie of Melancthon who defendeth with reasons inuincible the aforesayde confessyon translated by Rycharde Tauerner at the commaundeme [n] t of his master the ryght honorable Mayster Thomas Cromwel chefe Secretarie to the kynges grace</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Redman, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1536</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>35, 179 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="39"/>
   <pb facs="39"/>
   <head>¶ Philip Melancthon to the reder sendeth gretynge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the confessyon of our prynces was in open audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence solempnely redde, certaine diuines &amp; friars prepared a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>futation of our wryting, whiche whan the Emperours maiestie had caused to be solempnely red in the assemble of the prynces, he requyred thē to assent vnto it. But our prynces hearynge that many articles were there disproued whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to renounce without grudge of consciēce they coulde nat, demaūded that a copy of the cōfutacion myght be to them exhibited, to the entent that they myght bothe see what theyr aduersaries condempned and also refute their reasons. And in suche cause whiche appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to chrysten faythe and instruction of the conscience, they thought that the aduersaries wolde nat haue made it straunge to exhibite theyr wrytyng. But our rulers coulde in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse obtayne it, onles they wolde haue boūde them selues to moste perelouse and vnegal cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions whiche they coulde nat do excepte they wolde caste them selues into a manifest daunger. After this, there was publyshed a pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cification in whiche appered that our hedes refused no burdayne were it neuer so payneful so that it myght be susteyned without offence of conscience. But the aduersaries obstinatly required vs to allowe certaine manifest abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and errours, which thyng whan we myght nat do, agayne the emperours maiestie requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="40"/>
our prynces to assent to the confutacyon whiche to do our prynces vtterly refused. For howe shulde they assent in a matter touchinge the faythe to the thynge that they neuer red? And they herde that certayne articles were there cōdempned in which thyng they coulde nat allowe the iudgement of the aduersaries without offence. There were also certayne other whiche required me to make an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie or defense of the cōfessyon in which shulde be expouned vnto themperour the causes why we receyued nat the confutacyon and the thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges soluted whiche the aduersaries obiected. For there were certayne of vs whiche when theyr confutacion was red noted the sūme of theyr places and argumentes. This Apologie they offered at laste vnto the emperours ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie to the entent that he myght knowe that most graue &amp; hyghe causes letted vs to allowe theyr confutacyon. Howe be it the emperour receyued nat the boke that was offered hym. After this cam forthe a proclamacion, in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che our aduersaries do triūphe that they haue confuted by scripture our confessyon. Nowe therfore (o gentle reader) ye se our Apologie in whiche ye shall perceyue aswele the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of our aduersaries (for we haue faythfully reported it) as theyr condempnacyon of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne articles agaynst the manyfest scripture of the holy ghoste, so farre be they wyde from defetyng our opinions by scriptures. But all be it that in the begynnynge I made onely an Apologie, yet nowe in my settyng it forthe in prynt, I haue added other thynges. And for that purpose I haue put to my name, bycause they shulde make no cauillacion that the boke
<pb facs="40"/>
was published without any authour certayne.</p>
   <p>This alway hathe bene my custome in suche controuersies that (so muche as I myght law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do) I wolde retayne the fourme of the vsed and accustomed doctryne, to the entent that we myght the soner agre together. Nor I do nat muche vnlyke at thys tyme, all be it I myght iustly wade further in dissuadynge the people from the opinions of our aduersaries. But our aduersaries do so hādle theyr matter that they shewe them selues neyther to seke trouthe nor concorde, but to sup vp our blode. Doubtles I haue nowe also wryttē as soberly and moderately as I can, but yet if any thyng shal seme to be spokē ouer sharply. I here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test that I contende with the diuines &amp; frears and nat with Cesar or the prynces whome (as my dutie is) I haue in hyghe estimacyon and regarde. But I sawe lately theyr confutacion whiche I haue marked to be wrytten so cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously and slaunderously that in certaine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they may dysceyue yea the ware and cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspecte readers. Natwithstandyng I haue nat medlyd with all theyr cauilacyōs (for that were an infinite worke) but I haue comprised the chefe maters, to the entēt that amonge all nacyons a testimonie of vs maye appere, that our iudgement is ryght &amp; godly of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Christe. Discorde pleaseth nat vs. Nor our owne priuate peryll dothe nothinge moue vs whiche howe greate it is by reason of the vehemēt hatredes of our aduersaries kyndled agaynste vs, we easely perceyue. But we may nat renounce the manifest veritie and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the edificacion of the churche. wherfore we thynke that all incommodities and peryls
<pb facs="41"/>
are to be susteyned and suffered for the glorye of Christe and profite of his churche, trusting that God wyll allowe and accepte thys our office &amp; endeuour, and moreouer we hope that our posteritie and successours shal haue of vs here after a better opinion and a more indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iudgement. For it can nat be denyed but that many places of Christes doctryne, which are moste necessarie to be notified and knowen in the churche, be of vs and ours opened and clerely set forthe, which here to fore with howe greate and perelouse opinions they were sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed and hydde through deceitful friars, lawyers, and sophisticall diuines, it lus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me nat here to recite. we haue the open testimonies of many good men which cease nat to rendre thank{is} to god for this most hyghe benefite that nowe many ryght necessary matters be better opened by vs, than they were by our aduersaries here tofore taught or preached. wherfore we shal commēde and cōmytte our cause vnto Christe who shall another day iudge these debates and cōtrouersies, whom we also humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seche to caste his tendre eyes, vpon the afflicte &amp; rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous churches and shortly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them into a godly and perpetuall concorde. Amen. ❧</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>