<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the ryght ho¦norable syr Thomas Neuel knyght, Theodore Basille wysshethe lōge lyfe, cōtynuall helth, and prosperous felicite.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109686_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07085</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1749</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109686</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the ryght ho¦norable syr Thomas Neuel knyght, Theodore Basille wysshethe lōge lyfe, cōtynuall helth, and prosperous felicite.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A potacio [n] or dri [n] kynge for this holi time of le [n] t : very co [m] fortable for all penitent synners, newly prepared by Theodore Basille</title>
                 <author>Becon, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mayler, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gough (Gowghe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the ryght ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norable syr Thomas Neuel knyght, Theodore Basille wysshethe lōge lyfe, cōtynuall helth, and prosperous felicite.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue not forgotten w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> howe gentle &amp; thancke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mynde (as I maye passe ouer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sigulerbene ficēce &amp; grādliberalyte, which at that time ye shewed to me) your ryght honorable mastership did receyue y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Christmasse Bācket which nowe of late I dedycated vnto your name, chefely whan you had diligēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compared it with the moost holye worde of God, the towch stone of all <note place="margin">Gods word is a towche stone to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and try al doctryne.</note> doctryne to trye the adulteryne, fay ned &amp; false frō the syncere, germayne &amp; true learnyng, &amp; perceyued that it dyd not onlye agree wyth the moost
<pb facs="3"/>
sacred Scryptures, but also wythe the teachynge of the auncient Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the holy churche, whome you haue as all mē ought, in great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion, with whose authoryties it is opu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ently fortressed. Uerely for the probacion of that my worke, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parynge it with the trueth of Christ &amp; the doctryne of the holy &amp; learned Doctors, I can none otherwyse but hyghly cōmende, prayse, auaunce, &amp; magnifye the industrye &amp; laboure of your righte honorable maystershyp, whiche so prudently proue all kynde of doctryne with the true &amp; infally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble towchstone of gods moost blessed word. For in thus doynge you shew youre selfe not to be ledde wyth ony blynde or perciall affecte, but wyth an vpright &amp; high indifferēcy, much alienated &amp; estraunged from the mā ners of diuers men at this tyme, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whome some as folyshe sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple receyue all kynde of doctryne w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute
<pb facs="3"/>
ony probacion or triall, some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne contrarye to the dexteryte of Christen iudgemente lyke frantyke parsons do temeraryously, rashly, &amp; w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out ony aduysement condemne a thynge before they haue iustlye exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myned it by the holy Scryptures. S. Paule saythe: Quenche not the <note place="margin">ii. Thes. v.</note> spyryte. Despyse not Prophesyes. Proue and examyne all thynges, &amp; that whiche is good, holde. S. Iohn̄ <note place="margin">i. Ioan. iiii</note> also saythe, derelye beloued, beleue not euery spiryte, but proue the spy rytes, whyther they are of God or not. Hereto pertayneth the sayenge of Christ, search ye the Scriptures. <note place="margin">Ioan. v.</note> Dauid also saythe: Blessed are they <note place="margin">psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> that searche the testymonyes of the <hi>LORDE.</hi> Here are al Christē men com maūded not furyously streight way es to condemne, what so euer lyketh them not at the fyrst aspecte &amp; blush but to search the scriptures, &amp; by thē to proue, whither they be true or not
<pb facs="4"/>
Luke declarethe in the Actes of the <note place="margin">Act. xvii.</note> Apostles, that whan Paule &amp; Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las preached to certayne mē at Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, they that hearde them, receyued the worde gladlye, yet not withston<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge they searched the scryptures dayely, &amp; tryed by them, whyther it was so or not, as they preached. So becommeth it all mē to do, not rashe ly to admyte &amp; receyue, nor yet fury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to cōdemne euery thynge at y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> fyrste syghte, but as Paule sayth, to <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>i. Thes. v.</note> proue all thynges, &amp; to chose &amp; holde that which is beste. Chynges muste be proued by the Scryptures &amp; not by the spiryte of pryde, contencion, despyte, &amp; contumacy. If mē would do this, there shoulde not be so great diuision in the chyrche of Chryst, as there is nowe a dayes. Christ &amp; Chri <note place="margin">Note.</note> stes trueth is only learned of the ho ly scryptures. They that teache ony other thynges than the scryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, tech not Christ, but humayne
<pb facs="4"/>
inuēciōs. Neither ought ony thyng as a necessarye trueth to be beleued vnder payne of damnacion, for to be admytted in the chyrche of Chryste, except it may be establysshed by the holy scrypture &amp; pure word of God. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> righteousnes of god is proued saith s. Paule by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> testymony &amp; wyt <note place="margin">Rom. iii:</note> nes of the lawe &amp; Prophetes Agayn he sayth: Yf we our selues or an Aū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel <note place="margin">Gal. i.</note> from heauen do preach vnto you ony other Gospell, thā that we haue preached vnto you, hold it accursed. As I sayde before, so saye I nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, yf any man shall preach vnto you ony other gospell than y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, which ye haue receyued, holde it accursed. Hereto agreeth Origene, it is nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs, sayth he, to caull the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly scriptures into wytnes. For our iudgementes &amp; exposiciōs wythout these wytnesses, haue no fayth. Also S. Ierome, that we affyrme, muste <note place="margin">In Ierem: Hom. i.</note> be establysshed &amp; approued with the
<pb facs="5"/>
testimonies of the holye scryptures, <note place="margin">Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>iesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.</note> in the which God speaketh dayly to thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> beleue. Itē Cyrillus, Christ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <note place="margin">In Ioan. cap. vi.</note> is to be followed as a mayster, &amp; to hī alone ought we to cleue. They that brynge ony other thynge besy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the doctryne &amp; teachynge of the Apostles, sayth Theophilact, Paule <note place="margin">In Roma. cap. vlt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> playnly sayth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> slaūders, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say heresies &amp; dissēciōs are brought in of them. Do not these thynges declare howe colde &amp; vayne all thynges are, that fyght wyth the worde of God, and haue not theyr foundacions of the moost holy scryptures.</p>
   <p>Certes as towechynge my lucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracions <note place="margin">The mind of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor cōcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge all his bokes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> hathe or shal set forth here after.</note> and workes, which I haue hytherto made, or shall by the helpe of God here after make, I submytte them all with moost submission and humilite of mynde to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> syncere iuge mētes of them that are ghostly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; taughte of GOD in Christes chyrche to be iudged, tryed and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb facs="5"/>
by the infallible verite of god des worde. Yf the holy Scriptures shal approue &amp; allow thē, I moost hū bly besech all men thāckefully to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte them, &amp; to gyue all the glorye &amp; prayse vnto God. If they shall seme to fyght &amp; dissent wyth the worde of God, holde them accursed, as Paule sayth, &amp; so do in lyke manner y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes <note place="margin">Gala. i.</note> of all other, that consente not w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Euangelyke veritie. But yf the worde of God testifieth and beareth witnes of them, receyue thē, &amp; gyue God thanckes, which so plenteously worketh in his seruauntes for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacion of his chyrche.</p>
   <p>Moreouer this your diligēt sear <note place="margin">A Potaciō for Lent.</note> chynge &amp; comparynge of my Banc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket with the holy scriptures and the auncient Doctors dydde so greatly please me, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> syns y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> tyme I thoughte not vnsyttynge to prepare a Potaci on for this holye tyme of Lente, &amp; to dedycate that also vnto your name.
<pb facs="6"/>
Which thinge I haue done, yea and that in all poyntes accordynge to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> verite of Gods worde &amp; the mynd of the moost auncient and best learned Doctors. Who so euer shall vouch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">What pro fyt ther is to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at this Potaciō</note> safe to be present at this Potacion, &amp; with a gredy appetite to taste of it certes he shal not a litle reioyse of it. For he shal here lerne almoost all thi ges that are necessary to be knowen of a Christen man concernynge this tyme of Lent. Fyrst I haue entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Penaunce, declaryng what it is, how it ought to be done, of whom we shoulde aske grace truelye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, &amp; howe it maye be obtayned.</p>
   <p>Secondly I haue spoken of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, Cōfessiō &amp; satisfaccion or amēde ment of lyfe. Thyrdely I haue decla red y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> true māner of fastyng. Fourth ly I haue intreated of diuers Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, that be vsed in the Chyrche this tyme of Lent, &amp; declared what they signify &amp; preach vnto vs. Laste
<pb facs="6"/>
of all, I haue shewed howe we ought to prepare oure selues for to receyue worthelye at the tyme of Easter the moost blessed Sacrament of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>All these thinges haue I done in this Potacion following, not folow yng myne owne fātasy or imagyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion but the veryte of Gods worde, the authorite of Christes moost holy Chyrche &amp; the mynde of the aunciēt and best learned Doctours.</p>
   <p>This my laboure, what soeuer it be, I nowe dedicate &amp; offer to youre right honorable maisterships name, desyrynge you to accepte thys lytle gyft as a testimony of my good hert and obsequious mynd towarde you, moost instantly also besechyng you, &amp; all other in your name to iudge it by the word of God, &amp; to compare it with the trueth of Christes Gospel. In so doyng I doubte not, but that both this &amp; al my other workes shal
<pb facs="7"/>
be receyued wythe the more grate, thankefull &amp; acceptable myndes, vn to the great profytte of the readers, &amp; the hygh glorye of almyghty God, who euer preserue your right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maystershyp in cōtinuall helth and prosperous felicite.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>