<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109561_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20154</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109561</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The heauenly banquet: or The doctrine of the Lords Supper : set forth in seuen sermons. With two prayers before and after the receiuing. And a iustification of kneeling in the act of receiuing. By Iohn Denison, Doctor of Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Denison, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Allott, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Brooks (Brooke), William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 364, 4 pages, folded table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese, amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther papers, which haue layne long by me, I had long since destinated to priuatenesse and silence; But such hath bene the importunity of friends, that I haue at last beene ouer-ruled for publishing of them.</p>
   <p>If in this discoutse vpon the Sacrament, thou finde that which may helpe to build thee vp in Christ,
<pb facs="7"/> (which is indeed my hope and desire) imbrace it, and make vse of it. And when thou commest to the matter of kneeling at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, take heed, I seriously intreat thee, of <hi>rashnesse, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, partiall and personall respect of men contrary mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> For hence it is that some cannot indure, euen to looke vpon those things which may draw them from error, and direct them in the way of <hi>Truth.</hi> This thou wilt account wilfulnesse and obstinacy in the Papist. And I am sure it is against the Apostles precept: <hi>Try
<pb facs="7"/> all things, &amp; hold that which is good.</hi> I call the searcher of all hearts to witnes, that in the handling of these things, I haue dealt faithfully, and with a good conscience, which wishing thee also to doe in reading of them, I commend <hi>thee to God, and to the word of his grace, who is able to build further, and to giue thee an inheritance with all those that are sanctified.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>