<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all faythfull readers / that loue Chryst and his doctrine sincerely, Gracyous Menew wy∣sheth grace, peace of conscience &amp; gostly strength from god the fa∣ther thorowe our Lorde and sauyoure Iesu Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109986_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07435</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17821</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109986</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all faythfull readers / that loue Chryst and his doctrine sincerely, Gracyous Menew wy∣sheth grace, peace of conscience &amp; gostly strength from god the fa∣ther thorowe our Lorde and sauyoure Iesu Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutacion of that popishe and antichristian doctryne, whiche mainteineth ye ministracyon and receiuing of the sacrament vnder one kind : made dialoge-wise betwene the prieste and the prentyse by Gracyous Menewe</title>
                 <author>Menewe, Gracious</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all faythfull readers / that loue Chryst and his doctrine sincerely, Gracyous Menew wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth grace, peace of conscience &amp; gostly strength from god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorowe our Lorde and sauyoure Iesu Christe.</head>
   <p>SOme there bee, moste Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and faythful brethren, whyche nowe at thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sente, that true relygion go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to wracke, doe not one lye thynke but also are fullye perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in themselues, that it is no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at al to Communicate wyth the Papystes, that so shamefullye mutilate or mangle the sacramente of the body and bloud of Chryste,
<pb facs="3"/>
that they cut of, and take awaye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> one halfe from the lay people, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the institucion and ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the heauenly wysedome of god, our sauioure Iesu Chryst. But if they woulde weygh the say<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of S. Paul in the .5. Chapter to the Ephesians, where he wryteth on this wyse: haue no felowshyppe wyth the vnfrutefull woorkes of darkenes,<note place="margin">Eph. 5. <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. 5.</note> and agayne: be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of other mens synnes: they would be otherwyse mynded, and be dryuen cleane away from that foolyshe perswasyon of theyrs. For if the cutting of, manglyng or takynge awaye of halfe the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt from the people of god, is no vnfrutefull worke of darknes and such a synne, as none other in a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner is to be compared wyth it: I cā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not tell what we should cal works of darkenes or what we shold nāe synne. Thys is moste sure, welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,
<pb facs="3"/>
that whatsoeuer man doeth imagyne and inuente,<note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glyng of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramente is an inuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of mē and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a work of darkenes.</note> besydes &amp; wythoute gods worde or agaynst the institucion of hym, that is the only true lyghte that lighteth all men that come in to the worlde: It must be mere darkenes. But thys mangling of the sacrament is an inuencion of wycked men, whych leauyng or rather despicynge the worde of god and ordynaunce of hys sonne Iesu Chryst our Lord, folowe the madde phantasyes of their owne braynes: therefore it muste nedes folowe, that it is a worke of darkenes▪ not onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frutefull, but also most noyesome and hurtefull, ye and of all other moste pernytyous. For beesydes that by it gods wrath is kyndled, and hys vengeaūce prouoked: they goe aboute most earnestly, by this deuilishe inuentyon of theyrs, to nourysh, mayntayne, defende and
<pb facs="4"/>
vpholde their blasphemous doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of transubstantiacion in the sacramente,<note place="margin">The marke that the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pistes shot at in thys manglynge of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> perswadyng the sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignoraunt people, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the wordes of consecracyon (as they call it) be once spoken, there re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayneth neyther bread nor wyne, but the very true and naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our sauioure Iesu Chryste, flesh, bloud and bones, as he was borne of the virgin, hangynge on the crosse, dyd lie in the graue and afterwardes beeyng raysed again from the dead ascended vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and therefore say they, it can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be, but that vnder the forme of breade, they receyue both flesh and bloud, except we would haue a body wythout bloud. Thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, I say, goe they about to esta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyshe, by thys theyr manglynge of the sacrament what pretense or coloure soeuer they haue besydes. Therefore haue no felowshyppe
<pb facs="4"/>
wyth theyr vnfrutefull, noysome and hurtful workes of darkenesse: be no more partakers of their sīne lest ye be also partakers with thē of the ponyshmentes and plagues that god threateneth vnto them, that preferryng theyr vnwyse and foolyshe knowledge, beefore hys heauenly wysedome, doe arrogant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly presume and take vpon them to immutate, chaunge and alter any of hys ordynaunces and lawes. And that thys matter of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment myght the better bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standed,<note place="margin">The cōtēts of thys boke.</note> and the intollerable blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the manglyng therof so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner espyed and perceaued: I haue here compyled a small treatyse, wherein all the argumentes and reasons, that the Popes catholiks can bryng for the mayntenaunce of their abomynacyon, are, I truste, so substancially confuted, that theī shall not haue one woorde to saye:
<pb facs="5"/>
wherein also ye shall learne howe farre they are deceaued, that think it no offence to receyue wyth them that so blasphemouslye breake the lordes institucion and ordinaūce, what clokes soeuer they can bryng for to cloke their synnefull doings wyth all. Onely I desyer this one thyng of you, that ye wil take this my rude doyng in good parte, and pray wyth me that god of hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly goodnes and mercy vouche safe to loke vpon our afflyctions, and forgettyng our offences and the offences of our forefathers de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuer vs from thys moste mysera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble thraldome and captiuitye of conscience that we bee in: that we may wyth a free and vpryght hart honor, loue and serue hym in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ryghteousnes al the dayes of our lyfe. Whyche thyng wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all peraduenture, if wyth true repentaunt heartes and faythfull
<pb facs="5"/>
prayers we call vpon hym, he wyll graunte vnto vs, through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes of hys sonne Iesu Chryste oure Lord and sauiour, to whō, wyth the father and the holy goste, be all prayse, glory and honoure worlde wythoute ende. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>