<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Here foloweth my answere to the Contradictions they charge mee with.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109294_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19856</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6284</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109294</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Here foloweth my answere to the Contradictions they charge mee with.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The replie of Iohn Darrell, to the answer of Iohn Deacon, and Iohn Walker, concerning the doctrine of the possession and dispossession of demoniakes</title>
                 <author>Darrel, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Other</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 50, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="addendum">
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <head>Here foloweth my answere to the Contradictions they charge mee with.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>contradicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> 13.</note> The <hi>Discoursers</hi> charging me with a shamfull companie of <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> no lesse then fiftie, I first framed an answere to them, with full purpose to publish it, &amp; therein haue made it plaine there is not a contradiction. But this my Treatise prouing much larger then I intended, &amp; the answere to them being of litle or no vse, saue only to cleare my selfe of this slaunder, and to discouer their filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which needeth not, I thought good rather to suppresse, then publish it: yet so as I will giue thee, good Reader, a taste thereof, and of their vpright dealing herein, assuring, thee of my credit, that euen such be the rest of their contradictions.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Answere.</note> Darell, <hi>say they,</hi> in his <hi>Doctrine</hi> pag. <hi>54.</hi> saith, that prayer and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting being vsed aright, will certainly prosper either to the remouing or sanctifying of the iudgment. But pag. <hi>56.</hi> he saith, their is no assurance to preuaile.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>contrad.</hi> 23▪</note> I answere. There is no assurance to preuaile, that is, <hi>we can not be sure the partie shall be deliuered, the meanes being vsed,</hi> for so are my wordes. Had then I sayd <hi>pag.</hi> 54. <hi>fasting will certainlie prosper to the remouing of the iudgement,</hi> and no more, I had contradicted that I say, <hi>pag,</hi> 59 but adding <hi>or sanctifying,</hi> a child may see here is no con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tradiction. Such a contradiction is this: Certenly the <hi>Discoursers</hi> wil ether be ashamed of their contradictions, or their sinne is the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter: Assuredly they will not be ashamed of their contradictions. And this: The sun is either vnder a cloud, or set. It is not vnder a cloud.</p>
   <p>In his Detection <hi>163.</hi> Darrell saith, fire hath powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r to burne, &amp; in the same pag. hath no power to burne.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ans▪</note> All that we reade <hi>Detection</hi> 163. is that <hi>Somers hand being in the fire was not burnt.</hi> Would euer any man, these two excepted, hence collect <hi>a contradiction?</hi> How many thousands in this land haue said the same, and among them not a few that be learned, &amp; yet I dare say neither learned, nor vnlearned euer feared they spake contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>Shadrach, Meshech, &amp; Abednego</hi> being in the fire were not bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and yet they that cast them into the fire were burnt. I trust you wil not say here is a <hi>contradiction.</hi> But confesse both these to be true. Fire naturally burneth, but restrayned by God the ouer-ruler o nature, it doth not burne. Secondly, you should first haue shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where I say, <hi>Fire hath power to burne,</hi> before you told vs that I speake contraries.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="32"/>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ntrad.</hi> 24.</note> In his <hi>Dotrine</hi> pag. <hi>2.</hi> he saith, that it suteth altogether with Satans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ature to be filthie or wicked in speech. But <hi>Detection 175.</hi> he saith, that it sutethe as well with his nature to vse good and holy speeches.</p>
   <p>My wordes <hi>Detection</hi> 175. <hi>be, Holy wordes haue beene vttered by satan.</hi> Tel me is this a false proposition? Or yet this: <hi>vncleane and</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ans.</note>
      <hi>blasphemous speeches sute excellently with the nature of the vncleane spirit.</hi> If both these be true, which none will deny, with what truth doe you say that I speake <hi>contraries,</hi> whereof the one must needs be false? These men sure had forgot when they doted of this <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> that the diuel is as well by nature subtil, (and in his subtiltie <hi>ready to transforme</hi> him selfe into Angel of light) as vncleane and wicked. Of this stampe they haue 18 contradictions more.</p>
   <p>In his <hi>Doctrine 47.</hi> He saith the disciples by vertue of their so large <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ontrad:</hi> 11,</note>a commission could cast out a diuel of any kinde. But pag. <hi>50.</hi> the Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike child was possest with one of the worst kinde of spirits, and that thence it came the disciples could not cast him out.</p>
   <p>To make this <hi>contradiction</hi> they haue <hi>detracted</hi> part of my words <note place="margin">Ans,</note>in either proposition. In the former these, <hi>if their faith failed not:</hi> which words, or words to the same effect in the aforesaid <hi>pag.</hi> 47. &amp; the two <hi>pages</hi> precedent I vse no lesse then twelue times. In the latter proposition where I say, <hi>thence partly it came,</hi> they <hi>detract</hi> this word <hi>partly:</hi> wherby I intimate the Disciples faith did at that time faile them, when they could not cast the diuel out of the lunatike child, so that their incredulitie was one let, which oft els where I expresse. And this you well knewe, as appeareth by your next <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,</hi> the twelft I meane. What meant you then thus to sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and rent asunder those words which of purpose I had coupled together? And by <hi>detracting</hi> that which in either of the propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> so materiall, and in the one I <hi>inculcate</hi> so often, to pretend a contradiction where you knew none was? Who hath bewitched you to vse such curled deuises, for the compassing of your contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions? A cursed pretence must this needes be, seeing it can not be done in ignorance: For you cannot be ignorant hereof, that the wordes detracted by you I vsed, spcially those so oft iterated, and that in those <hi>pages</hi> from whence yee haue the sa de contradictorie proposition: considering also that to make another contradiction you aleag the very same words you omit here, &amp; that frō the same page, as witnesseth the contradiction here following. Neither can you be ignorant of this, that these wordes being vsed and added by me, I am not contrary to my selfe, yea hence it is that you did
<pb facs="32"/>
omit them. It must needes therfore be that you knowing here was no <hi>contradiction,</hi> haue against that knowledge of yours (by this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise of <hi>detracting</hi> these words) made yet a faire shew to the world of a contradiction. Here is no contrarietie except these be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions contradictory: <hi>The Disciples could cast out a diuell of any kind, if their faith fayled not: The Disciples their faith failing could not cast the diuell out.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>contrad,</hi> 31</note> In his <hi>Doctrine 47.</hi> he saith the Apostles faith failed not: But pag. <hi>48</hi> he saith it failed at this time when Christ spake to them and in this very worke.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ans,</note> These wordes, <hi>the Apostles saith failed not,</hi> you could omit, when such omission serueth for your purpose, as appeares by the former contradiction. But now when they must stand you in some steade, they are not to seeke. He wanteth the vse of one of his sences, that smelleth not here your stinking breath. My wordes be these. They <hi>were able to cast out al diuels, if their faith fayled not:</hi> which imply not <hi>that the Apostles faith neuer failed them,</hi> as you would haue it, for otherwise here is no contradiction, but rather the contrary, that their faith did at some times faile them. Again, though these words <hi>The Apostles faith failed not,</hi> with the former are mine, yet thus rent and separated from their fellowes, I may trulye say they are not mine. In your <hi>Discourses</hi> you say, <hi>if the skies fall we shall haue larks,</hi> By your wise rule you there affirme, that <hi>the skies do falle</hi> &amp; in the sāe booke <hi>pag.</hi> 24. where you haue these words: <hi>If Angels be vncrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted then are they eternall:</hi> you affirme, that <hi>Angels be vncreated:</hi> yet <hi>pag.</hi> 28. you say <hi>Angels be created.</hi> These propositions be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie, and the former of them absurd, and so here is a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (forsooth) and an absurditie, when indeed there is neither. Here is paltrie and childish stuffe. If I would walke but in this one croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked step of yours, how easily could I make a booke of your <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> and another of your absurdities. But suppose I had said no more then you produce. vz. <hi>The Apostles faith sailed not</hi> frō thence ye could not inferre a contradiction, except I had spoken of the same time mētioned in the latter contradictorie proposition. Their, faith might not falle them at one time, and yet saile them at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>contrad,</hi> 15,</note>
      <hi>In Doctrine 52</hi> Abrahams prayer is made a sole meanes of conception and procreation of chidren: But pag. <hi>60</hi> another meanes is found appoīted of God for that purpose, or els it would proue a miracle.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ans,</note> As before by detracting so here by adding you abuse both mee,
<pb facs="33"/>
and the Reader: The words I vse be these <hi>Who will deny but that as the sinne of Abimilech (in taking Sarah, Abrahams wife vnto him) had shut vp euery wombe of the house of Abimelech, so the pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was the meane whereby they were opened. &amp; that iudgement taken away?</hi> Do I here make <hi>Abrahams prayer a sole meanes of procreation?</hi> That I meane &amp; affirme is, that by <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayer as a meanes <hi>Abimelech</hi> his wyfe &amp; women seruants, were made able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, which before they could not, not excluding, but including the knowlege and seede of man: which no man in his right minde would hence gather, this couple excepted.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>urad,</hi> 46,</note> In his Doctrine pag. <hi>2.</hi> he saith, it is absurd to affirme that the diuel▪ being without a man) can dispose of the whole or any parte of mans bodie: but Detection, page <hi>11.</hi> he saith that thediuel (in all probability) did vse Sommers his tongue, notwithstanding he was essentiallie and sensiblic playing boe peepe vnder the couerleed.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ans,</note> The former proposition is not mine, <hi>I say euery part,</hi> you save, <hi>any part.</hi> And so by <hi>altering</hi> a word you haue made <hi>a contradic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion</hi> where none is: except there be no other part of <hi>Sommers</hi> his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, besides his tongue.</p>
   <p>And thus to thee Reader, but for breuitie, I would make it eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that of the <hi>discoursers</hi> fiftie contradictions, being examined one by one, there is not so much as one to be found. The greater is their siune and shame who charged me with so many.</p>
   <p>And here we are to obseruefirst, that of these contradic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions there are aboue 20. wherin there is no contradiction at all, taking them at the hucksters hand, euen as themselues haue quoted them. And namely these: contradiction 4. 6. 7. 8. 13. 14. 17. 18. 19. 21. 23. 24. 26. 28. 31. 35. 38. 36. 37. 41, &amp; 45</p>
   <p>Secondly, to marke the seueral deuises or sleights whereby they make semblance of contradictions when there are indeed none if you take the words as they be set downe in my treatises. I his sem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blance they make.</p>
   <p n="1">1 By <hi>forging</hi> that I neuer affirmed (but often the contrary) as in contradiction 1. 9. 17. 19. 20, 23, 25, 26, 27, 35, &amp; 46.</p>
   <p n="2">2 <hi>By omitting</hi> or <hi>detracting</hi> some worde or words material, as <hi>in contradiction</hi> 3, 11, 12, 25, 27, 30, 31, 33, 36, 39, &amp; 40</p>
   <p n="3">3 <hi>By adding,</hi> and thus haue they done in contradiction 15. 43. &amp; 47.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb facs="33"/>
4 By <hi>altering,</hi> as apeareth by contradiction 6, 17, 27, 29, 49</p>
   <p n="5">5 To this said end also, when both their contradictory propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions are in the same <hi>page,</hi> and somtimes in the very same sentence, they runne notwithstanding for the one of them to a <hi>page</hi> far off, or happelie to another booke: Hereby (I meane by alleaging two distinct pages of mine, somwhat also asunder) pretending, that what I say n one place, forgetting forsooth my self, I gaynsay in another. As appeareth by contradiction 1. 3▪ 5. 22▪ 26. 36. 42. &amp; 47.</p>
   <p>Thus haue these men so accustomed and taught themselues to falsife my writings in whole or in part: by <hi>forging, detracting, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; altering,</hi> as they haue alleaged very litle of mine truly: &amp; no marce: because truly alleaged they would not make for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Yet notwithstanding they haue by these cursed meanes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed their <hi>contradictions,</hi> I doubt not but that they please them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues greatly, and glory in them, specially in the great number of them, and doe thinke therein they haue shewed not a litle wit. But I <hi>will</hi> tel you, a very foole that will giue libertie to himself to <hi>adde, detract</hi> and <hi>alter</hi> but here &amp; there a letter, may easily make, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>contradictions,</hi> where none are: much more he that wil do thus by wordes &amp; somtimes by sentences, as you haue done.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ans. Epist, to the Reader fol, <hi>4</hi>
      </note> VVhether now you haue <hi>pretermited any thing material,</hi> and by such <hi>omitting,</hi> and <hi>taking what parte of my writings might make most for your purpose, euen purposely maymed my writings,</hi> which you deny and I affirme, iudge thou indissirently betwene vs good reader. And whether you will <hi>acknowledge</hi> and <hi>redresse the offred wrong,</hi> whereof I complaine, and which I trust to be a <hi>wrong</hi> I haue made manifest by this my <hi>Replie,</hi> vnto all men, &amp; to your owne consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as you pretend you will, nay, seeme to abhorre not to do it, if once the <hi>wrong</hi> shal be made to appeare, saying: <hi>God forbid that we should not doe it very willinglie:</hi> in time both thou and I shall know. And thus much for answer to their supposed <hi>contradictions.</hi> For bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitie sake I omit my reply to the <hi>Absurdities</hi> wherewith you charge me, and your slaunders conteined in them.</p>
   <p>Here not vnfitly may I charge you with the <hi>contradictions &amp; Absurdities</hi> I find in your writinges: and if it fall out so that your selues be found faultie in that, wherof vniustly you accuse another, then thereby learne henceforward to plucke rather the beame out of your own eyes, then busie your selues so much about lesse then a mote in your brothers eye.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="34"/>
      <hi>In their</hi> Answere <hi>page 55 and page 179 of their</hi> Discourses, <hi>they say, that</hi> the manifestation of Christ his deitie, and declaration of his glorious &amp; spell, were the maine ends of poss<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssion: <hi>and a little after, that</hi> the possession of diuels were especially for these two ends: <hi>therby in sinuating that there were some other ends or end. Yet page 67 of the same booke they say, that</hi> these were the two only ends of this von<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull iudgement.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2 In their</hi> Dial. dis. <hi>page 58 they say,</hi> angels doe euermore worke after an inuisible, insensible, and spirituall maner. <hi>And the next leafe, page 60 they say, that</hi> angels in all their ambassages they do other manifest themselues by seeing and hearing, or assist vs estsoon<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s by some other sensible means. <hi>And they bring</hi> Augustine <hi>flatly affirming</hi> that the angels do outwardly helpe vs by certaine visible apparitions or sights, which they propose and offer before our eyes.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3 In their</hi> Discourses <hi>pa. 42 they say,</hi> the mind it selfe, and it only is that wherein motion consisteth: and the body is but the minds organon or instrument, hauing naturally in it selfe no motion at all, or no further motion at the most, then for those only actions wherin the said mind (whose organon it is) imployeth the same. <hi>But in pag. 74 of the same booke they affirme, that</hi> the body it selfe hath, and may accomplish or effect corporall operations and motions by it selfe alone, without anie the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, moderation, guidance, or <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of the soule.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4 In their</hi> Discourses <hi>pag. 116 they say,</hi> the diuell did so bewitch and charme the Serpent, as that (through his craftie suggestion) shee was very wel able to propound such a diuination or sooths<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ing, as d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently circumuent or deceiue Fuah. <hi>And in the same booke page 1 9 they say, that</hi> a reasonable speech cannot possibly bee framed or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of anie but of a mind hauing vnderstanding and reason.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5 In their</hi> Answer <hi>pa 50 they say.</hi> These eight d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>moniakes might be possessed, though the diuell was not essentially inherent in anie one of their bodies: <hi>But page 43 of the same booke they say,</hi> The p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssession of diuels whatsoeuer is ceased long since.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6 In their</hi> Discourses <hi>173 they say.</hi> The Apostles might authētically auouch for insallible truth whatsoeuer they preached. <hi>But in their.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere <hi>page 126 128 129 130 they say, that</hi> the apostles sometime failed in doctrine. <hi>And a little after:</hi> all these were their err<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urs in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and iudgement. <hi>And againe.</hi> It was expedient for the apostles to erre in some things, <hi>that is, some points of doctrine.</hi> And <hi>this they
<pb facs="34"/>
vnderstand after the holy Ghost fell vpon them, as is plaine by the aforesaid pages.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7 In their</hi> Answer pag. <hi>7, they say, that</hi> wonders and miracles are flatly confounded: <hi>but in their</hi> Dialogicall discourses <hi>209, they say,</hi> the diuel may worke wonders, but can effect no miracles. And pag, <hi>310, thus,</hi> A thing effected by essentiall means, howsoeuer it may be a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet no miracle in any respect.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8 In your</hi> Discourses pag. <hi>352.</hi> for your parts you assure me, that you are very farre from all suspition of a precompacted confederacie betweene Sommers and me. <hi>Yet in</hi> page <hi>42.</hi> of your Answere <hi>you say,</hi> why should we wonder at all, that two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>unning compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ns <hi>(Meaning</hi> Sonnners <hi>and my selfe)</hi> consed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rate together before should conclude such a course betweene themselues, as the one (by the helpe of the other) should progm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>icate strange and mered<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ble euents.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <hi>9 In pag. 39. of their</hi> Discourses, <hi>they tell vs,</hi> There is not anie one sound Diuine that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n t vnderstand Possession as they doe, and none as I fondly imagine <hi>and yet in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pistle to the Reader prefixed before that booke, that which they deliuer</hi> concerning possession and d sposs ssion of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uels, they call, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t priuate opinion: <hi>and in page 195 of their Answere,</hi> The Lord his lately revealed counsels.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Part of their absurd and vnsound Positions</head>
      <p n="1">1 Godby good Angels may effect fantasticall, vaine, and filthie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <hi>Answers</hi> 15.</p>
      <p n="2">2 Good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ngels may effect vaine and filthy effects▪ ibid.</p>
      <p n="3">3 VVheresoeuer the Scriptures speake of Angels or diuels, they speake only by metaphore▪ ibid.</p>
      <p n="4">4 The Diuel hath no desire to be in any mans body. <hi>Ans.</hi> 22</p>
      <p n="5">5 The Iewes in Christs time did (partly) know the parties which were possessed, from the often reuelation of the parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. <hi>answ.</hi> 32</p>
      <p n="6">6 Godby his Spirit instructed the Cananitish woman (mentioned <hi>Matth.</hi> 15, 22) of her daughters malacie. <hi>answ▪</hi> 33</p>
      <p n="7">7 The manifestation of Christs deitie, and the confirmation of the Gospell, the only ends of Possession. <hi>answ.</hi> 67</p>
      <p n="8">8 Christ hath put a finall end to the possession of diuels by his death and resurrection. <hi>answ.</hi> 66</p>
      <p n="9">9 The supernaturall actions or effects of the Diuel in Demoniaks, cannot possibly be comprehended by humane senses. <hi>Ans.</hi> 69</p>
      <p n="10">
         <pb facs="56"/>
10 The working of miracles was only in Christ and his Apostles dayes, <hi>answ.</hi> 90</p>
      <p n="11">11 God hath appointed plowing and sowing for a meanes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance or barrennes vpon the ground, <hi>answ</hi> 172</p>
      <p n="12">12 Good angels do euormore worke after an invisible, insensible and spirituall manner, <hi>Dialogical discourses</hi> 58. This is to bee refuted by all those places where angels are said to haue appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and spoken in visible formes vnto men.</p>
      <p n="13">13 The body hath, and may accomplish by her selfe alone, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall actions and motions, without anie her soules direction, moderation, guidance, or consent, <hi>Dial. disc.</hi> 74</p>
      <p n="14">14 The dead carcasse of a man, or the body being separate from the soule, may and doth also effect corporall actions and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. ibid.</p>
      <p n="15">15 The Diuel did so bewitch and so charme the Serpent, as that (through his craftie suggestion) shee was very well able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound such a diuination or soothsaying, as did presently circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uent and deceiue <hi>Euah. Dial. disc.</hi> 16. Absurd, that the Diuell should not onely thus make the Serpent it selfe to speake, but also argue the matter like a reasonable creature</p>
      <p n="16">16 The apostles erred in some points of doctrine, after the holy Ghost fell vpon them: Yea, it was expedient for them so to erre <hi>answ.</hi> 126, 128, 129, 130</p>
      <p n="17">17 It is verie erronious for able to imagin, that the eyes may pos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sibly be deceiued, in discerning betweene spirits (that is, bodies assumed by spirits) and true naturall bodies. <hi>Dial. disc.</hi> 157. You forget that <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> were deceiued, as appeareth by <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. and 19.</p>
      <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>