<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>GENTLE AND CATHOLIQVE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109712_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20517</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6929</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>GENTLE AND CATHOLIQVE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reply to M. Nicholas Smith, his discussion, of some pointes of M. Doctour Kellison his treatise of the hierarchie. By a divine</title>
                 <author>Divine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 18, 301, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>GENTLE</hi> AND CATHOLIQVE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AISTER Doctour Kellison, as he hath vvritten diuers boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes tending to the Reconciliation of heretickes to the Catholique Church: so of late he sette forthe a <hi>Treatise</hi> entitled: <hi>The Hierarchie of the Church,</hi> that thereby he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile some Catholiques, the one to the other, to vvit the secular Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie and Regulars, vvho, though both vvorthie members of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>Church, seemed to be at some litle variance.</p>
   <p>The reason vvhy he published this Treatise, vvas, as I haue heard him saye, because he vvas infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by letters, and perceiued by certaine vvritinges and Pamphlets vvritten toe and froe, that there vvas some diuision betvvixt the most Reuerend Bishop and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie on the one side, and the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars on the other side, to the greate griefe, I am sure, of both sides, to the edification of fevv, and dishonour of all.</p>
   <p>Wherfore partlie out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion vvhich hee tooke to see tvvo so vvorthie bodyes (vvhich beare no litle svvaye in our litle Church of England, and vvhich heretofore ioyned both labours
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>and bloud in setting forth the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique cause) to be so deuided in opinions and affections; and partlie at the request of some frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, vvho vvished vvell to bothe (for setting these tvvo motiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, he vvould not haue entermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in so ticklish a busines, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he might offend one partie and peraduenture both, though he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noreth and loueth both, he vnder tooke the vvriting of the aforesayd Treatise of the Hierarchie, and of diuers orders of the Church, that so he might take occasion to vvrite of the dignirie and necessitie of Bishop, and secular Clergie, vvhich seemed by many clamours vvhich he heard of, and vvritings also vvhich he savve, to be oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; in so much that Episcopall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>in England, and in these tymes vvas counted a <hi>noueltie, odious, contrarie to ancient lavves of England, and preiudiciall to soules,</hi> and yet to speake also of the state and perfection, belonging to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, vvho seemed to bee oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, and so to dispose both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes to peace and concord.</p>
   <p>And therfore he vvrote a long Dedicatorie Epistle to all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques of England, exhorting all to agree in affections as they doe in matters of fayth and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Regulars to honour the seculars, and the seculars to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Regulars as their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv missioners, ayders and coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratours. VVhich exhortation he oftentymes vpon occasion repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his Treatise, and hath not
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>in all the booke so much as one bitter or tarte vvord against per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or state, vnles novv and then a glaunce against Luther and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin: but so he extolleth the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop and Clergie, as he depresseth not the Regulars, but giueth them as much as S. Thomas of Aquin an holy and learned regular doth yeeld vnto them. Jn so much that diuers vvere of opiniō, and he him self also verilie hoped, that this Treatise vvould not haue offended any, but rather vvould haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed all, and by pleasing all, induced all to an attonemēt Out of vvhich hope and opinion he feared not to put his name vnto his booke, nor to present it as a gratefull guift to the cheefe of our English Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars in Dovvay, vvhere the
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>booke vvas printed.</p>
   <p>But he hath vnderstood by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from England, and novv la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telie by a certaine Discussion fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered on a Regular deceased (the Father belike vvas ashamed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his <hi>Posthumus,</hi> and therfore dyed) that the Regulars tooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> this his Treatise in that good pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> he vvished and hoped; but rather thought them selues dishonored by it: vvhich the more grieued him, because as he sincerelie prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in his Epistle Dedicatorie, and often tymes hath made the same protestation by vvord of mouth, he intended in noe vvise to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the venerable and approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued state of Regulars, but so t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> commend the state of the Bisho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and Clergie, vvhich he savv vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainely
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>opposed, as yet to giue to the Regulars as much as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedst Regulars doe yeeld vnto them, and consequentlie so to right one partie, as not to vvrong the other, but rather to commend both.</p>
   <p>Some freinds haue vrged him to make a Replye to this <hi>Discussion</hi> fathered on <hi>M. Nicholas Smith:</hi> but <hi>M. Doctour</hi> had not (as he sayd) the harte to vvrite against a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and him a Regular, counting it no grace to disgrace a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, noe victorie to ouercome him: and fearing least in vvriting against him, he might contristate other Catholiques, and noe lesse make glad our common enemyes, vvho imagine our vvarre to be their peace.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="10" facs="6"/>Yea <hi>M. Doctour</hi> vsed to saye: To vvhat purpose should J ansvvere one vvho vvriteth not against mee. For I neuer think that he vvriteth against mee, vvho vvilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or ignorantlie mistaketh my vvords and meaning, and putteth vpō mee vvhat I neuer sayd or mēt, that so he may haue the greater aduantage and make a shovv of a victorie. But he vvriteth against mee (sayd the <hi>Doctour</hi>) vvho vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth against my vvords and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and if he fathereth on mee (as <hi>M. Nicholas</hi> vseth to doe) that vvhich J neuer sayd or ment, and in that sorte maketh his as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault; hee assaulteth not mee, but a supposed and fayned aduersarie. And yet if <hi>M. Nicholas,</hi> had not fayned such an aduersarie, he could
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>not haue made so much as a shovv of an ansvvere to the Hierarchie as shall euerie vvhere be shevved in the decourse of this reply. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides (sayd <hi>M. Doctour</hi>) I ame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in more important busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses; and if I vvere not, yet doe I not think a Reply necessarie, vvhere there vvas noe ansvvere, but only vvresting of vvords, vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly or vnvvittingly mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge, scanning of intentions, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of vntruthes, so to make a shovv of a victorie, vvhere indeed <hi>M. Nicholas</hi> him selfe vvas foyled. And moreouer he sayd the booke vvill ansvver for it selfe, and the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader (as he heareth a learned deuine in his <hi>Jnquisition,</hi> and some others haue done) vvill out of it ansvvere for him. And last
<pb n="12" facs="7"/>of all, he sayd: vvhy should I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter vvith an aduersarie that dareth not shevv him selfe in the field, and therfore goeth masked vnder another mās name: though it is thought he vvalketh rather in a nette; the question, vvho he should be, being not so hard to solue, as <hi>Gordius</hi> his <hi>Knotte</hi> vvas to bee dissolued.</p>
   <p>Yet out of the respect and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction J beare to <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> and in regard of the obligation vvherby J ame obliged to him (as hauing liued vnder his gouernment) and out of the care I haue of his good name and reputation (vvhich I thought could not be impeached vvithout some preiudice to the common cause) J haue vndertaken to ansvver for him, and in this my
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>Reply to imitate the temper and moderation vvhich hee in his <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie</hi> hath vsed: and not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv the splene, bitternes, immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie and smale respect of <hi>M. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Many, vvho haue redde <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> booke, haue much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him (to my knovvledge) by letters from England and other places for his mildnes, temper and discretion; and therfore as many, doe vvonder vvhy <hi>M. Nicholas,</hi> and he a Regular, should ansvvere him vvith such bitternes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modestie.</p>
   <p>VVhat is there in <hi>M. Doctours</hi> booke vvhich so moueth his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience? J ame sure there is not one tarte vvord in all <hi>M. Doctours</hi> booke: and he vvriteth against noe
<pb n="14" facs="8"/>person, noe state, noe order; nor meddleth he vvith the late contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie, and for no other reason but because he vvould not offend. It is true he vvriteth of the Hierarchie of the Church, and of all orders: but that is a point of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique fayth, vvhich (as <hi>M. Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> confesseth in his first question n. 2.) <hi>Hath beene handled most lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlie, copiously, and eloquentlie by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, both in latine and vulgartongues</hi> as indeed it hath by <hi>S. Thomas of Aquin, Suarez,</hi> and others in latine. VVhy then vvriteth not <hi>M. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> against them, as vvell as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> they hauing not handled the matter vvith mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re temper then he, nor hauing yeelded more to regulars then hee? vvhat then is it, <hi>M. Nicholas,</hi>
      <pb n="15" facs="8"/>that so moueth your Choler? <hi>M. Doctour</hi> exalteth the Bishop and Clergie. So doe <hi>S. Jgnatius, S Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose, S. Chrysostome</hi> cited by <hi>M. Doctour</hi> in his 7. chapter, so doe all that vvrite of the Hierarchie; so doth the Councell of Trēt,<note place="margin">Conc. Trid. seff. 23. c. 4. S. Th. 2. 2. q. 185. art. 8.</note> vvhich sayth, that <hi>Bishops doe appertaine principallie to Hierarchicall order,</hi> so doth S. Thomās of Aquin alleaged by <hi>M. Doctour</hi> in his 11. chapter n. 18. And as <hi>M. Doctour</hi> exalteth the Bishop and Clergie, so doth he the Regulars in their ranke. But he giueth the precedence in digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and state of perfection to the Bishop, as S. Thomas and all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines and Fathers doe: hee she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth the necessitie of Bishops in the Church of God; the need that all countries haue of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>vvhich ordinarilie can not be had vvithout a Bishop, vvhose splendour, <hi>M. Nicholas</hi> peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture feareth vvould obscure his ovvne.</p>
   <p>This then may bee the cause (for J can fynd no other, <hi>&amp; hincillae la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae.</hi> This is the cause of his rough ansvver vvhich in euerie page allmost is so bitter, that as the lavves of <hi>Draco</hi> the Legislatour of the <hi>Athenians</hi> vvere sayd to haue been vvritten vvith mans bloud, by reason of their crueltie, so <hi>M. Nicholas</hi> his <hi>Discussiō</hi> may bee sayd to haue been vvritten not vvith inke, but vvith galle, it is so byting and bitter.</p>
   <p>Certes although I vvill not iudge of his spirit, yet he seemeth to shevve litle of the spirit of a
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>Religious man, vvhich is the spirit of humilitie, patience, modestie, charitie, and of respect to Bishops, Prelats, Priests, and Pastours: such as vvas the Spirit of <hi>S. Benedict, S. Bernard, S. Dominike, S. Jgnatius, S. Xauier.</hi> For that he striueth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the state of Bishops and Pastours, and to extenuate the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie both of Bishops and of the Sacrament of Confirmation.</p>
   <p>VVherfore I protest sincerelie, and as God knovveth, from my harte, that I ame hartilie sorrie that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> hath giuen me a iust cause, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>osed a necessitie on me to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svver his <hi>Discussion,</hi> and defend <hi>M. Doctour</hi> and the true doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by him: because I feare I can not doe this sufficientlie (as I must, seing J haue vndertaken to
<pb n="18" facs="10"/>ansvver for <hi>M. Doctour</hi>) vvithout dishonour to <hi>M. Nicholas</hi> a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and Religious man, and in credit and estimation in his Order. Yet vvhat I can doe vvithout pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to <hi>D. Kellison,</hi> vvhose honour is deare vnto mee, and to the true doctrine, vvhich he hath taught, I shall doe: And therfore J meane not to imitate his odious manner of vvriting, vvhich J heare is displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to all iudicious and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Readers; rather I vvill passe ouer his harsh speeches vvith pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, though not allvvayes vvith silence, and vvheras it is his vsuall manner to insult before the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie vvith these and the like speeches: <hi>A doughtie argument,</hi> pag. 16. <hi>J vvill not say noe diuine, but euen no man in his right iudgement,
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>can affirme,</hi> pag. 48. <hi>J can not but meruaile that a learned man should vse such a forme of argument,</hi> pag. 48 <hi>still M. Doctour citeth Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours against him selfe,</hi> pag. 89. &amp;c. J shall not insult ouer him, though, as the Reader shall see, J get the maistrie ouer him, and the victorie of him; holding it a base thing, and not vvorthie a generous mynd, to strike his aduersarie or insult vpon him, vvhen he lyeth on the ground. But rather I vvill proceede vvith patience and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vvill content my selfe to ouercome, and to put my aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie to silence by argument, not by cryes and clamours: and though J be noe Regular, yet I vvill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to giue him example of religious humilitie, modestie,
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>and charitie.</p>
   <p>But to returne to the Reader to vvhom this preface is addressed, J shall desire him not to be scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized to see one Catholique vvrite against another: Catholiques as Catholiques agree allvvayes in matters of fayth, and good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques neuer breake charitie: but the best Catholiques,<note place="margin">Gal. 3. Act. 15. Hieron. Ep. 86. &amp; seq. Aug. Ep. 8. &amp; seq. Eus. l. 5. c. 24. &amp; 25. Beda l. 3. hist. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gl. c. 24. &amp; 25. l. 5. c. 16. Daniel 10.</note> as men, may va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in other opinions. S. Peter, S. Paule, and S. Barnabas: and S. Augustine, and S. Hierome, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreed in some opinions vvithout breach of fayth or charitie. About the obseruation of Easter there vvas greate debate betvvixt Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Saintes, till the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided the controuersie, yea Angels haue dissented in opinion. And so long as the dissensiō is not in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="21" facs="11"/>of fayth, it may be vvithout preiudice to faith, and vvithout breach of charitie. And hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer; this vvriting of one Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique against another, is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to <hi>M. Nicholas,</hi> vvho vvas the first that vvrote against a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique; for that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> vvrote against noe mā, and J vvould neuer haue vvriten against <hi>M. Nicholas,</hi> but in defence of a Catholique, and Catholique Doctrine.</p>
   <p>And as thou (Gentle Reader) art to be a spectatour of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter and combat betvvixt me and <hi>M. Nicholas;</hi> so I desire thou shouldst be the iudge and vmpier also; so that thou follovvest not affection vvhich oftentymes blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, but vnblinded reason, vvhich neuer deceiueth, but vvill
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>cause thee to pronouncē sentencē vvhere thou seest most reason, not vvhere thou settlest most thy affection.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>