<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109555_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20104</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6544</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109555</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The making, description, and vse of a small portable instrument for ye pocket (or according to any magnitude) in forme of a mixt trapezia thus called a horizontall quadrant : composed and prodused soly for the benefit and vse of such which are studious of mathematicall practice Written and delivered by Delamain, student and teacher of the mathematickes</title>
                 <author>Delamain, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hawkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 104 pages, 4 leaves of plates, illustrations, table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore</hi> I shew the <hi>Projection,</hi> describe the particulars, and deliver the uses of this <hi>Horizontall Quadrant,</hi> it will not bee impertinent, for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of some, to give the <hi>Reader</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what moved me unto it, how it exceeds other <hi>Instruments,</hi> and whence it might be drawne, and projected.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now</hi> the ingenious aptnesse for <hi>Inuention,</hi> and accomodating of things in a faire and expedite course for <hi>Mathematicall Practices,</hi> of that late professor of <hi>Astronomy</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Gunter</hi> is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne unto many about this kingdome, satisfying many of his friends (according to his free and noble affection) by <hi>Transcripts</hi> in that of more solid matter, but such of vulgar <hi>Practices</hi> he hath publikely made manifest for the use of all such as affect those <hi>Studies. In</hi> which worke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares past I tooke occasion to consider the <hi>Scheme,</hi> or <hi>Diagramme</hi> of the fourth <hi>Projection</hi> in
<pb facs="6"/> his <hi>Booke</hi> of the <hi>Sector</hi> Page the 64. &amp; 65. w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he saies is after the manner of the old <hi>Concaue hemisphere</hi> (but being in truth a naturall <hi>Projection</hi> of the visible <hi>Hemisphere,</hi> that is, one Moytie of the <hi>Globe,</hi> projected on a <hi>Plaine</hi>) which <hi>Diagram</hi> and <hi>Projection</hi> is now chalenged by my Reverend good friend <hi>Master Oughtred,</hi> and it should seeme that <hi>Master Gunter</hi> had the Original of it from his labours, &amp; invention, who composed and made the same so, for more then thirty yeares past, as appeares by his owne <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Manuscripts</hi> upon that <hi>Protection</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me in the time of the Printing of this <hi>Trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat</hi> upon my <hi>Horizontall Quadrant,</hi> whose ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent knowledge in <hi>Mathematicall</hi> Learning may evidently confirme it: which <hi>Projection</hi> the said <hi>Master Oughtred</hi> gave to the late <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Winchester, Doctor Bilson,</hi> for more then 20. yeares past, and to some others of very good quality.</p>
   <p>And it may also, by a Letter from that most famous and admired <hi>Geometer, Master Henry Brigges</hi> unto <hi>Master Oughtred</hi> dated from <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham College Iune,</hi> the 2. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1618. be collected that the said <hi>Master Gunter</hi> had the first overture of that fourth <hi>Projection,</hi> from the said <hi>Master Oughtred,</hi> in which <hi>letter</hi> are these words: <hi>Master Gunter</hi> doth here send you the <hi>Print</hi> of an <hi>Horizontall Diall</hi> of his drawing after your <hi>Instrument;</hi> And afterwards the said <hi>Projec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was also presented by <hi>Master Gunter</hi> to many Noble <hi>Personages,</hi> and in particular to
<pb facs="6"/> the <hi>Right Honourable</hi> the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> causing it to be cut in <hi>Brasse,</hi> in such a forme a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I have placed at the end of this <hi>Tractat,</hi> some uses of which <hi>Diall</hi> are extant, viz. the 2. 18. 21. and 34. <hi>Pro.</hi> of the <hi>Index</hi> or <hi>Table</hi> following.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now</hi> having considered diverse <hi>Pocket Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (that many men are practised in) &amp; looked into sundry <hi>Projections,</hi> amongst which that of <hi>Gemmafrisius</hi> (there drawne in the <hi>Booke</hi> of the <hi>Sector</hi>) is of admirable use, yet making a more serious quaere, &amp; contemplating more intensively upon that <hi>Diagram,</hi> drawne and specified in that 64. and 65. Pages of the <hi>Sector</hi> (aforesaid) I found it farre to exceede all others in the <hi>Multiplicity,</hi> and excellencie of performance.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>If</hi> I should adde unto it a <hi>Kalender</hi> of <hi>time,</hi> and an <hi>Index</hi> graduated with an <hi>Axis,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiculars</hi> to be erected vpon it at pleasure: &amp; referring only the <hi>Trapeziall forme,</hi> it should be fitted farre to exceede any portable <hi>Instrument</hi> for the <hi>Pocket,</hi> ever yet produced in respect of the general uses of it: in resolving such ordinary <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions</hi> which are practiced in <hi>Astronomie,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Globe, Spheare, Hemispheare, Quadrants</hi> of all sorts, <hi>Astrolabe</hi> of <hi>Frisius, Blagraue,</hi> and others for facility, expedition, or certaintie, (like <hi>Magnitudes</hi> considered) for in these <hi>Instruments</hi> for severall times, and severall <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions,</hi> there must be diverse rectifications of the parts belonging to these <hi>Instruments,</hi> and
<pb facs="7"/> that diversly by reason of their diversity: By this <hi>Horizontall Quadrant,</hi> the former redifications are avoided, Contemplation &amp; the eye being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Index,</hi> the aptnesse, &amp; fitnesse of the parts, and lines so naturally projected, or described as they are upon the plaine of the <hi>Instrument</hi> (being a part of the <hi>Horizon</hi> the <hi>Parallels Meridians,</hi> &amp; <hi>Verticall Circles,</hi> that are contained or may be des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed in our <hi>Latitude</hi> sufficiently necessary) indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth any one in the understanding of the uses of it that is but indifferently versed in the linaments and principles of the <hi>Globe,</hi> what to speake, and what to answere in a <hi>Proposition</hi> without farther direction: And having had this <hi>Horizontall Quadrant</hi> for many yeares past, as a <hi>Pocket In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument,</hi> diverse about this <hi>Kingdome</hi> being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate with me for to have it, or to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish the use of it, seeing its great facilitie, and expedition, in comparison of such <hi>Pocket Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> as are now used, here, or in forraigne parts: I was willing at last after I had given order for the making of fower of these <hi>Instruments</hi> in <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> for severall <hi>Noble Personages,</hi> to disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my selfe of <hi>Transcribing</hi> the uses of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument,</hi> and <hi>Tables</hi> for the making of it, to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie those which were importunate, and to let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are studious in <hi>Mathematicall Practices</hi> also participate of it.</p>
   <p>Now, what I have delivered vpon the accommodating of the <hi>Instrument</hi> thus, the making thereof, with the uses that I
<pb facs="7"/> have delivered in this <hi>Tractat</hi> upon it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: I acknowledge due to none <hi>Inferiour assistant,</hi> but to mine owne <hi>Industry, search</hi> and <hi>labour,</hi> and that 64. 65. and 66. <hi>Pages</hi> of the <hi>Booke:</hi> of the <hi>Sector</hi> before specified in which is onely shewne the 2. 3. 19. 22. 25. and 30. <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions</hi> of the <hi>Index,</hi> or <hi>Table</hi> following, as uses of the said <hi>Projection.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But</hi> I have extended them to many more, and abundantly, and plentifully supplied the obscuritie of that <hi>Scheme,</hi> or <hi>Diagramme</hi> there drawne (as for a generall good) in the use of this <hi>Horizantal Quadrant.</hi> I deliver therfore first the making of it, first by the <hi>Sector</hi> (somewhat different from that of <hi>Master Gunters</hi>) secondly by <hi>Geometrie,</hi> and lastly I shew a third way, how it may be <hi>Proiected</hi> and made by my <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Ring,</hi> and by <hi>Numbers,</hi> which I have <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated</hi> and accommodated to that end in <hi>Tables,</hi> for more exactnesse. <hi>Part</hi> of the generall scope, and use of which <hi>Instrument</hi> I deliuer in the <hi>Index,</hi> or <hi>Table</hi> following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>