<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his euer-honoured Lords, the right noble Lords, ALEXANDER, Earle of DVMFERMELING, Lord Fyuy, Great Chanceller of SCOTLAND, &amp;c. THOMAS, Lord BINNIE, Lord President of the Col∣ledge of Iustice, and his Maiesties Secretarie for Scotland, &amp;c. And to the rest of the most Iudicious and honourable Lords, tho Iudges and Senatours of the high Court and Senate of this Kingdome, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109476_Fr2_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15715</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109476</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his euer-honoured Lords, the right noble Lords, ALEXANDER, Earle of DVMFERMELING, Lord Fyuy, Great Chanceller of SCOTLAND, &amp;c. THOMAS, Lord BINNIE, Lord President of the Col∣ledge of Iustice, and his Maiesties Secretarie for Scotland, &amp;c. And to the rest of the most Iudicious and honourable Lords, tho Iudges and Senatours of the high Court and Senate of this Kingdome, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrimes farewell, to his natiue countrey of Scotland : vvherein is contained, in way of dialogue, the ioyes and miseries of peregrination. With his Lamentado in his second trauels, his Passionado on the Rhyne, diuerse other insertings, and farewels, to noble personages, and, the heremites welcome to his third pilgrimage, &amp;c. Worthie to be seene and read of all gallant spirits, and pompe-expecting eyes. By William Lithgow, the bonauenture of Europe, Asia, and Africa, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Hart, Andro.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lithgow, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To his euer-honoured Lords, the right noble <hi>Lords, ALEXANDER, Earle of DVMFERMELING,</hi> Lord Fyuy, Great Chanceller of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>THOMAS, Lord BINNIE, Lord President of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Iustice, and his Maiesties Secretarie for</hi> Scotland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to the rest of the most Iudicious and honourable Lords, tho Iudges and Senatours of the high Court and Senate of this Kingdome, &amp;c.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S thou art first (great Lord) in thy great worth,</l>
      <l>So thou dost liue a Loadstarre to this North:</l>
      <l>Next to our Prince, in all supreme affaires,</l>
      <l>Art chiefest Iudge, and greatest wrong repairs.</l>
      <l>A second <hi>Solon,</hi> on the Arch of Fame,</l>
      <l>Makes Equitie and Iustice seale thy name.</l>
      <l>And art indued with Faculties diuine,</l>
      <l>From whose sage Breast, true beames of Vertue shine.</l>
      <l>Out of thy fauour, then true Noble Lord.</l>
      <l>To this my Orphane Muse, one looke afford.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>AND PRESIDENT, lest flattrie should bee deem'd,</l>
      <l>I scarce may sing the height, Thou art esteem'd:</l>
      <l>Euen from thy Birth, auspicuous Starres fore-tolde,</l>
      <l>That mongst the Best, thy Name should bee enrolde.</l>
      <l>The source of Vertue, who procures true peace.</l>
      <l>A third <hi>Licurgus,</hi> in this well-rul'd Greece:</l>
      <l>VVhom Learning doth endeare, and wisdome more,</l>
      <l>That <hi>Atlas-</hi>like, supportes our Senate glore:</l>
      <l>Then as thine honours, in thy merit shine,</l>
      <l>Vouchsafe (graue Lord) to fauour this propine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>AND yee the rest, Sage SENATOURS, who swey</l>
      <l>The course of Iustice, whome all doth obey.</l>
      <l>VVhose wisest censures, vindicates vnright,</l>
      <l>To you I bring this Mite, scarce worthie sight.</l>
      <l>Yee doe the cause, the person not respect,</l>
      <l>And simple Ones, from Proudlinges doe protect.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
The VViddow findes her Right, the Orphane sort,</l>
      <l>And VVeaklinges yee with Iustice doe comfort.</l>
      <l>Yee with euen handes <hi>Astraeas</hi> Ballance holde,</l>
      <l>Iudges of Right, and Lampes of Trueth enrolde,</l>
      <l>Long may yee liue, and flourish in that Seate,</l>
      <l>Patrones of Poore, and Pillars of the State:</l>
      <l>That Iustice, Law, Religion, Loue, and Peace,</l>
      <l>By your great meanes may in this Land encrease.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lo. most Afold and quotidian Oratour,
WILLIAM LITHGOW.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>