<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the right worshipfull and god∣lie Lady, the Lady Vrsula Walsingham, Wyfe to the ryght honorable Syr Fraunces Walsing∣ham Knight, chiefe Secretarie to the Queenes ex∣cellent Maiestie, and of her Graces most honorable priuie Counsayle, N. B. Minister of Christes Gospell in the Towne of Ridborne, wysheth blessed lyfe, with increase of true Godlinesse in Christ Iesu.</title>
           <author>Baxter, Nathaniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109621_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17683</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4432</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the right worshipfull and god∣lie Lady, the Lady Vrsula Walsingham, Wyfe to the ryght honorable Syr Fraunces Walsing∣ham Knight, chiefe Secretarie to the Queenes ex∣cellent Maiestie, and of her Graces most honorable priuie Counsayle, N. B. Minister of Christes Gospell in the Towne of Ridborne, wysheth blessed lyfe, with increase of true Godlinesse in Christ Iesu.</title>
                 <author>Baxter, Nathaniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lectures or daily sermons, of that reuerend diuine, D. Iohn Caluine, pastor of the Church of God in Geneua, vpon the prophet Ionas, by N.B. student in Diuinitie. Whereunto is annexed an excellent exposition of the two last epistles of S. Iohn, done in Latin by that worthy doctor, August. Marlorate, and englished by the same N.B</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 71, 1, 20 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="82"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="82"/>
   <head>
      <hi>❧To the right worshipfull and <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Lady, the Lady</hi> Vrsula <hi>Walsingham,</hi> Wyfe to the ryght honorable Syr Fraunces Walsing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Knight,</hi> chiefe Secretarie to the Queenes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie, and of her Graces most honorable priuie Counsayle, <hi>N. B.</hi> Minister of Christes Gospell in the Towne of <hi>Ridborne,</hi> wysheth blessed lyfe, with increase of true Godlinesse in Christ Iesu.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing finished these</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections of <hi>Augustin Marlorat,</hi> that reuerend Diuine vpon the two last Epistles of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> I haue attempted right Venerable Ladie, (according to my purpose, when I first tooke them in hande, though not greatlie knowne vnto you) to publish them in your name: being perswaded that they wyll so much the sooner of the godlie be read and wel liked, as they shalbe accepted of you, whose vertuous life deserueth no lesse commendations in this your countrey, then did that Ladies life to whome the Apostle directed these E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles. The volume I confesse is not great, but the matter therein contained is delectable,<note place="margin">Eras. lib. 4 Aroth. Aelian lib var. Hist.</note> and not disagreeable to your Ladishippes state and profession. <hi>Lisander</hi> king of <hi>Sparta</hi> tooke in good part the selie wrytings of the poore Poet <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lochus,</hi> hauing no better present to geue: <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> grat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie receyued the Greeke verses which a poore scholler of Greece gaue him. <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> thankfullie, and with great curtesie tooke a handful of water which a poore subiect of his, <hi>Sinaetes</hi> by name, gaue vnto him hauing none abilitie to geue any greater gifte. <hi>Alfonsus</hi> king of <hi>Arragon,</hi> louinglie embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as a great iuell, a small booke of the Decades of <hi>Liuie,</hi> geuē
<pb facs="83"/>
to him by <hi>Cosmus</hi> the Phisition. <hi>Ludouicus</hi> the Emperour ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully imbraced the bookes of <hi>Dionisius</hi> the <hi>Areopagit,</hi> which he wrote <hi>de Hierarchia:</hi> May it please you therfore right vertuous Ladie to accept also, these two Epistles of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> being expoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Caluin</hi> and others, and brought into one booke by <hi>Marlorat:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sigeber.</note> and geuen vnto you by me, not being such a gift as I would, but as presētly I could present vnto your Ladiship: &amp; to defend the same frō the venemous darts of sclāderous tōgues which are more readie to carpe then to correct, more prone to find fault with other mens works, then either to amend them, or to publish any thing of theirs. VVherein (Madam) you shall immitate the best sort of men in humanitie, and nothing degenerate from Gentilitie. And as it seeketh to be shrowded vnder your name, so vouchsafe to harbor, and shielde it. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that, a simple Sparowe sometime, to auoyde the griping talents of a tirannous Sparhauke, pursuing her, fledde for suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour vnto the bosome of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> king of <hi>Persea,</hi> being in campe, where she laye panting for feare of death, and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of flight, vnto whome the King sayde: As I wyl defende thee, thou lyttle sparrowe from death, because thou flyest to me for succor, so wyll I do to those that repose them selues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me. The lyke fauor, good Ladie, if this my booke maie finde at your handes, I haue the thing in this case that I desire: And I assure your Ladishippe that, <hi>Cum meliores nanciscantur Aues:</hi> VVhen more precious byrds be hatched, as sayd <hi>Zenod:</hi> I wyll not (God wylling) forgette that you disdayned not to grace so small a Pamphlet as this. God the fountaine of all goodnesse, graunt vnto your Ladishippe continuall loue to the Gospell, with perfect faith in Christ Iesu. From <hi>Ridborne</hi> this .26. of <hi>March.</hi> 1578.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶Your Ladyships in the Lorde Christ. <hi>Nath. Baxterus.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>