<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE HARBINGER to the Progres.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109799_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20620</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7023</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109799</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE HARBINGER to the Progres.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first anniuersarie : An anatomie of the vvorld. Wherein, by occasion of the vntimely death of Mistris Elizabeth Drury, the frailtie and the decay of this whole world is represented</title>
                 <author>Donne, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 54, 10, 49, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <head>THE HARBINGER to the Progres.</head>
   <l>TWo soules moue here, and mine (a third) must moue</l>
   <l>Paces of admiration, and of loue;</l>
   <l>Thy soule (Deare Virgin) whose this tribute is,</l>
   <l>Mou'd from this mortall sphere to liuely blisse;</l>
   <l>And yet moues still, and still aspires to see</l>
   <l>The worlds last day, thy glories full degree:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="36"/>Like as those starres which thou ore-lookest farre,</l>
   <l>Are in their place, and yet still moued are</l>
   <l>No soule (whiles with the lugage of this clay</l>
   <l>It clogged is) can follow thee halfe way;</l>
   <l>Or see thy flight; which doth our thoughts outgoe</l>
   <l>So fast, that now the lightning moues but slow:</l>
   <l>But now thou art as high in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen flowne</l>
   <l>As heau'ns from vs; what soule besides thine owne</l>
   <l>Can tell thy ioyes, or say he can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relate</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="36"/>Thy glorious Iournals in that bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed state?</l>
   <l>I enuie thee (Rich soule) I enuy thee,</l>
   <l>Although I cannot yet thy glory see:</l>
   <l>And thou (Great spirit) which her's follow'd hast</l>
   <l>So fast, as none can follow thine so fast;</l>
   <l>So farre as none can follow thine so farre,</l>
   <l>(And if this flesh did not the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage barre</l>
   <l>Had'st raught her) let me wonder at thy flight</l>
   <l>Which long agone had'st lost the vnlgar sight</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="37"/>And now mak'st proud the better eyes, that thay</l>
   <l>Can see thee less'ned in thine aery way;</l>
   <l>So while thou mak'st her soules by progresse knowne</l>
   <l>Thou mak'st a noble progresse of thine owne.</l>
   <l>From this worlds carcasse hauing mounted hie</l>
   <l>To that pure life of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie;</l>
   <l>Since thine aspiring thoughts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues so raise</l>
   <l>That more may not beseeme a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures praise,</l>
   <l>Yet still thou vow'st her more; and euery yeare</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="37"/>Mak'st a new progresse, while thou wandrest here;</l>
   <l>Still vpwards mount; and let thy makers praise</l>
   <l>Honor thy Laura, and adorne thy laies.</l>
   <l>And since thy Muse her head in heauen shrouds</l>
   <l>Oh let her neuer stoope below the clouds:</l>
   <l>And if those glorious sainted soules may know</l>
   <l>Or what we doe, or what we sing below,</l>
   <l>Those acts, those songs shall still content them best</l>
   <l>Which praise those awfull powers that make them blest.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>