<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Newton in Commen∣dation of this Booke.</title>
           <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109828_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68436</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17203</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109828</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Newton in Commen∣dation of this Booke.</title>
                 <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gallant, delectable and pleasaunt hystorie of Gerileon of Englande : containyng the haughtie feates of armes, and knightlie provvesse of the same Gerileon, with his loues and other memorable aduentures. Composed in the Frenche tongue, by Steuen De Maison Neufue Bordelois. And now newly translated into English</title>
                 <author>Maisonneufve, Estienne de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 <publisher>Jennings, Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jugge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 112 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Thomas Newton in Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>of this Booke.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Perfecte paterne of Renowmne, a type of Cheualrie,</l>
   <l>An haughtie harte, a breast y fraught with Magnanimitie,</l>
   <l>A Stage of state and stoute attemptes, a Theatre of Fame,</l>
   <l>With eche odde circumstaunce of praise, belongyng to the same,</l>
   <l>Who list and is dispos'de to see in colours trimly touched,</l>
   <l>Mate in this Booke be fully stor'de with furniture well couched.</l>
   <l>Whiche though the subiecte of the same, in feigned matters standes,</l>
   <l>With names of persōs, places, hilles, Moūts, Iles, seas, castles, lādes:</l>
   <l>Yet (doubtlesse) it affordeth stuffe, right pleasaunt, fitte and good,</l>
   <l>To traine the mindes of noble wightes, &amp; Impes of <hi>Mars</hi> his blood,</l>
   <l>By valiaunt ventures to atchieue exploites of passyng praise,</l>
   <l>Whereby their fame maie reache beyonde the date of mortall daies.</l>
   <l>Whiche is and aye hath béen the spurre, whiche moued hath the same.</l>
   <l>To passe the pikes through thicke &amp; thin, through fier, sworde &amp; flame.</l>
   <l>To whiche effecte this worthie woorke, now lately taught hath bin,</l>
   <l>(Inuested erste in Frenche attyre) an Englishe threede to spinne,</l>
   <l>For verie loue to Natiue soile: to moue vs Englishemen,</l>
   <l>To trace the steppes of vertues lore, and rouze out of our denne</l>
   <l>And Cradle of Securitie, wherein wee lulled are,</l>
   <l>As men of Englishe prowesse earst, not takyng any care.</l>
   <l>In lieu of paines, the onely see that craued is of thée,</l>
   <l>Is that thou wouldst iudge of the same with singlenesse of eye,</l>
   <l>And freendly make reporte thereof: so shalt thou haue the reste,</l>
   <l>Of stoute <hi>Gerileons</hi> glorious actes hereafter more exprest.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Newton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>