<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST worthily honoured, and ver∣tuous beautified Lady, the Ladie Anne Glemnham, wife to the most noble, magnanimious, and woorthy Knight, Sir Henry Glemnham. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Olney, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109750_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06630</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17091</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109750</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST worthily honoured, and ver∣tuous beautified Lady, the Ladie Anne Glemnham, wife to the most noble, magnanimious, and woorthy Knight, Sir Henry Glemnham. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Olney, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diella : certaine sonnets, adioyned to the amorous poeme of Dom Diego and Gineura. By R.L. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Linche, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Olney, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST worthily honoured, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous beautified Lady, the Ladie <hi>Anne Glemnham,</hi> wife to the most noble, magnanimious, and woorthy Knight, Sir <hi>Henry Glemnham. &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, your many honourable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, hauing tyed mee to your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall seruice, to shevve some part of my dutie, I present your Ladiship with a fewe passionate Sonnets, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled
<pb facs="3"/>
vvith the loues of <hi>Dom Diego</hi> and <hi>Gineura.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Daine (gentle Lady) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them, and therein shew the greatnesse of your benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, in receiuing curteouslie a gift of so smal worth, which though it cannot any wayes equall eyther the number of your vertues, or the greatnes of that noble house, whence your Ladiship is discended, impute it not (Madam) to my defect of iudgement, but of Fortune, for were I furnished with the greatest riches that
<pb facs="3"/>
blind Goddesse could bestow on a man of my state, both they, and I woulde fall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate at your feete, and euer rest at your Ladiships deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet Madam as it is, it is a chylde of the Muses, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worthy to be cherrished, conceiued in the braine of a gallant Gentleman, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be fauoured: sent into the worlde by mee, who haue euer honoured your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp, and therefore craue of your Ladiship to bee protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="4"/>
to whom I euer vvishe long life, lengthened with all honorable happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships in all dutie, <hi>Henry Olney.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>