<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE APPROOVED, right valorous, and woorthy Knight, Sir Walter Ralegh, Lord Warden of the Stanneries, Captaine of her Maiesties Guard and her Highnesse Lieutenant general of the Countie of Cornwall.</title>
           <author>Kemys, Law.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109262_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04813</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14947</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109262</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE APPROOVED, right valorous, and woorthy Knight, Sir Walter Ralegh, Lord Warden of the Stanneries, Captaine of her Maiesties Guard and her Highnesse Lieutenant general of the Countie of Cornwall.</title>
                 <author>Kemys, Law.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A relation of the second voyage to Guiana. Perfourmed and written in the yeare 1596. By Lawrence Kemys, Gent</title>
                 <author>Kemys, Lawrence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE APPROOVED, right valorous, and woorthy Knight, Sir Walter Ralegh,</hi> Lord Warden of the Stanneries, Captaine of her Maiesties Guard and her Highnesse Lieutenant general of the Countie of Cornwall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue heere brieflie set downe the effect of this your second Discouerie, without anie enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of made wordes: for in this argument, sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle speech best besemeth a simple truth. Where the affinity of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with your person, leadeth me to write of your selfe, vnto your selfe: that small libertie which I haue therein vsed, shall, I doubt not, without offence, or sinister construction, be giuen to the cause in hand: which whether it suffer not detriment, by attributing lesse, then of right belongeth: the iudgement be theirs, that vprightly and indifferentlie shall weigh
<pb facs="3"/>
the consequentes of their euill purpose, who in seeking to detract from the Authour of these Discoueries, do so much as in them ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, wound, deface, and treade vnder foot the thing it selfe. But this is no noueltie, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only to these our dayes. For long since it hath bene said.<note place="margin">Pericles.</note>
      <hi>Laudes eo vsque sunt tolerabiles, donec ea dicuntur, quae auditores se quoque facere posse existi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant: si maiora proferantur: Inuident, non credunt.</hi> The feruent zeale and loyaltie of your mind in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with this birth of so honourable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, as it hath deserued a recompence farre different so needeth it not my poore suffrage to endeare the toyle, care, and daunger, that you haue willinglie vndergone for the good and aduauncement of our weale publique. The praise-worthines therof doth approoue it selfe, &amp; is better read in your liuing doinges, then in my dead vnregarded papers. All that I can wish, is that my life were a sufficient pledge, to iustifie, how much more easie, and more material, the course for the <hi>Guiana</hi> wold be thē others: which requiring greater charge, yeeld not so large benefit, and are subiect to
<pb facs="3"/>
more doubtful euents. If vnto their wisdoms, who sit in place and authoritie, it shal appeare otherwise, and that in following of other at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts there is lesse difficultie, certainer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, &amp; needfuller offence vnto the enemie: the cost and trauaile, which you haue bestowed, shall not, I hope, bee altogether lost: if vnto your Honour, I can well prooue, how, and where the amendes is to be had, maugre the force and preuention of all Spaniardes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships to be commanded</hi> in all seruice: Law: Kemys.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>