<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The copie of the Kynges Maiesties most grati∣ous priuiledge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109663_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02432</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12564</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109663</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The copie of the Kynges Maiesties most grati∣ous priuiledge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A consultorie for all Christians : Most godly and ernestly warnyng al people, to beware least they beare the name of christians in vayne. Now first imprinted, the. xxx day of Ianuarie</title>
                 <author>Hart, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oswen, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Worcester</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶The copie of the Kynges Maiesties most grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous priuiledge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Dwarde the sixt by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, Fraunce and Irelande, defender of the faith, and of the churche of England, and also of Ireland, in earth the supreme head. To all maner of Printers, boke sellers, and other our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, ministers and subiectes, gretyng: We late you were, that of our especial grace, we renderyng the godly edifiyng and ease of our louyng subiectes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Principalitie of Wales, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the same, by thaduise and cōsent of our most dere vncle Edwarde Duke of Somerset, Gouernour of our person, and Protectòur of all our realmes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and subiectes, and other our counsailours, haue graunted and geuen priuiledge and licence, and by thies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentes doo graunt and geue priuiledge and lycence, vnto our welbeloued sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect Iohn Oswen, of our citie of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceter
<pb facs="3"/>
Printer, and to his factours and assignes, to print, reprint, vtter and sell, or cause to be printed, reprinted, vttered, and solde, so many of euery kynde of boke or bokes, whiche haue or shalbe set forth by vs, by thaduise aforesaid, for ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to be vsed in our Churches, miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of Sacramentes, and instructiō of our said subiectes, as shall onely suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fise for the Churches and our subiectes within our said Principalitie and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, any other licence or priuiledge to the contrary in any wise notw<seg rend="sup">t</seg>standing.</p>
   <p>AND also, of our especiall grace by thaduise and consent aforesaid, we haue graunted and geuen priuiledge and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and by thies presentes do graunt and geue priuilege and licence, vnto the saide Iohn Oswen, and to his factours and assignes, to print, vtter and sell, or cause to be printed, vttered and sold, to all person and persons of whatsoeuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, degree, or condition they be, al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bokes conteinyng any storye or exposition of Gods holy scripture, or of any part thereof, beyng not contrary or against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, which at any time hereto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue bene, or hereafter shalbe made
<pb facs="3"/>
translated or cōpiled, by the same Iohn Oswen, or by his meanes, instigatiō, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie or procuremēt, and at his costes &amp; charges, of whatsoeuer qualitie or sort the saide bokes or any of thē shalbe, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the true copies of euery suche bokes be first diligently seen, perused and alowed, by suche person or persons as we shall frō time to time therunto assigne and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, before they be put to any sale or vtteraunce. And further our minde and pleasure is, &amp; by thies presentes we doo straightly charge &amp; inhibite, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons of whatsoeuer estate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or cōdition he or they be, do at any time hereafter print, or reprint, or cause to be printed or reprinted priuely or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly any of the bokes aforesaid, or any parte or parcell of thē, duryng the space of .vii. yeres, next after the printing or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printyng of the same bokes by the sayde Iohn Oswen, his factours or assignes: so that the same Iohn his factours &amp; as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, shall and may haue the profitte &amp; aduauntage cōmyng &amp; growyng of the printyng and reprintyng of suche bokes in recōpence &amp; alleinatiō of his industry paines &amp; charges in that behalfe to bee
<pb facs="4"/>
susteined. Wherfore we wil &amp; straightly charge &amp; cōmaund al &amp; singuler our sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, aswel printers &amp; bokesellers, as al other persons within al our dominions, that thei or any of thē do not presume to print vtter or sell, or cause to be printed vttered or solde within any our domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, any of the bokes aforesaid, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Iohn made cōpiled, or translated, or any parcell of thē contrary to the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of this our present lycēce &amp; priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, vpō pain that euery offēder therin shal forfait to our vse al suche bokes and euery of thē, where soeuer they shall bee foūd. Willyng therfore &amp; cōmaundyng all our officers ministers &amp; subiectes as they tēdre our fauour &amp; will auoide our high indignatiō, that they &amp; euery of thē if nede shal require, do aide &amp; assist y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Iohn Oswen his factours &amp; assignes in the due exercisyng &amp; executiō of this our presēt <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ēce &amp; priuiledge with effect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the true meanyng of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. In witnes wherof we haue caused these our letters to be made patentes. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our self, at Westminster the sixt day of Ianuary, the seconde yere of our Reigne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>