<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Earle of Port∣land, Lord Treasurer; on the mariage of his Sonne.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109308_Bo1_17</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19878</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6304</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Earle of Port∣land, Lord Treasurer; on the mariage of his Sonne.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Madagascar : with other poems. By W. Davenant</title>
                 <author>D'Avenant, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walkley, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 141, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="71" facs="45"/>
   <head>To the Earle of Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Lord Treasurer; on the mariage of his Sonne.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>MY Lord, this Night is yours! each wandring Star</l>
      <l>That was nnbusi'd, and irregular;</l>
      <l>Most gravely now, his bright Companion leads,</l>
      <l>To fix o're your glad Roofe, their shining Heads.</l>
      <l>And it is sayd, th'exemplar King's your guest;</l>
      <l>And that the rich-Ey'd-Darling of his Breast,</l>
      <l>(To ripen all your Joyes) will there become</l>
      <l>The Musick, Odor, Light, of ev'ry Roome!</l>
      <l>A mixture of two noble bloods, in all</l>
      <l>Faith, and domestick nature, union call,</l>
      <l>No trava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l'd Eyes have seene, with humbler state</l>
      <l>Of love perform'd, where Princes celebrate.</l>
      <l>This when I heard; I know not what bold Starre</l>
      <l>My Spirits urg'd, but it was easier farre</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="72" facs="46"/>The torne, the injur'd <hi>Panther,</hi> to restraine</l>
      <l>In's hot pursuit, or stroke him coole againe;</l>
      <l>To tell the cause, why Winds doe disagree,</l>
      <l>Divide them when in Stormes they mingled be;</l>
      <l>Strait fix them single, where they breath'd before;</l>
      <l>Or fanne them with a Plume, from Sea to Shore;</l>
      <l>Than bind my raging Temples, or resist</l>
      <l>The pow'r that swell'd me, as <hi>Apollo's</hi> Priest.</l>
      <l>Therefore my Robe, that on his Altar lay,</l>
      <l>My Virge, my Wreath, I tooke; and thus did pray:</l>
      <l>That you (my Lord) with lasting memory,</l>
      <l>And strength of fervent youth, may live to see,</l>
      <l>Your name in this blest nuptiall store the Earth,</l>
      <l>With such a masculine, and knowing birth;</l>
      <l>As shall at factious Councells moderate,</l>
      <l>And force injurious Armies to their fate.</l>
      <l>Let Time be fetter'd, that they never may</l>
      <l>Increasing others, feele themselves decay.</l>
      <l>To you (my Lord) who with wise industrie,</l>
      <l>Seeke Virtue out, then give it strength to be;</l>
      <l>Where ere you shall recide, let Plenty bring,</l>
      <l>The pride, and expectations of the Spring;</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="73" facs="46"/>The wealth that loads inticing Autumne grow</l>
      <l>Within your reach; let hasty Rivers flow</l>
      <l>'Till on your shores, they skaly Tribute pay,</l>
      <l>Then ebbe themselves in empty Waves away:</l>
      <l>Let each pale Flow'r, that springeth there, have pow'r</l>
      <l>T'invite a Sunne-beame, and command a Show'r;</l>
      <l>The dew that falls about you taste of Wine,</l>
      <l>Each abject Weed change root, and be a Vine!</l>
      <l>But I with this prophetick plenty grow</l>
      <l>Already rich, and proud; 'cause then I know</l>
      <l>The Poets of this Isle, in Vineyards may</l>
      <l>Rejoyce, whilst others thirst in groves of Bay!</l>
      <l>Sir, let me not your wary patience move;</l>
      <l>And sinne, with too much courage of my love!</l>
      <l>He that in strength of wishes, next shall trie,</l>
      <l>T'increase your blessings with his Poesie,</l>
      <l>May shew a fiercer Wit, and cleaner Art,</l>
      <l>But not a more sincere, and eager Heart.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>