<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull Sir James Scudamore,
Knight.</title>
           <author>Phillip, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109348_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05051</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15193</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109348</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull Sir James Scudamore,
Knight.</title>
                 <author>Phillip, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The description of a voyage made by certaine ships of Holland into the East Indies : VVith their aduentures and successe: together with the description of the countries, townes, and inhabitantes of the same: who set forth on the second of Aprill 1595. and returned on the 14. of August. 1597. Translated out of Dutch into English by W.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull Sir <hi>James Scudamore,
Knight.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull, this small trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (written in Dutch,
shewing a late voyage performed by certain <hi>Hollanders</hi> to the
Islandes of <hi>Iaua,</hi> part of the East <hi>Indies</hi>) falling into
my handes, and in my iudgement deseruing no lesse commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then
those of our Countrey men, (as Captaine <hi>Raimond</hi> in the
<hi>Penelope,</hi> Maister <hi>Foxcroft</hi> in the <hi>Marchant Royall,</hi>
and M. <hi>Iames Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> in the <hi>Edward Bonauenture,</hi> vnto the
said East <hi>Indies,</hi> by the Cape <hi>de Bona Sperance,</hi> in
<hi>Anno 1591.</hi> as also M. <hi>Iohn Newbery,</hi> and <hi>Raphael
Fich</hi> ouer land through <hi>Siria</hi> from <hi>Aleppo</hi> vnto
<hi>Ormus</hi> and <hi>Goa,</hi> and by the said <hi>Rapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Fich</hi>
himselfe to <hi>Bengala, Malacca, Pegu,</hi> and other places in <hi>Anno
1583.</hi> as at large appeareth in a booke written by M. <hi>Richard
Haclute</hi> a Gentleman very studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous therein, &amp; entituled the
English voyages) I thought it not vnconuenient to translate the same into
our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, thereby to procure more light and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to such
as are desirous to trauell those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, for the common wealth and
commoditie of this Realme and themselues. And knowing that all men are 
<pb facs="3"/> not like affected, I was so bold to shrowd it vnder your
worships protection, as being assured of your good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposition to
the fauouring of trauell and trauellers, (and whereby it hath pleased God to
aduance you to that honourable title, which at this present you beare) and
so not fitter for the protection of any then your selfe: and as a poore
friend wishing all happines and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in all your valiant actions.
Which if it please your worshippe to like and accept, it may procure the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in a more large and ample discourse of an East
<hi>Indian</hi> voyage, lately performed and set forth by one <hi>Iohn
Hughen</hi> of <hi>Linschoten,</hi> to your further delight. Wherewith
crauing your fauor, &amp; beseeching God to blesse your worship, with
my good Ladie your wife, I most humbly take my leaue:</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>This 16. of <hi>Ianuarie.
1597.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships to commaunde <hi>W.
Phillip.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>