<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Proheme to the Readers of
thys Table.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109324_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109324</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Proheme to the Readers of
thys Table.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and learned vvoorke of chirurgerie, called Chirurgia parua Lanfranci : Lanfranke of Mylayne his briefe: reduced from dyuers translations to our vulgar or vsuall frase, and now first published in the Englyshe prynte by Iohn Halle chirurgien. Who hath thervnto necessarily annexed. A table, as wel of the names of diseases and simples with their vertues, as also of all other termes of the arte opened. ... And in the ende a compendious worke of anatomie ... An historiall expostulation also against the beastly abusers, both of chyrurgerie and phisicke in our tyme: with a goodly doctrine, and instruction, necessary to be marked and folowed of all true chirurgie [n] s. All these faithfully gathered, and diligently set forth, by the sayde Iohn Halle</title>
                 <author>Lanfranco, of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 73, 23, 143, 25, 96, 64 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="59"/>
   <head>A Proheme to the Readers of
thys Table.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe it hathe bene the vse</hi>
of authores, to declare in the ende of
their bookes, suche strange termes
and darke wordes, as maye seme to
some obscure: I thinke it should not
be nedefull alwaye so to doe, but
that there is such slacknesse in men,
and negligence to learne, that they
remaine as vnperfecte as a dull boye: who for lacke of capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citye
coulde neuer procede farther then his crosse rowe.</p>
   <p>Alasse is it not necessarye that we growe from strength to
strength, till we come to a full perfection? Whye shoulde
we perswade oure selues, to stande at that staye, with that
secte of Phisiciens, whiche haue called them selues <hi>Empiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos,</hi>
or as we call them practisers: not because they helpe
their arte firste grounded on learninge and reason, by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctisinge
of anye newe thinge them selues: but because they
onlye obserue that whiche they haue seene others doe, be it
neuer so base or slender, wythoute anye farther considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
euen as some also at this daye thinke one salue suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente
for all sores, or with one water to heale or cure all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases,
whiche is as possible, as one shoe to serue iustlye eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
mannes foote. Or should we not rather solow the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
secte named <hi>Dogmatici:</hi> sekinge still for learninge, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe
the same by reason, till we haue perfecte knowledge?
And what is more cōducible to perfection, then the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of symples, with their names and natures: in suche
wise that knowinge the nature of the infirmity, there may
therby, throughe naturall reason, (ye thoughe there were
no practice,) be procured a spedy remedye? Oh that euer we
shoulde call oure selues men of science, and yet as thoughe
there were no science, we be ignorant of those thinges that
we shoulde chieflye knowe, beinge planted amongest vs.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="60"/>
In this case we are lyke the cocke, that Esope speaketh
of, whiche in a dunge heape found a precious stone, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
wondering therat, wished rather for a barlye corne, to
satisfy his hunger: what is a man the better for a Jewel, of
the whiche he vnderstandeth not the vertue, nor knoweth
the value? Let vs therfore endeuour oure selues to knowe
the symples, specially herbes, wyth theyr vertues, that we
nede not seke for strange drouges, of farre countryes: For
trulye I thinke, nature here in our naturall country hath
not broughte vs forthe, leauing vs destitute of necessarye
medicines to helpe our diseases, but rather hathe created
here amongest vs, more apt thinges for oure bodyes, then
strange drouges fet so far frō strange nations: whiche erre
they come here, haue susteined so many wethers, &amp; abidē so
many markets, that they are through age withred to dust.
Therfore, as in this litle booke of Lanfranke, there be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
medicynes, to cure diseases wyth small composity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and light cost, and that chieflye with symples: so for the
necessarye knowledge of the natures and names of those
symples, I haue made this table, after the order of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phebet,
that anye suche as shall happen to be doubted of,
may easily be found: so that consideringe the natures of the
symples, naturall reason may perswade the mynde, of the
noble and assured vertues of the medicines. For the good
Chirurgien knoweth by the natures of the symples, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
it stand with reason, the medicyne to cure the disease
it was ordeined for or not: therfore, amonge all other, it is
a moste laudable studye, to knowe the natures of symples.
And in this worke ye shall perceiue that (in diuers thinges)
I differ from the common opinion, whiche manye tymes
erroniously vseth one thyng for an other: euen as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries
also (for lacke of knowledge) do oftē sell one thing
for an other: as by occasion in this table, ye shall fynde the
same by the truthe confuted.</p>
   <p>For thoughe some may note it a kinde of presumption,
to vary from the common opinion: yet may I answer with
<pb facs="60"/>
Aristotle, that Plato is my frend and so is Socrates, but
the truthe before them bothe. And as mine opinion agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
wyth the truthe, I wishe it onlye accepted, and where
it will not stand wyth reason and truthe, to be reiected as
an vntruthe, and a thing not worthy of credite.</p>
   <p>For as Plato that diuine Philosopher saythe: if men in
resoning, as muche desired the truthe of the thinge it selfe,
as they do the maintenance of their own opinions, &amp; glory
of their wittes, there should not brede so muche hatred as
ther dothe, nor halfe so many matters be left vnconcluded.
And as semeth to me this worthy sentence of good Doctor
Recorde, (in the .iiii. boke of his castell of knowledge, in the
129. page), may serue well in the lyke sence.</p>
   <p>Often haue I redde in Galen (saithe he,) and more often
haue I sene it by experience, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> better it is for men to want
all arte of reasoninge cleane, then to haue suche confidence
in a meane knowledge thereof, as maye cause them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
them selues, and to seduce other. As truthe therfore
wyth reason will approue these iudgementes, I only wish
them to be credited of the studious reader, and otherwyse
not. For as I woulde gladlye my selfe embrace the moste
truthe, so wold I desire my doinges to be considered wyth
moste true authores, without partialitye.</p>
   <p>But seinge I haue moued here, the studye concernynge
the knowledge of herbes, I thinke it good to remember,
the scornynge ignorance of some, whiche because they are
not experte in the knowledge of symples, scorne the dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
of all other that trauell therin: as thoughe it were a
thynge wythoute frute or profyte, thinkinge therby to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
their neglygence, whyle they vpbraide with opprobry
the diligence of other men.</p>
   <p>For as (in the yeare of oure Lord a thousande fyue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
fifty and seuen,) I came throughe Bucklersbury: loe
a certaine woman came to sell hearbes, to the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes:
and asked if they woulde buye mayden heare. And
they desieringe to see it, she shewed to them an herbe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="61"/>
Nothinge agreinge with that whiche she named: But only
that it had rounde leaues, standinge in good order on eche
syde the stalke, as maiden heare hathe: but it had little flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res
like belles, somwhat redishe, mixed with whyte, with a
grene stalke, and thicke leues full of iuse: and in all poyntes
moste agreinge in likenesse to <hi>Nummularia,</hi> otherwise called
<hi>Centum Morbia,</hi> and in Englishe two peny grasse: sauing that
it was manye partes lesse, and almoste as small in deede as
<hi>Trichomanes,</hi> whiche we call in Englishe mayden heare.</p>
   <p>Because I neuer saw it before, I toke a small part therof,
&amp; bare it wyth me, if haply I might meete with anye, that
knewe it, and so to attaine the name therof. And truly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that houre were fullye at an ende, I fortuned (through
the societye of my reuerende frende master Gale Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gien
of London,) to come into the company of a Phisicien a
stranger borne: whome (after diuers communications,) I
desired to shew me his opinion of that herbe: which when
he had well vewed and also tasted, he answered, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he knew
it not. And because he estemed it a dishonor vnto him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute
some excuse or cauilation, he sayde it made no matter
to be so precise in the knowledge of herbes: for said he, what
nede I occupye manye herbes in a medicine, whereas one
wil serue? or what nede I confecte together <hi>Solanum, Papauer,
Hiosiamus, Mandragora,</hi> and <hi>Lactuca,</hi> when only <hi>Hiosiamus,</hi> or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<hi>Papauer</hi> wil serue my turne? vnto whome I thus answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
Sir (vnder your correction) I graunt it to be true, that
manye symples nede not be put together, where one wyll
serue the turne, and affirme farthermore that it ought not:
for as muche as Galen hym selfe geueth counsell neuer to
vse compoundes, where symples wyll serue. But how shall
I knowe that <hi>Mandragora</hi> will serue the turne of <hi>Papauer,</hi> or
<hi>Lactuca</hi> of <hi>Solanum,</hi> or <hi>Hiosiamus</hi> of any of them, if I first know
them not all? dothe not diuers regions bringe forthe diuers
herbes, accordinge to the diuersities of soyles, and natures
of heauenly climates? some place bringeth forthe <hi>Hiosiamum</hi>
and none of the other that ye named: and an other place, an
<pb facs="61"/>
other, without the rest. If nowe I know not the natures of
all, I shall sometime thinke that it is vnpossible to doe a
thinge, because I lacke there mine olde practise. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.
I would doe it with <hi>Malua,</hi> and none groweth there:
wheras yet the earthe bringeth forth herbes of the same
nature in an other forme: whiche neuerthelesse serueth not
my want, and that because I know them not. Wherfore I
conclude, that althoughe diseases may be cured with neuer
so few, yet is it necessary to know them all. And though
he coulde not denye this, yet he fell in rebukinge of Uigo,
because in his medicines he vseth suche greate composity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and saide plainlye that Uigo in that poynt was a foole:
so grossly master doctor termed him. But I perceiue what
procured master Phissicien to be offended wyth Uigo, he
playeth the Phisicien so muche in all his workes: for in the
moste parte of diseases that he wryteth of, he describeth an
order of life, and also purgation, to take away the originall
cause: Happye was he, that he dwelte amongst the Phisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens
of Rome and Italye: for if he had dwelte in this region,
he must not haue put his owne knowledge in vse, but haue
lefte that to oure doctores. Well the time woulde not then
serue vs anye more to reson, but here will I saye some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
in Uigo his defence. Whereas ye call Uigo foole,
because of his greate compositions &amp; costlye medicynes, I
answer. Then was Galen also a foole, so was Auicen and
Mesues, with diuers other, who deuised the greate compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions
of <hi>Theriaca</hi> and <hi>Mithridatium:</hi> which (for all your wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)
in your moste weighty affaires ye are constreigned
to vse, for your gaine and worship. Or whye maye not any
man put in wrytinge a greate composition, wherin he hath
founde vtility, that other after him maye doe the like by his
example? But if anye man can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oe the like, with anye one
or two, the symples chosen out of so many: what hinderāce
is the composition to the symple medicine? But I saye, that
in the moste parte of medicines, ye muste of necessitye vse
compositions, for otherwise trulye the wisest maye fortune
<pb facs="62"/>
to erre and worke folishly, and that specially in inward me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines,
namelye purgations: for as Mesues saith, ther is no
symple purginge medicine that can be taken, that leaueth
not behinde it some hurte in the body. For the which cause,
it is necessarye to compose wyth them, such thinges as haue
power to defende the body from the said hurtes, by qualify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
the hurtfull proprety of the medicyne.</p>
   <p>It may please you therfore, to leaue your blamyinge of
Uigo: or elsse if his doinges like you not, set your pen to the
booke, and make a more perfecte woorke: So shall the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> geue you thankes. Otherwise we must necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
iudge, that ye speake suche vprobrious wordes against
Uigo, out of the mouth of enuye.</p>
   <p>In the meane season, Jexhort all my brethren Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giens,
that they (after due trauels taken in the former par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes)
moste diligently studye, the knowledge of symples and
the natures of them, from the most to the least, so shall you
haue perfect knowledge how to worke: whether it be with
symples or compoundes, many or fewe.</p>
   <p>For though Diogines threwe away his drinking dishe
as a superfluous thinge, when he sawe an other poore man
drinke in his bare hande, yet is it not euell a man to haue in
hys house pottes and glasses, yea goblets of siluer &amp; cuppes
of gould: for his hand is neuer the farther from him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
he may drinke if he lift, or when nede constreigneth him,
for lacke of an other vessell. What if Diogenes had seene a
man lye alonge by a riuer side, drinking of the water onlye
wyth his mouth as dothe a beast, woulde he also (trowe ye)
haue throwne awaye hys hande?</p>
   <p>The laborynge man, the poore ploughe man, lyueth as
long in good health, wyth martelmasse beffe, bakon, home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
cheese, course breade and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hin drynke: as the richest noble
man, withall his deintye fare he can deuise. Is it necessarye
that prynces and noble men therfore, shallbe driuen to that
fare, because pore men can so liue? There are diuers barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
nacions of people, that liue only with herbes &amp; rootes,
<pb facs="62"/>
is it necessarye therfore, that we shall leaue oure fleshe, and
fish, and holsome bread? It is an olde sayinge, that store is no
sore, and plēty no deinty. Is it not better to know so much,
that I may take and leaue, then to know so litle, that I shal
many times lacke?</p>
   <p>Hinder not the diligent mindes therfore, of such as wold
learne: for though some thinke it a thinge vnmete for theyr
age to learne, yet wherfore shuld they discourage yoūg mē,
for whose estate and age, it is most meete to seke for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?
For whyche cause Aristotle councelled men in theyr
youthe to learne, ye (saythe he) allthough it be painfull for it
is lesse peyne for a man to learne in hys youthe, then in age
to be vncunninge.</p>
   <p>Oh worthy saying. Thys sentence of Aristotle, I wish ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to be weyed and folowed, then that any mannes minde
should be remoued from study and diligence to learne, with
fonde perswasions. Some will saye, I am an olde man, and
haue done great cures, and neuer knewe so muche: and my
master before me was an auncient man, and was neuer so
curious.</p>
   <p>Surely science at some time florisheth, whych in time to
come is darkened againe by ignorance: so that time maketh
all thinges old, and after bringeth forth that olde thynges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
causing them to be called newe.</p>
   <p>The frutefull bookes of <hi>Dioscorides, Hippocrates, Galen,</hi> and
<hi>Plini,</hi> are olde and auncient thinges: ye they were counted so
old, that some of them wyth most men were worne oute of
minde, and the goodly doctrines also conteined in them. Yet
time bringing forthe the same thinges againe in other men,
they are called new lerning, ye of some newe fāgles: though
it be the very same auncient thinges, &amp; no thing elsse. Such
an enemy vnto knowledge is ignorance, euermore murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
and grudging therat, with hainous reproche.</p>
   <p>Therfore let all men, that minde to haue perfection of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
good science, arme them selues with patience and constā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
and regard not such vaine iangling: but goe forth to your
<pb facs="63"/>
businesse, not caring for their bablinge, euen as you may see
the very great and stout horsses, shewing the like example:
which passe forth on their way, not once regarding the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
of curres, nor shewing anye token of reuengment: for
euen suche iangling wil time weare and wast, and consume
also suche enuious disdaine. Accept my good will therfore I
moste hartelye desyre you, all ye that loue, to learne: for as I
loke at your handes to finde good report and loue (whych is
the frute of a good gentle inclination: (so I loke at the hands
of the enuious ignorant for none other, but the frutes
of theyr beastly nature. So that in fyne it semeth
that of them I may thus iustly conclude.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>LIke as the flye, that fedeth styll,</l>
      <l>In vile corrupte degre:</l>
      <l>Dothe still despise and hate as ill,</l>
      <l>All herbes that holsome be.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And as the man, whose trade was aye:</l>
      <l>To scoure the fylthye gonge,</l>
      <l>Of spicers shoppes was wonte to saye:</l>
      <l>They stinked very stronge.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Or as the swynes filthye desyre:</l>
      <l>Dothe flee eche holsome place,</l>
      <l>And for to walow in the myre,</l>
      <l>More gladlye dothe embrace.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>In wicked men so wickednes,</l>
      <l>Wil alway haue a sway:</l>
      <l>Dispraising still, throughe hatefulnesse,</l>
      <l>Eche good and perfect way.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>Fare ye well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>