<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1537</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109793_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03856</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13970</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109793</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The enquirie and verdite of the quest panneld of the death of Richard Hune wich was founde hanged in Lolars tower</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Peetersen van Middelburch, Heyndrik</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1537</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O see (moost deare Reader) how suttellie the trueth is euer persequuted might seame grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te woonder / but that the holie goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste hath oft tymes shewed and testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scripture that hit shuld so be. What kynd of persequucion hath bene vnproued? what can be imagined that hathe not hitherto bene prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisede concerning soche thynges? In some places they heede &amp; afterward burne / in some places they bringe straighte wayse to the fyre. When that shift will not serue / or y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they dare not hurte the person liuyng by cause of his riches or power &amp;c. yet wyll they burne him after he died peasablie in his bed / as they dide Wicleffe &amp; Tracie with other / to kepe the symple innocent sowles wich they haue made blyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de still to continewe in darknes / sayyng / he was an heretique who so euer kepe his opiniōs shalbe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lyuyng / and so the burning of that which feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te no paine is a greate feare to the ignoraunt that seith hit.</p>
   <p>Some be cause they be wyse and vtter the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisye and abhominable lyuing of whorehunters with discrete communicacion / so that no man can gayne saye or accuse them but they say trweth be brought in to presone and heresies fained oute of hande that be sparppled abrode to the people with all the apparence of veritie that can be diuised to persuade them that the parties be not presoned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deserued / wich if they wyll not confesse and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to be openlie abiured to theyre greate shame
<pb facs="3"/> theire neckes be broken or elles they be some other wise conueyde / and after hanged vp / and than saide and preached to that they hanged them sealues / as was this Hune / wich to be trewe thou shal easelie perceaue by the enquirie and verdite of the queest here in this litell treatise conteyned. yf they be poo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and want frendes and no euident cause founde wherfore they shuld suffre / then die they in presone no man knowith howe / hit is straight waise saide if any man axe of them that they died of one disease or other and no mooe woordes ar made. yf a man knowyng theyre malicyouse hertes get hym fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from daunger in to some other realme / wich haplie is to circumspect to be taken by any commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne officer or knowen enemie / straighte waye cause they one or other for money to play Iudas part and to make him sealf greate with the partie / &amp; as thow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe he fauored him singularlie to make moche on hym tyll he see his tyme &amp; than betray him / as they haue euen now played with William Tyndal a man of synguler vertuousnes and of no lesse lernyng and iugement in scripture and of a rare gentillnes of cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicions as all they can testyfie that knewe him and vsed familiaritie with him. Summa to kepe vp the Kyngdome of fornicatours and aduowtrers that they may liue in all pleasure and ydelnes / seruyng theyre belies onelie and lyuing more viciouslie than euer did the hethen / &amp; for the enstablishement ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to thrust downe vertuouse lyuyng and trew prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng hath no sotteltie bene vnsought for / nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne shalbe I feare me of theyre parties / vntyll they be yet brought lower / I speake of the bad / for the good as they haue in euerie place for the moost part
<pb facs="3"/> to litell so can they not haue to moche. Thus seist thou theire practise before this tyme vsed how they haue with all sottelltie persequuted them that of good zeale and loue haue frelie spoken the trueth / and how they haue hyd and clocked that they dyd with the apparence of holines / as thowghe they had done hit to extinct heresies / for so made they the people to beleue. Other frutes haue they hither to not brought forth. So long space violentlie to haue subdued goddes holie woord weere as me semyth to moche and the tyme now counuenient with hast to reforme them sealues and to prepare theire hartes louynglye to receaue the woorde of theire sowles health and wyllynglie to distribute hit to the sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignoraunte people / euerye man accordyng to his gift / yet se I not that they be any thing wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng therunto but rather in mynde to rage moare then they did before.</p>
   <p>The light is now broken forth (thankes be to the Lorde) mager theire beardes / and they brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght in no small feare of sodaine ruine of theire kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gdome / yet by cause they se the world hath not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forsaken theire deceyuable doctrine in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / they hope of a chaunge / and haue theire secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conspirisies deuised with all sutteltie to bryng that to pas / the good they do they do by compulsion and for feare of losyng theire possessions / hitherto is there no sygne of repentaunce taken in herte for theire abhominacions so long vsed. Styll lyue they as they did before / they ar no les desirouse of promo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion / no les delited in bely Ioye / in wealfaring / in gorgiouse rayment / as readie to abhorre chast matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monye and daylie to commit whordome and aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie
<pb facs="4"/>
/ as lothe to do the busines wich they ar onelie bound to as euer they weere / I meane to preache with synceritie goddes wholie woorde and that for loue and zeale that they haue to se christen lyuing florisshe and not for the fylthie lukres sake. They stand but at a stay tyll they may fynd by one mean is or other awaye to bryng in theyre olde accostomed vices to be counted holines / as they in tymes past haue made the world to beleue. They do but disseam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble in vtwarde apperaunce / in hert they be infect w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> theyre accostomed traterie / euer readie when occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on shalbe geuen to playe theyre partes a thowsand tymes moare tyranniouslie than euer they did. So leaue they theire olde furiouse heyte of mākquelling that neuerthelesse they styll intend yet ones a gayne to raise hit vp. what hertes haue these men? what token of meaknes and sofferaunce is yet espied in them: what signe of retorne from theire vnspekable malice? wich springeth of no nother thyng than of auarice &amp; desire to liue voluptuouslie. Those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be good note I not but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euyll nether hate I or wold any man shuld hate the persons of them but the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / wich I wold gladlie were amended not increa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed. If we touch them neuer so littell then heare we that we rayle on them / blaspheme them / belie them and speake vncharitablie by them▪ to wich thyng I thus answere / yf they wold indifferentlie serch what is saide &amp; applie hit to the reule of haritie they shuld fynd no thyng spoken but trueth / no thyng so sharpelie touched as is of theyre parte deserued. Leat euerie man wich fyndeth hym sealf anie thing greued descend in to iugment of his awne conscien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and axe what hit saith / wich yf they wold often
<pb facs="4"/> do they shuld sone fynde all that is spoken to be les than the trueth / seme hit at the fyrst neuer so sharp or rigourose. Nether is euerie sharp woord vnchari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table / except S. Iohn baptist were not wel auised when he called the Pharizees &amp; Saducees the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracion of vipers Mat. iij. or oure sauioure Christ oute of charitie vsyng the sealf woordes. Math. xij. And agayne sayyng to them woo be to you Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes pharizees hipocrites. Mat. xxiij. Luce. xi. &amp; in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> viij. of Iohn calleth he them the sonnes of the deuill. Sainct Paule also to one Elimas a socerer was not a ferde to saye. O full of sotteltie and deceytful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the chyld of the deuill and the enemy of al right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wisnes thou ceasist not to peruert the straightwai se of the lord. Acto. xiij. Men may not liue as blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de as betelles / as ignoraunt as asses / as sottell as foxis / as lecherouse as gootes / moare beastlie than beastes / and loke styll that God wyll suffer them ether to be vnspoken of or vnpunnysshed / but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shuld think that theire offences be (as the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is) so hanouse that no tong can expresse them no hand endite them no wit cōprehend them &amp; sorow and repent them and continuallie praye to theyre most mercifull father to geue them some sparkell of grace wherbie the may amende them.</p>
   <p>Leat falshed giue place to the trueth. Leat viciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se lyuing be hated / and vertue had in price. Leat rancor be torned in to loue vnfayned. Leat the ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beare with the ignoraunt so far as may be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered / and the ignoraunt be obsequiouse to heare the lerned: ye leat the lerned rather studie one to be cōformable to a nother / and one charitablie and indifferentlie heare a nother / and dispute with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēce
<pb facs="5"/> not with braunlyng and a gree louinglie with oute scholdyng / euery man knowyng that he may erre &amp; excludyng sealff wyll and sinistre iugement and than no doute but all sharp moniciōs shall ceas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se and in theire steade succede praise to the eternall God / in whose power hit onelye lyeth this thyng to performe and a mongest men greate loue and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde / and also thankes geuyng for his inestimab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le goodnes / to whom be all honoure and praise for euer. Amen.</p>
   <p>Of theire dyuers and manyfold facions this be sufficient at this tyme / now her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the enquirie and sentens geuen concernyng the death of the affor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>saide Richard Hune.</p>
   <p>Reade Reader and iuge.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>