<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVEREND FATHERS, THE LEARNED PREACHERS AND GODLIE BRE∣thren in this our English Church: I. D. and I. W. doe hartily wish the abundance of Reuelation in Iesus Christ, with an holy discerning spirit; that they may be the better inabled thereby, to discerne aright of the things that differ, and to hold fast for euer the infallible truth, for the glorie of God▪ the Churches good, and their owne euerla∣sting comfort in Iesus Christ. So be it.</title>
           <author>Walker, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109440_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20001</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6440</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109440</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVEREND FATHERS, THE LEARNED PREACHERS AND GODLIE BRE∣thren in this our English Church: I. D. and I. W. doe hartily wish the abundance of Reuelation in Iesus Christ, with an holy discerning spirit; that they may be the better inabled thereby, to discerne aright of the things that differ, and to hold fast for euer the infallible truth, for the glorie of God▪ the Churches good, and their owne euerla∣sting comfort in Iesus Christ. So be it.</title>
                 <author>Walker, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summarie ansvvere to al the material points in any of Master Darel his bookes : More especiallie to that one booke of his, intituled, the Doctrine of the possession and dispossession of demoniaks out of the word of God. By Iohn Deacon. Iohn Walker. Preachers</title>
                 <author>Deacon, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 240, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE REVEREND FATHERS, THE LEARNED PREACHERS AND GODLIE BRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in this our English Church: I. D. and I. W. doe hartily wish the abundance of Reuelation in Iesus Christ, with an holy discerning spirit; that they may be the better inabled thereby, to discerne aright of the things that differ, and to hold fast for euer the infallible truth, for the glorie of God▪ the Churches good, and their owne euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting comfort in Iesus Christ. So be it.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Euerend <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 31.32.33.</note> beloued and longed for in the Lord: The blessed <hi>Apostle</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe some certaine <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts</hi> or <hi>Canons</hi> concerning the sacred <hi>Schooles of prophesie,</hi> obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth (in effect) this following order. First, hee permitteth the <hi>Prophets</hi> to speake by <hi>two or by three,</hi> appointing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prophets</hi> to determine vprightlie of that which they speake: and then next, hee decreeth, that if any thing <hi>be reuealed to another</hi> which sitteth by, the <hi>former</hi> should be <hi>silent a time,</hi> and the other man <hi>speake,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause all (being thereunto called) <hi>may prophesie one by one,</hi> that all may learne, and all may haue comfort. Howbeit, least any the <hi>Prophets</hi> should happily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume (vpon this his permission) to speake at their pleasure, the <hi>Apostle</hi> forthwith (for auoyding disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered confusion) <hi>subiecteth the spirits of the Prophets</hi> to
<pb facs="3"/>
which more is (if wee found them able to mannage their matters) to giue them the <hi>hand of fellowship</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their <hi>doubtfull cause.</hi> Or if happily (vpon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deliberation) they yeelded the <hi>question</hi> to vs: wee protested further, to conceale their secret being, vntill some good course might forthwith be taken for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming authoritie as well of their present <hi>conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> as also for procuring their <hi>speedie deliuerance from the Ecclesiasticall censures,</hi> so farre foorth as possiblie might be effected.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, beholding the holie <hi>Religion of Christ</hi> verie shrewdly <hi>scandalized,</hi> by reason of such falsely preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>miracles:</hi> we knew (in our conscience) we might <hi>doe nothing at all against the truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8.</note>
      <hi>but for the truth,</hi> and therefore not possiblie conceale those <hi>truthes</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath discouered vnto vs.</p>
   <p>Seuenthly, our holy established <hi>Religion</hi> being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie scornefully derided with <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Atheists,</hi> as a <hi>Religion</hi> that needeth now at length to be presentlie supported by superfluous <hi>miracles:</hi> we verely perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our selues, that no good Christian heart could possiblie forbeare his best endeuour to stay their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate courses.</p>
   <p>Eightly, Master <hi>Darel</hi> and his fellowes very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently persisting in the vnhappie support of those their newly broached <hi>opinions,</hi> hath mightily moued our hearts,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iude.</hi> 22.23.</note> to haue (at the least) a <hi>compassion of some, by putting a difference, and othersome again to saue with feare, by pulling them violently forth of the fire.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Ninthly, their deceitful and coloured kind of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, in that they not onely pretend an <hi>holie cause,</hi> but which more is, doe varnish the same with <hi>holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,</hi> with <hi>faire words and flattering speeches,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18.</note>
      <hi>to intangle (if possiblie they may) the very hearts of the simple:</hi> hath
<pb facs="3"/>
made vs the more carefully to discouer vnto all the world, what <hi>lurking poyson</hi> lieth shrowded vnder those <hi>glorious pretences.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastlie, who would not both speake and write whatsoeuer they conscionablie knowe concerning these <hi>causes,</hi> if hee but respect (as in conscience hee ought) that shamefull reproch which Master <hi>Darell</hi> and his fauourits (like disordered persons) doe verie iniuriouslie impose vpon the whole land,<note place="margin">
         <hi>D. Doctrine pag.</hi> 88.</note> vpon <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracie, Ministery</hi> and people in these following words. Wee doubt not (say they) but that other <hi>nations</hi> and <hi>kingdomes</hi> about vs, will both giue credit to this <hi>matter of fact,</hi> so soone as they shall heare thereof, and see how the same hath been witnessed vpon the <hi>oathes</hi> of many: and will also receiue the <hi>Doctrine of possession and dispossession,</hi> which we so much haue gaine-saide. Blush then oh <hi>England,</hi> and be thou ashamed of this thy incredulitie, which is such as the like thereof hath not bin read nor heard of before: for others haue yet acknowledged the worke which hath been done in them, but thou hast not gone so farre, but rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the same. Loe, these (in effect) be the maine <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions</hi> themselues, which moued vs especially to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour these <hi>matters.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now next,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The maine ends which the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in writing. Psal.</hi> 122.6.7.</note> the <hi>principall ends</hi> which we propound to our selues in publishing our <hi>labours,</hi> are these that follow. Namely, we haue (first) done it, to testifie our hearts desire for the timely accomplishment of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salems peace.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, to make knowne to the world, our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident care for the speedie preuenting of euery such future disordered courses,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10.11.</note> as happily might preiudice the whole, or any part of <hi>Gods truth,</hi> as heretofore the <hi>Brownists</hi> and <hi>Hackets</hi> haue too inconsideratlie effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, by their vnruly and headie conceits.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.9. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.14.</note>Thirdly, to insinuate vnto al the world, our arnest endeuours to know the <hi>truth:</hi> and to be better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if happily we erre in these <hi>matters.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25.</note>Fourthly, to lay open our Christian care for the timely informing of such as are contrarie <hi>minded.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psa.</hi> 119.113.128. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.163.</note>Fiftly, to discouer our vndoubted <hi>detestation of all false waies</hi> in any, how deare soeuer vnto vs.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, to vnfold the preposterous <hi>giddines</hi> of such <hi>humorous spirits,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. 3. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.</note> as dare (in this our <hi>doting age</hi>) so dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouslie pester the <hi>Church</hi> with strange and vnwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>opinions:</hi> very fitly consorting with their <hi>fauourits natures.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, wee haue more especially published our <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> to stand in steede of some prouident watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word for <hi>yong students in Diuinitie,</hi> and newly <hi>conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Christians</hi>; that in any wise they beware how they doe either <hi>broach abroad,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.14. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.14. 2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1.2.</note> or receiue any such <hi>phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall conceits</hi> of <hi>priuate persons,</hi> as are not <hi>primarily exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined</hi> according to the infallible <hi>rules</hi> of the word, neither yet <hi>authentically</hi> approued by publike authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Loe, these (in effect) were the <hi>maine occasions</hi> and <hi>ends,</hi> for the now publishing of our labours in <hi>print.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>premisses</hi> therefore considered, and the <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> on both sides rightly respected: we beseech you reuerend <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> to consider diligentlie whether of vs both haue <hi>caused diuisions and offences,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.18.</note> contrarie to the infallible <hi>Doctrines</hi> which you haue learned <hi>from Christ,</hi> and auoyd them. For they that are such, <hi>serue not the Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> but their <hi>owne bellies:</hi> and with <hi>faire speech and flattering, deceiue the hearts of the simple.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iudg.</hi> 19 30.</note>
      <hi>Consider</hi> therefore we humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, <hi>consult and giue sentence,</hi> either with vs, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, as the <hi>Lord</hi> shall direct your hearts. If wee be thought to haue the <hi>truth</hi> on our sides; we doubt not but that you will <hi>fight together with vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.</note>
      <hi>in one and the
<pb facs="4"/>
selfesame faith of the Gospell.</hi> On the other side, if we be found to haue faulted either in <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>manner,</hi> wee beseech you <hi>confute vs</hi> and spare not: and the <hi>blessing of God</hi> doe light on your hearts for your labour that way. Neither shall our <hi>priuiledged bookes</hi> be any stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page at all to so good a purpose: for if you be vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deale that way because of <hi>authoritie,</hi> your <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate conuictions</hi> shall suffice, to procure from vs a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like retractation</hi> of whatsoeuer shall bee soundly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged amisse.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Augustine.</hi>
      </note> For howsoeuer we may <hi>happily erre,</hi> we purpose <hi>(by Gods grace)</hi> to bee <hi>no Heretikes.</hi> Referring therefore our selues and our labours to your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued <hi>considerations:</hi> we humblie betake you all in our hartiest <hi>prayers,</hi> to the <hi>holy directions</hi> of the <hi>onely wise God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> who iudgeth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to trueth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing brethren assuredly in the Lord, and the Lord his vnworthiest on earth, <list>
            <item>IOHN DEACON.</item>
            <item>IOHN WALKER.</item>
         </list>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>