<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY VVORTHY FRIEND, Mr. THOMAS HAMMON, OF GRAYES INNE, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109853_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06991</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109853</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY VVORTHY FRIEND, Mr. THOMAS HAMMON, OF GRAYES INNE, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famous tragedy of the rich Ievv of Malta : As it vvas playd before the King and Queene, in his Majesties theatre at White-hall, by her Majesties Servants at the Cock-pit. Written by Christopher Marlo</title>
                 <author>Marlowe, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Vavasour, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Millington, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY VVORTHY FRIEND, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. THOMAS HAMMON, OF GRAYES INNE, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Play, composed by so worthy an Authour as Mr. <hi>Marlo</hi>; and the part of the Jew presented by so vnimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table an Actor as Mr. <hi>Allin,</hi> being in this later Age com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the Stage: As I vsher'd it unto the Court, and presented it to the Cock-pit, with these Prologues and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilogues here inserted, so now being newly brought to the Iresse, I was loath it should be published without the ornament of an Epistle; making choyce of you vnto whom to deuote it; then whom (of all those Gentlemen and acquaintance, within the compasse of my long knowledge) there is none more able to taxe
<pb facs="3"/>
Ignorance, or attribute right to merit. Sir, you haue bin pleased to grace some of mine owne workes with your curteous patronage; I hope this will not be the worse accepted, because commended by mee; ouer whom, none can clayme more power or priuilege than your selfe. I had no better a New-yeares gift to present you with; receiue it therefore as a continuance of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable obliegement, by which, he rests stil ingaged; who as he euer hath, shall alwayes remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Tuissmus:</hi> THO. HEYVVOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>