<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL WIL∣LIAM FENYS Esquire, and Sir WILLIAM COPE Knight, grace, mercie and peace.</title>
           <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109740_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20547</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6957</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109740</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL WIL∣LIAM FENYS Esquire, and Sir WILLIAM COPE Knight, grace, mercie and peace.</title>
                 <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and familiar exposition of the eleuenth and twelfth chapters of the Prouerbes of Salomon</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sharpe, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 191, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM FENYS Esquire, and Sir WILLIAM COPE Knight, grace, <hi>mercie and peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE due regard which wee haue of you both, for the speciall gifts wherewith it hath pleased God to grace you; hath moued vs to present vnto you ioyntly this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie of our vnfained loue. We doe the rather publish this Treatise vnder your names, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we would encourage you, to runne forward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly in that Christian race which you haue alreadie so happilie begunne, and to answere that good expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is generally and iustly conceiued of you. We haue long waited and much desired to be imploied againe as formerly (through Gods mercie) wee haue been. But being hitherto disappointed of that hope, and esteeming an vnprofitable life, to be a kinde of vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable death; we thought it our bounden dutie to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our seruice to the Church, and furtherance to your faith, in the best manner wee can, since wee may not vse
<pb facs="3"/> such meanes as we would. As you haue been attentiue hearers whiles we preached, so (we doubt not) but you will be diligent readers of that which is here written. We shall esteeme it a sufficient gaine for our trauaile, if either your selues, or any other, may reape fruit by our labours. The God of all mercie increase his graces in vs all, and multiplie his blessings vpon vs, that our life and death may bring glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to him, and euerlasting peace to our owne soules.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all Christian duties to be commanded, Iohn Dod, Robert Cleauer.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>