<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Halle to the gentle Readers, that thirste
for science, wisheth the increase of knowledge in good thinges,
and as to hym selfe a Christian felicitye.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109324_Fr3_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109324</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Halle to the gentle Readers, that thirste
for science, wisheth the increase of knowledge in good thinges,
and as to hym selfe a Christian felicitye.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and learned vvoorke of chirurgerie, called Chirurgia parua Lanfranci : Lanfranke of Mylayne his briefe: reduced from dyuers translations to our vulgar or vsuall frase, and now first published in the Englyshe prynte by Iohn Halle chirurgien. Who hath thervnto necessarily annexed. A table, as wel of the names of diseases and simples with their vertues, as also of all other termes of the arte opened. ... And in the ende a compendious worke of anatomie ... An historiall expostulation also against the beastly abusers, both of chyrurgerie and phisicke in our tyme: with a goodly doctrine, and instruction, necessary to be marked and folowed of all true chirurgie [n] s. All these faithfully gathered, and diligently set forth, by the sayde Iohn Halle</title>
                 <author>Lanfranco, of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 73, 23, 143, 25, 96, 64 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="63"/>
   <head>Thomas Halle to the gentle Readers, that thirste
for science, wisheth the increase of knowledge in good thinges,
and as to hym selfe a Christian felicitye.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that (dere brethrē) to publish these gestes,
to the prospect and iudgment of the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
(from whose face then it can not be kepte,)
is an enterprise no lesse dangerous, then to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit
a skiffe or small whirey charged, to horry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
tempestes on the raginge seas: howe greate
cause hath my brother had, to detracte or delaye
the time of publishing the same? yea how lyttle
maruel had it bene, if when it was finyshed, he
had neuer doen it? So it might otherwise haue
ioinde to oure handes: for whose sakes he bothe tooke the paynes, and
is content to beare the bitter woundes of scornfull sclaunders dartes,
shotte alwaies by the arme of ignorance. Not doubtinge thy good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
to be euer prest, to thinke and saye the best, and to take all thynges
tollerable in good parte, wherby thou mayste render to hym his hartes
desire: whyche is also no more then duetye, for of mere good wyll I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
thee he hathe done it. Thoughe perhaps it maye more please some
man to iudge w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> lesse loue, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vaine glory was hereof the efficient cause.
to whome I saye, that vayne in dede are all men and theyr thoughtes:
nether is there anye thinge as the Apostle saythe, wherin we shoulde
reioyce, or whereof we shoulde boaste, but onlye the crosse of Christe:
y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is, hys paciēt death &amp; giltlesse sufferāce, for vs wretches. In respect
wherof all other things are very vain. And <hi>Gloria</hi> sayth <hi>Seneca,</hi> vanū
<hi>&amp; volatile quiddâ est, aura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> mobilius.</hi> That is glory is a vain and
fletyng thing, and more wauering then the winde. Whiche vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
in deede (as he also noteth in an other Epistle, couplinge it wyth
ambition,) hathe doubtlesse caused diuers hyghe potentates to attempt
manye dangerous, yea and sometime most wicked enterpryces. And is
no doubte at this daye one vice cleauinge almoste in euery mannes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some:
so large is follyes reigne.</p>
   <p>But as lyke Parasites wyth friuolous adulatyons, to rocke suche
fooles a sleape (to whome it weare muche more meete wyth bytter
tauntes to bridle theyr endlesse arrogancye,) it is not a womanlye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,
but a very wickednesse, yea more then bestiall: so to withholde good
reporte, (whyche is <hi>Vera virtutis gloria,)</hi> from any that hath of mere
good wyll (by anye vertuous trauell) profited the common weale, or
(which is worse) in stead therof to calumniate, is a heathenish iniury:
(but I might more rightly say an iniury, which ought amōg y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godlesse
heathen rather to be sought, but alasse whyche is now among vs chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians
much more frequent.) For who planteth a vyneyarde, &amp; tasteth
not of the frute? who fedeth a flock, and cateth not of the milke?</p>
   <p>Of thys glory (as contrary to the former as light vnto darknesse)
Seneca speakinge in <hi>Epistola. 80. ad Lucilium</hi> saythe, <hi>Gloria vmbra
<pb facs="64"/>
virtutis est, etiam inuitos comitabitur. Sed quemadmodum aliquan
do vmbra antecedit, aliquando sequitur, vel a tergo est: Ita gloria
aliquando ante nos est, visendamque se praebet, aliquando in aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
est, maiorque quo serior, vbi inuidia secessit.</hi> That is: glorye is
the shadowe of vertue, and wyll accompany euen suche as are not desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
of hir, or couet hir not. But as the shadowe goeth sometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
and sometime foloweth, or is behinde: euen so is glory somtime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
vs, and offereth hyr selfe to be sene and somtimes after or behynde
vs. And the later, the greater it is, when enuye hathe geuen plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>Hereof also <hi>Cicero in Laelio</hi> sayth, <hi>Praestantes viri nunquam tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta
conati essent, quae ad posteritatis memoriam pertinerent, ni ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo
vidissent posteritatem ad se pertinere posse. Nonne melius mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
fuisset, otio sam aetatem &amp; quietam sine vllo labore &amp; contentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
traducere?</hi> Worthye men saythe he, woulde neuer attempt so great
thinges, that mighte continue vnto posteritye, vnlesse they did foresee
that the posteritye mighte belonge vnto them: For weare it not elsse
muche better to leade an idle and quyet life, wythoute any labor or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention?</p>
   <p>And who so wyll from time to time, marke the conditions of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:
shall skant fynde one, that for hys labors taken, and perilles sustei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">Cicero pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arch poeta.</note>
desireth not glory as a reward for his dedes. For the Philosophers
them selues, euen in the bookes that they wrote in the contempt of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
haue wrytten theyr owne names: so that wherin they despise fame,
and nobility, yet would they haue them selues named, &amp; made famoue.</p>
   <p>And agayne he saythe. <hi>Nullam virtus aliam mercedem laborum,
periculorumque desiderat, praeter laudis &amp; gloriae: Qua quidem de
tracta, quid est <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> in hoc tam exiguo vitae curriculo, &amp; tam breui,
tantis nos in laboribus exerceamus?</hi> To saye, vertue desyreth none
other recompence of hyr labors and perils, but prayse and glory: whych
beinge taken awaye, what is there, for the whych we should in so small
and short a course of life, vexe our selues with so great laboures. A like
sayinge he hathe in his <hi>Philippicis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Nullam mercedem tanta virtus, praeter hanc laudis et gloria de
siderat: qua etiam si careat, tamen est seipsa contenta. Quanquam
in memoria gratorū hoīm, tanquam in luce posita letetur.</hi> which is,
Uertue only desyreth none other reward, but laud &amp; glory: which true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
if she lacke, yet is she contented: althoughe she reioyce in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of thankfull men, as placed in the lighte. Loe heare see you that true
glory or honest fame, is the good reporte of iuste men, for vertuous tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels,
and honest desertes: a dette whyche the benefyte receiuers oughte
moste willyngly to pay, thoughe not of the deseruers to be ouer busilye
craued, seing that as of the wycked, (whose loue is enuy, and his praise
sclaunder,) it can not be had: so of the vertuous, who is neuer vnthāk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
it can not be wythholden.</p>
   <p>And whether I may in my brother hys behalf, require this at your
handes, as a well deserued duetye, let the thynge it self wyth his frutes
<pb facs="64"/>
be iudge (least I should say more then me besemeth.) Is firste in trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating,
and reducing to perfection, <hi>Lanfrancus</hi> his lyttle worke of chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery,
(not the worste wryter of that age, as hys so muche profyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
doctrine, in suche breuity, dothe ryght will declare.) Then for hys
exposityue table therof, whiche he hathe gathered and adioyned therto.
And lastly for his Anatomy in the end: bothe the whyche, he hathe (at
my sute partly) decked with the Greeke, as wel as the Latin names, of
symples, diseases, members. &amp;c. as the purpose of teachinge the yoūger
sorte gaue occasion: that suche as are as well as I, desirous of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
in bothe the tongues, myght layntlye receiue some vtilitye, (or at
least delight) therby: Trustinge that others will fauorablye permit the
same, as a thing to them though not delightful, yet no impediment.</p>
   <p>In readynge all the which, I trust you wil not repent your paines,
for truely these for the most part are not his, but (as ye may easily see,)
the authorityes of the moste worthy, and best approued wryters, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in
if you shall finde any thinge, (whether it be his owne, or amonge the
authorities,) to be misliked: Examine it fyrste wyth reason, vpryghte
iudgment, and like authorities. By all the whiche if it be found faulty:
Consider, that <hi>hominis est errare,</hi> (neither hathe anye man as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
in humane sciences, otherwise wrytten,) and that muche better it
is to erre, wyth the learned and vnder correction, then singularly of self
wyll or stubberne opinyon.</p>
   <p>But opinyon is nowe a dayes so beloued, that men had muche ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> toothe &amp; nayle defend the same (yea though truth be therby vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
defaced,) thē to geue ouer to reasō or good authority. which thing
ryghte well noteth <hi>Seneca</hi> sayinge. <hi>Inter cetera mortalltatis incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,
&amp; haec est caligo mētiū, nec tantū necessitas errandi, sed erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ū amor.</hi>
That is among other discommedities of mortall men, thys is the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of myndes: not onlye the necessitye of errynge, but also the loue
of the same.</p>
   <p>Whome therfore shall I iudge more happye and wyse, then hym
that is free from error, or at least no slaue to opinion: Then the which
there is not a greater enemy to truthe and perfect knowledge.
Bothe the whyche louynge brethren, I beseche the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
God to plante in vs, to hys endlesse glorye, and
the profyte of hys creatures, and to the vtter
banishment of that ougly monster
Ignorance.</p>
   <closer>Valete.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>