<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader of either sort.</title>
           <author>L., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109635_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06183</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16677</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109635</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader of either sort.</title>
                 <author>L., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>VVits miserie, and the vvorlds madnesse : discouering the deuils incarnat of this age</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 111, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader of either sort.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eaders whatsoeuer (courteous I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire it, if otherwise I care not) I present you as subtile vintners are woont, with my quart at the end of a large recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wherin though I striue to delight your tast, you must hold your selfe assured to pay for your pleasures; for books craue labour, and labour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serues money, pay therfore the Printer for his pains, and if you meet not Carpes in your dish, you may hap haue Gogins if you angle: You run sweating to a play though there want a spirit of wit, I meane meriment in it, then sticke not to giue freely for this, for my Commedie is pleasure, the world is my sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e and stage, and mine actors so well trained, that without a foole and a Deuill I passe nothing, (and thats no smal credit in a countrey towne where hornd beasts yeeld most pleasure and profit) <hi>Kind heart</hi> shall not show you so many teeth tipt with siluer in his Sunday hat, as I Deuils incarnate in clokes of the new fashion, But what Deuils say you? (for if <hi>Plato</hi> lie not, they are in the aire like <hi>Atomi in sole,</hi> mothes in the sonne.) Faith, earthly Deuils in humane habits, wherof some sit on your pillows when you sleepe, wait on
<pb facs="4"/>
your tasters when you drinke, dresse ladies heads when they attire them, perfume courteours when they trim them, and become Panders if you hire them: and if you know them not rightly, they may hap to leaue their horns behind them among some of you. Buy therfore this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stall, and you shall see them in their common appearance; and read these exorcismes aduisedly, &amp; you may be sure to coniure them without crossings: but if any man long for a familiar for false dice, a spirit to tell fortunes, a charme to heale diseased, this only booke can best fit him, let him but buy it, read it, and remember it, and if he be not well instructed when he hath ended it, he shall be a Deuill himselfe on my conscience without ending. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well and thanke him that hath studied thee so much profit; if thou doest not I pardon thee because thou doest as the world teacheth thee. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in charitie and loue: T. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>