<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the christian READER.
grace, mercie and peace.</title>
           <author>I., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109081_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03963</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14068.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the christian READER.
grace, mercie and peace.</title>
                 <author>I., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vvorld of vvonders. A masse of murthers. A couie of cosonages : Containing many of the moste notablest wonders, horrible murthers and detestable cosonages that haue beene within this land. Not imagined falso to delight vaine heads ociose, not practised trans mare to breed trueth cum ambiguitate, but commited euen at home re vera, and may be prooued cum honestate. A matter moste fit to be knowen, well wayed and considered of all men</title>
                 <author>T. I.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barley (Barlow), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the christian READER.
grace, mercie and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch (gentle and beneuolent Reader) as
wee are now abyding in that same iron worlde
wherof <hi>Ouid</hi> speaketh in which is small store of
good frutes but such as barren soyles doe buy:
Nature yeelds, to witthistles, brambles &amp; such
like, whereof small gaine is to bee expected,
wherwith mens harts are hardned, charitie chased, loue lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
trueth thrusted out of doores, liberalitie laide along, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paision
coupled in chaines and all good and vertuous exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
either seldome vsed or vtterly extinct: as fire smothered
vp in ashes, and in stede of these carnall and most vnnaturall
murthers, detestable periuries, cankerd coutousnes incesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
adulterie, hardnes of hart, peeuish extortion, exactions
vsury and diuers such most horrible and abhominable practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
yeerly, monthly, nay howrely are vsed and practised. All
which and other like to the learned are thought to bee moste
euident and manifest signes, that that finall end that conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
and shutting vp of these transitories and vanities of this
mortall world are at hand and that Christ is euen readie to call
vs vnto iudgement: and forasmuch as calling of Preachers,
execution of lawes and iustice and other like woorketh but
small amendment in vs, yet neuerthelesse because that signes
threats, tokens of Gods wrath, signes in the ayre, murthers,
incest and such like heard of and seene with our corporall eyes
although they be not in continuall remembrance to terrifye
by vs from committing such abhominations, yet doe they
for the present time that they are seene, heard or done, stirre
and moue vs vp to prayer to God to amendment of our sinful
liues, to the horror of such wicked actions and such like.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
And for this cause I haue collected these exampses not from
straunge languages or from forrain nations which might breed
some ambiguitie or doubtas touching the trueth, but I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken
them out of our owne natiue Cuntry (not without sorrow
that such hainous sins &amp; enormities should be so rife amongst
vs) wherof can no doubt be made for trueth of action or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
for processe of time or antiquitie, being done all for
the most parr within these few yeares within our memory with
in our knowledge. All which I say are collected togither in a
redines as apretious glasse to see the frailitie of man, to vein
the wickednesse of this world, the end of mischiefs, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
of such greeuous enormities &amp; such like
that therby, other seing the same may refrain the
like, and seeke to shunne such paths as
lead to distruction which graunt
vs so to doe hee that for sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
shed his pretious
blood vpon the
tree. <hi>Amen.</hi>
(.)</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ.
T. I.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>