<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the woorshipfull my verie good friend the fauourer of all good actions, and nouri∣sher of good spirits Iohn Linewray Esquire, Clerke of the deliueries and the deliuerance of all her Maiesties Ordenance, and other munition as well within and out of the Tower of London, as all other her Highnesse Stores within the Realme of England, health, hap∣pines and heauen.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109673_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3702</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109673</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the woorshipfull my verie good friend the fauourer of all good actions, and nouri∣sher of good spirits Iohn Linewray Esquire, Clerke of the deliueries and the deliuerance of all her Maiesties Ordenance, and other munition as well within and out of the Tower of London, as all other her Highnesse Stores within the Realme of England, health, hap∣pines and heauen.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The strange fortunes of two excellent princes : in their liues and loues, to their equall ladies in all titles of true honour</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 61, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the woorshipfull my verie good <hi>friend the fauourer of all good actions, and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher</hi> of good spirits <hi>Iohn Linewray</hi> Esquire, Clerke of the <hi>deliueries and the deliuerance of all her Maiesties Ordenance,</hi> and other munition as well within and out of the Tower of London, as all other her Highnesse Stores within the Realme of England, health, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines and heauen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, vnthankefulnesse is so neare to vnhonestie, as to auoid the touch of both, I haue been often desirous of some good meane, to deserue some one of your many receiued fauours, which loath to burie in such obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that I should be thought vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the regard of so good a minde, I haue thought good to acquaint your kindnesse with such occurrents, as haue lately come to my hands, though they bee no matter of this state, yet were they such tracts in the fortunes of two Princes, as being read with that discretion, which, in your good leasure, can iudge of the labour of wit, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of vertue, I doubt not but that you will fauourablie patronage this first apparant proofe of my loue, till in some better occasion of employment, you maie haue a more sufficient triall of my affection. The substance of my
<pb facs="3"/>
historie being loue, the subiects Princes, the nature ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, the aduentures dangerous, the fortunes strange, and yet the ende happy: will suffice I hope, to perswade the wittie to reade, the wise to fauour, the learned to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the honest to commend, and your good mind to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of: which being no more then I desire, nor lesse then I hope of, leauing my booke to your kind patience, with my selfe to your commandement I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, very much in assurance, N. BRETON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>