<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109155_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19713</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6130</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109155</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pasquine in a traunce : a Christian and learned dialogue (contayning wonderfull and most strange newes out of heauen, purgatorie, and hell) wherein besydes Christes truth playnely set forth, ye shall also finde a numbre of pleasaunt hystories, discouering all the crafty conueyaunces of Antechrist. Wherunto are added certayne questions then put forth by Pasquine, to haue bene disputed in the Councell of Trent. Turned but lately out of the Italian into this tongue, by W.P. Seene allowed [sic] according to the order appointed in the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Curione, Celio Secondo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 112 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCHE HATH
bene the miserie of
these latter dayes
(good Reader) eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
where, and yet is
in some places (the
more is the pitye)
wher iniquitie hath
gotten the vpper
hand, that the truth
findeth few friends,
and canne euill be
heard, especially the
truth of Gods holy Worde, but so odious it is to
mens eyes and eares, (suche is the nature thereof)
as any other thing else, (be it neuer so vayne, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
or abhominable) might be muche soner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
and heard, than the truth of Religion, and
the more that such wickednesse tēded to deface, or
ouerthrow, the truth of Gods holy worde, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
was the same welcome &amp; the more ioyously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued,
and embraced. So as the truth receyuing
this open iniurie (&amp; though not suppressed by al,
yet oppressed by the most) was driuen therefore to
lye close, and secretly to walke with <hi>Nichodemus</hi> by
night for feare of Iewish Christians, and in caues,
dennes, and other vnknowne places (lyke as in
the tyme of former tirranny) to haue hir conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation
and abiding, declaring still as she might, hir
naturall operation to many, and wayting in the
meane season, the appointed tyme of hir delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce.
<pb facs="3"/>
And if it so chaunced hir to be seene or
heard abrode (for the candell whelued vnder the
Busshell wil burne a hole throughe, and shewe it
selfe) then straight way must she so be scaled, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
and prompted, by Pollicie who must be hir
Tutour, as she must not therefore seme so roughe
as to rippe vp matters that are raked long since in
the ashes, but muste talke a farre off, and either
cloth hir s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lfe with the misty cloudes, of darke
and doubtfull speach, which few shal vnderstand,
and must offend no man, or else must appeare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
to be so plyaunt, and in such glaring gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
as least may become clawing and well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
talke, and nothing else, and such as shall cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
all men, and cut no one.</p>
   <p>For the which cause, the authour hereof called
<hi>Celius Secundus Curio</hi> an Italian, a man surely zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,
and godly learned, lamenting this great and
malicious kinde of blindenesse, as a thing moste
daungerous both for bodye and soule, thought
good and his bounden duetie, (to relieue thereby
the mindes, and consciences, of suche, as not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
but for want of due knowledge, went gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
in by pathes at none dayes, and to confirme
suche other in the right path way of heauenlye
truth, as had tasted some little fruite of Gods holy
spirite) to write therefore this little worke, which
about XXV. yeares since, (or there vpon) he toke
in hande and set forth, what time <hi>Paule</hi> the thirde
of that name (a man of great worldely wisedome
and admiration with christen Princes, and a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
professour of that diuellishe knowledge of
Necromancie) sate &amp; occupied Caiphas (I should
say) <hi>Peter</hi> Chaire. And so the authour following
<pb facs="3"/>
in some parte, the politique councel of Saint <hi>Paule</hi>
the Apostle, (who sayeth, So that Christ be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
any maner wayes, whether it be vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēce<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note>
or sincerely, he reioyceth therein) hath publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
the same his labour vnto the world, vnder the
pleasaunt name of <hi>Pasquine</hi> that aunciēt Romaine,
as a fit instrument to aduaunce Gods truth, who
for his same being acquaynted with all Princes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states
and affaires, and for his wonted mirth and
straunge newes, coulde the better spredde abroade
the same, and cause it to be more ioyefully recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
and read, than if many great Potentates and
Princes had commended it to the worlde, with
their priuilege and authoritie. As to <hi>Pasquine,</hi> and
to tell thee what he is, shall not nowe be necessarie,
for I will not holde thee with so long a discourse:
if thou can not other wise learne of him, I shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
thee to the booke it selfe, where thou shall
finde him fully described.</p>
   <p>But nowe me thinketh I heare some nose wise
papist, make a very vnnecessarie obiection: what
sayeth he is <hi>Pasquine</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> nowe become a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,
that was wont so to be talking alwayes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
our holy Father and his colledge of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals:
to whome, it may right well be answered in
this sorte, as in that he is come from <hi>Rome</hi> hither
to preach, is to fulfill the saying of Christ,<note place="margin">Luk. 4.</note> that no
Prophete is accepted in his owne country, and
therfore cannot be heard (no more was Christ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
his owne country men the Iewes) which is
straunge, that C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ristes messanger, comming to
Christes Vicaire (if there be any suche on earth,)
shoulde be refused of audience, bringing a true
message, but much more is it, that for declaring
<pb facs="4"/>
the same, (for their soule health and saluation) he
shoulde be in daunger. But to be banished his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
for saying as he is commaunded, passeth
all law of God and men, yea and <hi>ius gentium</hi> also.
And in that some will accompt him, suche one as
wil be alwayes talking at his pleasure, I will turne
suche ouer to the Poet <hi>Horace</hi> who sayeth, <hi>Ridentem
dicere verum, quid vetat?</hi> Why should not a Iester or a
mery fellow tel truth. And if that wil not serue to
stop their blasphemous mouthes, I will bring forth
Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> who sayeth,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> If he himselfe or an Angell
preach any otherwise, than the Gospell which he
preached, let him be accursed, whereby he infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
that the message shoulde not be the better
welcome or heard, for the messangers sake, but
the messanger for the truth, and worthinesse of the
message he bringeth, (yea, if he were a Diuell)
ought to be beleued. To the matter it selfe, I shal
referre to thy direct iudgement (so thou spoile thy
selfe in the reading therof, of all malice and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
wherein thou shalt see, vnder the wittie and
pleasaunte inuention of <hi>Pasquines</hi> going to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
purgatorie, and hell, the whole packe of the
Popes pedlary wares, is opened &amp; not set to sale,
bicause men shoulde buy therof, but rather to the
shewe and brought to the touchestone of Goddes
worde to be thereby tryed and seene what maner
stuffe it is: So as all men may see, howe the Romish
Apoticaries haue so conserued, confected, and
couloured, with the drugges &amp; other the fine deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
of their subtile Sophistrie, all their whole pelfe
and trumperie, as meritorious Masses, fayned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,
superstitious obseruances, hypocriticall
fastings, paynted holynesse, and Sodomiticall
<pb facs="4"/>
chastitie, and that with their chauntings, pypings,
gaye glistering shewes and sightes, sweete smelles
and odours, (all deuised to feede and occupie the
outwarde senses of man, and to stuffe his head and
vnderstanding with the vaine gazing, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of their counterfeit Religion) so as manye
that tooke themselues to be verye nycenosed, and
coulde as they thought iudge colours, were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
in their folly, and toke <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curium
sublimatum,</hi> for good and wholesome Suger.
And how this broode of smoth smiered shauelings
haue the inuentions, and dreames, of their owne
ydle and drousie braynes, sette vp to themselues
a mortall God, that mitred Monarche of <hi>Rome,</hi>
who with power and tirannie, shoulde mayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
them in a perpetuall, and flourishing king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
and they for their part, euen from the seliest
hedge priest, or other most simple in degree vnder
them (being greased with the Popes Oyle) euen
to the proudest, and most princelie Prelate, euery
one in his kinde to labour, and apply themselues,
with tongue and pen, or rather with tooth and
nayle (if they doe not besides, vse any other more
violent weapons) to deuise, studie, serch and vse al
the fetches possibly how they may keepe all things
vpright, and cloute vp with stable straw, and such
paltry, the ruynes, breaches, and decayes, of this
their <hi>Chaos,</hi> or confused common wealth. Thou
shalt also see, as it were by an <hi>Antithesis</hi> or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison,
the sacred Scriptures, set against their vayne
and fantasticall toyes and inuentions, and the
same Scriptures so aptely applyed, and truely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged,
as can not be desired to be better or more
effectually done, to the purpose. And betwene the
<pb facs="5"/>
serious and fruitefull allegation of the scriptures,
and the necessary detection of their chast life and
holynesse, thou shalt finde some things (and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
not fewe in number) that thoughe the same
be no meere nor malicious inuentiōs, yet can they
not be iudged to be Fables, but rather matters of
truth, bicause the worlde else hath in their seuerall
places, had the tryall and experience of the same.
And histories haue also in some parte set them
forth to the great cōmendation of the doers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
But one thing (gentle Reader) thou wilt not a
little maruell at, that their spirituall weapons,
wherewith they defend their Romish kingdome▪
(I meane their owne councels, and constitutions
herein alleaged) are so brought against them
selues, and so retourned home to their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion,
and ouerthrowe, that there remayneth
now, no more spirituall defence, or resistence, but
that they lay hande on the Temporall sworde, and
vse the violent argumentes offyre, sworde, and
halter, which howe muche they haue done, in this
Realme of late dayes, that very Rome it selfe hath
abhorred. I leaue to thy iudgement, for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne
children in the mothers wombe, and the
louing dogges with their masters haue witnessed
the same. Thou mayest chaunce to finde this
boke (beside that it is writtē in the Italian tongue)
in the Latine also, which seemeth to haue beene
done, by the authour him selfe, what tyme he saw
his laboure so well to be lyked and allowed, as he
wrote the same in the latine tongue also, for the
better edifying and calling home of the sheepe
that went a straye, and the more assured confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of them in the truth of Gods worde. Yet bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="5"/>
this Italian copie is the larger, wherevnto is
added the voyage to Hell (which the Latine booke
hath not) I haue therefore chosen, and followed
the same, and tourned it into our tongue as nowe
thou seest.</p>
   <p>There follow in the ende therof, certayne questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
put forth by <hi>Pasquine,</hi> to be disputed (but not as
<hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>adoxes</hi>) in the Councell holden in that holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
dayes, <hi>Paule</hi> the thirde, at <hi>Trent,</hi> wherein he
scorneth priuily, the great and manifolde abuses
of the Churchmen, aswell of the proude Prelates,
as the single soled sir Iohns, the fat bellyed monks,
&amp; lying Fryers, their false allegations of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
their idlenesse, their pride, their voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse,
tiranny, hipocrisie, wyuelesse but not
womanlesse chastitie, and other their endlesse, and
abhominable doings, the which articles maye, (as
it were in a briefe) comprehende the whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
of the booke afore going, and shewe forth
the spirituall fruites that spring of that Religion.
So as to conclude, gentle Reader, you may see, and
finde, that there is no matter of controuersie,
wherein the papistes differ from the true Church
of Christ, (and the heauenly doctrine taught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
and since by the Patriarches, Prophetes, and
Apostles) as in their purgatorie, their iustifying
workes, their corporall presence of Christ in the
Sacrament, their transubstantiacion, adoration,
&amp; al the rest of their new found learning, but that
the same all, and euery of them are quite defaced,
and ouerthrowen by the manifest worde of God.
Thou canst therefore desire no more to the certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying,
and confirmation of thy conscience in the
truth, or otherwise to satisfie thy minde, with the
<pb facs="6"/>
detection of popery, and the merie and pleasaunt
disposing of the matter: so as whether thy profite,
or pleasure shal be most, I know not, and therfore
will not take vpon me to iudge. This shall I one-desire
thee, to reade with iudgement, and lay aside
all affection and malice, (both which are partiall
Iudges,) and so to walke directly throughe the
whole worke, whereby thou mayest discerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene
the truth and falshode, to thy edifying and
comfort, so shal I think my labour &amp; trauaile thus
to translate it for thee, well bestowed, and shall
sende thee to the booke to heare what he
sayeth himselfe, from the which
I thought good with no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
Preface to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
thee.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>