<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1520</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109570_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20430</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6833</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109570</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dyetary of ghostly helthe</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Worde, Wynkyn de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1520</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the begynnȳge of this newe yere / my good systers whan I consyder and se many frendes gyue tokens of custome one to another / whiche custome / some vse it for good lucke of a newe yere / some to {pro}cure carnal loue / some to get a greater be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefyte therby / some to gette worldely fauour or maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce in yll / some to please &amp; flatter them that ben yll / (whiche causes ben not commendable) some to procure loue and to contynue frendshyp and peas in the comune lyfe / bytwene neyghbour &amp; neyghbour / whiche is ryght good and conuenyent to do. And some with ryght godly intent to purchace ghostly loue. For one ghostly frende to remembre another the more hartely in prayers / whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I thynke ryght commēdable. And after this intent (as I suppose) dyuers of you haue gyuen tokens vnto me. Wherfore hauynge nothynge redy to gyue vnto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / I purpose in my mynde to prepare one token for you all / to profyte eche of you. This token thynke it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I haue not of my selfe / but of god / as I haue herde &amp; redde of holy doctours / and by coniecture of the waye to good lyuynge / and nothynge by experyence of my selfe. It is full vnsemynge to me for to shewe or wryte vnto you of the waye to vertue / whiche am not yet all out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> way of wyckednes. Yet a gryndyngston maketh a knyfe bryght &amp; sharpe / thoughe it be neuer the sharper it selfe. So I maye moeue you to make you sharpe &amp; quycke to ghostly thynges &amp; to clerenesse of good lyuynge / though I my selfe be ryght slowe and dull vnto the same. To teche goodnesse is a thynge that may not be vndone / of them that haue cure &amp; rewle of other persones / though
<pb facs="3"/> they do but lytell good themselfe. Cryst sayd of the pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rysyes rulers of the people. Do as they saye / but not as they do. Not withstandynge our lorde hathe gyuen me a desyre to do well. I beseche hym I maye haue grace to perfourme my desyre to his pleasure / honoure &amp; laude. Therfore though my symple lyuȳge can styrre you but lytell. I trust that my good wyll and desyre that I haue to your ghostly profyte shall mcyte you bothe to encreace the more in vertu / and also to helpe me with your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto the same. Alytell Dyetary for your dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersacyō I purpose for to wryte / deuydȳge it into. xxiiij consyderacyons / as the daye is deuyded into. xxxiiij. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / whiche though it be rudely wryten / it maye profyte you moche / yf ye wyll dylygētly put it ī execucyon of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge / and elles it profytech lytell / but rather hurteth. For cryst sayth a sermaunte that knoweth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wyll of his mayster and wyll not do therafter shalbe bette with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great strokes. And who soeuer studyeth for the wyll of god &amp; forgete it not / but dylygētly put it to workynge / he shalbe blessed of god / and haue euerlastynge Ioye for so doynge / yf he perceyuer therin.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>