<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109031_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10233</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2051</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109031</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two very lerned sermons of M. Beza, togither with a short sum of the sacrament of the Lordes Supper: Wherevnto is added a treatise of the substance of the Lords Supper, wherin is breflie and soundlie discussed the p [r] incipall points in controuersie, concerning that question. By T.W</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                            <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 250 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="128"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>AT the motion and request of sundrie my deere friends in the Lord, I haue thought good to put downe these two praiers following, not thereby minding, either to tie anie person to the vse of these onelie (for they may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their seuerall necessities, conceiue some other of their owne, or practise some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forme alredie set foorth, by men of greater gifts or feeling) nor yet so to busie their minds, and to occupie their heads, as that they should be imploied in these, when the publike praiers and exercises of the church, performed by the ministers, are in hand (for be it farre from vs, when the minister (Gods mouth) speaketh from the Lord to vs, or when he as our mouth, speaketh to the Lord for vs, to haue either our hearts or our mouthes occupied about any other thing, than the reuerend hearing and consenting vnto, of such things as hee vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.) But that aiding the infirmitie of our brethren, such as haue not the gift to conceiue praier, and shall thinke this fit for themselues, might haue a forme to exercise themselues in, both before they repaire to the publike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises of the church, and also after the celebration and partaking of these reuerend mysteries shall be finished.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>