<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Religious and well affected Gentrie of this King∣dome.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109009_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06635</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17097</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109009</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Religious and well affected Gentrie of this King∣dome.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Via tuta : the safe vvay. Leading all Christians, by the testimonies, and confessions of our best learned aduersaries, to the true, ancient, and catholique faith, now professed in the Church of England. By Humfrey Lynde Knight</title>
                 <author>Lynde, Humphrey, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 323, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Religious and well affected Gentrie of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F for no other cause, yet for this alone that the world may know it is no difficult matter for a meane Lay-man to prooue the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient visibilitie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant profession, I haue attempted to send foorth this Essay of my poore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours in this cause, being
<pb facs="3"/>
thereunto prouoked by a challenge heretofore sent vnto me, by a Iesuite, in these words: (viz.) <hi>That Sir Humfrey, or his friends should prooue out of some good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that the Protestant Church was in all ages visible, especially in the ages before Luther.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is not my profession, I must confesse, to returne challenges or publish works of this nature; yet knowing that <hi>Truth is iustified of her children;</hi> I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed, as a child of that Mother, to vindicat her
<pb facs="3"/>
cause, and maintaine my owne reputation: and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer hereunto I shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent such proofes as are warranted by Certificat and confession, not onely of the most orthodox Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but of the Romish Bishops and Cardinals, and other moderne Writers in the Romane Church.</p>
   <p>It is an vndoubted truth &amp; subscribed by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that the faith which Christ and his Apostles taught in the first age had visible professors in al ages. It were therefore sufficient (without any further recital of
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
succeeding witnesses) to proue that the now Faith of the Church of England is that Faith which was once deliuered to the Saints by Christ and his Apostles, but I rather condescend to meete the Aduersarie vpon his owne ground, and to deale with him at the same weapon which himselfe hath chosen, wherein on our part the Ancient Fathers shall be my <hi>Champions,</hi> and his owne Romish Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and Cardinals, and Schoolemen shall be my <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds,</hi> as being <hi>Testes veritatis</hi> witnesses of Gods
<pb facs="5"/>
truth professed in our Church.</p>
   <p>Of what strength and force is Truth, shal appeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> his that shee extorts a full and ample testimonie from her sworne enemies to make good the visibility of our Church, nor that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but she denyes antiquity and vniuersalitie to the principall Articles of the new Romane Creed, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in she points forth that old and true way, and this is acknowledged on both sides to be <hi>Via tuta, The safe Way:</hi> vpon which ground it is likewise lawfull for me
<pb facs="6"/>
to frame a counterchallenge by demanding, <hi>By what authoritie of Scriptures, &amp; ancient Fathers they haue imposed new Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Christian beliefe vpon Priests &amp; people?</hi> sure I am, those twelue new coined Articles declared by their grād Councel of Trent and published by Pope <hi>Pius the fourth,</hi> are so far short from the knowledge of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, that as yet they are scarce vnderstood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst their own Disciples for Articles of Faith. And their best learned Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists professe openly, that
<pb facs="6"/>
most of them were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to former ages.</p>
   <p>It is no wonder, that a blind obedience and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith is so much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded to the ignorant of the Romane Church, when their best learned Doctors are forced to confesse tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the chiefe Articles (wherein they differ from vs) that they can neither subsist by Antiquitie, nor stand with the safety of the beleeuer: Neither may it seeme strange that these mē should create new Articles of faith, when as they dare alter and detract from the
<pb facs="7"/>
Commandements of God; witnesse their Decalogue so often published by the Church of Rome, (here now prefixed) wherein not only the second Commandement is left out (as it is vsually in all their Psalters) but the fourth Cōmandement, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Sabbath day is changed into these words: <hi>Remember thou sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Holy-dayes:</hi> But as for these <hi>peccadillos,</hi> the recitall of them I account a sufficient refutation: In the meane time, those men who call for a Catalogue of names of such Protestants
<pb facs="7"/>
as taught and professed the <hi>39.</hi> Articles of Religion of our Church, in all ages, let them in euery age produce one Ancient and orthodox Father, who did teach and maintaine their twelue new Articles <hi>de Fide</hi> (which they command vnder a curse to be beleeued of all men) I say let them produce but one in euery age, or but anyone in all the ages for <hi>1500.</hi> yeares after Christ, till the dayes of <hi>Luther,</hi> that taught and beleeued all their twelue new Articles <hi>de Fide</hi> as points of faith, and for that one <hi>good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
sake, I will be so libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, as to acknowledge their professors visible in al ages; I will say their Bishops, and Cardinals, and Schoolemen, which haue witnessed the Antiquitie of our doctrine, were mistaken, and ought to bee reformed by an <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> I will te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are guiltie of Noueltie, and submit my obedience with an implicit faith to the Romane Church.</p>
   <p>And, as touching my owne particular, I professe, through the prouocation of a Iesuite, I haue vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="8"/>
thrust my sickle into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens haruest; yet I witnesse a true confession before God and man, that I haue neither willingly, nor wilfully falsified any one Author either in citation, or translation in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise: If any slips haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (which I doe confesse for want of helpe and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie may befall me) let it be shewed mee by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer moderately, plainely, and faithfully, and I will ingeniously confesse the weaknesse, not of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but of my own hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>So for this time, vntill it please God to giue oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to publish some fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruits of my labours in this kind: I heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire good interpretation, and fauourable acceptance of the beginnings and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of him, who is</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>At your seruice in Christ, and for his Truth,</hi> H.L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>