<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Reader, in the commendation of Fables.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109053_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16191</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3114</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109053</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Reader, in the commendation of Fables.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A schole of wise conceytes : vvherin as euery conceyte hath wit, so the most haue much mirth, set forth in common places by order of the alphabet. Translated out of diuers Greke and Latine wryters, by Thomas Blage student of the Queenes Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 276, 12 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the gentle Reader, in the commendation of Fables.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I reuolued in my minde the sundrie kindes of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which for the profit of Man haue put in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance their imaginations, they that haue writ Fables are to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the reste: for they haue not onely wonderfully delighted the harts of men, but also haue more allured them to doe thinges both good and profitable with their Fables, than Philosophers with their preceptes. For they with such a sweetnesse do so pierce the hartes of the Readers, and by similitudes do declare (whiche are of much force to moue affection) what men ought to take, and what to refuse, that thereby they are compelled, against their wils to agree vnto them. For the minde is disdaynfull to heare, neyther will it easely abyde things profitable and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, excepte they bee poudered with some merry ieste Hereunto beareth witnesse a certein Orator of <hi>Athens,</hi> who on a tyme speaking to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued them lesse attentiue, required them
<pb facs="6"/>
that they would vouchsafe to heare a Fable: they were contented: then he began thus: Ceres, the Swallowe and the Egle sometime iorneyed togither, when they were come to a riuer, the Swallowe flue ouer, and the Eele swam through the riuer: when he hadde so sayd he held his peace, then they asked him what Ceres didde? Your Gods (quod he) are offended at you whiche will not heare them that counsell you for your profit, but if they tell any tales ye heare them willingly. What force fables are of to moue affection, I could declare by many examples, yet will I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound but three. The inhabitants of <hi>Samos</hi> would haue put their ruler to death, whome <hi>Aesope</hi> dissuaded saying: As a Foxe passed ouer a riuer, he was driuen into a ditch wher he stucke so fast in the mudde, that he could not escape, whō the flies stinged: the Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hog seing him there, moued with compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, asked him if he shoulde driue the flies from him. No (quod he) for these are full with my bloud and can litle trouble me, but if thou shouldest dryue them away, other hunger sterued flies wil occupie their romes, and suck out all the bloud that is left within me. The like shall happen to you O <hi>Sami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
for if ye slaye your Ruler whiche is so wealthie, ye must needes chose others, which whiles they enriche them selues, shall poll you of all that this man hath left: wherwith all the <hi>Samians</hi> being moued, left off their purpose. By the like meanes was <hi>Tiberius Caesar</hi> persuaded, when he appointed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day Magistrates, wherevpon (as <hi>Iose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> telleth) the Countrey of <hi>Iurie</hi> was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by <hi>Cratus</hi> and <hi>Pilatus</hi> onely by the space of twentie yeares. For (as <hi>Statius</hi> saith) he that ruleth but a litle while, sheweth smal fauour to the people. The <hi>Himerians</hi> som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time minded to chose Captaine of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie <hi>Phalaris</hi> the tyrant of <hi>Agrigentum,</hi> whome <hi>Stesichorus</hi> the Poet with this Fable discouraged from their purpose, saying: A horse fed alone in a medow, at length came a Harte thither and spoyled it: wherevpon the Horse tooke the aduise of man, by what meane he might be reuenged, to whome the man sayde: If thou wilt take a bytte in thy mouth and suffer me armed to gette vpon thy backe, whose counsell he followed, and by his helpe put the Harte to flight and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the conquerer, but from that tyme forth he could not rid his mouth from the
<pb facs="7"/>
byt nor the man from his backe. Euen so (sayde <hi>Stesichorus)</hi> the like shall happen to you, if ye chose <hi>Phalaris</hi> your captayne, for your enimies ye shall subdue, but ye shall be in bondage to this Tyraunt for euer: with which wordes the <hi>Himerians</hi> being discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, forsoke the counsell to chose suche a Captayne, what time the people of <hi>Rome</hi> separated themselues from the Senators, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they payd tribute and were combred with warfares, did not <hi>Agrippa Menenius</hi> turne them from their purpose with this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Sometime (quoth he) ye <hi>Romaines,</hi> the members of man perceyuing the belly to be slouthfull, fell at variance with her and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to giue her no longer any succor. It happened, that, bicause they denied her nourishment, they became faynt, whervpon they were at one againe. In like maner the Senate and people of <hi>Rome</hi> are as the belly and members, whiche neede one of anothers helpe, and as by discord they perishe, so by concord they are of strength: By whiche Tale the people turned from their purpose and became friends again with the Senate. Therfore not without good cause both the Greeke and Latin Poets, as <hi>Hesiodus</hi> and
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Horace,</hi> haue mingled such Fables amongst their workes, and also the chiefest and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Philosophers, as <hi>Plato, Aristotle,</hi> and <hi>Plutarche,</hi> with many moe, haue highly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended them, whose opinion was, that they much auayled to the instruction of a moral and ciuill lyfe: wherefore <hi>Leouicenus</hi> and <hi>Ʋalla,</hi> of late writers the best lerned, did trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate Fables out of Greke into Latin, which they knew would be to their prayse, and to the delight and profite of others: Neyther were they deceyued, for they are dayly redde of most learned men. I can not therefore perceyue, why by translating these Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, I should be defrauded of the prayse due to me, whiche other haue had, excepte we be so spitefull, that to vs that is not lawful, which with great commendation to the Grecians and Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistes is allowed. Fare well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>