<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my verie good friend, Maister Ionas Tirill of Burstow, all hap∣pinesse bee wished.</title>
           <author>O., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109360_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05203</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109360</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my verie good friend, Maister Ionas Tirill of Burstow, all hap∣pinesse bee wished.</title>
                 <author>O., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasaunt and delectable historie of Lazarillo de Tormes, a Spanyard : and of his maruellous fortunes and aduersities. The second part. Translated out of Spanish and into English, by W.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Oxenbridge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my verie good friend, Maister <hi>Ionas Tirill</hi> of <hi>Burstow,</hi> all <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse bee wished.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough good will and perfect friendship is not to be requited nor sought with mony, yet such is the exellencie thereof, that it is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times requited with some ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, wherwith the vertue is much more beautified, as it was with the good and wise King <hi>Don Alonso</hi> of <hi>Spaine:</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen to vnderstand, that one vnto whome hee had done great good by preferring him to honour, besides many liberal gifts, was verie vnthankfull for the same; he answered in a milde maner, that a great good turne is neuer requited without some ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, euen so I may compare you in this happinesse vnto him, and in vnhappinesse my selfe vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: who for much good, haue returned but ill; wherefore I am the bolder, being acquainted so wel with your good disposition, to shew my self thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, being well assured that you cannot think of my seruice euill, seeing, (as I haue saide) you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies done well, beeing deliuered vnto mee by a
<pb facs="3"/>
Gentleman of mine acquaintaunce, a small Spanish Pamphlet, by him new done into English, intituled <hi>Lazarillo de Tormes,</hi> a Spanyard, discoursing the many hard fortunes &amp; aduersities he susteined in the Sea, beeing transformed into a Tuni Fish; though but a toy, yet I assure you passing pleasaunt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable; which I haue aduentured to dedicate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: Onely crauing you will accept it as friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I present it willingly, and then I haue my one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly request. And so resting in hope of your fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptance, I commit you to the Almightie, and this poore <hi>Lazarillo,</hi> to the friendly Readers cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing friend who wisheth you all hearts ease. <hi>I. O.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>