<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY ennobled Donogh O Bryan, Baron of Ibrackan, Earle of Tho∣mond, and Lord President of the Pro∣uince of Munster in the Kingdome of IRELAND: Robert Daborne wisheth the increase of all Ho∣nours, and the fruition of his sanctified desires.</title>
           <author>Daborne, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109200_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19756</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6183</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109200</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY ennobled Donogh O Bryan, Baron of Ibrackan, Earle of Tho∣mond, and Lord President of the Pro∣uince of Munster in the Kingdome of IRELAND: Robert Daborne wisheth the increase of all Ho∣nours, and the fruition of his sanctified desires.</title>
                 <author>Daborne, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of the citie of Waterford : in Febr. 1617. before the Right Honorable the Lord President of Munster, and the state: as also, before Sr William Iones knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of Ireland, and Gerrard Loder Esquire, one of the iudges of the Common Pleas, the then iustices of assize held in the same place. At which time the charter of the same citie, being by diuers iuries found forfeit, was lastly surrendred. By Robert Daborne chancelor of the said cathedrall church of Waterford</title>
                 <author>Daborne, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY ennobled <hi>Donogh O Bryan,</hi> Baron of <hi>Ibrackan,</hi> Earle of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> and Lord President of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Munster</hi> in the Kingdome of IRELAND: <hi>Robert Daborne</hi> wisheth the increase of all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and the fruition of his sanctified desires.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all Vertue findes both originall and perfection in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion; so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially <hi>Gratitude:</hi> that if I would deliuer in a word,
<pb facs="3"/>
what our Profession teaches, it should bee this; <hi>To bee thankfull</hi>: And though my ablest endeauor, assisted with most fauourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, can neuer render mee more then willing to deserue the greatnesse of your H: bounties; yet if I onely of many my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (as who knowes your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor truly, but must confesse you a Father of our Nation) come back with the <hi>Samaritane</hi> to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique acknowledgement as it can no way take from the constancie of your goodnesse, so it addes this benefit to mee, that I haue some testimony of my desire to pay, as I haue many witnesses of my debt. Not to trouble your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
<pb facs="3"/>
with much, as the wisdome of Kings best appeares in their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Vicegerents and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellors: An example where of wee haue in <hi>Salomon</hi> and his Sonne <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. So the Lord grant in preferring such Religious and truely Honourable Personages as your Lordship, to the seat of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, we his Maiesties loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects may euer continue to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his high Iudgment, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blesse the Lord for him.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors faithfull Seruant and Chaplaine, ROB: DABORNE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>