<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Prologue]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109324_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109324</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Prologue]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and learned vvoorke of chirurgerie, called Chirurgia parua Lanfranci : Lanfranke of Mylayne his briefe: reduced from dyuers translations to our vulgar or vsuall frase, and now first published in the Englyshe prynte by Iohn Halle chirurgien. Who hath thervnto necessarily annexed. A table, as wel of the names of diseases and simples with their vertues, as also of all other termes of the arte opened. ... And in the ende a compendious worke of anatomie ... An historiall expostulation also against the beastly abusers, both of chyrurgerie and phisicke in our tyme: with a goodly doctrine, and instruction, necessary to be marked and folowed of all true chirurgie [n] s. All these faithfully gathered, and diligently set forth, by the sayde Iohn Halle</title>
                 <author>Lanfranco, of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 73, 23, 143, 25, 96, 64 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="146"/>
   <p>The vtilitie of Anatomye, (as the sayde author defineth) is, that
those incommodities and dangers, whervnto the body is often sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,
may be the more easely preuēted or defended. The which incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
doe runne in dyuers partes and offyces of the body, and also
may greatly offende: For there are very fewe members (or rather
none) that are formed vnto no vse, or that dooe not exercyse theyr
gyfte, eyther in theyr owne office or in helpyng some other action.</p>
   <p>And in the proheme of hys seconde booke, vehemently praysing the
vtilitie therof, he sayeth: for what in comparyson, is more to bee
wyshed for then the absolute knowledge of Anatomye? What is
more excellent? what to the physicien more profitable? What to the
chyrurgien more worthy? The whiche who so endeuour to gette and
the same obteyne, are onlye worthyly called physiciens and chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giens:
neyther is there ought that maye more commende the phisicien
or chyrurgien, then the same Anatomie. Whiche studie who so setteth
at nought, I knowe not what in suche men and their artes maye be
praysed. For when the myndes delectation is coueted, or perfection
and an absolute arte sought for: what doth so muche delyght or moue
ingenious wyttes, as the dilygent editions, difficultly searched out of
our founders, in the procreation of this <hi>Micro cosmos</hi> or lytle world?
and surely Medicine without Anatomie, shalbe neyther arte nor any
thyng els.</p>
   <p>This beyng true, as I thynke no learned or reasonable man wyll
denye, howe vntruly doe (in these our daies) a great number beare the
names of physike and chyrurgerie: or howe ill deserue they to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
by those honorable names, (being not only ignorāt in the Anatomy
them selues, but also disdainfully contempne &amp; reproue, both the thing
it selfe, and all suche as trauell ther is, eyther to profite them selues or
others) let wyse men iudge.</p>
   <p>These thynges considered, it may seme necessary, that the neglygent
myndes of suche, as lyttle esteme this delectable fountayne or swete
well sprynge of theyr profession, be spurred forwarde vnto vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
by some compendious treatise, that may farther there trauell, or
cause them at the least (their dull slouthfulnes set a parte,) to procede
forwarde, not turnyng backwarde nor loyteryng by the waye, til they
haue scaled the forte of perfection, and wunne the citie of science.</p>
   <p>But if I shall at this tyme determyne a treatyse of so hyghe a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession,
of whiche also so many noble clerkes haue wrytten before,
whiche shall be pervsed of so many at this present, ye iudged also of
those that are to come: howe shall my handes refrayne from fearfull
shaking, or my face from bashfull blushynges: sythe my simple and
indigested frase, must shewe it selfe before so many excellent, euen such
whose intellection wyll them leade my rudnes to controwle. Whiche
I feare muche the rather may chaunce, because that of some one thing
many tymes dyuers authers make dyuers difinitions: for dyuers mē
haue dyuers myndes, and diuersitie of myndes, causeth dyuersitie and
<pb facs="146"/>
varietie in opinions: whiche happeneth not only in this profession, but
also in all sciences, yea and most of all (whiche is lamentable) among
the diuynes or teachers of christen theologie.</p>
   <p>Yet not withstanding I doubt not, but whosoeuer shall indifferētly
beholde this simple treatyse without parcialitie, conferring the same
with the most accepted authors, they shall fynde the same both soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
with truthe and reason.</p>
   <p>But truly the malyce of men so excedyngly encreaseth, that no man
no not the best learned, (muche lesse I,) can doe ought without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche
and slaunder: yea and that chiefly by men of his owne profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.
Oh how hatefull and vyle a matter is this, and a playne demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration
of enuy, when one man of science shalbe asked by a stranger.
what opinion he hath in an other man of science that he knoweth, he
shall answer, he is a good herbarian, he knoweth well herbes: or he
is good at the Anatomie. I know nothing els of hym. They that are
perfect in nothyng them selues, haue euer in readynes suche disdeyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
reproche to hyde their owne ignorance: as though a man, beynge
excellent in any other thing, it proued hym to be ignorant in all other:
Whiche thing if it dyd proue I myght thus answer. It is better to
be perfect in some one thyng, then to medle with many thynges beyng
perfect in none. And yet as it is euydent to proue, it argueth no suche
thyng but rather the contrary: for he whose capacitie hath atayned,
to the perfect knowledge of any one part of science, is the better to bee
hoped in that he shall procede to the pure sincerite of all the reste. For
the phylosopher compareth the wytte of man vnto Iron: for as I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,
the more it is scoured the bryghter it is: so the wytte of man, the
more it is vsed or occupyed, is alwayse the finer and the better.</p>
   <p>Certaynly the remembrance of suche disdainful obiectiōs, (when I
had already finyshed this thyng) made me in doubte to put forth thys
worke: but that my frendes with whom I conferred my doynges,
earnestly perswaded me not to regarde the rage of enuye, so longe as
truthe would beare out it selfe, whyle tyme consumed bothe selander
and also enuy, the author of all reproche: and that I should in no case
cease to doe that should profite many, for the euell of a fewe: whiche
thynke it an hyghe poynt of knowledge, to munte and speake euell of
the doynges of all other, whyle they them selues doe nothynge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
to profite any.</p>
   <p>Seyng therfore I shall procede in this simple worke, I thynke it
good first to declare what names the learned Anatomistes haue geuen
to the body of mā. For though dyuers haue vsed the bodies of beastes
for Anatomies, yet seynge that the bodye of man is the subiect of our
worke, we (settynge a syde all other) wyll treate onlye of it. Whiche
is called in Greeke <hi>Mycro cosmos,</hi> in Laun <hi>Minor mundus,</hi> in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyshe
a lyttle worlde: because in the same (euen as in the frame of
the greate worlde) so manye wonders maye bee seene of natures
workes, to the hyghe honor and glorye of almyghtye God.</p>
   <p>Maye it not be proued, that the brayne (lyke vnto the heauens,)
<pb facs="147"/>
hangeth without any maner of staye or proppe, to holde vp the same?
nay, It is so euident, that euery learned Anatomiste wryteth of the
same, as a thyng not to be doubted of: and therfore iudge the same to
haue a certeyne lykenes with the heauenly nature. And as the world
hath two notable lyghtes to gouerne the same, namely the Sonne and
the Moone: so hath the body of man, planred lykewyse in the hyghest
place twoo lyghtes, called eyes: whiche are the lyghtes of the body, as
the Sonne and the Moone are the lyghtes of the worlde. And it is
also wrytten of some doctors, that the brayne hath .vii. concauites, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
instrumentes of the wyttes: which answere vnto the .vii. spheres
of the planetes. And to be briefe, it is a worlde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o beholde, and a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
wonder to thynke, that as great merueyles maye bee seene,
wrought by God in nature in this litle worlde man his body, as ther
is to be considered in any thyng in the vnyuersall great worlde, aboue
or benethe at any tyme.</p>
   <p>Secondly, it is called a common weale, for as muche as there is
therin conseyned as it were a ryghteous regiment, betwene a prynce
and this subiectes: as for example. Let vs call the harte of mā a king,
the brayne and the lyuer the chiefe gouernours vnder hym, the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mache
and the guttes, with other aperteinyng to nutrymente, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
of his courte, and all the members vniuersally his subiectes.
And then let vs see, if any man can deuyse any necessary instrument of
a common weale, nedefull for the wealth of the same, from the hyghest
to the lowest, that the lyke shall not be founde in the body of man: as
it is so well knowne, to all those that trauel in the knowledge of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie,
that I nede not here muche therof to wryte. Can it be percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
that the hande or the fote, or any part of them or such lyke (which
we may lyken to the labourers, or as some call them vyle mēbers of a
common weale,) at any tyme to resiste or rebel against the harte their
soueraigne lorde, or any other officer vnder hym their superiors? no
truly. The body of man is a common weale without rebellion: the
kyng so louyng his subiectes, and the subiectes so louyng their kyng,
that the one is euer redy to mynister vnto the other all thynges nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:
as if the harte by any occasion susteyne damage, as we may see in
the disease called <hi>Sincope,</hi> or swoundyng. At suche a tyme I saye the
face, the handes, and the fete, are founde colde and without felynge,
strengthe or lyfe: and what proueth it, but that as louynge and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
subiectes, they thynke nothyng theyr own wherof the harte hath
nede, whiche is their lorde and gouernor? yea they vtterly depryue thē
selues of altogether, to serue and please theyr lord. Immediatly as the
swoundyng ceaseth, the bloude resorteth to the face, she handes and the
feete are warme agayne: as it were benefites done, rendered agayne
with thankes and ioye. And is not suche a lorde and kyng worthye of
good subiectes, that for the helpe of one of the leaste of them, wyl spend
all that he hath, so long as lyte endureth? as if a mēber be hurte, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
any veyne or artery is cutte, the bloud or spirite will issue in suche
<pb facs="147"/>
wyse that it wyll not cease commyng thyther so longe as any is lette,
if it be not in tyme preuented. Oh kynd and gentyll gouernour, oh wel
wyllyng and obedient subiectes.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, the body of man is called in greeke <hi>Anthropos,</hi> &amp; in latin,
by interpretation <hi>Arbor euersa,</hi> as we myght saye in Englysh, a tree
turned vpside downe. For as a tree hath his roote in the earth, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng
with his body and branches from the earth vp towardes the
heauens: so contrariwyse, man hath his roote (whiche is the head)
vpwarde towardes the heauens, &amp; all other partes descendyng down<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards
to the earth: which standeth by good reason, that for this cause
man of al otherthinges vnder heauen should be most excellent, &amp; by the
vse of reason receiued of the soule (and of the same immortalitie) most
like vnto god.</p>
   <p>Consideryng therfore that the body of man is so precious, it shoulde
seme that the science that serueth to kepe the same in healthe, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store
health beyng loste to the same, should be a thyng of no smal value,
but rather of great regarde. Therfore as I iudge, they erre not that
esteme the medicinall arte next vnto diuinitie: for as muche as diuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
is the meane wherby the soule is saued, &amp; chirurgery the meane
to saue the body: whiche is next in value vnto the soule. Wherfore
as they which lytle esteme that arte, (wherof the office is so precious)
seme very vnwyse, and to wante vtterly the vse of reason: so is it a
great enormitie for any to enterpryse to vse that arte, not able to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende
the knowledge of the same.</p>
   <p>For the which cause, that I myght partly helpe younge studentes,
(as I am one my selfe) to the ataynyng of some perfectiō, I haue here
gathered a lytle worke, conteynyng three shorte treatyses of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy
or dissection of the partes of man his body. Wherin I wyl not
he so curious, as to take vpon me the precise numberyng of euery smal
and difficulte parte, nor to be exquisite in the dyuersitie of names: but
only shewyng suche number and names briefly, as serue moste to the
commodities of the chyrurgiens intelection, with an order of conduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
notes, howe to vse our handy worke of medicine, (called in greke
<hi>Chirurgia)</hi> vpon the body of man or any parte therof: whether it be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ncisions, cauterizations, bloudlettyng called phlebotomy, or ventosing
called also cuppyng or boxyng, scarification, or openyng of apostemes
on what parte of the body so euer it be, that none error be committed
in the same. For of the contrary, as of the vncunnyng doynges of any
of these, commeth dyuers dangers, as the depriuation and losse,
both of members and lyfe. And (as it may euidently apeare) for that
cause was the cutting out of dead bodies first put in vse: and the large
volumes wrytten therof by auncient authors, declare their intent to
be chiefly for that thing. So that as <hi>Guido</hi> affirmeth, Anatomy is .ij.
wayes to be learned, The first and beste by cuttyng of dead bodyes:
The seconde by doctrine wrytten in bookes.</p>
   <p>Of this later maner, we shall by the grace of God in this short trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyse
saye a lytle, as occasion serueth, and as the smalnes of the volume
<pb facs="148"/>
wyll geue me leaue. Beyng therto somwhat encouraged, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of good maister U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>carie, late sargeante chyrurgien to the que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
highnes: Who was the firste that euer wrote a treatyse of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie
in Englyshe, (to the profite of his brethren chirurgiens, and
the helpe of younge studentes,) as farre as I can learne. Wherin I
haue omytted narracion by tables or payntyng out of pyctures: thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng
it more profitable for learners, to exercyse the cuttyng out of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes
them selues, then to beholde the grauyng or paynting of others.
For Galen sayeth in his seconde boke of the vse of partes, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
wyll be a dyligent beholder of the workes of nature: It beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
hym not to beleue only bokes of Anatomie, but rather his owne
proper eyes.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding if hereafter it shal seme good to my frendes, that
I I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erate this worke with augmentations: I wyll surely not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse
to doe whatsoeuer shalbe thought profitable to the cōmon weale,
and commodious to the studentes in this arte. Wherin I desire the
studious readers not to iudge of me, that I trust euer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more to mine
owne iudgementes, because I haue so boldly done this thyng, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
that as I affirme all that I alledge by authoritie, so woulde I
gladly be taught where I make any fault, of those y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> are my betters.
For I esteme not my head so good, neither thynke I it so cleare and
voyde of error, that I should in this worke be so exquisite as to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
all men in their variable iudgementes: but verily thynkyng my self
faynt of perfection, desiryng in my harte that the faultes of this my
worke, may cause some man of charitie to sette forthe a more excellent
worke, to dashe this out of name and countenance: so that I myghte
therby be instructed of that whiche I longe moste for, earnestly desire,
and thirste to learne.</p>
   <p>If this my simple worke may geue that occasion, at the leste I shal
hartely reioyce therin: for though I be vnperfect, yet if myne vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectnes
may be a cause of perfection, bothe vnto my selfe and other: it
were as I suppose a good chāce. For (as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diuines interprete) the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belefe
of Thomas, was a great helpe to the faythe of vs all that come
after: for because of his vnfaythfulnes Christe shewed hym selfe, &amp; his
precious woundes also, after his resurection: whiche caused not only
Thomas to beleue vnfaynedly, but vs all to be put out of doubt &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayned
of the glorious resurection of our mercie seate Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.
Whom I moste hartely beseche to kepe you moste gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
that wytsafe me your good wyll and fauourable reporte.
And to sende both vnto you and me, (through the shy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
beames of his eternall grace,) A bryght, cleare,
and frutefull vnderstandyng of that whiche
we moste earnestly couet to
learne. Amen.
(∴)</p>
   <pb facs="148"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>