<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Addicion, to fill vp vacant pages.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109091_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14279</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109091</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Addicion, to fill vp vacant pages.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrinal of princes made by the noble oratour Isocrates, [and] translated out of Greke in to Englishe by syr Thomas Eliot knight</title>
                 <author>Isocrates</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="addendum">
   <head>Addicion, to fill vp vacant pages.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ul truely writeth Salomon, The herte of the kynge is in the hande of god, and whiche wai so euer he willeth he shal incline it: but the very laude of a good kynge is, if he againe incline his herte to god, the kynge of all kynges, alwaie bendyng to his will, without whose fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable
<pb n="19" facs="19"/>aide, mans indeuour can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge dooe: and so frameth all his actes, as knowlageyng and myndyng, that what so euer he dooeth, he dooeth it before his eies, who is no lesse iudge ouer kynges then ouer common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Nothyng is truely prosperous, nothynge can be called welthy, that the authour of all felicitee wyll not vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to make fortunate. Most luckely, moste happily it is doone, what so euer is doone accordynge to his wyll, who saieth: By me kynges do reigne, and the lawe makers decerne iuste thinges: by me princes rule, and mighty men iudge iust thynges. This saide the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wisedome, whiche is the sonne of God. What prescribeth Sapience to kynges? Mercy (saieth she) and Trouthe doe kepe the kynge: and his Throne is made stronge with clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. He sheweth Mercie in succouryng the oppressed: Trouthe in iudgeyng
<pb facs="20"/>truely. Clemencie in temperyng the seueritee of the lawes with lenitee.</p>
   <p>The speciall duetie, and whervnto kynges were wonte to bee sworne, whan thei beganne their reigne, was this, to helpe widowes, to succour the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlesse, and to deliuer and defende all that are oppressed frō iniurie. Trouthe hath two companions, Sapience and Constance. Sapience geueth light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eies: wherby is perceiued, what is right, and what not, what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the weale publyke, and what is contrarie to it. Constancie causeth, that the mynde, ouercomyng all coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touse desires, neither with ire, nor with loue, nor with hatred, is moued from honestie. Clemencie tempereth with lenitee necessarie Seueritee. Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is not foorthwith to goe in hande with warre, whan cause of warre is geuen, but to leaue no reasonable meane vnassaied, to see whether the
<pb n="20" facs="20"/>matter maie bee determined without warre. And otherwhile it is better to dissemble the iniurie, than to reuenge it by force of armes. It is Clemencie, if by no meanes it maie be eschewed, so to make warre, that as littell hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine bloudde be spilte as can be, and that the warres be ended as shortely as maie be. For this wisedome, that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all good thynges with it, Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praied for, that she shulde alwaie bee assistent to his Throne, as a moste faithfull and trusty counsailour.</p>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>