<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ABSTRACTS AND ADVERTISEMENTS concerning the Contents of this HISTORIE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109765_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20577</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6982</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109765</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ABSTRACTS AND ADVERTISEMENTS concerning the Contents of this HISTORIE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of the ancient and moderne estate of the principality of Wales, dutchy of Cornewall, and earldome of Chester : Collected out of the records of the Tower of London, and diuers ancient authours. By Sir Iohn Dodridge Knight, late one of his Maiesties iudges in th Kings Bench. And by himselfe dedicated to King Iames of euer blessed memory</title>
                 <author>Doddridge, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Emerson (Emondson, Edmonds), Godfrey</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 142, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>ABSTRACTS AND ADVERTISEMENTS concerning the Contents of this HISTORIE.</head>
   <div n="Wales" type="part">
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He originall and antient estate of <hi>Wales,</hi> before, and vntill the Conquest thereof by King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the First, in the eleuenth yeere of his Raigne.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>Carnaruon,</hi> (so called because he was born at <hi>Carnaruon</hi> Castle in <hi>VVales)</hi> and sonne to King <hi>Edward</hi> the First, consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> and the policy vsed therein by King <hi>Edward</hi> the First.</p>
      <p>The creation of <hi>Edward,</hi> sirnamed the <hi>blacke Prince,</hi> to be Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> and the antient manner of the inuesture of the Princes of <hi>VVales.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The strange limitation of the estate of the Lands of the said Principality, and the reasons
<pb facs="6"/>
thereof, and the difference betweene the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality of <hi>VVales,</hi> and the Dutchy of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi> for the eldest sonne and heire apparant of the King of <hi>England,</hi> is Duke of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi> as soone as be is borne, or as soone as his father is King of <hi>England.</hi> But he is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Prince of <hi>VVales</hi> by a speciall creation, inuesture, and donation of the lands thereunto belonging, and not by birth.</p>
      <p>The yeerely value of the reuenues of the Principality of <hi>VVales,</hi> as the same were in the bands of the Prince, commonly called the <hi>blacke Prince.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>Richard</hi> sirnamed of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> sonne of the said <hi>blacke Prince,</hi> was after the death of his father, created Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> at <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering,</hi> at the Bower, in the Countie of <hi>Essex,</hi> by <hi>E</hi> 3. his Grandfather.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Munmouth,</hi> sonne to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, created Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> he was afterwards King, by the name of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fift.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Edward,</hi> the sonne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixt, created Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Chester,</hi> and for that hee was then very
<pb facs="6"/>
yong, there was ordained by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what allowance should bee made vnto the said Prince for his Wardrobe, seruants wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and other necessary expences, vntill the said Prince should be of fourteene yeers of age.</p>
      <p>There was also a Counsaile of diuers ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable personages, as Bishops, Earles, and others for the gouernement and direction of the reuenues of the said Prince, which dispose the same accordingly, with the assent and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Queene, who was also especially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in that behalfe.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Edward,</hi> the sonne and heire apparant of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, created Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> and a Councell of honourable perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages allowed to him also for the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his reuenues, and the Lord <hi>Riuers,</hi> Vncle by the mothers side of the Prince, was appointed Gouernour of the Person of the said Prince.</p>
      <p>The creation of <hi>Arthure,</hi> sonne and heire apparant to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenth, to bee Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> the Copie of the Charter of that creation obserued for the forme and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of penning thereof, and the names of the
<pb facs="7"/>
Councellors that were assigned vnto him.</p>
      <p>After the death of Prince <hi>Arthure, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> his brother, who was afterwards King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, was created Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> after whose time there are no Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters found of the creation of any Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> although King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixt, in the life of his Father, and Queene <hi>Mary</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the name of Prince generall: and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why this discourse hitherunto is drawne after an historicall manner.</p>
      <p>
         <label>After the said historicall discourse.</label> Three things are further considered of, <hi>viz.</hi> First, in what manner and order the said Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie and Marches of <hi>Wales</hi> were gouerned and directed vnder the Princes of <hi>Wales,</hi> as well before, as after the <hi>English</hi> Conquests thereof: wherein by the way are noted, the Courts of Iustice of the said principality of <hi>Wales,</hi> the originall of the Baronyes Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: and when the first Councell was establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in the Marches of <hi>Wales</hi> vnto <hi>England,</hi> and in what manner the same was done, and the commodities ensuing thereof; which vnion or annexation may serue in some respect, as a
<pb facs="7"/>
president in other cases of like consequence.</p>
      <p>The second principall thing proposed, is the consideration of the antient and moderne Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the said principality, seruing the Lord <hi>Prince,</hi> and none others, and what fees and sallaries were allowed vnto them.</p>
      <p>The third principall matter is the present reuenues of the principality of <hi>Wales,</hi> as the same was in charge before the Auditors this last yeere past, <hi>viz.</hi> the fortie foure yeere of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="Cornwall" type="part">
      <head>The Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>The Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall</hi> was the first erected Dutchie in <hi>England</hi> after the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> conquest, and made to be a Dutchie in the eleuenth yeere of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, and giuen to his eldest sonne, commonly called the <hi>blacke Prince,</hi> who was the first Duke in <hi>Cornewall</hi> after the Conquest, to him and to his first begotten sonnes and heires apparant of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and the difference that is betweene the Principalitie of <hi>Wales</hi> and the said Dutchie.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="8"/>At what age of the Duke of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> Liuery may bee made vnto him of the said Dutchy.</p>
      <p>Moreouer touching the said Dutchie of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> three things are considered; First, what reuenues were bestowed vpon the said Dutchy, for the erection thereof, both annuall and casuall, and the particulars thereof: the seuerall natures and differences of them in the construction of the Law, together with the Stanneryes and coynage of Tynne, and the lawes, vsages, and customes of the said Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryes concerning the managing of Tynne.</p>
      <p>The diuers kindes of Tynners and Tynne, and the coynage of Tynne is, and for what cause due and payable, and the priuiledges that the King and Duke of <hi>Cornewall</hi> haue in their preemption of Tynne.</p>
      <p>The reuenues of the Dutchie of <hi>Cornewall</hi> as it is rated by suruey taken in the fifth yeere of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third.</p>
      <p>The reuenues of the said Dutchie of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi> as it was in the fifteenth yeere of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight.</p>
      <p>The reuenues of the said Dutchie, as it was
<pb facs="8"/>
in account vnto the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in the 44. yeere of her raigne, which is the last account, and the cleere yeerely value thereof, as it may be drawne to an estimation annuall, appeareth.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="Chester" type="part">
      <head>The Countie Palatine of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Flint.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>The third principall reuenue belonging to the Prince, as Earle of <hi>Chester,</hi> which Earledome is a Countie Palatine.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Edward</hi> sirnamed the <hi>blacke Prince,</hi> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Earle of <hi>Chester,</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third his Father, in the seauenth yeere of the said King <hi>Edward</hi> the Thirds raigne.</p>
      <p>The totall reuenue of the said Countie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Flint,</hi> as it was in the 44. yeere of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The antient reuenues of the said Earledome of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Flint,</hi> as the same were in the fifth yeere of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="9"/>The reasons why in this History diuers an tiquities (not vulgarly knowne) are discouered concerning the Principality of <hi>VVales,</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> and Earledome of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Inconueniens erit omissis initijs atque origine non repetita, atqueillotis (vt ita dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erim) manibus, protinus materiam tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</q>
      <bibl>Ex lege prima Digestorū Iuris Ciuilis, titulo de origine Iuris.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>