<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Honourable THEOPHILVS HOVVARD, Lord HOVVARD of Walden, sonne and heire apparent to the Right Honorable Earle of Suffolke, Lord Chamber∣laine to his Maiestie.</title>
           <author>Digges, Dudley</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109705_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20463</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6872</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109705</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Honourable THEOPHILVS HOVVARD, Lord HOVVARD of Walden, sonne and heire apparent to the Right Honorable Earle of Suffolke, Lord Chamber∣laine to his Maiestie.</title>
                 <author>Digges, Dudley</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foure paradoxes, or politique discourses : 2 concerning militarie discipline, written long since by Thomas Digges Esquire. 2 of the worthinesse of warre and warriors, by Dudly Digges, his sonne. All newly published to keepe those that will read them, as they did them that wrote them, from idlenesse</title>
                 <author>Digges, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 111, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Honourable THEOPHILVS <hi>HOVVARD,</hi> Lord <hi>HOVVARD</hi> of Walden, sonne and heire apparent to the Right Honorable Earle of Suffolke, Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine to his Maiestie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Generall report (worthy Lord) of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable disposition bred in mee euen at my first cōming into France, an earnest desire to see you, which through your courtesy &amp; my good fortune was happily effected: But when I perceiued with what vertuous industrie you indeauored to make the best vse, of your wel spent time, in those parts; I cōceiued great hope to receiue much greater contentment, in so truly honourable acquaintance, and the tast I had of your fauours assureth me I had beene happy in my hopes, had not my vntimely returne, such were my vnfortunate crosses, depriued mee of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort I tooke, in the company of your admired vertue. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing I haue hitherto fed my selfe with the hope of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne &amp;c. <hi>Hoc equidem occasum Troiae tristesque rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas solabor,</hi> this shall bee my refuge. In the meane time as <hi>Lewes</hi> of <hi>France</hi> did his country friends rape roote, or as the <hi>Percian</hi> King did the poore mans Apple, I intreat your Lordship to accept these sleight discourses as a token of the dutifull respect I owe you: They are I know most vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your Maiden patronage, yet my first fruites they bee, and I earnestly desire, that my first borne should beare your honours Name.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors deuoted</hi> Dudly Digges.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>