<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE FOVRE HONOV∣RABLE SOCIETIES, AND famous Nurseries of Law, the Innes of COVRT.</title>
           <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109406_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05323</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15466</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE FOVRE HONOV∣RABLE SOCIETIES, AND famous Nurseries of Law, the Innes of COVRT.</title>
                 <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Innes of Court anagrammatist: or, The masquers masqued in anagrammes : Expressed in epigramique lines, upon their severall names, set downe in the next page. Composed by Francis Lenton Gent. one of her Majesties poets</title>
                 <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lash, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE FOVRE HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE SOCIETIES, AND famous Nurseries of Law, the Innes of <hi>COVRT.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou Noble stockes of Gentry, Plants that higher</l>
   <l>Grow, till you unto the Cedars height aspire:</l>
   <l>You creame o'th kingdome, either in your wealth,</l>
   <l>Wit, learning, valour, or iust lawes lov'd health,</l>
   <l>Who, by your worthy breedings, births, and blood,</l>
   <l>Are chose for Guarders of your Countries good:</l>
   <l>And to that end are here trayn'd up by Fate,</l>
   <l>To be the glory of great Brittaines state:</l>
   <l>I here present you with the Masquers names</l>
   <l>Of your foure Houses, in quick Anagrams,</l>
   <l>Led by that then made Knight, who first I place</l>
   <l>In these conceits, as Captaine of that grace;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>Which each of you deserv'd, and in high merits,</l>
   <l>Shew'd <hi>Englands</hi> Gallantry, and Noble spirits.</l>
   <l>Accept my Muse then, which shall make you merry,</l>
   <l>Like rich Nepenthe, Nectar, or old Sherry;</l>
   <l>And for your grace that way, my best endeavour</l>
   <l>By hand, head, heart, shall waite on you for ever:</l>
   <l>Let not rash anger then, blame my intent,</l>
   <l>To gaine your loves with mirth, I onely meant.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>The true honourer of your persons, pedigrees, and dignities, FRA. LENTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>