<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>


The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1535</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109685_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06515</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16988</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109685</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>


The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here after ensueth a propre treatyse of good workes</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1535</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>316 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
</figure>
      <pb facs="2"/>
The preface.</head>
   <p>IT is not vnknowen to all men (good chrysten reader) but that the true &amp; syncere teachers of the infallyble truthe of our sauyour Iesu Chryst, ben falsely defamed vnto the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned people, &amp; theyr good name defaced to the, no lytell hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and reproche of the same truth / in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they (as they be borne in hāde vniustly) shulde in theyr wrytynges and sermons, allure and withdrawe the forsayd rude people from penaūce, frō prayer, from fastyng, from watchynge, frō paynes, from labours / &amp; fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally from all good work{is}. But what they ben and theyr workes also whiche reproue, sclaunder, calumpnyate, and falsely impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the pure, syncere, and true worde of god pronounced by the mouthes of those his good and
<pb facs="3"/>
vertuous seruauntes / it is nowe (thanked be god) ryghte metely well perceyued / ye and for what intent, truely for none other, thā for the mayntenaunce of the god theyr belyes, theyr ambycyon, theyr symony, theyr pryde, theyr promocyon, theyr treason, theyr trechery, theyr glotony, theyr le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherye, theyr murdre, with all theyr vngracyousnes. God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moste good and almyghtye of his excedynge and bountefull mercy and grace, to declare and set forth his infinyte goodnes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes his electe, moste welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued and faythful seruauntes / that they to theyr great conforte and consolacyon, may be proued innocent of this most vntrue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusacyon wrongfully layde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theyr charge / and chiefely to the garnysshynge and deckynge
<pb facs="3"/>
of his emperyall glory, &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaūce of his vndoubtable tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, hathe sent the here (O reder) a ryghte famous and excellent worke, wherin is comprehended what good workes be / howe we may please god in all oure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / &amp; howe our workes do not please hym, and out of what foū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne they ought to spryng and flowe, yf they shulde please his godhede: truely out of the fres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>she and lyuyng fountayne of an vndoubted faythe &amp; truste / that his moste benygne petye, swet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and gentylnes, which is the father of all mercyes, &amp; the god of all consolacyon and conforte / dothe loue the, fauoure the, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye the, accepte the. And thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes also done at his cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the blode, passyon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcyon, and satysfaccyon of
<pb facs="4"/>
his moste dere and welbeloued sone Iesu Chryst / in whome, by whome, and for whose sake thou arte thus entyerly loued, fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and accepted. As wytnessed our father of heuen hym selfe at the baptysme of our sauyour Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>su Christe, sayenge. This is my welbeloued sone, in whom or for whose sake I am well pleased, that is to say, appeased and swa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged of my wrathe, immedyately here hym, that is to saye, beleue, truste hym, stycke &amp; cleaue harde to hym by faythe. For it is he for whom I delyte in you, loue you, fauour you, petye you, &amp; accepte bothe you and your dedes. This is the fountayne, out of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che all the workes of a chrysten man oughte to procede / so that what soeuer buddeth out of the tre of this fayth, is accepted and
<pb facs="4"/>
pleasaunte before god / and els it is but synne and not accepted. As saynte Paule wryteth in the xiiii. chapytre to the Romaynes / what soeuer (sayth he) is not of faythe is synne. And in the .xi. chapytre to the Hebrues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faythe it is impossyble for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to please god. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why is this, albeit thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowe neuer so moche in almes / fast neuer so moch, paye neuer so moch, watche neuer so moch / yea albeit thou haddest done as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good dedes as all the worlde. Yet yf thou haue not the faythe before rehersyd / that god for the blode of his sone doth accept the &amp; thy workes / loue the, fauoure the, petye the / yea and that enty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly and as his owne son &amp; heyre by adopcyon, all that euer thou doste can not please god / but is
<pb facs="5"/>
abomynable synne and dysplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syth hym vtterly. For howe is it possyble that thou shuldest plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se hym, whan thou art but a Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>das vnto hym &amp; doste beare two faces in one hoode / doynge one and thynkynge another. In thy dedes thou woldeste seme to be his seruaunte, &amp; in thy hert thou dost neyther loue hym, nor truste that he loueth the. And albeit he hathe made neuer so many and great {pro}myses of saluacyon, mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye, loue, pety, and fauour, in the blod of his sone to al that repent &amp; doubt not therof / but assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truste vnto it, yet thou (what soeuer thou arte that haste not this fayth) lyke an hethen houn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and an vnfaythfaull myscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt, by thy infydelyte and false herte dost make no better of hym but a lyer, and false of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myse
<pb facs="5"/>
/ a tyraunte, and a butchers curre delytyng in blode, and ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther doste thou loue hym, truste hym, nor fauour hym. For howe shuldest thou loue hym, whan thou accōptest no better of hym than I haue sayde. And agayne howe is it possyble that he shuld loue the, fauoure the, petye the, accepte other the or thy workes, seynge thou doste fyrste abiecte hym by thy synful dyspayre and incredulytie. Yea what worldlye prince wold kepe such a wretche in his house yf he knewe hym / howe moche lesse than wolde he loue hym, fauoure hym, accepte hym, or any of his seruyce. Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynste suche workes it is that the true and faythfull mynysters of Chrystes worde haue foughten, as done in most false hypocrysye and deuelysshe despayre, whiche
<pb facs="6"/>
otherwyse they haue &amp; do hyghe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prayse and cōmende, as whan they be done in true faythe and loue towarde god &amp; his cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, as thou shalte se and fynde in this moste goodly and excellente volume of good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / whiche (I beseche god ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to fauour me) yf any of those vntrue men / I wyll not saye, false deceyuers, dyd euer wryte to teach any thyng halfe so good in theyr lyues. But it is an olde prouerbe that a good thyng wyl prayse it selfe / wherfore I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte it vnto thyne owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment (good reader) to prayse it, euer as thou shalte fynde cause / So bolde I am of the goodnes therof. And yf thou fynde my word{is} to be true, that good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be here of our auctor requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, taught, praysed, and cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="6"/>
to the vttermost, (as the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the is) then I beseche the (moste gentyll and indyfferent reader) to take &amp; admytte all false backe byters &amp; sclaunderers of goddes true mynysters euermore here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after as they be, &amp; not to thynke the contrary, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as they most deadely belye those good men in this behalfe / so they do also in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges, as I truste in god it shall more playnly appere / bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the to the (gentyll reader) &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to all the worlde in tyme com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng. And that as I beleue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned to the great glorye of the lyuyng god, the inestymable so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace and comforte of his electe chyldren, and the vtter confusy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the chyldren of Antechrist? So be it.</p>
   <trailer>¶Here endeth the preface of this present worke.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>