<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❀ Prologue of the Translatour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109656_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21216</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109656</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❀ Prologue of the Translatour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The knight of the swanne : Here beginneth the history of the noble Helyas knyght of the Swanne, newly translated out of Frensshe in to Englysshe at thinstygacion of the puyssaunt [and] illustryous Prynce Lorde Edwarde Duke of Buckyngham</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Copland, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>148 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❀ Prologue of the Translatour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Erytably it is that all vertues and noble in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tencions ben nourysshed &amp; engendred in the hertes and courages of gentyl persons, the which causeth them to enclyne to all perfec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of bounte. Endeueryng thē to heare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>and auaunce the gloryous renowne of theyr foregoer, predecessours replenisshed with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> grace and loue of god Amonge all other endewed with bountie and noblesse ī hygh dygne and Illustryous prynce my lorde Edward by the grace of god Duke of Buckyngham Erle of Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, Stafforde, and of Northampton desyringe cotydy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally to encrease and augment the name and fame of such as were relucent in vertuous feates and triumphaunte actes of chyualry. And to encourage and styre euery lus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and gentell herte by the exemplyficacyon of the same hauyng a goodli booke of the highe and miraculous his<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori of a famous &amp; puyssaunt kinge named Oryant som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time reynynge in the parties of beyonde the sea hauynge to his wife a noble Lady of whome she conceiued sixe son<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and a Doughter &amp; chylded of them at one onely tym at whose byrthe echone of them had a chayne of Syluer at their neckes the whiche were all tourned by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydence of god into whyte Swannes (saue one) of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che this present Hystory compyled, named Helyas the knight of the swanne of whome linially is dyscended my sayde Lorde. The whiche ententifly to haue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayde his<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory more amply and vnyuersally knowen in thys hys
<pb facs="2"/> natif countrie as it is in other, hath of hys hie bountie bi some of his faithful &amp; trusti seruauntes cohorted mi may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster wynkin de worde to put the said vertuous hystori in printe. And he as willing and glad to content accomplish &amp; obey the gracious mynde and pleasure, hath sough and found a true approued copie, enprinted and corrected in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> frenssh language, at whose instigaciō &amp; stirrīg (I Robert Copland) haue me applied moienīg the helpe of god to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce and translate it into our maternal &amp; vulgare english tonge, after the capacite and rudenesse of my weke enten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demet. Beseceing my sayd lorde &amp; consequently al them y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> redeth or hereth it red to take no regard to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lāguag mis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>orned and rude, for wythout hygh style &amp; enerue industry I haue al onely verbated &amp; folowed mine auctour as ny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe as I coulde w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> profoūdite of good herte, and where as oni faute bi me or wrong Impressiō be foūd intelligi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly after their science to correct and amēd in pardonīg al ygnoraunce. In the whiche doynge I shalbe oblygate &amp; boūde to praie for thē to almighti God that he geue vnto them his realme celestiall vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which we al mai come Amen.</p>
   <trailer>Explicit prologus.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>