<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader whatsoeuer, T. L. sendeth greeting.</title>
           <author>L., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109564_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06164</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16655</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109564</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader whatsoeuer, T. L. sendeth greeting.</title>
                 <author>L., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diuel coniured</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mattes, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>92 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader whatsoeuer, <hi>T. L.</hi> sendeth greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous, sith you haue long time drawn the weeds of my wit, and fed your selues with the cockle of my conceits, I haue at last made you gleaners of my haruest and partakers of my experience. Here shall you find that which <hi>Aristotle</hi> requireth in euery science, probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in argument, and demonstration and truth in the end: here shal you find the stile varieng according to the matter, the matter sutable to the stile, and all of these aimed to profit: The reading hereof requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Tota hominem, &amp; non distractum,</hi> for there is as much lost in slighting ouer, as won by perusing warelie; if the title make you suspect, compare it with the matter, it will answer you: if the matter, apply it with the censures of the learned, they will countenance the same; if the handling, I repent me not, for I had rather you should now condemn me for default in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricke, then as in times past, commend my stile, and lament my iudgement: neither let it seeme displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, that herein I affect not vain flourish, for that I am experienced in this point of the law, that the mind is mightier then the words; beside, this is a certaine
<pb facs="4"/>
principle, <hi>Vbi mens est certa, de verbis non cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> The Poet saw this, when he song thus:
<q>
         <l>Ornari res, ipsa negat contenta doceri.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Thus resolued both of the matter, and satisfied in my method, I leaue the whole to your iudgements, which if they be not depraued with enuie, wil be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in knowledge, and if not carried away with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, will receiue much profit. For as the Apothica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vseth his drugs, so do I my delights, I make no protestation or show of the purest and best simples, but for those conceits are shrunke in the wetting, spoild by the hast, &amp; are corrupted by irregard, those wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting matter to sol themselues, had need of good words to sute them: play you therefore the wise marchants, buy not that only which delighteth the eie, and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the eare, but buy that which perfecteth the iudgement and enricheth the memorie. The thought that is light, tempteth the mind and vanisheth, but those principles that hasten our experience, perfit our memories. These considered, read, iudge, and vse me as best pleaseth you; for to beshort, my scope is your profit, and my good <hi>Genius,</hi> your praise and incouragement.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all profitable delights. T. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>