<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Generous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109190_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109190</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Generous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The knave in graine, new vampt : A witty comedy, acted at the Fortune many dayes together with great applause. Written by J.D. Gent</title>
                 <author>J. D., gent</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Nicholson, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Generous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, the ancient Latin Adage is, <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum,</hi>
but I say <hi>Nebulonum plena sunt omnia,</hi>
Knaves be about all persons, and in all places.
There are twelve Coat-Cards in the bunch, of
which foure are Knaves, Heart, Diamond, Spade,
Club, suiting with the foure C C C C: Court, City, Country,
Campe: My purpose is not to touch any in particular; onely
thus much of them in generall: some are notable, some notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
some pimping, some panderly Knaves; some prating, some
pestilent; some cousening, some cunny-catching Knaves. There
are also lazy and lying, base, and deboist, fantasticall, foolish, and
false Knaves. To these we may adde Hereticall and Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
schismaticall, and separisticall Knaves: not forgetting
perjur'd, and shamelesse; impudent, and informing; arrogant,
and arrant Knaves, <hi>Cum multis alijs.</hi> And besides these, I
have heard of a Knave Tapster, a Knave Ostler, a Knave Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant,
and a Knave Broker: but with these we have nothing to
doe at this time; onely with a Knave in graine, or a Knave
new vampt, in decyphering of whom, I give all the rest this
Caveat, <hi>Have amongst you my Masters:</hi> And now if any of
the rest shall finde himselfe touch't, hee hath his mends in his
owne hands, for he cannot say but I gave him faire warning.
And so much of the Argument, the Act followes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>