<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>

¶ Here foloweth a notable treatyse and full neces¦sary to all crysten men for to knowe and it is na∣med the Ordynarye of Crystyanyte or of crysten men. ¶ Here foloweth the Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1502</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109058_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18687</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5198</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109058</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>

¶ Here foloweth a notable treatyse and full neces¦sary to all crysten men for to knowe and it is na∣med the Ordynarye of Crystyanyte or of crysten men. ¶ Here foloweth the Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here foloweth a notable treatyse and full necessary to an crysten men for to knowe and it is named the Ordynarye of crystyanyte or of crysten men</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Worde, Wynkyn de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1502</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>508 pages, woodcut illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
</figure>
¶ Here foloweth a notable treatyse and full neces<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sary to all crysten men for to knowe and it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Ordynarye of Crystyanyte or of crysten men. ¶ Here foloweth the Prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very creature resonable vnto who me god hath gyuen mynde &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandynge &amp; wyll. Hym ought to knowe serue &amp; loue with all his myght as moche for the goodnes and noblenes of his creacyon as
<pb facs="6"/>
well as of his redempcyon &amp; of the glory that we trust in. The whiche thynges be so grete &amp; good that no herte them may thynke ne tonge can them declare. Also he ought to be fered for to eschewe y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> payne of eternall dampnacyon. The whiche is so horryble a thynge oonly to ymagen that there is none erthely herte that by a thousande yeres yf he so longe sholde lyue vpon erthe / but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euery daye he ought to tremble. And these paynes we may not eschewe ne the goodes of eternall glorye haue ne possed. Yf we be not obedyent vnto our creatour in kepynge our vowe &amp; baptem / and in accomplys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shynge all his cōmaundementēs. The whiche to<note place="margin">Si vis ad vitam ingredi serua mā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>data. Math<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>xx.</note> knowe &amp; vnderstande euery man ought to put al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so grete dilygence &amp; more / as he doth for to saue his corporell lyf. For otherwyse he may not longe<note place="margin">Cōfitebor tibi in directōe cordis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eo {quam} didi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia iusticie tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. ps. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>xviii.</note> go eschewynge synne nor of the fautes cōmytted ayenst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wyll of god hym clense repent &amp; confesse. And for as moche vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> blessyd trynyte the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the fader y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sone &amp; the holy goost one essence of deite / and for the helth of soules that the swete<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mo corinth. xiiiii In ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o qn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>a sensu meo loqui vt et alios <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> {quam} decē mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia verbo &amp; lengua</note> Jhesus hath with his holy blood agayne bought / Foloweth a breue doctryne true &amp; catholyque and ryght necessary for the instruccyon &amp; saluacyon of crysten men. In the whiche shall be spoken pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypally of fyue thyng{is}. Of the whiche sayth saynt Poule in the fyrst epystle ad Corinthios / that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it is worth and profyteth vnto the saluacyon of soules fyue wordes then. x. thousande. And vpon<note place="margin">Hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mū scientes {quam} veniēt ī nouissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis die{bus} ī decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione illusores iux<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta {pro}<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>as {con}cupiscē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias ambulātes &amp;c .ii. petri vitimo. ii. thi. iiii. Erit em̄ tē puscū sanā doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nā nō sustinebunt sʐ ad sua dsideria coaceruabunt sibi magistros purien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes auri{bus} &amp; <abbr>vitare</abbr>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dē auditū auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēt ad fabulas au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem <abbr>{con}uertent</abbr> &amp;c. Itē. ii. pet. ii. ca. fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erūt vero &amp; {per}seudo {pro}phete in pptō si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut &amp; in vobis erūt magistri mē daces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> itroducēt sectas {per}diriois &amp;c. et in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaricia fic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s <abbr>vbis</abbr> de vobis negocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur.</note> that sayth Nycolas de lyre that of these fyue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the whiche vnderstandeth. saynt Poule. The
<pb facs="6"/>
fyrst is of the artycles of the fayth. The seconde of the cōmaūdementes of the lawr. The thyrde of synnes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche a man ought to eschewe. The fourthe of the paynes of helle the whiche a man ought to fere. And the fyfth of the glory the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is without ende that euery man ought to desy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. Of these fyue thynges in example of the holy apostell ought to wryte preche &amp; teche all they that wyll please god / and vnto these soules proufyte / &amp; all ryght faythfull crysten men / the whiche haue desyre to come vnto saluacyon hym ought aboue all thynges to rede or here. For whoos deth the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary hath in hym the sygne of eternall dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / as they that loue better Romayns of warr{is}. of bataylles / wrytynges of poetes / &amp; of these phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophres erthely. The whiche make not the lyues &amp; examples of holy sayntes and other holy wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges that touchen the dede of conscyence and of theyr saluacyon / and man sayth that wylfully su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che people renneth after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prechers the whiche pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypaly secheth to speke vnto the worldely people for to go with theyr substaūce &amp; syluer / the whiche oftentymes inplye the mynde of them worldely in hye harde &amp; curyous questyons / &amp; by the swetnesse of fayre speche they wrape them &amp; brynge them to theyr ende. So as prophecyed saynt Poule in the pystle vnto the bysshop Thimothee sayeng the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me shall come that the worlde wyl no more of the good doctryne and salutary / but they shall desyre maysters that them shall tell &amp; preche thynges cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous &amp; fables the whiche vnto them shall be plea
<pb facs="7"/>
saūt. Of the whiche synners wryteth saynt Peter in spekyng vnto crysten men / &amp; sayth that so as it was of the people of the Jewes fals &amp; cursyd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes sȳners / so vnto them shall it come for ther shall come &amp; aryse amonge them some maysters full of falsenes of cursydnes &amp; of disceyte the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che shall gyue vnto the people occasyon of theyr pardicyon. And many shall take and folowe the pathes &amp; the wayes of theyr adulteracyon. ¶ Here<note place="margin">Semen est verbū dei. Luce. viii.</note> sayth mayster Nycholas de lyra that the worde of god is the seed / he than that soweth this seed for auaryce or for pryde pryncypally renoūceth y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of god his creatour / and many ther shall be the<note place="margin">Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> ad galla. i. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> adhuc homi{bus} placerē xp̄i seru{us} nō essē. p̄s. Cōfus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sūt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> hoī{bus} plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ dniam dn̄s spreuit eos.</note> whiche shall here gladly here suche prechours not pryncypally for theyr saluacyon or for to correcte theyr vyces or synnes / but for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> swete &amp; fayre lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage of theyr phylosophy &amp; these newe thynges &amp; curyous the whiche they shall fayne for theyr excu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se and inuencyon / and by this forme &amp; maner the waye of god &amp; of trouth that is of the cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes<note place="margin">Math. viii. Atten dite a falsis {pro}phe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ūt ad vos in vestimē<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> ouiū. et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eta. Item surgēt pseu do xp̄i &amp; pseudo {pro}<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete et seducent multos.</note> &amp; of the artycles of the fayth shall be blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed of suche maner of worldely people curyo{us} the whiche shall disprayse these prechours of the symplenes of the gospell. And for so moche sayth saynt Gregory that none is wylfully herde yf he please not vnto the herers. Some of these prechers of the gospell consyderynge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> predicacyon of these<note place="margin">Item Actuū. xx. Attendite vobis &amp; vniuerso gregi in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vos spūssanctus posuit ep̄os rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>am dei quā ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>siuit sāguiesuo</note> worldely maysters afore sayd to be praysed &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syred &amp; theyr predycacyon dyspraysed shall them enforce to do ayenst them &amp; them to folowe in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgynge phylosophres poetes &amp; other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>octrynes
<pb facs="7"/>
not of the gospell / by the whiche they shall fall in thraldome of the deuyll of helle / &amp; in the bonde of<note place="margin">Ego scio q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>būt post discessio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nē meā lupi rapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>os nō par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes gregi et ex vobisipsis consur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</note> god our creatour. For the holy goost sayth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they that desyre worldely pleasures in the curyosyte &amp; vanyte of theyr desyre come to grete confusyon / the gospell &amp; these other holy wrytynges in many places vs forbydde ayenst the temptacyon of the<note place="margin">Qui nō est mecū {con}tra me ē. Luc. ix.</note> fals euyl &amp; disceyuable prechours / the whiche shal be the token &amp; pronosticacyon of the Antecryst as we haue late seen by many experyence &amp; in specyal<note place="margin">Diuisio presentis opuscult.</note> w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>in these fyfty yeres &amp; shall be seen / so that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue from ylle vnto the worst vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reygne of the fals Antecryst. And I vnderstande of those sȳners that do &amp; lyue otherwyse then that / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our moder the holy chirche vnto them hath lymytted &amp; ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in Sexte of the Decretales in the Chapytre. Cum ex eo. And in tho. vij. in the Chapytre the whiche begynneth. Abusioni{bus} &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. the whiche pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypally secheth not the loue of god nor the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of theyr soules / but golde and syluer after the apetyte of theyr coueytousnes / for he that wyl is suche maytene with takynge parte y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> suche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers weren of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> party of Jhesu cryst / he hym she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth a very heretyke and excōmenged then for to eshewe the peryll of this errour &amp; dampnacōn for to resemble &amp; aduyse these poore blynde of Jhesu cryst they be all trewe &amp; faythful crysten men they shal haue in this present treatyse as of late it hath be sayd fyue partes. The fyrst parte shall be of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> noblenesse &amp; of the trouth of the vowe of crysten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome / the whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owe is made in the sacrament
<pb facs="8"/>
of baptyme / &amp; also of the .xij. artycles of the fayth The seconde shall be of the .x. cōmaūdementes of the lawe with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> transgressyon of them that be the .vij. deedly synnes. The thyrde shall be of the .vij. werkes of mercy the whiche werkes shall be holdē the grete &amp; last Jugemēt / and the good &amp; ylle shall be examyned / &amp; these cruwell and coueytous folke vnto deth eternall condempned / and these pytous &amp; mercyfull people in the glory of paradyse shall be rewarded. The fourth partye shall be techyng{is} for well▪ &amp; enterly hym to confesse of synnes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he may cōmytte ayenst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> arty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les of the fayth &amp; of the cōmaūdement{is} of the lawe of good werk{is} that a man leueth to do ayenst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mercy of god w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whiche no man may wel come vnto salua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>on / for all synne is reherced &amp; compryseth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>missyon in doynge synne / or abomynacōn in leuȳ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the good the whiche a man is holden &amp; bounde to do. The fyfth &amp; the laste partye shall be of the paynes of helle &amp; of the Joyes of paradyse. Also it is to be noted y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as well for to satysfye vnto these clerkes &amp; for the more parfectly to conferme y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the whiche is wryten in englysshe as also for to esche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp; detraccion of lytell vnderstandynge of sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people I put in the heed of this boke in many passages these auctorytees conuocacions &amp; allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions the whiche be made in latyn / excepte y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> texte of the vowe of baptyme the whiche I haue wyll to put worde by worde in this wrytynge for to shewe the charyte ruyne of crysten people in all estates in the whiche they lyuen at this daye. That is to
<pb facs="8"/>
wyte the .xiiij. daye of January the yere of our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. M. CCCC. lxvij. after the Natyuyte of our lorde Jhesu cryste after dyuers cronycles &amp; maner of nombre the yeres. In the whiche yere and daye this present boke hath be fyrst begonne to be wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
   <p>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
   <trailer>¶ Here endeth the prologue / and now foloweth the fyrst parte of baptem.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>