<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THEODORE BE∣ZA
TO THE READERS, GREE∣ting
in the Lord.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109029_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10192</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2047</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109029</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THEODORE BE∣ZA
TO THE READERS, GREE∣ting
in the Lord.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tragedie of Abrahams sacrifice, written in french by Theodore Beza, and translated into Inglish, by A.G. Finished at Povvles Belchamp in Essex, the xj. of August. 1575</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 45, 3 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THEODORE BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZA
TO THE READERS, GREE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
in the Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now a two yeares, since
God graunted me the grace
to forsake the contrie where
he is persecuted, to serue him
accordinge to his holy will.
During which time, because that in my
aduersity many fancies ranne in my head,
I resorted to Gods word, where I founde
two thinges that comforted me marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously.
The one is the infinite number of
promises vttered by the mouth of him
which is the truth it selfe, whose sayinges
are alwayes matched with effect. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
is the multitude of examples, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="3"/>
euen the least are able enough, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to encourage and harten the weakest &amp;
fayntest harted in the worlde, but also to
make them inuincible. Which thing we
must needes see to haue come to passe, if
we consider by what meanes Gods truth
hath bene mayntayned to this present
time. Howebeit among all them that are
set afore vs for example in the olde testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
I finde three persons, in whome (to
my seeming) the Lorde ment to set forth
his greatest wonders: namely, Abraham,
Moises, and Dauid: in the liues of whome
if men would nowe a dayes looke vppon
them selues, they should knowe thē selues
better then they doe. Therefore as I redd
those holy stories with wonderfull plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
and singular profit: there came a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
vppon me to exercise my selfe in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
such matters in verse, not onely of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēt
to consider &amp; remēber thē the better,
but also to praise God by all the meanes
I could deuise. For I confesse, that euen of
<pb facs="3"/>
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I haue delighted in poetrie, &amp; I can
not yet repent me of it: neuerthelesse it
greueth me right sore, that the litle grace
which God gaue me in that behalfe, was
imployed by me in such things, as the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
remembrance of them irketh me now
at the hart. Therefore I gaue my selfe as
then to more holy matters, hoping to go
forwarde in them afterwarde, specially in
the translating of the Psalmes which I am
now in hand with. And woulde God that
the great number of good witts which I
know in Fraunce, would in steede of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zying
them selues about vnhappy inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
or imitations of vaine and vnhonest
fancies, (for so they be, if a mā iudge them
according to truth) rather set their minds
to the magnifying of the great God, of
whom they haue receiued those so great
giftes, then to the flattering of their Idols,
that is to say, of their Lordes and Ladies,
whom they vphold in their vices by their
fainings &amp; flatterings. Of a truth it would
<pb facs="4"/>
become thē better to sing a song of God,
then to counterfet a ballet of Petrarks, &amp;
to make amorous dities, worthy to haue
the garlande of sonnetts, or to counterfet
the furies of the auncient Poets, to blase
abroad the glory of this world, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate
this man or that woman to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie,
thinges which beare the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
on hande that the authors of them
not only are mounted vp to the toppe of
their Pernassus, but also are come to the
very circle of the Moone. Othersome (of
which number I my selfe haue bene, to
my great greefe as now) write twoedged
Epigrams cutting on both sides or sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
&amp; pricking at both endes. Others
buzie them selues rather in ouerturning
then in turning of thinges: &amp; othersome
intending to inrich our tongue, do pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
it with Greeke and Latine tearmes.
But how now wil some man say: I looked
for a tragedie, and thou giuest vs a Satyre.
I cōfesse that in thinking vpon such mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="4"/>
I was caried away and ouershot my
selfe. Neuerthelesse I ment not to rayle
vpon good witts, but onely to discouer to
them so plainly the open wronge which
they doe both to God and to them selues,
as they might through a certeine enuie,
take vpon them to passe me in the descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
of such matters as I haue taken tast
of to their handes, according as I knowe
that it shall be very easie for them, if the
meanest of them will giue him selfe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.
But to come to the matter that I haue
in hand, it is partly tragical and partly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall:
&amp; therefore I haue separated the
prologue, &amp; diuided the whole into paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
after the maner of actes in comedies,
howbeit without binding of my self ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.
And because it holdeth more of the
one then of the other: I thought best to
name it a tragedie. As touching the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of dealing, I haue altered some small
circumstances of the storie, to apply my
selfe to the companye. Moreouer I haue
<pb facs="5"/>
followed the ground as neare the text as
I could, according to such coniectures as
I thought most conuenient for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
and persons. And although the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
be very great, yet haue I absteined frō
wordes and speeches to farre estraunged
from the common ordinarie, notwithstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
that I know it was the maner of the
Greekes and Latines so to doe, specially
in their chorusses, as they termed them.
But I passed so litle of imitating them, that
contrariwise me thinkes nothing is more
vnseemely, than those forced translations
and speeches drawne out of such a lēgth,
as they can neuer come to the pith of the
matter: whereof I report me to <hi>Aristopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi>
who iustly rebuketh the Poets of his
time for it so often times. Verily I haue
made a songe without a chorus, nother
haue I vsed the termes of <hi>Strophies, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophies,
Epirrhemes, Parecbases,</hi> and other
such wordes, which serue to no purpose
but to amase simple folke, seeing the vse
<pb facs="5"/>
of such thinges is worne away, &amp; they be
not so commendable of them selues, that
a man should trouble him selfe to bringe
them vp again. As touching the ortogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,
I haue willed the Printer to followe
the common order, notwithstanding the
fond fancies that haue ben set forth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
these three or fower yeares in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.
And I would gladly counsel the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardest
of them that haue altered it, (if
they were men that would take any other
bodies counsell then their owne) that sith
they will needes reduce it to the pronoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
that is to say, make as many fashiōs
of writinge, not onely as there are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
but also as ther are persōs in Fraūce:
they should first learne to pronounce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they teach mē to write. For to speake
&amp; write after their fashion, he is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye
to giue rules of the writinge of our
tongue, which is not able to speake it.
Which thinge I speake not to blame all
those that haue set downe their dowts in
<pb facs="6"/>
that behalf, which I graunt are very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
to be reformed: but for such as sette
forth their dotages as certeine rules for al
the world to follow. Furthermore, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
the profit that may be taken of this
singular storie, besides the things that are
treated of it in insinite places of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
I wil refer it to him that shal speake
of it in the conclusion: praying you who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
you be to accept this my small
labour with as good will as I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
it you.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Lausan
<date>the first of October.
1550.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>