<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Miles Monopodios the Souldiour, to his Capitayne Cornelius Theophilus.</title>
           <author>Miles, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109674_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68098</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11888</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109674</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Miles Monopodios the Souldiour, to his Capitayne Cornelius Theophilus.</title>
                 <author>Miles, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pleasaunt dialogue, betweene a souldior of Barwicke, and an English chaplaine : Wherein are largely handled [and] laide open, such reasons as are brought in for maintenaunce of popishe traditions in our Eng. church. Also is collected, as in a short table, 120. particula corruptions yet remaining in our saide church, with sundrie other matters, necessarie to be knowen of all persons. Togither with a letter of the same author, placed before this booke, in vvay of a preface</title>
                 <author>Gilby, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>200 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ Miles Monopodios the Souldiour, to his Capitayne <hi>Cornelius Theophilus.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THERE be great controuersies here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade (God turne them to good) about the displacing of godly Preachers. Vpon the which occasion, I (falling in talke with Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narde myne olde fellowe souldiour, who is nowe a Lordes Chaplaine) thought it at the firste lawfull, as Horace teacheth: Ridentem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere verum: with myrth to haue passed ouer this lamentable matter, and so to haue made, but a light skirmishe. But when I was once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, our communication waxed more earnest, and there followed some bitter wordes. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde we had such argumentes, that Sir Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narde was almost readie to forsake his benefice, as a great sorte of that order would doo, if they knewe where to finde so easie liuinges: they are so despised of all the worlde, and some of them so troubled in conscience. I sende you the whole discourse, something (I graunt) enlarged: pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishe it, if you please. For whosoeuer other men thincke lightlie of it, this displacing of Christes true Ministers, for Popishe trashe, doeth so grieue me at the harte, that I can not but speak against it. And so would I haue all men to doo,
<pb facs="8"/>
that are touched with anie godly zeale: so shal we not be guiltie of other mens faultes, thorow our silence.</p>
   <p>So long as the Parliament indured, wee all had hope of amendement, and kept silence: but nowe that it is ended, and all hope of man is past, we must turne to God by prayer, and that which we can do by wordes and by writing, let vs do it. Let vs not ceasse to fight against the remmanauntes of the Romane Antichrist, and to labour to breake downe and abolishe (if it be possible) all his ensignes. For it is of necessitie, that his lawes should cease, seeing his blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous priesthoode is renounced. Let vs do our diligence in driuing away all Popishe trashe, and leaue the successe vnto God. Our fathers haue fought the bloodie battle, and some of our owne brethren do fight against vs. Howebeit, we are yet but in a light combate: more is to be feared, Let vs resiste the beginnings.</p>
   <p>In this Dialogue that I sende vnto you, if I do seeme sometimes pleasaunt, knowe that it is not, without some bitternes of minde, as had the Prophetes, when they had to do with halters &amp; neutrals: whose foolishnes being counted great wisedome in the worlde, they did thus deride. If I seeme to angrie, and to whote and earnest, consider that it is not in myne owne cause or
<pb facs="8"/>
quarell, but in Gods cause, in the cause of his seruauntes, in the common cause of this whole Church of Englande: For which, howe can we be to much carefull, earnest, and zealous? And I do thinke assuredlie, that God doth call vs all by this controuersie, to a reckoning, for our cold and carelesse trifling in Religion: by the which Atheisme, Papisme, and Lutheranisme, striue against vs fainte souldiours, hoping for the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie. Therefore whom the Lorde findeth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther colde nor whote, he will surelie vomit out. He that is not with me, is against me, doeth he say. But happie shall he be, that fighteth man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vnder his Captaine Christ, against the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Antichrist: whose dregges who soeuer drincketh, he is incountinently druncken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, be it little, be it much that he tasteth: as we may see, by the Lordlie Bishoppes, who nowe for the dregges and patches of Poperie, despise their fellow ministers: and persecute those same persons, whom of late they loued as brethren, and bare Christes crosse with them, in the late persecutions.</p>
   <p>But if this Poperie continewe, they wilbe younge Popes doubtlesse, and poperie it self will growe vp againe: The wounde of the first beast wilbe healed in that, that the seconde shall doo the same things, which the firste hath done.
<pb facs="9"/>
Therefore, let all good men labour all that they can, to plucke vp these wicked weedes of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, the remmenauntes of superstition and Idolatrie. For Christes garden can neuer bee purged cleane inough from such poyson. For if anie little twiste, of Antichristes inuentions bee lefte, the bodie will growe afterwarde. It did so creepe vp at the beginning, like a little Iuie stalke, eating out the hartes of the great Oakes, Kings and Emperours, and destroyed the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian congregations.</p>
   <p>We Christians are commaunded to absteyne from al shewe of euil: and we are straitlie char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to haue no parte with the whore of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon: neither to haue anie fellowshippe with the fruitlesse workes of darknesse, but to reprooue them. And if they will not do so, which will be counted the Pastours, the Doctours, and leaders of the flocke, God can and will rayse vp others, to pitie his cause, and to purge his Temple: as he hath done many times heretofore. For in the cleare light of the Gospell, God will haue Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppes or Ministers, that shalbe discerned from the people, by doctrine and conuersation, and not by garmentes of straunge fashion. The people are nowe to be instructed, and no longer with ragges to be mocked. Neither must a Priest of clowtes any longer be set before their eyes: but
<pb facs="9"/>
the messengers of God must be sought, to powre Gods worde into their harts: the course wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whosoeuer stoppeth or hindereth, hee shall beare his iudgement what soeuer he be. Playe you therefore the parte of Cornelius, as you haue done heretofore. Call your seruauntes and souldiours to the knowledge of Christes Gospel. Chearishe the true Preachers, of whome this worlde is vnworthie: and though they should be murdered, as they are nowe robbed and imprisoned, yet let vs with honor burie their bodies, as Ioseph did their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From LONDON, <date>The x of May,<lb/>
1566.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Miles your olde<lb/>
Seruaunt.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>