<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull Master Edward Stanley Esquire.</title>
           <author>Danter, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109998_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07482</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17866</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109998</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull Master Edward Stanley Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Danter, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famous historie of Chinon of England : with his strange aduentures for the loue of Celestina daughter to Lewis King of Fraunce. VVith the worthy atchiuement of Sir Lancelot du Lake, and Sir Tristram du Lions for fair Laura, daughter to Cador Earle of Cornewall, beeing all knights of King Arthurs round table. By Chr. Middleton</title>
                 <author>Middleton, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Danter, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gosson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull Master Edward Stanley Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, were I not more comforted with assurance of your Generous disposition, than perswaded of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie merit on my part, by offering the Patronage of this Historie to your hands; I should as certainly dispaire of the acceptaunce, as I am vncertaine whether it bee worthie to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted From the time of my first entraunce in Printing till now, it is the first Booke of this kinde I euer had power to dedicate, from my first yeres of capacitie to read anie printed thing, my affectionate dutie hath to your W. been dedicated.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Enisham</hi> one of your Lordships was my
<pb facs="3"/>
birth-place; and as my Frends there pay due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the place they liue in, so tender I this here as part of my duteous loue.</p>
   <p>The Authour of the Booke hath left it to the wide world without a Patron, perchance esteeming it vnworthie protection: neyther doo I thinke it in the least part worthie your protection, before whose excelent iudgement (so daily conuersant among the most iudiciall) it cannot but vanish like light smoake before a bright flame. All my excuse is loue, all my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest is pardon; which as (I first inferd) your noble disposition assures mee of. On which foundation building, I cease now to bee more bold.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your VVorships, most du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully affectionate:</hi> Iohn Danter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>