<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109629_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20391</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6801</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109629</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dialogve, concerning the strife of our churche : wherein are aunswered diuers of those vniust accusations, wherewith the godly preachers and professors of the Gospell, are falsly charged; with a briefe declaration of some such monstrous abuses, as our byshops haue not bene ashamed to foster</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 136 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle reader, thou art not ignoraunt, that in this our Churche of Englande, there hath been a scisme for sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry yeares, which of late is growen so strong, that vnlesse the Lord looke vpō vs in great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, it will in short time bring foorth a very lamentable desolation. Now, it is the part and duetie of euery true-harted Christian, to do his best both by heartye prayer and otherwise so far as his calling doth reach, to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, ayde, and support that side, which hath the truth. For this consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration haue I bestowed my poore trauell in writing this little dialogue. In which I haue as faithfully as I can, set downe the greatest accusations, and most vsuall crimes, that haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="3"/> colour, which are slaunderouslye cast foorth, and laid to the charge of Gods faithfull messengers: with a short aunswere to shew the vanitie of the same. On the other side, I haue lightly touched as it were, the heades or fountaines of diuers corruptions, maintayned by the contrarye part, which are so grosse &amp; manifest, that he which shall saye he knoweth not of them, maye well be suspected for vntruth: and he that shall defende them, must put on his foreheade of brasse. My sute vnto thee, gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is no more but this, that thou wilt well waigh, and iudge vprightly, which part follow the steppes of the blessed Apostles, and so be the true ministers of Iesus christ. I know right well, some will bee offended at this kind of dealing, and say it is hurtful. But vnlesse I would be vnfaithfull to my Lord and master Iesus Christ, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful to his poore Church, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall to my soueraigne prince, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer I am bound to do more, I can with safe conscience do no lesse, then
<pb facs="3"/> I haue here done. Some will say these are but words, and who can not easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye make the like pretence for anye matter whatsoeuer. I will therefore note some particular causes, to shew the truth of my wordes. He that will be the faithfull seruaunt of Iesus Christ, must stande for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Gospell, and not holde his tongue when the course thereof is stayed and hindered. But the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are so plentifull, will some man saye, that although here and there a few which will not conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, be put to silēce, yet the course of the gospel is not hindered. I wold to God a true suruaye were made, that first all those which haue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully laboured, whō they terme Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, being set aside, they would take the veiw and number of such as haue great titles and roomes, and yet feed not any flockes of sheepe or lambes: and in the next place set those which apply all their great learning, to get liuinges and dignities, not caring for soules: as namely to heape be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice
<pb facs="4"/> vpon benefice, to seeke to bee Archdeacons, Deanes, and byshops: For these seek after the things which are their owne, and not the thinges which are Christs: these serue not the Lord Iesus, but their own belly: and though they can speak like angels, yet the Church shall not bee blessed by them. For they are not sent of God, they bee not the ministers of Iesus Christ, by whome he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his Gospell. If yee can also number those which goe vnder the names of Preachers, and doe either so seldome, so slenderly, and vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully teach, that their people are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the better. And in the last rancke place the vnable men, with those of spotted life: I warrant yee the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant wil be <hi>Methemispar,</hi> as the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture speaketh. There shall need no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetrician to take the account. Now to the second point.</p>
   <p>When God hath prepared the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Manna, and appointed to his Church that she shoulde eate her fill thereof, euen to the fatting of her
<pb facs="4"/> soule, to make her liuely and strong: and that her Children &amp; babes may sucke from her breasts the sincere milk of the word: Who is there that hath a minde touched with any care of duety and seruice towardes her, that can holde his peace, and not complaine in her behalfe, when shee is denyed her right, in being debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of this heauenly bread, or at the least so stinted and scanted, that shee can scarce haue sufficient to preserue life. Solomon saith, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man considereth the soule of his beast, wheras the bowels of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are cruelty. A righteous man can not behold an Oxe, or an Horse pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to death for want of foode, but that the mournefull voyce of the Dumbe Beaste will strike his heart, and mooue compassion: and shall not the heart of a righteous man bleede? shall not his raines pricke? shall it not kindle and burst out as a fire in him, shall hee not lament with pittie, when he beholdeth the Ladye and mistresse of the worlde, the Lambes wife, euen the very deare
<pb facs="5"/> spouse to him that is Lord of Lords, depriued of her daylye foode? Can anye true Christian man, with drye eyes looke vppon the leannesse and palenesse of her face, the feeblenesse of her ioyntes, and weakenesse of her bodye? Her beautie shoulde bee so excellent, and her maiestie so great, that she should be a terrour to those enemyes which nowe despise and mocke her. Let them keepe silence that can, all good men will speake and speake againe in her behalfe: yea, euen against those bishops which doe her this great wronge, and seeke to destroy her children with famine. The blessed Apostle S. <hi>Paule,</hi> whose care was as tender ouer the weake ones of the Church, as the care of any mother towardes the babe that sucketh vppon her brestes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> saith <hi>Who is offended and I burne not?</hi> If there be anye sparckle of his spirite in a man, how can he but burne, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at this day, so many weak ones to stumble? both men and women, yong and old, in many places, which
<pb facs="5"/> had receiued some taste of the word, and began as greene plantes to bud being continually watred by Apollo: Nowe following the drought as it were of an whote Summer, the siluer dews being restrained frō dropping vpon them, and the fountains of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters shut vp, do wither away: yea, many are made to stagger, and doubt whether it were a true gospell that was preached vnto them. For say they, if it were good, how should any learned man go about to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, or to put those to silence that publish it? For the third point, is ther any man ignorāt, how manifold trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons are practized by the papists, euē like greedy bloud-houndes of hell, which thirst for the very heart bloud of our souereign Queen? what conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth thē still in hope to bring their purpose to passe after so many repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses? Is it the goodnes of their cause: no, it is the ignorance and blindnes of the vntaught multitude, in which their might is reposed. These night birds, know right well, that where
<pb facs="6"/> the Sunne shineth, ther is small place for thē. Let the people be taught to know wholsome doctrine, and they will neuer abide the rotten drugges of these Romish Apothecaries. Let them see the light, and be taught out of the blessed worde, that it is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to those that rebell againste their Prince, yea, though it be but a disloyall minde, &amp; no outward thing practized. Let them feele what bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing is come vnto them, by a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Mother in Israel, a nurse of Gods Churche, and that they are deepely bound, not onely vppon their knees to powre out plentifull prayers vnto God for her: but also, that it is their duety to aduenture their liues for her defence: and you shall haue them farre from giuing eare vnto traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous persuasions of Iesuites, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary Priestes. Beholde, for this cause, how those that are known fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers of the Romish Religion, do now bestirre them, to throwe downe the Preachers, by procuring matters of complaint against them vnto the
<pb facs="6"/> byshoppes. If this dishonour be not done vnto Christ, which I haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, this iniurye to his poore Churche, and daunger to our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Queene, by heartning and strengthning the handes of her eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: let this my doing bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted sedicious, as I am out of doubt, some will not sticke very malitious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to terme it. But if it bee as I haue sayde, and as many thousandes with griefe doe beholde, and can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse (by whome let me be tried, and accounted shamelesse if I lye) then I craue, that I may not bee blamed for speaking in so waighty causes, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a little of those things which all the Seruauntes of God ought to cry out of: But to what purpose, or wher shall there be redresse fought for? O ye Byshops, euen in this, repent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, repent in time that GOD may haue mercye vppon yee. Will yee bee offended with him that shall giue ye wholesome counsell? or will yee say that yee are wrongfully char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? good counsel ye wil say is neuer
<pb facs="7"/> to be reiected, then may it easily be prooued, that ye stand in neede of it. To let other thinges passe, ought not the ministers of the Gospell to bee paterns and examples vnto the flock both in wholsom doctrine and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuersation? ought they not to be the lights of the worlde, and the salt of the earth, to season the hearts of the people with spirituall graces, &amp; to shine vnto them as starres, that they may see the paths of life? ought they not to feed the lords flock with the bread of life, to lead thē into the green pastures, and vnto the streams of liuing waters? ought they not to seeke vp that which goeth astray, to heale that which is diseased, and to carry the tender Lambes in their bosom? are your ministers with whō ye haue filled the church such? or will yee seeke for excuses to make your fault light? surely if ye do not repent, ye cannot bee saued. God doth not respect the personnes of men. Wil ye repent at the last, and leaue the thing vnrefourmed when ye dye? what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce
<pb facs="7"/> will that be? will ye make your prayers vnto God, and will he heare them? your garmentes being ful of bloud, euen the bloud of many soules that perish for want of foode: yee would haue those that be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt and wallowe in their sinnes to be counted Christians, that it might not be knowne, that the want of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching destroyeth souls. But the word of the Lorde will bee too stronge for ye, which teacheth manifestly the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity thereof. Are yee ashamed to bee reprooued by your inferiours, when your sinne is manifest? It is a shame to continue, but no shame at all for a man to amend his fault. Do ye count it a discredite to yeelde any thing at all vnto those which are your inferiours, &amp; haue also their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities? count it no discredit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; yeelde vnto the word of God, which is free frō all impurity. Looke not vppon the offences of any that reprooue yee, neither bee delighted to heare slanderous things of them: For their sinnes shall be no helpe at
<pb facs="8"/> all to couer yours before God, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer ye may make them some pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of your doinges before men. The Lorde God of his mercy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your eyes, and take pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his desolate peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>