<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR Charles Haward, Lord high admirall of England, knight of the moste honourable order of the Garter, and one of her highnesse priuy Counsel. Edward Ienings wi∣sheth long and prosperous health, with in∣crease of all happinesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109137_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04372</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14486</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109137</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR Charles Haward, Lord high admirall of England, knight of the moste honourable order of the Garter, and one of her highnesse priuy Counsel. Edward Ienings wi∣sheth long and prosperous health, with in∣crease of all happinesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discouery of the damages that happen to this realme by disordered and vnlawfull diet : The benefites and commodities that otherwaies might ensue. With a perswasion of the people: for a better maintenance to the nauie. Brieflie compiled, by Edward Ieninges</title>
                 <author>Jeninges, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR Charles Haward, Lord high admirall of England, knight of the moste honourable order of the Garter, and one of her highnesse priuy Counsel. Edward Ienings wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth long and prosperous health, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of all happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honourable and my good Lord, after long consideration had of the sundrie and great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities that happeneth to this Realme by the misdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of diuers disordered persons contrarie to manie good &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable lawes carefully orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, heaping harmes on our own heades thorow wilfull disobedience. As a poore mēber a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the rest lamenting this carelesse contempt, I pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred earnestly in my minde, what way to imploy my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and small skill for some redresse herein to the benefit of my countrie: and considering amongest manie other thinges, the great harmes that happen to this realme sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie waies by the contempt of fish, and inordinate or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull expence of fleshe, growing as may be supposed through want of true vnderstanding, to what end the law in that behalfe made is ordained, as one amongest manie muche vnable effectually to discharge so great a worke, of a zealous minde I haue compiled this small treatise for the persvvasion of such as herein will be persvvaded. And aduenturing to proceede with all humblenesse I haue made bold, for the better publishing thereof to shroud my selfe for defence vnder the protection and fauour of your good honour, as a speciall and carefull magistrate
<pb facs="3"/>
for such things as concerne the common-vvealth of this realme, ordained of God vnder her Maiestie to haue the ouersight and gouernement in these affaires which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth moste chiefly a maintenance to her highnesse Nauie: besides the sundrie and great commodities othervvaies grovving to the vvhole common-wealth. Not onely need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be published, but moste carefully also considered and remembred, as by the discourse follovving shall mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly appeare. But the common sorte of people to auoyd the ceremonicall abuse heretofore vsed by obseruation of fish daies, notvvithstanding the paines and penalties by the lavv threatned, not onely neglecteth, but vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth the same: nothing remembring the harmes that to them thereby may happen. And some reason is for that no matter hath heretofore bin shewed, so largely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to persvvade them as in this my small vvorke is rudely compiled. Most humbly crauing your honours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable patience in considering the contents thereof, not respecting the rude still but my affectioned heart and minde for the benefite and safetie of my Prince, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try then as vnvvorthie of such acceptation, I shall finde my selfe for this small paines, most bountifullie satisfied, and according to dutie pray for your honorable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous estate long to continue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>