<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1485</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109148_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21429</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109148</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>This book was compyled [and] made atte requeste of kyng Phelyp of Fraunce : whyche book is callyd in frensshe. le liure royal· that is to say the ryal book. or a book for a kyng</title>
                 <author>Laurent, dominican</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caxton, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Westminster</pubPlace>
                    <date>1485</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>324 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <p>WHan I remembre and take hede of the conuersacion of vs that lyue in this wretched lyf. in which is no surete ne stable abydyng. And also the contynuel besynes of euery man. how he is occupyed and dayly laboureth to bylde &amp; ede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye as though theyr habytacion and dwellyng here / were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent and shold euer endure. &amp; also practyse how they may gete temporalle possessyons. goodes and rychesses. of whyche they are neuer contente ne satysfyed as for the moost partye. but contynuelly entende and laboure by many subtyl meanes how they may encreace theyr sayd possessyons and richesses for to come and attayne to worldly honour and estate. In whiche they wene be veray felycyte and blessydnes / and whan I haue wel ouerseen &amp; examyned these forsayd thynges and lyf. I fynde nothyng in them but vanyte of vanytees and all vanyte &amp; yet I merueylle moche of them that ben lerned wyse &amp; noble men in the lawe. that not withstondyng their rychesses. &amp; sure lyuyng as wel in the spirituelte as in the temporalte contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly laboure to be enhaunced &amp; promoted to hye dygnytees and offyces. as though therin were perpetuel felycyte. In whyche ye may see at eye that al is but vanyte. &amp; they that mē repute for wysest &amp; gretest aboute prynces in a moment ben ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen &amp; brought to nought. Not withstondyng for the moost parte. they of the spyrytuelte &amp; also of the temporalte entende more to gete. worldly honours. rychesses &amp; possessyons for to satisfye the appetyte of their inordynate desyre here in this tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sytorye lyf / which anone &amp; hastely shal departe fro the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyble body. thā they do for theternal lyf which shal euer endure in Ioye or in payne. Thēne to thende that euery man resona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble remēbre hym self that he is mortal. &amp; shal withoute fayle departe out of this lyf hastely &amp; sone. &amp; ought while he is here lyuyng to purueye &amp; ordeyne for the perpetuel lyf to come / &amp; so to lyue accordyng to the lawe &amp; comandements of our lord &amp; ocupye hym self in vertuous <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>racyons and werkes. in
<pb facs="2"/>
eschewyng al vices &amp; synnes &amp; al the braūches of thē. that they may after this short &amp; trāsytorye lyf attayne &amp; com to the euer lastyng lyf in heuen / I purpose &amp; attende by the suffraunce of almyghty god to trāslate a book late delyuerd to me &amp; reduce it out of frensshe in to our comyn englysshe tonge. in whyche euery man may be enformed how he ouzt to kepe the lawe &amp; comaūdemēts of god. to folowe vertu &amp; flee &amp; eschewe vyces &amp; to pourueye &amp; ordeyne for hym spyrituel rychesses in heuen ppetuel &amp; permament / which book was made in frensshe atte requeste of Phelip le bele kyng of fraūce in the yere of thyncar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion of our lord MCClxxix. &amp; reduced in to englisshe at the request &amp; specyal desyre of a synguler frende of myn a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of lōdon the yere of our sayd lord / M.iiij C.lxxxiiij. which book is entytled &amp; named in frensshe. le lyure royal. whiche is to say in englisshe· the ryal book. or a book for a kyng. in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che book ben comprysed the x comandemēts of our lord. the xij artycles of the fayth / the vij dedely synnes with their braūches the vij petycions of the pater noster· the seuen yeftes of the holy ghoost. the vij vertues and many other holy thynges &amp; maters good &amp; prouffytable for the wele of mānes soule. Thenne I exhorte &amp; desyre euery mā that entendeth to the prouffyt &amp; sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon of his soule / to ouer see this sayd book / in whiche he shal fynde good &amp; prouffytable doctryne by which he may the rather attayne to come to euerlastyng blysse· &amp; alwaye what that is wryton is vnder correctyon of lerned men / humbly be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sechyng them to correcte &amp; amende where as is ony d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>faute. &amp; so doyng they shal doo a merytory dede. For as nyghe as god hath gyuen me connyng I haue folowed the copye as nyghe as I can. &amp; I beseche almyghty god that this sayd werk may prouffyte the redars. &amp; that is the special cause that it is made fore / that knoweth god to whome noo thyng is hyd / whyche gyue vs grace so to lyue vertuously in this short lyf. that after this lyf we may come to his euerlastyng blysse in heuen amē</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>