<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable the Earle of Lei∣cester, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109079_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19619</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6052</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109079</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable the Earle of Lei∣cester, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The copie of a letter to the Right Honourable the Earle of Leycester, Lieutenant generall of all her Maiesties forces in the vnited Prouinces of the lowe Countreys : written before, but deliuered at his returne from thence: vvith a report of certeine petitions and declarations made to the Queenes Maiestie at two seuerall times, from all the lordes and commons lately assembled in Parliament. And her Maiesties answeres thereunto by her selfe deliuered, though not expressed by the reporter with such grace and life, as the same were vttered by her Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 3, 1, 4-32, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle of Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit with earnest desire of my hart (right honourable my very good Lord) I haue alwayes ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to do your Lordship some acceptable seruice, for the honour you first vouchsafed me from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my cradel, and after confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the fauourable opinion wherewith you haue alwayes countenaunced me euer since, euen thus farre onward on my daies, which also to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my yeres hath increased faster then mine abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to performe, being crossed in nothing more deepely, then when I was letted by the ouermuch tendring of me by my parents, to attend your Lordship in your late voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and honourable expedition into the Lowe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: yet haue I bene euer since most studious to obserue and apprehende some good occasion, or fitte oportunitie, to testifie the duetifull reuerence I beare to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: wherein if hitherto I haue beene slacke in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance during your absence, it hath proceeded of the care I had, not to entertaine your Lordship with matter either friuolous or vulgar: though thinges of that nature might best become my condition, and well agree with my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding.</p>
   <p>In which cogitation it came to my minde, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the speaches deliuered by the Queenes most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="2" facs="3"/>Maiestie in a late and weightie cause dealt in this Parliament, in answere to the petitions presented to hir Maiestie the 12 &amp; 24. of Nouember at Richmond by the Lord Chauncelour and Speaker, respectiuely, in the name and behalfe of both Estates, accompanied with diuers of either sort, would doubtlesse bee a thing to your L. most gratefull, as one euer pleased iustly to admire the rare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of her mind, and approoued Iudgement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, according to your Estate &amp; place, deseruedly, your L. hath beene vsually acquainted: as also worthie of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal monument and euerlasting memorie, for as much as on the sodaine they were deliuered by her selfe, for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere of a matter propounded, debated, resolued, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested, with great labour and premeditation, of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, grauest, wisest, and most choise persons of the whole Realme. Whereof although I haue but slēderly purtraied the lineaments, without expressing to life the external or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of her Royall speach, accompanied with all Princely and gracefull accomplementes: yet doubt I not but your Lordship will easily finde her inward vertues, whereof it is impossible for mee to make the least adum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration.</p>
   <p>And because in the dayly expectation of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships returne, I rested vncertaine how these might come safely to your Lordships hands: I did therefore aduise to haue this my letter with the included copies to be ready to attend your first arriuall, in gratulation of the safetie thereof, which hath bene long desired. Wherein, as I striue to performe a particular duetie to your Lordship, so trust I you will haue that honourable consideration, that in the communication thereof with others, there growe not any preiudice to me for my presumption, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturing to be a reporter of that, which in the deliuerie wrought so great astonishment to all the hearers, as it exceeded the fulnes of euery mans expectation: and therefore, without some fauourable construction of mine
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>attempt, I might incurre great blame by my slender ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of report, so to haue blemished the excellencie of her Maiesties speaches, whereof I humbly beseech your Lordship to haue fauourable regard. Thus referring them to your Lordships disposition, and my selfe to your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable protection, I humbly take my leaue. 25. Nouemb. 1586.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humbly in all duetie to commaund. <hi>R. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>