<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY VERIE Honourable and most respe∣cted good LADIE, Dame Beatrix Ruthven, LADIE Coldenknowes. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lyon, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109753_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06665</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17120</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY VERIE Honourable and most respe∣cted good LADIE, Dame Beatrix Ruthven, LADIE Coldenknowes. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lyon, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Teares for the neuer sufficientlie bewailed death of the late right honourable and most worthie of all honourable titles, Alexander Earle of Dumfermeling, Lord Fyuie, and Vrquhart late Lord Chancellar of Scotland</title>
                 <author>Lyon, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro, Heirs of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>TO MY VERIE Honourable and most respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>good LADIE,</hi> Dame <hi>Beatrix Ruthven,</hi> LADIE <hi>Coldenknowes.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Madam</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I condemne the vnnaturall custome of the Auntient <hi>Thracians,</hi> who vsed to weepe at the birth of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to rejoyce at the death of their Parents, Kins-folke, and Friends: So I can not but commend your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyships firm-fixt affection to your friends, which (contrarie to the common custome of this time-seruing Age) Death doeth not diminish which your La. makes manifest at this time, for no sooner had fame▪ filled the eares of all, with the sorrowfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, of the neuer sufficientlie bewailed death of the late right honourable Lord Chancellar: but your La. to show, that as in this generall losse your losse was more then commone, hauing lost so honourable a Patrone, so faithfull a Friend, and so louing a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all your affaires: so you in sorrow exceeded the most sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull,
<pb facs="3"/>
      your La. repledged from the fire, this vnpolisht ryme, to the which (as vnworthie of the worlds view) I condemned the same, and caus'd the same so bee printed: to the which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discended, willing rather to publish mine owne imperfections them that your La. scarce imitable and vnfained affection to that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord should bee concealed, accept then (Madam) in good part those lines which by your owne procurment passes to the Presse and as they beare the badges of your Ladiships sorrow for your so great a losse, let them serue as signes to show the willingnes I haue to doe your Ladiship all the seruice I can performe, to the which I am tyed both by bandes of blood and nature, and by your Ladiships manifold vndeserued courteous fauours to my selfe, hoping that the Title of your Ladishippes name shall seruee as a sufficient defence for all the imperfections of those vnperfect and vnpolisht lines, kissing your Ladiships hands I rest, and shall euer remaine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships Cousen most humblie devoted to serue you <hi>John Lyoun.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>