<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109247_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04691</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14817</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109247</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine description of the Barmudas, now called Sommer Ilands : VVith the manner of their discouerie anno 1609. by the shipwrack and admirable deliuerance of Sir Thomas Gates, and Sir George Sommers, wherein are truly set forth the commodities and profits of that rich, pleasant, and healthfull countrie. With an addition, or more ample relation of diuers other remarkeable matters concerning those ilands since then experienced, lately sent from thence by one of the colonie now there resident</title>
                 <author>Jourdain, Silvester</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>Good Reader, this is the first Booke published to the world touching <hi>Sommer Ilands:</hi> but who shall liue to see the last? A more full and exact description of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and Narration of the nature, site, and commodities, together with a true Historie of the great deliuerance of <hi>Sir Thomas Gates</hi> and his Companie vpon them, which was the first disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of them; thou maiest surely expect, if God will, to come into thy hands. This short Narration, in the meane time, shall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prepare thee for it, then preuent thee of it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>