<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109144_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19703</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6120</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109144</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Explication, of - Thrissels - banner : Containing a brief interpretation &amp; declaration, of the forme &amp; fashion thereof, as also of the matter therein expressed</title>
                 <author>Cunningham, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>SInce never Man at any tyme could so wysely frame his <hi>Work</hi> or compose his <hi>Wryttings</hi> but (it comming to the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike view) either <hi>Ignorance</hi> or <hi>Envy</hi> (if not both) <hi>Mortal Ennemies to Vertue</hi> did always labour to <hi>Under-Myne</hi> the Sinceritie of the <hi>Author,</hi> seeking (with the pricking <hi>SPi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> to draw theyr <hi>Venem</hi> out of the best <hi>Herbes</hi> and sweetest smelling <hi>Floures?</hi> I Considering this, darre promese no Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to My self (tho a continual <hi>Amator</hi> yet no dayly <hi>Practiser)</hi> being but a new graffed <hi>Impe</hi> in comparison of those innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable flourissing famous (and yet neverthelesse controlled) <hi>Poets,</hi> Notwith standing (being mooved with a entire <hi>Affection</hi> towards al those that from theyr Hearts wish, Labour for, and Ayme at, <hi>the Peace of Syon)</hi> I have enterprysed and, by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> finished and perfyted, My <hi>first Fruit,</hi> Intitulate <hi>Thrissels Banner?</hi> And knowing that the same shal rencounter, and come to, the Hands and Eyes, both of <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Foes,</hi> which I al include in three Ranks, the <hi>First, Wyse and Understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> (only Absolute <hi>Friends)</hi> the <hi>Second, Ignorants</hi> (both <hi>Frieuds</hi> and <hi>Foes)</hi> the <hi>Thrid Malicious Partial Calumniators</hi> (only Absolute <hi>Foes)</hi> Therefore I have thought it most Necessary and Expedient (for Preventing and Eschewing, so farre as possibly I can, al <hi>false Glosses of Adversaries)</hi> to Accompany and Convoye the foresayd <hi>Banner,</hi> with this My owne <hi>Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> where in I have (so Briefly and playnly as I could) faythfully Declared <hi>My Meaning and Intention</hi> in everie thing,
<pb facs="3"/>
as wel anent the <hi>Forme</hi> of it, as concerning the <hi>Matter</hi> and words therein contayned; which I Hope shal tend, <hi>To,</hi> the <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Edification</hi> of the <hi>First. Instruction</hi> of the <hi>Second, Conviction</hi> and <hi>Disclosing</hi> of the <hi>Third,</hi> and in Al and Everie one of them, to the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> whom I earnestly beseech to Maintayne <hi>His owne Cause,</hi> to Strenthen Encouradge and Assist the <hi>Defenders</hi> thereof, to Open the Eyes of such as yet are Blinded, to Arme al those that suffer Persecution for His sake, with <hi>Wisdome</hi> and <hi>Christian Patience,</hi> graunting thame, that passing Natural understanding, <hi>Peace of Conscience.</hi> Here in this Lyfe, and in His owne good Tyme Everlasting.</p>
   <closer>Repos Ailleurs.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>