<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109810_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20765</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7147</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109810</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Spiritual physicke to cure the diseases of the soule, arising from superfluitie of choller, prescribed out of Gods word : Wherein the chollericke man may see the dangerousnesse of this disease of the soule vniust anger, the preseruatiues to keepe him from the infection thereof, and also fit medicines to restore him to health beeing alreadie subiect to this raging passion. Profitable for all to vse, seeing all are patients in this disease of impatiencie</title>
                 <author>Downame, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simson, Gabriel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones, William 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 36, 35-81, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall infection of this contagious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease of the soule vniust anger, and the manifould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious euils which it worketh, both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publique, I thought good to prescribe out of Gods word, some reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for those patients which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my cure, whereby they might eyther be preserued from these feuer-like fits, which cause men outwardly to shake, and tremble when as inwardly they are most inflamed; or els haue their heate somewhat allayed and abated when they are alreadie fallen into them. The which my prescript I thought at the first should haue beene communicated to no more then mine owne patients, till I was perswaded by more skilfull Physitions then my selfe,
<pb facs="4"/> that the publishing thereof might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd to others profit. And therefore desiring nothing more then to exercise my poore talent to the glory of my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster who bestowed it, and the benefit of my fellow seruants, for whose good also I haue receiued it, I willingly condescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their motion. And for as much, as I had onely shadowed a rude draught without colour or countenance, I was fayne to take a reueiw of my woorke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering some things, and adding others as it were new lineaments, which I thought more fit for the Presse then for the Pulpit. If any thinke me too quick in practise, they will (I hope) excuse me, if they consider that I make experience of my slender skil, not in the vital parts, but in the feete of the soule, namely the affections, and yet the curing of them, or but this one of them, may greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the benefit of the whole, for as the diseases of the feete doe grieue the hart and offend the head, and the curing
<pb facs="5"/> and healing of them doth ease and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort both, so when the affections are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered beeing infected with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of our originall corruption, euen the chiefe parts of the soule the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing &amp; wil, are not a little disturbed and disordered, by receiuing from them their contagious pollutiō. And therfore he who can skilfully purge these neather parts shall ease the higher, by drawing downe those corrupt humors which do offend and annoy thē. Seeing then there may come by my practise great good with little danger, I haue the rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured the cure: beeing contented to vndergoe the censure of some for too much hast, who (I feare me) are in these cases as much too slow, to the end that I may to the vttermost of my skill benefit many. The Lord who is the onely true Physition of soules diseased with sinne, blesse this and all other my indeauours that they may be profitable for the setting forth of his glory, the benefit of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and furthering the assurance of mine owne saluation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>