<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           <author>D., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109244_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19762</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6190</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109244</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 <author>D., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Orthoepia Anglicana: or, the first principall part of the English grammar : teaching the art of right speaking and pronouncing English, with certaine exact rules of orthography, and rules of spelling or combining of syllables, and directions for keeping of stops or points between sentence and sentence. A work in it selfe absolute, and never knowne to be accomplished by any before: no lesse profitable then necessary for all sorts, as well natives as forreigners, that desire to attaine the perfection of our English tongue. Methodically composed by the industry and observation of Simon Daines schoolemaster of Hintlesham in Suffs</title>
                 <author>Daines, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>—English Stock</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Linguistics and philology</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <p>
      <pb facs="2"/>
reduce this confused manner of practice to some regular form; whereby the Teacher might be exonerated a great part of his burden, the Learner encouraged with more faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and expedition to proceed, we, in generall, induced to repose more confidence and delight in our owne Tongue, and the stranger allured to the knowledge of it.</p>
   <p>Now therefore, since the perfection of all Arts (whereto the knowledge of Tongues ought to be reduced) consists as well in the Theory, as the Practice: (the one whereof makes a knowing man, the other a ready) and this Theory in the resolutive mood, or knowledge of Universals; wee are, as well in this, as all other Tongues or Languages, to have recourse to Grammar, as the generall fountain. This the Greeks call <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or the knowledg of Letters. But according to the acception of the term, it is usually (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Latins especially) divided into foure parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Orthoepie &amp; Orthography (w <hi>
         <seg rend="sup">ch</seg>
      </hi> only differ in this, that the one hath respect to right speaking, the other to right wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) Etymology (which teacheth the knowledg of the parts of speech, and how to order and propose them truly) Syntax (which treateth of the construction of the parts) and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sody (which chiefly belongs to Poets) that expostulateth the accent, rythme, quantity, and measure of feet in every word or verse. The two former integrall Parts, to wit, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoepie and Etymologie (as most necessary and only abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely requisite in our English Tongue) I have for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose sufficiently discussed, and reduced into a classicall
<pb facs="2"/>
method: The latter two I remit to Practice in reading such Oratours and Poets as our Tongue affords, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with every Stationers shop is amply replete.</p>
   <p>But for the present I have only set forth the first part, (as he that would not spend all his shot at once, or the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that first rigs out his Pinnace to certifie whatseas) espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since it is more chiefly conducing to all sorts, it being indeed dressed to sympathize with every palate. The Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologicall part being onely intended for such as are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in higher Classes, shall (God willing) speedily follow, accompanying the Latin Introduction, the better to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate the difference between both Tongues. The benefit that may hereby redound to the Learner, I will not here stand to expostulate, after the custome of every idle Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleter, that is enforced to be the blazer of his own praise to make his book sell the better. Let those that shall make triall speak for me what they find: only this I dare presume, that this little Treatise, rightly taught, will be enough to inform any ordinary capacity the knowledg of our English Tongue, so far as concerns Orthoepie and Orthography: whereby he that is to proceed further, shall not need to waste so much time in English, and yet be sufficiently instructed.</p>
   <p>The manner of teaching it I refer to the judgement of the Teacher, accounting it too much to set up a light, and hold the candlesticke too. The variety of Impressions, (or Prints as we call them) will serve as an instance to my
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
purpose. For the child in <hi>A. B. C.</hi> (as it is termed) that I may begin with the babe, I have caused a new Alphabet, or order of Letters, to be imprinted in the three severall sorts of Characters most usuall in our English, &amp; most Tongues of Europe. When he is perfect in them, and able to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish the Vowels and Consonants asunder, then let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, going presently to the Dipthongs, to be informed by his Master their number and use: thence immediately to the Syllables mixt. The rest at the discretion of the Tutor (for I presume no Teacher is so ignorant as shall need in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions for the ordring of his Pupils.) <hi>Et siquid novit rectius, candidus impertiat;</hi> if not, make use of this with me, that desire to assume no further to my selfe, then what may stand with the glory of God, and the generall good of my endeared Countrey.</p>
   <p>This (as I said) I propose as a servant to all: for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding my whole scope herein be onely to assist the stranger and ignorant, and not to bring in captivity them whose more happy Intellects may of themselves produce more cleare conception; yet if any scholler of our own shall vouchsafe the reading of so poor a Pamphlet, he perhaps in somewhat may find the Proverb true, that saies, <hi>No tree is so barren but may yeeld some fruit,</hi> be it never so little. At least I desire his censure of this <hi>Opusculum,</hi> but newly hatched, may be but as milde, as my intentions reall for the more certain and speedy advancement of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; lest the blossome be blasted ere it comes to perfection.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Thus courteous Reader (of what ranke soever) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of these small labours, as thou shalt find them bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall. Many (I confesse) as well friends as strangers, have much animated and desired me to publish them for the common good. But when they shall come to the open view of the world, I know not how after the Presse they will escape the Rack and Strappado; for bookes and bondage are subject to the most heavie censures: <hi>Sed age Liber, vade liber, &amp; vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>S. D.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="5"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>