<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A briefe Catalogue of Master Darel his apparant contradictions.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109440_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20001</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6440</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109440</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A briefe Catalogue of Master Darel his apparant contradictions.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summarie ansvvere to al the material points in any of Master Darel his bookes : More especiallie to that one booke of his, intituled, the Doctrine of the possession and dispossession of demoniaks out of the word of God. By Iohn Deacon. Iohn Walker. Preachers</title>
                 <author>Deacon, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 240, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary_of_contradictions">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>A briefe Catalogue of Master Darel his apparant contradictions.</head>
   <list>
      <item>
         <hi>1</hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N his doctrine, pag. <hi>29.</hi> he saith to be possessed of a diuell, is as ordinary a disease as blindnes, deafnes, and such like: but ibidem pag. <hi>67.</hi> hee makes both it and the cure an extraordinarie worke, calling for an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie vse. And ibidem pag. <hi>79.</hi> a disease supernaturall, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine supernaturall. And ibidem. pag. <hi>103.</hi> a rare and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie worke of God. And ibidem pag. <hi>105.</hi> the casting out of the diuell at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> is made the same with Christes miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous worke, and aboue some other miraculous actions. Also dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction pag. <hi>41.</hi> supernaturall meanes, supernaturall disease. And pag. <hi>58.</hi> prayer is as ordinarie a meanes as other medicines. And pag. <hi>59.</hi> prayer and fasting an ordinarie meanes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>2</hi> In his detection pag. <hi>54.</hi> signes of dispossession not necessary: but pag. <hi>57,</hi> as also doctrine, pag. <hi>36.</hi> they are absolutelie neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie for sundrie reasons: and a direction left in the word for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the same signes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>3</hi> In his doctrine pag. <hi>39.</hi> no eiection of Satan in the papacie: yet pag. <hi>70.</hi> a true deliuerance in the papacie graunted, and that by their humiliation.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>4</hi> In pag. <hi>39.</hi> he auoucheth a voluntarie departure of diuels: but pag. <hi>77.</hi> the diuell (he saith) must be inticed out.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>5</hi> In his doctrine pag. <hi>12.41.81.</hi> he saith the Demoniakes receiue no hurt at all by anie their torments, and pag. <hi>13.</hi> he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth a reason why: but pag. <hi>36.</hi> hee saith <hi>Darling</hi> was so sore hurt, as for thirteene weekes after he was lame, and had no vse of his legges.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>6</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>40.</hi> hee saith that diuels are now cast forth by Christ his owne absolute authoritie, and pag. <hi>41.</hi> by his absolute &amp; supreame authoritie: but in pag. <hi>55.</hi> he saith that this supernaturall disease is cured by the supernaturall medicine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied thereto, as a natural medicine is applied to a natural disease.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="12"/>
         <hi>7</hi> In his doctrine pag. <hi>41.</hi> hee maketh fasting and prayer a warranted ordinance for the expelling of diuels by the wordes of Christ, in <hi>Matth. 17.21.</hi> and in <hi>Mar. 9.29.</hi> but in his detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pag. <hi>41.</hi> wee read not (saith he) of the first ordayning of anie such meanes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>8</hi> In examining the words of <hi>Math. 17.21.</hi> and <hi>Mar. 9.29.</hi> he saith the same words were spoken to the <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> as appeareth in his doctrine, pag. <hi>41.42.50.</hi> but pag. <hi>43.44.45.46.47.48.49.</hi> he flatlie opposeth himselfe to that exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and inuents many reasons why that speech of Christ should not be appropriated to them of that age: but all this in his detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pag. <hi>43.</hi> hee doth plainely confute in this sort. Christ speakes not (saith he) of the <hi>future</hi> but of the <hi>present</hi> time, saying thus: this kind (<hi>goeth</hi>) not out, but this kind (<hi>shall</hi>) goe out, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>9</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>42.</hi> hee maketh sole prayer the onely meanes that euer was or shal be for casting out <hi>diuels:</hi> but pag. <hi>43</hi> he makes fasting the more effectuall <hi>meanes,</hi> and in pag. <hi>79.</hi> the more soueraigne <hi>meanes.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>10</hi> In his doctrine, pag, <hi>43,</hi> he saith, that by prayer alone, and betimes in the day, euen straight after dinner, and without any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting at all, were sundrie <hi>Diuels</hi> cast out from <hi>K. Wright:</hi> but in his detection, pag. <hi>46.</hi> he makes it a difficult matter to driue out a <hi>diuell</hi> by prayer alone, or by prayer and fasting together.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>11</hi> In laying downe the scope of the text, <hi>Matth. 17.21.</hi> hee noteth two impediments why the <hi>Apostles</hi> could not driue forth the <hi>diuell</hi>; namelie their incredulitie, and the nature of the <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> but pag. <hi>46.</hi> he saith that the <hi>Apostles</hi> then (by vertue of their <hi>miraculous faith</hi>) could doe any thing, and therefore cast out a <hi>diuell</hi> of any kind whatsoeuer, which he further confirmeth, pag. <hi>47.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>12</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>47.</hi> hee saith that the <hi>Disciples</hi> by vertue of their so large a <hi>Commission,</hi> could cast out a <hi>diuell</hi> of anie kinde: but pag. <hi>50.</hi> in the second part of that his <hi>diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> hee saith that the childe was possest with one of the worst kind of <hi>spirits,</hi> and that thence it came that the <hi>Disciples</hi> could not cast them out.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>13</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>54.</hi> hee saith, that prayer and fasting being vsed aright, will certainely prosper, eyther to the remouing or sanctifying of the <hi>iudgement:</hi> but pag. <hi>59.</hi> hee saith there is no assurance to preuaile.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="13"/>
         <hi>14</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>52.</hi> he maketh <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayer the sole <hi>meanes</hi> of conception, and procreation of children: but pag. <hi>60.</hi> another <hi>meanes</hi> is found, and the same also appointed of God for that purpose, or els the conception by sole prayer alone, would proue a <hi>miracle.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>15</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>60.</hi> and <hi>73.</hi> hee saith that <hi>miracles</hi> are vndoubtedlie ceased: but pag. <hi>63.</hi> he saith there is no determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>miracles</hi> in the word.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>16</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>59.</hi> he saith it is plaine, that <hi>prayer,</hi> or <hi>prayer</hi> with <hi>fasting</hi> may be an ordinarie <hi>meanes</hi> appointed of <hi>God</hi> to driue out <hi>diuels,</hi> and yet (being vsed) not prosper to that selfe same end: but page the same, he saith that if any should af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>fasting</hi> are not of that efficacie, to cure any Demoniake without exception, it were an impious affirmation.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>17</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>69.</hi> hee saith. In as much as our Church hath this power to cast out a <hi>diuel,</hi> it conuinceth the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> touching the power they onlie bragge of for casting out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels: but pag. <hi>74.</hi> he saith, the papists haue no more cause to brag of that power, then the <hi>Rogue</hi> hath to boast of the hole in his eare.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>18</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>63.</hi> he saith, there is no determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>miracles</hi> in the word: but pag. <hi>74.75.</hi> that it is now the sole and vndoubted badge of Antichrist to worke <hi>miracles.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>19</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>74.75.</hi> he saith that the <hi>Papists</hi> may worke true <hi>miracles:</hi> but pag. <hi>76.</hi> he saith that <hi>spirits</hi> are neuer cast forth by <hi>papists,</hi> but of themselues goe willinglie out: which if it be so, then there is no miracle wrought.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>20</hi> In his doctrine, (in manie places) he saith that <hi>God</hi> hath left but one <hi>ordinarie meanes</hi> for expelling <hi>diuels,</hi> which is <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>fasting:</hi> but pag. <hi>79.</hi> he makes two distinct <hi>meanes</hi>; the first is the supernaturall medecine of <hi>prayer</hi> alone: the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond he calles another of the same kind, but yet more soueraigne, namely <hi>fasting</hi> and <hi>prayer.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>21</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>11.</hi> and in his Detection, pag. <hi>100.</hi> and pag. <hi>107.</hi> he labours to proue that the parties in deed, were truely <hi>possest,</hi> and <hi>dispossest,</hi> and that vndoubtedly <hi>Satan</hi> did vex them. But in his Doctrine page <hi>81</hi>: he saith, that <hi>Satan</hi> is so cunning, as he can cause things to be in appearance, which are not at all.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>22</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>5.16.25.</hi> and <hi>29.</hi> he saith, that <hi>pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions</hi> are onely to be iudged by the Scriptures, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb facs="13"/>
there is a direction left by the Lord, for the discerning of them. But in his Detection, pag. <hi>34.</hi> he saith that <hi>Christ</hi> did not ordaine any such meanes, for then we should haue it in the Scriptures; and such an <hi>ordinance</hi> there, I dare be hold to say we haue none.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>23</hi> In his Detection, pag. <hi>163.</hi> he saith, fier hath power to burne: but in the same pag. that fier hath no power to burne.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>24</hi> In his Doctrine pag. <hi>2.</hi> he saith, that it suteth altogether with <hi>Satans</hi> nature, to be filthy and wicked in speech: but in his Detection pag. <hi>175.</hi> he saith, that it suteth as well with his nature, to vse good and holy speeches.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>25</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>89.</hi> he saith, that the <hi>Lord</hi> (in these daies) doth send <hi>Diuels</hi> into men for these speciall endes, Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, first,<note place="margin">Luk. <hi>16.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>▪</hi>
         </note> to confound <hi>Atheists:</hi> secondly to reforme some. But (in the same page) he alleageth such a Scripture as sheweth euidently that no such thing can be possiblie effected: which causeth him to say, there is little hope, that any of the aforesaid ends should there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be effected. Yet (opposing himselfe to the word) he vseth many ydle speeches about that matter, and brabbles much for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of those ends thereby.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>26</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>37.</hi> he saith, the <hi>Spirits</hi> were seene and felt of the parties in some visible <hi>formes</hi> or <hi>shapes.</hi> But pag. <hi>9.9.</hi> he saith, they could not possibly be seene, or felt, being inuisible creatures: onely they were beheld in their operations and effectes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>27</hi> In his Doctrine (in many places) he makes it a most neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary work which was done vpon those his pretended <hi>Demoniakes.</hi> But pag. <hi>102.</hi> he saith it was such a worke, as neither any part of truth needeth nor yet man, in regard of his weakenesse: but in the words following, he would pinne many necessary vses vpon it, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, confirmation of the strong, perswasion of the weake, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>28</hi> In his Detection, pag. <hi>102.</hi> he doubts not, but <hi>Sommers</hi> may be recouered. But in his <hi>Narration</hi> of the <hi>Lancashire De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniakes,</hi> pag. <hi>13.</hi> he giues a definitiue sentence, that he, and two others, shall neuer be cured, quoting for proofe, Luke <hi>11.26.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>29</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>60.</hi> he saith. It is no <hi>miracle</hi> that is done by <hi>meanes.</hi> But pag. <hi>63.</hi> he saith, that God can, and often doth bring most mightie thinges to passe, by small, and weake <hi>meanes.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>30</hi> In in his doctrine, pag. <hi>10.</hi> The Demoniakes in their fits, are depriued of all their <hi>senses externall</hi> and <hi>internall:</hi> but pag. <hi>11.</hi> they seeme onlie to be so, and therefore are sayde to be so.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="14"/>
         <hi>31</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>47.</hi> hee saith that the <hi>Apostles</hi> faith failed not: but pag. <hi>48.</hi> hee saith their faith fayled at this time when <hi>Christ</hi> spake to them, and in this very worke.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>32</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>38.</hi> he saith that these words (<hi>going out</hi> and <hi>entring in</hi>) are neuer vsed in the spirituall sense: but (in the same place) hee saith they are often and vsuallie taken in the literall sense: howbeit in his Detection, pag. <hi>58.</hi> hee saith those words are onely but <hi>Metaphors.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>33</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>50.</hi> he saith that the <hi>Disciples</hi> could not driue forth the <hi>diuell</hi> from the child by that their <hi>miraculous faith</hi>: but pag. <hi>47.</hi> and in his Detection, pag. <hi>24.</hi> he saith they could, and that one eiected so is much more admirable, then that which is done by prayer.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>34</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>59.</hi> hee saith, that neyther the whole Church, nor any member thereof (in vsing the meanes) can haue assurance to preuaile: but (in the same page) hee saith, the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is or may be great in such a case.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>35</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>66.</hi> hee maketh fasting and prayer the onelie ordinarie meanes to cast out <hi>diuels</hi>: but (in the same page) he saith, that Satan was so cast out of <hi>Darling</hi> and the rest, as Christ himselfe did cast him out, namelie by the finger of <hi>God:</hi> which manner of working he aduiseth to distinguish from all other manner of casting out <hi>diuels,</hi> as appeareth pa. <hi>55.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>36</hi> In his detection, pag. <hi>49.</hi> he saith, that faith temporarie, and historicall, are of sufficient force to cast out <hi>diuels</hi>: but in his doctrine, pag. <hi>93.</hi> where he expresseth what he meanes by fasting, he requireth such fruits of faith to be ioyned with <hi>fasting,</hi> as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possiblie proceed from these his two former kinds of faith.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>37</hi> In his doctrine (euerie where) hee saith that <hi>prayer</hi> is the Churches ordinarie <hi>meanes</hi> to driue out <hi>diuels</hi>: but in his dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, pag. <hi>6.</hi> he saith, to intreat <hi>Christ</hi> to cast out a <hi>diuell</hi> is <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>38</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>45.</hi> hee saith that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> they needed not to haue prayed before their working of <hi>miracles,</hi> their faith being strong: but pag. <hi>45.</hi> hee saith they did so pray, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to encrease their faith or to some other good end.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>39</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>46.</hi> he concludes directlie against his owne <hi>Analysing</hi> and expounding of that scripture, which was put downe, pag. <hi>42.</hi> Also he sets <hi>Matth. 17 21.</hi> and <hi>Luk. 9.1.</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fast by the eares. Againe, he alleadgeth <hi>Act. 19.12. Luk. 9.1.</hi>
         <pb facs="14"/>
and <hi>Matth. 10.1.</hi> directlie crossing his owne exposition, concerning <hi>Math. 17.21.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>40</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>30.</hi> he calles all men to the <hi>Law</hi> and to the <hi>testimonie.</hi> But pag. <hi>54.</hi> and in his Detection, pag. <hi>42.</hi> he standes for the defence of secret, and vnreuealed <hi>ordinances.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>41</hi> In his Doctrine (euery where) and in his Detection, pag. <hi>23.</hi> he saith that those are no <hi>miracles</hi> which are done by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <hi>meanes</hi> of <hi>fasting</hi> and <hi>prayer.</hi> But in his Detection. pag. <hi>49.</hi> he alleadgeth Math. <hi>7.22.</hi> to proue that there were others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the <hi>Apostles,</hi> who cast out <hi>Diuels</hi>: which place of <hi>Mathew</hi> telleth vs expresly, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the men spoken of there, did work miracles.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>42</hi> In his <hi>1. Narration,</hi> pag. <hi>10.</hi> and in his Doctrine, pag. <hi>6.</hi> he saith, there is no determination for the ceasing of <hi>miracles</hi> in al the Scriptures: but in his Doctrine, pag. <hi>63.</hi> &amp; <hi>73.</hi> he saith that the gift of working <hi>miracles</hi> continued in the <hi>Church</hi> but a time. And in his Detection, pag. <hi>23.</hi> and <hi>25.</hi> he saith, that before <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Cyprian,</hi> and those Fathers times, the working of <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> was vndoubtedly ceased.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>43</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>42.</hi> he calleth <hi>fasting</hi> and <hi>prayer</hi> a secret <hi>ordinance.</hi> But pag. <hi>44.</hi> he makes it an expresse <hi>ordinance</hi> and a <hi>meanes</hi> expreslie and by name spoken of by Christ.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>44</hi> In his Doctrine, pag. <hi>42.</hi> he putteth downe two impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments why the <hi>Apostle</hi> could not cast forth the <hi>Diuell</hi> from the <hi>Child.</hi> But pag. <hi>44.</hi> he saith, that, that text can no further be vnderstood of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> then onely to signifie vnto them, the nature of that <hi>spirit</hi>: whence partlie it came to passe, that they could not cast him out.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>45</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>44.</hi> he saith that <hi>Stapleton</hi> doth not appropriate the text in <hi>Mat. 17.21.</hi> to the <hi>Apostles</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> but pag. <hi>45.</hi> he saith, that <hi>Thyreus</hi> and <hi>Stapleton</hi> both doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that text of the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselues, who (notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their <hi>miraculous faith</hi>) should also haue prayed.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>46</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>42.49.50.</hi> he so vnderstandeth these words of <hi>Christ (this kind goeth not forth)</hi> as if they should containe in them an exception of the <hi>particular,</hi> from out of the <hi>generall:</hi> but pag. <hi>46.</hi> hee saith that hee taketh that <hi>sense</hi> to be very vnsound, and contrarie to the meaning of <hi>Christ.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>47</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>49.</hi> hee distinguisheth <hi>diuels</hi> by their sundrie sorts, degrees, or orders: but pag. <hi>51.</hi> hee distinguisheth them by their only naturall qualities: as malice, crueltie, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="15"/>
         <hi>48</hi> In his doctrine, pag. <hi>59.</hi> he saith God is at libertie, and not tied to meanes: but pag. <hi>61.</hi> he tieth him fast to <hi>meanes</hi>; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs that if <hi>God</hi> hath appointed a thing to come to passe by this or that <hi>meanes,</hi> then the <hi>meanes</hi> must be vsed, or els that thing will neuer come to passe.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>49</hi> In his doctrine pag. <hi>2.</hi> hee saith, it is absurd to affirme that the <hi>diuell</hi> (being without a man) can dispose of the whole or ante part of mans bodie: but detection, pag. <hi>110.</hi> he saith that the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell</hi> (in all probability) did vse <hi>Sommers</hi> his tongue; notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hee was essentiallie and sensiblie playing boe peepe vnder the couerled.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>50</hi> In his detection, pag. <hi>111.</hi> he saith he would be ashamed to auouch, that the diuell would neuer giue <hi>Sommers</hi> ouer, vntill he had repossessed him: but in his doctrine, pag. <hi>102.</hi> hee confidently affirmeth, that though <hi>Sommers</hi> should (in deed) be dispossest by the appoynted <hi>meanes:</hi> yet would the <hi>diuel</hi> labour very earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to reenter, and neuer giue ouer till he had repossessed him, which also (he saith) he hath.</item>
   </list>
   <p>These and sundrie such other apparant <hi>contradictions</hi> so v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersallie scattered in euerie of M. <hi>Darel his pamphlets:</hi> they may giue the sound hearted <hi>Readers</hi> some precedent tast of that subsequent soundnes, which they are likely to find throughout the whole building.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>7.26.27</hi>
      </note> For euen as when the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oundation</hi> it selfe is sandie and sliding, the whole <hi>frame</hi> that is founded theron, must necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie become but a reeling and tottering <hi>Tower,</hi> and lie hourelie subiect <hi>to a desperate downefall:</hi> so surely when the <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels,</hi> the <hi>studs,</hi> the <hi>raysing peeces,</hi> the <hi>iouystes,</hi> the <hi>tracings,</hi> and all the rest of the timber belonging thereto, are at such an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant oddes in euerie of their <hi>Geometricall proportions,</hi> the workemanship whatsoeuer (when it is brought to the best) it will seeme but a bungerlie hotch potch, and the whole frame it selfe can neuer be firme, howsoeuer <hi>M Darel</hi> or any his <hi>Fauorits</hi> may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies hugge the same in their armes as the <hi>Ape</hi> doth her brood, till she hath vtterlie beref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them all of their liues.</p>
   <p>The consideration hereof may make the considerate <hi>Readers</hi> to conceiue thus of the matter and say. If these mens seuerall writings be apparantlie found at such deadlie debate in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: how is it possible they should continue or hold any confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable concord with the approued writings of others.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, it may please the good <hi>Reader</hi> to remember withal,
<pb facs="15"/>
that such absurd <hi>positions</hi> and so many apparant <hi>contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> they cannot possiblie proceed from that <hi>spirit of truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iohn <hi>16.13.</hi>
      </note> which <hi>leadeth</hi> into all soundnes of <hi>truth and religion:</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue in them no force at all to fight for the <hi>Lord,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. <hi>13.9.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>who needeth not the lies of mortall men.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Brieflie, this we our selues doe certainely know, &amp; all men (more especiallie the <hi>iudiciall</hi> sort) they plainely perceiue, that howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer those their pretended essentiall <hi>possessions</hi> and <hi>dispossessions</hi> of <hi>diuels</hi> may haplie accord with the truth of the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> yet these their published <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> they will neuer be able to make good the supposed <hi>truths</hi> which themselues doe pretend: and that therefore they must of necessitie be forced to begin a new ground, or to giue ouer their cause. The <hi>Lord</hi> by his <hi>spirit</hi> direct vs only vnto that which tends to the glory of his great name, the present good of his <hi>Church,</hi> and our owne euerlasting comforts in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ.</hi> So be it: euen so Lord Iesu. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>