<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>


The prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1519</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109114_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18180</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4815</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109114</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>


The prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here begynneth the orcharde of Syon : in the whiche is conteyned the reuelacyons of seynt Katheryne of Sene, with ghostly fruytes &amp; precyous plantes for the helthe of mannes soule</title>
                 <author>Catherine, of Siena, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Worde, Wynkyn de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1519</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>350 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <head>
      <figure>
</figure>
      <pb facs="2"/>
The prologue.</head>
   <head type="sub">¶ Marcus Cinilis (a Bryxian) wryteth an Epystle in latyn to a deuoute fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / Frere Paule Sauche / an Aragon / obseruaunt of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fcere prechers / in to the commendacyon of the dyalogys or reuelacyons of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vyrgyn seynt Katheryne of Sene / of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche Epystle in sentence / here foloweth parte / trāslated ī to englysshe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monges many ylles of them that be professed to crystes rely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y on / one there is ferre out of of the waye of helthe that we were in stytute in / and greately to be reproued. That men now a dayes (and that relygyous) do not regarde those holy workes / rules / &amp; doctrynes / that be necessary to theyr ghostly helthe / but take thē in vayne and as thynges of no valour / whiche they oughte dylygently to loke vpon / and to apply thē bothe nyghte and daye to worke and lyue after the same. And those that be vayne &amp; superfluus / lytell sauour hauynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> swete name and loue of Ihesu cryst / smally condusynge to helthe of soules / be moche set by and desyred / dayly had in hande as thynges moche beloued. Doubtelesse it is a greate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>efaute &amp; a deedly blyndenesse of mynde. yf they wolde lerne and folowe those techynges / wherby the soule and the mynde myght be lyghtned to spyryall and heuenly thynges / attēdynge &amp; lokynge to theyr ende that they be ordeyned vnto / they sholde full besyly serche and loke what waye and meanes sholde conduce them to it / and folowe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. But no man desyreth greately that good thynge / nor excheweth that yll / that he hathe no knowlege of. who is so frowarde and vnkynde vnto hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe / that yf he knewe that heuenly Hierusalem and the ioye therin (but one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly after the maner / as the charyte of god hathe shewed it vnto our weyke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstondynge / by his owne wordes / &amp; by the doctryne of holy seyntes) And agayn warde yf he wolde sadly ponder those ylles that be prepared for thē that shall be exyled fro thens / wolde he not lose hȳselfe frome all erthely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccyons / and full faste renne vnto it / and all thynges cōtrary and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tynge / exchewe as dethe / as truly they be moche worse thā dethe ī dede. This haue I thoughte alwaye / but than most specyally &amp; appered manyfest vnto me / whan I toke on honde to rede the dyaloges of the holy vyrgyn seynt Kathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryne of Sene / a meruaylous myrtour of holynesse. Whome oure sauyoure Ihesu chose vnto his spouse / and induced her with many graces / after a syn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guler maner. And for her moste feruent loue / profounde mekenesse / merua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ylous pacyence / and wonderfull compassyon y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> she had / he impressed in her body the pryntes of his woundes / and preserued her lōge tyme in this lyfe / without bodyly sustenaunce. Pope Pius the secunde / and Raymundus w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> dyuers other holy men / besyde the cronyculers / testyfy her holynesse / and wryte greate bookes of her lyfe / &amp; the actes that she hathe done / greately to the edyfyenge of crystes chyrche. O meruaylous goodnes of god / that hath
<pb facs="3"/>chosen so weyke a parson of woman kynde / to confounde the greate men of myghte and all theyr pusaunce. what techynges be there set furthe: to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounde and order the maners of men? what preceptes be ther gyuē to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styce and subdewe the bodyly affeccyons? what counseyles haue we there shewed / to kepe vs vnder the bondes of reason? No wher can mā more plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sauntly be alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and drawen to the loue of god. No where more terryble can he be made afered to cōmytte synne. No wher more profoūdely the truthe is shewed without errour / nor the dygnyte of vertu more clerely opened / and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abhomynacyon of vyce more openly dyscouered. There is the rule and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of chastyte and clennesse to be conserued. There is gadered togyder compendyously: dyscyplyne of lowlynesse / and vertu to be noryshed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresced. There be opened secrete counseyles of god. There is shewed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his prouydēce. There to them that be blynde by malyce or ygno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce / is restored the lyght of truthe. And to them that haue knowlege of truthe / it is there preserued for to defende errours. There to them that be cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryous in reasonynge / it is answered and satysfyed to theyr argumētes. To thē that be good and wyse / is shewed thynges worthy theyr knowlege. And truly it is so plentefully / so holsomely / so holyly / prouyded all maner wayes / for mannes pylgrymage here in this lyfe / that (after my Iudgement) there can no erthely creature counseyle or prouyde more wysely for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> helthe of mā / nor more surely. Nor no meruayle / for very often (and in maner whan she wolde) she was rauyshed in spyryte vnto god / and so she was acustomed in extasy to haue reuelacyōs and dyologes bytwene cryste and her / and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to endyte them. Wherfore I wyll not fere to saye and affyrme this / that there is no man of so paruerse and obstynate malyce / but yf he loke vpō thē with good auysement not hastely nor enuyously) not onely parceyuynge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wordes with his eres outwardely / but also the sence w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his mynde inwarde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly he shall not repente hym / but fynde greate grace therby / and pleasure in his soule. Who sholde not be greately moued meruaylynge moche / suche a yonge mayde of tender age / to be lyke in lernynge to noble clerkes / and to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yte so profounde sentences / so depely drawe fro y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> well of the hye dyuyne wysedome / that it is harde for many to parceyue / excepte they haue meke lernynge and ghostly wysdome. So thoughe that her gloryous and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente holynesse sholde gyue none auctoryte to her doctryne and preceptes / yet frome what soeuer condyte they come out of / they bere moste sure testy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of themselfe without doubte / that they flowe out fro none other / but fro the godly funtayne &amp; sprynge of grace. Nor they haue none other begyn nynge but that (where vnto) they enforce besyly to brynge the reder vnto / whiche is god hymselfe. The bryghtnesse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sonne / can procede from none other thynge / but frome the sonne. So heuenly thȳges come not / but from heuē. And that thynge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> belongeth to god / hymselfe onely dothe knowe / &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>they whome it pleaseth hȳ to shewe it vnto. Therfore all you y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be louers of youre owne helthe (&amp; not onely you) but onely al you y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue lytell feythe and affeccyon to heuēly thynges / you that be ylecte &amp; snarled in the dysceyuable pleasures &amp; lustes of the flesshe &amp; the worlde. yf you couet to haue eternall Ioye / come hyder &amp; fyll the vessels of youre hertes at this well / with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of holsome doctryne. Fede you here with the swete meet of ghostly coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayll y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cometh fro heuen. He that lacketh this ghostly syght / here maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue lyght. He that is in sorowe or heuynesse / here maye haue comforte and consolacyō. He that is wery / here maye take reste. He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is dull &amp; slowe / shall be quyckened &amp; made dylygent. He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is weyke / here maye receyue strengthe. He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is rude &amp; vnlerned / maye gette here lernȳge &amp; holy maners. And more ouer he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath good syght in lernȳge / a quyet mȳde / and is strōge / cōstant / &amp; vertuous / yf he drȳke of this wel / it shal not helpe onely to enorme hȳ &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serue hȳ therin / but also it shal enlarge &amp; encrease hȳ in all goodnesse. I ony mā thynke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I saye or promyse other wyse than it is in dede / let hȳ loke wel vpon this worke / and compare my sayenges vnto it / and yf he fynde not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I haue sayde moche lesse for the mater (than I ought to do) let hȳ take me for a babbeler / and poynt me with his fynger / as a man of no fydelyte. Let no man dysdayne it or set lesse by it / by reason of the rude style / or of the symple translacyon / for he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> translated it / intended more y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eloquence of maners thā of wordes. ¶ The eloquence of good lyfe oughte not to be contempned nor hated for lacke of eloquent speche. This booke is not ordeyned for to delyte &amp; please the eeres &amp; the outwarde senses / but to instructe the soule / and to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte the inwarde senses. It conteyneth no preceptes of eloquence / but it is ful of heuenly speche and of vertuous doctryne. Therfore let not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lytell byt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternesse of the outwarde huske / kepe you fro y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plesaunt tastynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> swete kernell within (that is) let not the symplenesse of the style / nor laboure of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge: kepe you fro the swete doctryne &amp; ghostly comforte y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye maye haue in this booke / whiche promyseth truthe &amp; sheweth it clerely. It she with heuē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thynges &amp; bryngeth thē forthe habūdantly. It graūteth eternall Ioye / to all thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> wyll worke after it parseuerantly. whiche our lorde graunte vs to do (In whome) all ye reders / fare ye well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>