<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Fiction by way of Argument on this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109400_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05324</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15467</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109400</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Fiction by way of Argument on this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The young gallants whirligigg: or Youths reakes : Demonstrating the inordinate affections, absurd actions, and profuse expences, of vnbridled and affectated youth: with their extravagant courses, and preposterous progressions, and aversions. Together with the too often deare bought experience, and the rare, or too late regression and reclamation of most of them from their habituall ill customes, and vnqualified manners. Compiled and written by F.L</title>
                 <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bostock, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 22, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A Fiction by way of Argument on this Booke.</head>
   <l>POndering the pathes of this polluted age,</l>
   <l>And viewing every Scene vpon the Stage</l>
   <l>Of this vile orbe; me thought I did behold</l>
   <l>A giddy spirit in an Isle of Gold;</l>
   <l>His head me thought was like a Wind-mill, bigge,</l>
   <l>In which ten thousand thoughts run Whirligigg,</l>
   <l>Inclos'd he was (not by delusiue dreames)</l>
   <l>With reall luftre of <hi>Pactola's</hi> streames;</l>
   <l>In which he proudly sailes with glorious deckes,</l>
   <l>Vntill the frigide Zone his passage checkes</l>
   <l>By hard congealed Rocks, by which he split</l>
   <l>His goodly <hi>Bulke</hi>; shipwrackt himselfe, and it.</l>
   <l>But <hi>Neptune</hi> tendring his vnhappy goare,</l>
   <l>Commands the waues to cast him on the shoare,</l>
   <l>Where when a while in mind he had forecast</l>
   <l>His finne against the gods by times ill past,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Ioue</hi> sent his messenger to tell him yet,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Pallas</hi> had promis'd wisedome, to his wit;</l>
   <l>This rais'd his spirits, and twixt griefe▪ and zeale,</l>
   <l>By bright <hi>Apollo's</hi> ayde, rings youth a Peale.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>