<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ILE OF GVLLS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109425_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69188</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6414</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109425</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ILE OF GVLLS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ile of gulls : As it hath been often acted in the Black Fryers, by the Children of the Revels</title>
                 <author>Day, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheares, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE ILE OF GVLLS.</head>
   <stage>I Enter severally three Gentlemen, as to see a Play.</stage>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW now gallants, what ist? what ist?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>The Ile of Guls.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>The Ile of Guls, what should that be?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>A play by the name, but come shals quarter our selues?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>If some had had the wit to doe so in time, they might haue sau'd the hang-man a labour. But come boy, furnish us with stooles.</p>
   </sp>
   <stage>Enter Prologue.</stage>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Pardon mee sir, my office is to speake a Prologue, not to provide you stooles.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>And you were the Epilogue to sir—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Fie be not incivill: dost heare youth, prethee what's he that discovered your new found Land, <hi>the Ile of Guls?</hi> what is he?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>A meere stranger sir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>A stranger? the better welcome: comes hee East-ward, West-ward, or North-ward hoe?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>None of the three wayes I assure you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>Prethee where is he?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Not on his knees in a comer to <hi>Apollo,</hi> praying that his play may hold in a good hand at Passage, nor on the stage amongst gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, preparing a bespoke Plaudite; but close in his study writing hard, to get him a handsome suite against Summer.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>And where sit his friends? hath he not a prepared company of gallants, to applaud his jests, and grace out his play?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>None I protest▪ Do Poets use to bespeake their Auditory?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>The best in grace doe, and but for that, some that I know, had never had their grace in Poetry till this day.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Then must our Author looké for a certaine disgrace, for he is altogether unfurnisht of such a friendly audience.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>Then he must lay his triall upon God and good wits But why
<pb facs="3"/>
doth he call his play <hi>The Ile of Gulls?</hi> it begets much expectation.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Not out of any dogged disposition, nor that it figures any certaine state, or private government: farre bee that supposition from the thought of any indifferent Auditor: and the argument being a little string or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ivolet, drawen from the full straine of the right worthy Gentleman Sir <hi>Phillip Sydnies</hi> well knowne Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, confirmes it: only a Duke, to make triall of certaine experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, retires with his retinue into a namelesse desert. Now as well for fashion sake, as that all those which haue to doe in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, are guld in the reach of their hopes; therefore he cals it, (and as he presumes, not improperly) <hi>The Ile of Gulls.</hi>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>Out a question he hath promised thee some fee, thou pleadest so hard for him, but and he be a right Poet he will never performe it. But what method obserues he in his Play, ist any thing Criticall? Are Lawyers fees, and Citizens wiues laid open in it? I loue to heare vice anatomizd, and abuse let blood in the master vaine, is there any great mans life charactred in't?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>None I protest sir, only in the person of <hi>Dametas,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses to the life the monstrous and deformed shape of vice, aswell to beget a loathing of abuse, as that his villany may giue the greater luster to the vertuous dispositions of true-borne gentility.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>All that's nothing to mee, and there bee not Worme-wood water and Copperes in't, Ile not like it, should <hi>Apollo</hi> write it, and <hi>Rosius</hi> himselfe act it.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Fie upon thee, thou art too too criticall: is there any good baudry in't, jests of an ell deepe, and a fathome broad, good cuckol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, may a couple of young-setters-up learne to doe well in't? Giue me a Scene of venery, that will make a mans spirits stand on their tiptoes, and die his blood in a deepe scarlet, like your <hi>Ovids Ars Amandi,</hi> there flowes the true Spring-head of Poetry, and the very Christall fount of <hi>Parnassus.</hi>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Chast eares would never endure it fir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Chast eares? now deafenesse light upon them, what should chast eares doe at a play?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>Tis strange now, I am of neither a both your opinions, I like neither rayling nor baudry: no, giue me a stately pend historie, as thus: <hi>The rugged winds, with rude and ragged ruffes, &amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Fie upon't, more fustian; I had rather heare two good baudy jests, then a whole play of such teare-cat thunder-claps.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Alas Gentlemen, bow ist possible to content you? you wil haue rayling, and invectiues, which our Author neither dares, nor affects: you baudy and scurrill jests, which neither becomes his modesty to write, nor the eare of a generous Auditory to heare: you must haue swelling comparisons, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ast Epithites, which are as fit for the body of a Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>edy▪ as <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>les</hi> shooe for the foote of a Pigmey: yet all these we must haue, and all in one play, or tis already condemn'd to the hell of eternall disgrace.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>Looke to't, if there be not gall in't, it shall not passe.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>If it be not baudy, tis impossible to passe:</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>If it bee both criticall and baudy, if it bee not high written, both your Poet and the house too, loose a friend of me.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Nay I beseech you sir, if you be his friend, stand so to him still, for he hath too many enemies already, in whose judgements, he and his labours stand excommunicate, as though unworthy to present themselues in this assembly.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>1</speaker>
      <p>Enemies? nays foote then there's some hope in his play, for Envie never workes but against desert and merit. If he be envied theres some worth in him, and ile see out his play for that onely.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Faith and Ile see an act or two out, but I tell you afore-hand I cannot see it out.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>Not see it out? your reason.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Fore God I lay in bed till past three a clock, slept out my din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and my stomacke will toule to supper afore fiue, therefore you must pardon me.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>Either see it all or none; for tis growen into a custome at playes, if any one rise (especially of any fashionable sort) about what serious busines soever, the rest thinking it in dislike of the play, though he never thinks it, cry mew, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esus vilde; and leaue the poore heartlesse children to speake their Epilogue to the empty seats.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>3</speaker>
      <p>Why doest thinke thy audience like a flock of sheepe, that one cannot leape over a hedge, but all the rest will follow? they haue more of reason in them then so.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>2</speaker>
      <p>Well, Ile sit out the play, an't bee but to avoyd that sheepish imputation, but see it be baudy, or by this light I and all my friends will hisse.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Prol.</speaker>
      <p>You should not deale gentleman-like with us els.</p>
   </sp>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>