<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣REND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, by divine Providence, Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate, and Metropolitan of all England, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuie Counsaile.</title>
           <author>Day, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109428_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19984</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6424</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109428</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣REND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, by divine Providence, Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate, and Metropolitan of all England, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuie Counsaile.</title>
                 <author>Day, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Day's descant on Dauids Psalmes: or A commentary vpon the Psalter, as it is vsually read throughout the yeere, at morning, and euening prayer : And first, of the first eight Psalmes, appointed to be read, the first day of the moneth</title>
                 <author>Day, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 176, 179-222 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, by divine Providence, Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Primate, and Metropolitan of all <hi>England, and one of his</hi> MAIESTIES <hi>most Honourable Priuie Counsaile.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Reuerend in Christ:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Liuy</hi> of the Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick:<note n="a" place="margin">Liv. <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 1</note>
      <hi>Aut me Amor Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotij suscepti fallit, aut nulla vnquam Resp. nec Maior, nec Sanctior, nec bonis Exemplis Ditior fuit:</hi> so may I of the BOOKE of PSALMES, or I am too too farre transported with the Loue I beare to that <hi>Booke,</hi> or there is no <hi>Booke</hi> in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more necessary to be intreated of, or which containeth more excellent Matter, or is more repleat with heauenly Passages. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Booke of holy Scripture,</hi> saith great Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasius, <hi>hath that which is proper, and peculiar to it selfe,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> Epist. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellin, <hi>de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terp. Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 740. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> Comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: <hi>but as for the Booke of Psalmes</hi> saith he, <hi>that is a Paradice, wherein i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> planted euery Tree.</hi> So S. Basil: <hi>The Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="3"/> haue Doctrine proper to themselues, the Bookes of History haue Matter peculiar to themselues, the Law her particular Forme of Teaching, and againe the Prouerbiall Bookes theirs,</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Basil.</hi> Hom. in Princip. Ps. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>99.</hi> Edit. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil. 1532.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: <hi>but the Booke of Psalmes compriseth in it the Profit of them all.</hi> So S. Chrysostom: <hi>Forasmuch as the Reading of Scripture hath much labour and paine, the Apostle here perswades thee not, to the Reading of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, but to the Psalmes, that so by singing them, thou mayst not only delight thy Mind but beguile the Paine that would otherwise clog and cloy thee.</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Chry.</hi> in ep. ad Coloss. c <hi>3.</hi> Hom. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>74.</hi> b. Edit. <hi>Veron. 1529.</hi> Edit. <hi>SAVIL.</hi> Tom. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>138.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>the Psalmes containe all.</hi> But what need wee goe to <hi>Greece</hi> for <hi>Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> in this case, hauing so ample Testimonie of his at hoame, for whom the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> may blesse the time that euer he was borne. I meane Reverend <hi>Hooker,</hi> who spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Psalmes, <hi>VVhat is there necessary</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Hooker <hi>Eccles. Pol. l.</hi> 5. §. 37.</note> saith he, <hi>for Man to know, which the Psalmes are not able to teach. They are to Beginners an easie and familiar Introduction, a mighty Augmentation of all Vertue, and Knowledge in such as are entred before, a strong Confirmation to the most perfect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst others. Heroicall Magnanimity, exquisite
<pb facs="3"/> Iustice, graue Moderation, exact VVisdome, Repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance vnfained, vnwearied Patience, the Mysteries of God, the Sufferings of Christ, the Terrors of VVrath; the Comforts of Grace, the VVorkes of Prouidence ouer the VVorld, and the promised Ioyes of that World which is to come, all Good necessarily to be either knowne, or done, or had, this one Celesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Fountaine yeeldeth. Let there be any Griefe, or Disease incident to the Soule of Man, for which there is not in this Treasure-House a present comfortable Remedy at all times ready to be found.</hi> All which, hauing bene experimented in euery Age, hence it is that <hi>Dauids</hi> HARP hath euer had the preheminence aboue the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort of those Heathen Musitians <hi>Simonides, Pindarus, Alcaeus, Horace, Catullus,</hi> and the rest; howsoeuer<note n="f" place="margin">My LORD of LOND. vpon <hi>Ionas.</hi> Lect. 27. p. 355. in Marg. &amp; <hi>Barth. Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raei</hi> Itinerar. in Psalt. <hi>Epist. Dodic.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Angelus Politianus,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus Bonamicus</hi> preferred <hi>Pindarus</hi> before him. Hence it was that <hi>Frederick</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> late King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> wrote a little Manuell with his owne Hand, of some of the choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest of them, which was his continuall <hi>Vade Mecum,</hi> as his most <hi>Excellent</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">His MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES. Meditation vpon the LORDS Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. p. 96.</note> MAIESTY, our SOVERAIGNE hath bene pleased to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. Hence it was that long before,
<pb facs="4"/> ALFRED, great ALFRED, the<note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Sam. Daniel</hi> Hist. of En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> l. 1. p. 36.</note> First let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered <hi>Prince</hi> we had in <hi>England,</hi> and by whose meanes, &amp; incouragement, publique <hi>Schools</hi> had here, either their reviving or beginning, that ALFRED, I say, began to translate the <hi>Psalter</hi> into <hi>English,</hi> and well nigh had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished it, but that<note n="i" place="margin">M <hi>Fox</hi> his Act. and Mon. Edit. 4ae. p. 144 Col. 1. ex Hist. <hi>Guliel.</hi> de <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gib. Angl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Death</hi> which could by no means be intreated to spare, prevented him. In a word, hence it is that our Mother the CHVRCH of ENGLAND hath taken such speciall care that the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Psalmes</hi> should be read ouer, every <hi>Moneth,</hi> and to be otherwise read then other <hi>Scripture,</hi> namely by interlocution, and with a mutuall returne of sentences from side to side, that so it might proue the more familiar to every of vs. To say nothing of the<note n="l" place="margin">Polid. Virg. <hi>De Iuvent. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> which causeth them to be read ouer once a weeke, forasmuch as She stands vpon the <hi>Opus O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratum</hi> onely, and takes no<note n="m" place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>te No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i, apud qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Scriptura coelestes legun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur potius quàm intelligu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tur. <hi>Cyp. ad No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat.</hi>
      </note> care at all to haue it interpreted to the People.</p>
   <p>This and more then this being to be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the BOOKE of PSALMES, I haue adventured among the Variety of <hi>Bookes</hi> now extant, to interpret the same vnto the
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Church.</hi> Which though it hath as other <hi>Bookes</hi> of <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> store of Interpretours, yet in the Course that I follow, and in the Way that I take, I could neuer yet light, asmuch as vpon <hi>One.</hi> The way that I take, is the way of our <hi>English Church,</hi> and that <hi>Translation</hi> which Shee followeth in the <hi>Liturgie</hi> Shee vseth. Which <hi>Translation</hi> of Hers, howsoeuer it is not altogether as is the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> yet is it that which for the most part is correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with the <hi>Greeke,</hi> and our <hi>Church</hi> besides approouing it, as hitherto She hath, and still doth it well deserueth these paines to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken therewith.</p>
   <p>And indeed it will bee Paines to goe in this kinde through all. For being in all an <hi>Hundred</hi> and <hi>Fifty,</hi> and divided into <hi>Thirtie Daies</hi> according to the <hi>Daies</hi> of the <hi>Moneth,</hi> what will it bee to <hi>Comment</hi> on all? What to bring for every of them the Provision our<note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2.</note> Saviour speakes of, <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Old.</hi> Vpon the <hi>First Eight,</hi> and the <hi>First Day</hi> of the <hi>Moneth,</hi> I haue here aduentured, as your GRACE may see. If they be acceptable to your GRACE, as I nothing doubt but they shall bee, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="5"/> the <hi>Author</hi> of them hath been so many wayes oblieged to your GRACE, (and to loue them on whom wee bestow <hi>Benefits</hi> is <hi>Nature,</hi> because in them wee behold the <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> of our <hi>Vertue</hi>) your GRACE hereafter may make him in Gods <hi>House</hi> no lesse then a MONETH, who is as yet but one DAY.</p>
   <p>The Lord of <hi>Heauen</hi> blesse your GRACE and affoord you many good <hi>Dayes,</hi> and <hi>Moneths,</hi> and <hi>Yeeres</hi> amongst vs, that your GRACE reuiued, as it were, out of the <hi>Ashes</hi> of that Glorious <hi>Martyr,</hi> your Predecessor, CRANMER of blessed memory (who died before the<note n="o" place="margin">Act &amp; Mon. Edit. 4ae. p. 1569. and 1888.</note>
      <hi>Gates</hi> of that <hi>Colledge,</hi> out of which, your GRACE is risen vnto vs) you may still with the help of that most Glorious MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY in <hi>Heauen,</hi> and his Excellent MAIESTY here on <hi>Earth,</hi> stand against <hi>Thousands</hi> of the <hi>Church Malignant,</hi> and that whole <hi>Alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Rabble of Pontificious and Factious<note n="n" place="margin">M.C; N.D; C.E; I. E; H.I; I. R; L.R; S.R; W.R; <hi>and such like impetuous ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Snarlers. DOMINI</hi> Seru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere nati.</note>
      <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits,</hi> the Ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of CHVRCH and COMMONWEALTH.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your GRACES in all<lb/> dutie.<lb/> JOHN DAY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>