<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109271_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19812</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6239</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109271</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine small poems lately printed : with the tragedie of Philotas. Written by Samuel Daniel</title>
                 <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                            <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>VPon the second agreement (the
first being broken through iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie
of a disproportion of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie)
betweene the <hi>Triumuiti
Octauius Caesar, Marcus Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi>
and <hi>Lepidus: Octauia</hi> the
sister of <hi>Octauius Caesar,</hi> was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
to <hi>Antonius,</hi> as a linke to combine that which
neuer yet, the greatest strength of nature, or anie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
of nearest respect could long hold togither, who
made but the instrument of others endes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
vp as an Ostage to serue the oportunity of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantages,
met not with that integritie she brought:
but as highly preferred to affliction encountred with
all the greeuances that beat vpon the misery of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
exposed to stand betwixt the diuers tending
humours of vnquiet parties. For <hi>Antonie</hi> hauing yet
vpon him the fetters of AEgipt, layde on by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of a most incomparable beauty, could admit no new
lawes into the state of his affection, or dispose of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
being not himselfe, but as hauing his heart tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Eastward whither the point of his desires were
directed, toucht with the strongest allurements that
ambition, and a licencious soueraintie could draw a
man vnto: could not truly descend to the priuate loue
<pb facs="4"/>
of a ciuill nurtred. Matrone, whose entertainment
bounded with modesty and the nature of her educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
knew not to cloth her affections in any other colours
then the plain habit of truth: wherein she euer suted al
her actions<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and vsed all her best ornaments of honesty,
to win the good liking of him that helde her but as a
Curtaine drawne betweene him and <hi>Octauius</hi> to sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
his other purposes withall; which the sharpe sight of
an equally iealous ambition could soone pierce into, &amp;
as easily looke thorow and ouer bloud and nature as he
to abuse it: And therefore to preuent his aspiring, he
armes his forces either to reduce <hi>Antonie</hi> to the ranke
of his estate, or else to disranke him out of state and al.
When <hi>Octauia</hi> by the imployment of <hi>Antonie</hi> (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
not yet ready to put his fortune to her triall) throwes
her selfe, great with childe, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> big with sorrow, into
the trauaile of a most laboursome recon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iliacion: ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
her iourney from the farthest parte of <hi>Greece</hi> to
find <hi>Octauius,</hi> with whom her care and teares were so
good agents that they effected their Commission be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
all expectation, and for that time quite disarmed
their wrath, which yet long could not hold so. For <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>
falling into the relaps of his former disease, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
his oportunity got ouer again into <hi>Egypt,</hi> where he
so forgot himselfe, that he quite put off his owne nature,
and wholy became a pray to his pleasures, as if hee had
wound himselfe out of the respect of Country, bloud &amp;
alliance, which gaue to <hi>Octauia</hi> the cause of much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
and to me the Argument of this letter.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>