<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109766_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20578</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6983</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109766</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lavvyers light: or, A due direction for the study of the law : for methode. Choyce of bookes moderne. Selection of authours of more antiquitie. Application of either. Accommodation of diuers other vsefull requisits. All tending to the speedy and more easie attayning o the knowledge of the common law of this kingdome. With necessary cautions against certaine abuses or ouersights, aswell in the practitioner as student. Written by the reuerend and learned professor thereof, I.D. To which is annexed for the affinitie of the subiect, another treatise, called The vse of the law</title>
                 <author>Doddridge, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 119, 1, 8, 93, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present vnto you here two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the one whereof hath an Authour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne; The other a Father deceased; Both Infants; both Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans; and both so like, as if they were <hi>Gemini horoscope uno.</hi> The Law enioynes you to keepe them; and their descent deserues it: If you keepe, and cherish them in their infancie, the Law by whose letters
<pb facs="3"/>
of commendations they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your tuition, will keepe and preserue you and yours, your persons, goods, and good names from violence, depredation, and detraction, vnto posterity. Case them in what fashion you please: And put them into what livories you like best; They are both so seasoned, that no weather can alter their constitutions: And both so solid that no teste can disrepute their perfections; Indeede they were intended for generall good. For he that will calculate their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, shall by a true Iudiciall finde in either a plentifull promise of publique profit and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall fabrique both of the study and vse of the Lawes of this Realme. It is a duty we owe to the knowne
<pb facs="3"/>
Authour though deceased, and a charity to the Authour whose mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty conceales his name, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the generall what was so collated in their particular, and so legaterily provided for their common behoofe; which not as <hi>proximiores sanguinis,</hi> or proper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors of the will of the deceased, but as creditors to whom the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of their good intentions for the publicke is committed; we do now publish and commend to all Students in the Lawes, and others which shall desire to enable their iudgments in this kinde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>