<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109075_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19610</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6042</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109075</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lover: or, Nvptiall love. VVritten, by Robert Crofts, to please himselfe</title>
                 <author>R. C. (Robert Crofts)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Meighen, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, if you aske mee, to what intent I publish this Treatise, I may answer, to please you: A well resolved man cannot please himselfe, but hee desires to please others also, and endeavours in all good wayes so to doe. And I am not out of hope, but that this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, wil profit some men also, since I have made use of many and divers Authors in the composing thereof. But I have endeavoured to digest the same into such a new manner, method stile and forme, as was most pleasing to my selfe; adding therevnto such Inventions, Raptures, observations, Poems, Alterations, &amp; experiments, as
<pb facs="3"/>
met with my meditations: so as the Treatise may seeme and bee even as pleasing as if it were all new. Which to doe, oft times requires wel nigh as much Art, as wholly the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of new matters. It is true, I know the world is cloyd with bookes and many there bee perhaps more then needs of this subject; but this is a breife and Compendious discourse; and therefore I hope will neither cloy the world or the Reader. It was written for Recreation, amidst more serious occasions; and so I desire it may be read. I know there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny malicious, envious, male contented and maligne Spirits in the world, who will pine, greive, and grudge at the prosperity and pleasures of True-lovers, as they doe at all happinesse, and that there bee many carping Readers who vsually read all (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially pleasing) bookes, in a sneaking manner, and endeavor to find nothing
<pb facs="3"/>
so much as faults; and by their jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and cunning art of detraction, can make one or a few faults, seeme to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure a multitude of good Actions, endeavouring nothing so much as to discourage and hinder all good, pleasant and happy waies. But for the censure of such men, I shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor not to regard, or else to contemn them. Yet truely I shall thinke my selfe much obliged to such, as in good will shall tell me of my faults, Errors, Ignorances and negligences. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever knowing that all things in the world are imperfect, it shall suffise to please my selfe, that I have done as well as I could for the present time. But I had not so easily nor so soone bin perswaded to be, a foole in Print as the proverb goes, and as the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and barking Reader is especially like to say, if I had not had some ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (aswel as many friēds) who have provoked me rather to be cēsured by
<pb facs="4"/>
many, then abused by a few. But if I did not thinke and hope that this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course would be pleasant &amp; profitable to some in reading, as it hath bin to me in writing, &amp; if that I had not bin great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encouraged herein by many men, I should still have bin content to have suffered the aspersion of a Pocket Author, ashamed to shew himselfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, fearing to be a foole in Print.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>