<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The translatour to the readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1534</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109046_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68433</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17113</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109046</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The translatour to the readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Constitutions p [ro] uincialles, and of Otho, and Octhobone, translated in to Englyshe. Cum priuilegio</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Redman, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1534</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 136 157-184 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <head>¶ The translatour to the readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can nat forget catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke readers it was so lately donne that when certayne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyshe bokes began to issue frō the parties of beyond the sees into this realme of eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land / the prelates and pastoures be gan to watche diligently in
<pb facs="3"/> euery corner to kepe theyr shepe that they shulde nat feed vpon them admonishīg vs with open mouthe to folow our forefathers and to beware of this new lernīg lately sprongen. And if they sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected any that had tasted therof he could nat auoyde but eyther he must beare or els burne a fagot. Wherupō I began to muse with my selfe howe thys myght by Iustice com to passe that so new lernyng (if it were so new as they made it) myght haue so olde a ponyshement which was so long before hand prouided and also ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cercised. And then to auoyde such ponyshement I began to diuine and serche what maner lernynge that was &amp; where it was wryten whiche they called olde and wold haue vs to folowe accordyng as
<pb facs="3"/> our forfathers (as they sayd) haue done. And to saye the trouthe I could nat with all the wit I had com to any thynge certayne that I mought saye, thys is it. As I was thus busyed in my selfe ther cam one and desyred me in his name that myght vpon my dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty haue commaunded me to take the paynes to translate in to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyshe the constitutions prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> constitutions legan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine whiche thynge at the fyrste mocion I was very desyrous to accomplyshe nat only because I shuld therin do my duety but also as me therin thought gyue a tast vnto the layete of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> olde doctrine if the prelates called that olde whiche they themselfe had made which thyng I deny nat but they mought do full wel &amp; cōueniētly.
<pb facs="4"/> For if Adam be the olde man and Christe the newe why may nat Adams doctryne be called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> olde and Christes the newe. Nowe therfore you y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hunger and thurst for olde lernynge come hereunto put in your fore fete and fyll your belyes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ye may growe &amp; be lyke vnto them that be the authors therof. For it becōmeth euery dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to be perfyght in that same wherein his mayster is perfyght Let me nat I pray you spend my laboures which I haue taken in vayne. This one thynge I can assure you of, if ye wyll be y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of this doctrine and do as it biddeth you, ye shall lyghtly es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape all maner ponishement and shame whiche the newe lernynge hathe alwayes hytherto suffred. This doctrine also is gentyll to
<pb facs="4"/> be vnderstonde, althoughe it be, somwhat greuos to fulfyll, it con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth no senses anagogicall or tropological or hath in it any hid misteries though it haue an eye to hyde treasour, but euen as it soūdeth so it meaneth. As for my parte I haue nat sought anye prayse in the trāslation, but was contentyd so to set it forth rudely &amp; playnly without any straunge termes that it myght be as well vnderstond of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnlerned layete in englyshe as it was before of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lerned clergy ī latyn, which thīg I doubte nat but I haue brought to passe, and therfore fare ye wel.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>