<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my owne Nation.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109511_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20047</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6487</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109511</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my owne Nation.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>O per se O. Or A new cryer of Lanthorne and candle-light : Being an addition, or lengthening, of the Bell-mans second night-walke. In which, are discouered those villanies, which the bell-man (because hee went i'th darke) could not see: now laid open to the world. Together with the shooting through the arme, vsed by counterfeit souldiers: the making of the great soare, (commonly called the great cleyme:) the mad-mens markes: their phrase of begging: the articles and oathes giuen to the fraternitie of roagues, vagabonds, and sturdy beggers at their meetings. And last of all, a new canting-song</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Busby, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my owne Nation.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Readers,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter it was proclaymed abroad, that <hi>(vnder the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Bel-man of London)</hi> new Forces were (once more) to be leauied against certaine Wilde and barbarous Rebels, that were vp in armes against the tranquilitie of the <hi>Weale-publicke:</hi> It cannot be told what numbers of voluntaries offred themselues daily to fight against so common, so bold, so strange, and so dangerous an enemie. <hi>Light horse men</hi> came in hourely with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery where these Mutiners lay intrenched: deliuering (in briefe notes of intelligence) who were their Leaders, how they went armed, and that they serued both on horse and foote: onely their Strengths could not be discried, because their Numbers were held infinite. Yet instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions were written, and sent euery minute by those that were fauourers of Goodnesse, shewing what militarie discipline the Foe vsed in his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes, and what Forts (if he were put at any time to flight) he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to; what stratagems he would practise, and where he did determine to lye in <hi>Ambuscado.</hi> They that could not serue in person, in <hi>this Noble quarrell,</hi> sent their <hi>Auxiliary</hi> Forces, well armed with Counsell. So that the <hi>Bel-man</hi> (contrary to his hopes) seeing himselfe so strongly and strangely seconded by friends, doth now brauely aduance forward, in maine battalion. The day of encounter is appointed to be in this <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmas Tearme:</hi> the place, <hi>Paules Church-yard, Fleetstreete,</hi> and other parts of the Citie. But before they ioyne let me giue you note of one thing, and that is this.</p>
   <p>There is an <hi>Vsurper,</hi> that of late hath taken vpon him the name of the <hi>Bel-man,</hi> but being not able to maintaine that title, hee doth now call himselfe the <hi>Bel-mans</hi> brother, his ambition is (rather out of vaine-glory then the true courage of an experienced Souldier) to haue the leading of the <hi>Van,</hi> but it shall be honor good enough for him (if not too good) to come vp with the <hi>Rere.</hi> You shall know him by his Habiliments, for (by the furniture he weares) he will be taken for a Beadle of <hi>Bridewell.</hi> It is thought he is rather a Nevvter then a friend to the cause: and therefore the <hi>Bel-man</hi> doth here openly protest that hee comes into the field as no fellow in armes with <hi>Him.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Howsoeuer it be strucke, or whosoeuer giues the first blow, the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie depends vpon the valour of you that are the Wings to the <hi>Bel-mans</hi> army, for which conquest he is in hope you will valiantly fight, sithence the quarrell is against the head of monstrous abuses, and the blowes which you must giue are in defence of <hi>Law, Iustice, Order, Ceremonie, Religion, Peace,</hi> and that honourable title of <hi>Goodnesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Saint <hi>George▪</hi> I see the two Armies moue forward: and behold, the <hi>Bel-man</hi> himselfe first chargeth vpon the face of the Enemy, Thus:</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>