<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Mason, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109928_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07216</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17616</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109928</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Mason, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discourse of the Nevv-found-land : with the situation, temperature, and commodities thereof, inciting our nation to goe forward in that hopefull plantation begunne</title>
                 <author>Mason, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as there bee sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie relations of the New-found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and the commodities thereof, Some too much extolling it, some too much debasing it, preferring the temperature of the aire there of before ours, the hopes of commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties there without paines and mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralles, as if they were apparent (which as I deny to bee a veritie, yet I affirme not to bee impossible) with other narrations dissenting from the trueth, the which although done out of a good affection, yet had they better beene vndone. I haue therefore (gentle Reader) hoping of thy fauourable construction, set downe in few and plaine tearmes out of that experience I haue gained in three yeares and seuenth monthes residence there, the trueth, as thou shalt finde by proofe thereof, to the which I recommend thee and vs all to his Grace, that is able and will plant those that feare him in a better Kingdome.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.
<signed>Thine and his Countries in part, not whollie his owne.
<hi>IOHN MASON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>