<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Bayliefes, Burghemaisters, &amp; Counsell of the
Towne of Middelborgh in Zeelande.</title>
           <author>Langhenez, Bernardt</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109348_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05051</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15193</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109348</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Bayliefes, Burghemaisters, &amp; Counsell of the
Towne of Middelborgh in Zeelande.</title>
                 <author>Langhenez, Bernardt</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The description of a voyage made by certaine ships of Holland into the East Indies : VVith their aduentures and successe: together with the description of the countries, townes, and inhabitantes of the same: who set forth on the second of Aprill 1595. and returned on the 14. of August. 1597. Translated out of Dutch into English by W.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Bayliefes, Burghemaisters, &amp; Counsell of the
Towne of Middelborgh in <hi>Zeelande.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may well bee thought (Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull) as many learned
men are of opinion, that the actions and aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the ancients long
since done &amp; performed, haue beene set forth with more show of wonder
and strangenesse then they in truth deserued: the reason as I think
was, because that in those daies there were many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wise men,
who in their writings sought by all meanes they could to excell each other,
touching the description of Countries &amp; nations: And againe to the
contrarie, for want of good Historiographers and writers, many famous actes
and trauels of diuers nations and Countries lie hidden, and in a manner buried
vnder ground, as wholly forgotten and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, vnlesse it were such as
the Grecians and Romanes for their owne glories and aduantages thought good to
declare. But to come to the matter of voyages by sea, it is euident to all
the world, what voyage <hi>Iason</hi> with certaine yong Grecian Princes made
to <hi>Colchos</hi> in the Oriental Countries to winne the golden Fleece, as
also the trauels by <hi>Hercules</hi> performed into <hi>Libia</hi> in the
West partes, to winne the <hi>Aurea Mala</hi> or golden apples of
<hi>Hesperides,</hi> which notwithstanding neither for length, daunger, nor
profite, are any thing comparable to the nauigations and voyages, that of late
within the space of <pb facs="4"/> one hundreth years haue been performed &amp;
made into the East &amp; West Indies, whereby in a manner there is not one
hauen on the sea coast, nor any point of land in the whole world, but hath
in time beene sought and founde out. I will not at this present dispute
or make an argument, whether the Countries and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of late yeares found
out and discouered, were knowne to the auncients, but this is most certaine,
that not any strange worke or aduenture was, or euer shall be performed,
but by the speciall grace, fauour and mightie hand of God, and that such
are worthy perpetual memory, as with noble minds haue sought to effect, and
be the first enterprisers thereof, and with most valiant courages and
wisedomes, haue performed such long &amp; dangerous voyages into the East
and West Indies, as also such Kinges and Princes, as with their Princely
liberalities haue imployed their treasures, shippes, men and munitions to
the furtherance and performance of so worthy actes, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
in the end turned to their great aduancementes and inriching with great
treasures, which by those meanes they haue drawn, &amp; caused in great
aboundance to be brought from thence, in such manner, that the King of
<hi>Spaine</hi> nowe liuing, (hauing both the Indies in his possession,
&amp; reaping the abundant treasures which yearly are brought out of those
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries) hath not only (although couertly) sought all the means he could
to bring all Christendome vnder his dominion, but also (that which no King
or country whatsoeuer although of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might then he hath euer done) hee
is not ashamed to vse this posie, <hi>Necspe, nec metu.</hi> And
although the first foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and discouerers of those Countries haue
alwayes sought to hinder and intercept other nations from hauing any part of
their glorie, yet hereby all nations, &amp; indifferent persons may well know
and perceiue the speciall policie, and valour of these vnited Prouinces, in
trauelling into both the Indies, in the <pb facs="4"/> faces, &amp; to the great
griefe of their many and mighty enemies. Wherby it is to be hoped, that if they
continue in their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prises begun, they will not onely draw the most
part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian treasures into these Countries, but thereby
disinherite &amp; spoyle the Countrie of <hi>Spayne</hi> of her principall
reuenewes, and treasures of marchandises and trafiques, which she
continually vseth and receyueth out of these countries, and out of
<hi>Spayne</hi> are sent into the Indies, and so put the King of
<hi>Spaine</hi> himselfe in minde of his foolish deuise which hee vseth
for a posie tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the new world, which is, <hi>Non sufficit orbis,</hi>
like a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Alexander magnus,</hi> desiring to rule ouer all the
world, as it is manifestly knowne. And because this discription is fallen
into my handes, wherein is contayned the first voyage of the Low-country men
into the East Indies, with the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures happened vnto them, set downe
and iustified by such as were present in the voyage, I thought it good to
put it in print, with many pictures and cardes, whereby the reader may the
easilier perceyue and discerne, the natures, apparels, and fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of
those Countries and people, as also the manner of their shippes, together
with the fruitfulnesse and great aboundance of the same, hoping that this
my labour will not onely be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto all Marchants and Saylers, which
hereafter meane to traffique into those Countries, but also pleasant and
profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all such as are desirous to looke into so newe and
strange things, which neuer heretofore were knowne vnto our nation. And
againe for that all histories haue their particular commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, (specially
such as are collected and gathered together) not by common report, from the
first, seconde, or thirde man, but by such as haue seene and beene
present in the actions, and that are liuing to iustifie and verifie the
same: And although eloquence and words well placed in shewing a history,
are great ornamentes and beautifyinges to the same, yet such reports &amp; 
<pb facs="5"/> declarations are much more worthy credite, &amp; commendabler for
the benefit of the commonwealth, which are not set down or disciphered by
subtill eloquence, but showne and performed by simple plaine men, such
as by copiousnesse of wordes, or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie do not alter or chaunge the
matter from the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which at this day is a common and notorious
fault in many Historiographers: And thinking with my selfe to whome I were
best to dedicate the same, I found it not fitter for any then for the right
worshipfull Gouernours of this famous Towne of <hi>Middelborgh,</hi> wherein
for the space of 19. yeares I haue peaceably continued, specially because
your worships do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deale with great store of shipping, and
matter belonging to nauigation, but are also well pleased to heare, and
great fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers to aduance both shipping and traffiques, wherein
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth not onely the welfare of all marchants, inhabitants, and
cittizens of this famous City, but also of all the common wealth of the
vnited Prouinces, hoping your worships wil not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this my labour,
but protect &amp; warrantise the same against all men: Wherwith I
beseech God to blesse you with wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and godly policie, to gouerne
the Common wealth: <hi>Middleborgh</hi> this 19 of October. 1597.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships seruant to command <hi>Bernardt
Langhenez.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>