<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Lady, G. O. C. K.</title>
           <author>S., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109941_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20863</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7240</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109941</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Lady, G. O. C. K.</title>
                 <author>S., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The school of patience. Written in Latin by H. Drexelius. And faithfully translated into English, by R.S. Gent</title>
                 <author>Drexel, Jeremias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 545, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Lady, G. O. C. K.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Never had the happinesse per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonally to see, or present my service to your Honour, yet so much have I heard of your vertue, specially this of Patience, that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume, amongst all the Ladies of this Kingdome to choose you sole Patronesse of this School of Patience; of which booke
<pb facs="3"/>
the famous <hi>Drexelius</hi> may well chalenge himself Authour, I nought else but the errours. In this Scool, Madam, all we mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, from the highest to the lowest, must of necessity be Scholars; not to suffer, were not to live. Then, as the kid in the fable breaking from the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, when its fellows were sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed, and falling afterward amongst a heard of wolves cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out; why not rather to the Gods? So we Christians, sith suffer needs we must, why not rather for God, for him who suffered first for us, then for him who goeth about like a roaring lion, seeking whom he may devour? If patiently and willingly we suffer, the labour's
<pb facs="3"/>
lesse, the reward greater; if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently and unwillingly, the labour more, the reward none at all, but contrariwise eternall punishment. All the art then and mastery is, not to be too dissolute in prosperity, nor dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, or impatient in adversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; this skill is learnd by Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the precepts and rules whereof this booke declares; which would not presume to shew it self in publike, without the honour of your Ladiships protection; To whom I likewise recommend the most dutifull respects of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most humble servant R. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>