<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS
PREFACE.</title>
           <author>Crane, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109020_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19556</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5986</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109020</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS
PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>Crane, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorkes of mercy, both corporall, and spirituall</title>
                 <author>Crane, Ralph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS
PREFACE.</head>
   <l>THe <hi>Citie</hi> had my Birth, my Father (free</l>
   <l>Of a much fam'd, &amp; royall<note n="*" place="margin">Marchant-Taylors.</note> Company)</l>
   <l>With good esteeme bore offices of worth:</l>
   <l>My education past, I then went forth,</l>
   <l>And tride the Aire of diuers noble <hi>Counties,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>There tasted some free fauours, gen'rous bounties.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Much variation</hi> I haue had since then</l>
   <l>With one blest Gift, <hi>A Ready Writers Pen,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>(The vse whereof (without vaine-glory told)</l>
   <l>It not extinguish'd yet, though I am old.)</l>
   <l>First was I seuen yeares Seruant, painfull <hi>Clarke,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Vnto a <hi>Clarke o'th' Counsell,</hi> and did marke</l>
   <l>Within the circuit of those hopefull yeares,</l>
   <l>The <hi>goodnesse</hi> and <hi>nobilitie</hi> o'th' <hi>Peeres,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Those reuerend <hi>Lords,</hi> those <hi>Counsellors of State,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Vpon whose <hi>vertues</hi> I must meditate</l>
   <l>While I haue breath; and praise while I am able,</l>
   <l>Each gracious<note n="*" place="margin">Cl: of the Couns:</note>
      <hi>Second</hi> of that <hi>honour'd Table.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>And (as a thankefull <hi>Riuer,</hi> that doth send</l>
   <l>His <hi>Tribute</hi> to the <hi>Ocean)</hi> I commend</l>
   <l>One speciall <hi>Sacrifice</hi> (with heart sincere)</l>
   <l>Vnto his worth whom I call'd <hi>Master (there.)</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That (haplesse) <hi>thence</hi> I sl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pt, (wanting firme hold)</l>
   <l>I only sigh the fate, but leaue 't vntold.</l>
   <l>The <hi>Signet</hi> and the <hi>Priuie-Seale</hi> was next,</l>
   <l>(Those deare <hi>Colleagues)</hi> who giue me for my Text</l>
   <l>A <hi>Field of honour,</hi> and shall be my Song,</l>
   <l>Whilst <hi>Fame</hi> a Trumpet hath, or I a Tongue.</l>
   <l>Some gentlenesse from <hi>thence</hi> I still possesse,</l>
   <l>Which makes their <hi>goodnes</hi> more, my <hi>sorrowes</hi> lesse.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>To th' <hi>Tribe of Leuy</hi> (heauens chiefe <hi>Miracles</hi>)</l>
   <l>I haue done seruice, writ their <hi>Oracles;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Which so diuine Instinction doth infuse,</l>
   <l>(For their blest sakes) Ile make my Soule their <hi>Muse,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And pray with the best power my zeale affords,</l>
   <l>All happy Gifts, to crowne their sacred words:</l>
   <l>The <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> in <hi>Clouen Tongues</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Descend on them, when they good things desire.</l>
   <l>But most of all doth my laborious hand</l>
   <l>'Mongst the renown'd and learned <hi>Lawyers</hi> stand</l>
   <l>A Monument; each <hi>Office,</hi> and each <hi>Court</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Vouchsafing me such matter of Report,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>That if my voice to th' utmost world could stretch,</l>
   <l>Eu'n thither should their fames and honours reach.</l>
   <l>And some imployment hath my vsefull <hi>Pen</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Had 'mongst those ciuill, well-deseruing <hi>men,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That grace the <hi>Stage</hi> with <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Of whose true honesties I much could write,</l>
   <l>But will comprise't (as in a Caske of Gold)</l>
   <l>Vnder the <hi>Kingly Seruice</hi> they doe hold.</l>
   <l>Should there be here a harsh obiection cast,</l>
   <l>Why (hauing tride so many wayes, and past</l>
   <l>So many places) All, or none of these,</l>
   <l>Could me establish: (oh) let them but please</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>To note what I haue heard some <hi>Merchants</hi> say,</l>
   <l>That what they'ue got on Land, they'ue lost at Sea;</l>
   <l>'Twill stop the current of that crook'd conceit,</l>
   <l>And light vnto constructions farre more streight:</l>
   <l>For so (God knowes) haue I by Stormes and Floud</l>
   <l>Of Time and Sicknesse, lost my Land-got good.</l>
   <l>Loe, this hath beene my lifes sad Pilgrimage,</l>
   <l>Vnto this houre (the Euening of my Age)</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> I haue seene, and <hi>Court,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And in them some of each degree, each sort,</l>
   <l>Of each <hi>Sex</hi> too (for eu'n my willing duties</l>
   <l>Reflected haue vpon some <hi>Female Beauties)</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>To whom my <hi>Soule</hi> hath vow'd such deare affection,</l>
   <l>I shall not giue it ample satisfaction,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>If</hi> Deaths darke-night, <hi>my</hi> sight-depriued eyes,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>A shaking hand,</hi> or ought else should arise,</l>
   <l>Ere I had consecrated (with my Name)</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Some</hi> speaking honour <hi>to their</hi> liuing Fame.</l>
   <l>And 'mongst all them, whom I haue (thus) obseru'd,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>You</hi> stand in a chiefe place, and are (thus) seru'd:</l>
   <l>True worth <hi>will neu'r esteeme't a</hi> wandring Shift,</l>
   <l>For a poore man, in a poore <hi>well-meant Gift,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To tender his <hi>hearts-zeale;</hi> but take't aright,</l>
   <l>As <hi>Christ</hi> accepted the <hi>poore Widowes</hi> Mite.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>Doe you but so, and of the <hi>Leapers</hi> ten,</l>
   <l>Ile be the <hi>Tenth,</hi> and humbly come agen,</l>
   <l>And pay my <hi>vowes,</hi> and in <hi>a way more knowne</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Sing <hi>double honour</hi> to your <hi>vertues</hi> showne.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>The humbly deuoted,
R. CRANE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>