<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worshipfull and true Moecenas
of learning, M. Thomas Smith, T. L. G. wisheth
all aboundance of worldly fortunes in this life,
and the benefites of heauenly felicitie in the
life to come.</title>
           <author>G., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109566_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06166</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16657</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109566</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worshipfull and true Moecenas
of learning, M. Thomas Smith, T. L. G. wisheth
all aboundance of worldly fortunes in this life,
and the benefites of heauenly felicitie in the
life to come.</title>
                 <author>G., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famous, true and historicall life of Robert second Duke of Normandy, surnamed for his monstrous birth and behauiour, Robin the Diuell : VVherein is contained his dissolute life in his youth, his deuout reconcilement and vertues in his age: interlaced with many straung and miraculous aduentures. VVherein are both causes of profite, and manie conceits of pleasure. By T.L. G</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 43, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the worshipfull and true Moecenas
of learning, M. Thomas Smith, T. L. G. wisheth
all aboundance of worldly fortunes in this life,
and the benefites of heauenly felicitie in the
life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing in these our days, men rather seeke the increase
of transitorie wealth, than the knowledge of deuine
wisedome, preferring stuffed baggs, before studious
bookes, their pounds, before precepts, loosing the true
ritches of the minde, to leuell at the transitorie allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of this world, feeding fooles with siggs, and philosophers with
floutes; I haue among the multitudes of these men, made choice of
your Worship for my Patron and Moecenas, who of a farre more
happy nature with <hi>Theodosius,</hi> honour <hi>Appian,</hi> and seeing lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
almost suppressed with contempt, or discountenanced with neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,
haue in this famous Citie (like a vertuous member of the same)
begun to exile ignorance, to reuiue artes: knowing <hi>Ladislaus</hi> reasons
to be of force, that Citizens who are vnlettered, are lesse than men,
or rather (as <hi>Frederick</hi> the Emperour was wont to say) manlike
beastes. Which vertuous indeuor of yours (worthie both your name
and fortune) shall in time to come more aduance you, than they who
tooth and nayle labour to purchase lands, which ordinarily perish
through their heires lauishnes. It is true fame which is gotten by
vertue, &amp; perfect vertue to maintaine learning; which is so kinde to
those that seeke after it, that in all changes of fortune, in all miseries
of this life, and casualties whatsoeuer, it prepareth the mind, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth
mishaps. And least I among the poore Tirones of learning,
who desire the increase therof with the most, though deserue therein
with the least, should seeme to forget this especially and ingrafted
vertue so admirably bestowed vpō your worship, I haue thought good
to present you with a rude and homely written history, which if with
like regard you shall accept, as <hi>Alphonsus</hi> did the silly Satires of
<hi>Philelphus,</hi> I doubt not but in short time to publish that vnder your
name, which shall not only merit and deserue your acceptance, but
also mightely profit all such as are studious in all sorts of learning.
Till when, I most humbly commend me, desiring your Worship most
earnestly to prosecute your vertuous enterprises, beseeching God to
prosper you in them and all other, to the aduancement of Letters.
From my Chamber 2. Maij. 1591.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to commaund,
<hi>T. L. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>