<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The preface, or the pystle.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1541</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109177_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04524</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1465</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109177</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The preface, or the pystle.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The treatyse answerynge the boke of berdes. Compyled by Collyn clowte, dedycatyd to Barnarde barber dwellynge in Banbery</title>
                 <author>Barnes, satirist</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1541</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶The preface, or the pystle.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the ryght wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shypfulle (Barnarde Barber,) dwellynge in Banberye, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyn▪ Clowte, surrendreth gretynge with immortall thankes.</p>
   <p>IT was so worshypful syr, that at my last beynge in Mountpyllour I chaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed to be assocyat with a doctor of Physy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / which at his retorne had set forth .iij. Bokes to be prynted ī Fleetstrete, within Temple barre, the whiche Bokes were compyled togyther ī one volume named the Introductorie of knowledge / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon there dyd not resort only vnto hym marchauntes, gentylmen, and wymen / but also knyghtes, and other great men, whiche were desyrous to knowe the effy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyte, and the effecte of his aforesayd bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis, and so amonge many thynges, they desyred to knowe his fansye, consernyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the werynge of Berdes / He answeryd in great experyence. Some wyl weer ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis bycause theyr faces be pocky, maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy
<pb facs="3"/>
sausflewme, lyporous, &amp; dysfygured / by the whiche many clene men were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. So this done he desyred euery mā to be contentyd: Vvherfore I desyre no man to be dyspleasyd with me. And whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as he was anymatyd to wryte his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to thende, that great men may laugh therat / I haue deuysed this answere to the entent: that ī the redyng they myght laughe vs bothe to scorne / And for that cause I wrote this boke, as god know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my pretence / who euer keape youre maystershyp in helthe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>