<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An aduertisment to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109262_Bo1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04813</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14947</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109262</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An aduertisment to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A relation of the second voyage to Guiana. Perfourmed and written in the yeare 1596. By Lawrence Kemys, Gent</title>
                 <author>Kemys, Lawrence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>An aduertisment to the Reader.</head>
   <p>IN this Breuiarie, the names onlie are comprised of such as being led with the generall fame of <hi>Guiana,</hi> haue endeuoured to discouer &amp; pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse it. The whole histories are long and cannot suddenlie be transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or Englished at large, as we in these Elegies find them. It may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps seeme strange and incredible, that so manie Caualeros should all faile in this one attempt, since in many partes of the Indies, far smaller numbers in shorter time haue performed as great matters, and subdued mightie Kingdoms: I haue therefore thought it good, here to alleadge those reasons, which by circumstance may be gathered to haue beene chief impediments to the Spaniard in this intended search &amp; conquest.</p>
   <p>The first may be the remotenesse or distance of their places of <hi>Ronde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow,</hi> from the <hi>Dorado:</hi> which appeare to be foure, <hi>Nueuo Reyno:</hi> the mouth of <hi>Amazones</hi> or <hi>Oreliano. Cubagua,</hi> or the coast of the <hi>Carackas:</hi> &amp; <hi>Trinidado.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">1. From <hi>Moisbanda,</hi> where <hi>Oreliano</hi> hath his head-spring to his mouth the Spaniards account it 2000. leagues. <hi>Raleana</hi> riseth neere the saide mountaines in <hi>Moiabanda,</hi> and tributeth his waters to the sea, not farre from the other: <hi>Guiana</hi> is enuironed with these two fresh water seas, wher their distance is greatest from their risinges, and is besides guarded with impassable mountains, which in close &amp; defend it on al partes, excepting <hi>Topiawaries</hi> country. It is no maruel then, if the vigor, heat, &amp; life of those Spaniards, who sought it from <hi>Nueuo Reyno,</hi> were allayed and spent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came nere it in those long, desolate, and vncomfortable waies.</p>
   <p n="2">2. From <hi>Cubagua</hi> to seek it by sea, in vessels of any burthen, is a worke of farre greater labour, then to saile directly from <hi>Spaine.</hi> And to passe
<pb facs="33"/>
ouerland is a matter of great difficultie, by reason that the Indian Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inhabiting between the coast of the <hi>Carackas</hi> and <hi>Guiana,</hi> being wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and harried with the daylie incursions of the Spaniards, haue now turned their abused patience into furie, refusing to suffer any forces of men to be led through their countries. For the Spaniards trauelling in those parts, when they found not golde answerable to their expectation, ouerlaid them with cruelties, tyrannie, and thraldom: forbearing neither men, women friends, nor foes. Which maner of dealing, though in some sort it satisfied their desire of present profit: yet hath it otherwise done them much harme in hardening and driuing those nations to desperate resolutions.</p>
   <p n="3">3 From the mouth of <hi>Oreliano</hi> to seeke entrance with any number of men, and to bore a hole through the mountaines, is all one. Neither find we, that any seeking it that way, haue at anie time boasted of their gaines or pleasurable iourneyes.</p>
   <p n="4">4 From <hi>Trinidado</hi> as the course is shortest: so doth it promise best like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of successe. Howbeit, impossible it is with any vessell of ordinarie burthen by that way to recouer the riuer of <hi>Raleana.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The second. The Spaniards haue bene so far from furthering and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping on another, or admitting partners or coadiutors in the <hi>Guiana</hi> cause that amongst so many attempts, from the beginning to the last, I cannot find any one, when they were otherwise likliest to preuaile, free from dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, mutinies, and cruel murders amongst themselues.</p>
   <p>Thirdly. The Spaniards in this place haue mist that aduantage, which els where hath steeded them in all their conquests: namelie, the dissenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and mutuall warres of the Indians amongst themselues, Which of what force it is, may be gathered by the example of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>awcania</hi> in <hi>Peru.</hi> For the Indians of that one prouince containing in circuit not aboue 20. leagues, haue maintained warres aboue these 30. yeares, against all the Spaniards, and in despight of them haue kept their own countrie, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times discomforting their enemies in many set battayles, burning &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying some of their strongest townes. The chiefe reason wherof I take to be, because no Indian nation was enemy vnto them. And howsoeuer the Spaniards vaunt of their redoubted exploits in the Indies: yet do their owne writings in effect testifie, that without the aid of the Indians diuided amongst rhemselues, <hi>Mexico, Peru,</hi> and the rest, had neuer bene Spanish.</p>
   <p>Lastly. I can impute it to no cause so rightly, as immediately to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence. For by him princes raigne. And in my beleefe (except we will looke to be warned by miracle from heauen,) we need no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther assurances, then we already haue to perswade our selues that it hath pleased our God of his infinit goodnesse, in his will and purpose to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and reserue this Empire for vs.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>