<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109541_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20069</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6510</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109541</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The magnificent entertainment : giuen to King Iames, Queene Anne his wife, and Henry Frederick the Prince, vpon the day of his Maiesties tryumphant passage (from the Tower) through his honourable citie (and chamber) of London, being the 15. of March. 1603. As well by the English as by the strangers: vvith the speeches and songes, deliuered in the seuerall pageants. Tho. Dekker</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>REader, you must vnderstand, that a regard, being had
that his Majestie should not be wearied with teadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
speeches: A great part of those which are in this
Booke set downe, were left vnspoken: So that thou doest
here receiue them as they should haue bene deliuered, not as
they were. Some errours wander vp and downe in these
sheetes, vnder the Printers warrant: which notwithstanding
may by thy Authoritie be brought in, and receiue their due
Correction. As in F. 2. For, <hi>From his owne cleare strength,</hi>
Read, cleare, straight, &amp;c. And within fewe lines beneath
that: In steede of, (<hi>Because alluring this tryumph</hi>) Read, because
that during these, &amp;c. In the <hi>Cant.</hi> likewise, beginning thus,
<hi>Shine Titan Shine,</hi> In steed of, <hi>O this is Had,</hi> read, O this is He.
And in the sixt staffe: For, <hi>Here stayd,</hi> Had still. But here
<hi>Had</hi> list not tary. Read for euery <hi>Had,</hi> hee▪ Other faults par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
these I thinke are the grosest.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>