<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109679_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6824</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109679</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short explanation, of the epistle of Paul to the Hebrewes. By David Dickson, preacher of Gods Word, at Irwin</title>
                 <author>Dickson, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 333, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore the tyme that something of myne did passe the PRESSE, without my knowledge, or allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wance, I did not mynde to come abroad in this Learned Age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in manie, more able Men than I am, doe keepe silence; my Furniture beeing fitter for my present Charge, than for more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Edification, in my judgement; and my Employmentes so frequent, as my spare tyme is little, for farther extent of what the <hi>LORD</hi> hath bestowed vpon mee. But, since that tyme, my just Feares, from apparent grounds,
<pb facs="3"/>
that numbers of my <hi>SERMONS,</hi> vvhich were rudelie, and popularlie, delivered, (as thryse, or foure tymes Preaching a-weeke, might yeelde) and taken from my Mouth, as it was possible to over-take the current of running speach; the judicious Wryter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king what hee had over-taken, to coheare, the best hee could; and Copies going from him, to manie, with numbers of Faultes, and misstakinges of the Transcribers; I beeing vnable to revise, (for straytnesse of tyme) anie thing which was written by them, first, or last. My just Feares, I saye, that these should come to thy Handes, rude and faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as they are, made mee willing rather, when <hi>GOD</hi> should graunt mee leasure heere-after, to draw vp, in short, the poyncts of Doctrine delivered by mee in these <hi>SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS</hi>; that thou mightest haue a twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or thirtie of them, or moe, possible, in the boundes and pryce of one at large.</p>
   <p>With this passage of <hi>GOD'S</hi> providence, another hath concurred, to drawe foorth this piece vnto thy view in the meane tyme, which is this: When I considered, howe largelie <hi>GOD</hi> hath provyded HELPS, for vnderstanding of holie SCRIPTVRE, by large Commentaries, and sweete Sermons,
<pb facs="3"/>
especiallie from His Church in ENGLAND; where-by increase of Knowledge is given to the Learned, and such whose meanes to buy, and leasure from their calling to reade, and victorie over their owne laysinesse, for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king paynes, doeth concurre with their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, for making vse of this the <hi>LORD'S</hi> Liberalitie; I haue often requested the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lightes▪ To helpe such as eyther could not, or else would not, profite themselues by that, vvhich is alreadie graunted in His Bountie, by some short, and playne manner of wryting; vvhere-by the weaker judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes might bee supported, and all Excuse taken away from the wittie Sluggard, and such whose worldlie Employmentes, and great Effayres, haue seemed sufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, to excuse their negligence, and the small and naughtie matters of their owne Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Kingdome of <hi>HEAVEN,</hi> and Evidences thereof in <hi>SCRIPTVRE.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And, to this purpose, I haue beene verie instant, vvith the Godlie-Learned of myne acquayntance, to take this matter in hand; and, to divyde, amongst them, the hard parts of <hi>SCRIPTVRE,</hi> at least; that this worke might bee done by the handes of manie, vvhich could not bee done by one. I found
<pb facs="4"/>
their approbation of my desire, and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable willingnesse, to put hand to worke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so. But, some of them, for the weyght of their ordinarie Charge, some of them for age, and infirmitie of bodie, some of them for their handes full of the <hi>LORD'S</hi> worke in another sorte, could not adventure to bee straytlie ingaged in the worke. Where tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row I was forced, eyther to forsake my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, which daylie were kindeled within mee more and more; or else, come foorth with some-thing, of this kynde, as might bee; and seeke amongst my Readers, some to take this Matter to heart; and, to doe there-in, as the <hi>LORD</hi> should enable them, by themselues, or by others.</p>
   <p>I haue made choyse of this <hi>EPISTLE,</hi> which is a piece of hard Meate, in the estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation both of the <hi>APOSTLE,</hi> the Wryter there-of, (CHAP. 5. and 6.) and of <hi>PETER,</hi> giving his judgement of it, (2. PET. 1.15.16.) That if I should attayne anie parte of myne intent, in anie measure, in so hard a place, I might encowrage others, to take in hand a more easie parte of <hi>SCRIPTVRE,</hi> with more hope of successe.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Summe</hi> of each <hi>Chapter,</hi> or the <hi>Contents,</hi> doe stand in steade of <hi>Analysis</hi>; and, in some
<pb facs="4"/>
places, of a <hi>Paraphrase.</hi> The <hi>Text</hi> doeth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, <hi>Verse</hi> by <hi>Verse.</hi> The exposition of the <hi>Verse,</hi> serveth for groundes of Doctrines; which Doctrines, following vpon the groundes, are joyned, moste parte, with the Note of Collection [THEN.] Pluralitie of Doctrines from the ground, or from the <hi>Text</hi> where the consequence is easie to bee percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is distinguished by Figures, according to their numbers. Tearmes of Arte I haue es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed, because I would bee playne to all. I haue spared all enlargement of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which I could spare; leaving them as graynes of Seede, to get their growth in thy mynde, by Meditation, which is necessarie for such as loue to make vse of this sort of wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; because I would be short. The speciall handeling of such Passages, as the Apostle ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out of the Olde Testament, I haue left to their owne proper place. Quotations, for confirmation of my Doctrines, drawne from the ground, I haue spared also: Because, I jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, If the Doctrine was pertinentlie colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the ground, the <hi>Text</hi> in hand was sufficient confirmation. And if it bee not pertinentlie collected, I am content that thou passe by it, and take onelie what is pertinent. A quotation could prooue the Doctrine true▪
<pb facs="5"/>
but not prooue it pertinent: and, so, not serue my purpose. Manie moe, and more perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Consequences, the Learned will finde, which I haue not observed: but not <hi>for</hi> the Learned, or such as are able, and willing, to make vse of larger Wrytinges, doe I intende this present.</p>
   <p>Therefore, doe not looke howe much thou doest misse, which might haue beene sayde; but, what in the first frame of this moulde could bee done, in such brevitie. Which moulde, I trust, the Learned shall helpe, if it please the <hi>LORD</hi> to stirre them vp, to take this matter in hand. I haue preassed, singlie to poynct out Trueth, without <hi>Partialitie</hi>; not wresting the Text, to reach a Blowe to anie man. And, what thou shalt make of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Piece, I am not carefull, if I can obtayne there-by, that more able Men may bee set on worke, to doe what I intend, but cannot doe.</p>
   <p>If the precious Iewell of the <hi>SCRIPTVRE</hi> may bee more esteemed of, and made vse of, which is more necessarie for our Soules, than the Sunne in the Firmament is for our bodies; and, the greatest gift next after our <hi>LORD IESVS</hi> downe-sending amongst vs, that ever the Worlde saw. If I may by this piece, I say, bee an Instrument, to stirre vp anie to the
<pb facs="5"/>
loue of searching the <hi>SCRIPTVRES,</hi> I haue not lost my Paynes, what-so-ever shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of this little Booke: Where-vnto I haue sollisted for no Patronage vnder Heaven, but thy Christian Good-will to my Ayme, to haue our <hi>LORD</hi> the more honoured, in the sounde Knowledge, and right vse of His <hi>SCRIPTVRE.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I am confident, that thou wilt easilie judge, with mee, That the prowde, and prophane Despysers of <hi>GOD,</hi> are worthie to perish, amongst His Enemies: But, consider, and judge againe, If prophane Despysers of holie <hi>SCRIPTVRE,</hi> vvho disdayne to reade, or obey, what <hi>GOD</hi> commaundeth therein, bee not to bee ranked in the same Roll. For, <hi>GOD</hi> draweth so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>igh vnto vs in His Word, speaking vnto vs, as a king vnto his Subjects, or a Master vnto his Servauntes; that the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or disobedience, which wee giue to His Speaches, resolveth, directlie, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatelie, vpon <hi>GOD HIMSELFE.</hi> For, vvhat is it else, to heare, and belieue, and obey <hi>GOD</hi>; but, To heare, and belieue, and obey His Speaches? And, vvhat is it, Nor to take notice of <hi>GOD,</hi> to despyse, and disobey <hi>GOD</hi>; but, Not to take notice of His Speaches, not to reade His Wrytings,
<pb facs="6"/>
and not to care for anie thing that Hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, promiseth, or threatneth? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath the <hi>LORD</hi> written the Great thinges of His Lawe vnto vs, even to bee a Touch-Stone, not onelie to trye all mens Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine there-by, but also to trye all mens dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position towardes Himselfe▪ and, howe they stand affected to His Honour, whether as Foes, or as Friendes. For, What readier way is there, to get evidence of a man desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Knowledge, Fayth, Loue, Feare, and the rest of the partes of the Image of <hi>GOD,</hi> than to finde him destitute of the Knowledge and Loue of the <hi>SCRIPTVRE?</hi> What surer Signe of a man, who, for the present, is enemie to <hi>GOD,</hi> and to the enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of His Gracious Kingdome, than to find him traducing the perfect Law of the <hi>LORD,</hi> and marring, to his power, the free course of the Scriptures light, which is the Scepter of <hi>CHRIST'S</hi> Kingdome? Agayne; What surer Signe of a Chyld of Promise, begotten of <hi>GOD,</hi> than to see him, with DAVID, PSAL. 119. making more of the Scriptures, nor of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and powring out all his Affections vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, as vpon the nearest Meane where-by <hi>GOD'S</hi> Spirit may be conveyed into his soule, for perfecting of Holinesse; and the readiest
<pb facs="6"/>
Chariot, to carrie vp his spirite, to dwell in <hi>GOD,</hi> for perfecting of his happinesse?</p>
   <p>Wee shall find, also, answerable to <hi>GOD'S</hi> Purpose of trying men by His Scripture, His Wisdome, giving a due meeting vnto men, as they doe make vse of His Scripture▪ Doe they not reade it? or, doe they reade, and not consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it? Doe they not weygh, what is impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by it, in sense, and meaning? It fareth with them, as with those to whom <hi>CHRIST</hi> sayd, MATTH. 22.29. <hi>You erre, not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor the power of God.</hi> Doe they not loue it? Behold their Plague, 2. THESS. 2.10.11.12. <hi>Because they receaved not the loue of the Trueth, that they might be saved, for this</hi> verie <hi>cause,</hi> sayeth the Text, <hi>God shall send them strong delusion; that they should belieue a Lie, that they might be damned.</hi> Doe they not steadfastlie belieue, what they learne in Scripture? In God's judgement, with the foolish, and vnstable, they are suffered to wrest the Scriptures, to their own destruction, were they never so great wits, 2. PET. 3.16. Doe they not studie, to giue obedience vnto the knowne Trueth of it? He dealeth with them, as with <hi>Israell,</hi> PSAL. 81.11. <hi>My people would not hearken vnto My Voyce, and Israell would none of Mee.</hi> (Hee counteth Himselfe rejected, because His Word was rejected.) But what followeth,
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Vers.</hi> 12. <hi>So I gaue them vp, vnto their owne heartes lust: and they walked in their owne counsels.</hi> But to such as will bee Christ's Disciples indeede, Students, seeking to grow in Knowledge, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and obedience of His Word; seeking to loue Him, and keepe His Sayings, Hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, (IOHN 14.26▪) to sende vnto them, <hi>The Spirit of Trueth, the Comforter, the holie Ghost, to teach them all things</hi>: That is, To perfect their knowledge, more and more, by His Spirit, to fill their hearts with joye and comfort, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to His Trueth, and to make them holie, more and more.</p>
   <p>And why are all these styles given? Even to show, that such as will haue Christ's Spirit to worke anie of these, must seeke Him to worke all of these, joyntlie, or not to haue Him for working anie of them at all. Neyther Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort without Trueth, nor Comfort without Holinesse. The same is it which Wisdome cryeth, PROV. 8.34.35.36. <hi>Blessed is the man that heareth Me; watching daylie at My Gates; way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the Posts of My Doores: For, who so findeth Mee, findeth Lyfe; and shall obtayne favour of the Lord. But hee that sinneth agaynst Me, wrongeth his owne Soule: all that hate Mee, loue Death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore, howe thou doest hate Death, and loue thyne owne Soule, howe thou stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest
<pb facs="7"/>
affected towardes GOD, and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship of the <hi>COMFORTER,</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>SPIRIT,</hi> the <hi>SPIRIT</hi> of <hi>TRVETH,</hi> and towardes the enlargement of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>CHRIST</hi>; let thy affection TOWARDS the <hi>SCRIPTVRES,</hi> more aboundant dvvelling in thy selfe, and FOR the <hi>SCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVRES</hi> more free course amongst others, beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
   <trailer>Fare-well.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>