<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Hono∣rable Lord Thomas Howard, &amp;c. R. I. vvisheth health, ho∣nor and happinesse.</title>
           <author>I., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109165_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04555</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14677</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Hono∣rable Lord Thomas Howard, &amp;c. R. I. vvisheth health, ho∣nor and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>I., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most famous history of the seauen champions of Christendome : Saint George of England, Saint Dennis of Fraunce, Saint Iames of Spaine, Saint Anthonie of Italie, Saint Andrew of Scotland, Saint Pattricke of Ireland, and Saint Dauid of Wales. Shewing their honorable battailes by sea and land: their tilts, iousts, and turnaments for ladies: their combats vvith giants, monsters, and dragons: their aduentures in forraine nations; their inchauntments in the holie land: their knighthoods, prowesse, and chiualrie, in Europe, Affrica, and Asia, with their victories against the enemies of Christ</title>
                 <author>Johnson, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 204+ pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord Thomas Howard, &amp;c. R. I. vvisheth health, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing heard (Right Honourable) by a general report of the lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; vertuous qualities, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith your Honours minde is beautefied, and your fauourable acceptance of good vvill from the meanest, I haue attempted (though fearing to fall like <hi>Phai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>) to present into your Lordships handes this homely gift: vvhich is a Historie of the seauen Champions of Christendome, vvhole names to this day is held in great estimation through Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope: vvhere in steede of musicke, I bring you mislike: for a learned booke, an ildle discourse: thereby to beguile your ingenious Iudgements exercised in the best rudiments. Yet presuming vpon this, that as the Noblest mindes are euer the most curteous, so your Honour vvill vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to cast a smiling glaunce at this simple toy:
<pb facs="3"/>
if not for the vvorkemanship, yet for the good vvill of the giuer: vvherevvith if I be fauoured (as I hope vvell) my labour hath his revvard, and my desire his content: in vvhich assured hope resting, I commit your Honour to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all humilitie most affectionate. R. I.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>