<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To The Right worshipfull, my cu∣teous
friends, the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court,
Thomas Lodge of Lincolnes Inne Gentle∣man,
wisheth prosperous successe in
their studies, and happie euent in
their trauailes.</title>
           <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109563_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06162</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16653</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109563</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To The Right worshipfull, my cu∣teous
friends, the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court,
Thomas Lodge of Lincolnes Inne Gentle∣man,
wisheth prosperous successe in
their studies, and happie euent in
their trauailes.</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An alarum against vsurers : Containing tryed experiences against worldly abuses. Wherein gentlemen may finde good counsells to confirme them, and pleasant histories to delight them: and euery thing so interlaced with varietie: as the curious may be satisfied with rarenesse, and the curteous with pleasure. Heereunto are annexed the delectable historie of Forbonius and Prisceria: with the lamentable complaint of truth ouer England. Written by Thomas Lodge, of Lincolnes Inne, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, Sampson.</publisher>
                            <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 40 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶To The Right worshipfull, my cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
friends, the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court,
Thomas Lodge of Lincolnes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Inne Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
wisheth prosperous successe in
their studies, and happie euent in
their trauailes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Urteous Gentlemen, let it not séeme
straunge vnto you, that hée which hath
long time slept in silence, now begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
publikely to salute you, since no
doubt, my reasons that induce me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
be such, as both you may allowe
of them, since they be well meant, and account of them
since they tend to your profit. I haue published héere of
set purpose a tried experience of worldly abuses, descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing
héerein not onely those monsters which were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished
<hi>Athens,</hi> I meane Usurers, but also such de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
caterpillers, who not onely haue fatted their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
with many rich forfaitures, but also spread their
venim among some priuate Gentlemen of your profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
which considered, I thought good in opening the
wound▪ to preuent an vlcer, and by counselling before
escape, forewarn before the mischiefe. Led then by these
perswasions, I doubt not, but as I haue alwayes found
you fauourable, so now you will not cease to be friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
both in protecting of this iust cause, from vniust slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
and my person from that reproch, which, about two
yeares since, an iniurious cauiller obiected against me:
You that knowe me Gentlemen, can testifie that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
my life hath bene so lewd, as y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> my companie was
edious, nor my behauiour so light, as that it shuld passe
the limits of modestie: this notwithstanding a licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Hipponax,</hi> neither regarding the asperitie of the
lawes touching slaunderous Libellers, nor the offyring
from whence I came, which is not contemptible, attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
not only in publike &amp; reprochfull terms to condemn
me in his writings, but also so to slander me, as neither
iustice shuld wink at so hainous an offēce, nor I preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
a commodious reply. About thrée yeres ago one <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen
Gosson</hi> published a booke, intituled, <hi>The schoole of
Abuse,</hi> in which hauing escaped in many &amp; sundry cōclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
I as the occasion thē fitted me, shapt him such an
answere as beséemed his discourse, which by reason of the
slendernes of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> subiect (because it was in defēce of plaies
&amp; play makers) y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> godly &amp; reuerent y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> had to deale in the
cause, misliking it, forbad y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> publishing, notwithstanding
he comming by a priuate vnperfect coppye, about two
yeres since, made a reply, diuiding it into fiue sectiōs, &amp;
in his Epistle dedicatory, to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> right honorable, sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
Walsingham,</hi> he impugneth me with these reproches,
y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> I am become a vagarāt person, visited by y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> heuy hand
of God, lighter then libertie, &amp; looser thē vanitie. At such
time as I first came to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> sight héerof (iudge you gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
how hardly I could disgest it) I bethought my selfe
to frame an answere, but considering y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> the labour was
but lost, I gaue way to my misfortune, contenting my
selfe to wait y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> opportunitie wherein I might, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the impertinacie of the iniurye, but as equitye
might countenance mée, cast a raine ouer the vntamed
curtailes chaps, &amp; wiping out the suspition of this slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
from the remebrance of those y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> knew me, not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell
this iniurious <hi>Asinius</hi> to become more conformable
in his reportes: and now Gentlemen hauing occasion
to passe my trauailes in publike, I thought it not amisse
somewhat to touch the slaunder, &amp; prouing it to be most
wicked &amp; discommendable, leaue the rest to the discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of those in authoritie, who if the Gentleman had not
plaid bo péep thus long, would haue taught him to haue
counted his cards a little better: and now <hi>Stephen Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
let me but familiarly reason with thée thus▪ Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
thou y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> in handling a good cause it is requisite to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
a fals propositiō, although thou wilt say it is a part
of Rethorike to argue <hi>A Persona,</hi> yet is it a practise of
small honestie to conclude without occasion: if thy cause
wer good, I doubt not but in so large &amp; ample a discourse
as thou hadst to handle, thou mightest had left the honor
of a gentleman inuiolate. But thy base degrée, subiect to
seruile attempts, measureth all things according to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling
capacitie, thinking because nature hath bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
vpō
thee a plausible discourse, thou maist in thy swéet
termes present the sowrest &amp; falsest reports y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> canst ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine:
but it may be, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> as it fortuned to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> noble man of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi>
it now fareth w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> me, who as <hi>Petarch</hi> reported, giuē
greatly to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> intertainmēt of strangers, &amp; pleasure of the
chase, respected not the braue &amp; gorgious garments of a
courtier, but delighted in such clothing as seemed y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> place
where he soiourned, this noble gentleman returning on
a time frō his game, found all his house furnished with
strangers, on whō bestowing his accustomed welcome,
he bent himself to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ouerseeing of his domestical prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiō,
&amp; cōming to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> stable among the hors kéepers of his
new come guests, &amp; reprehending one of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for faulting
in his office, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> felow impatient of reproofe, &amp; measuring
y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> gentleman by his plaine coat, stroke him on the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, &amp;
turned him out of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> stable, but afterward attending on
his master, &amp; perceiuing him whom he had stroken to be
y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Lord of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> house, he humbly craued pardō: y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> gentleman
as patient as pleasant, not only forgaue him y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> escape, but
pretely answered thus, I blame not thée good fellow for
thy outrage, but this companion, pointing to his coate,
which hath made thée mistake my person. So at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
estéeme I M. <hi>Gosson</hi> hath dealt with me, who not
mesuring me by my birth, but by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> subiect I hādled like
Will Summer striking him y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> stood next him, hath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided
me in person, whē he had no quarrell, but to my
cause, &amp; therein pleaded his owne indiscretiō, &amp; loded me
<pb facs="5"/>
with intollerable iniurie. But if with <hi>Zoylus</hi> hée might
kisse the gibet, or with <hi>Patacion</hi> hop headlesse, the world
shoulde bee ridde of an iniurious slaunderer, and that
tongue laboured in suppositions, might be nailed vp
as <hi>Tullies</hi> was for his <hi>Philipicall</hi> declamations. But
good <hi>Stephen,</hi> in like sorte will I deale with thée, as
<hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> with <hi>Nicanor,</hi> who not respecting
the maiestie of the king, but giuing himselfe ouer to the
petulancie of his tongue vainly inueighed against him,
whom notwithstanding <hi>Philip</hi> so cunningly handeled,
that not onely he ceased the rumor of his report, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
made him as lauish in commending, as once he was
profuse in discommending: his attempt was thus perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
he séeing <hi>Nicanor</hi> sorely pressed with pouerty, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued
him to his content. Wherevpon altering his cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie,
and breaking out into singular commendation of
<hi>Philip,</hi> the king concluded thus: Loe, curtesie can make
of bad good, and of <hi>Nicanor</hi> an enimie, <hi>Nicanor</hi> a friend.
Whose actions my reprouer, I will now fit to thée, who
hauing slaundered me without cause, I will no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
reuenge it, but by this meanes, that now in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
I confesse thou hast a good pen, and if thou kéepe thy
Methode in discourse, and leaue thy slandering without
cause, there is no doubt but thou shalt bée commended
for thy coppie, and praised for thy stile. And thus desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
thée to measure thy reportes with iustice, and you
good Gentlemen to answere in my behalfe if you
heare me reproched. I leaue you to your
pleasures, and for my selfe I will
studie your profit.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing friend,
<hi>Thomas Lodge.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>