<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGHLY DISCENDED And Heroicke Dutchesses Grace of LENOX, and all the great and vertuous Countesses, and Virgin Ladyes, Associats in this Royall Assembly.</title>
           <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109403_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15465</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109403</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGHLY DISCENDED And Heroicke Dutchesses Grace of LENOX, and all the great and vertuous Countesses, and Virgin Ladyes, Associats in this Royall Assembly.</title>
                 <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Great Britains beauties, or, The female glory : epitomized, in encomiastick anagramms, and acrostiches, upon the highly honoured names of the Queenes most gracious Majestie, and the gallant lady-masquers in her Graces glorious grand-masque. Presented at White-Hall on Shrove-Tuesday at night, by the Queenes Majestie and her ladies. With disticks, and illustrations, upon their severall anagramms, being in number fifteene, whose names ensure in order on the next side. Published by authoritie. Framed, and formed, by the humble pen of Francis Lenton, the Queenes poet</title>
                 <author>Lenton, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Parsons, Marmaduke</publisher>
                    <distributor>Becket, James</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 31, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGHLY DISCENDED And Heroicke Dutchesses Grace of <hi>LENOX,</hi> and all the great and vertuous <hi>Countesses, and Virgin Ladyes, Associats in this Royall Assembly.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>YOu rarer Beauties of great <hi>Britaines</hi> Court,</l>
      <l>(Imploy'd in this most glorious Masquing sport)</l>
      <l>At your high <hi>Altars</hi> I doe humbly proffer</l>
      <l>These Poems, which my modest <hi>Muse</hi> doth offer</l>
      <l>To each of your faire Hands, and gracious Eyes,</l>
      <l>Craving you would receiue this <hi>Sacrifice</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Assigned to your Praise; whose reall worth</l>
      <l>My painefull Pen here study'de to set forth:</l>
      <l>Though in the best endeavours of my Spirits,</l>
      <l>I fall farre short of your transcending Merits;</l>
      <l>Yet pardon, Ladies, and accept the Will,</l>
      <l>Of your true Honourer, whose worthlesse Quill</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Knowes what he wants in <hi>Fancy,</hi> and in <hi>Flames,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Will be supply'd by your Heroick Names:</l>
      <l>Thus grac'd, when you have read, I doe not feare,</l>
      <l>A kind Acceptance from each <hi>Lady</hi> here.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Devoted to your Vertues, FRA: LENTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>