<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>T. LL. In praise of this booke, and the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109296_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04954</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109296</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>T. LL. In praise of this booke, and the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blessednes of Brytaine, or A celebration of the Queenes holyday : conteining, a breefe rehersall, of the inestimable benefits, generally had &amp; enioyed, not only all England ouer, but also in forrein partes, through the gracious bountie, and incomparable blessed rule o our royall Queene Elizabeth. Composed, and set foorth, in due reuerence, &amp; ioyfull memoriall, of her Maiesties present entrance into the thirtieth yeere of her most triumphant raigne, with hartie prayer, for the long continuing, and prosperous preseruing of the same: by Maurice Kyffin. Published with authoritie</title>
                 <author>Kyffin, Maurice</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>T. LL. In praise of this booke, and the Author.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WHo list to see her Noble deeds displaid,</l>
      <l>Whose golden gifts, eche creature doth adore,</l>
      <l>Whose Vertues Rare, haue hauty harts dismaid,</l>
      <l>Whose Name, and Fame, encreaseth more &amp; more:</l>
      <l>Let them peruse this Poem, with Aduise.</l>
      <l>By <hi>Kyffins</hi> pen, put down in perfect wise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A work of woorth, beseeming well his Arte,</l>
      <l>So fitly framd, and fraught, with tryed Truthe.</l>
      <l>As may Reioyce, eche loyall subiects hart,</l>
      <l>To heare, and see; which hidden had bin Ruthe.</l>
      <l>Our Queenes long Raigne, to our still during ioy,</l>
      <l>The King of Kings, preserue free from Annoy,</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>