<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, VVILLIAM Lord SAYE, and SEALE, together with the re∣ligious Lady ELIZABETH his wife, Grace and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Hinde, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109713_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20524</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6935</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109713</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, VVILLIAM Lord SAYE, and SEALE, together with the re∣ligious Lady ELIZABETH his wife, Grace and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Hinde, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bathshebaes instructions to her sonne Lemuel : containing a fruitfull and plaine exposition of the last chapter of the Prouerbs. Describing the duties of a great-man, and the vertues of a gracious woman. Penned by a godly and learned man, now with God. Perused, and publishe for the use of Gods church, by Iohn Dod, and William Hinde</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 78, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, VVILLIAM Lord SAYE, <hi>and</hi> SEALE, <hi>together with the</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Lady ELIZABETH his <hi>wife, Grace and peace in</hi> Christ Iesus.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY GOOD LORD:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present you here with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine <hi>Iewell,</hi> which as it was found by a <hi>rich Merchant</hi> in his <hi>field,</hi> so was it polished by the cunning skill of his owne most <hi>curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hand. Jf</hi> you behold the <hi>quantitie,</hi> it may seeme but as a <hi>Mite:</hi> but if you consider the <hi>quality</hi> and vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is farre to bee preferred aboue much <hi>refined gold.</hi> For among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it hath this <hi>hidden vertue:</hi> that
<pb facs="3"/> whosoeuer contemplates the <hi>lustre</hi> thereof with a <hi>chaste eye,</hi> it will reflect a <hi>sanctified illumination</hi> into his <hi>very heart.</hi> And seeing that by <hi>Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence</hi> it came to my hands, when as by the death of the Author it was like to haue been <hi>lost: I</hi> thought my selfe bound in conscience to communicate it with the <hi>Church of God</hi> for the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good,</hi> rather then to keepe it still in my closet for my owne <hi>priuate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And howsoeuer the <hi>splendor</hi> of this <hi>Iewell</hi> will glad the <hi>heart</hi> of euery <hi>eye</hi> that seeth it, yet being well conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you shall finde it belongeth by a more <hi>peculier right,</hi> to such among the sonnes and daughters of men, who are <hi>eminent</hi> for their <hi>birth,</hi> and <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> for their <hi>place</hi> and <hi>condition.</hi> And because the <hi>worth</hi> of the <hi>Iewel</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a <hi>Patron</hi> of no meaner ranke then one of the <hi>sonnes of Nobles:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 10, 17</note> I thought
<pb facs="3"/> good to recommend this <hi>Iewell</hi> vnto your <hi>Lordships Patronage</hi> and <hi>protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and the rather, that it might bee some <hi>testimonie</hi> of the <hi>fauours</hi> which <hi>I</hi> haue receiued from: and of that <hi>duty</hi> wherein <hi>I</hi> acknowledge my selfe to be <hi>indebted</hi> vnto your <hi>Lordship. It</hi> is now your <hi>owne:</hi> oh let the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>lustre</hi> of euery <hi>beame</hi> therein, shine in your <hi>Person,</hi> and appeare in your <hi>practise:</hi> that to the glorie of <hi>God,</hi> the ioy of your <hi>friends,</hi> and solace of your owne <hi>conscience, Grace</hi> and <hi>Honour, Godlinesse</hi> and <hi>greatnesse, knowledge</hi> and <hi>sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> may be seene in you amiably to <hi>embrace,</hi> and beuatifully to <hi>adorne</hi> one another. For when after a <hi>long account</hi> you shall at the last come to cast vp your <hi>Summa totalis,</hi> you shall finde, that <hi>Godlinesse</hi> will proue the <hi>greatest gaine, Grace</hi> the richest <hi>treasure,</hi> and <hi>Gods fauour</hi> the <hi>highest honour.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> with his fauorable countenance
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>blesse</hi> you and your <hi>vertuous Lady,</hi> and euery <hi>branch</hi> of your <hi>vine;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 92.13, 14</note> that as the <hi>Lords planting</hi> you may so flourish in <hi>Gods courts,</hi> that <hi>branches</hi> be neuer wanting to your <hi>stocke,</hi> nor <hi>fruit</hi> vnto your <hi>braunches,</hi> that men may see that verified <hi>of</hi> your <hi>honourable vine,</hi> which the heathen man said of his <hi>golden tree;</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Primo avulso non deficit alter</l>
         <l>Aureus, &amp; simili frondescit virga metallo.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Bunbury in Cheshire.
<date>
            <hi>Iuly</hi> 13. 1614.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honours in all christian duty, to be commanded: WILLIAM HINDE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>