<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣shipfull our approoued good friend ERASMVS DRIDEN Esquire: Grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109743_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20556</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6963</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109743</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣shipfull our approoued good friend ERASMVS DRIDEN Esquire: Grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and familiar exposition of the fifteenth, sixteenth, and seventeenth chapters of the Prouerbs of Salomon</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland (Haveland), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sharpe, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 157, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull our approoued good friend ERASMVS DRIDEN</hi> Esquire: <hi>Grace and peace be</hi> multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, hauing had long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of your Christian and constant loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, as also of your wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes to read our bookes, and your godly wisdome to iudge and discerne of all that you read: we are bold to offer vnto your worship this testimonie of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained thankfulnesse, and to craue your fauourable patronage for the same.</p>
   <p>Our former writings comming only as strangers, yet alwaies found all good and kinde entertainment at your hands. Therefore we cannot doubt but that this present treatise shall be welcome and well accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; not only for that it is like to the former for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="3"/> and manner, but also because it shelters it selfe vnder your name, and in speciall manner craueth our countenance. And thus beseeching almightie God to blesse and prosper the faithfull indeuours of all that truly seeke the peace and welfare of his Church, and daily more and more to multiplie his gratious mercies vpon your selfe, your godlie wife, and hopefull familie, wee humblie take our leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord to be commanded, John Dod, Robert Cleauer. </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>