<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109217_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19797</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6225</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109217</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Maroccus extaticus. Or, Bankes bay horse in a trance : A discourse set downe in a merry dialogue, betweene Bankes and his beast: anatomizing some abuses and bad trickes of this age. Written and intituled to mine host of the Belsuage, and all his honest guests. By Iohn Dando the wierdrawer of Hadley, and Harrie Runt, head ostler of Bosomes Inne</title>
                 <author>Dando, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Readers, or
Gentlemen Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
which you
will, though it past
manners in vs to
stand like a couple
of eaues-dropping
knaues, and steale awaie a discourse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
Banks &amp; his bay horse from Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauage
without Ludgate, which in our
conscience we must confesse is a kinde of
coosning, &amp; in a maner such a matter as
if we should haue gone into a Cooks shop
in Fleet lane, and with the smell of roast
meat filled our bellies, not emptying our
purses, a flat robberie, and by a figure
such a peece of filching as is punishable
with ribroast among the turne spits at pie
<pb facs="4"/>
corner, where a man of an ill minde may
breake his fast with the sent of a peece of
beefe puld piping hot out of the furnace.
Yet considering the case as it concernes
the commonwealth, and the nature of the
subiect handled betwixt this horse &amp; his
master, which not anie in the world, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
yee, heard or vnderstoode but our
selues that came hether vpon other busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
wee could not choose but doo as wee
huve done: verie pure loue to our countrie
leading vs to lay our wits together, and
present the worlde with this pamphlet,
which if it bee not mistaken, may as well
serue to driue away pastime &amp; good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie,
as the finest philosophical discourse
you can light vpon. If it hang not wel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
thinke the fault is ours that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
it not well awaie, for truly there was
neuer horse in this world aunswered man
with more reason, nor neuer man in this
<pb facs="4"/>
world reasond more sensibly with a horse
than this man and this horse in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
as for example. And so committing
you (not to prison) no, but to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
of this <hi>Dialogue,</hi> we end
our Epistle to the
Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>