<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of my selfe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109368_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19913</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of my selfe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Wittes pilgrimage, (by poeticall essaies) through a vvorld of amorous sonnets, soule-passions, and other passages, diuine, philosophicall, morall, poeticall, and politicall. By Iohn Dauies</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>168 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Of my selfe.</head>
   <l>VVHat meane I miscreant my Braines to beate</l>
   <l>To forge these Fancies light as <hi>Leuity,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To set the World on fire which amorous heate,</l>
   <l>That now lies drowned in such vanity?</l>
   <l>I know I should not do it, and I know</l>
   <l>This knowledge much exaggerates my blame:</l>
   <l>Why do I then my science herein show,</l>
   <l>Where greatest skill doth merit greater shame?</l>
   <l>And who doth loue this vaine of fancy vaine</l>
   <l>But vainest mea? then, ô how vaine am I</l>
   <l>That thus the powers of my wit doe strayne,</l>
   <l>To please vaine Skums with skumme of vanity?</l>
   <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re VVit it self (though wit it selfe I had)</l>
   <l>Wants skill to coyne excuse the faults so fowle:</l>
   <l>Then, Reason run right, whether dost; thou gad?</l>
   <l>VVilt thou misleade the blind, thy Queen, my Soule?</l>
   <l>To please base Earth, wilt thou the, Heauens displease,</l>
   <l>That knowest so well the Earth yeeldes nought but dust?</l>
   <l>Seekst thou for fame with my whole mannes disease,</l>
   <l>That wotst all fame, but vertues is vniust?</l>
   <l>Or yet (by Faith instructed) knowst thou not</l>
   <l>(For, <hi>Faith,</hi> in Truth, knows more thē thou canst know)</l>
   <l>That names of famous men away shall rot,</l>
   <l>If from such gracelesse Grounds theyr fames do growe?</l>
   <l>Art thou my guide, and yet dost me direct</l>
   <l>To laby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inthes of loue, where we are lost?</l>
   <l>Dost thou (most wise) cause this most fond effect?</l>
   <l>Or'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rossest me, sith thee I oft haue crost?</l>
   <l>Ah <hi>Reason</hi> wilt thou now to <hi>Passion</hi> turne,</l>
   <l>That wast the Prince predominating it?</l>
   <l>Shal thy Slaue (fraile <hi>Affection</hi>) thee oreturne?</l>
   <l>And, mad to make me, wilt thou straine thy wit?</l>
   <l>VVilt thou instruct mee so to please the <hi>sence</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That none but sensuall men shall like my Lines?</l>
   <l>And misinforme the best <hi>Intelligence,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That paies beliefe to thee, and thine assignes?</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>
O <hi>Reaso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> weigh thy selfe in thine owne Scales,</l>
   <l>Ponder thy power which is as good, as strong:</l>
   <l>Be thou thy selfe, though thou art wrongd by Fools,</l>
   <l>And right that wrong with Iustice, not with wrong.</l>
   <l>I see thou hearst me, for thou teachest me,</l>
   <l>To teach thee what we both should learne and doe:</l>
   <l>Thou prompst me now, wherein I erd through thee;</l>
   <l>And bidst me those light Lines againe vndoe;</l>
   <l>And tye them to the lasting Lord of loue,</l>
   <l>VVith such a knot as nere shall be vndone:</l>
   <l>Those Lynes will draw, and hold, and stay, and mooue.</l>
   <l>Sith they are by the hand of <hi>Vertue</hi> spunne.</l>
   <l>Then <hi>Reason</hi> I acquite thee from disgrace,</l>
   <l>Sith thus thou promptst me what I ought to write:</l>
   <l>Lett <hi>Tyrant</hi> shame with bloud stil fil my face.</l>
   <l>For so abusing thy right ruling might.</l>
   <l>My frinds (though fraile as I am) pres me stil</l>
   <l>To presse these lines (more fraile) to publike view:</l>
   <l>If <hi>I</hi> shoulde saie it is againste my will</l>
   <l>I should speake truly, and yet most vntrue:</l>
   <l>For my wills fixt my fast friends stil to please:</l>
   <l>But yet still wauers thus, to publish these,</l>
   <l>Yet sith, in wauering wise, thus fixt, it stands</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Fames</hi> wind, <hi>Wits</hi> weather-cocke, my will, commands.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>