<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOV∣rable Robert Deuorax, Earle of Essex, Vi∣count Herefford, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. &amp;c. Peter Lowe wisheth good successe in all his woorthie enterprises, and high attempts.</title>
           <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109939_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06401</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16872</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109939</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOV∣rable Robert Deuorax, Earle of Essex, Vi∣count Herefford, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. &amp;c. Peter Lowe wisheth good successe in all his woorthie enterprises, and high attempts.</title>
                 <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An easie, certaine, and perfect method, to cure and preuent the Spanish sicknes : Wherby the learned and skilfull chirurgian may heale a great many other diseases. Compiled by Peter Lowe, Arellian</title>
                 <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Robert Deuorax,</hi> Earle of Essex, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Herefford, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. &amp;c. <hi>Peter Lowe</hi> wisheth good successe in all his woorthie enterprises, and high attempts.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (right honorable) this Treatise be far disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from your studies, yet I haue emboldened my selfe to let it passe, vnder your honourable patronage, for by Gods assistance, I intend heereafter to publish diuers other Bookes of Chirurgie, all which shall bee shrouded vnder your honourable shield, and protection, in regard of your manifold curtesies, and liberalitie to all Strangers bountifully extended, whereof you cease not euery day to giue experiment, but especially in respect of your honours valiant prowesse, and rare Martiall exploits in ayding my dread Soueraigne, &amp; Maister, the most victorious King of France, so that in honoring him, I must loue you, and for your heroicall vertues, admire your wisedome, and courage, in prosecuting all venterous, and hard attempts: as lately hath beene experimented to the terror of the Enemie, peaceable welfare of this Realme, and immortall fame vnto you, &amp; your posteritie for euer. Then forasmuch as the dedication heereof, cannot bring, any addition of credite vnto you, but rather, be the more acceptable, vnder the tytle of your honourable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, most humbly with my selfe, I present the same vnto your honours good lyking, as one, that daylie intermitteth not, to wish the aduauncement of your honourable estate.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all dutie most affectionate▪ Peter Lowe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>