<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣ble and his most esteemed Lorde, Robert Lord Sempile, Sheriffe of Renfrowe, and Baily of the Rega∣litie of Pastlay, Knight of his Maiesties most noble Order, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Counsell, P, L. wisheth increase of all honorable Vertues.</title>
           <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109645_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06400</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16869.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109645</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣ble and his most esteemed Lorde, Robert Lord Sempile, Sheriffe of Renfrowe, and Baily of the Rega∣litie of Pastlay, Knight of his Maiesties most noble Order, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Counsell, P, L. wisheth increase of all honorable Vertues.</title>
                 <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The whole course of chirurgerie : wherein is briefly set downe the causes, signes, prognostications &amp; curations of all sorts of tumors, wounds, vlcers, fractures, dislocations &amp; all other diseases, vsually practiced by chirurgions, according to the opinion of all our auncient doctours in chirurgerie. Compiled by Peter Lowe Scotchman, Arellian, Doctor in the Facultie of Chirurgerie in Paris, and chirurgian ordinarie to the most victorious and christian King of Fraunce and Nauarre. Whereunto is annexed the presages of diuine Hippocrates</title>
                 <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>296 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="137"/>
   <pb facs="137"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and his most esteemed Lorde, Robert Lord <hi>Sempile,</hi> Sheriffe of <hi>Renfrowe,</hi> and Baily of the Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of <hi>Pastlay,</hi> Knight of his Maiesties most noble Order, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Counsell, P, L. wisheth increase of all honorable Vertues.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had turned into our vulgar language this little worke, <hi>Right Honorable,</hi> I considered with my selfe, that in auncient time, and also in this our Age, men haue accustomed to dedicate their trauels vnto such vertuous Personages as they haue honored: and I examining my selfe, vnto whom I might addresse this little labour of mine, I thought good to presume to your goodnesse, and present the same to your Lordshippe, as a pledge of my zeale and humble duetie towards you, your honourable and matchlesse vertues deriued in part from your noble Parentes, but more plentifully inriched by your inuincible mind, valiant prowesse, and rare martiall exploytes, in prosecuting all venterous and hardy attemptes which was experimented at your being in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to the terrour of your enemies, honour of your countrey, and immortall Fame to you and your Posteritie for euer: wherein you manifest to the eye of the worlde the true <hi>Idaea</hi> of perfect Nobilitie, leauing to succeeding posteritie a memorable remembrance of your neuer-dying Fame. If your Lordship vouchsafe to patronize my endeuours (not worthy so honourable a Patrone) I shall be surely protected from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous teeth of all carpers and beare with ease the burthen of their reproches: my labours wantes not their reward, if they winne your good will, nor my minde his desire, if you vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fafe to fauour. I cease, wishing your Lordship as many happie yeeres as vertues: commending my labours to your honorable protection, I humbly take my leaue. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>London</hi>
         <date>the <hi>20.</hi> of <hi>Aprill. 1597.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your L. most duetifull to commaund.</hi> Peter Lowe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>