<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all faythfull brethren / that loue Iesu Chryste sincerelye, Gracious Menewe wysheth grace and peace of consci∣ence, and Godly strength from God the father throughe oure Lord Iesu Chryst.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109991_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07436</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17822</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109991</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all faythfull brethren / that loue Iesu Chryste sincerelye, Gracious Menewe wysheth grace and peace of consci∣ence, and Godly strength from God the father throughe oure Lord Iesu Chryst.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine subuersyon or turnyng vp syde down of all the argumentes, that the Popecatholykes can make for the maintenaunce of auricular confession : with a moste wholsome doctryne touchyng the due obedience, that we owe vnto ciuill magistrates, made dialogue wyse betwene th prentyse and the priest by Gracyous Menewe</title>
                 <author>Menewe, Gracious</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all faythfull brethren / that loue Iesu Chryste sincerelye, Gracious Menewe wysheth grace and peace of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Godly strength from God the father throughe oure Lord Iesu Chryst.</head>
   <p>MAny in these moste pery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tymes, whych haue deseruingly chaunced vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs for our synnes, are in such perplexite and tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble of conscience, that they can not tel, which waye to turne thēselfes, whom to helpe and succoure, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the lyttell talent that God
<pb facs="3"/>
hath lent me, I haue thought to be my bounden duty. And truelye I would haue long agone discharged my conscience in thys parte, If I myght by any meanes haue conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently published and sette forth abroade those thynges, that I had prepared for the purpose. But that could not bee, whyche thynge was to me no lesse gryeuous, than if I my selfe had felte the same burdē and payne, that I sawe my poore brethren to fele: howbeit sith, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the commen prouerbe, it is better late then neuer: I haue now at thys present penned or written out a litle treatyse, wherin I show briefly out of Gods boke and such auncyent wryters, as ground their sayinges vpon the same, how farre forth we oughte to bee obedyente vnto ciuill magistrates.<note place="margin">What is cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned in thys boke.</note> And thys I dyd because many are of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that they are bounde to do
<pb facs="3"/>
whatsoeuer the higher powers cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde them, though their lawes were directlye agaynste God and his word,<note place="margin">What mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to wryte here of the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diēce due to magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates.</note> in so much that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade them selues that they shalbe excused by them in the dreadful dai of iudgemente, when we shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare all before god, if at anye tyme they commit manifest Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trye and playne vngodlynesse throughe theyr commaundement. Whom I desyer in the bowels of our sauiour Iesu Christ, who hath shedde his blood indifferently for all them, that heare his worde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyently, and wythout any feare what man can doe vnto them, stike and cleaue stedfastly vnto it: that they wyll dyligently and wythout affectyon, puttyng asyde all vayne loue of their selues, looke vpon the places and examples of the holye scripture, and vpon the autorites of the olde auncyente fathers, that
<pb facs="4"/>
I haue here alleaged in thys my small boke, truly aunswerynge all maner of obiectyons that ar made to the contrary, then I truste, they wil be better aduised, and ceasse to please themselues in that which is euil, or to iustifie their manifest disobedyence towardes God and hys woorde, vnder the pretence and colour of the obedyence that we owe vnto hys magistrates and rulers of the earth: whom in the scriptures we are streightlye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to obeye,<note place="margin">Roma. 13. 1. Peter. 2.</note> yea vpō paine of damnacyon. But in the meane season, we muste alwayes haue before our eyen the golden sētence of our sauiour Chryste, where he sayeth: pay that vnto Ceasar, that is due vnto Ceasar,<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> and paye that vnto God, that is due vnto God. If Ceasar, that is to say, the ciuill magistrates commaunde the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng
<pb facs="4"/>
that God hath forbyddē, or forbydde thee nothynge that God hath commaunded, if thou doeste not then obeye, yea thoghe it were to the ieopardye of losinge both lyfe and goodes, thou mayst be sure that the vengeaunce of god and euerlastynge damnacyon of hell hangeth ouer thy head▪ but if the magistrates forgettyng theyr duetye towardes GOD, from whom they haue receaued all auto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte and power, dooe take vpon them, to commaund thee ani thing that GOD hath forbydden, or to forbydde thee any thynge, that the hygheste Monarche of all hath commaunded: thou oughtest in no wyse to obeye, not that thou shouldeste make any resystaunce, whyche thynge GODDES worde teacheth thee not, but that thou shouldest rather w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Sidrach,
<pb facs="5"/>
Misach and Abednago and wyth the holy prophete Daniel offer thy selfe to dye a most shamefull and cruel death,<note place="margin">Dani. 3.6.</note> than in any wyse to be obedyent to theyr vngodly lawes, &amp; wycked constitutiōs or statutes. This thou mayest learne, with dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent and affectuouslesse readynge in this boke, wherin also thou shalt haue a moste necessary doctryne of confession, teachyng thee how au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular confession,<note place="margin">Auriculare confessyon hath no groūde nor foundaciō in goddes worde.</note> whiche nowe a dayes to the great hynderaunce of Goddes trueth, and defacynge of hys glory, is set vp agayne, hath no grounde at al nor foundacyon in Goddes woorde, but is a mere tradition of that Antichryste of Rome, beeyng now, besydes al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enormites, that bee conteined in it, made a snare to snarle &amp; catche men wyth all.</p>
   <p>Here are all the argumentes, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Popecatholykes can make for
<pb facs="5"/>
the maintenaunce of thys Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian tradycyon, cleane subuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and turned vpside down, with the mightye thunder boltes of Goddes word, and with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> strong batteryng peces of the holye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the true catholike church, and spouse of oure sauyoure Iesu Christ.</p>
   <p>And then, immediatlye after, it is declared, what maner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessyon God doeth requyre of vs in his most sacred worde and holy scripture.</p>
   <p>Thys small laboure of myne, I desyre all true faythfull Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styans, to take in good worth, and to praye wyth me instaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, that God of hys infinite good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse and mercye vouchesafe to strengthen them, that doe stande, and to coumforte and helpe the weake hearted, to rayse them vp that fal, and finally to beate down
<pb facs="6"/>
Sathan vnder oure fete. Whiche thing, doubtelesse, he wyll doe for hys sonne Iesu Chrystes sake, to whom wyth the father, and the holy goste, bee al praise, glorye and honoure, for euer and euer. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>