<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109738_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20544</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6954</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109738</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and familiar exposition of the ninth and tenth chapters of the Prouerbs of Salomon</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wisedome of God, who best knoweth euery mans affections, doth testifie, that <hi>such as are full doe loath an hony</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 27. 7.</note>
      <hi>combe: but to them that are hungry euen bitter things beecome sweete.</hi> That which is very good, yea precious, and desired of the best, is distasted of such as regard not instruction: but that which is good at all, though meane, and despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of the most, is sauoury to such as soundly seeke saluation. The perswasion whereof hath incouraged vs to bring forth our prouision, and to set before thee such foode as God hath inabled vs to prepare. We rest assured of thy Christian loue towards vs, &amp; prouidence for thine owne soule, that thou wilt be more affected with the matter of this treatise, being, as we hope, sound, and without corruption, then offended with the manner thereof, being homely, and without elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. As in expounding this Scripture to our owne flocks, we respected the capacitie of our vnlearned hearers, so in publishing the same to others, we tender the profit of the simplest readers. And as for them that are iudicious, and Godly learned, we presume that their owne knowledge, &amp; the reading of more excellent discourses, will minister wisdome, to make their vse of this slender worke, as this worke will giue them occasion to esteeme the better of more excellent discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. We haue thought good to choose these two Chapters to beginne with, though almost in the middest of the booke, that we might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to thee a patterne of the exposition of both sorts of parables, aswell of such as are set downe in forme of a treatise, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued discourse, as of those which are for the most part single senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. If thou shalt iudge, that there may be any fruit of these trauels,
<pb facs="4"/> we are minded, if God will, to explicate the rest; but by parts, and at seuerall times, and not all entirely together. Now in reading of this, obserue that the reasons and vses of the points, are not inferred vpon the allegations, or amplifications, immediately going before, but depend vpon the propositions which are the doctrines raised out of the seuerall verses: And into them are we compelled to enter ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly without any precedent introduction to lead vs, least we shuld either weary our selues in seeking varietie of preambles, or wearie thee with innumerable tautologies and repetitions. In the printing, the pointing in sundry places is misplaced, which in reading thou shalt easily finde, and we hope wilt easily redresse.</p>
   <p>The God of mercie grant thee that grace which we can but wish thee, and by the efficacie of his spirit worke in thine heart the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power of this his holy word, which we can onely by tongue and penne declare vnto thee. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>