<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authours
Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109154_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19712</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109154</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authours
Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A notable historie of the Saracens : Briefly and faithfully descrybing the originall beginning, continuaunce and successe aswell of the Saracens, as also of Turkes, Souldans, Mamalukes, Assassines, Tartarians and Sophians. With a discourse of their affaires and actes from the byrthe of Mahomet their first péeuish prophet and founder for 700 yéeres space. VVherunto is annexed a compendious chronycle of all their yeerely exploytes, from the sayde Mahomets time tyll this present yeere of grace. 1575. Drawen out of Augustine Curio and sundry other good authours by Thomas Newton</title>
                 <author>Curione, Celio Augustino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Veale (Vele), Abraham</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 144 leaves, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Authours
Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any a time and often,</hi>
considering and debating with
my felfe, the acwarde course of
this changeable world, among
other things I haue bene greatly desyrous
to know, what the very &amp; chief cause should
be, of the subuersion and ruyne, from time to
time, of al mightie kyngdomes: And againe
of the setting vp and aduancement of manie
obscure persones of base degree and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
to most high honors and dignities. For
when I throughly consider and call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
the alteration and decay of the
<hi>Romane</hi> Empire, and the manifolde cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
that haue happened to noble▪ and
puyssaunt Kingdomes in times past, I well
see, that dissolute life, ambitiō and discord of
Rulers amonge themselues hath from time
to time bene the chief &amp; originall cause ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
Insomuch that by reading out of olde
Monumentes and Histories, thinges long
agone atchieued and done, I perceaue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Empires haue ben planted and constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
many Nations subdued, many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
with long continuance firmlye esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished
and most assured peare and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytie
among the Communaltie conserued by
temperaunce and sobrietie, but chiefly and
<pb facs="5"/>
specially by ciuill concord and mutuall amy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
Wherfore, both reason, &amp; dayly examples
enforce me to think, that Wealth, Ritches,
strength and skilfull pollicie in warlyke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres
without concord and goodwyl of the
people hurteth many times, but profiteth
almost neuer. Whereas concord and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence
(euen without wealth and rychesse)
be of great force and of themselues able to
doo very mutch. Therefore, they which
neglected the sauegard, quietnesse and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie
of their subiectes (whereby, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyll
is both purchased and also nourished,)
and wholy yeelded themselues to Ambition
and desire of souereignty (bestowing al their
studies and cogitations onely to enrich and
bring themselues to hye estate among their
owne People, desiring rather to be feared of
them then of their enemies) were in the end
vnprofitable to themselues and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
to their countrey. Contrarywise, they
that so arme themselues with the vnfayned
loue and goodwyll of their owne people and
subiectes, that they might both be tenderly
and intirelye beloued of them, and also bee
terrible and dreadfull to the enemy abroad:
those (I say) were thei, which notably bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited
both themselues and their common
wealth. And if we would peruse and rip
vp th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> auncient beginnings of al Kingdoms,
and throughly consider their fyrst originall,
<pb facs="5"/>
wee shall finde that so many of them as long
florished, were by most honest Artes and
wayes at the fyrst gotten, and by the best or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
of gouerment constituted. For it is wel
inough knowne, that at the beginning, the
name of a king (which alwaies was a name
moste holie and venerable) was geuen and
attributed to those that had done best ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
and been most meritorious to their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
whom the people for their common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
and vtilytie created Kinges and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes
ouer them. For when as the sacred
worde of God was not yet amonge men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged,
no religyon reuerenced, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ciuill order regarded, when no man tooke
any respect to lawfull matrymonie, or to any
certaine procreation of Children, and the
due administratiō of iustice and lawes with
the profites therof not once heard of, much
lesse executed: when men after a brutishe
sorte lyued abroad in the woods and open
fieldes, wholy drowned in errour and blind
ignorance, abusing their strength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
onely to the satisfyinge of their owne sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall
affections and beastlye lustes: what
mans power was so great, or who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
with al the strength he had to gatherto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
these sauage and rude persones lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in woods &amp; cabines abrod, into one fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship?
&amp; to perswade thē to be obedient &amp;
conformable to his cōmandements? Certes
<pb facs="6"/>
wee muste needes confesse, that this redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
of them from their fyrste vnmannerly
rudenesse, to honeste order and comelinesse,
was not brought to passe by force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
but by wisedome, equity, iustice, curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
dealyng and liberall benefites bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
vpon them all generallye, whereby the
hartes of the people were rauished and as it
were with a certain bond of beneuolence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured
to haue them in admiration, and to
beare vnto them an earneste zeale of duty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
good wyll. And although at the fyrste,
thei semed after a sort (because of the strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
thereof) to be halfe vnwyllynge, yet at
length by meanes of benefits receaued, and
other liberal curtesies, together with an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
equitie in euery respect obserued, they
brought them into order and ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
vnto euerye thinge that seemed honest
and profitable. By these politique meanes,
Saturne the aunciente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> founder of Rome
reigned firste in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and escaped the
conspiracye and force of the mightiest kings
of <hi>Babilon</hi> by nothinge so much, as by his
iustice aud equitie and the assured good wils
of his owne people, and by their onely help,
fleeing the furie and crueltie of Iupiter, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned
and wanne a new kingdome in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
By this way, <hi>Romulus</hi> the other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of Rome, of a poore and beggarly sheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,
was aduanced to the degree of a king.
<pb facs="6"/>
In lyke manner were <hi>Numa</hi> and <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius
Priscus</hi> of straungers and priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
made Kinges in the same place. By
such good will and affection of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
<hi>Alexander</hi> the Great conquered all the
East. By concorde, the <hi>Greeques</hi> victorious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
augmented and enlarged their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
by concord, the common wealth of the
<hi>Carthaginians</hi> grewe to bee moste mightye:
the same concorde made the Romanes,
Lordes ouer al Lands, and conquerours of
al forraine nations. In this bond of concord
the <hi>Sarracens</hi> a weake and slender rable of
Peyzants at the fyrst, being ioyned and lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
together, ouercame and possessed verye
many prouinces belōging to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romane em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire:
&amp; by this meanes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> power of the Turks
at the fyrst &amp; euer since hath increased. But
Insolency, Ambition and Discord hath ben
the subuersion of all Kingdomes, mightye
Empires and populous common wealthes.
For when princes (neglecting and forsaking
those trades and waies by which their king
domes were at the fyrst constituted) thinke
Money and wealth, to be the chief defence,
and as it were the Sinewes and stayes of
their kingdomes, when any secret hatred
and harte burninge enkindleth betweene
them and their people, then do they hazard
and endaunger both themselues their Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>almes
and subiectes to the spoyle of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.
<pb facs="7"/>
For nature hath thus ordayned, that as
we feele &amp; perceaue others to be affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
vs, we also ar affected towards thē: &amp;
<hi>Plato</hi> his saying is well known concerning y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
same matter who writeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as the princes &amp;
rulers in a common welth are, such common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
bee the people and Citizens of the same.
Therefore no man ought to marueile, why
those Princes which set more by their own
priuate lucre and gayne then by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
commodytie of their Realme, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
times but slenderlye beloued of their sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes:
and that all their Officers vnder
them by their euyll example, are more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
to enriche their owne Coffers then to
further the common wealth of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.
Thus mens harts being diuersly bent
and their good wils alieuated one from an
other, the common wealth consequently go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
to wracke &amp; confusion. These were the
causes, why the Empyre was first trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
from the <hi>Chaldayes</hi> to the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> from
the <hi>Assyrians</hi> to the <hi>Medians,</hi> from the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
to the <hi>Persians</hi> and last of all from the <hi>Persi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
to the <hi>Macedonians.</hi> Discord was the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
and disparcling of that famous and
large Monarchy left by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great,
while his successours (not cōtent euery man
with his owne Territory) quarelled among
themselues for the whole Monarchy. Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde
abated and tamed the whole power
<pb facs="7"/>
and common wealthe of the Greeques: by
discorde and ciuill warres, the Romane
state was destroyed and brought almoste
to nothing: and agayne the ciuill diuision
of the Greeques amonge themselues was
the only cause that the flourishing empire of
<hi>Constantinople</hi> was brought vnder the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
yoke and slauerye of a Nation moste
barbarous. Discord was the vtter vndoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng
and defacyng of the <hi>Sarracens</hi> Empire, as
in this History it shall playnly appeare: and
the same plague doth at this day so infest
and trouble all Christendome that I feare
(and I beseech God my feare may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
effect) least wee shall to late rue and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
either the vtter subuersion or at least,
the miserable oppression thereof. What do
wee meane therfore? seeyng Ambition and
her daughter Discorde haue euer bene the
causes of so great calamyties and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieues,
why doo we thus runne headlong
vpon the Swordes poinct, and cut one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others
throat? why haue we such delyght
in ciuill warres and domesticall murder?
why doo wee not (alas for pitie that our
mindes should be somuch blinded and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched)
lay asyde all priuate grudges and
controuersies which ought rather to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided
by equitie and the infallible lawe of
God, then with war and effusion of Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian
bloud? why doo wee not rather bende
<pb facs="8"/>
all our force and power against the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
enemies of Christianitie, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōtemners &amp;
destroyers of all humanitye, relygion and
learning? These warres (I say) which are
deuided into many partes and factions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
vs, one conspiringe an others bane
and thyrsting after his brothers bloud, wil
in the end bring all Christendome to vtter
ruine and wofull desolation. Which if they
would ioyne in one and liue together in
Christian league, no doubte, <hi>Constantinople</hi>
might be agayn recouered and annexed to
the Romane Empire, <hi>Grecia</hi> and a great
nnmber of Christiā cuntries now lyuyng in
perpetual moorning, &amp; pitiful slauery might
bee deliuered out of the thraldome of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufferable
tyraunts, that Sathanical crew
of Turkish lurdens might be expulsed and
driuen to trudge out of all <hi>Europa,</hi> and the
sincere profession of christian religion there
eftsones planted and truely acknowledged.
Paraduenture some wyll cast doubtes and
obiect, that this our mortal foe is not neere
hand, but must be sought out (as aforetime)
in farre countryes, that they must passe sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
aduentures ouer many perilous Seas,
that they must goe a great way beyonde all
<hi>Europa,</hi> and set foote into <hi>ASIA</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi>
by daungerous places, vnknowne waies
suspect countreies and fierce people. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde,
euen at our dores and ready to come
<pb facs="8"/>
into our houses, we haue this arrogant and
bragging helhound, triumphyng ouer vs,
laughyng at our misfortunes, reioycinge to
see vs thus to lye together by the eares, and
gapyng in hope short lye to enioy our goods
and Scigniories. O dolefull and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
times. O corrupt and wylfull maners.
In times past, one <hi>Peter</hi> an Heremite beyng
but a poore seely soule, was able with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortyng
wordes and orations to perswade
three hundreth thousand men to put on ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur
against the <hi>Sarracens,</hi> and to procure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable
Gentlemen &amp; Potentates with
all the power they were able to make, to
march against them, &amp; to bring them as far
as into <hi>Afia,</hi> where they valiantly conquered
and wanne from the <hi>Sarracens</hi> many of their
Kingdomes and Prouinces. For the people
in those daies were of themselues so willing
to adueuture their liues in Christes quarell
against the blasphemers of his name, that
without any stipend or wages (godly zeale
so pricked them forwarde) they tooke in
hand such long Expeditions and weary vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages:
and while Kinges and Rulers were
geuen either to rest and riotte, or els busyed
with ciuill and domesticall warres, they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
their weapons into farre Regions to
fight against the Infidels and miscreaunt
people. But now whereas our most mightye
and the same most vnmercifull Enemye the
<pb facs="9"/>
great Turke is ready euery day to spyll out
bloud and to work our confusion, possessing
&amp; hauing alredy vnder his iurisdiction many
of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Christian Prouinces, to some others lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng
batterye and siege: and hopyng ere it be
long, to spoyle &amp; ouerrunne the rest, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
that Christendome hath <hi>Maximilian</hi> an
Emperour moste prudent and wyse, yet
neuerthelesse, by the sinister perswasions,
and deuilish counsailes of some sedicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonnes
w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>slea and kill one an other. Which
thing I considering, and greatly lamentyng
the state wherein Christendome presentlye
standeth, albeit that I being but one man,
and such a one, that lackyng both strength &amp;
health, am able in person to doe no good in
the exploites of martiall affaires: yet to the
intent I might stirre vp and kindle a desire
and go dwyl in many others which are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
hable, to repulse this our common daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
by such examples as are in Histories re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistred
and writen, I haue heere taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
mee orderlye to describe and set out the
Actes of the <hi>Sarracens</hi> and Turkes, buried al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
in the rust ye dongeon of cankard obly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyon:
that we seeyng by what meanes and
sleightes they haue increased, and by what
folies and ouersightes our power hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minished,
may now at length decline and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chue
the lyke. This whole Historye breeflye
comprysinge the whole Discourse of their
<pb facs="9"/>
raignes and conquestes, collected aswell out
of many Greeque, Constantinopolitan, and
Latine Authours, as out of the Chronicles
of the <hi>Arabians</hi> &amp; <hi>Moores,</hi> is deuided into three
Bookes. The firste containeth the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie,
education, raigne and continuaunce of
dotynge <hi>Mahomet</hi> and the beginning of the
<hi>Saracens,</hi> with the successe and increase of their
Empire euen tyll it was at the highest, for
two hundreth yeeres space. The seconde is
contynued from the fyrst inclynation tyll the
beginning of the destruction and laste ende
thereof, contayninge also the space of two
hundreth yeeres. The third breefly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth
the finall end of it, and the original
beginning of the Turkishe Empire, (which
succeeded the Saracenical Domination) till
<hi>Othoman</hi> the first Emperour of Turks which
intreateth of their acts, for the space of three
hundreth yeeres. So that this Historye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
his beginning at the byrth of <hi>Mahomet,</hi>
which was fiue hundred &amp; sixty yeeres after
the incarnation of our Sauiour Christ, and
reacheth vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeere one thousand &amp; three
hundreth. As for the seueral Acts of <hi>Othoman</hi>
and other Emperours that succeeded hym,
we haue heere omitted, because they be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally
written and described by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
But of that argument which wee in
these three Books declare and comprehend,
<pb facs="10"/>
there is none, neither amonge the <hi>Latines</hi>
nor yet the <hi>Greeques</hi> (that I know) which
hath compiled and made any seuerall Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.
Which labour of mine, if I may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
to be well lyked and allowed, by the
iudgment of the honest and learned sorte, I
wyll heerafter aduenture to take in hande
other matters of greater waight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaunce.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>