<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Prince.</title>
           <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109271_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19812</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6239</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109271</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Prince.</title>
                 <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine small poems lately printed : with the tragedie of Philotas. Written by Samuel Daniel</title>
                 <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                            <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="67"/>
   <pb facs="67"/>
   <head>To the Prince.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>TO you most hopefull Prince, not as you are</l>
      <l>But as you may be, do I giue these lines:</l>
      <l>That whē your iudgmēt shal ariue so far,</l>
      <l>As t'ouerlooke th'intricate designes,</l>
      <l>Of vncontented man: you may behold</l>
      <l>With what incounters greatest fortunes cloze,</l>
      <l>What dangers, what attempts, what manifold</l>
      <l>Incumbrances, ambition vndergoes:</l>
      <l>How hardly men digest felicity;</l>
      <l>How to th'intemperat, to the prodigall,</l>
      <l>To wantonesse, and vnto luxury</l>
      <l>Many things want, but to ambition all.</l>
      <l>And you shall find the greatest enemy</l>
      <l>That man can haue, is his prosperity.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Here shall you see how men disguise their ends,</l>
      <l>And playte bad courses vnder pleasing shews,</l>
      <l>How well presumption broken wayes defends,</l>
      <l>Which cleere-eyed iudgment gráuely doth disclose.</l>
      <l>Here shall you see how th'easie multitude</l>
      <l>Transported, take the party of distresse;</l>
      <l>And onely out of passion do conclude,</l>
      <l>Not out of iudgment; of mens practises.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="68"/>
      <l>How powr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s are thought to wrong, that wrongs debar,</l>
      <l>And kings not held in danger, though they are.</l>
      <l>These ancient representments of times past;</l>
      <l>Tell vs that men haue, doo, and alwayes runne</l>
      <l>The selfe same line of action, and do cast</l>
      <l>Their course alike, and nothing can be donne,</l>
      <l>(Whilst they, their ends, and nature are the same<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>But will be wrought vpon the selfe-same frame.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This benefit, most noble Prince, doth yeeld</l>
      <l>The sure recordes of Bookes, in which we finde</l>
      <l>The tenure of our state, how it was held</l>
      <l>By all our ancestors, and in what kinde</l>
      <l>We hold the same, and likewise how in the end</l>
      <l>This fraile possession of felicitie,</l>
      <l>Shall to our late posteritie discend,</l>
      <l>By the same pattent of like destinie.</l>
      <l>In them we finde that nothiwg can accrew</l>
      <l>To man, and his condition that is new.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And though you haue a Swannet of your owne,</l>
      <l>Which on the bankes of <hi>Douen</hi> meditates</l>
      <l>Sweete notes for you, and vnto your renowne</l>
      <l>The glory of his Musique dedicates;</l>
      <l>And in a loftie tune is set to sound</l>
      <l>The deepe reportes of Sullein tragedies.</l>
      <l>Yet may this l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st of me be likewise found,</l>
      <l>Amongst the vowes that others sacrifize</l>
      <l>Vnto the hope of you, that you one day,</l>
      <l>May grace this now neglected harmonie:</l>
      <l>Which set vnto your glorious actions may</l>
      <l>Record the same to all posteritie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="68"/>
      <l>Though I the remnant of another time.</l>
      <l>Am neuer like to see that happinesse:</l>
      <l>Yet for the zeale that I haue borne to rime,</l>
      <l>And to the Muses wish that good successe</l>
      <l>To others trauaile, that in better place,</l>
      <l>And better comfort, they may be incheerd</l>
      <l>Who shall deserue, and who shall haue the grace</l>
      <l>To haue a Muse held worthy to be heard.</l>
      <l>And know, sweete Prince, when you shall come to know,</l>
      <l>That tis not in the powre of Kings to raise</l>
      <l>A spirit for verse that is not borne thereto:</l>
      <l>Nor are they borne in euery Princes dayes.</l>
      <l>For late <hi>Elizas</hi> raigne, gaue birth to more</l>
      <l>Then all the kings of <hi>England</hi> did before.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And it may be, the Genius of that time,</l>
      <l>Would leaue to her the glorie in that kind;</l>
      <l>And that the vtmost powers of English Ryme,</l>
      <l>Should be within her peacefull raigne confinde.</l>
      <l>For since that time, our songues could neuer thriue,</l>
      <l>But laine as if for lorne: though in the prime</l>
      <l>Of this new rising season, we did striue</l>
      <l>To bring the best we could vnto the time.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And I although among the latter traine,</l>
      <l>And least of those that sung vnto this land,</l>
      <l>Haue borne my part, though in an humble straine,</l>
      <l>And pleasd the gentler that did vnderstand:</l>
      <l>And neuer had my harmlesse Pen at all</l>
      <l>Distaind with any loose immodestie,</l>
      <l>Nor euer noted to be toucht with gall,</l>
      <l>To aggrauate the worst mans infamy.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="69"/>But still haue donne the fairest offices</l>
      <l>To virtue and the time, yet nought preuailes,</l>
      <l>And all our labors are without successe,</l>
      <l>For either fauour or our virtue failes.</l>
      <l>And therefore since I haue out liud the date</l>
      <l>Of former grace, acceptance, and delight,</l>
      <l>I would my lines late-borne beyond the fate</l>
      <l>Of her spent line, had neuer come to light.</l>
      <l>So had I not bene tax'd for wishing well</l>
      <l>Nor now mistaken by the censuring stage</l>
      <l>Nor, in my fame and reputation fell.</l>
      <l>Which I esteeme more then what all the age</l>
      <l>Or th'earth can giue. But yeares hath don this wrong,</l>
      <l>To make me write too much, and liue too long.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And yet I grieue for that vnfinisht frame,</l>
      <l>Which thou deare Muse didst vow to sacrifize,</l>
      <l>Vnto the Bed of peace, and in the same,</l>
      <l>Designe our happinesse to memorize,</l>
      <l>Must, as it is remaine, though as it is:</l>
      <l>It shall to after times relate my zeale</l>
      <l>To kings, and vnto right, to quietnesse,</l>
      <l>And to the vnion of the common-weale.</l>
      <l>But this may now, seeme a superfluous vow,</l>
      <l>We haue this peace; and thou hast sung ynow</l>
      <l>And more then wilbe heard, and then as good</l>
      <l>As not to write, as not be vnderstood.</l>
   </lg>
   <signed>Sam: Dan.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>