<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Noble, Honourable, and wor∣thy Lord, William Earle of Pembrok, Lord Herbert of Cardiffe, Marmion, and Saint Quintine, Lord Cham∣berlaine of his Maiesties houshold, one of his Maie∣sties most Honorable Priuie Counsell and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</title>
           <author>Dauison, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109387_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19946</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6376</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109387</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Noble, Honourable, and wor∣thy Lord, William Earle of Pembrok, Lord Herbert of Cardiffe, Marmion, and Saint Quintine, Lord Cham∣berlaine of his Maiesties houshold, one of his Maie∣sties most Honorable Priuie Counsell and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Dauison, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Dauisons poems, or, A poeticall rapsodie : Deuided into sixe bookes. The first, contayning poems and deuises. The second, sonets and canzonets. The third, pastoralls and elegies. The fourth, madrigalls and odes. The fift, epigrams and epitaphs. The sixt, epistles, and epithalamions. For variety and pleasure, the like neuer published</title>
                 <author>Davison, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 272 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Noble, Honourable, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lord, <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembrok,</hi> Lord Herbert <hi>of Cardiffe, Marmion, and Saint Quintine, Lord</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine of his Maiesties houshold, one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties most Honorable Priuie Counsell and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</head>
   <l>GReat Earle, whose braue Heroike mind is higher,</l>
   <l>And nobler, then thy noble high Degree:</l>
   <l>Whose outward shape, though it most louely be</l>
   <l>Doth in faire Robes a fairer soule attire:</l>
   <l>Who rich in fading wealth, endlesse Treasure</l>
   <l>Of Vertue, Valour, Learning, richer art,</l>
   <l>Whose present greatnesse men esteeme but part</l>
   <l>Of what by line of future hope they measure,</l>
   <l>Thou worthy Son vnto a peerelesse mother,</l>
   <l>Or Nephew to great <hi>Sidney</hi> of renowne,</l>
   <l>Who hast deseru'd thy Coronet to crowne</l>
   <l>With Lawrell Crowne a Crowne excelling th'other</l>
   <l>I consecrate these Rimes to thy great Name,</l>
   <l>Which if thou like, they seeke no other fame.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Fra: Dauison.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>