<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the High and Mightie Prince, CHARLES, Prince of Great Britane. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109476_Fr2_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15715</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109476</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the High and Mightie Prince, CHARLES, Prince of Great Britane. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrimes farewell, to his natiue countrey of Scotland : vvherein is contained, in way of dialogue, the ioyes and miseries of peregrination. With his Lamentado in his second trauels, his Passionado on the Rhyne, diuerse other insertings, and farewels, to noble personages, and, the heremites welcome to his third pilgrimage, &amp;c. Worthie to be seene and read of all gallant spirits, and pompe-expecting eyes. By William Lithgow, the bonauenture of Europe, Asia, and Africa, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Hart, Andro.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lithgow, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the High and Mightie Prince, <hi>CHARLES,</hi> Prince of Great Britane. &amp;c.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LOe heere (braue Prince) I striue thy Worth to prayse,</l>
      <l>But cannot touch, the least of thy Desertes;</l>
      <l>I showe good-will, let brauer Spirits rayse,</l>
      <l>Thy Name, thy Worth, thy Greatnesse, and good partes:</l>
      <l>Late famous <hi>Henry,</hi> did not leaue the earth,</l>
      <l>(The Heauens esteem'd the Earth too base for him)</l>
      <l>Till thou his second selfe, in blood, in birth,</l>
      <l>Hadst strength to his most Princely parts to clim:</l>
      <l>Sweet youth, in whome, thy Grandsires worth reuiues,</l>
      <l>And noble vertues, are renew'd againe,</l>
      <l>In Thee, the hope, of that Succession liues:</l>
      <l>VVhose braue beginning, cannot ende in vaine.</l>
      <l>Most hopefull Image, of thy vertuous Sire,</l>
      <l>And greatest Hope, of that renowned Race,</l>
      <l>These Unite Kingdomes, limite thy desire,</l>
      <l>From seeking Conquest, in a Forraine place.</l>
      <l>This Noble Yle yeeldes matter in such store,</l>
      <l>For thy braue Sprite, to gaine a glorious Name:</l>
      <l>And rayse thy State, all <hi>Europe</hi> yeeldes no more,</l>
      <l>Heere stay, and striue, to match thy Fathers Fame.</l>
      <l>VVho knowes, but thou, resembling him in face,</l>
      <l>Mayst one day liue, to equall him in Place?</l>
      <l>So euer Happie Prince, I humblie bring,</l>
      <l>This Eccho of Farewell, Farewell I sing.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnesse most prostrate and Obsequious Oratour,</hi>WILLIAM LITHGOW.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>