<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Unto the Christē reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109287_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18673</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5189.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109287</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Unto the Christē reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christen rule or state of all the worlde from the hyghest to the lowest : and how euery man shulde lyue to please God in hys callynge. Item, the Christian state of matrimony: and how ma [n] and wife shuld kepe house together with loue. Item, the maner oe [sic] saynge grace after the holy scrypture</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 72, 71-78, 81-91, 5, 33 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>Unto the Christē reader</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuche as all persones cā not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue leyser to reade many bok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, nor yet get all suche as be necessary for thē (so me for lacke not beyng able to bye thē, and some that cā not get them for theyr mony) I haue here gathered toge ther out of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> most famous anthors of our Englishe tōge, the whole office and dewtye of euery Christē man. And spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially &amp; aboue all thinges is here at lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge declared the dutye of subiectes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde theyr princes▪ &amp; of maried wifes toward their husbandes▪ And truly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was it more nede to be taught thā now. For neuer had any prince so much nede of harty obediēt subiectes whych wolde geue theyr goodes &amp; aduenture theyr lyues in hys most iust qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>relle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his enemies, thn̄ haue our moost dreade souereyne lord kyng Henry the eyght. Here in shal you lerne your duty towardes hys grace, and to gyue your aydes vnto hys grace, not as cōpelled ther vnto, but wyth a fre harte▪ Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng that his graces welth is all our welfares. Pray therfore vnto the lord that he wyll graunte hym victory ouer
<pb facs="3"/>
hys enemies. And ye wyfes, al though thys lytle boke hath long contynued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge you (called the Christen state of matrimony (yet are you neuer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but contynue styll in your dysobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the displeasure of god and your husbandes greate dysquietnesse. The husband that hath bene a brode (eyther a boughte hys matchaundise or at hys worke (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n he commeth home wolde gladly be made of and cheryshed of his wyfe, whome he so hartely loueth, &amp; thē shal she neytheer geue hym a good coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, nor set any thyng before hym that myght conforte him, the one syttin ge so strangely and so farre from the o ther, as though they had neuer one sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the other, more lyke straunges than frindes, yea more lyke enemies thā mā and wife. Therfore reade not this boke only, but marke what is therin writtē and shut it vp in your hartes &amp; occupie it whan nede shall requyre. For blessed are they that heareth or readethe anye thyng that perteyneth to theyr lyues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement and do therafter The grace of our Lorde Iesus Christ be wyth al thē that loue the lord vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>