<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109367_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19911</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6342</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109367</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A select second husband for Sir Thomas Ouerburie's wife, now a matchlesse widow</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marriot, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>94 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O Rest is in Motion. <hi>The</hi> Circle <hi>of</hi> Opinion <hi>is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> Center: <hi>yet, past that</hi> Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe, <hi>no</hi> lines <hi>haue</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. <hi>One</hi> singular Wit <hi>(af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting</hi> singularity, <hi>in</hi> matter <hi>and</hi> manner <hi>of</hi> verse) <hi>lately put foote into that</hi> Circle, <hi>and</hi> there <hi>so arrests the</hi> Worlds <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it finds no comming forth; but, lies there</hi> forth-comming <hi>to be</hi> iustified, <hi>or</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, <hi>as</hi> Reason, <hi>in</hi> Time <hi>shall find</hi> Eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>An</hi> Opinion <hi>without</hi> learning, <hi>cannot be good, say the</hi> learned. <hi>Therefore, in this, to spend</hi> mine, <hi>were a sinfull</hi> prodigality; <hi>because it may be</hi> much <hi>to</hi> little <hi>purpose. But I will not long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thee,</hi> Reader. Fools-bolts <hi>are soone</hi> shot. <hi>Then take</hi> mine <hi>with thee: it is but</hi> light, <hi>&amp; shal</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>cost thee</hi> nothing. <hi>In few; if all</hi> Poets, <hi>in their</hi> Poems, <hi>are said to</hi> sing; <hi>then, they make harsh</hi> musicke, <hi>who, to please</hi> Iudgement <hi>with the</hi> Ditty, <hi>offend the</hi> Eare <hi>with the</hi> accent: <hi>and, he that sings</hi> much, <hi>out of</hi> tune, <hi>though he sing</hi> wel, out of cry, <hi>may, haply, sing to please</hi> himselfe, <hi>and</hi> few; <hi>but shall be sure to displease</hi> many. <hi>In</hi> well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, <hi>it is well done to follow; but, in</hi> ill, <hi>the</hi> imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <hi>is worse than the</hi> example. <hi>Tomarre the</hi> musicke <hi>of the</hi> Line <hi>for the reason of</hi> Sense, <hi>is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> sense <hi>and</hi> reason: <hi>seeing</hi> words <hi>may bee found as well to fit the</hi> tune, <hi>as the</hi> sense <hi>in what</hi> line <hi>soeuer. But, to affect</hi> harshnesse <hi>in</hi> fashion <hi>with</hi> some, <hi>should be an</hi> affectation <hi>out of</hi> fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>with</hi> all: <hi>for canst thou not sing</hi> sharp <hi>in</hi> sense <hi>but thou must sing</hi> flat <hi>in</hi> sound? <hi>Thou maist: else (peraduenture) thou canst</hi> SAY; <hi>but (without peraduenture) thou canst not</hi> SING. <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well; and sing in tune; else</hi> fast <hi>for me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I. D.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>