<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT honorable and verie ver∣tuous ladie, Brigit, countesse of Bedford: and to the right worshipfull and his verie good freends, sir CHARLES MORISINES knight, and the ladie DOROTHIE MORISINES his wife, T. W. vvisheth togither vvith all outvvard abu∣dance of vvorldlie blessings the continuall comfort of a good conscience heere, and the eternall saluation of their soules at the last through Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109031_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10233</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2051</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109031</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT honorable and verie ver∣tuous ladie, Brigit, countesse of Bedford: and to the right worshipfull and his verie good freends, sir CHARLES MORISINES knight, and the ladie DOROTHIE MORISINES his wife, T. W. vvisheth togither vvith all outvvard abu∣dance of vvorldlie blessings the continuall comfort of a good conscience heere, and the eternall saluation of their soules at the last through Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two very lerned sermons of M. Beza, togither with a short sum of the sacrament of the Lordes Supper: Wherevnto is added a treatise of the substance of the Lords Supper, wherin is breflie and soundlie discussed the p [r] incipall points in controuersie, concerning that question. By T.W</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                            <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 250 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> honorable and verie <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ladie, Brigit, countesse of Bedford: and to the right</hi> worshipfull and his verie good freends, sir <hi>CHARLES MORISINES knight, and the ladie DOROTHIE MORISINES his wife, T. W.</hi> vvisheth togither vvith all outvvard abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of vvorldlie blessings the continuall comfort of a good conscience heere, and the eternall saluation of their soules at the last through Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He consideration of the christian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, which you (right honorable, right worshipfull, &amp; my verie deere freends) haue carried towards me, and the memorie of some benefits that I haue receiued from you, hath sundrie times so affected my heart, that I could not, but in the good remembrance therof, in some measure of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feinednesse, as in respect of God, praise his holie name for those his mercies, and as in regard of you, with earnestnesse pray vnto him, for your prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous estates, and that in the best things especiallie, and as in consideration of my selfe, thinke vpon some good meane, wherby I might at the least shew my selfe, in some sort mindfull of, and thankefull for
<pb facs="3"/> the same. Whatsoeuer I write in this behalfe, I vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it (I humblie thanke God for it) not vaine glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouslie to boast, before God or men, in anie thing I haue done, for I know &amp; feele in my selfe, that (ouer and besides my grosse &amp; greeuous iniquities) euen in the best seruices that euer I performed in pietie towards God, or in charitie towards his people, there was by reason of mine owne corruption, and the imperfections that through the same did cleue thervnto, matter sufficient inough, in truth to abase and to humble me indeed: neither yet as cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to craue dailie and new kindnesses (a vice too common in this corrupt age) the Lord hauing bin pleased in that behalfe, to bestow vpon me more simplicitie, than by fawning flatterie to fetch from my freends, anie thing that might satisfie large af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, or releeue present want. But to these ends I protest, and that in singlenesse of heart, haue I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the same, namelie that all my christian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and amongst others your honour and worships especiallie might be assured, that the good you haue doone me, though at the first it might seeme to be cast away, in as much as present testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my gratefull minde were not then prest and readie, hath not yet vtterlie beene lost, because now at the length God hath inabled me by some small meanes to declare the contrarie: and againe, that I my selfe feeling my selfe now and then, by Gods grace I doubt not (for as I know, so I freelie confesse, that in my flesh, that is to say, in my selfe, dwelleth nothing that is good) stirred vp to such holie duties, might receiue, not in the things as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by my self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, but as they are graces of God, flowing from his goodnesse, and wrought by his word and spirit, both some comfort in the daies of
<pb facs="3"/> my great greefe and heuinesse of heart, and some incouragement to goodnesse also, when mine owne dulnesse and backwardnesse to the same, not onelie ariseth vp in me, but standeth against it, as with force and might, to stop and hinder me therein. In regard whereof also, I doo at this time humblie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and present vnto you (right honorable &amp; right worshipfull) togither, first a sound discourse or two, which that learned man M. Beza wrote, and I long ago translated, and withall a short summe, that I my selfe penned heeretofore, and haue inlarged againe all of them touching that great question of the Lords supper. For that woorthie mans woorthie works, I dare protest and auer, that if the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, either of the man, or matter, or maner, may purchase a frutefull commendation, and procure fauorable acceptation (with them that feare God I meane, &amp; loue his truth sincerelie) it shall not want either the one or the other. For as concerning the writer himselfe, he is one of the woonders &amp; woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the world at this day, a man of rare parts euerie maner of way (whatsoeuer some, either of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in themselues, or pride of themselues, barke out against him to the contrarie) whether we respect sound knowledge and iudgement, in the toongs and trueth of God, or faithfull paines, and frutefull trauels in his ministerie and place. And as for the worke, it concerneth a great ground of our christian faith, and the same controuerted, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie betweene the superstitious papists and vs, in the question of transubstantiation, but with such also as in the common profession of Gods holie word and religion, we charitably take for our brethren, thogh otherwise in this point, ouershot as we say, &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seene also. The maner of handling is deepe &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found,
<pb facs="4"/> and not shallow or meane, after the maner and dealing of other men, there being for the more full explication of the question, deducted and laid out, sundrie of the fundamentall points and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our christian faith, and namelie touching the seuerall and distinct natures of God and man, and the personall vnion of them in our sauiour Christ. But for mine owne I mind not to say much, speciallie as in commendation therof. That which I thinke, I will plainelie expresse, and protest also, namelie that as nothing of mine, is in anie respect meet, to behold the light of this learned age, both by reason of mine owne wants &amp; insufficiencie, and also by means of the great ripenesse of knowledge and iudgement, that God hath shed abrode into the hearts of manie men: so I confesse my selfe &amp; my writings, much more vnwoorthie, either the same day to be named with that woorthie man of the world, or anie maner of way to be ioined with his. And yet if the church approoue that which I doo, and the godlie receiue some profit by it to spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all edification, I shall much reioice therin, not as in respect of that I haue doone (for I acknowledge my selfe to haue nothing saue that which I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) but as in regard of the good effects, that it hath through Gods almightie and secret blessing, brought foorth in the hearts of them, that haue bin or shalbe acquainted therewith: in which treatise, I haue speciallie laboured two things. First in the daies of so great blindnesse and ignorance, amongst the multitude and common sort of people, as now preuaileth, to instruct the simple as much as I could in the sound knowledge of these most holie myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that so neither with the idle and vnskilfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of their owne heads, nor with the superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="4"/> and erronious opinions of other men concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the same, cast abrode into the world as baits to catch them, they might be deceiued, and carried away into vntruth, as if it were with a violent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest &amp; whirlwind. And secondlie, that in the midst of so great and generall carelesnesse, of fitting and preparing men for such woorthie graces, as be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and offered there (howsoeuer a common corruption that way, hath almost carried all away) I might at the least, by reaching them my weake hand and feeble arme, if not altogither pull some out of that puddle, and so bring them to more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and sanctified vse of these pledges of Gods grace, and their faith in the same, yet let them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my loue and sound affection for the effecting thereof to my vttermost. How I haue pursued these points, and atteined that I aimed at, let the godlie iudge, to whose good censures, I doo willinglie sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my selfe, &amp; all things that shall come from me praieng charitable construction in that I haue doone, and brotherlie admonition if anie thing I haue failed. How it shall preuaile, either with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie or anie I know not: the gratious issue and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing thereof I leaue to the Lord, who if our sinnes hinder not, standing betweene him &amp; vs, as a huge and high wall, can and will no doubt make it effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall in the minds of manie, to their spirituall good. But if your honor (good madame) and you (right worshipfull and my verie good freends) togither with them that depend vpon you, and belong vnto you, may reape christian instruction, and holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thereby, and hauing faith &amp; a good conscience in all things, may by this and other holie meanes gratiouslie grow, and mightilie continue, with the increaces of God, euen vnto the fruition of eternall
<pb facs="5"/> life at the last through Christ, I shall haue that, which I greatlie wish &amp; desire, and shall thinke my poore paines well satisfied &amp; answered, in the good that shall light vpon them, whom I doo (as dutie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so requireth) vnfeinedlie both reuerence and loue in Iesus Christ. Thus humblie praieng pardon of my boldnesse for this dedication, and earnestlie crauing acceptation of my simple trauels, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that accustomed courtesie that you are woont to shew to them, that come to shroud themselues vnder you, I doo in the most dutifull maner that I may or can for this present time end. <hi>At London the sixt of this Februarie:</hi> 1587.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your honors and vvorships alvvaies duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and bounden in Christ Iesus</hi> T.W. <hi>the Lordes vnvvoorthie seruant.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>