<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Readers.</title>
           <author>Crowley, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109120_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19670</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6093</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109120</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Readers.</title>
                 <author>Crowley, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A setting open of the subtyle sophistrie of Thomas VVatson Doctor of Diuinitie : which he vsed in hys two sermons made before Queene Mary, in the thirde and fift Fridayes in Lent anno. 1553. to prooue the reall presence of Christs body and bloud in the sacrament, and the Masse to be the sacrifice of the newe Testament, written by Robert Crowley clearke. Seene and allowed according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Crowley, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 209, 1, 188, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing occasion oftentymes to be in place where suche as are not yet perswaded that the Popes Church can erre, haue bene bolde to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their minds fréely, affirming that the doctrine which the Protestants teache, is erronious and false, especially concerning the presence of Christ in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his body and bloud, and the sacrifice of the Masse: I haue perceyued, that the same haue bene chiefely perswaded &amp; stayed by these two Sermons, made by Doctor Watson in the first yere of Quéene Maries reigne. I haue therefore wyshed, that some man of lyke learning, would haue published in print, an answere to those Sermons: that thereby such as haue bene dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by the subtiltie thereof, might by the plaine and simple aunswere, be brought to the knowledge of the truth, which no doubt the greatest number of them would embrace, if they might once be brought to sée it. Yea, I know some of them doe hunger and thirst, to sée what may be sayde to the contrarie of that which they are yet perswaded in, by that which séemeth to them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunswerable.</p>
   <p>But whiles I thus wyshed with my selfe, many yeares are passed by: and I feare me, manye soules haue perished, being blinded by the subtilty of these Sermons. And hitherto, I can not vnderstand that any man hath once purposed to aunswere them.</p>
   <p>Although therefore, I be of many the most vnméete, and of some most dispised, accounted and reported to be none of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet rather then the prowde Philistine should still blaspheme the God of Israell, and defie his whole armie, no man being so hardie as to buckle with him, I haue in the courage and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of dispised Dauid, taken in hande to fight the combat with him, and doe not doubt by the helpe of Dauids God, eyther to cause him to yéelde, or to lye headlesse, dispised and forsaken euen of his owne sort and folowers.</p>
   <p>Some man will say (peraduenture) that it is but a vayne bragge to make such a chalenge, knowing that the aduerse party
<pb facs="5"/> may not without lycence encounter with mée: and if he shall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne lycence, yet shall not his doings be suffered to come to light, vnlesse the same shall be lyked by such as fauour my cause. For my part, I wishe that it were as frée for him to replye to thys mine aunswere and to publishe the same, as it is for mée to aunswere his Sermons: and I know that if he be able and wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to replie, he can neyther lack libertie so to doe, nor meanes to publish it when it is done. This obiection therfore is but vaine.</p>
   <p>But that you may haue some vnderstanding of that which I haue done in this aunswere (deare Christians) and with better will read it thorowe and weigh it: I will in fewe wordes declare the effect of my doing therein. First, I haue faythfully reported the Sermons, as they are to be séene in his printed Copie: alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or chaunging no one sillable or letter, but such onely as doe manifestly appéere to be faultes escaped by the ignoraunce or negligence of the Printer. Secondly, I haue weighed and considered the Authorities that he hath alledged with their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances: setting downe the same in wryting to be séene, that you may in the feare of God, weigh the same also, and iudge whether he haue applied them aright or not. And thirdly, I haue aunswered, by the lyke, or greater Authoritie, all that he hath laboured to confirme by Authoritie: eyther of the scriptures or auncient fathers.</p>
   <p>The Lorde Iesus direct you all in the reading of these Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and aunswere: that you may vnderstande and embrace the truth of the matters in controuersie, &amp; in life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, glorifie him that hath with his spirite of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort caused mée to go thorow wyth this aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere: notwithstanding the manifold waies that Sathan hath sought to cause me to cast it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side. Fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christ Robert Crowley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>