<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109966_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20900</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7275</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109966</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A breefe aunswere of Iosephus Quercetanus Armeniacus, Doctor of Phisick, to the exposition of Iacobus Aubertus Vindonis, concerning the original, and causes of mettalles : Set foorth against chimists. Another exquisite and plaine treatise of the same Iosephus, concerning the spagericall preparations, and vse of minerall, animall, and vegitable medicines. Whereunto is added diuers rare secretes, not heeretofore knowne of many. By Iohn Hester, practicioner in the spagericall arte</title>
                 <author>Du Chesne, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hester, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 61, 5 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the gentle <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xperientia stultorum gubernatrix,</hi> is with some held as a Prouerbe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenticke: but in mine opinion, (freendlie Reader) they are most fooles that want it. For without it howsoeuer otherwise well read, a man can say no more in Artes then the great Trauailer, (who in some fewe daies, hauing coasted the worlde in a Card-makers shop) can discourse directlie eyther of this or that, but must be faine if fault be found, to confesse his owne ignoraunce, and blame the Maps falsenes; yet as wee haue with vs a custome, when we heare thinges incredible spoken from a far, to say, it is better beleeuing it, then going the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to disproue it: so are there many, yea the most, which will not stick to talke most, that least of all aduenture in this perrilous passage to Science, and yet the onely directed path called experience: for besides the daily cares, nightly watchings, external woundes, internall woes, deforming of members, disquieting of minde, debilitie of senses, and losse of sight, with infinite other incombrances, which lie as Adders in his way that treads this walke, he shall on each hand be terrified with Legions of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirits, deluding flatterers, of tame beastes by the Philosopher held the most deuouring, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious slaunders of wilde beasts, the most impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, selfe tryall hath taught mee this since I first
<pb facs="3"/>
vndertooke to search the secrets of Earthes flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bountie, and her Minerall vaines, I haue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all the vnpleasant sharpnes that experiences pathes yeeldes, and endured euery enuie that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice could deuise: yet the end I hope for, beeing the benefite of this Weale publique, in which I lyue, a willing, (though vnworthy member) animates me in despight of enuie, to professe the neuer dying labors of my ouer-wearied powers, to those that are willing to buy, (for nothing in a manner) what I haue obtained with my precious life. O the God that rewardeth all things, &amp; will in my Redeemer, accept (I doubt not) of my intent, hath secretlie summoned my soule to discharge the fruites of her experience.</p>
   <p>I haue translated this insuing worke, and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten these present lines for thy good (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.) On these flowers let no Spyder presume, for they are ful of vertue, that makes enuy mute. They are free gifts, and shoulde bee gratefully accepted, the best intend the best, the worst I write not for.</p>
   <p>Such faultes gentle Reader, as by vnskilfulnesse of the Printer in this argument, and want of my continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all presence in the printing, which are in any place to be found, J pray thee courteously to pardon, and freendly to correct.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>