<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶A generall preface / to be rehersed in the begynnynge of euery sermon, made vp∣on the Lordes prayer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109272_Bo1_4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5993</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109272</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶A generall preface / to be rehersed in the begynnynge of euery sermon, made vp∣on the Lordes prayer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cathechismvs, that is to say, a shorte instruction into Christian religion for the synguler commoditie and profyte of childre [n] and yong people : Set forth by the mooste reuerende father in God Thomas Archbyshop of Canterbury, primate of all England and Metropolitane</title>
                 <author>Evangelisch-Lutherische Kirche in Ansbach (Principality)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos)</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lynne (Lin), Walter (Gualter, Wouter van)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, xix, 17, xx-lxxi, lxxiiii-ccxxxii, ccxxiii-ccxxxviii, ccxxxviii-ccxliii, 2 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="general_preface">
   <pb facs="167"/>
   <head>¶A generall preface / to be rehersed in the begynnynge of euery sermon, made vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lordes prayer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E haue learned heretofore good childrē in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Crede, what we ought to beleue, and in the ten cōmaūdemē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes what we ought to do, but we can neyther beleue nor do as we ought to do, excepte the holy gost worke with in vs, bothe a true faith &amp; also a dewe obedyence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God and his lawe. For faith is the gyfte of God, and all good thinges commeth from the father of lightes.<note place="margin">Iacob. i▪</note> Therefore we must nedes aske and craue these benefites at his hande whiche on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the gyuer of theim. For so Christ saieth, that God the father
<pb n="cxlv" facs="167"/>
wyll gyue to vs his children all thinges, so that we sue to hym for theim.<note place="margin">Psalm. i.</note> And the prophet Dauyd saieth. Cal vpon me in the daye of thy trouble, and I shal deliuer the, and thou shalt glorifye me. Also our Sauioure Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maūdeth vs to do y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, sayng.<note place="margin">Mat. vii. Iere. xxix. Mar. vii. Luke. xi. Ioh. xvi.</note> Aske and you shal haue, seke and you shall fynde, knocke and the dore shall be opened vnto you. Now therfore, seyng that we haue learned what we shoulde beleue and do, it is most necessary for vs, to cal for gods grace with most feruēt and ernest prayers, that we may be able to performe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thinge whiche we are bounde to do. For our sauiour Christ hath promised vs, that what soeuer we aske the father in his name, he wyll gyue it vs. Also he saieth,<note place="margin">Ioh. xiii▪</note> that what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we aske, yf we beleue, we shal
<pb facs="168"/>
receaue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. Wher is to be no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, that yf we wyll obteyne oure requestes, we must aske in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of Christ, and also trust assuredly, that for Christes sake our praiers shal be heard. To aske in Christes name is to aske accordynge to his wil, that is to say, to aske y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which he hath commaunded.</p>
   <p>Therefore when we praye we may saye thus. O God our father and the father of our Lorde Iesu Christ, which art in heuē, I durst not of myne awn head be so bold, to come vnto thy most highe and excellent maiestye to desyer any thyng of the, but thy welbeloued sonne our Lord Iesus Christ hath commaūded me so to do, and only in his name and at his commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente am so bolde. Therfore yf thou hear me, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> hearest thy dearly beloued sonne oure Lorde Iesus
<pb n="cxlvi" facs="168"/>
Christ. And yf thou heare me not, thē thou hearest not Iesus Christ him selfe, who hath sent me to the, and hath commaunded me to aske in his name. Of this prayer made in fayth, speaketh saincte Iohn in his epistle saying. This trust we haue in God, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> when we aske any thynge accordinge to his will, he doth heare vs.</p>
   <p>Therefore we shoulde stedfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleue that God doth heare our prayer. For he that beleueth not, he shall obtayne nothynge. And therefore Christe saith. If you beleue, you shall obtayne. And to thentent,<note place="margin">Mark. xi.</note> that we should beleue &amp; surely thynke, that we be herde, he hath promysed to graunt what soeuer we aske in his name. And agayne to thentent that we shuld knowe and be suer, that we praye accordyng to his wil, he hymselfe
<pb facs="169"/>
hath taught vs, howe &amp; what we should praye and aske. Therfore it is not in our lybertye, whether we wil praie or not, but by goddes commaundement, we be boūde to praye, as you haue hearde in the seconde commaundement. Now therefore with all dilygence lerne good children, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy prayer of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord, which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greate doctour and our Lorde Iesus Christ taught vs hymselfe, saying to his disciples. Ye shall praye after this maner.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="cxlvii" facs="169"/>
      <figure>
</figure>
      <note place="margin">Math. vi. Luke▪ xi.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ure father which art in heauē / halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed be thy name. Thy kyngdome come. Thy wil be don in earth as it is in heauē. Geue vs this day our daily bread. And forgeue vs our trespaces
<pb facs="170"/>
as we forgeue them that trespace against vs. And suffre vs not to be led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptacion. But dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from euyl. Amen. This good children is the prayer of the Lorde, whiche althoughe it be short, yet it conteyneth moste great and weyghty matters, suche as neyther aungell nor man, nor other creature, was able so pitheli to cōprise in so few wordes. For in this prayer Christ oure Lord tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to aske all thynges, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be cōmaūded vs in the ten cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes, or promysed vs in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> article of our Crede. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good children you ought to endeuour your selfes, not only to lerne without y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> boke this most ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prayer, taught vs by Christes owne mouthe, our great master &amp;
<pb n="cxlviii" facs="170"/>
teacher, but also you ought to giue dilygence to vnderstāde &amp; iustlye to weye euery worde of so great a master, that when you be apposed herein, you maye be able to make a directe answer, and also in tyme to come to teache your childrē the true vnderstāding of this praier, as you youre selfes be nowe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed. For what greater shame can ther be before God and man, thā whā in our mouthes we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse our selues to be christē men, and to knowe what we ought to beleue, and howe to lyue, and yet to be ignoraunt what thynge we ought to aske of God, and after what maner we ought to aske those thinges, whiche he of his goodnes hath promised most lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely to gyue vs.</p>
   <p>Or els yf we knowe howe and what to aske, yet of neglygence,
<pb facs="171"/>
slouth or contempt of God, not to aske the same in dede in suche wise as we ought to do. Specially se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the propre office of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten man is, to call vpon God in all his busynes and necessities, to gyue thankes, and euermore to honoure his mooste blessed name with moost hye laudes and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Wherfore good children for asmuche as God hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to resorte to hym boldelye, and to moue oure selues to him in all our troubles and aduersities, and hathe promysed that he wyll heare our praiers, delyuer vs, and graunt vs al thinges necessary for our saluatiō, let vs not refuse this honoure that we be called vnto, let vs not refuse this remedie, helpe, ayde and succoure that is freelye offered of oure most mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to all his children that wyll
<pb n="cxlix" facs="171"/>
call vpon his name. For this is a sacrifice most acceptable to God, wherwith he is moost higly hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and pleased.</p>
   <p>Wherfore good children bothe daily and hourely accustome your selfes, euen from your tender age, to praye to your heauenly father, for all thinges necessarie. Offer vp vnto hym at youre vprisinge and downe leyinge, before youre meales and after your meate, this sacrifice of your lyppes, the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō of praise and thankes gyuing, wourshippe hym at al tymes with the frankyncense of thys prayer taught vnto you by your sauiour Christ. The perfume wherof, yf it be cast into the burnynge coles of faythe and charitie, it perceth the cloudes, and is so swete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant vnto God, that it vanishethe not awaye, vntyll it haue obteined
<pb facs="172"/>
that thynge, that it was sente for. For it is writen, that the prayer of a iust man can do much with god, and the eyes of the Lord do looke vpō the rightuous, and his eares be opened to heare theyr prayers.</p>
   <p>Wherfore studye you, to be the children of God, and there is no doubte, but youre heauenly father wyll gyue all good thinges, which you shal desire of him, in the name of his sonne and your brother Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, to whom be all glorye nowe and euer. Amen.</p>
   <p>This preface must be reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed before euery sermon of the Lordes pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>