<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all true Christen readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1541</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109263_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19466</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5888</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109263</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all true Christen readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutacion of that treatise, which one Iohn Standish made agaynst the protestacion of D. Barnes in the yeare. M.D.XL : Wherin, the holy scriptures (peruerted and wrested in his sayd treatise) are restored to their owne true vnderstonding agayne by Myles Couerdale</title>
                 <author>Coverdale, Miles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Froschauer, Christoph 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Switzerland--Zurich</pubPlace>
                    <date>1541</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>208 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="101"/>
   <head>To all true Christen readers.</head>
   <p>Faynt not thou in faith (deare reader) nether waxe colde in loue and charite / though the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of gods worde be gathered together and growne in to such swarmes. Be thou strong in the lorde / and in the power of his might. And let it not discorage the / that the sayd worde is so litle in the estimacion of the world / so great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly despised / so sore persecuted / so wickedly peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / wrested and belyed / so vnthankfully receaued / so shamefully denied / and so slouthfully folowed.</p>
   <p>Arme thy selfe therfore with the confortable en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>samples of the scripture / And as touchinge those ioly Nimrottes that persecute gods worde / hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it out of euery corner / whetting ther swerdes and bendyng their bowes agaynst it / Be thou su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / that the god of oure fathers Abraham / Isaac and Iacob shall do with thē as he euer was wont to do with tirauntes in times past. Thou seist tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row out the stories of the holy byble / how that like as he turneth some of their hartes from crueltie to mekenesse / Euē so with death / with fyre / with wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / and with such other his plages destroyeth he them that will nedes despise his warninge / Yee breaketh their bowes in peces / and killeth thē with ther own swerdes. As for Iamnes and Iambres those wicked sorcerers and couetous chaplens that teach cōtrary to gods worde / and dissuade the greate mē of the world frō it / Their owne wrestin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and belyeng of it must nedes cōfound thē / For
<pb facs="102"/>
though ther be many that resist the truth / yet whan it is uttered and commeth to light / their madnesse (as. S. Paul saieth) shall be manifest vnto all men. And as Moses rodd deuoured their roddes in the Kynges presence / So likewise the same pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of scripture that they alledge for their wicked purpose / shall destroye their false doctryne in the face of the world. Yee euen as litle honestie as the papistry hath gotten by wresting of (Tu es Petrus et cet.) so small profit are they like to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue for belyeng of other textes. Nether is it to be feared / but god will do for one parte of his worde asmuch as for another / whan he seith his tyme.</p>
   <p>Concernyng those bely beastes / that (for no cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement ner promes of god / for no example / warnyng ner exhortacion) will be counsayled / but still blaspheme his holy worde thorow their vngodly conuersacion / let not that withdrawe the from the waye of righteousnesse. Loue not thou Christ the worse / though Iudas be a traytoure. Sett not thou the lesse by his wholsome doctrine / though dogges turne to their vomite / and though swine walow in their stinking mire agayne.</p>
   <p>I knowe (gentle reader) that to all true Christē hartes / it is a great tentaciō / to se gods holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de either persecuted / belyed / or vnthankfully recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But first remembre thy selfe well by the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyse of all stories / whan was it without persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion? Whan was there not one tyraunt or other / that exercised all his power / strength / witte / and
<pb facs="102"/>
counsaill against it? Whan were the childrē of Is<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael without some bloudy Edomites / Egiptians Assirians / Babilonians / Philistines / or other?</p>
   <p>Secōdly / Whan was not gods worde belied / peruerted or euell spoken of by one false Prophet or other? Were there not heretikes and flatringe chaplens in all ages / that withdrue men from the trueth / and misreported the straight waies of the lord? Thirdly / whan were there not some multitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / that pretēding a loue toward Christes word / did but folow him for their own belies sake? whan was the sede of Christes word sowē / but some par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of it fell vpō the stony ground where it withred / and among the thornes that choked it vp?</p>
   <p>Wherfore seynge thou art compased aboute with so great a nombre of witnesses / <note place="margin">Heb. xij</note> that is to saye / with the ensamples of so many godly and holy mē / which not onely dyd chose rather to suffre aduersite with the people of god then to enioye the pleasures of synne for a season / but also eschued false doctryne and brought forth allwaye good workes in their liuinge / folowe thou the same tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / folowe thou them (I saye) as thou seist they folowed Christ / and no farther. And as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge anye maner of doctryne / beleue no man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out gods worde / acording as. S. Hierome counceleth the. In Epistolam ad Gal. ca. v. For certaine it is / that like as many tymes thou shalt spie euen great faultes in the conuersaciō of gods electe / so readest thou of very few teachers sens the
<pb facs="103"/>
Apostles tyme / which haue not erred (and that grossely) in sondry thinges.</p>
   <p>Wherfore whom so euer thou hearest teach / preach or wryte / or whose bokes so euer thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest / trye them by gods worde / whether they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable ther to or no. Whan thou knowest them (I saye) and art certayne and sure by Christes doctryne / that they are false / sedicious or abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable / then hold them accursed / avoyde them utter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / eschue them in anye wise / and geue ouer thy sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe to the wholsome hearing and readinge of the scripture. But so / that thou be sober and discrete in the knowlege and vse therof / And that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the true faith and beleue of Christ / thy hart mouth and dede go together / and that thou cōsent to none opinion contrary to the same / That god maye haue the prayse / and thy neghboure be edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all thy conuersacion. So doyng / thou shalt not onely stoppe the mouth of euell speakers / but also allure and prouoke other men to be frutefully geuē to faith and good workes / and to helpe (with such their vnfained faith and godly liuinge) that the tabernacle of god maye be set vp againe. The grace of our lorde Iesus Christ be with us all. Amen.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>
         <pb facs="103"/>Iacobi. iij.</bibl>
      <q>Yf ye haue a bytter Zele / and there be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions in youre hartes / make no boast / nether be lyars agaynst the trueth.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>