<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull M. George Trenchard Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iustices of the peace, in the County of Dorset, and one of the depu∣ties Lieuetenants of the same sheyre. W. Chub wisheth the plenty of Gods graces in Christe Iesu.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109852_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18708</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5212</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull M. George Trenchard Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iustices of the peace, in the County of Dorset, and one of the depu∣ties Lieuetenants of the same sheyre. W. Chub wisheth the plenty of Gods graces in Christe Iesu.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two fruitfull and godly sermons : preached at Dorchester in Dorsetshyre, the one touching the building of Gods temple, the other what the temple is</title>
                 <author>Chub, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull M. George Trenchard Esquire, one of <hi>her Maiesties Iustices of the peace, in the</hi> County of Dorset, and one of the depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Lieuetenants of the same sheyre. W. Chub wisheth the plenty of Gods graces in Christe Iesu.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great zeale of good King <hi>Iosias,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. King. 22.</note> and the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler care he had in repai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the Temple of God, &amp; maintaining true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, was not onely prophesied by <hi>Id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> 300. yeeres before his byrth, but is now remēbred many hundred yeeres after his death, as a most worthy presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for all godlye and well affected mindes, for in him was first found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, in disbursing money toward the building therof, then wisedom in appointing godly ouerseers to see it well doone, and last of all care, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing skilfull workmen to doo it, the which godly disposition of his, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
<pb facs="4"/> the very fruits of a good mind in asmuch as he wold willingly haue the place erected, wherein the name of God myght bee glorified, and hys lawes &amp; statutes read and exercised, and the people of God taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed: such dispositions are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry badges and shewes of a feeling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and a godly setled minde.</p>
   <p>I may think no lesse in you (right worshipfull) but as a seconde <hi>Iosias,</hi> haue endeuoured your selfe very care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully for the erecting of gods glory in the Towne of Dorchester, my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue towne, in that you haue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ben willing for the exercising of preaching in the same towne, but haue offred your liberality for the fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thering, continuing, and establishing, thereof, to the great comfort of the towne, &amp; no les ioy to the borderers. By occasion whereof, I was not onely moued with a comfortable minde for my natiue country, to see the prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of so good a purpose, but was
<pb facs="4"/> also bent vpon the same argument to preach these two Sermons following, which as well in thankfulnes for your proceedinges, as in signification of mine vnfained goodwyll, I humbly present vnto your worship, beseech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to allow of the slender gyfte, and to couer the vnwoorthines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with your accustomed clemency. And therein, as I shall think my pains cased, my works bettered, and my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell well bestowed, euen so shall I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade my self, to be much bound vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to your worship for your louing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation. And for the same shal con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue mine vnfained hart in faithfull prayers vnto GOD, to blesse your dayes with the increase of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, to whose mercifull tuition I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your vvorships poore coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman ready at commandement.</hi> W. Chub. Minister.</signed>
      <dateline>VVritten in Froome zel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <date>the xii. of December. 1585.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>