<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109237_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04658</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14780</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109237</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nevv inne. Or, The light heart : A comoedy. As it was neuer acted, but most negligently play'd, by some, the Kings Seruants. And more squeamishly beheld, and censured by others, the Kings subiects. 1629. Now, at last, set at liberty to the readers, his Maties seruants and subiects, to be iudg'd. 1631. By the author, B. Ionson</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord <hi>FRAMPVL,</hi> a noble Gentleman, well edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and bred a Schollar, in <hi>Oxford,</hi> was married yong, to a vertuous Gentlewoman, <hi>Sylly's</hi> daughter of the South, whose worth (though he truly enioy'd) hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer could rightly value; but, as many greene Husbands (giuen ouer to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauagant delights, and some peccant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of their owne) occasion'd in his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer louing wife, so deepe a melancholy, by his leauing her in the time of her lying in, of her second daughter, shee hauing
<pb facs="5"/>
brought him only two daughters, <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and <hi>Laetitia:</hi> and (out of her hurt fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) interpreting that to bee a cause of her husbands couldnesse in affection, her not being blest with a sonne, tooke a resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her selfe, after her <hi>months</hi> time, and thanksgiuing ritely in the <hi>Church,</hi> to quit her home, with a vow neuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, till by reducing her <hi>Lord,</hi> she could bring a wish'd happinesse to the family.</p>
   <p>He, in the meane time returning, and hearing of this departure of his <hi>Lady,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, though ouer-late, to resent the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he had done her: and out of his cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braind resolution, entred into as solemne a quest of her. Since when, neither of them had beene heard of. But the eldest daughter <hi>Frances,</hi> by the title of <hi>Lady Frampul,</hi> enioyed the state, her sister be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lost yong, and is the sole relict of the family.</p>
   <div n="1" type="act">
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <head>Act 1. <hi>Here begins our</hi> Comoedy.</head>
      <p>This <hi>Lady,</hi> being a braue, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull <hi>Lady,</hi> and enioying this free, and plentifull estate, hath an ambitious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to be esteemed the Mistresse of many seruants, but loues none. And hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a famous new-Inne, that is kept by a merry <hi>Host,</hi> call'd <hi>Good-stock,</hi> in <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> inuites some <hi>Lords,</hi> and Gentlemen to wait on her thither, as well to see the fashions of the place, as to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues merry, with the accidents on the by. It happens, there is a melancholique <hi>Gentleman,</hi> one Master <hi>Lovel,</hi> hath beene lodg'd there some dayes before in the <hi>Inne,</hi> who (vnwilling to be seene) is sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd by the <hi>Lady,</hi> and inuited by <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> the <hi>Ladies</hi> Chamber-maid, who is
<pb facs="6"/>
elected <hi>Gouernesse</hi> of the <hi>Sports,</hi> in the <hi>Inne,</hi> for that day, and instal'd their <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lovel</hi> is perswaded by the <hi>Host,</hi> and yeelds to the <hi>Ladies</hi> inuitation, which concludes the first <hi>Act.</hi> Hauing reueal'd his quality before, to the <hi>Host.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="act">
      <head>In the second Act.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Prudence,</hi> and her <hi>Lady</hi> expresse their anger conceiu'd, at the <hi>Taylor,</hi> who had promised to make <hi>Prudence</hi> a new suite, and bring it home, as on the <hi>Eue,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this day. But, hee failing of his word, the <hi>Lady</hi> had commanded a stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of her owne best apparrell to bee brought downe: and <hi>Prudence</hi> is so fitted. The <hi>Lady</hi> being put in mind, that shee is there alone without other company of women, borrowes (by the aduice of <hi>Pru</hi>) the <hi>Hosts</hi> sonne of the house, whom they
<pb facs="7"/>
dresse with the <hi>Hosts</hi> consent, like a <hi>Lady,</hi> and send out the Coachman, with the empty Coach, as for a kinswoman of her Ladiships, Mistresse <hi>Laetitia Sylly,</hi> to beare her company: Who attended with his <hi>Nurse,</hi> an old chare-woman in the <hi>Inne,</hi> drest odly by the <hi>Hosts</hi> councell, is belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be a <hi>Lady</hi> of quality, and so receiu'd, entertain'd, and <hi>loue</hi> made to her, by the yong Lord <hi>Beaufort,</hi> &amp;c: In the meane time, the <hi>Fly</hi> of the <hi>Inne</hi> is discouer'd to <hi>Colonell Glorious,</hi> with the <hi>Militia</hi> of the house, below the stayres, in the Drawer, Tapster, Chamberlaine, and Hostler, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour officers, with the Coachman <hi>Trun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, Ferret,</hi> &amp;c. And, the preparation is made, to the <hi>Ladies</hi> designe vpon <hi>Lovel,</hi> his vpon her, and the <hi>Soueraignes</hi> vpon both.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="act">
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <head>Here begins, at the <hi>third Act,</hi> the <hi>Epita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> or businesse of the <hi>Play.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <hi>Lovel,</hi> by the dexterity, and wit of the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> of the <hi>Sports, Prudence;</hi> hauing two houres assigned him, of free colloquy, and loue-making to his <hi>Misiresse,</hi> one, after Dinner, the other after Supper; The <hi>Court</hi> being set, is demanded by the <hi>Lady Frampul,</hi> what <hi>Loue</hi> is? as doubting if there were any such power, or no. To whom, hee first by definition, and after by argument answeres, prouing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing the effects. of <hi>Loue,</hi> so viuel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, as she, who had derided the name of <hi>Loue</hi> before, hearing his discourse, is now so taken both with the Man, and his matter, as shee confesseth her selfe enamour'd of him, and, but for the ambition shee hath to enioy the other houre, had presently
<pb facs="8"/>
declar'd her selfe: which giues both him, and the <hi>spectators</hi> occasion to thinke she yet dissembles, notwithstanding the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her kisse, which hee celebrates. And the <hi>Court</hi> dissolues, vpon a newes brought, of a new <hi>Lady,</hi> a newer Coach, and a new Coachman call'd <hi>Barnaby.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="act">
      <head>Act <hi>4.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>The house being put into a noyse, with the rumor of this new <hi>Lady,</hi> and there being drinking below in the court, the <hi>Colonel,</hi> Sir <hi>Glorious,</hi> with <hi>Bat: Burst,</hi> a broken Citizen, and <hi>Hodge Huffle</hi> his champion; she fals into their hands, and being attended but with one foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is vnciuilly entreated by them, and a quarrell commenc'd, but is rescued by the valour of <hi>Lovel;</hi> which beheld by the <hi>Lady Frampul,</hi> from the window, shee is
<pb facs="8"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nuited vp, for safety, where comming, and conducted by the <hi>Host,</hi> her gowne is first discouer'd to bee the same with the whole suite, which was bespoken for <hi>Pru:</hi> and she her selfe, vpon examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, found to be <hi>Pinnacia Stuffe,</hi> the <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors</hi> wife, who was wont to be preocupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all his Customers best clothes, by the footman her husband. They are both condem'd, and censur'd, shee stript like a <hi>Doxey,</hi> and sent home a foote. In the <hi>interim,</hi> the second houre goes on, and the question, at sute of the <hi>Lady Frampul,</hi> is chang'd from <hi>loue</hi> to <hi>valour;</hi> which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he receiues his second kisse, and by the rigor of the <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> fals into a fit of melancholy, worse, or more despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate then the first.</p>
      <p>The fifth, and last <hi>Act</hi> is the <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe,</hi> or knit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing vp of all, where <hi>Fly</hi>
         <pb facs="9"/>
brings word to the <hi>Host,</hi> of the <hi>Lord Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts</hi> being married priuately in the new stable, to the suppos'd <hi>Lady,</hi> his sonne; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ch the <hi>Host</hi> receiues as an <hi>omen</hi> of mirt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. But complaines, that <hi>Lovel</hi> is gon to bed melancholique, when <hi>Prudence</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares drest in the new suit applauded by her <hi>Lady,</hi> and employd to retriue <hi>Louel.</hi> The <hi>Host</hi> encounters them, with this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of L. <hi>Beauforts</hi> mariage, which is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the L. <hi>Latimer,</hi> and all the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the house. In this whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, L. <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> comes in, and profes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es it, calls for his bed, and bride-bowle, to be made ready, the <hi>Host</hi> forbids both, shewes whom hee hath married, and discouers him t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> be his <hi>sonne,</hi> a boy. The <hi>Lord</hi> Bridegrome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, the <hi>Nurse</hi> enters like a franticke bed lem, cries out on <hi>Flie,</hi> sayes shee is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, in her daughter, who is confessed to
<pb facs="9"/>
be the <hi>Lord Frampuls</hi> child, sister to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lady, the <hi>Host</hi> to be their Father. She his wife. He finding his children, bestows them one on <hi>Louel,</hi> the other on the Lord <hi>Beaufort,</hi> the Inne vpon <hi>Flie,</hi> who had beene a <hi>Gipsey</hi> with him, offers a portion with <hi>Prudence,</hi> for her wit, which is refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; and she taken, by the <hi>Lord Latimer,</hi> to wife; for the crowne of her vertue, and goodnesse. And all are contented.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>