<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface. ¶ To the mooste vertuous Ladie and gratious princes Katherine Quene of Englāde, Fraūce and Irelande, her humble seruaunte Sir Anthonie Cope Knyght desyreth longe lyfe wyth health and muche ho∣nour to the pleasure of God.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109096_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19303</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5717</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109096</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface. ¶ To the mooste vertuous Ladie and gratious princes Katherine Quene of Englāde, Fraūce and Irelande, her humble seruaunte Sir Anthonie Cope Knyght desyreth longe lyfe wyth health and muche ho∣nour to the pleasure of God.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly meditacion vpon. xx. select and chosen Psalmes of the prophet Dauid : as wel necessary to al them that are desirous to haue ye darke wordes of the prophet declared and made playn: as also fruitfull to suche as delyte in the contemplatio [n] of the spiritual meanyng of them. Compiled and set furth by Sir Anthony Cope knight</title>
                 <author>Cope, Anthony, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>200 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface. ¶ To the mooste vertuous Ladie and gratious princes Katherine Quene of Englāde, Fraūce and Irelande, her humble seruaunte Sir Anthonie Cope Knyght desyreth longe lyfe wyth health and muche ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the pleasure of God.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He vse of gyuyng gyftes by men to theyr frendes the fyrst day of the newe yere (mooste noble La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and vertuous Quene) hath of longe time continewed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thys Realme of Englande, wyth an opinion that the luckie beginning is a good token of lyke prosperous suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse duryng the rest of the yere. Which maner of presentyng gyftes, as I do ryghte well alowe, if they be gyuen as a declaration of mutuall loue and hertie beneuolence: so the opinion therto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, I thynke not so commendable, whiche is, that the gyft should be a token or presage of good fortune to come: no more then mondayes handsel of a peny gyuen to a poore begger, shoulde be so esteamed, that the happy begynnyng of the weke muste drawe to it also a fortunate ende therof.</p>
   <p>The good intent of the gyuer of the peny: is to releue the poore mans necessitie, not to be an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurie of thinges that shal folowe. So in likewyse ought the newe yeres gyftes to be deliuered, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a testimony of the hertie seruice or louynge myndes of the gyuers. And for so muche as the mooste numbre of the giuers do search to present
<pb facs="3"/> suche thynges as they iudge shoulde be moste ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the receyuers therof: I longe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wyth my selfe what thynge I myght best of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre vnto your grace at thys present, wherein I myght in some parte declare my loyall and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent herte towarde you, of whose heaped goodnes I haue so muche tasted, that I can neuer be able to deserue the thousande parte, but onely wyth my prayer and hertie seruice. At the laste when I consydered your gracious entent and godly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose in the readynge and studie of holy scripture, and the auauncement of the trewe worde of God: I thought I coulde in no thynge do your grace a more pleasaunt seruice, then to make an expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of certeyne psalmes of the noble prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, whose harmonie is so swete &amp; pleasaunt, that the eares of the faythfull, maye scantly therwith be fully satisfied. The poetes faine that Orpheus made so pleasaunt harmonie on his harpe that he caused the beastes and stones dauncing, to folow hym. Theyr meanynge was, that his language was so plesaūt, and his entent so reasonable, that he brought the people to good ciuilitie, whiche be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore were rude and beastly. But our celestial Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus the prophete Dauid hath so sette forth his songes that they haue strength and force to cause men which be carnall and beastly, to become spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and heauenly. Who so wyll learne to geue to God dewe honoure and prayses: maye in them take a perfecte patron. Agayne to gyue thankes for the benefites receyued, to cal for grace, to pray for the deliueraunce from all enemies spirituall
<pb facs="3"/> and temporall, to lyue in the heauenly meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of goddes lawes, to dispise the vanities of this worlde, to become mere spirituall: maye men, in them abundauntly, be instructed. In conclusion there is nothynge necessarie for any christian to do, thynke, or saye, but in them as in a myrroure he maye beholde the perfecte image therof, bisyde the playne prophecienge of Christes cōmyng our very Messias, his natiuitie, passion, death, resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and ascention, as lyuely as they were in colours set forth before oure eyes, wyth so many tropes, figures and allegories, that there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moste no worde whiche lacketh na hidde misterie, as the Apostle Paule sayeth, all thynges happed to them in figure, and were darke and obscure.</p>
   <p>But nowe that the thynges are come whereof it was spoken: the vayle is taken awaye from the face of Moyses Now are fewe thinges leaft vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discussed by good holy fathers, who hauynge a good zeale to bestowe theyr talent of knowledge gyuen them by God, to the profite of his people haue earnestly trauayled in the manifestation of suche secrete and hidde thynges beinge holpen by the holy spirite of God to thachiuing of their gost<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly purposes, whom I hauing very smal learning, but onely to gratifie your mynde and to auoyed idlenes haue folowed, settyng forth a rude expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition (in our maternal tonge) vpon twentie psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes whiche I haue chosen forth, reducynge the same to the kynde or fashion of prayers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatife meditations, whiche I turste your grace of your accustomed and naturall goodnes:
<pb facs="4"/> wyl take in good part, sinse there wanteth in me, not wyll but knowledge to do better. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les I trust (conferring the paraphrase to the text) ye shal haue greate lyghte of the meanyng of the Prophete, and therby fynde his diffuse darke wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des made open and playne. To moue your grace and al other of the flocke of Christ to the reading of psalmes, maye it please you to reade the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the boke of Kynges, where Dauid by play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge on his harpe and syngynge therto expelled from Kynge Saule his father in lawe (for the season whyle he played) the wycked spirite which was entred into hym and sore tourmented hym.</p>
   <p>And thys thynge I truste none wyl iudge to be done by the vertue of the sounde of his harpe, but through the power of the noble Psalmes that he sange playinge theron: whiche Psalmes he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly being inspired with the spirite of God had before made. Muche more maye we thynke and assurdly iudge that for our owne deliueraūce from the power of oure spiritual enemies, God wyl not fayle to sende his holy spirite to assist vs and comforte vs, expellynge vtterly the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the wycked serpent, if we in fayeth er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly and hertely prayinge and trustyng to hym reade or vtter the sayed Psalmes. And I shal praye to God who is the authoure and geuer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all good gyftes, so to illuminate the eyes of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> graces herte, that ye maye proceade in the path o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his lawes wherin you are al readye entred, acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the ardent desyre which ye haue hithert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> had to atteyne to the knowledge of them, so tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/> whē ye shall leaue thys transitorie worlde (whose pleasures in al your time ye neuer esteamed) ye maye ascende to the place prepared for Goddes electe, there to receyue ioyes perdurable worlde wythout ende.</p>
   <figure>
      <head>DIEV · ET · MON · D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>OVT</head>
   </figure>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>