<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>F., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109027_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2045</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109027</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>F., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The other parte of Christian questions and answeares : which is concerning the sacraments, writte [n] by Theodore Beza Vezelian: to which is added a large table of the same questions. Translated out of Latine into Englishe by Iohn Field</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>334 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>¶ <hi>To the Christian</hi> Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, concernyng the words of arte contained in this booke, I muste pray thee to take a litle paines, by the circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to gather the meaning of thē. If I shoulde, as some other haue done, make them speake English, yet if thou be ignorant of the arts, they woulde in myne opinion haue bene as darke to thy vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, and muche darker then they be nowe. And that may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by those curious heads that haue gone about too make Logique speake Englishe, both to the disagracing of it, and also to the lessening of the force and
<pb facs="23"/> signification of those woordes of Art, which al Artes haue &amp; must haue proper and peculiar to them selues: but if thou will marke the matter diligently, that which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before and followeth, it shall bee easie for thee, to vnderstande what the Authour meaneth. In meane tyme, I for my parte haue done the best I can, and will bee glad to learne at the feete of any that shall teach me better. The Lorde Iesus increase our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and giue vs Fayth in him for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell,</salute>
      <date>the 3. of May. 1580.</date>
      <signed>I. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>