<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ANNE, LA∣DY WAINTVVORTH, in∣crease of all true honour and happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Winston, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109731_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73836</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6944</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109731</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ANNE, LA∣DY WAINTVVORTH, in∣crease of all true honour and happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Winston, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seven godlie and frvitfull sermons. The six first preached by Master Iohn Dod: the last by Master Robert Cleaver. Wherevnto is annexed, a briefe discourse, touching, 1. Extinguishing of the spirit, 2. Murmuring in affliction</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 211, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="117"/>
   <pb facs="117"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ANNE, LA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DY WAINTVVORTH, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of all true honour and <hi>happinesse, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, may it please you to take in good worth my bold attempt, in presuming to recommend vnto your fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patronage these Sermōs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Your honours vndeser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued respect of me, made me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to testifie my vnfained thankfulnesse: which I could not imagine how with greater conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie to expresse and manifest, then by taking hold of this present occasion; especially conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that your constant and more then ordinarie pains-taking to heare such holy instructions, is a sufficient argument to euince your loue and liking of the matter therein comprised: and your good regard of the authors (well knowne vnto me) gaue me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ccasion to thinke that their labours, in this sort offering themselues vnto your eye, would
<pb facs="118"/>be no lesse welcome then formerly they haue beene, being in another manner presented vnto your eare.</p>
   <p>Concerning the Tract of Zeale annexed to these Sermons, it is a collection of diuers rules which I heard &amp; read touching that subiect, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally of such as were scattered heere and there in Maister R. <hi>Greenhams</hi> Workes: which being exceeding vsesull, I thought good to gather them into one (with an addition of sundrie prooses of Scripture) for the ease and helpe of those that are well affected, especially of such whose abilitie will not reach to the price of that great volume of M. <hi>Greenhams</hi> labours.</p>
   <p>And thus humbly beseeching your Honour to pardon my boldnesse, and to beare with my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold defects which shall be found in the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of these Sermons, I recommend you to the gratious protection of the Almightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours according to my poore abilitie readie to be commanded, IOHN WINSTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>