<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATER TO
the Christian Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109401_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19220</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5636.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATER TO
the Christian Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Catholike moderator: or A moderate examination of the doctrine of the Protestants : Prouing against the too rigid Catholikes of these times, and against the arguments especially, of that booke called, The answer to the Catholike apologie, that we, who are members of the Catholike, apostolike, &amp; Roman Church, ought not to condeme the Protestants for heretikes, vntill further proofe be made. First written in French by a Catholike gentleman, and now faithfully translated. See the occasion of the name of Huguenots, after the translaters epistle</title>
                 <author>Constable, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 18, 17-68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATER TO
the Christian Readers.</head>
   <head type="sub">AND TO ALL THOSE ESPECIAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
whose hard hap it is, or may be, to be sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
vnto Popery: That by the helpe of this Booke,
and their owne Prayers, they may be deliuered
from the the Euill, when the Priests and Iesuits
would Lead them into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a bold Nation of men (the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
aboue mentioned I meane) slily of late
crept in amongst you (well-meaning and
abused people) whose enticements (as you
know too well) still begin with the Church;
saying you <hi>Protestants</hi> are direct Hereticks,
you haue no Church: Are you therefore reconciled to the
Church? Meaning all this time the <hi>Romane</hi> Church. Had
they fairely meant the Catholike Church, I know no <hi>Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist</hi>
that hath put this Article out of his Creed, <hi>I beleeue in the
holy Catholike Church.</hi> And to say, <hi>I beleeue:</hi> What else im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies
it, but to beleeue himselfe to be of it; else, why his
<hi>Creed?</hi> That therefore you may make one <hi>Romanist</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
all the rest; doe but turne him, that would seduce you,
vnto these two first Chapters; and he shall there finde, that
for those few points of Reformation, both in matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
and Ceremonie, wherein the <hi>Protestants</hi> haue iustly
dissented from the <hi>Papists;</hi> we can be no Heretiques. And
that their owne new Doctors, who boast so much of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,
can no where shew our Doctrine to be sufficiently
condemned, before the time of that fifth Gospell of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> I meane, which ended no more
than some 60 yeeres agoe; the third Chapter will euidently
shew them. And how incompetent a Iudge an Aduersarie is,
and how vnlawfull a Councell that of <hi>Trent</hi> was, the Instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of the fourth and fifth Chapters will euince it. Lastly, that
we Protestants, hauing euer continued true members of the
true, holy, and catholique Church, doe not now need any
Reconciliation to theirs of <hi>Rome,</hi> the last Chapter will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
demonstrate it. Which six Chapters being written by
a Gentleman, who euery where professes himselfe one of
theirs, if they would offer to shift off (as they haue euasions
enow) by saying that what is written in this Booke, is but
the opinion of one Doctor: Loe then, we haue not only the
Authors opinions, but the strength of his reasons to vrge
them withall. All which are so mannerly, so directly, and so
succinctly toucht vpon, and come off so handsomely, as no
man (in my opinion) hath yet said better, that purposed to
say so little.</p>
   <p>To giue you therefore the minde of the Authour in a
word: Nothing was here written, with any intention to
vrge vs Protestants, any whit to depart from our Right in
yeelding to a Reconciliation with them; but to perswade
them rather, to esteeme better of vs: and to demonstrate
withall, that if they will iudge right, they must needs thinke
well. And this is the purpose of the Translator also. To shew
you therefore to vnderstand all this Booke: If the Reader
shall sometimes feele, that this Author now and then giues
the Protestants a light fillip by the way; he shall obserue in
the conclusion, that it was to reach his owne Romanists, a
smarter blow; which is satisfaction enough. And that hee
giues vs any at all, let vs but consider, that the Author
though he were a moderate man, yet that he was withall a
Papist, and it will take away much of the scandall. Lastly,
<pb facs="3"/>
which will giue vs as much aduantage as we can desire from
one man, which is to answer them by one of their owne; this
Gentleman the Author <hi>H. C.</hi> was too well knowne here in
<hi>England</hi> to haue continued a most zealous Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
vntill his dying day, and yet neuerthelesse are all his
Reasons for Moderation, directed to the Papists, as if they
should first begin it; and all his conclusions directly for the
Protestants, as though we should still hold them. Nay and
which is somewhat more; whereas all this is with vs of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi>
common to our Brethren the Protestants of <hi>France,</hi>
yet doth this Booke make more for vs at home, than it doth
for them, for whose sakes it was first written. For though we
haue with them entertained the points of Reformation; yet
haue we not so far receded from the more Primitiue Roman
Church (which he stands for) but that we still retaine more
of the necessarie Ceremonies, Solemnities, and Church Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,
than they of <hi>France</hi> haue done; witnesse his second
Chapter of Ceremonies; which is still for our aduantage.</p>
   <p>As therefore this little Booke hath beene twice already
printed in <hi>France,</hi> which is an Argument of the Protestants
good liking of it there; so hath it foure or fiue seuerall times,
both by Diuines and Gentlemen of our owne Religion, been
translated both into Latine and English, which is a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratiue
Reason to me, how much it hath beene lik'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired.
To saue therefore the labour of writing it out, which I
still obserued, as many desirous to doe as could get Copies
of it, I haue thought fit to let mine be published: desiring all
those that light vpon it, to be as impartiall and charitable, as
the Author himselfe wishes them; which if they be, I hope
well that the strictest need not be offended, and the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded
may reape much benefit by it. Which being my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
desire, I shall euer pray for.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>