<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The testimonies and reportes made of Demosthenes his worthynesse, by diuers learned men in all ages as follovveth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109558_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20143</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6578</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109558</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The testimonies and reportes made of Demosthenes his worthynesse, by diuers learned men in all ages as follovveth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three orations of Demosthenes chiefe orator among the Grecians, in fauour of the Olynthians, a people in Thracia, now called Romania : with those his fower orations titled expressely &amp; by name against king Philip of Macedonie: most nedefull to be redde in these daungerous dayes, of all them that loue their countries libertie, and desire to take warning for their better auayle, by example of others. Englished out of the Greeke by Thomas Wylson doctor of the ciuill lawes. After these orations ended, Demosthenes lyfe is set foorth, and gathered out of Plutarch, Lucian, Suidas, and others, with a large table, declaring all the principall matters conteyned in euerye part of this booke. Seene and allowed according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Demosthenes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 145, 15 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="testimonials">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>The testimonies and reportes made of Demosthenes his worthynesse, by diuers learned men in all ages as follovveth.</head>
   <div type="extract">
      <head>The report of Aristotel.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ristotel</hi> was woont to say, to King Philip, and to Alexander his sonne, that whereas a great sort, had bene hys Scholers, yet had he neuer any one in such admiration, as he had <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> aswell for the greatnesse of his iudgement, as for his temperancie, his grauitie, his promptnesse, hys fréedome of speach to others, &amp; his sufferance in all things. You thinke, saith <hi>Aristotel,</hi> that <hi>Demosthenes</hi> is like vnto <hi>Eubulus, Phrynon</hi> and <hi>Philocrates,</hi> and you thinke to corrupt this man also with mony, who hath bestowed his whole patrimonie vpō the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, both priuately and publikely: and bicause you can do no good with mony, you manace him, that doubteth nothing at all, to die for his Countrie. And if he reproue any thing in your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yngs, you are much agréeued therewith. Whereas he doth not spare the people to tel them of their owne, and feareth them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all. Doe not you sée that he taketh gouernement vpon him, for the loue he beareth to his Countrie, and thinketh that thys charge so taken vpon him, is a certaine schoole as a man woulde saye, of Philosophie, and vertue: the which were not méete to be vsed for gaine, or for the satisfaction of mans coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous desire and lust.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <head>The report of Marcus Tullius Cicero.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>CIcero</hi> in his booke entituled <hi>Brutus,</hi> where he talketh of Orators, and first of the Grecians, as the chiefest aboue all others, after he hath sayde hys minde of a great meany, and
<pb facs="12"/>
was come to talke of <hi>Lysias,</hi> thus he wrate and sayde. At that tyme was <hi>Lysias,</hi> a man not exercised in pleading causes at the barre, but a notable fine and excellent writer, whome a man might almost be bolde to call a perfite Orator. But as for a very perfite Orator in déede, and such a one as wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him at all: <hi>Demosthenes</hi> may easily be sayd to be the man. For in those causes that he wrate, there could be nothing wittily founde out, nothing as a man woulde saye artificially deuised, nothing to be cunningly handled that he did not espie, nothing finely to be sayde, nothing compactly knit togither, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing exactly to be done, that coulde be better pullished or trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer handled: of the other side, nothing could be great, nothing high, nothing adorned eyther with grauitie of wordes or sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, that coulde be more high and loftie. Lykewise in his booke <hi>De Oratore,</hi> he sayth, that <hi>Demosthenes</hi> did not giue place to the Orator <hi>Lysias</hi> in finenesse of witte, nor to <hi>Hiperides</hi> in quickenesse or sharpenesse of vnderstanding, neyther yet to <hi>Aeschines</hi> in smoothnesse and gaynesse of wordes. Manye of his Orations are altogither pure and fine, as against <hi>Lepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> Many altogither graue, as certaine against <hi>Philip.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are partly fine &amp; partly graue, as against <hi>Aeschines de falsa legatione,</hi> &amp; against the sayd <hi>Aeschines</hi> in fauor of <hi>Ctesiphon.</hi> And when he listeth, he vseth the middle kind of eloquence, and leauing that most graue maner, descendeth chiefly to that low and familier kinde of speaking. And as touching exclamations, and crying out against abuses, them he vseth, and doth moste of all occupie in his speaking: when hée vttereth forth the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of grauitie. And a little before, he saith, that he remembreth he did preferre <hi>Demosthenes</hi> a great deale before all others. And in his seconde booke <hi>De Oratore,</hi> he willeth him that shoulde be an Orator to followe <hi>Demosthenes</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> who is graunted to be the chiefest Orator aboue all others. And again he sayth in an other place. None hath bene more graue, none more ware, none more temperate, than this man. Therefore they had néede to be warned by vs, whose vnlearned maner of
<pb facs="13"/>
speach is much knowne abroade, such as eyther desire to bée counted fine Attickes, or else haue a minde to speake Attickly, (<hi>that is to speake purely as the Athenians did</hi>) that they estéeme and honor this man chiefly, than the which I doe thynke that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> it selfe was neuer more Atticke, <hi>that is more pure or more fine,</hi> for they may learne by him, what it is to be Atticke, <hi>that is, pure and fine,</hi> and let them iudge of eloquence, by his might and value, not by their owne weakenesse. For nowe euery bodye praiseth so much, as he thinketh himselfe able by his own force to compasse. In many places else, <hi>Tullie</hi> is full of such large reports, but these may suffice, to shewe his iudgement and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion vpon so famous an Orator as <hi>Demosthenes</hi> was.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <head>Lucian in his Dialogue where he prayseth Demosthenes.</head>
      <p>AMongst other things whereof he speaketh at large, and I haue partly declared the same in the description and setting forth of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> his life according to <hi>Lucians</hi> report: he sayth these few wordes, the which cary great force with them. What other thing hath Fortune giuen to <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> but that which is great and sumptuous? yea what other thing, but that which is most honorable and renowmed? And after this he sayth, who knoweth not what maner of Orator <hi>Demosthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> was, howe he beautified his Orations with wordes and sentences, how he poudred his arguments with the stirring of affections? what brightnesse appeared in his plentyfulnesse and copie? what vehemencie and mightynesse of force? what reuerencie and sparenesse vsed he in his words and sentences? what shift and varietie had he of figures? And therefore <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osthenes</hi> sayde, that he onely amongst all other Orators, vsed the most liuely and naturall speach in his Oration aboue them all, without any hammer worke, or framing his talke with Béetles or Mawles, and so goeth on forth in a large discourse, as partlye elsewhere, somewhat is sayde to that ende.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <head>Dionisius Halicarnasseus.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>DEmosthenes</hi> was counted by the opinion of all the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to bée the most excellent and moste perfite Orator a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them all, as well in copie and cunning, as in finenesse of the Atticke tongue.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <head>Quintilian in his tenth booke De institutione Oratoria.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>QVintilian</hi> in making rehersall whom he woulde haue read chiefly of anye one that should be an Orator: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long speach of others in certaine professions, he commeth to the Orators, and sayth thus. Now followeth a great compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Orators in Athens, amongest whome <hi>Demosthenes</hi> was farre passing the chiefest Orator of them all, and almost the verye lawe of eloquence. So great pith was in him, all things so full and so thicke sette, so fastened with certeyne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nothing idle or superfluous, such a measure of speach, that a man can not tell what is wanting in him, nor yet what is too much. And a little after in matching <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosthenes</hi> togither, he giueth the proper praises to them both, as I haue more largelye declared in the Prologue, and sayth that <hi>Demosthenes</hi> being before <hi>Tullie</hi> hath made him to bée such a one for the most part as he was, and woulde therefore that <hi>Demosthenes</hi> shoulde chiefly be read, or rather learned without booke, and so forth, he goth on heaping vp his praises, as elsewhere I haue shewed.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <head>D. Erasmus vpon the Preface of Demosthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes printed in Greeke.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>DEmosthenes</hi> hath more Arte hid in him than he sheweth at the first sight. For this man as <hi>Demades</hi> the Orator
<pb facs="14"/>
sayde, with an honorable ieast, did write to the water, that is to say, to sober men: neyther can he be vnderstoode of anye, but of those, that are sober and watchfull men. That therefore which <hi>Quintilian</hi> did write of <hi>Cicero,</hi> may be sayde with like reason of <hi>Demosthenes.</hi> Let that man knowe and assure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, to haue profited in eloquence: whom <hi>Demosthenes</hi> hath begoon greatly to please and like. And euen as a péece of worke cunningly painted, doth not greatly please them that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt of the Arte: so that heauenly graue maner and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> the which all eloquent men did alwayes greatly marueyle in him, is not perceyued, but of those that are well practised in the Arte of Rhetoricke, and stored wyth knowledge of hystories. Therefore I shall bée well contented that a childe shall taste of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> but yet I would haue him returne to him againe, and reade him earnestly when he is of better iudgement, that he may perceyue that very Attike swéetenesse, that sounde iudgement, those short argumentes called <hi>Enthymemata,</hi> framed togither with excellent cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: &amp; last of all, that pithinesse and great grauity of his, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull to all men, and not attayned yet vnto by any man. And a goodly exercise it were (the which thing hath bene done by el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der time in <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Virgill</hi>) if any woulde doe the same in <hi>Demosthenes</hi> and <hi>Tullie,</hi> that he might finde by making conference of places, what <hi>Tullie</hi> hath borowed of him, and where our Latin Orator is equall to the Gréeke, and where he passeth him, and where the counterfayting of him, doth alter from the originall. There is nothing in the worlde so méete to perfite a mans iudgement withall. And here I will not spende labor to commende <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> to the setting forth of whose praises worthily, we had néede of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> eloquence: naye there néedeth no eloquence at all to set him foorth, whom all men with one whole consent doe prayse and set vp to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye heauens.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <head>Ludouicus Viues, a Spaniarde and one notably lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in his seconde booke of Rhetoricke.</head>
      <p>THerefore is <hi>Demosthenes</hi> preferred before <hi>Cicero</hi> in the opinion of some men, in that he hideth his Arte, and smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the lesse of Schooles, being more enclined to applye him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to the playne and familiar speache of the vulgar people: than otherwise to write or speake aboue the common capacitie and vnderstanding of men.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <head>Sadoletus in his booke <hi>De liberis rectè instituendis.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>IT will doe good to knowe, and therewithall to haue in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration that vnspeakable pythinesse and vehemencie of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> whose maner of speache séemeth to mée to bée knit togither as though it weare with certaine hookes or links, that if you take awaye neuer so little, the whole disposition and order of the matter must néedes quayle. And so passing fierce is his speache that it is like alwaies to preuaile, and so full and so well stored therewithall, that it is able to ouerthrowe, and so artificiall and cunning, that it is able alwayes to beguyle the aduersaries. And besides this, howe often report is there made in his Oratiōs of auncient things? what choyce of words and sentences? how many exhortations vsed vpon the sodeyne? and as the cause serued both for praise &amp; for honor? that in good reason the eloquence of Gréecelande may be sayde to depende vppon the glorie and honor of this onely man the chiefe and péerelesse Orator in the profession of eloquence aboue al others.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="extract">
      <p>The like opinion had sir Iohn Chéeke Knight of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous man, and sayde plainly that he passed all others, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for learning, witte, and iudgement, but also for his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier and plaine kinde of writing, and was the méetest to bée
<pb facs="15"/>
folowed and studied of all those that would be in déede without colour or painted Arte, such as they woulde séeme in outwarde showe to be reputed and estéemed of others.</p>
      <p>And yet thus much must I saye, after so many speaches vsed of this man, that although nothing can be more excellent than <hi>Demosthenes</hi> Orations: yet in <hi>Demosthenes</hi> there wanteth a great péece of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> himselfe, bicause he is rather knowne now by reading his workes, than by hearing his speach and vtterance, wherein he did chiefly excell, and got thereby the greatest prayse. But to conclude at length, what is he, that euer was taken for wyse and learned, that eyther coulde prayse this man sufficiently, or durst in any poynt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish the glorie of his most famous and worthie renowme? And therefore I will saye of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> as one sayde of <hi>Carthage, Satius est silere quam parúm dicere,</hi> It were better to be silent, or at leastwise to forbeare speaking any more, thā not to vtter at full the iust commendation of so worthy a man. And when all is done, I maye applie <hi>Titus Liuius</hi> saying vppon <hi>Cato,</hi> iustly to <hi>Demosthenes: Hic ille est cuius gloriae nemo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam laudando addidit, ne{que} vituperando quisquam aliquando detraxit.</hi> This is he whose glorie no man hath euer made greater by praysing him, nor yet any hath euer made lesse by dispraysing him. So that he hath bene, is, and will be euer, the honor of learning, the fame of well doing, and the verye patterne of vertue and knowledge for all men liuing, euermore to follow. And as for his faithfull and heartie minde that he did beare to his Countrie, I will giue him none other prayse, than onely set forth those Gréeke verses of <hi>Sophocles</hi> in <hi>Antigona,</hi> the which he himselfe rehearsed in his Oration <hi>De falsa legatione</hi> agaynst <hi>Aeschines,</hi> and shewed to haue euer obserued for his part in the whole course of his lyfe as a very excellent lesson both to himselfe, and to all others that shall beare office or rule in their countrie: the which verses are thus to be englished.</p>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <q>
         <lg>
            <head>A playne declaration of a iust Magistrate and true subiect to his Countrie.</head>
            <l>Mans heart and minde cannot be tryde,</l>
            <l>Nor invvarde thought be fully spyde</l>
            <l>Before he hath, in office beene,</l>
            <l>And of the lavves the force vvell seene.</l>
            <l>Novv then if one, be set in place,</l>
            <l>That shrinkes for feare to shevv his face,</l>
            <l>And vvill not vse his best aduyse,</l>
            <l>The state to saue by lore most vvyse:</l>
            <l>Him doe I novv, and euer shall,</l>
            <l>Of vvicked men, most vvicked call.</l>
            <l>And he againe, that doth his frinde</l>
            <l>Preferre before his Countrie kinde:</l>
            <l>I doe not saye, a friende is hee,</l>
            <l>But him starke naught, count I to bee.</l>
            <l>As for my selfe, (that iudge I call,</l>
            <l>The God on hie, vvho knovveth all)</l>
            <l>If any euill, I happe to see,</l>
            <l>VVhich to the state, may daunger bee,</l>
            <l>That vvill I shevve, vvith heart and minde,</l>
            <l>Fall backe, fall edge, euen as I finde.</l>
            <l>No publyke foe vvill I once take,</l>
            <l>In priuate loue, to be my make.</l>
            <l>For vvell I knovv this Realme shall saue</l>
            <l>All subiects true, euen till their graue.</l>
            <l>And that so long, as state shall stande,</l>
            <l>No friendes can vvant vvithin this lande.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
      <p>Thus much of this worthy and famous Demosthenes, whose name as it is by interpretation, the strength and force of the people: so was he in very deede and by nature, the strong bulwarke, and mighty defence of his most deare natiue Countrie.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>