<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS Reader.</title>
           <author>L., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109939_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06401</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16872</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109939</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS Reader.</title>
                 <author>L., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An easie, certaine, and perfect method, to cure and preuent the Spanish sicknes : Wherby the learned and skilfull chirurgian may heale a great many other diseases. Compiled by Peter Lowe, Arellian</title>
                 <author>Lowe, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS Reader.</head>
   <p>GEntle Reader, I haue taken some paines in making thys booke, to doe the sicke pleasure, and the whole profit, that thereby the diseased may recouer theyr health, and sound men may preserue themselues from thys maladie. And albeit that diuers heretofore of sundry Nations, haue published Treatises of this subiect, whereby at this present many coppies are extant, so it may seeme superfluous to reiterate the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Yet seeing I by mine owne diligent practise, and conference with learned men in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, haue found out, diuers waies to cure this disease, more easie, certaine, and speed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen hath been put in vre by any of this age, and that learned Artists, and skilfull Practitioners in all ages, haue written their seuerall iudgements, almost vpon euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let subiect, I thought it pertinent and necessary for the aduauncement of knowledge, and case of many afflicted with this maladie, to impart my skill herein, for the better instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Common-wealth. For as this disease is dispersed throughout all Nations, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, Citties, townes, and priuate houses, yea, &amp; so many kindes thereof daily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and multiplyed, whereby men that know the nature of the maladie, complexion of the Patient, age, season, climate, and other circumstances in the like case considered, are of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie many times vrged to varie from the common cure, and for the better extirpation of newe sorts hereof, to deuise, vse and apply, new remedies: so it is needfull, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe of the weale publique, enlargement of knowledge, and acquitall of euery mans par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler dutie, whereby he is bound so much as in him lyeth, to aduaunce and further the Common-wealth, to publish his experience, in, and touching the premisses. The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd reasons moouing mee there-vnto, I haue set forth to the view and reading of al men, such knowledge herein, as by long studie and experience I haue gotten: to the intent that a further learning might be added to the Artists skill, and such as haue no learning at all, may be instructed, without any other teaching. As in this subiect I haue manifested my cunning for your benefit, so I purpose heereafter, (if GOD prolong my dayes with hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie successe,) to make you pertakers of my labour in the whole course of Chirurgerie, and my Booke <hi>De partu mulierum:</hi> by whose helpe, I doubt not, but many women shall ease, &amp; shorten their course in trauaile. And thus (gentle Reader) I wish your furtherance of knowledge, both in this, and all other needfull Arts.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>P. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>