<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109521_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17192</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4069</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109521</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A moste sure and strong defence of the baptisme of children, against [the] pestiferous secte of the Anabaptystes. set furthe by that famouse clerke, Henry Bullynger: &amp; nowe translated out of Laten into Englysh by Ihon Veron Senonoys</title>
                 <author>Bullinger, Heinrich</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oswen, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Worcester</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <p>To the reader.</p>
   <p>I haue, good christian reader, alredy proued and set furth these artycles that folow, agaynst these erroneous dyuels the Anabaptistes.</p>
   <list>
      <item>i The spiryt, which repugneth against the spiryt, which speketh in the holy scriptures, is not of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> father of truth but of the deuyl, the father of liyng.</item>
      <item>ii Of the simplicyte and lernyng, that ought to be in godly preachers.</item>
      <item>iii Of the vocatyon and callynge vnto the ministery &amp; offyce of preachinge against them that thrust them selues vnto it, beyng not called.</item>
      <item>iiii Of the vnitie of the church, agaynste the sectes of heretikes.</item>
      <item>v That Christ dyd not suffer onely for originall synne.</item>
      <item>vi That a synner is receyued to grace as often as he repenteth, and that no
<pb facs="3"/> man is without synne.</item>
      <item>vii That saluation &amp; ryghteousnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pēdeth not of our works, but of faith</item>
      <item>viii That the soules, which are departed from the bodye, doo not slepe but lyue in Christ.</item>
      <item>ix That a christian may execute the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of a magystrate.</item>
      <item>x That a christiā magistrate is not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly profytable, but also most necessary to a christian commune weale.</item>
      <item>xi That we ought to be obedient vnto magistrates.</item>
      <item>xii That it is not lawful to resist the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gistrates. which thinges if thou dost reade dilygently, I trust thou shalte be well enarmed against this pestife<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous secte. Beware of them, for they are worse then all other herytyques haue bene, yea, they are renewers of all olde heresyes. So fare ye well.</item>
      <item>And praye to god that all erroneous sectes beyng vanquysshed, his glory may florysh for euer and euer. Amē.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>