<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109324_Fr3_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109324</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and learned vvoorke of chirurgerie, called Chirurgia parua Lanfranci : Lanfranke of Mylayne his briefe: reduced from dyuers translations to our vulgar or vsuall frase, and now first published in the Englyshe prynte by Iohn Halle chirurgien. Who hath thervnto necessarily annexed. A table, as wel of the names of diseases and simples with their vertues, as also of all other termes of the arte opened. ... And in the ende a compendious worke of anatomie ... An historiall expostulation also against the beastly abusers, both of chyrurgerie and phisicke in our tyme: with a goodly doctrine, and instruction, necessary to be marked and folowed of all true chirurgie [n] s. All these faithfully gathered, and diligently set forth, by the sayde Iohn Halle</title>
                 <author>Lanfranco, of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 73, 23, 143, 25, 96, 64 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="66"/>
   <head>The Preface</head>
   <p>But one thyng yet I must warne all yong men of, that will profite
in suche studie as I haue instructed, which is in one pointe to refrain
and discente from the most part of yong men: that is to saye, from ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
and spendyng the time in playe: for in my fantasy, who so euer is
adicte to play &amp; games shall neuer profite in this arte. For thou shalt
fynde it time litle enough for thy study, if thou occupie all thy leysour
from thy maisters or thyne owne busines at thy booke, that as thou
workest or seest thy maister work: so thou maist therwith vnderstand
the reason how, and howe muche suche worke is profytable.</p>
   <p>And hereof assure thy selfe, that if thou haue not as great desyre to
thy boke, as the greatest gamner hath to his game, thou shalte neuer
worthily be called cunnyng in this art. For thou must thynke and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steme
all tyme of leysure from thy worke and busynes, euen loste and
euyl bestowed, in which thou hast not profyted somwhat at thy boke.
Let thy boke therfore, I say, be thy pastyme and game: which (if thou
loue it as thou oughtest) will so delight thee, that thou shalt thinke no
tyme so well bestowed as at it. Yea thou muste desyre it as the childe
doeth his mothers pappe: and so will it nourishe thee, that thou shalt
worthily growe and increace to a worshypfull same of cunnynge and
learnyng.</p>
   <p>And nowe whatsoeuer vnto this work is added by me, as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positiue
Table, and the natomie: I most hartyly desyre al the good
Readers to interprete it to the beste, regardyng the good wyll of the
worker, rather then thexcellency of the woorke, whiche I confesse to
be very faynt: trustyng that all suche as in those thynges are my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
and betters, wil rather seke the redresse and amēdement of such
thynges as to them shall seme faultie, then disdaynfully to reprehende
my good wyll, in settyng foorth of this worke. But as I feare it not
in any godly or charitable personage: so am I past care, what be said
of suche disdayners as speake euel of the doynges of all men, and yet
wyll do nothyng that good is them selues. Not consydering that a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
creature is not borne into this worlde, onely to profite himself,
but much rather to gratifie his frendes and contrey (as Cicero saith)
besides Christian charitie, whiche byndeth vs to profy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e all men.
And our sauiour Christ warneth vs, that no man hyde his
talent. Thus (wyshyng to the gentyll readers theyr
hartes desyre, that trauayle for the perfectnesse
of this art, euen as vnto my self in my
moste weighty affayres:) I ende
this my symple
Preface.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>