<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109832_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A97351</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17350.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English Arcadia : alluding his beginning from Sir Philip Sydneys ending. By Iaruis Markham</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rocket, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 71 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He innumerable tortures wherewith seuere censures will torment and whip me, their pewes, their pyshes, their wrye lookes, Apish iestures, and vntunable pronuntiations, haue not so much retained me any time this halfe-score yeares from the publication of this morall Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as the imputations of arrogancie immitation, affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and euen absurd ignorance, which I euer feared En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie would vniustly lay vpon me: but hauing by custome, and the weaknesse of detraction loosed my selfe from such sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowie fetters, and with a more airie spirit freed my soule from such insubstantiall feares, I haue aduentured to cast into the world this Orphan, which how-euer it was once begot by noble parents, and bosomed in the most celestiall eares that euer was worthie to retaine noble mysteries, is now like a vagabond inforst to begge, and liue vpon mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable charitie: yet for vertues sake, whom I euer desire to satisfie with my best powers, before I, be araignd at the barre of bitternesse, I am willing to make this defence for the crimes which crueltie may suggest against me. First for the Title, thogh it be only excellēt in the most excellēt creature that first taught vs the sound of excellent writing, yet hath it likewise beene vsed by others in sundrie pamphlets, without either pride or ostentation, men taking libertie to lay their hystories in Countries by them most affected: next for mine allusion and imitation, which beareth a colour of much greater vain-glorie: mine excuse must onely bee the
<pb facs="3"/> worthinesse of former presidents, as <hi>Virgill</hi> from <hi>Homer, Ariosto</hi> from <hi>Baiardo,</hi> famous <hi>Spencer</hi> from renowned <hi>Chaucer,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> with as good priuiledge, from the onely to be admired Sir <hi>Philip Sydney,</hi> whose like, though neuer age hath or shall present to memorie, yet shall it be renowne to the meanest that indeuour to liue by the crummes of his Table: who were our age but blest with his liuing breath, he would himselfe confesse the honie hee drew both from <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> and <hi>Diana.</hi> For other faults I must answere with Maister <hi>France,</hi> if there were a bond to compell men to read, there should then be an authoritie likewise, to bind vs that write, to delight: But since both haue free will, my counsell is to reade no longer then till your appetite be either cloyed, or filled, and so by preseruation of your sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes, make them apt to taste others better labours: to which, and to your owne content I commit you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>