<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well affected Gentle∣men, together with the rest of the faith∣full
in the Congregation of Malpasse, who haue giuen their names vnto Christ I. P. wisheth al holy and perfit increase of Gods gra∣ces, with the happie finishing of that good worke begun in them, euen through our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Parker, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109979_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08940</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19217</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109979</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well affected Gentle∣men, together with the rest of the faith∣full
in the Congregation of Malpasse, who haue giuen their names vnto Christ I. P. wisheth al holy and perfit increase of Gods gra∣ces, with the happie finishing of that good worke begun in them, euen through our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Parker, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true patterne of pietie : meete for all Christian householders to looke vpon, for the better education of their families, in the feare and seruice of almightie God. Collected out of the fountaine of holy scriptures, for the especiall vse of the faithfull in the congregation of Malpasse in Cheshire. By Iohn Parker</title>
                 <author>Parker, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Judson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well affected Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, together with the rest of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<hi>in the Congregation of Malpasse, who</hi> haue giuen their names vnto Christ I. P. wisheth al holy and perfit increase of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with the happie finishing of that good worke begun in them, euen through our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Christian brethren, my prayers to God on your behalfe are, that you may grow in all spiritual graces, and bee establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent faith. And if I (though vnworthie I
<pb facs="3"/>confesse) might in some measure bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed as Gods instrument and meane, for the furthering and building of you vp in that worthy worke, I should surely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my selfe greatly fauoured of the Lord. So that if I may know wherein to doe you good, (beyonde that which is done already) assure your selfe of this, that according to my poore power, I wil not faile you. And hereunto I will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly bee led, not onely in regarde of worldly kindnesses, and curtesies recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued lately and liberally from you, (for al the which I rest greatly indebted) but especially for the holy bond of our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian profession: whereinto, as we haue through Gods goodnesse made some entrie, and in some sort well begun: So I hope we shall holde on therein, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee wearie, vntill wee come to the ende of our faith and hope, euen the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our soules. And because I haue no better way yet to testifie my loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned, then either by writing, or spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: therefore: (though not as I would)
<pb facs="3"/>yet as I coulde, by reason of my mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde infirmities and sicknesses, I haue diligently laboured to offer vnto your Christian and curteous acceptations, a few holy rules and briefe obseruations, for the godly and well gouering of your seuerall families, by Catechising them, and ioyning in faithfull prayers to Almightie God with them. The matter it selfe is collected out of the sacred wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of Gods holy word, and reduced into as short an epitome as possiblie I could, for memories sake. I haue not taken this paines, as one that would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade you to accept of this direction and none other, (knowing right well, that there are farre better set foorth by more learned and godly Ministers) or for that I would tye you to one speciall forme of Prayer in your Families: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the spirite which is in you, wil in due time teach you aboundantly to craue al things at Gods hands, according to your seuerall necessities. But my simple and vnfained purpose herein is this; that for
<pb facs="4"/>as much as, that I am better acquainted with your estate and wants, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can be who knoweth you not, and that the continuall care which I haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you for your good, can no better way be signified or manifested, than by prouoking you to well doing. I haue therefore endeauored to frame this spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle for you to looke vpon, that you hereby finding out, and conceiuing the order and manner how to glorifie God, by offering vp holy and continnall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of praiers and praises vnto his maiestie, as also howe to occupie your selues in other exercises of pure religion before him, might hereby in some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient time hauing learned both the matter and maner of the seruice of God: wholy bend your selues to the carefull and constant practise of all holy duties, vnto so mercifull a Father, most to his glory and your edification and comfort. And if I vnderstande that you take that in good part, &amp; esteeme this little work. though as a simple (I confesse) yet as a
<pb facs="4"/>sound significatiō of my vnfeigned loue towards you, and care to doe you good: then shall I not onely thinke this labour (though it be not worthy of that name) well bestowed for your sakes, but also to accomplish some far better thing, if my poore talent will extende thereunto for your better proceeding in that good race, whereinto you are entered. You know the poore widowes mite was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God, not in regard of the gift, but the mind of the giuer, &amp; I hope this shall be no lesse. Farwell my good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and the Lord Iesus be with you to confirme and inable you to euery good worke, that you may be kept blamelesse vntil his glorious comming, &amp; so walke in this world in his feare, that we may in the conclusion of your pilgrimage, ende your daies in his blessed fauour, &amp; at the last, liue with him for euer. <hi>Amen,</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your assured brother in Christ, yea your seruant for Christ his sake to further your saluation.</hi> I. Parker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>