<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS ESPECIALL good friend Master Raph Crane, and the rest of
his most entire wellwil∣lers, the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court and
Chauncerie. Tho∣mas Lodge of Lincolnes Inne Gent. Wisheth increase of worship
and continu∣ance in vertue.</title>
           <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109632_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06181</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16674</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109632</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS ESPECIALL good friend Master Raph Crane, and the rest of
his most entire wellwil∣lers, the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court and
Chauncerie. Tho∣mas Lodge of Lincolnes Inne Gent. Wisheth increase of worship
and continu∣ance in vertue.</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Scillaes metamorphosis: enterlaced with the vnfortunate loue of Glaucus : VVhereunto is annexed the delectable discourse of the discontented satyre: with sundrie other most absolute poems and sonnets. Contayning the detestable tyrannie of disdaine, and comicall triumph of constancie: verie fit for young courtiers to peruse, and coy dames to remember. By Thomas Lodge of Lincolnes Inne, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Lodge, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS ESPECIALL good friend Master Raph Crane, and the rest of
his most entire wellwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court and
Chauncerie. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Lodge of Lincolnes Inne Gent. Wisheth increase of worship
and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VVeete Master <hi>Crane,</hi> I had not thought at this instant
to haue partaked my passions with the print, whose discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented thoughts so
long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ured to obscuritie, were diuorsed many yeares since, from vaine glories
inordinate follie: but the base necessities of an extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant melancholie
mate, that had no other <hi>vnde</hi> of <hi>quod ad victum attinet,</hi> but
the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stalling of other mens inuentions, made my vnperfit Poems (in spite of
waste paper) to hazard an apprenteship in Poules: so that, that which in the
first peeping foorth was <pb facs="3"/> wholie predestinate to your friendship,
by an vnderhand marte, is made the mercina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie recreation of euerie ridiculous
mate. Our wits now a daies are waxt verie fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and our Pamphleters more
than prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall; So that the postes which stoode naked a tedious <hi>non
terminus,</hi> doo vaunt their dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble apparrell as soone as euer the
Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer openeth; and euerie corner is tooke vp with some or other penilesse
companion that will imitate any estate for a two pennie almes. I could afford
you whole seruices of absurdities, that would disquiet the disgesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Arte
<hi>vs{que} ad nausaeam,</hi> were it not that I pittie to particularize
simple fellowes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and am altogether loath to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture my paines
in so vngratefull a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince. For transformed <hi>Scilla</hi> how euer she
hapned now to bee disioyned from disdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Charybdis</hi>; thinke not,
but if they haue good shipping they wil meete ere long both in one shop: and
landed they had at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, in one and the selfe same bay, if
<hi>Scilla</hi> (the vnfortunater of the two) had not met with a needie pirate
by the way. Ariued shee <pb facs="3"/> is, though in a contrary coast, but so
wrackt, and weather beaten, through the vnskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of rough writers, that
made their poast haste passage by night, as <hi>Glaucus</hi> would scarce know
her, if he met her: yet my hope is Gentlemen, that you wil not so much ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
what she is, as what shee was; insomuch as from the shop of the Painter, shee
is falne into the hands of the stainer. Thus referring the supportāce of my
credit, &amp; the inability of my verse to your ingenious opinions, I bid you
farewel til the next Tearm; at vvhich time I hope to entertaine your seuerall
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, vvith farre better discourses, and bee suppliant to my good friend
Master <hi>Crane,</hi> in some or other more acceptable Poem. In the meane time
let my appliable <hi>voluisse,</hi> intitle me to your curtesie: vvhose I am
during Iife in all enterchangeable dutie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend assured <hi>Thomas
 Lodge.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>