<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull Maister VVilliam Hawkins Esquier, Maior of the Towne of Plimmouth, and to the worship∣full companie his Brethren the Maisters of the Towne. W. K. wisheth pro∣speritie in this life, and euerlasting ioy in the life to come.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109252_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68296</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14926</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull Maister VVilliam Hawkins Esquier, Maior of the Towne of Plimmouth, and to the worship∣full companie his Brethren the Maisters of the Towne. W. K. wisheth pro∣speritie in this life, and euerlasting ioy in the life to come.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The education of children in learning : declared by the dignitie, vtilitie, and method thereof. Meete to be knowne, and practised aswell of parents as schoolemaisters</title>
                 <author>Kempe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Porter, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull Maister <hi>VVilliam Hawkins Esquier, Maior of the</hi> Towne of <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> and to the worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>full companie his Brethren the Maisters</hi> of the Towne. <hi>W. K.</hi> wisheth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie in this life, and euerlasting ioy in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it bee a matter of it selfe most euident, that the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and vertuous bringing vp of children in good learning is the very foundation and groundworke of all good in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery estate aswell priuate as publike: yet such is the corruption and iniquitie of our time, that most men are found very carelesse and slacke to do their duetie therein; yea there want not those that in flat termes affirme it to bee superfluous, insomuch that they can do well enough (in their owne iudgement) without it. For what parents in these daies haue not more care to prouide wealth for their children, than wisedome? More care to leaue thē lands and liuings in this world,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>than to bequeath them that knowledge whereby they may enioy the right vse and fruites of these temporall blessings, &amp; be directed the right way to that glorious inheritance layd vp for Gods children in heauen? The common practise of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parents proueth this complaynt to bee true, and the priuate talke of some defendeth this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise to be good. VVherefore hauing regard of my duetie in this behalfe, and being assured of your VVorships courtesie in accepting my good will, to withdraw my neighbours and countrie men from this prophane opinion and pernicious custome, and to allure them vnto a better and more godly consideration, I haue thought good in your VVorships name to set before them, first (as it were) in a Preface the excellent dignitie of this Discipline, then the vtilitie, and afterwards in the rest of the booke a Treatise of the easiest and playnest way to be vsed therein.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships euer to commaund in the Lord,
W.K.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>