<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Considerations to be had in shooting of Ordinance.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109410_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16508</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3420</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109410</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Considerations to be had in shooting of Ordinance.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of shooting in great ordnaunce : Contayning very necessary matters for all sortes of seruitoures eyther by sea or by lande. Written by William Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 94, 2 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="considerations">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ Considerations to be had in shooting of Ordinance.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>Tenne principall things are to be considered in the shooting of Ordnance, to keep the length of the marke, or to make a perfit shotte at any marke assigned, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the distance of the marke, and knowing what such a peece wil do at such an aduantage in mounting.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">1. The goodnesse or badnesse of the pouder.</p>
   <p>THe good pouder driueth the shotte further than the marke, the badde pouder shooteth short of the marke: therefore you must vse discretion in lading of the peece, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the pouder.</p>
   <p n="2">2. The lading of the peece.</p>
   <p>IF you doe giue the peece more than hir dutie, you doe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uershoote the marke: if you do giue hir lesse than hir duty, you shoote short of the mark: you must therefore giue the peece hir dutie and no more.</p>
   <p n="3">3. The winde, and especially to be mounted at much aduantage.</p>
   <p>THe winde with you, causeth you to ouershoote y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> marke, according vnto the hardnesse. The winde against you, maketh you shoote short of the marke according vnto the hardnesse. The winde one the side, the peece casteth beside the marke: therefore you must weather the marke, according vnto the hardnesse of the winde, and the distance vnto the marke.</p>
   <p n="4">4. Of the shotte.</p>
   <p>THe shotte too bigge or too high, it putteth the peece in daunger: for you must driue the wodde and shoote home vnto the pouder in the pecce, for if the shotte doe rest any thing short, it will breake the peece (or else it is a chaunce) in the vacant place betweene the pouder and the shotte. The shotte too low or small, it will be too shorte of the marke, &amp; also it will not do his execution according vnto the peece and the pouder, and it may chance to swarue in the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="2" facs="8"/>
out of peece, the therefore the shotte must be fitte for the peece</p>
   <p n="5">5. Of the wadde or the pouder rammed in too hard or too loose.</p>
   <p>THe pouder rammed in too hard, and the wadde also, and especially the pouder being badde, or els not drye, it wil be long before the peece goe off, and also halfe the force of the pouder will be decayed, before the shotte bee deliuered, for that it bloweth out of the tutchhole, and also the peece will tremble before shee goe off, &amp; that may cause the shotte to flee awrye from the marke, for that the peece is remoued from hir leuell: and also it will heate the peece, and make the peece daungerous to shoote in presently afterwards.</p>
   <p>The pouder too loose, and not well put vp with the ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer head, and also the wadde too slacke in like manner, will make the shotte to come short of the marke by the meanes of the loosenesse: you must therefore put vp the pouder with the rammer head somewhat close, and the wadde to go close in, and driue it home vnto the pouder, but beate it not in too hard.</p>
   <p n="6">6. Of the standing of the peece.</p>
   <p>THe peece standing so that it maye or doth recoyle vnto the lower ground, that is to say, that the grounde bee lower at the tayle of the peece, than it is where the wheeles stand, it ouershooteth the marke, for that in the deliuerance of the shotte, the breech goeth downewards, and the mouth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, and the peece is apte to recoyle downe the hill: and if that the ground be higher behind the peece then it is before the peece, then it may happen to shoote shorte: but that is but a chaunce, for that is not so apte to recoyle agaynst a hill, as it will do downe the hill.</p>
   <p>And if it doth happen so, that the one wheele dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyle faster than the other wheele, then the peece will shoote awrye from the marke, or if any thing doe lette or stay the wheele, it may shoote awrye, for the deliuerance of the shotte
<pb n="3" facs="8"/>
causeth the recoyle of the peece, which is nothing else, but the suddayne thrusting or the putting out of the ayre whiche is in the mouth of the peece.</p>
   <p n="7">7. Of shooting towards a hill or valley with a Quadrant.</p>
   <p>IF you shoote towardes a hill, you shoote shorte in the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing leuell with a Quadrant. If you shoote towardes a valley, you do ouershoot y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> marke, as in the thirteenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you shall se the reason therof. If vppon a leuell ground, you shall keepe the length of the marke by the degrees of the Quadrante, otherwise not.</p>
   <p n="8">8. If you giue leuell with an ynche rule, you shall shoote at no certaynetie, but in such a peece as you doe knowe wel, for that it doth varie according vnto the length of the peece: as for example this, if you haue three Culuerings, the one is the ordinarie length, that is, twelue foote long: the other is more then the ordinarie length by two foote, that is, foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene foote longe: and the thirde is shorter than the ordinarie length by two foote, that is, but tenne foote longe: nowe if you doe shoote at any marke, and doe knowe the distance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the marke, and also doe knowe, that a Culuering moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at so manye ynches vantage, wyll reach the marke, and admitte that it wyll reache the marke at twelue ynches vā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, nowe in the shorter peece, it ouershooteth the marke, and in the longer peece it shooteth shorte of the marke, and in that peece that hathe the ordinarie length, you shall keepe the length of the marke: and the cause thereof is this: In y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peece that is but tenne foote longe, the twelue ynches van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage commeth neere vnto syxe degrees wyth the Quadrante in the mounting: and in the peece of twelue foote long, the twelue inches commeth not to fiue degrees in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Quadrant, and in the peece of foureteene foot long, it commeth but vnto foure degrees in the mounting with the Quadrāt, as in the eyght Chapter you may plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <pb n="4" facs="9"/>
9. It is to be considered what dispart your pecce must haue, if you doe giue leuell with an ynche rule at any aduantage, and also, if you doe shoote at any marke within the right line or poynt plancke, as in the fourth Chapter it is shewed.</p>
   <p n="10">10. You must consider whether the peece be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bored, as it is declared how you shall know it in the second Chapter: and how to shoote with a peece that is not truely bored, you shall see by the eleuenth Chapter.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>