<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>C., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109129_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19692</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6111</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109129</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>C., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A ready vvay to remember the Scriptures. Or, A table of the Old and Nevv Testament. By that late able, painfull, and worthy man of God, Ezekiel Culuervvell, minister of the Word</title>
                 <author>Culverwell, Ezekiel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Skelton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 76, 79-94 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving many yeares agoe gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and made this briefe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all the principall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters contained in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> whereby I may say (I lost not my labour) for I found it by good Experience no small helpe vnto me; for by it I could easily finde any principall matter; Now although the chiefe vse thereof be for Divines and young Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, yet vpon the desire of many good Christians, which have found the like fruit and benefit, I was willing to publish the same and make it more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; vnto whom I wish, that reading over the New Testament, they diligently observe the contents and chiefe matter contained in every Chapter and Verse, and often repeat them over, and every day to goe thorow some Chapter or other; and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="3"/> to keepe the Contents in memorie, to say over daily that which is past; wherby I have good proofe, that by this meanes, in short time one may readily tell what are the Contents of any Chapter, and where any speciall matter is written, (which I conceive may be a good Exercise for the trayning vp of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of tenne yeares old and vpward) for by reading over these Contents, a man well exercised in the Scriptures, may is one houre see the principall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the whole <hi>New Testament:</hi> One speciall vse thereof will be this▪ to fill the Head, and so the Heart, with much heavenly matter, which is the best way to keepe out idle thoughts. And therefore now having my hearts desire in what I did expect, I have thought good to publish the like on the <hi>Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> For direction I need not say much, for it is easily perceived, that the Figures at the beginning of each line, stands for the Chapter, and the figures following the words, for the Verse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>