<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WELWISHING READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109936_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20860</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7238</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109936</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WELWISHING READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nicetas or the triumph ouer incontinencie : written in Latin by. F. Hier. Drexelius of the Society of Iesus. And translated into English by. R.S. 1633</title>
                 <author>Drexel, Jeremias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Courant (Fournieres), Marie</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 140, 161-426, that is 424, 429-464, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE WELWISHING READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> present vnto thee (gentle Reader) an heroical act, admirable to precedent &amp; succeeding Ages. I present Nicetas an Aegyptian, a yong man, a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and admirable subduer of himselfe &amp; his owne lust, who by a stupendious stratagem obtayned the victory. I am of opinion that in al Christendom there is not the like found. Verily we may with much more truth affirme of this yong man what was said of <hi>Vlisses:</hi> He sayled past Scilla and was nor deuoured; touched at Caribdis, &amp; was not swallowed; tasted of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cup, and was not transformed; set foot amongst the Lothophagi, but staied not, heard the Sirens, but approached not.<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> de Deo Socr. fine.</hi>
      </note> I wil adde more; he was bound, tied, bereft of al
<pb facs="10"/>
weapons, yet could not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: yea he heard and came nere, or at least was compelled to come nere the most deceitful Siren, yet was he not drowned. His tongue fought, his tongue ouercame, whereby we are al in a manner vanquished. Yet this did he not by volubilitie of speech, but by a painful mayming of his tongue. Wouldest thou know (Reader) the vncomparable proiect of this most generous Nicetas? read this little booke; but let me request thee to read it with repose &amp; recollection of mind, willing to reape benefit thereby. Our endeauour here is to compose manners not words, to profit mens soules, not to please their eares. The scope of my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is, that which I desire should be likewise thyne in reading, to destroy the extreamest of al euils, the most capital of al plagues, the
<pb facs="10"/>
deepest sourse of al vices <hi>(Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency)</hi> the pregnant mother of al sinnes, diffusing herselfe into al shapes. He that is an enemie to chastitie, is in a manner a friend to al vices. Neuer was there anie man denounced warre against chastitie who had not first entred a league with more then one enormitie. Whosoeuer is minded compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diously to attaine to the knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of vices, let him but make himselfe a scholler to Lasciuious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and he shal shortly won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to see himselfe of a scoller be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a maister. No man can liue vertuously if he liue not chastly. And (good Reader) deceaue not thy selfe, it is not for yong men only these things are written, not for Virgins, nor those only of the Sodalitie who are batchlours. This belōgeth to euery state, Sex,
<pb facs="11"/>
age, and degree, for of necessitie must the widow, the wife, the husband and wife keepe Chastity each in their kindes. Hardly shal he keepe the lawes of wedlocke who knowes not how to preserue those of chastity. Yea I dare boldly avouch, that man must haue an exact knowledge of the lawes of chastity, who wil obserue those of wedlocke. It is not lawful for any order of men, of what age soeuer to goe beyond the bounds of chastitie. How can a man agree wel with vertue, who is at variance with modestie, the onlie feat of vertue? So that these things which are said of auoyding incōtinencie are necessarie for euerie one to know. I adde more, that manie things are taught in this booke auailable for maintaying al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vertue. And to the intent thou maist know (my Reader) that
<pb facs="11"/>
I here purpose a Summary of holie instruction: whatsoeuer I discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of in the yeare 1621. in presence of the most excellent Electour <hi>Maximilian</hi> and his most gratious wife the Ladie <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> cōcerning the presence of god in al places, during the time of the sacred Aduent of our Lord, I haue here briefly collected and as it were drawne forth the quintessence thereof; which I haue set downe for thy vse in the tenth chapter of the second booke. And what I spake out of Pulpit in the yeare 1633. before the most excellent Duke and <hi>Duchesse</hi> of <hi>Bauaria</hi> &amp; their Courtlike Attendance, cōcerning the nynefold torment of infernal Eternitie, I giue thee here compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diously touched in the selfe same latter treatise the eleauenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And albeit this booke is but
<pb facs="12"/>
little, it was none of those written in post-hast, or vpon the suddaine. It is the aduice of Horrace, what thou wouldest expose to light and publike view, ought to be nyne yeares laboured.<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>De arte poetica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> propius finem.</hi>
      </note> I haue obserued it, and that with aduantage. The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and order of my booke is as before I haue declared.</p>
   <p>Foure and twentie chapters in al are assigned to both bookes. The first sheweth in twelue what the allurements and effects of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency are. The secōd in as many chapters yealdeth Antidotes for the same vice. The original cause, as likewise the tenour and scope of my writing is <hi>Nicetas,</hi> that Miracle of continencie and Spectacle wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of Heauen. My desire was (gentle Reader) these things might be known to thee, and that thou make the best benifit of them.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>