<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Elizium. To the Duchesse of BVCKINGHAM.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109308_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19878</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6304</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Elizium. To the Duchesse of BVCKINGHAM.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Madagascar : with other poems. By W. Davenant</title>
                 <author>D'Avenant, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walkley, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 141, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="22" facs="21"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Elizium.</hi> To the Duchesse of BVCKINGHAM.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM,</salute>
   </opener>
   <lg>
      <l>SO sleeps the Anchoret on his cheap bed,</l>
      <l>(whose sleep wants only length to prove him dead)</l>
      <l>As I last night, whom the swift wings of Thought,</l>
      <l>Convey'd to see what our bold faith had taught;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Elizium,</hi> where restored formes nere fade;</l>
      <l>Where growth can need no seeds, nor light a shade;</l>
      <l>The joyes which in our flesh, through fraile expence</l>
      <l>Of strentgh, through age, were lost t'our injur'd sense,</l>
      <l>Wee there doe meet agen; and those we taste</l>
      <l>Anew, which though devour'd, yet ever last:</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="23" facs="21"/>The scatter'd treasure of the Spring, blowne by</l>
      <l>Autumn's rude winds from our discoverie;</l>
      <l>Lillies, and Roses; all that's faire and sweet,</l>
      <l>There reconcil'd to their first roots we meet:</l>
      <l>There, only those triumphant Lovers reigne,</l>
      <l>Whose passions knew on earth so little staine,</l>
      <l>Like Angels they nere felt what sexes meant;</l>
      <l>Virtue, was first their nature, then intent:</l>
      <l>There, toyling Victors safely are possest,</l>
      <l>With servent youth, eternitie, and rest;</l>
      <l>But they were such, who when they got the field;</l>
      <l>To teach the conquer'd, victorie, could yeeld</l>
      <l>Themselves againe; as if true glorie were</l>
      <l>To bring the foe to courage, not to feare.</l>
      <l>There are no talking Greeks, who their blood lost,</l>
      <l>Not for the cause, but for a theame to boast;</l>
      <l>As if they strove enough for Fame, that sought</l>
      <l>To have their Batailes better told, than fought.</l>
      <l>There I a <hi>Vestal's</hi> Shadow first did spy,</l>
      <l>Who when a live with holy huswifry,</l>
      <l>Trick'd up in lawne, and flow'ry Wreaths (each hand</l>
      <l>Cleane as her thoughts) did'fore the Altar stand:</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="24" facs="22"/>So busie still, strewing her Spice, and then</l>
      <l>Removing Coales, vexing the Fire agen,</l>
      <l>As if some queasie <hi>Goddesse</hi> had profess'd,</l>
      <l>To taste no smoak that day, but what she dress'd:</l>
      <l>This holy coyle she living kept; but farre</l>
      <l>More busie now, with more delightfull care</l>
      <l>Than when she watch'd the consecrated Flame,</l>
      <l>Sh'attends the <hi>Shade</hi> of gentle <hi>Buckingham;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Who there unenvi'd sits, with Chaplets crownd;</l>
      <l>And with wise scorne, smiles on the Peoples wound;</l>
      <l>He call'd it so; for though it touch'd his heart,</l>
      <l>His Nation feeles the rancour, and the smart.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>