<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>K., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109252_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68296</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14926</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>K., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The education of children in learning : declared by the dignitie, vtilitie, and method thereof. Meete to be knowne, and practised aswell of parents as schoolemaisters</title>
                 <author>Kempe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Porter, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To the Gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue sent you, deere friend, a little pamphlet, of the education of Children in learning, which is no phantasticall nor idle toy, but a verie profitable matter, and most necessarie to be vrged in this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and licentious generation. Wherein I confesse, that many learned men haue alreadie bestowed verie exquisit and commendable labours: yet for that we haue endeuoured not only to fill vp the emptie roome with such members as wanted, and to sepatate that which seemed superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but also to new cast the whole in another mould, and to bring it to another forme, breefe, and easie: I suppose that it will seeme altogether a strange and a new Booke. Furthermore, where as the charge of teaching apperteineth but onely to a fewe of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neder sort, namely, to Scholemaysters, we to make the argument more popular, haue prefixed a necessarie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation for all other sort of people, setting foorth the dignitie and vtilitie of the matter, with such holie and ancient Histories, with such plaine and sensible reasons, as may teach the vnlearned with some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and not be tedious to those that are learned. Agayne, to satisfye in some part the expectation of the learned, we haue handled the method more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically, and adorned the whole worke with some
<pb facs="4"/>
wittie, Greeke, and Latin sentences, englishing the same neuertheles in the Margent for the behoofe of the vnlearned. And as generally both sorts may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture thinke that the reading of it will be worth the labour, so almost euery one of each sort in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, may finde somewhat for his purpose. For who is it of what state or degree soeuer, vpon whom God hath not cast the care and charge, either of teaching, or of learning, or else of causing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be taught and learned?</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell,
VV. K.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>