<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Magnanimous, Renowned, and most Valourous Lorde, IOHN Earle of MONTROSE, LORD GRAHAME, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109476_Fr2_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15715</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109476</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Magnanimous, Renowned, and most Valourous Lorde, IOHN Earle of MONTROSE, LORD GRAHAME, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrimes farewell, to his natiue countrey of Scotland : vvherein is contained, in way of dialogue, the ioyes and miseries of peregrination. With his Lamentado in his second trauels, his Passionado on the Rhyne, diuerse other insertings, and farewels, to noble personages, and, the heremites welcome to his third pilgrimage, &amp;c. Worthie to be seene and read of all gallant spirits, and pompe-expecting eyes. By William Lithgow, the bonauenture of Europe, Asia, and Africa, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Hart, Andro.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lithgow, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Magnanimous, Renowned, and <hi>most Valourous Lorde, IOHN Earle of MONTROSE,</hi> LORD GRAHAME, &amp;c.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>GRant this (graue Lord) to patronize my paines,</l>
      <l>This my Conflict, before thine eyes I bring:</l>
      <l>If thou affect good will, O there's my gaines.</l>
      <l>I show my best, though plaine, the trueth I sing:</l>
      <l>A two-folde debt mee bindes, Thy Worth, Thy Name,</l>
      <l>That still protectes all them that heght a GRAHAME.</l>
      <l>So (Noble Earle) accept these small Effectes,</l>
      <l>Thy Vertue may draw Vales ou'r my Defectes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To lift thy worth, on admirations eye,</l>
      <l>It farre exceedes, the reach of my engine:</l>
      <l>But this (great Lord) I dare attest to thee,</l>
      <l>While breath indures, this wandring breast is thine:</l>
      <l>And that great loue, I found in thy late Sire,</l>
      <l>I wish the Heauens the same in thee inspire:</l>
      <l>And as his late renowne, reuiues his name,</l>
      <l>So imitate his life, increase his fame.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>That thou when dead, thy Race the same may doe,</l>
      <l>As thou, I hope, shalt once excell thy Father;</l>
      <l>That time to time, thy long successours too,</l>
      <l>May each exceede the former, yea, or rather,</l>
      <l>The one ingraft, the other stampe it more,</l>
      <l>That who succeedes, may adde anothers glore.</l>
      <l>So shall thy selfe liue famous, and thy race,</l>
      <l>Shall long enjoye the earth, then Heauenlie grace.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lo. most seruile seruitour on his low bended Knees,
WILLIAM LITHGOW.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>