<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN AND WELL AFFECTED REA∣DERS, WHO EXPECT THE COM∣ming of the Lorde Iesus to their immortalitie: I.D. and I.W. doe wish the necessarie graces of the spirit, with a sauing knowledge in Iesus Christ: So be it.</title>
           <author>Walker, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109440_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20001</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6440</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109440</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN AND WELL AFFECTED REA∣DERS, WHO EXPECT THE COM∣ming of the Lorde Iesus to their immortalitie: I.D. and I.W. doe wish the necessarie graces of the spirit, with a sauing knowledge in Iesus Christ: So be it.</title>
                 <author>Walker, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summarie ansvvere to al the material points in any of Master Darel his bookes : More especiallie to that one booke of his, intituled, the Doctrine of the possession and dispossession of demoniaks out of the word of God. By Iohn Deacon. Iohn Walker. Preachers</title>
                 <author>Deacon, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 240, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN AND WELL AFFECTED REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS, WHO EXPECT THE COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lorde Iesus to their immortalitie: I.D. and I.W. doe wish the necessarie graces of the spirit, with a sauing knowledge in Iesus Christ: So be it.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood <hi>Christian Reader,</hi> when we dulie considered <hi>Maister Darel</hi> and his complices their lately dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed <hi>pamphlets,</hi> concerning their <hi>new-found trade of Diuillitie,</hi> as also their vndutifull manner of <hi>imprinting</hi> and <hi>publishing</hi> the same to the world: we could not but call to remembrance a most pestilent practise, which <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Benno</hi> reporteth of <hi>Hildebrand.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Benno Cardinal. in vita Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andri. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> Who (hauing killed <hi>Alexander</hi> the second, for that he refused to sit at his speciall appointment in the <hi>Apostolike Sea,</hi> without the good <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours</hi> licence) was (by the ayde of his <hi>souldiours</hi>) forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with enthronized into the <hi>Popedome</hi> himselfe: not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therein the consent either of <hi>Cleargie or people.</hi> The which his prowd <hi>vsurpation,</hi> when <hi>Abbas Cassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensis</hi> was come to redresse, <hi>Hildebrand</hi> that insolent <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surper</hi> very scornefullie sayth vnto him thus, <hi>Frater, nimium tardasti,</hi> Brother, you haue beene somewhat too slowe: to whome <hi>Cassinensis</hi> very boldly replyed saying, <hi>&amp; tu Hildebrande nimium festinasti,</hi> and thou O Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrand, thou hast beene ouer-hastie by much, both in kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="5"/>
thy good predecessour, &amp; in procuring the <hi>Popedome</hi> by such prowd <hi>vsurpation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Euen thus (surely) it falles forth with vs at this present, concerning especiallie the matters controuerted betweene our selues and those our Antagonists. For they, not only giuing the <hi>Canuisado</hi> of late to her Maiesties high <hi>Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but hauing withall (by the venemous <hi>infection</hi> of their <hi>viperous pennes</hi>) verie vncharitablie endeuoured to wound <hi>S. H.</hi> vnto death, for that (by meanes of the sayd <hi>S. H.</hi> his dutifull <hi>discouerie</hi> of those their vndutifull dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings) they might not be permitted to vsurp (in our <hi>English Church</hi>) a new <hi>Apostolicall power</hi> at their pleasures, without any her Maiesties <hi>authenticall licence.</hi> Maister <hi>Darel</hi> the <hi>principall agent</hi> (partly by the inherent pride of his <hi>insolent spirit,</hi> and partly by the prowde support of many his <hi>vnder-hand fauorits</hi>) is very prowdlie <hi>enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized</hi> into a new <hi>Popedome</hi> forsooth. And by priuiledge thereof he hath very peremptorily <hi>imprinted</hi> and <hi>publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed</hi> sundrie <hi>seditious pamphlets,</hi> hauing thereunto nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>warrant</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>dispensation</hi> from <hi>Prince,</hi> nor <hi>testimonie</hi> of sound <hi>conscience,</hi> no nor so much as the holie <hi>approbation</hi> of any good christian <hi>subiect.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Notwithstanding all this, he hath for a season (though feare and shame enforceth him now to pluck in his head) very prowdlie <hi>ietted</hi> from countrie to countrie like a pettie new <hi>Pope</hi> among his owne <hi>Cardinals</hi>; yea and that also in his <hi>pontificalities,</hi> portrayed and contriued after the <hi>new-found popelike cut.</hi> The which their <hi>vnbridled insolencie,</hi> when we indeuoured to encounter, by publishing (as we verily beleeue) the infallible <hi>truth</hi> of these intricate <hi>matters</hi> in a <hi>treatise</hi> at large, and had signified so much to themselues by <hi>word</hi> and by <hi>letters</hi> in an only desire of doing them good, they labored by <hi>letters</hi> and otherwaies to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our said enterprise a time at the least. And in the meane time (<hi>by printing and publishing</hi> the <hi>trifling toyes</hi> of
<pb facs="6"/>
that their new found <hi>trifling trade</hi>) they haue sought <hi>to forestall</hi> our former good purpose, and laboured to calme our carefull endeuours for doing them good. Yea, and by these their <hi>preuenting practises,</hi> they do (in effect) but disdainefullie say vnto vs, with <hi>Pope Hildebrand</hi> their prowd <hi>copartner, Deere brethren, you haue bin some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what too slow in publishing those your dialogicall Discourses concerning Spirits and Diuels.</hi> Howbeit, we (by these our <hi>subsequent labours</hi> and second <hi>encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>) may with <hi>Cassinensis</hi> very conscionablie replie vpon them thus: and you, oh counterfeit <hi>Exorcistes, you haue bin ouer-hastie by much,</hi> not only in killing your good <hi>predecessour</hi> by your <hi>poysoned penne,</hi> but also in broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching a fond <hi>triall</hi> abroade, without any <hi>triall of truth:</hi> in designing a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> so opposite to the <hi>Doctrine of Christ:</hi> and in discouering a <hi>Detection,</hi> to <hi>detect</hi> your great follie, and shame to the world.</p>
   <p>The truth of the <hi>premisses</hi> (good christian <hi>Reader</hi>) may be made more apparantlie euident, if thou wilt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently examine, first, the <hi>pamphlets</hi> themselues: and then next, the <hi>spirit</hi> it selfe which may be supposed to endight the same.</p>
   <p>The <hi>pamphlets</hi> themselues (notwithstanding any their outward florishing shewes) they are inwardlie faultie (we verily thinke) both in <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That they are ouermuch faultie in <hi>matter,</hi> is more then may be denyed, being euery of them fraught full of vnsound, and <hi>absurd positions,</hi> as shall be shewed hereafter in a short <hi>Catalogue</hi> prefixed before this <hi>booke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Moreouer, that they be likewise faultie in their <hi>manner or forme,</hi> may easily appeare vnto such as are not vtterlie ignorant of <hi>methode:</hi> or, do any thing know what belongs to <hi>an orderlie manner of writing.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For first, their <hi>manner</hi> of writing, it seemes to be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>Schismaticall,</hi> and very shrewdlie to sauour of a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine
<pb facs="6"/>
subtiltie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.3.4.</hi>
      </note> because (whatsoeuer their <hi>pamphlets</hi> pretend) they proceede not by a plaine course of teaching, but do rather <hi>incedere tortuosè,</hi> goe <hi>wrigginglie</hi> to worke, and walke this way and that way, like to the hunted <hi>Hare,</hi> which knoweth not whereon to resolue for a certaine.</p>
   <p>Besides that, their <hi>manner</hi> of writing, it is also verie enigmaticall, obscure, and cloudie: their <hi>sentences or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods</hi> they are (in effect) no better then <hi>riddles,</hi> and for the most part so vncertaine, so variable, so flitting, and so chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, as none but themselues may possiblie <hi>spell, or spie forth their meaning.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Briefely, the very <hi>frame</hi> itselfe of their whole proceeding resembleth fitlie a paire of <hi>tarriours,</hi> or <hi>tyring yrons,</hi> and serueth to no other purpose at all, but to hold men occupied all the day long about <hi>a new nothing to hang on their sleeues.</hi> Or they may well be compared to an intricate <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth,</hi> or <hi>maskaring maze,</hi> from whence (when a man is once entred into them) he wots not which waies to winde himselfe forth, as may plainely appeare vnto such as careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie consider the same, and this in effect for the <hi>Pamphlets</hi> themselues.</p>
   <p>The <hi>spirit</hi> which may be supposed <hi>to indite those pamphlets,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>13.1.2.3▪</hi> Matth. <hi>7.15.16▪ 1.</hi> Ioh. <hi>4.1.3.</hi>
      </note> should make wise men beware how they doe rashlie entertaine them for <hi>truths,</hi> before they haue soundly tried the same with the <hi>touchstone of truth.</hi> This sacred <hi>triall</hi> being dulie obserued herein, it may greatly be feared, that the <hi>spirit inditing those pamphlets,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iam. <hi>3.17.</hi>
      </note> will hardly be found to sauour of that <hi>wisedome which is from aboue,</hi> which is <hi>pure, peaceable, gentle, easie to be intreated, full of mercie and good fruites, without grudging, without hypocrisie:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iam. <hi>3.15.</hi>
      </note> but rather to tast of that <hi>wisedome</hi> which <hi>descendeth not from aboue, but is earthlie, sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall, and diuellish.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>2.11.</hi>
      </note> And howsoeuer no man <hi>knoweth the secrets of man, saue only the spirit of man</hi> which is in him, and therefore may <hi>iudge nothing too rashly of
<pb facs="7"/>
man,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>4.5.</hi> Heb. <hi>4.12.13.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>before the time:</hi> yet when <hi>the Lord himselfe is come, and hath lightned things which were hid in darknes, and made manifest the counsels of the hart to all mens eyes,</hi> then, I see no reason at all, but that (<hi>by the out-goings of the spirit</hi>) a man may as easily discerne the <hi>nature of the spirit it selfe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>7.16.17</hi>
      </note> as iudge <hi>of a tree by the fruites.</hi> And therefore, when we behold men caried head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with <hi>selfe conceits,</hi> vaunting very prowdlie with the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and saying, <hi>Quod volumus, sanctum est: quod nolumus, id iniquum &amp; iniustum.</hi> Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer <hi>we will or affect,</hi> that same is <hi>holie;</hi> whatsoeuer <hi>we nil, or affect not,</hi> that same is <hi>vniust &amp; vnholie.</hi> Briefly, when we do heare <hi>M. Darel</hi> and his vnderhand fauorits (in sundrie places of their <hi>published pamphlets</hi>) to cry out and confesse, that <hi>all the learned men in the land are of a contrarie iudgement to them,</hi> and yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, do prowdlie oppose themselues to all the learned men in the land,<note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>14.36.</hi>
      </note> as though <hi>the word of truth came out only from them, or came only vnto themselues:</hi> what should set them agog in such a glorious vaunt, but only a <hi>prowd</hi> and <hi>insolent spirit?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Iude. <hi>9.10. 3.</hi> Ioh. <hi>10.</hi>
      </note>Againe, when we heare how these vnrulie <hi>spirits</hi> doe nothing else in effect but <hi>rayle</hi> vpon men, <hi>reuile</hi> their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, yea, and euen vtterlie <hi>disable the iudgements</hi> of such and so reuerend <hi>personages,</hi> as they themselues (in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of true learning in deede, of sound knowledge, and of all good <hi>gifts and graces of the spirit</hi>) are vtterlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie to be named the seauenth day after the meanest of those, whom they so deepely <hi>disable:</hi> what may we imagine should hale them headlong an end in such <hi>a disgracing course,</hi> but only some <hi>phrentike,</hi> some <hi>furious,</hi> or some <hi>carnall spirit?</hi> sith the <hi>holie spirit of truth</hi> hath told vs for <hi>truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>3.3.</hi>
      </note> that <hi>where there is nothing but enuying, but strife and diuisions, there the men themselues are yet carnall, and walke but as men.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>Againe, when as their published <hi>pamphlets</hi> are peste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red full of apparant <hi>contradictions,</hi> the one very cruellie giuing a countercheck, and cutting the <hi>throate</hi> of the other, as hereafter appeareth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> King. <hi>22.22.</hi> Ioh. <hi>8.44.</hi>
      </note> how may we iustlie imagine that any other then <hi>an erronious and a lying spirit</hi> should be the <hi>primarie inditor</hi> thereof:<note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>14.17.</hi>
      </note> seeing the <hi>holie spirit of God, is the spirit of truth,</hi> euermore but one and the same, and <hi>leadeth men alwayes into all soundnes of truth and Religion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, when as they do nothing in effect, but accuse and sclaunder throughout their seuerall <hi>pamphlets</hi> they care not whome:<note place="margin">Reuel. <hi>12.10.</hi>
      </note> what drawes them thereto, but a <hi>diuellish satanicall spirit?</hi> sith the <hi>Diuell</hi> (you know) hath euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more beene <hi>the accuser of our brethren.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If they haplie imagine, that those whom they <hi>accuse</hi> or <hi>slaunder,</hi> are but <hi>beasts</hi> and no <hi>brethren</hi> at all: we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, that is much more then they are able to know, and we hold them no <hi>competent Iudges,</hi> concerning such <hi>cases</hi> especially as the <hi>Lord</hi> hath purposely reserued to his <hi>proper Consistorie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>29.29.</hi>
      </note> and appropriated wholly to his <hi>owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment seate.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neither shall it suffice to say, that (howsoeuer they be thought to accuse, or to slaunder) they speake but the <hi>truth</hi> of euery of them: because, if that were so indeede, yet they do it <hi>vntrulie,</hi> in as much as they do it only <hi>to reproch,</hi> and <hi>to slaunder the persons of men,</hi> and not <hi>to reforme</hi> their <hi>supposed disorders.</hi> For, neither do they proceede therein <hi>by a iudiciall course,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>20.16.</hi>
      </note> neither yet are they <hi>iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie</hi> called to testifie against them: and so, not only they breake the ninth commaundement, but (which more is) they do very daungerouslie <hi>scandalize the minds</hi> of so many in the land, as (being but ignorant before of those their falslie supposed <hi>crimes</hi>) are now (by their clamorous accusations) vncharitablie drawne into an hard conceit against their <hi>persons.</hi>
      <note place="margin">D. Doctrine, pag. <hi>86.</hi>
      </note> Whether this be not a <hi>diuellish Satanicall
<pb facs="8"/>
spirit,</hi> let <hi>M. Darel</hi> himselfe determine: who doth very confidently affirme, that so many as are giuen to <hi>cursing</hi> and <hi>lying,</hi> to <hi>speake euill of persons which are in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> to <hi>rayling, reuiling, sclaundering, hatred,</hi> and such like, they are vndoubtedlie <hi>the childrē of the Diuel,</hi> who himselfe <hi>was a liar,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>8.44.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>and a murderer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Briefly, when we behold them throughout their whole <hi>pamphlets,</hi> not only to impugne her Maiesties <hi>high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission</hi> concerning <hi>ecclesiasticall persons and causes,</hi> but (which more is) by <hi>toong,</hi> by <hi>penne,</hi> by <hi>practize,</hi> and such other apparant shewes of <hi>vndutifull subiects,</hi> to resist her highnesse authoritie, and (which is worst of all) euen then to accomplish euerie of these, when they were by <hi>God forbidden,</hi> by her <hi>highnesse restrayned,</hi> by due <hi>order of lawe conuented, conuicted, apprehended, impriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> by the sentence of <hi>Iustice</hi> definitiuely condemned for <hi>grosse malefactors,</hi> adiudged to <hi>prison;</hi> and so conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie by <hi>God</hi> himselfe, by her excellent <hi>Maiestie,</hi> by course of <hi>lawe,</hi> by all good <hi>conscience,</hi> and by the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>practise</hi> of all <hi>holie Martyrs,</hi> enioined eftsoones to a <hi>dutifull silence:</hi> whence come these <hi>vnrulie procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> I pray you, but from such a <hi>rebellious spirit,</hi> as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>for feare,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.5.</hi>
      </note> nor for <hi>conscience</hi> can be made to <hi>subiect it selfe to Gods sacred ordinance,</hi> but prowdlie resisteth the same,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.2.3.4.</hi>
      </note> and so procureth the <hi>sword of Iustice</hi> to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheathed against themselues, and to <hi>take vengeance on them,</hi> as vnrulie and <hi>turbulent spirits?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus then, the <hi>truth</hi> of the <hi>premisses,</hi> is verie apparant you see, as well by the <hi>seuerall pamphlets,</hi> as by the <hi>spirit</hi> it selfe, which may well be supposed to be the <hi>indighter</hi> thereof. And therefore we would to <hi>God</hi> (good christian <hi>Readers</hi>) you could <hi>suffer vs a little in our foolishnes:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.1.2.3.4.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>and in very deede you do suffer vs.</hi> For, <hi>we are iealous ouer you with a godlie iealousie,</hi> because <hi>we labour
<pb facs="8"/>
to prepare you for one husband,</hi> and to <hi>present you as a pure virgin to Christ.</hi> Howbeit, we feare, <hi>least as the Serpent beguiled Euah through his subtiltie,</hi> so your <hi>minds</hi> should be <hi>corrupt from the simplicitie that is in Christ.</hi> For, if these men do <hi>preach another Iesus</hi> then him whom others haue <hi>preached before,</hi> or, if you receiue <hi>another spirit</hi> then that which you haue receiued; either yet <hi>an other Gospell</hi> then that which was taught you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: you might well haue admired their <hi>persons,</hi> approued their <hi>practises,</hi> and so desirouslie haue entertained their <hi>factious pamphlets.</hi> Notwithstanding, when there are no such <hi>matters</hi> at all as you haplie imagine, why haue they so stronglie <hi>bewitched your minds,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. <hi>3.1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>that you should not obey the truth, to whom Iesus Christ hath bin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in your sight, and among you crucified</hi>? They do ring in your eares, and would beare you in hand, that they only but <hi>display that authenticall power of the Lord,</hi> which others <hi>doe darken</hi>: as though all other saue onely themselues did daylie <hi>obscure the glorious scepter of Christ;</hi> and herein also (by the preposterous approbation of their <hi>vnderhand fauourets</hi>) they haue gotten a <hi>popular applause.</hi> But wherein will they not very fitlie resemble <hi>Sulpitius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Silla.</note> a man fearefully confect in all kind of mischiefe? who hauing (by the voyce of the <hi>vulgar sort</hi>) very peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torilie passed <hi>a Decree,</hi> that no <hi>Senatour</hi> should borow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue two hundred Crownes at the most, was found at his death to owe thirtie thousand himselfe. So surely, these men do seeme with the vulgar sort to dislike that any should <hi>dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the glorious power of the Lord:</hi> whereas they them selues <hi>do obscure it</hi> the most of all others. For (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they wholie pretend to <hi>vphold the kingdome of Christ</hi>) what do they else by those their <hi>iollie pretences,</hi> but <hi>couer themselues</hi> (as we say) <hi>with a wet sack?</hi> For, it will euidentlie appeare by the following <hi>discourses,</hi> that none haue more dangerouslie <hi>trampled downe the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb facs="9"/>
of Christ</hi> then themselues: and yet <hi>(as if the Crow had engendred the Swanne)</hi> these men forsooth, they will seeme now to <hi>build vp the dignitie they destroyed before.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Perhaps thou wilt say or surmize at the least, that we our selues (by omitting, and taking what part of their <hi>pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> might make most for our owne purpose) haue therein euen purposely <hi>maymed their writings,</hi> and foyled the very force of their <hi>cause.</hi> Our <hi>answer</hi> is this, we haue care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie <hi>quoted the page it selfe,</hi> from whence we do drawe our <hi>seuerall collections:</hi> and therefore, let the <hi>learned</hi> determine, whether we haue any where <hi>abstracted</hi> their <hi>pamphlets</hi> besides their <hi>purposed scope,</hi> or haue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise pretermitted any thing <hi>materiall,</hi> which might but (in shew) either mannage or further their <hi>cause:</hi> and <hi>God forbid,</hi> but that we should very willinglie acknowledge and redresse the offred wrong. In deede, we haue purposelie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted many <hi>impertinent vagaries, extrauagant speeches, idle excursions, needles dilatations, friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous amplifications,</hi> and <hi>humorous illustrations,</hi> which (like vnto vglie <hi>botches,</hi> and swelling <hi>tumours</hi>) do fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie disfigure the <hi>bodie</hi> it selfe, and are nothing <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,</hi> but meerely superfluous, because the very <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke</hi> it selfe whereon they seeme to be builded, is <hi>ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandie</hi> or weake to support such a <hi>combersome frame:</hi> very confidentlie concluding withall, that for vs to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere <hi>their nothing,</hi> with <hi>something,</hi> would be (in the iudgement of the learned) <hi>a labour worth nothing.</hi> For, what do they (by such their <hi>clamorous outcryes</hi>) but deale with their ignorant <hi>Readers,</hi> as the foolish <hi>huntsman</hi> deales with his <hi>hounds,</hi> who by his crying <hi>so, ho,</hi> before the game it selfe be <hi>on foote,</hi> or, first <hi>found</hi> at the least: do <hi>but set the vnskilfull hounds</hi> at an <hi>idle gaze.</hi> Our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonists</hi> in deede, they do keepe a clamorous coyle against the impugnings of any their pestilent <hi>practises,</hi> and tels i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="9"/>
in the eares of all the world, that (do the <hi>aduersaries</hi> what they are able) their <hi>wisedome</hi> forsooth,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>11.19.</hi>
      </note> it must <hi>and shall be iustified of all her children:</hi> as though they thought it but an easie matter <hi>to breake an Eele with their knee,</hi> or to build vp the <hi>roofe</hi> without <hi>a foundation.</hi> Howbeit, they haue herein verie earnestlie solicited sundrie of our <hi>honorable Iudges</hi> and <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and presumed to prescribe them their <hi>seuerall courses,</hi> concerning anie their <hi>iudiciall proceedings</hi> against their <hi>persons:</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting belike that they who take in hand to <hi>limit autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> are like vnto such as seeke <hi>to stay the course of the Sunne.</hi> They should rather acknowledge with <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that it is <hi>vnfitting for him who falleth, to lift vp: who knoweth nothing, to teach: who is disordered, to order: who is vnrulie, to rule: or, who cannot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe obey, to commaund obedience to others.</hi> It had beene much better for them to haue trulie learned their dutie to <hi>God</hi> and their <hi>Prince,</hi> before they had so prowdly presumed to <hi>pester the Church</hi> with such <hi>vndutifull and disordered Pamphlets.</hi> Howbeit, because they haue publisht abroade such perilous points without any respect of <hi>Princes authoritie,</hi> or due regard of the <hi>Churches peace:</hi> it shall not be amisse to tell to their faces, that they haue therefore iustlie deserued the selfesame recompence, which <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> gaue to his friend <hi>Vetronius Turmius:</hi> namely, <hi>vt fumo pereant, qui fumum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt,</hi> that they perish with smoake, who sell forth smoake. For what other thing else do they set forth <hi>to sale,</hi> but such <hi>fuming smoke,</hi> as is readie to breake forth into <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous firie flames?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Beware therefore good christian <hi>Reader,</hi> that thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease not <hi>the fire</hi> alreadie kindled, <hi>by blowing a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar applause into the wide open eares</hi> of any those <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent spirits.</hi> Be not too credulous or rash in intertayning their <hi>Bookes</hi> as the approued <hi>oracles of Apollo Pythius
<pb facs="10"/>
at Delphos.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Seneca. <hi>1.</hi> Thes. <hi>5.21.22.23.24.</hi>
      </note> Know this for a certaine, <hi>that euerie light beliefe is none other thing else but a foolish docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Therefore, <hi>try all things,</hi> and <hi>keepe that which is good: abstayne from all appearance of euill.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now the verie <hi>God of peace sanctifie you through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; and we pray God that your whole spirit, and soule and bodie may be kept blameles vnto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Iesus Christ. Faithfull is he which calleth you, who also will do it:</hi> Amen.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>15.30.31.</hi>
      </note>And now brethren, wee beseech you <hi>for our Lord Iesus Christs sake,</hi> and for <hi>the loue of the spirit,</hi> that you would <hi>striue together with vs, by prayers to God for vs:</hi> that we may be <hi>deliuered from them which are disobedient in Iudea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. <hi>9.6.</hi> Rom. <hi>15.33.</hi>
      </note> and, that <hi>our ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice which we haue to do at Ierusalem may be acceptable among the Saints of God.</hi> Thus the <hi>God of peace be with you all,</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing brethren assuredly in the Lord, and the Lord his vnworthiest on earth,<list>
            <item>IOHN DEACON. </item>
            <item> IOHN WALKER.</item>
         </list>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>