<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Lectori.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109548_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20092</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6532</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109548</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Lectori.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhore of Babylon : As it was acted by the Princes Seruants. Written by Thomas Dekker</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Trundle, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Lectori.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall scope of this Drammaticall Poem, is to set forth (in Tropicall and shadowed collours) the Greatnes, Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, Constancy, Clemency, and other the incomparable Heroical vertues of our late Queene And (on the contrary part) the inueterate malice, Treasons, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations Vnderminings, &amp; continual blody stratagems, of that Purple whore of Roome, to the taking away of our Princes liues, and vtter extirpation of their Kingdomes. Wherein if accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the dignity of the Subiect, I haue not giuen it Lustre, and (to vse the Painters rhethorick) doe so faile in my Depthes &amp; Heightnings, that it is not to the life, let this excuse me; that the <hi>Pyramides</hi> vpon whose top the glorious Raigne of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased Soueraigne was mounted, stands yet so high, and so sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pointed into the clouds, that the Art of no pen is able to reach it. The streame of her Vertues is so immēsurable, that the farther they are waded into, the farther is it to the bottom.</p>
   <p>In sayling vpon which two contrary Seas, you may obserue, on how direct a line I haue steered my course: for of such a scant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are my words set downe, that neither the one party speakes too much, nor the other (in opposition) too little in their owne defence.</p>
   <p>And whereas I may, (by some more curions in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nsure, then sound in iudgement) be Critically taxed, that I falsifie the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of time, and set not down Occurrents, according to their true succession, let such (that are so nice of stomach) know, that I write as a Poet, not as an Historian, and that these two doe not
<pb facs="3"/>
liue vnder one law. How true Fortunes dyall hath gone whose Players (like so many clocks, haue struck my lines, and told the world how I haue spent my houres) I am not certaine, because mine eare stood not within reach of their Larums. But of this my knowledge cannot faile, that in such Consorts, many of the Instruments are for the most partout of tune, And no maruaile; for let the Poet set the note of his Nombers, euen to <hi>Apolloes</hi> owne Lyre, the Player will haue his owne Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets, and sing false notes, in dispite of all the rules of Musick. It fares with these two, as it does with good stuffe and a badde Tayler: It is not mard in the wearing, but in the cutting out. The labours therfore of Writers are as vnhappie as the children of a bewtifull woman, being spoyld by ill nurses, within a month after they come into the world. What a number of throwes doe we endure eare we be deliuered? and yet euen then (tho that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly issue of our braine be neuer so faire and so well lymd,) is it made lame by the bad handling of them to whome it is put to learne to goe: if this of mine bee made a cripple by such meanes, yet dispise him not for that deformity which stuck not vpon him at his birth; but fell vpon him by mis-fortune, and in recompence of such favour, you shall (if your Patience can suffer so long) heare now how himselfe can speake.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>