<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109860_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06971</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17395</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109860</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The teares of the beloued: or, The lamentation of Saint Iohn, concerning the death and passion of Christ Iesus our sauiour. By I.M</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>E seemeth, the same, who had so reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute a purpose to enlarge our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours suffring, tooke on him a weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some and needelesse iourney (for that he left the most sacred Scriptures) and made inquirie after <hi>Codrus,</hi> that was sometime King of Athens: which <hi>Codrus,</hi> begirt with a strong siege of the Peloponesians, hazarded his best health for his cities good. For though the example appeareth to hold in our head Christ, and their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, because both beare the titles of Kings; else in this, for that both died for the good of their people: Yet questionlesse, the oddes betwixt both are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull: for what is the shaddow to the substance? A King for a small time, to a King beyond all time? the one a creature, the other a Creator? The one for a few, but our King from before all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, to the end of the world, is that Lambe of God, &amp;c. Leauing the one which was finite, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thee (courteous reader) to the same who is as he
<pb facs="3"/>
euer hath beene, and will be, infinite in his fauors to those that are his: And I offer thee my harsh and vntuned muse, which being as my talent is, slender and simple, so accompt of the first part, that I may not be discomfited in the second. The highest conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue his fauours and graces vnto his Church, and shield vs in these dangerous dayes, from his and our enemies, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine vndoubtedly, <hi>I. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>