<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right Noble, Algernon, Lord Percy, sonne and heire apparant to the right Ho∣norable Henry Earle of Nor∣thumberland.</title>
           <author>Davies, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109342_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69177</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6332</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right Noble, Algernon, Lord Percy, sonne and heire apparant to the right Ho∣norable Henry Earle of Nor∣thumberland.</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Humours heau'n on earth : with the ciuile warres of death and fortune. As also the triumph of death: or, the picture of the plague, according to the life; as it was in anno Domini. 1603. By Iohn Dauies of Hereford</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 41, 142-248, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right Noble, Algernon, <hi>Lord</hi> Percy, sonne and heire apparant to the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Henry Earle of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THrice Noble, and more hopefull Pupill I</l>
      <l>(Who learnes thy Hand to shew thy Hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits</l>
      <l>Would make thy heart, before it Vice doth trie,</l>
      <l>To know her Lures, to shunne her slie deceits.</l>
      <l>But, in the Prime but of thy Pupillage</l>
      <l>Before the ioynts of <hi>Iudgement</hi> can be knit,</l>
      <l>(Although for Wit thou mai'st be Wisedomes Page)</l>
      <l>Vice throwes her Lures aboue thy reach of Wit.</l>
      <l>But yet when Time shall throwly close thy Mould,</l>
      <l>Wherein all rare Conceits still cast shall bee,</l>
      <l>Then shalt thou (with cleere eies) darke lines behold,</l>
      <l>That leade thee to all knowledge fit for thee.</l>
      <l>And, sith that Childhood more in Tales delights</l>
      <l>Then saddest Truths; Ile tell thee merry Tales,</l>
      <l>Of Lords and Ladies, with their merry Knights,</l>
      <l>Their merry Blisses, and their sory Bales.</l>
      <l>The outside of these Tales are painted o're</l>
      <l>With colours rich, to please thine eagre sence;</l>
      <l>But, lin'd with naked Truth (yet richly poore)</l>
      <l>More fit for thy more rich <hi>Intelligence.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>When thou canst cracke this Nut, within the Shell</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>Thou shalt a Kernell finde will please thy Taste;</l>
      <l>The Pallate of thy Wit will like it well,</l>
      <l>When thou shalt swallow it, for ioy, in haste.</l>
      <l>Then make this Nut a whirligigge the while,</l>
      <l>To make thee merry (if thou canst be so)</l>
      <l>To see the turning of our Sports to toile,</l>
      <l>Wherein obserue how pleasures come and go:</l>
      <l>For, as a whirligigge doth turne so fast,</l>
      <l>That sharpest sights the fruit do scarse perceiue:</l>
      <l>So can no Pallate fruits of Pleasure taste</l>
      <l>When they are come, so soone they take their leaue!</l>
      <l>Read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> little Lord, this Riddle learne to reede;</l>
      <l>So, first appose; then, tell it to thy Pecres:</l>
      <l>So shall they hold thee (both in Name and Deed)</l>
      <l>A perfect <hi>Pierc-ey</hi> that in darkenesse cleeres.</l>
      <l>A <hi>Pierc-ey,</hi> or a pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rcing Eie doth sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>w</l>
      <l>Both Wit and Courage; and, if thou wilt learne</l>
      <l>By morall Tales sinnes mortall to eschew,</l>
      <l>Thou shalt be wise, and endlesse glorie earne:</l>
      <l>That so thou mai'st, the meanest Tutors praise;</l>
      <l>So, Percies fame shall pierce the Eie of Daies:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then, by those Raies my Pen (inflam'd) shall runn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>Beyond the Moone, to make thy Moone a Sunne!</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Meane while, and euer, I rest prest to honour thee with my poore vttermost, Iohn Dauies.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>