<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Mr D. BLENCOW, Dr of the Civill Law, and Provost of ORIEL COLLEDGE in Ox∣ford: and to the FELLOWES, FELLOW-COMMONERS, and STV∣DENTS there: As also TO THE REST OF THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL, WORSHIPFVLL, AND Others, of the Parish of St Maries, Prospe∣ritie and Welfare, both in Body, and in Soule.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109429_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19986</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6426</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109429</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Mr D. BLENCOW, Dr of the Civill Law, and Provost of ORIEL COLLEDGE in Ox∣ford: and to the FELLOWES, FELLOW-COMMONERS, and STV∣DENTS there: As also TO THE REST OF THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL, WORSHIPFVLL, AND Others, of the Parish of St Maries, Prospe∣ritie and Welfare, both in Body, and in Soule.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Day's festiuals or, twelve of his sermons : deliuered by him at seueral times to the parishioners of St Maryes in Oxford, on the three chiefe festivals of the yeere, Christmas, Easter, and Whit-sontide. Three of vvhich sermons, are touching our Saviour; one, the Holy Ghost; two, the two sacraments; the other six, such severall duties, as belong to the severall sorts of all Christians</title>
                 <author>Day, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 352 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> D. BLENCOW, D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> of the <hi>Civill Law,</hi> and <hi>Provost</hi> of ORIEL COLLEDGE in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford:</hi> and to the FELLOWES, FELLOW-COMMONERS, and STV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENTS there: As also TO THE REST OF THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, WORSHIPFVLL, AND Others, of the <hi>Parish</hi> of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Maries,</hi> Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and Welfare, both in <hi>Body,</hi> and in <hi>Soule.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now well neere <hi>Six Yeeres</hi> since, Right Worshipfull, and dearely Beloued, that I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto you at the <note n="a" place="margin">Christ-mas Day, Decem. 25, 1609.</note> first, of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids desire to goe to Church.</hi> An Argumēt (it might be thought) more befitting our <hi>Recusants,</hi> then any of our owne Sort, and such as are <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> but who so wil visit our <hi>Parish Churches</hi> in time of <hi>Divine Service</hi> on the <hi>Weeke-daies</hi> throughout the Yeare, I meane <hi>Wedensdaies, Frydaies,</hi> and <hi>Saterdaies,</hi> &amp; that in populous <hi>Townes,</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> (to say nothing of the <hi>Country,</hi> where they may seeme to haue some excuse by reason of dwelling farre from <hi>Church</hi>) shall find too too often, two sufficient Witnesses, the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> &amp; the <hi>Clarke,</hi> that <hi>Protestants</hi> even <hi>Protestants,</hi> are almost as peccant in this kind as <hi>Popish Recusants</hi> themselues. Herevnto if wee adde withall the prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterous zeale of a <hi>Many</hi> besides, who vnlesse there be <hi>Sermons</hi> too, will scarse bee there on the <hi>Saboth Day,</hi> seldome or never on <hi>Holydayes,</hi> and they of the <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser Sort,</hi> and who will take it in some snuffe, if wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them not more <hi>Religious,</hi> then the <hi>Meyny,</hi> or Multitude are, and what may wee thinke <hi>Religion</hi> it selfe, will come to even in our <hi>Daies,</hi> who so little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of DIVINE SERVICE, so <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ne contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui essent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes Ecclesiae Preces, eas splen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>didis elogiis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim Deus orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit: praesertim vbi Templum Vocavit Domū Orationis. Nam &amp; praecipuam Cultus sui par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem hac voce docuit esse Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi Officium, at{que} vt in eose Fideles vno cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sensu exerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rēt, instar Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illi erectum illis fuisse Templum.</hi> Calvin. Instit <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 20. §. 29.</note> principall an <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise</hi> of the same. This it was that made me at the first, as to preach that <hi>First</hi> Sermon of <hi>Davids Desire</hi> to the <note n="c" place="margin">Novemb. 5. in the <hi>After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone,</hi> 1609.</note>
      <hi>Vniversitie,</hi> so to Preach the <hi>Second</hi> to <hi>Your selues:</hi> and after that for your sakes to commit them <hi>Both</hi> vnto the <hi>Presse.</hi> From whence that they came to <hi>You,</hi> and in a manner to <hi>You</hi> onely, and not to the <hi>Church</hi> in generall: it was for I would endeauour to be <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 25.23.</note>
      <hi>Faithfull in a little,</hi> and in these perillous backsli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Times as much as may be, to <note n="e" place="margin">Cant. 1.5.</note>
      <hi>Keep my own Vine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Since that time it hath pleased the Lord, towards the Furtherance of your Salvation, to put other <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sages</hi> into my Mouth, all which as they were at diuers and sundry times related vnto <hi>You,</hi> I meane as many of you as could cōveniently be present, so haue J bin at a second Paines to deliver them now vnto you all, that no exception may be taken of not hauing heard what hath beene spoken. <hi>When a man hath done his best</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Ecclus. 18.6.</note> saith the Sonne of Syrach, <hi>he must begin againe, and when he thinketh to come to an end; he must againe to his
<pb facs="3"/> labour.</hi> I dare be bould to say that to <hi>Print</hi> is to begin againe, he knowes not what Printing is that knowes it not to be a <hi>Labour.</hi> It was as <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Calvin. Praef. in Esay, &amp; in Esay. c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Calvin</hi> obserues the Custome of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> after they had spoaken to <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> to make a <hi>Brief</hi> of what they had spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and to fasten it on the <hi>Gates</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> where it was to stand some certaine daies to the veiw of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>One</hi> that would pervse it. <hi>Printing</hi> is that in our Age, which that kind of <hi>Publishing</hi> was in theirs, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Vnsavorie Pamphlets</hi> haue beene so many, that haue passed the <hi>Presse</hi> aswell as <hi>Sermons,</hi> as that it makes vs (a <hi>Many</hi> at the least) esteeme no more of having <hi>Sermons</hi> printed, then it did the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> of those three Miracles which <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> wrought, namely the <note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 7.11,</note>
      <hi>Serpent,</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">V. 22.</note>
      <hi>Bloud,</hi> and <note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 8.7.</note>
      <hi>Frogs,</hi> which their <hi>Inchaunters</hi> wrought aswell as they. You, I trust, are otherwise minded, &amp; will be towards these <hi>Sermons,</hi> the rather for they cal to mind what the most of you haue heard, and some haue beene desirous to haue in this sort: as also for they are more <hi>Compleat</hi> then when they were first delivered to you, by reason of the <hi>Marginall Noats</hi> annexed therevnto. It is <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Mountaignes Essayes l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 25</note> said of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> that in <hi>Three Hundred Volumes</hi> which hee wrote, he made no vse of any one <hi>Allegatiō</hi> at all. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius</hi> borrowed much, but acknowledged not his <hi>Creditors,</hi> and therefore is <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Macrobius homo satis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eruditus, sed ingenio max<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>imè ingrato, at propè impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti: vt qui in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Aeris alieni cumulo nusquā Creditoris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mē profiteatur.</hi> P. Crinitus De honest. Discipl. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>c</hi> 4. For an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the first Booke of his <hi>Saturnalia,</hi> with <hi>Seneca</hi> his <hi>Seaven</hi> &amp; <hi>Fortith</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle.</note> taxed as <hi>Vngratefull</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue measure. They that list to follow the <hi>One,</hi> or the <hi>Others</hi> Example, let them: J professe, I like neither, but had rather say with that never enough praised <note n="o" place="margin">My Lord of London vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Ionas, <hi>Lect.</hi> 40. <hi>p.</hi> 552.</note>
      <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> vpon <hi>Ionas, I never could be bould to offer mine own
<pb facs="4"/> Inventions, and Conceipts to the World, when I haue found them such in S. Augustine, and Others, as might not bee amended.</hi> And hence it was, as that worthy PRELATE there <note n="*" place="margin">So, B. Iuel: Origen, <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Ecclesiarū:</hi> Basil, <hi>Canon Fidei:</hi> Eusebi{us} Samo satensis <hi>Regula verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> Athanasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>Orbis Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi> B. Iuel De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Apol. <hi>Part.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Divis.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 765.</note> observeth, that S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Cyprian</hi> called <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> his Maister; that S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Cyprian</hi> himselfe by S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten,</hi> was reputed in the nomber of most excellent Men; that S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Austen</hi> was tearmed the Hammer of Heretickes; that <hi>Athanasius</hi> called S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Ambrose</hi> the Eie of the World; that <hi>Athanasius</hi> was called by the World it selfe, <hi>Athanasius</hi> the Great. Besides, that the <hi>Quoting</hi> in this sort, referres such <hi>Novices</hi> as shal read my <hi>Bookes,</hi> to the principall <hi>Places</hi> themselues where they may read of the Matter more at large, a necessary Helpe to young <hi>Students,</hi> such as a many were that heard mee, and to whom, as to the more <hi>Learned</hi> among you, these <hi>Labours</hi> of mine are now dedicated.</p>
   <p>I should here write more vnto you, but that my <hi>Portion</hi> of <hi>Paper</hi> allotted mee to the selfe same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, is now farre spent, and indeed what need I write vnto <hi>You</hi> now more, who both <hi>Write</hi> and <hi>Speake</hi> vnto <hi>You,</hi> in all that followeth. I, as it was <note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> said of <hi>Abel,</hi> that <hi>By Faith being dead, hee yet speaketh:</hi> so I trust that ETERNALL WORD, who hath beene the <hi>Fountaine</hi> of all this, will permit mee even when I am <hi>Dead,</hi> to <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Praedicandi scientia est quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammodo An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica vtrovis modo iuvans, seu per</hi> Manū, <hi>seu per Linguā operetur.</hi> Clem Alex. Strom. <hi>l.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>speak</hi> vnto <hi>You</hi> by these <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> and not vnto <hi>You</hi> onely, but also vnto <hi>Yours,</hi> to whom <hi>Your Selues</hi> shall leaue them as a <hi>Legacy.</hi> This if his <hi>Great Goodnesse</hi> shall grant vnto mee, it is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of this World, the <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Summa Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum attigi.</hi> Senec. Thyest <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Sc. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualu.</hi>
      </note> vtmost of my <hi>VVishes▪</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> And it shall more content me at my parting from it, to haue beene in this kinde a <hi>Speaker</hi> thus, then to haue gone even in this <hi>Age,</hi> the <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Dealbatiores Vias saeculi.</hi> Aug. Confess. <hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note>
      <hi>Milky way</hi> of much <hi>Preferment.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. Confess. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> DOMINE, <hi>miserere mei, &amp; exaudi Desideriū meum. Puto enim quod non sit de Terra, non de Auro, &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gento, aut de Lapidibus, aut decoris Vestibus, aut Honori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; Potestatibus, aut Voluptatibus Carnis, ne{que} de Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarijs Corporis, &amp; huic Vitae Peregrinationis nostrae, quae omnia nobis</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note>
      <hi>apponuntur quaerentibus Regnum, &amp; Iustitiam tuam. Vide Domine Deus meus, vnde sit Desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derium meum.</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">Ps. 118.85.</note>
      <hi>Narraverunt mihi Iniusti Delectatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes suas, sed non sicut Lex tua Domine. Ecce vnde est De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderium meum. Vide Pater, aspice, &amp; vide, &amp; approba, &amp; placeat in conspectu Misericordiae tuae, invenire me Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ante te, vt aperiantur pulsanti mihi interiora Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monum tuorum. Obsecro per Dominum Nostrum</hi> JESVM CHRISTVM <hi>Filium tuum, Virum Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terae tuae, Filium Hominis, quem confirmasti tibi Mediatorem tuum &amp; nostrum, per quem nos quaesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti non quaerentes te, quaesisti autem vt quaereremus te: Verbum tuum per quod fecisti omnia, in quibus &amp; me, Vnicum tuum per quem vocasti in adoptionem, Populum Credentium, in quo &amp; me, per eum te obsecro qui</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8.34.</note>
      <hi>sedet ad Dexteram tuam, &amp; te interpellat pro nobis, in quo sunt omnes</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">Coloss. 2.3.</note>
      <hi>Thesauri Sapientiae &amp; Scientiae absconditi.</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">Rev. 1.6.</note>
      <hi>Ipsi Gloria, &amp; Imperium, in saecula saeculorum,</hi> AMEN.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>