<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO ALL GRATIOVS,
Vertuous, Courteous, Honest,
Learned, and gentle spirits, that are
truely poeticall, &amp; not too fantasticall:
that will patiently read, indifferently cen∣sure,
and honestly speake of the labours
of those wits that meane nothing
but well, the writer hereof wish∣eth
all contentment, that
a good conditiō may
desire.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109105_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16765</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3672</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109105</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO ALL GRATIOVS,
Vertuous, Courteous, Honest,
Learned, and gentle spirits, that are
truely poeticall, &amp; not too fantasticall:
that will patiently read, indifferently cen∣sure,
and honestly speake of the labours
of those wits that meane nothing
but well, the writer hereof wish∣eth
all contentment, that
a good conditiō may
desire.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>No vvhippinge, nor trippinge: but a kinde friendly snippinge</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Deane, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶TO ALL GRATIOVS,
Vertuous, Courteous, Honest,
Learned, and gentle spirits, that are
truely poeticall, &amp; not too fantasticall:
that will patiently read, indifferently cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
and honestly speake of the labours
of those wits that meane nothing
but well, the writer hereof wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
all contentment, that
a good conditiō may
desire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good friendes, if such yee be;
if not, God blesse me from yee;
for the world is so full of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
that a man can meete with
little goodnesse: Maye it please
you to vnderstand, that it was my happe of late,
passing through Paules Church yarde, to looke
vpon certaine pieces of Poetrye, where I found
(that it greeues me to speake of) one writer so
<pb facs="3"/>
straungely inueigh against another, that many
shallow wits stoode and laught at their follies.
Now, findinge their labours so toucht with ill
tearms, as befitted not the learned to lay open,
I thought good, hauing little to doe, to write
vnto all such writers, as take pleasure to see
their wits plaie with the world, that they will
henceforth, before they fall to worke, haue in
minde this good prouerbe: <hi>Play with mee; but
hurt me not: and iest with me; but disgrace
me not;</hi> Least that the world this iest do kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
smother, Why should one foole be angry with
an other? Now for my selfe, I proteste that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
of Charitie, that I wish to finde at all their
handes that see and will reprooue my folly: for
I am none of the seauen wise men, and for the
eight, I knowe not where to seeke him. Beare
with me then, if out of the principles of a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
cloth I haue pickt out matter to mooue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience.
And if there be any thing out of that
poore library, that may take place in any of your
good likings, I will honour your good spirits for
your kinde acceptations. But, in any wise, what
ere you think, giue me no word of cōmendation:
least, too glad of such a mischaunce, I trust the
<pb facs="3"/>
better to my euill fortune. Well, in earnest, I
will entreat all good schollers to beare with
my lacke of learning, and wise men with my
lacke of witte, and my creditors with my lacke
of mony. Which, though it haue nothing to doe
in this Treatise, yet entreaty sometime doeth
well with honest mindes: which I wish, and hope
of in them, yea, and all the world that I shall
haue to doe withall. Leauing therefore the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
to their Paradice, and the displeased to
their better patience, in my loue to all schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
(but chiefly to those, that in the ioy of their
studies, make vertue their heauen) I Rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend, as I finde cause.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>