<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most reuerende Father in God, Iohn by the diuine prouidence, Archbyshoppe of Canterbury, Metrapolytane of England, hys Grace, and one of her Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell: Rychard Cromp∣ton wysheth euerlasting felicitie. (∴)</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109080_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19623</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6055</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109080</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most reuerende Father in God, Iohn by the diuine prouidence, Archbyshoppe of Canterbury, Metrapolytane of England, hys Grace, and one of her Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell: Rychard Cromp∣ton wysheth euerlasting felicitie. (∴)</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short declaration of the ende of traytors, and false conspirators against the state : &amp; of the duetie of subiectes to theyr soueraigne gouernour: and wythall, howe necessarie, lawes and execution of iustice are, for the preseruation of the prince and common wealth. Wherein are also breefely touched, sundry offences of the S. Queene, co [m] mitted against the crowne of this land, &amp; the manner of the honorable proceding for her conuiction thereof, and also the reasons &amp; causes alledged &amp; allowed in Parliament, why it was thought dangerous to the state, if she should haue liued. Published by Richard Crompton, an apprentice of the common lawes. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Crompton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most reuerende Father in <hi>God, Iohn by the diuine prouidence,</hi> Archbyshoppe of Canterbury, Metrapolytane of England, hys Grace, and one of her Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell: Rychard Cromp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton wysheth euerlasting felicitie. (∴)</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch (most reuerend Father) as these dayes are very dangerous, and full of perill, in which wickednes hath so deepely entred into the hartes of manye, who not hauing the feare of GOD before theyr eyes, nor regarde to the faith and loyaltie, which euery Subiecte ought to beare to his soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Gouernour, nor respect to the zeale and loue that euery good manne naturally ought to carie to his natiue soyle and Country, haue in these dayes so often entred into such wycked trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and conspiracies as well against her Maiesties sacred personne, as also this most happy gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the like hath not beene hearde of in the
<pb facs="3"/>
raigne of any her noble Progenitors, Princes of thys Lande, sithence the Conquest thereof vnto this day. And for that the same hath beene preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to bee for matters touching Religion, I haue therefore set down in this smal Treatise, the mysera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble end &amp; confusion of dyuers, which within our memory among vs most iustly haue suffered, for such their wicked conspiracies and treasons, and withall, the duties of Subiects to theyr Prince and soueraigne Gouernour, both which, at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sessions of the Peace, in the Countie of Staff: among other thinges pertayning to that seruice, I lately published, as a matter which I thought then much necessary for this present time, to the ende, that the one, might be a terror to all men to offende in the like, and the other, an instruction in the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; obedience, which euery good Subiect ought to embrace. And because some of that audience seemed (as they sayd) to like wel therof, &amp; thought it in theyr opinions conuenient to bee made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all men, I haue at theyr request thought good to publish the same. And forasmuch as no Kingdome nor Common wealth can stand, where good Lawes are not established, and Iustice exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, I haue therefore also heerein sette downe in parte, the commodities and profittes which grow to the same thereby. And because the Lawes of themselues are dombe thinges, remayning in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes, Bookes and Customes, and must therefore be published and put in execution by officers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb facs="3"/>
appointed, I haue shewed what personnes they ought to bee, which shoulde bee called to sitte in place of Iustice, and to whom the trust and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidence of the execution of Lawes ought to bee committed, and what great care they ought to haue to performe the same: and withall haue tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the duties of Iurors, and what regarde they ought to haue of theyr oathes, verdytts and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentments, sith that without them, iustice cannot be doone vppon offenders, &amp; transgressors of Law cannot be punished. And am bolde vnder your Graces fauour, to present these fewe leaues to the same, as to one, who I am assured wysheth well to this whole state, and daylie prayeth for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of her Maiestie, whom God of his mercie long preserue and continue vnto vs. From the Myddle Temple, the xij. of Februarie. 1587. (∴)</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>At the commaundement</hi> of your Grace most humbly.
R. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>