<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader. To all them that either reade or heare gods holy worde / and geue ouer them selues to lyue vnfan∣nedly acording to the same / do I hartely wysshe the grace / peace and mercy of god the father in and thorow oure lorde and one∣ly Sauioure Ie∣sus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1541</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109263_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19466</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5888</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109263</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader. To all them that either reade or heare gods holy worde / and geue ouer them selues to lyue vnfan∣nedly acording to the same / do I hartely wysshe the grace / peace and mercy of god the father in and thorow oure lorde and one∣ly Sauioure Ie∣sus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutacion of that treatise, which one Iohn Standish made agaynst the protestacion of D. Barnes in the yeare. M.D.XL : Wherin, the holy scriptures (peruerted and wrested in his sayd treatise) are restored to their owne true vnderstonding agayne by Myles Couerdale</title>
                 <author>Coverdale, Miles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Froschauer, Christoph 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Switzerland--Zurich</pubPlace>
                    <date>1541</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>208 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader. To all them that either reade or heare gods holy worde / and geue ouer them selues to lyue vnfan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly acording to the same / do I hartely wysshe the grace / peace and mercy of god the father in and thorow oure lorde and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauioure Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ.</head>
   <p>THe seuenth daye of Decembre / was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered vnto me a certayne treatyse / compo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed by one Iohn Standish Felow of Whitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton college in londō (so is the tytle of it) and pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by Robert Redeman / Anno M. D. XL. iij. Nonas Octobris. At the reading wherof I mourned sore within my selfe for certayne oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions offred vnto me in the sande treatyse. First that vnder the Kynges priuilege any thing shuld be set forth / which is either agaynst the worde and trueth of allmightye god / or agaynst the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges honoure. Secondlye / that good / wholsome / and Christen wordes shulde be calumpniated and reuyled. Thirdly / that the sayde Iohn Standish pronouncyng Doctoure Barnes to haue taught heresye so longe / is not ashamed all this whyle to haue hold his penne / but now first to wryte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst him / whan he is deed. et ce.</p>
   <p>As touching the first / whether I haue cause to mourne or no / I reporte me to all true Christen hertes. for (as I am credibly enfourmed / <note place="margin">Diuersyte amonge wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters.</note> and as I partly haue sene) there is now a wonderful diuersite in writing bokes and balates in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb facs="3"/>
/ one enueyenge agaynst another / one reuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and reprouyng another / one reioysinge at anothers fall and aduersite. And not onely this / but also at the ende of euery balate or boke in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (whether it be the better partye or worse) is set the Kynges priuilege. Which as it is aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynst the glorye of god that one shulde reuyle ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / Is it not euen so agaynst the Kynges ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure (Yee the shame is it of all Englande) that vnder his priuilege anye erroneous / conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious / or slaunderous boke or papyre shulde be prynted? Men wonder in other contrees / that ther is so greate negligence of this matter / in a realme where so wyse and prudent a counsail is▪ And they that are moued with godly compassiō / do lament Englande. sory / that ther is so great discencion in it.<note place="margin">Tryfles are prynted with the Kynges priuilege / vnknowing to him.</note> sory / that blasphemous ieasting / and raylinge balates or bokes agaynst the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest worde of god / shulde either be suffred or priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legied. sory / that gods trueth shulde thus spiteful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be intreated of so greate a nombre. Now the reformacion of this and all other defaultes lyeth onely in the hande of god / To whom I referre it / and to the rightfull admynistracion of his holy ordinaūce and auctorite in the kynges hyghnesse. who / whan he knoweth of the saide inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (how tryflinge and raylinge bokes and rymes are prynted vnder his priuilege) wyll no doubte set a redresse herein.</p>
   <p>Concernyng the seconde occasion aboue rehear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="3"/>
Is it not cause ynough forme and all other Christen / to be right sory / to mourne and lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / that the wordes which are good / wholsome / and acordinge to the holy scripture and Chrisies faith / shulde be either blasphemed or taken to the worst? Yf the Kynges grace / shulde put forthe an wholsome proclamacion / iniunction or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement (as he doth many) what true sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte louynge gods holy ordinaunce and auctori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in his prynce / wold not be greue to se anye man either spytt at those his soueraignes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / or to defye them? Yf we now which are Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten / haue so iust occsion (and are bownde) to be thus wise mynded in this outward regiment / wherein god hath appoynted us to be obedient to the hyer powers / how much more cause haue we to water our eyes with sory hertes / whan the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clamacion / iniunction / <note place="margin">Good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed.</note> cōmaundement and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of him which is kyng of all Kynges and lord of all lordes / is thus reuyled and euell spoken of? That the wordes of. D. Barnes spoken at tbe houre of his death / and here vnder written / are good / wholsome / acording to gods holy scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and not worthy to be euell taken / It shalbe eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dently sene / whan we haue layed thē to the twych stone / and tryed them by gods worde. To the open text wherof yf ye take good hede / ye shal se the peruerse doctryne and wycked opynions of Standish clerely confuted. And (no doubte) god wyll so haue it / because that vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb facs="4"/>
of bearing a zeale toward gods worde / he taketh apon him to be iudge and geuer of senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce agaynst gods worde / and to condemne it that gods worde aloweth.</p>
   <p>And this (as I sayde) is another cause of the sorynesse of my hert / that he which darre auo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we another man to be an opē heretike / is not asha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med thus longe nether to haue written / ner open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached agaynst him by name / but now to starte vp whan he is deed. Is it not a greate wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shippe for him to wrestle with a shadow / and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ll a deed man? Is he not a worthy souldyer that all the battayll tyme thrusteth his hand in his bosome / <note place="margin">St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ndish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yll a deed man.</note> and whan mē are deed / then draweth out his swerde / and fighteth with them that are slayne allreadye? Iudge ye (gentle readers) yf Standish playeth not such a parte with D. Bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / To whom also he imputeth treason / and yet proueth neuer a poynte therof agaynst him. Yet were it as charitable a dede to confute all treason and to geue us warnynge of it by name / as either to establishe false doctryne / or to enueye agaynst good sayenges. Yee a Christen and charitable acte were it in reprouyng anye traytoure / to tell the Kynges subiectes in what thing he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the treason / that they maye beware of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. But thus doth not Standishe here in this his treatise / which because it is buylded on sande and on a false foundaciō / I doubte not / but with gods worde (which is the swerde of the sprete / <note place="margin">Ephe. vj.</note>
      <pb facs="4"/>
and a weapen mighty / to ouerthrow euery yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginacion that exalteth it selfe agaynst the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of god) To geue it a fall / <note place="margin">ij. Corin. x.</note> and with holy scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to shewe euydently / that Standishe hath farre ouershott himselfe / in condemnynge the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enges which gods word doth not disalowe. He that wolde wryte agaynst anye man / shulde le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell his ordinaunce agaynst his euell wordes (yf he had spoken or written anye) and not agaynst his good wordes. ffor god is the authoure of all good / which as his holy scripture aloweth / so will he himselfe defende the same. He that is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an enemye to the thinge which is good / or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth it / is gods aduersary / and withstondeth him. Wherfore let Standish frō hensforth and all other beware / <note place="margin">Let no man take parte agaynst the trueth.</note> that they take no parte agaynst gods worde / ner defende any false matter / lest god be the auenger. ffor yf the lyon begynne to roare / he will make all his enemies afrayed.</p>
   <p>And yf. D. Barnes dyed a true Christen man / be ye sure / his death shalbe a greater stroke to ypocrisye / then euer his life coulde haue bene. Yf he was falsly accused to the Kynges high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse / and so put to death / woo shall come to tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se accusers / yf they repent not by tymes. And yf D. Barnes in his hert / mouth and dede / commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no worse thinge towarde the Kynges high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse / then he committed agaynst god in these his wordes at his death / he is like at the later daye to be a iudge ouer them / that were cause of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath yf they do not amende.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>Now (indifferent reader) to the intent that thou mayest the more clearly / discerne light frō darknesse / and knowe gods true worde from false docrine / I shall (whan I haue sayde somwhat to Standish preface) rehearce vnto the. D. Barnes wordes. Secondly though I rehearce not vnto the all Standish wordes (lest I shuld make to greate a boke) I shall poynte the to the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his sentence / requyring the (yf thou wilt) to reade out the rest thy selfe in his treatise. Third<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly though he hath desserued to be roughly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led / yet do I purpose (by gods onely grace) to dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le more gently with him beynge alyue / then he doth with the deed. This interpryse now as I ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in hand agaynst Standishe in this behalfe / so am I ready to do the same agaynst the greate graundsire and captaine of false teachers / I mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne greate Goliath of Rome and his weapen-bearer. That is / agaynst all such as are enemies to Kynge Dauid oure lorde Iesus Christ / for whose moost confortable sprete (gentle reader) I beseche the to praie with me vnto our moost deare father in heauen / whose name be praysid / whose kyngdome come / whose onely wyll be fulfilled now and euer Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>