<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The second Question.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109042_Fr1_5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17509</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4323.6</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109042</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The second Question.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Decimarum et oblationum tabula. = A tithing table : Or Table of tithes and oblations, according to the Kings ecclesiasticall lawes and ordinances established in the Church of England: now newly reduced into a booke. Contayning as well the very letter of the law vnder which these rights be seuerally comprised, together with such questions of tything, and their resolutions by the lawes canon, ciuill, and approued doctors opinions of the same, as be ordinarily moued, and which doe often proue to controuersies heerin: as also a briefe and summarie declaration of composition, transaction, custome, prescription, priuilege; and how they preuaile in tything. Compiled by W.C. Bach. of the Civill Lavv</title>
                 <author>Clark, William, Bachelor of civil law</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div n="2" type="question">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The second Question.</head>
   <list>
      <label>Decima De <hi>Siluis caeduis,</hi>
      </label>
      <item>i. Of woods felled; and preserved to grow againe.</item>
      <label>Decima De <hi>Lignis,</hi>
      </label>
      <item>i. Of wood not in vse, nor apt for Timber, but for fyring.</item>
      <label>Decima De <hi>Thenitijs agrorum,</hi>
      </label>
      <item>i. Of trees planted for fencing of grounds, in fields, pastures, and hedge-rowes.</item>
      <label>Decima De <hi>Turuis,</hi>
      </label>
      <item>i. Of Turues growing in fennish &amp; moorish soiles as in the Isle of <hi>Ely.</hi>
      </item>
   </list>
   <p n="1">1 Wood of 20. yeares growth and vpward, whether it bee tithable or not? And what of lopping of timber trees?</p>
   <p n="2">2 When woods be felled and sold, who shall answer the tith? the buyer, or the seller?</p>
   <p n="3">3 If the inheritance of a wood be sold, that is in arrerages for tyth, whom the Parson may implead?</p>
   <p n="4">4 Turues, amongst what tythes they be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned?</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>