<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORIE, To the nine Pernassian Sisters, The Conseruers of HELICON.</title>
           <author>Lithgow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109476_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15715</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109476</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORIE, To the nine Pernassian Sisters, The Conseruers of HELICON.</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrimes farewell, to his natiue countrey of Scotland : vvherein is contained, in way of dialogue, the ioyes and miseries of peregrination. With his Lamentado in his second trauels, his Passionado on the Rhyne, diuerse other insertings, and farewels, to noble personages, and, the heremites welcome to his third pilgrimage, &amp;c. Worthie to be seene and read of all gallant spirits, and pompe-expecting eyes. By William Lithgow, the bonauenture of Europe, Asia, and Africa, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Lithgow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Hart, Andro.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lithgow, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORIE, <hi>To the nine</hi> Pernassian <hi>Sisters,</hi> The Conseruers of HELICON.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou sacred <hi>Nymphes,</hi> which haunt <hi>Pernassus</hi> Hill,</l>
      <l>Where <hi>Soron</hi> flowes, and <hi>Demthis</hi> run at will:</l>
      <l>Out from your two-topt Valley shew me grace</l>
      <l>And on the lower Listes meete mee apace.</l>
      <l>Infuse in me the Veine, I gladlie craue,</l>
      <l>To sing the sadde FAREWELS my SOYLE must haue.</l>
      <l>And yee Supreames of this poore MUSE of mine,</l>
      <l>As Iudges justlie censure this Propine:</l>
      <l>I bring no Stones from <hi>Pactole,</hi> Orient Gemmes,</l>
      <l>Nor Bragges of <hi>Tagus,</hi> singes of Golden Stemmes:</l>
      <l>I search not <hi>Iris,</hi> square-spread clowdie VVinges,</l>
      <l>Nor of the strange <hi>Herculian Hydra</hi> singes,</l>
      <l>These Franticke Fansies, I account as vaine,</l>
      <l>In Vulgare Verse, my FAREVVELS I explaine.</l>
      <l>If I debord in Stropiate Lines, or then</l>
      <l>In Methode faile, attache my wandring Pen.</l>
      <l>This Veine of Nature, and a Mother VVit,</l>
      <l>Is more than haughtie Schollers well can hit.</l>
      <l>So this small Fondling, borne of your nine VVombes,</l>
      <l>Turnes backe, and in your Bosome her intombes.</l>
      <l>Then nurse your Youngling, and repurge her Veines,</l>
      <l>And sende her backe in haste, to yeelde mee Gaines.</l>
      <l>In doing this, to you, and to your Fame,</l>
      <l>I consecrate my Loue, and her new Name.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, longing to bee drunke of Helicon.
WILLIAM LITHGOW.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>