<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Glory of our owne, and griefe of other Nations.</title>
           <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109223_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14289</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109223</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Glory of our owne, and griefe of other Nations.</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The masque of queenes : celebrated from the house of fame: by the most absolute in all state, and titles. Anne Queene of Great Britaine, &amp;c. With her honourable ladies. At VVhite Hall, Febr. 2. 1609. Written by Ben: Ionson</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                            <distributor>Walley, Henry</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Glory of our owne, and griefe of other Nations.</head>
   <head type="sub">My Lord HENRY Prince of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN it hath beene my happinesse (as would it were more frequent) but to see your face, and, as passing by, to consider you; I haue with as much ioy, as I am now farre from flattery in professing it, cal'd to mind that doctrine of some great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitors in <hi>Nature,</hi> who hold euery royall &amp; <hi>heroique</hi> forme to partake and draw much to it of the heauenly vertue. For, whether it be that a diuine soule, being to come into a body, first chooseth a palace for it selfe; or, being come, doth make it so; or that <hi>Nature</hi> be ambitious to haue her worke equal; I know not: But what is lawful for me to vnderstand, &amp; speak, that I dare; which is, that both your <hi>Vertue</hi> &amp; your <hi>For me</hi> did deserue your <hi>Fortune.</hi> The one claim'd that you should bee borne a <hi>Prince,</hi> the other makes that you do become it. And when <hi>Necessity</hi> (excellent Lord) the mother of the <hi>Fates,</hi> hath so prouided, that your <hi>Forme</hi> should not more insinuate you to the eies of men, then your <hi>Vertue</hi> to their mindes: it comes neere a wonder to thinke how sweetly that habite flowes in you, and with so hourely testimonies, which to all posterity might hold the dignity of examples. Amongst the rest, your fauour to letters, and these gentler studies, that goe vnder the title of <hi>Humanitie,</hi> is not the least honor of your wreath. For, if once the worthy Prosessors of these learnings shall come (as heretofore they were) to be the care of <hi>Princes,</hi> the Crownes, their <hi>Soueraignes</hi> weare, will not more adorne their temples;
<pb facs="3"/>nor their stamps liue longer in their Medals, then in such subiects labours. <hi>Poetry,</hi> my Lord, is not borne with euery man; nor euery day: And in her generall right, it is now my minute to thanke your <hi>Highnesse,</hi> who not only do honor her with your eare, but are curious to examine her with your eye, and inquire into her beauties, and strengthes. Where though it hath prou'd a worke of some difficulty to me, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine the particular <hi>Authorities</hi> (according to your gracious command, and a desire borne out of iudgement) to those things, which I writ out of fulnesse, and memory of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer readings: yet, now I haue ouercome it, the reward, that meetes me, is double to one act: which is, that thereby your excellent vnderstanding will not onely iustifie me to your owne knowledge, but decline the stiffenesse of others origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ignorance, already arm'd to censure. For, which singular bounty, if my <hi>Fate</hi> (most excellent <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>onely Delicacy</hi> of <hi>Man-kind</hi>) shall reserue me to the Age of your Actions, whether in the Campe, or the Councell-chamber, that I may write, at nights, the deedes of your dayes: I will then labour to bring forth some worke as worthy of your fame, as my ambition therein is of your pardon.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By the most true admirer of your <hi>Highnesse</hi> vertues, And most hearty Celebrater of them, BEN: IONSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>