<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣full Syr VVilliam VVray of Glentworth, in the Countie of Lincolne Knight.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109073_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19602</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6036</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109073</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣full Syr VVilliam VVray of Glentworth, in the Countie of Lincolne Knight.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The estate of the Church : with the discourse of times, from the apostles vntill this present: also of the liues of all the emperours, popes of Rome, and Turkes: as also of the Kings of Fraunce, England, Scotland, Spaine, Portugall, Denmarke, &amp;c. With all the memorable accidents of their times. Translated out of French into English by Simon Patrike, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Hainault, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 71, 74-708, 30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Syr <hi>VVilliam VVray</hi> of <hi>Glentworth,</hi> in the <hi>Countie of</hi> Lincolne <hi>Knight.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His worke (Right Worshipfull) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Estate of the Church,</hi> from the beginning of the raigne of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Augustus,</hi> to the first yeare of <hi>Rodolph</hi> the second, now liuing; First written in French, by <hi>I. Crispinus,</hi> and lately translated into our mother tongue by a Gentleman of desert: at the request of my very friends, I haue bene intreated to propagate to this present time. For him, although some hold, that trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is not capable of that elegance, as is the original, because the one hath full libertie of inuentiō, the other is by necessitie tyed to obseruation: yet in my opinion the Author hereof, for his faithfull &amp; significant inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour therin, hath deserued to be ranked with the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest inuentions. For my selfe in the continuation, as I haue alwaies in matters of small consequence, shewed the mightie perturbation of my mind, feare; so in this labour of extraordinary moment, especially in presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of protection vnder your worships patronage, I am confounded, since the shewe of my deuotion is begun with so meane a sacrifice: for to this heape I haue onely added an handfull. In the whole discourse
<pb facs="3"/>
is set downe at large, the originall of Papacie (that slaughter-house of consciences) the aduancing &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing therof, the beginnings of all heresies, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions of the faithfull, the chaunge of religions, the decrees and Councells of Bishops, the Canonie and lawes of the Church. The iudiciall knowledge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is a light, illuminating the blindnesse of soules, and deliuering them from the more then Cimerian darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of ignorance. This rectifieth the iudgement of man, and teacheth him rightly to distinguish between true Religion and superstition, who both haue one ground, which is his soule. This prospectiue shewing the spots and errors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with the darke &amp; sullen colours of hypocrisie &amp; heresie, (which two venemous wormes like snakes do poyson and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the florishing estate of a setled Church,) will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest the right Diaphonia and concord thereof. But iealous of this ouer-boldnesse I take my leaue: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly dedicating my poore labours to your Worships true-iudicial consideratiō, desiring withal, your gentle hand of approbation to this essentiall testimony of my most dutious loue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships humbly at commaund,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>