<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Reverend Father in God, THOMAS, By Divine Providence, Lord B. of DURESME, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109013_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14661</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17101</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109013</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Reverend Father in God, THOMAS, By Divine Providence, Lord B. of DURESME, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A case for the spectacles, or, A defence of Via tuta, the safe way, by Sir Humphrey Lynde Knight, in answer to a book written by I.R. called, A paire of spectacles, together with a treatise intituled, Stricturæ in Lyndomastygem, by way of supplement to the Knights answer, where he left off, prevented by death. And, a sermon preached at his funerall, at Cobham, Iune 14th 1636. By Daniel Featley, D.D</title>
                 <author>Lynde, Humphrey, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Parsons, Marmaduke</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 208, 217-279, 9, 220, 195, 200-219, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Reverend Father in God, THOMAS, <hi>By Divine Providence, Lord</hi> B. of DURESME, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>May it please your good Lordship;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER I had taken a reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to apologize for my departed friend, and make a kind of <hi>hedge</hi> to his <hi>Via tuta,</hi> I seriously bethought my selfe, who would <hi>maimtaine the fence,</hi> by one so made; and patronize this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of that his worthy worke. For though the cause in hand, be the truth of God; and the person whom I undertake to defend against the Calumniations of
<pb facs="4"/> his Adversarie, be now <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, out of the eye of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Horat. Od. <hi>14.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> Subla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ex ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis quaerimus invidi. Ovid. l. <hi>3.</hi> De Pont Pascitur in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis livor post fata quiescit. Et Iuvenal. Sat. <hi>1.</hi> Nulli gravus est p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rcussus Achilles, aut multum quaesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Hylas.</note>
      <hi>envie,</hi> and the reach of <hi>malice;</hi> yet I well know, that neither the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the one, nor regard to the other, will prove any <hi>Amulet</hi> against the poyson of the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Aristoph. in Plut. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, id est, annulis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinalis aut antidotus.</note> Sycophants tooth, or venom of the Detracters tongue. Death I grant, which sets a period to all suits in Courts, should grant a <hi>Supersedeas of Course,</hi> against all <hi>Arrests</hi> and molestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them who have taken <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> in the grave; and therefore<note n="(c)" place="margin">Brusonius facet et exemp. l. <hi>1.</hi> Solon legem condidit, quâ prohibuit in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunctos maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta consicere. Et Theodorus Chius cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peium in aegypt, admittendum addens <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos non mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> Erasm. Apoph. p. <hi>374.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Selon</hi> ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a Law, whereby, under a great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, he prohibited any to cast any foule aspersion on the dead. And<note n="(d)" place="margin">Bruson. ibid. Asinius Pollio cum orationes condidisset in Plancum quas post mortem ejus legendas servabat audiit à Planco, <hi>cum mortuus non nisi larvas pugnare.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Plancus</hi> sharply reproved the folly of <hi>Asinius Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio</hi> (who threatned to stigmatize him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, by publishing his declama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions against him) saying, <hi>None but Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goblins fight with ghosts.</hi> Notwithstanding this privilege granted to the dead, even by the Law of Nature; I cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="4"/> without horrour, nor expresse with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out griefe, what the <hi>Acts and Monuments</hi> of the Church, present to the view of all men, concerning Popish malice survi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving life it selfe, and committing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane (not onely unchristian) outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges on the corpes, and not lesse upon the workes of Orthodoxe Professors now with God. The blessed Martyr, Saint<note n="(e)" place="margin">Cypr. de lap. &amp; Ep. l. <hi>2.</hi> Saevitum est in plagas, saevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est in vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera: &amp; in servis Dei non jam membra torquebantur sed vulnera: manabat pro fletibus san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis, &amp; pro lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymū cruor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e semiustulatis visceribus deflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebat.</note>
      <hi>Cyprian,</hi> setting the cruelty of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as it were, <hi>upon the Racke,</hi> could <hi>straine</hi> no <hi>higher</hi> after hee had said, <hi>These Salvage Persecutors wreake their furie on the brused, and battered servants of Christ; and torture not so much their members as their wounds.</hi> Yet there is a <hi>Plus ultra</hi> in the enraged malice of our Romish Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries, <hi>Saevitum est in cadavera, saevitum est in ossa, saevitum est in cineres.</hi> For they<note n="(f)" place="margin">Vide hist. de mort. Spala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensis. M.S.</note>
      <hi>Arraigne the dead,</hi> they sue against them an <hi>Ejection</hi> out of their <hi>long homes,</hi> and interre them in<note n="(g)" place="margin">Acts and Monuments, volume <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>778.</hi> The body of <hi>Peter Martyrs</hi> wife, at <hi>Oxford,</hi> was taken up by Doctor <hi>Marshall</hi> out of her grave, in the Church of <hi>Saint Frideswids,</hi> and buried in a dunghill.</note>
      <hi>Lestals;</hi> nay they
<pb facs="5"/> burne their<note n="(h)" place="margin">
         <hi>Acts and Monuments, vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 606. <hi>The body, and bones of</hi> Iohn Wickliffe, <hi>by the Decree of the Synod of</hi> Constance, were taken up &amp; burned, 41. yeares after he was buried, in his owne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ish at <hi>Lutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> and his ashes taken &amp; throwne into the river; <hi>and so was hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved into three ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Earth, Fire, and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: thinking thereby, utterly to exstinguish and abolish both his name and Doctrine for ever. Acts &amp; Monuments, volume</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 771. <hi>The Vicechancelior taking with him a publike Notarie, bound the Parishioners with an oath, to digge up</hi> Paulus Fargius <hi>his bones: and received the like oath of</hi> Roger Davis, <hi>and</hi> William Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zell, <hi>for doing the like with</hi> Martin Bucer, <hi>when they came to the place of execution, the</hi> Chests were set up an end, with the dead bodies in them, and fastened on both sides with stakes, and bound to the post with a long iron chaine, fire being forthwith put to, as soone as it began to flame round about, a great sort of bookes that were condemned with them, were cast into the same.</note> bones, and strew their ashes on the rivers.</p>
   <q>Tantene animis coelestibus irae?</q>
   <p>Loe the <hi>bowels</hi> of them who most boast of <hi>workes of Mercie,</hi> towards the bodies of true Professors, whilome, <hi>Temples of the holy Ghost:</hi> yet their charitie to their soules, exceeds this; for these they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily <hi>exclude out of heaven, and send them pell-mell, without Baile, or Mainprise, to the dungeon of hell;</hi> and there sentence them to more <hi>exquisite</hi>
      <note n="(k)" place="margin">Coccleus <hi>hist. Hussit. l.</hi> 2. Multo graviora esse crediderim Wicklefi tormenta quam sint apud inferos, vel scelera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimorum hominum <hi>Iudae</hi> proditoris Christi, &amp; <hi>Neronis</hi> Christianorum perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutoris.</note>
      <hi>torments, than either</hi> Nero <hi>the monster of men, or</hi> Iudas <hi>the betrayer of Christ himselfe, indure.</hi> Of this<note n="(i)" place="margin">Edmund. Camp. rat. <hi>10.</hi> Calvinum &amp; hes principes unum coelum capere non potest. Et <hi>Fishers</hi> resp. to Doctor <hi>White,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Fearley.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>152.</hi> Out of the unity of the Romish Church, no salvation. Et <hi>Coster</hi> resp. ad resut. <hi>Osiander</hi> proposit. <hi>8.</hi> wisheth himselfe damned with Lucifer, if ever my <hi>Lutheran</hi> were saved.</note>
      <pb facs="5"/> straine is the Knights<note n="(l)" place="margin">Flood, Spect. c. <hi>17.</hi> per tot. Papists dying in their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion saved, <hi>Protestants damned.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Alastor,</hi> with whom I am to deale; whose perfect cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter your Lordship may see in <hi>Sozimus,</hi> drawne to the life by <hi>Isidorus Pelusiota,</hi>
      <q>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,</q> as your Lordship may find likewise, an exact Emblem of his booke in <hi>Plinie</hi> his description of the<note n="(m)" place="margin">Plin. nat. hist. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>36.</hi>
      </note> Beares whelpe, <hi>Jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formis caro sine oculis, sine pilis, ungues tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum prominent?</hi> In which consideration, I thought it most needfull to make choise of a Patron of eminent qualitie,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ben. Syr. Apoph. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, Sapiens nutu stultus fuste, Drus. in Alph. vet. sap. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> who with his Authoritie, might stoppe the mouth of such railing <hi>Rabshakah's;</hi> and if need be, lend them a <hi>smart blow</hi> with his <hi>Crozure,</hi> as<note n="(o)" place="margin">Hom. Is. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Ʋlisses</hi> did <hi>Thersites</hi> with his <hi>golden Scepter.</hi> Now, although the Knight vvanted not many Noble and vvorthie friends, and some of your Lordships Sacred order, who honoured him living, and would willingly have afforded him their protection being dead. Yet two reasons were prevalent with me, to dedicate this <hi>Apologie</hi> to your
<pb facs="6"/> Lordship. First, because none of your Lordships ranke now living, to my knowledge hath so often <hi>entered into Lists</hi> with the <hi>Romish</hi> Adversaries, nor <hi>served</hi> so long in this <hi>sacred Leguer</hi> as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; in so much, that at my aboade in <hi>France,</hi> now 25. yeares agoe: where I saw the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Fitzg: Hector Romuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum cecidit sub Achille <hi>Iuello.</hi> Rhemensi Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibali Scipio <hi>Fulcus</hi> erat. Tum cor papico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <hi>Rainoldus</hi> fregit in <hi>Harto. Alba Stapleto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num jugera</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde premunt: Ac cedes nostris pretium <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe</hi> papyris. Nec <hi>gemmae</hi> Renues <hi>Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> ire comes. Abfuit Ely siis tantum sua <hi>Laurea</hi> lucis. Te Deus in lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>os transtulit er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go suos.</note>
      <hi>Armes</hi> of other Champions of the truth <hi>blazoned</hi> in a Latin Epigram, I descried your Lordships among them in an apposite Anagram, made by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Pastor of the <hi>French</hi> Church.</p>
   <q>
      <hi>THOMAS MORTONIVS</hi> homo Martis notus.</q>
   <p>With this, or the like Euloge.</p>
   <q>Quassanda est istâ Pelias hasta manu.</q>
   <p>The other reason was, your Lordship in your last, no lesse unimitable, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answerable<note n="(q)" place="margin">
         <p>Mort. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitut. sacram. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>158.</hi> Of Rom. Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sub. This sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence I have seene lately can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vased by a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit against a <hi>judicious and religious Knight,</hi> falsly imputing unto him diverse falsities, &amp;c.</p>
         <p>And l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>545.</hi> Your Iesuit in his booke of Spectacles made in confutation of a <hi>judicious and religious Knight,</hi> among many other of his Paradoxes and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdities &amp;c.</p>
      </note> masterpiece, <hi>held up your buckler</hi> over the <hi>Knight</hi> then living, more
<pb facs="6"/> then once, and <hi>ward off</hi> the <hi>Iesuits blowes;</hi> and therefore I doubt not but that your Lordship will now <hi>bestride</hi> him being <hi>dead,</hi> and save him from all further injury. For my selfe, as nothing induced me to make this supplement to his Apologie, but the love of Gods truth, and the truth of my friends love: so I hope that all who love the truth in sincerity, upon the impartiall perusall hereof, will doe the <hi>Knight</hi> honour, and me right. For envie it selfe cannot denie that he hath much advantaged the common cause, both by convincing the Adversaries, in all the maine p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ints of difference betweene us, out of their owne mouthes, and disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering more at large then any the <hi>mystery of their Indices expurgatorij;</hi> wherein though they professe to correct onely their owne writers, and that but from the yeare 1518. yet the <hi>Knight</hi> hath tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them upwards, and detected their corruption of all sorts of Writers in all former ages: whereby the judicious
<pb facs="7"/> Reader may observe such indirect dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in our Adversaries towards us, as<note n="(r)" place="margin">Melancth. orat. Tom <hi>1.</hi> de Od Sophist. Cum triginta Tyranni legem tulissent, ne quis è suo Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogo in dictâ causâ necaretur Critias tamen Therammenem collegam suum, cujus nomen in Catalogo scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum erat, in dictâ causâ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfici jussit cumque The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rammenes legis occiliū peteret, respondet, legem scriptam esse de iis quorum nomina sunt in Catalogo, se vero jam The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rammenes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go delevisse.</note>
      <hi>Critias</hi> in the <hi>Athenian</hi> State practised against <hi>Therammenes:</hi> there being a law enacted in the time of the 30. Tyrants at <hi>Athens,</hi> that none of them should be put to death without a legall tryall, whose names were written in a certaine Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, <hi>Critias</hi> bearing a spleene to <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rammenes,</hi> first blots his name out of the Catalogue, and then proceeds to sentence him to death; and when <hi>Therammenes</hi> pleaded the priviledge of the law, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the thirty Governours, whose name was set downe in the Catalogue; <hi>Critias</hi> answered, that the benefit of the law was restrained to those whose names were in the Catalogue; but that he had newly strucke out the name of <hi>Therammenes.</hi> Let any that hath a single eye, judge whether the proceedings of our <hi>Romish</hi> Adversaries against us, are not altogether as injurious as this of <hi>Critias</hi> towards his Collegue <hi>Therammenes.</hi> First,
<pb facs="7"/> they raze out our Records, and burne our writings, and then <hi>nonsuit</hi> us for want of <hi>Evidence.</hi> Secondly, they blot and cut out by their <hi>Indices Expurgatorij,</hi> the most pregnant testimonies of Antiquity for us, and then charge us with false Allegations, because, forsooth, they agree not with their <hi>castrated</hi> Copies. I freely confesse that if any man shall search all the <hi>Knights</hi> quotations, especially out of the <hi>Romish</hi> Writers, in the latter corrected, or rather corrupted Editions of them, or looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him through the <hi>Iesuits</hi> Spectacles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbed, he will thinke him very foule in some Allegations at least: but let him in quire into the more Auncient and uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Copies, or looke upon the <hi>Knights</hi> writings without the <hi>Iesuits</hi> false <hi>glasses, and glosses,</hi> or even through those <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> he hath fitted for him in this last Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet; as they are now <hi>wiped and clensed</hi> by me, he will finde him a most faire and ingenuous Writer.</p>
   <p>There is no text of Scripture among
<pb facs="8"/> many scores, no Allegation of Antiquity among many hundreths, <hi>vellicated</hi> by the <hi>Iesuit,</hi> which is not here <hi>vindicated:</hi> no argument seeming to be <hi>blunted,</hi> which is not <hi>sharpened,</hi> and a <hi>new edge set on it;</hi> no <hi>paint, colour,</hi> or <hi>varnish</hi> layed by the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit</hi> on the rotten <hi>Pillars of Popery,</hi> which is not here <hi>scraped out,</hi> or <hi>washed away.</hi> And thus at the length the <hi>Case for the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles</hi> begunne by the <hi>Knight</hi> is finished: on which I crave leave to <hi>imprint</hi> your Lordships <hi>Name and Armes;</hi> entreating your Lordship to accept this <hi>Dedication</hi> as an <hi>indication</hi> of my sincere love to my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased friend, and withall an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of that great <hi>debt</hi> of thankes I <hi>owe</hi> your Lordship for your Lordships many undeserved favours, which I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble no other wayes to <hi>discharge,</hi> then by underwriting my selfe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humbly and affectionatly Devoted, <hi>DA. FEATLEY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>