<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle and friendly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109189_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19746</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6170</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109189</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle and friendly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A hedgerovv of busshes, brambles, and briers: or, A fielde full of tares, thistles and tine : of the vanities and vaine delightes of this worlde, leading the way to eternall damnation: with seuerall exhortations or cauiats for the carelesse to shun and beware the same. No newly compiled by I.D</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the gentle and friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are in forraine countries (gentle Reader) certayne men called by the name of Quack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saluers, who vse in Fayres, Markettes, and open places, to shew foorth in desiphered cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors many infirmities, griefes, and diseases, which doe afflict and reigne in mans body: and withall they lay open in viwe of the people diuers waters, powders, and drugges of diuers sortes, as remedies for the same: And also there they doe tell and expound vnto the beholders, aswell the nature and qualities of the same diseases, as the vertue, force, and efficacie, of the same Drugges, to the intent the hearers and beholders may take knowledge, and receiue benefite thereby. The which ensample (gentle Reader) being (in my simple opinion) very good and christian like, I haue immitated, by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open before our eyes in this small Booke folowing, (according to my small skill and knowledge) the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and vayne delightes of this Worlde, and haue named it (as me thinkes most fit) A Hedgerowe of Bushes, Brambles, and Briers: or a Fielde full of Tares,
<pb facs="3"/>
Thistles, and Tine; of the Vanities and vayne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes of this Worlde, leading the way to eternall damnation, with seuerall exhortations or cauiats for the careles to shunne and beware the same: That as I haue reduced another Booke into a smaller volume, called <hi>Paterickes Places,</hi> a Treatise concerning the doctrine of Fayth, and the doctrine of the Law; which is the onely marke to shoote at, and the onely meanes to obtaine saluation: So by reading and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of both, we might thereby learne to choose the right and good way, and to shunne and flie the wrong and busshie bad way: as for a familiar example. If two men were set in a playne to runne a race for a great prize, and it were decreed that he which came first to the ende of the race, should haue the prize for his rewarde: The one steppeth aside out of the way amongst Busshes and Briers, seeking after Butterflies, whereby he looseth the prize; the beholders would not onely thinke him a vayne man, but would also deride and laugh him to scorne for his vanitie &amp; foolishnes: Euen so (gentle Reader) wee hauing two wayes layde before our eyes, one leading to damnation, and the other to saluation; it were a great follie, or rather mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, for vs to leaue the right way, and to take the wrong: Therefore it behooueth vs to be warie and carefull, that we chouse the right way; for it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed vnto vs by our Sauiour Christ, to be verie <hi>narrow &amp; straight,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note>
      <hi>and few there be that finde it.</hi> And let vs examine our selues, that yf we be intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in any Brier of this Hedgerow, we striue to get out in time, least being caught by one Brier, and carelesse
<pb facs="3"/>
to get loose, an other also layeth holde; and so by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees we be fastened and ouerwhelmed in the Hedge, as when we would get loose we can not,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note>
      <hi>and the night come vpon vs at vnwares,</hi> whereby we be taken tardie, as the <hi>foolish Virgins,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reue. 12.</note>
      <hi>and our aduersarie or accuser, bring vs before the Iudge, placing vs amongst those careles liuers, after the lustes of the flesh, and workers of iniquitie, on the left hand;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 13.</note>
      <hi>and the Iudge pronounce that heauie sentence,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note>
      <hi>Depart from me ye cursed, into euerlasting fire, prepared for the Deuill and his Angels:</hi> But rather let vs thinke vpon, or take example by the seely Sheepe, feeding by the Hedge, or in the Fieldes; so soone as he findeth him selfe caught by the Brier, he foorthwith turneth and windeth himselfe about to get loose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and deferreth not the time, but will so struggle and striue, that in the ende he will get loose, albeit he leaue some of his Wooll behinde him. And Sainct <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs to <hi>cast off the olde man,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.</note>
      <hi>which is corrupt through the deceiueable lustes:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. 5.</note>
      <hi>and put on the new man, which after God is created in righteousnesse and true holinesse:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> And willeth him <hi>that hath stollen, to stoale no more, hauing no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship with the workes of darknesse: but deny vngodlines and worldly lustes:</hi> And that we should <hi>liue soberly and righteously and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent worlde, walking in the spirit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note>
      <hi>and doing and performing the fruites of the spirit: which is loue, ioy, peace, long suffering, gentlenes, goodnes, fayth, meekenes, temperancie, agaynst such there is no law: for they that are Christes, haue cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="4"/>
the flesh, with the affections and the lustes. If we liue in the spirit, let vs also walke in the spirit,</hi> that we may be set amongst the number of those on the right hand, and the Iudge will say vnto vs,<note place="margin">Math. 25. 1. Iohn. 2.</note>
      <hi>Come ye blessed of my father, inherite the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the worlde:</hi> For those that walke in the spirit, loue God, and are good and righteous, and doe those thinges that please him: therefore such must not doubt, but that God will also giue them the crowne of righteousnes: To which we pray him, he will graunt vs. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your welwiller in the Lord, and most vnworthy. <hi>I.D.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>