<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Johan Frith vnto the Christen Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1531</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109726_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01273</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11386.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109726</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Johan Frith vnto the Christen Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A disputacio [n] of purgatorye made by Iohan Frith which is deuided in to thre bokes. The first boke is an answere vnto Rastell, which goeth aboute to proue purgatorye by naturall philosophye. The seconde boke answereth vnto Sir Thomas More, which laboureth to proue purgatorye by scripture. The thirde boke maketh answere vnto my lorde of Rochestre which most leaneth vnto the doctoures</title>
                 <author>Frith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cock (Cowke), Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1531</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Johan Frith vnto the Christen Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race and peace be with the christen reader. I am sure there are manye that will moch mer uel and counte it a greate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumpcion that I beinge so yon ge and of so smalle lerninge da re attēpte to dispute this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agēst these thre personages of the which numbre two / that is to saye my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> de of Rochestre ād Sir thomas More / are aun cient mē both of greate witte and dignite. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstondinge I wil desire them pacientlye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> heare mine answere / not aduertysinge who spea keth the wordes but rathere what is sayed. And<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> as concerninge myne youth / let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre what paule monischeth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Timo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. willinge that Timothens shuld instrude the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and that no man shulde despice his youthe for as the sprete of god is boūde to no place / euē so is he not addicre to any age or person / but enspireth when he will and where he wil makin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the yonge to se visiōs &amp; espye the truth / and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he eldres to dreame dreames and to wandre in phantasyes Ades. 2. Joe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>. 2.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 2.</note>
   </p>
   <p>And as touchinge my l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ninge I must nedes aknowiege (as the truth is) that it is verysmal / neuerthelesse that litle (as I am bounde / haue<note place="margin">1. Lo. 12</note> I determed / by goddes grace) to bestowe to the edefyinge of christes congregaciō which I praye god to encrease in the knowlege of his worde.</p>
   <p>I wolde not that any man shulde admitte my wordes or lerninge / excepte they will stonde with the scripture and be approued therbye. Laye them to the touchstone ād trye them with goddes worde. If they be founde false ād coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaite / then dampne them / and I shall also
<pb facs="3"/>
reuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e them with all myne harte. But if the scri pture alowe them / that you can not denye but it so is / then reciste not the doctrine of god / but knowlege youre ignoraunce and seduccion and retourne gladlye in to the right waye. For if you can not improue it by goddes worde / and yet / of an hate and malicious minde that you beare vnto the truth laboure to resist it and cō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it that it shulde not sprede: I ensure you youre sinne is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>remissible and euen agenst the holye gost / and the bloude of them that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 33.</note> for faute of enstruccion shalbe requyred on youre handes.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>araduenture some of you will saye that youre fathers and olde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> with ma ny holye men and doctoureo haue so heleued / &amp; that therfore you will abyde by the olde. I an swere: The wayes and iudgementes of god are m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ruelous / who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> whethere god haue suffered his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to erre and be seduced for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> / to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that the vnfaithfull which wold not beleue the truth but had pleasure in iniquite might st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ble at their erroure in to their<note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> confusion and ruyne? Al though a mā be neuer so faithfull and holye / yet is there moch imperf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ction in him as longe as he is included in this mortall bodye / how be it it is not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him / but thorow the faith in christes bloude hoellye pacefyed and forgeuen. And ther fore it is not sure that we folowe their exterior workes or other imaginacions / but let vs euer conferre them vnto the pure worde of god / and as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> testefyeth so let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> lorde of Rochestre doth testefye him silfe writinge vppō the. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. article / that there are manye poyntes both of the gospels and other
<pb facs="3"/>
scriptures which are now discussed more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> lye / and more clerelye vnderstondē then they ha ue bene in tymes past. And addeth furthermore that there are diuerse places ī scripture yet sum deale darke / which he douteth not but that they shalbe more open and light vnto our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> posterite / for why shall we despayre of that (sayeth he) sith that the scripture is for that entent lefte with vs that it maye be vnderstonde of vs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actlye and to the vttmost poynte? Of this maye you euidentl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e perceaue that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he olde fathers and holye doctoures haue not sene all the truth. But sumwhat is also lefte / thorow the hye prouision of god / to be discussed of their suc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cessoures. And therfore is it not mete that we streyght wayes cleaue vnto their wordes with out any further enserchinge the scriptures / but we must examine all thinges by the scriptures although. S. Paule or Peter shulde preach it vnto vs / as we se experience Actes. xvij. that<note place="margin">Actes. 17.</note> when Paule preached / the audience daylye ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched the scriptures whether it were as he sayed</p>
   <p>But you haue bene of longe continuaunce secluded from the scriptures / which is the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of such grosse erroures as ye are now fallen in / so that ye coulde neyther serch them / nor yet once loke on them. Alas what blindnes doth oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupye oure ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s? Are ye so childishe to beleue that the same worde which hath made the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull and heretikes / faithfull and christen in tymes past / is now so farre altered that it shul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de cause the faithfull and christen to become he reti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>es? I praye god open youre eyes. How be it we maye now wel tast at oure fingres endes that we haue longe bene in that miserable case that Paule prophesyed vppon vs. ij. Thessalo.
<pb facs="4"/>
ij. that god hath sent vs stronge delusions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Thes. 2</note> we wolde not receave the knowlege of the truth: what greater delusion can we haue / then to thinke that the verye worde of god / which was writen for oure comforte / which is the verye fode and sastenaunce of oure soules / which is the sure metyarde and perfeyte touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone that iudgeth and examineth all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:<note place="margin">Rom. 15</note> to thinke (I saye) that this holesome worde shulde be oure poyson and condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon?</p>
   <p>And al be it oure forefathers haue ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed with out it and receaved all for truth that ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re prelates belyes haue imagined: yet is not their faute and oures a like (although I tan not excuse their ignoraunce but that it is sinne before the face of god) for they had not the light of goddes worde opened vnto them. Now sith we haue the light declared vnto vs / and yet will proceade in blinde ignorauncye and not cō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rre and examine these iuglinge mistes with the light of goddes worde / oure ignoraunce is wilfull and with out excuse.</p>
   <p>Suffer therfore all thinges what so euer they be / to be tryed and examined by the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. If they be true then shall the scripture do them no hurte / but stablish and strengthen them / for the scripture discloseth nothinge but falsehed / and condempneth nothinge but that is damnable.</p>
   <p>And now to descende vnto oure matter and disputacion which is of purgatorye / I shall shewe you what occasion I had to take it in hande. I wrote a let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ter vnto a certayne frynde in englonde / desyringe him instantlye to sende me certayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> which I thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarye
<pb facs="4"/>
for my vse and were not to be gotten in these partyes / as the cronicles / Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mores boke agenst the supplicacion of beggers and certen other. These bokes I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> vppon. S. Thomas daye before Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stmas / theyeare of oure sauioure a. M. ccccc. and. XXX. with a lettre writen in this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: Sir I haue sent you such bokes as you wrote for and one moo of Rastels makinge / wherin he goeth aboute to proue purgatorye / by natural philosophye: which thinge (quod he) I think be more easye to do / then to proue it by any good scripture. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. This stuffe receaved / I was mervelouslye desyrous and tickled to se what reasons he brought for his probacions. And in the beginninge and prologe of the boke / he sette seven reasons which he sayed that fonde felowes alleged for them to proue that there coulde be no purgatorye. And in dede they are verye fonde that wolde denye purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye / if there were no better argumentes to confute it then he assigneth. But by goddes gra ce I will propounde seven tymes seven which shall haue such pith / that their paynfull pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorye shall not be able to abyde the worst of them / for these seven that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> assigneth are not worth one bene.</p>
   <p>Uvhen I had red and wel pondered these rea sons / I thought that he shuld sharpelie haue confuted them / as he might full well haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / speciallye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ith they were but of his awne imaginacyon. Neuerthelesse when I came vnto his solucions I founde not one but it had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>erten poyntes repugnaunte vnto the scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re (vnto which on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e reason must euer be obe
<pb facs="5"/>
dient) yee and also they were extremelye iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious vnto christ and his precious bloude.</p>
   <p>Then left I him / and red sir Thomas Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>es boke / to se what scripture might be brought for that purposse. And after that made I dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get enquyre to come by my lorde of Rochesters boke which also writeth on the same matter / ād when I had wel examined their reasons / and had sene the ordre and processe of the scriptures<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> gel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> which they alleged: I founde that clerelye vere fyed which Aulus Gellius saieth / that it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<note place="margin">☞</note> a greate deale better for a man to be sharpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> lye rebuked yee and openlye to haue his fautes published of his enemye / then to be coldlye and slenderlye praysed of his frende. For a mannes enemie ensercheth narowlye ād gathereth to gi ther all that he can imagyne / and so accuseth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> mā more of a fumous heate then of any verite: and therfore the audience (if they be wyse) con sidre his wordes therafter / and so geue verye small credence or els none vnto them. But if a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nnes frinde before audience do prayse him slenderlye and coldlye / it is an argument that the person is verye fautye / for a frinde behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth al qualityes and circumstaunces / his birth bringinge vpp / and what feates he hath done all his liffe longe: yee and applieth manye thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnto his frindes prayse / which serue but smallye for it / for he will leaue nothinge behin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that maye he imagened to employe his fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des fame ād honoure. Now if in all these poyn res he can not coloure out a glorious apparent laude / but is compelled for lacke of matter to prayse his frinde slenderlye / then (if the audien
<pb facs="5"/>
ce be wyse) they maye sone coniecture that he is no prayse worthye / and also maye well doubte whether that small prayse which he gaue him be true or not. Euen so / when I had red these bokes of Sir Thomas More and my lorde of Rochestre / and sawe the smalle probacions ād <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>lender reasons that those two wittye and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rned men had brought to confirme purgatorye / consideringe also that they are the chefest frin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / proctoures and patrones therof / and that they had applyed manye reasons ād scriptures for their pourposse (for lacke of matter) that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made agenst them / yee and not that onlye / <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> but also that they dissented betwene thē selues<note place="margin">More ād my lorde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> stre can not agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> in their probacions / for. M. More sayeth that there is no water in purgatorye. And my lorde of rochestre saveth that there is water there. Master More sayeth that the ministres of the punishment are deuels. And my lorde of roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre sayeth that the ministres of the punishmēt are aungels. master More sayeth that both the grace and cherite of them that lye in the paynes of purgatorye / are in creased. My lorde of Ro / chestre sayeth that the soules in purgatorye on tayne there neyther more faith nor grace nor cherite then they brought in with them. These thinges considered / it made myne harte yerne and fullye to consent / that this their paynfull purgatorye was but a vayne imaginacion / and that it hath of longe tyme but deceaued the people and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed them from their monye.<note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatoryes that god hath orde ned</note>
   </p>
   <p>Notwithstondinge god hath lefte vs two pur gato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>yes. One to purge the herte and clense it from the filth which we haue partelye receaued of Adam (for we are by nature the children of wrath Ephe. ii) and partlye added therto by cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentinge
<pb facs="6"/>
vnto oure natural infirmite. This pur<note place="margin">Ioan. 15.</note> gatorie is the worde of god as christ sayeth Io.<note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> harte.</note> xv. Now are ye clene for the worde which I ha ue spoken vnto you. This purgaciō obtayneth no mā but thorow faith / for the vnfaithfull are not purged by the worde of god / as the scribes and pharisees were nothinge the better for hea ringe his worde but rather the worse for it was a testimonye agenst them vnto their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion. And because we receaue this purgacion onlye thorow beleuinge the worde / therfore is the vertue of this purginge applied also vnto<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 15.</note> faith / for Peter saieth Ac. xv. that the gētles har <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> were purged thorow faith, / that is to saye / thorow beleuinge the worde. And what wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is that? verelye the preachinge that chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes deeth hath fullye fatisfyed for oure sinnes and pacefyed foreuer the fathers wrath towar des vs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. This faith purefyeth the harte and geueth vs a will and gladnes to do what so euer oure most mercifull father commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs. Neuerthelesse because oure infirmit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e is so greate and oure membres so weake and frayle that we can not<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> pur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> eschewe sinne as oure harte wolde and as ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re will desyreth: therfore hath god lefte vs a no ther purgatorye which is christes crosse. I mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne not his materyal crosse that he him silfe died on / but a spretuall crosse which is aduersite / tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion / worldlye depression. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. And this is called the rod or scourge of god wherwith he scourgeth euerye sonne that he receaueth / that<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> we maye remembre his lawe and mortefye the olde Adam and fleshlye lust which els wolde wate so rebellious that it wolde subdue vs / rai <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne in vs and holde vs thraulde vnder sinne.
<pb facs="6"/>
when so euer we haue committed a cryme theu<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>sal. 89</note> is god present with this rod as he sayth psalm lxxxix. If they defyle my ceremonyes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obserue my commaundmentes / then with a rod shall I punish their sinnes and with bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges shall I rewarde their iniquityes / but yet my mercye shall I not take from him neyther will I deceaue him of my promisse.</p>
   <p>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> must we receave with a glad harte and thanke oure lovinge father for it / for it is but a medicyne to healc oure infirmitye ād to subdue oure rebellious membres. But when oure membres are fullye mortefyed / that is / when deeth hath subdued oure corruptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye / and oure flesh committed to rest in the erth / then cease the purgatoryes that god hath ordeyned / and then are we fullye purged in his sight.</p>
   <p>If oure clergye coulde haue founde in their hartes to haue taken these purgatoryes vppon the / they had neuer neded to imagine any other but sith their li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e begane to waxe so dissolute / speciallie sith they shuld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e the salte of the erthe and lantrens of light: It was necessarye for thē to imagyne a purgatorye after this li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e / for els they might be sure that the most parte of them were never like to come in heaven.</p>
   <p>Iudge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> reader whych hast the sprete to discerne ād knowest the voyce of chryst what reasons rastell hath brought and how he hath soluted them. for in my mynde both hys reasōs and solucyons are so childysh and vnsauerye / so vnlerned and barē / so full of fautes and phā rasyes / that I rather pitye the mannes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce and blindenesse (whych hath so decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="7"/>
hym selfe thorow phylosophye and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reason) then I feare that he by hys vayne probacyons shuld allure any mā to consent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym.</p>
   <p>Iudge and conferre the scryptures whych Syr thomas More and my lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>de of Rochestre allege for theyr oppinion / and I doubte not but that god shall opē thyne eyes to espye that thin ge whych hath blinded them.</p>
   <p>Iudge and compare the scriptures to gether whych I haue brought to confyrme my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posse. ponder theyr reasons and my solucyons vnto them / and I am sure thou shalt perceaue that my smalle lerninge hath condēpned theyr hye eloquence / that my folye hath brought to nought theyr wisdome / ād that my youth hath disclosed their old and festred ignoraunce.</p>
   <p>And thys is euen the olde practyse of god: to chose the folysh thynges of the wolde: to con founde the wyse. to chose the weke / to confoūde the myghtye: And to chose the vile thynges whi ch are of no reputacyon: to confounde them of hye degre: that no flesh might bost it selfe in his syght to whom onlye be prayse and thankes for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uer.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>