<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Christophorus Hegendorf∣fyne, Doctour of ye law, to the right wise &amp; excellent man lord Thomas Reiben senatour of Francoforte▪ by syde Oderam, hys syn∣guler good patron, wis¦sheth health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109407_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02882</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13021</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109407</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Christophorus Hegendorf∣fyne, Doctour of ye law, to the right wise &amp; excellent man lord Thomas Reiben senatour of Francoforte▪ by syde Oderam, hys syn∣guler good patron, wis¦sheth health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Domestycal or housholde sermons : for a godly housholder, to his children and famyly, compiled by the godlye learned man Christopher Hegendorffyne, doctor, moste necessarye for all faythfull housholders: nowe fyrste translated oute of laten into Englysshe: by Henry Reiginalde</title>
                 <author>Hegendorph, Christoph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oswen, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Ipswich</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Christophorus Hegendorf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyne, Doctour of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> law, to the right wise &amp; excellent man lord Thomas Reiben senatour of Francoforte▪ by syde Oderam, hys syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler good patron, wis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sheth health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all other benefytes whiche we christians haue receyued of our onely saui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our Chryste (my especyall good frende) these be euen the chieffest, that by him we are al made both kynges and priestes. Kynges true lye, not that we haue anye kyngdome earthly to rule, but that by christ we sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>due all vices, both death, synne, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, and hell. For we Christians be as well kynges, as Christ is our heade and kynge: &amp; that bycause we beleue in him. Now, Christe is no worldely kynge, for the scripture sayth. Io. 18 (The kyngdō of Christe is not of thys world) for he is kyng of kynges: for bycause he hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer all thyng. And all thynges are subdued vnderneth his seat. So therfore as Christe is a kynge, so are we Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb facs="3"/>
kynges, for all that apperteyneth to Christe are ours. And also, al we christy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans, be Christes, for christ and by Christ, For by hym we all do offer spirituall sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifyces dayly vnto God, and one pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for an other: and we haue power to preache goddes worde, whiche thynges S. Peter in hys firste Epistle. 2. Chap. doth comprehend in a few wordes, whā he sayth, ye are the chosen generation y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kyngly priesthode that holye nation &amp;c. Thys place is knowen to euerye man. And so we christians in Christ, be al Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes. But leaste anye tumulte or scisme myght ryse amonge the Christyan con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, the Churche or those to the which the Churche doth commyt suche aucthoritie: do chose certeyn minysters whiche do bothe mynyster the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and openly preach the worde of God, accordynge to the doctryne of S. Paul. 1. Corin. 14. when he sayth, let all thynges be done honestly and in ordre, amongest you. Euery Christen man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng father of a housholde hath auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie in his own house, to enstructe and teache hys children and housholde with
<pb facs="3"/>
the worde of God, and of ryght he is, or ought to be a very Bisshoppe ouer hys owne housholde. And that that we saye vnto fathers of housholdes, we wyll to be spoken vnto euery Christian woman which is mother ouer her houshold, for the which thynge, leste that any might doubte in this matter, I wyll proceade a lytle further in it. Fyrste of all, Iose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus in the first boke of his Antiquites doth wryte, that Adam and hys sonne Seth did make two tables, one of slate, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other of stone, in the which they wryt the worde of god and hys Prophecyes, the which they did, without any doubt, that they myghte both brynge vp theyr houshold in the worde of god, and leaue it to their posterytie, and to to exercyse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> offyce of a Bisshoppe in teachynge the worde of God. Gene. Chap. 35. Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses doth shewe how▪ Iacob callynge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther all hys housholde, vydde make a shorte and a vertuoule scrmonde, when he sayde. Caste ye away straunge Gods which be in the myddest of you &amp;c. thys place is knowen to euerye one that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth scripture.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
But what nede I to bryng this or that example, as though the olde Tastament were not full of thē, wherewith it might be easely proued, that a good and a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouse father of a housholde oughte to enforme all hys hole honsholde, bothe in godly doctrine and in good manners Furthermore, Deute. 11. God commaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding after thys manner fathers of house holdes, sayth these wordes euen at the fyrste (where he speaketh of the x. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes) put thesemy wordes in your herte, and in your soule. Deute. 6. and bynde them for a signe vpon youre hande, that they may be as a warnynge betwene your eyes, Prouerb. 3. And ye shall teache them youre Chyldren, that they may talke of them, when thou syt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teste in thy house: and when thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest by the way, when thou liest downe and when thou rysest vp, yea, and thou shalt wryte them vppon thy dore postes of thy house, and vppon thy gaates that your dayes may be multiplyed &amp;c. Do we not heare in this place, that god wyl that euerye good father of a housholde shall teache his Chyldren and hys famy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="4"/>
the commaundementes of god, and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he shal take the office of a priuate Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop and preacher. Euen lykewise, euen a lytle before. Deute. 6. God doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund when he sayth. Thou shalt loue thy lorde God with all thy herte &amp;c.</p>
   <p>And these wordes which I commaund the thys day, shalbe in thy herte &amp; thou shalte shewe them vnto thy Chyldren, &amp; shalte talke of them, when thou arte at whome in thy house, and as thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest by the way &amp;c. But here some men wolde say. God dyd commaunde them vnto the Iewes, that they myght teach theyr famyly the preceptes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> x. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, what haue Christē men that be fathers of housholds, to do with those preceptes? He not Christen mē de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered from all Moyses lawe by Crist therfore heare thou (o Christian) of the Christian libertie. At this tyme I do no thynge speake of the abrogation of the lawe, for that euery father of a houshold shoulde institute and teache hys Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and famyly, aswell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> x. cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mētes, as any other Christian doctryne. S. Paul teacheth us playnely and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfestly
<pb facs="5"/>
in his Epistle to the Ephesy. 6 Chap. when he saith. Ye Fathers moue not your Chyldrē to wrath. But bring them vp thorowe the doctryne and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the lorde.</p>
   <p>What meaneth it to brynge them vp in the doctryne or discyplyne of the lorde? truely nothyng else, but their Chyldren alwaye frome their tender infancy to be Christianly brought vp, in those thinges which our lord god wyll require at their handes. What thynges be those? The x. commaundementes do suffycyentlye declare. Furthermore, leste that youthe shoulde forgette or contempne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of god (as euen in dede y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sort is most neglygent) therfore Paul sayth, that they ought to be admonys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed and warned of their gouernoures, with the admonirion of the lorde: and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thynge to be grafted in their myndes, whiche God doth speciallye requyre in them. And as we maye easely perceyue by the wordes of Paul, that it is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> trew part of a father of a houshold, to brynge vp dyly gentlye his Chyldren &amp; house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in the ten commaundementes. And
<pb facs="5"/>
lette no householde keper agaynste thys thynge wynce or kycke: but lette theym brynge them vp, in fayth, hope and cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytie, and in other wholesome preceptes and doctrynes of Christe: that the lawe maye be as a scolemaister (As S. Paul sayth vnto Christe) that is, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng brought to the knowledge of their synne by the lawe, may prepare and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne theyr selues to seke vnto Christe, and to his ryght herytage: for why, the law (as Paul to the Romaynes &amp; Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathyans doth argue) doth make vs to prepare our selues to receyue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> grace of god, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it setteth before our eies our sin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and putteth downe the stubbernes of our mynde. and maketh vs very gree die of Christes doctryne. Furthermore when Christe (as it is shewed in the 5. of Marke) had delyuered a certeyne man of a deuyll, and he dyd pray Christ, that he wolde tarry styll wyth hym. Chryste made answere vnto him. Go thy waies into thyne owne house, vnto thy famy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and shew them how moche the Lorde hath done for the, and what compassy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had ouer the.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Nowe, we haue herde Christe our one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye sauyour commaunde also, that he which was delyuered by hym frome a Deuyll, shoulde take the office of a Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop and preacher of his worde in hys house amonge his Chyldren and famy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that he shoulde set forth the gret benefyciall goodnes, which he had recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued of god: and so to brynge his famyly by the loue of god, to the very knowe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of God.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we maye gather oute of dyuers Epistles of Paule: that in hys tyme, there was both fathers of house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes, and mothers of housholdes, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che dyd bryng vp very earnestlye their famyly, both in the fayth of Iesu Christ and also in other pryncypall matters of Christes religion, for whi, in the Epistle vnto the Romayns the laste Chapter, he doth salute the housholde and faythfull church of Prisca &amp; Aquyia (or as I may vse his termes) the Christen family whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was in the house of Prysca and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila: for wythoute doubte, theye were informed priuyly in the fayth of Christ. And in the fyrste Epistle to the Coryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyans
<pb facs="6"/>
the laste Chapter he saith. Aquy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la &amp; Priscilla, with those which be of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faythefull congregation in their house doth salute you hertely in the lord. And where agayne, he calleth the housholde faythefull Churche, the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faythfull Chyldren, men seruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and women seruauntes, which were in the house of the womā Priscilla (whō he calleth to the Romayns Prisca) and Aquyla her housbande.</p>
   <p>The self same thynge Paul to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lossians the laste Chapter sayth. Salute the Bretheren which are at Laodicia, &amp; salute Nymphas, and the congregation which is in his house, where S. Ambrose thynketh that thys Nimpha was a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man diligeut in the commaundementes of God, thys artycle in greake, <hi>Aphtae,</hi> doth reproue it, that he was no woman but a man, which did noryssh and bryng vp his Christian famyly at home in hys house in Christian loue and godlynesse. The selfe same thynge dothe S. Paul exhorte Tytus. Tit. 2. That old women shoulde be soberlye aparelled, no slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and that they shoulde teache ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neste
<pb facs="7"/>
thynges, that they myght cause yonge women to be sobre &amp;c. And here Paul wylleth also, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> old women should instructe their yonge women at home in their house, to godlynesse and good manners. And also Paul vnto Tymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the fyrst Epistle the fourth Chapter commaundeth wydowes to learne god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynesse at home in their houses, and to haue a godly famyly. And howe canne they haue a godly familie, excepte theye teache theyr housholde dylygently and priuately in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> learnyng and erudition of Goddes word?</p>
   <p>To conclude, that holy man Sayncte Chrisostome in hys fyrst homely in Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesis saythe. When ye shall depart from hence from thys sensyble table, let there be put afore you a spiritual table, and let the good man of the house saye some of these wordes, whiche be here sayde. Let the woman here. Let the seruantes lecne Let their aquayntaunce lerne, and let y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> house be the Chuche of God, that the Deuyll may be dryuen away, and that our daily aduersary may be put to flight wyth all the enemyes of our health and
<pb facs="7"/>
let the grace of the holye ghoste here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyde in this place, that all peace and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde maye defende all inhabytauntes herein. &amp;c. These be the wordes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome. Of the which wordes what mā can not vnderstande, that it perteynethe to godly fathers of housholdes, to make their house the churche of God, and the congregation of Christiā people: and to take the office of a Bisshop vpon them Also Chrisostome setteth fourth the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whiche ryse of sermonnes made at home in houses: for bycause of them the deuyll is driuē awaye. As S. Peter saith which goeth aboute as a rorynge Lyon fekyng whome he may deuoure. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy ghoste doth reste vpon the inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes and dwellers in the housewhere the worde of god is taught: and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habytauntes and dwellers doo lyne in concorde and vnytie, and they do agree peaceably, one wyth an other. Whiche frutes verelye do easely brynge to thys poynte all fathers of housholdes, that they shoulde dylygently instructe their famyly, with the worde of God in their houses.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
For we may see by dayly experyence, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the deuyll goeth aboute with all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, to make debate and stryfe in how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and breaketh amitie &amp; peace and sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth discord. And it is no doubt (y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sostom truly sayth) the deuyll y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enemie of mans saluation, and of our hole famy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, sekethe oure lyfe: and often tymes wolde brynge bothe the father of the housholde, the wyfe the Children, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole family to perels, onlesse he be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen away of godly fathers of housholds by the swerde of the spirite, which is the worde of God. With these examples of holy fathers, with the preceptes of god in tyme paste gyuen and commaunded in the olde Testamente, withe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of Christ, which he gaue vnto hym whome he delyuered from a deuyll, and by these examples of fathers of housholdes and mothers of houshol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, whiche I haue rehersed oute of S. Paules Epistles.</p>
   <p>And where as Sainct Paul, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre of olde women and widowes, we may gather esely by the wordes of Cri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sostome, euery father of a houshold hath
<pb facs="8"/>
lybertie to teach his famyly at his own house the worde of God, and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> of ryght he is, and ought to be, the very Bisshop of his famyly. And there is no lesse to be thoughte of mothers of housholdes. If there be any brother of a houshold whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is illyterate or vnlerned, and can not teache pryuately hys housholde, let him hyer one, whiche in hys stead may lerne hys famyly, or if he can not, let hym ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uygysantly marke the sayenges of Pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lycke and open sermons, and let hym re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pete those saiengs at home in hys house before hys famyly, assone as supper or dynete is done. Therfore I beyng per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded wyth those arguementes of S. Paul, which I haue made relation of, y<seg rend="sup">s</seg> I euer thoughte dylygently wythe my selfe, that it were very necessary to write for my chyldren and for my hole house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, certeyne housholde sermons. In the whiche those thynges whiche were requisite to a very trew and Christian re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygion, myght be expounded wyth few wordes propise &amp; corespondent for the matter, which sermons often tymes I vse to reade in my house, to mye Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="9"/>
in laten, to my famyly, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mother tonge. And do earnestly require at their handes after my readynge, whether thei do vnderstand these thynges which are rede or no, and leaste they should forget veri quycly those thinges which I haue red, I do require oftentymes of theym all thynges, which in these sermons be entreated of, euen as of their distafe and spyndell, which sermons I beyng ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly requested of my especiall frendes haue suffered to come abroad, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by them euen other fathers of housholdes maye be styrred towarde their famyly, to tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che them wel and godly. For I knowe that fathers of housholdes be slacke in this thynge: and do not dylygently exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cute their office commytted to them of God.</p>
   <p>Fyrste I wyll leaue out some of my ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons in laten, yf my fryndes shall think it beste, and set out those that be necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mother tonge. But vnto the (mi welbeloued Thomas) doo I dedycate these my pryuate sermonnes, for that I know the to be gyuen studiously to a perfecte godlynesse. And althoughe I
<pb facs="9"/>
knowe thou haste no nede of these ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to enstructe thy famyly wyth, for that thou haste attempted many godly thynges wyth the studie of godly wys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: yet for all that seyeng I knowe that euery thynge which may be condu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyble and profytable to obteine and get some godly wisdome is most acceptable vnto the, I doubte not but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou wylte take these my sermons well at worthe. For bycause I haue writen them to the furtheraunce of Christes true relygion. Some perchaunce wyll laughe me too scorne, for that I wolde be taken for an earnest lawer, and haue taken vpon me to interlace my selfe with holy scripture, whose laughinge to scorne I wyll vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dispise, Although that I am amonge the company and the felowshyp of law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers: yet I will not be forgetful of those thynges which perteyneth to a christian father of an houshold, for this is a bles<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed saiynge of S. Paul: he that hathe no care of hys, and espeacially for hys housholde, denyethe hys faithe, and is worse then an infideele. This byd the wel to fare, my espe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall good frend.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>