<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A prologe. wherbye a man maye the better percea ue the occasyon and hole cause of thys boke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1531</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109726_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01273</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11386.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109726</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A prologe. wherbye a man maye the better percea ue the occasyon and hole cause of thys boke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A disputacio [n] of purgatorye made by Iohan Frith which is deuided in to thre bokes. The first boke is an answere vnto Rastell, which goeth aboute to proue purgatorye by naturall philosophye. The seconde boke answereth vnto Sir Thomas More, which laboureth to proue purgatorye by scripture. The thirde boke maketh answere vnto my lorde of Rochestre which most leaneth vnto the doctoures</title>
                 <author>Frith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cock (Cowke), Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1531</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <head>¶ A prologe. wherbye a man maye the better percea ue the occasyon and hole cause of thys boke.</head>
   <p>There was a brother of oures named Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō Fysh (whych now I truste resteth in goddes hādes) whose yies god had opened / not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the wilie walkinge of hypocrites
<pb facs="7"/>
and ruyne of the royalme which thorow theyr meanes was nye at hāde: but also to marke and pondre the perill of mēnes soules / and how that the ignoraunte people by their seducciō was fal len in to that frantick ymaginacyon that they more feared the pope and his decrees which are but vanite / then god hym selfe &amp; his lawe which are most rightwyse and eternal. This man th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> fore of a feruēt and burnynge zele that he bare to the welth of the cominaltie, brake out &amp; tou ched these hypocrytes in a litle treatyse whych he called / the supplicacion of beggers / wyllynge that we shulde geue the abundaunce of oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> chesse vnto the poore to whom yt ys due by the lawe of god: and that we shuld no lenger suffer oure selves to be dyspoyled &amp; robbed of a syght of sturdye lubbarres whych vnder a false cloke of vertue and prayer deceyue the poore of theyr lyuyng and both the poore and the rych of their soules helth / if credence be geuen vnto them.</p>
   <p>And where these wilye foxes wolde haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> tendyd the cloke of purgatorye affirminge that it were due vnto thē because they praye for the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yr frendes soules that they myght come to rest / he answered vnto that poynte preuētinge theyr obieccyon / and proued that eyther there coulde be no such purgatorie / or els that the pope were a mercilesse tyraunte whych (as he sayeth hym silfe) maye delyuer them from thence and wyll not excepte he haue monye. At thys poynte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane. M. More to fume and toke vppō him sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe to be proctoure for purgatorie (I wil not saye that he was hyred therto of oure spiritualtye al though many men dare swere it) &amp; to conferme hys purposse he wrested sore the scriptures / and tryumpheth also that the verye miscreauntes
<pb facs="8"/>
and idolatres beleue that there is a purgatorie He addeth therto (to stablysh hys matter wyth all) that there is no man whych beleueth that there is a god and that the soule of man is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall / but he must neades graunte that there is a purgatorye. There toke Rastell hys holde / <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> whych is a prenter dwellinge at poules gate in london and of master Mores allyaunce / whych also coucteth to countre fayre hys kinseman / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the beames of hys braynes be nothinge so radiaunte nor hys conueyaunce so commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in the yies of the wyse. Notwithstandin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge thys Rastell hath enterprised to dilate thys matter / and hath diuided it in to iii. dyaloges / imagininge that two mē dispute this matter by naturall reason and phylosophye secludynge Chryst and all scripture. The one of them (that shulde dyspute thys matter) he calleth Ginge min / and fayneth him to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and of Ma hometes lawe. The seconde he nameth Comin go an almayne and of Christes fayth. And he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eth the turcke to teach the chrysten man what he shulde beleue.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he fyrst dialoge goeth aboute to proue by rea son that there is a god / whych is mercifull and ryghtwyse. The seconde entendeth to proue / that the soule of a man is immortal. Agenst the se two dyaloges I wyll not dispute / partlye be cause this treatise shulde not be ouer longe and tedyous / and partlye because that those two poyntes whych he there laboureth to proue are soch as no christen man wyll denye (although manye of hys probacyons are so slender that they maye well be improued) but as cocerninge hys thirde dyaloge wherin he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> proue pur gatorye / it is hoellye miuryous vnto the bloude
<pb facs="8"/>
of Chryst and the destruccyon of all chrysten fayth / yfmen were so mad as to beleue his vay ne persuasyons. And therfore I thought it expe dyent to compare thys thyrde dyaloge with all the deceytfull reasons vnto the true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and pure worde of god that at the lest Rastell hym selfe might perceyue hys awne blinde ignoraū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and retourne agayne in to the ryght waye. And if anye man haue bene deceyued thorow hys boke (as I trust there are but fewe except<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> they be verye ignoraunte) that they maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent wyth hym and glorefye go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> for his in estimable mercye whych hath sent hys light in to thys worlde to dysclose and expell theyr darke and blin de ignorauncye / that they maye se his wayes &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in thē praysinge the lorde eternallye.</p>
   <closer>Amen</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>