<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Rea∣ders whatsoeuer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S109568_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06167</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16658</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S109568</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Rea∣ders whatsoeuer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fig for Momus : containing pleasant varietie, included in satyres, eclogues, and epistles, by T.L. of Lincolnes Inne Gent</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Knight, Clement.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whatsoeuer.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, I know you wonder, that hauing so long time kept silence, I salute the world with so peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie a title: But if thou consider the reasons before you enter into mislike; you shall be satisfied, and I excused.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I entitle my booke</hi> (A fig for Momus,) <hi>not in contempt of the learned, for I honor them: not in disdaine of the wel mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, because they cherish science; but in despight of the detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, who hauing no learning to iudge, wanteth no libertie to reproue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>VVho worthily deseruing the name of</hi> Momus, <hi>shall rather at my hands haue a figge to choake him, then hee, and his lewd tongue shall haue a frumpe to check me: Sheepe are soonest woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by curdogs, because they are mild: but hee that nips him soundly, that bites him cowardly, purchaseth his owne peace, &amp; escapes much perill.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Heraclitus <hi>intituling one of his bookes with</hi> Ponou Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mion, <hi>the praise of labour, King</hi> Ptolemey <hi>(causing all the copies to be bought,) commanded the first letter of</hi> Ponou <hi>to be put out, and called the booke</hi> Onou Encomion, <hi>the praise of the asse: But had</hi> Heraclitus <hi>begun with</hi> Ptolemey, <hi>and toucht him with cowardly flight from</hi> Demetrius, <hi>with effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb facs="4"/>
vanity in apparell, with exceeding gluttonie, and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes; with his letcherie with</hi> Agathoclea, <hi>and bawdry with</hi> Oenante, <hi>the King would rather haue giuen a talent to stop his mouth, then deuised (by taking away of a letter) to abuse his title. UUhere detraction is giuen to chalenge, it is good stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king first, for whelpes that are whipt for brauling, are quicklie quiet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>This cause (gentlemen) hath drawne me to vse this title, and vnder this title I haue thought good to include</hi> Satyres, Eclogues, <hi>and</hi> Epistles: <hi>first by reason that I studie to delight with varietie, next because I would write in that forme, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no man might chalenge me with seruile imitation, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with heretofore I haue beene vniustlie taxed.) My</hi> Satyres <hi>(to speake truth) are by pleasures, rather placed here to prepare, and trie the eare, then to feede it: because if they passe well, the whole</hi> Centon <hi>of them, alreadie in my hands shall sodainly bee published.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In them (vnder the names of certaine Romaines) where I reprehend vice, I purposely wrong no man, but obserue the lawes of that kind of poeme: If any repine thereat, I am sure he is guiltie, because he bewrayeth himselfe. For my</hi> Eclogues, <hi>I commend them to men of approued iudgement, whose mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents though I fill not with quotations, yet their matter, and handling, will show my diligence: For my</hi> Epistles, <hi>they are in that kind, wherein no Englishman of our time hath publiquely
<pb facs="4"/>
written, which if they please, may draw on more; if displease, haue their priuiledge by authoritie. Briefly, I haue so written, as I haue read: so read, as I can iudge: In which respect, if any man doubt, let him aske and I will resolue him: if any man reproue, let him looke to it, I will nip him: for as I am readie to satisfie the reasonable, so I haue a gird in store for a Railer. Finally, gentlemen as</hi> Prometheus, <hi>after he had formed his image of earth, presented it to the sunne; and</hi> Ops <hi>when she had brought forth</hi> Iupiter, <hi>(for feare lest he should be deuoured by time, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured in</hi> Saturne) <hi>gaue him in keeping to the</hi> Cureti; <hi>So I present this fraile image of my art, to take life, and light, from the sunne of your approued iudgements, &amp; desirous to commend, this infant of my wit to immortalitie, and defend it from the assaults of time, and enuie: commit, and submit it to your protection, the true</hi> Cureti <hi>of all cunning: who accepting these fragments in good worth, shall shortly receaue from me, matters both worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and reading.</hi> Vale 6. Maij. 1595.</p>
   <p>Yours as you vse him,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>T. L.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>