<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Bengalassa del Mont. Pri∣sacchi Retta, vnto Seig. Princisea Ganzar Moretta. For his behauiour. vz.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110654_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10867</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Bengalassa del Mont. Pri∣sacchi Retta, vnto Seig. Princisea Ganzar Moretta. For his behauiour. vz.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nevv yeeres gift : The courte of ciuill courtesie: fitly furnished with a plesant porte of stately phrases and pithie precepts: assembled in the behalfe of all younge gentlemen, and others, that are desirous to frame their behauiour according to their estates, at all times, and in all companies: thereby to purchase worthy praise, of their inferiours: and estimation and credite amonge theyr betters. Out of Italian, by S.R. Gent</title>
                 <author>S. R. (Simon Robson)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 18, 18-38, that is 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Bengalassa del Mont. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacchi Retta, vnto Seig. Princisea Ganzar Moretta. For his behauiour. vz.</head>
   <head type="sub">To my Nephew Seig. Princisca Ganzar Morretta.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T MY LAST BEING at Prisacchi, vnderstanding by your fathers talke, that he minded to haue you a while in the Court, where hee hath spent the better part of his life▪ and because it is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented with all sortes of companies, as any place in Italy is. I haue directed this little booke, which if you read and marke diligently, shall be as it were a guide, to leade you from a number of snates which you may be trapt withall, also for your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour in all companies: with many other things fit to be knowen of younge Gentlemen, and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for sutch as haue not beene conuersant in all companies.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare ye well.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>