<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT CARR Knight, Baron of Branspeth, Vicecount Rochester, Earle of So∣merset, of his Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter; And Lord High Treasurer of Scotland.</title>
           <author>Norden, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110180_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08278</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18611</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110180</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT CARR Knight, Baron of Branspeth, Vicecount Rochester, Earle of So∣merset, of his Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter; And Lord High Treasurer of Scotland.</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The labyrinth of mans life. Or Vertues delight and enuies opposite. By Io: Norden</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT CARR Knight, Baron of <hi>Branspeth, Vicecount Rochester,</hi> Earle of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset,</hi> of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> most honorable <hi>priuie Counsell,</hi> Knight of the most noble order of the Garter; <hi>And Lord High Treasurer</hi> of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Honorable Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue bin long ballanced betweene <hi>Desire,</hi> and <hi>Feare:</hi> The first inclining vnto: The second swaying me from, the publishing of these vnworthy lines: especially vnder so honorable a Name. But the first beeing a passion, in counterpoysible preuailed. Onely <hi>Feare</hi> remayneth, least your high <hi>prudence,</hi> and admired <hi>grauity,</hi> should disesteeme the gracing of seeming <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tlie.</hi> Because many friuolus <hi>Poems,</hi> are dayly begotten and brought forth, worthy to be abandoned. Yet many worthy subiects haue been handled in <hi>verse,</hi> much graced and imbraced of the wise. And howsoeuer these silly lines, may seeme vnworthy the hand, or eye, of so worthy a <hi>Patron,</hi> there is vse in some of them, to be made by men of whatsoeuer condition: If it be but to the chasing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away of that common enemy <hi>Idlenes;</hi> And to preuent thoughts lesse beseeming mindes inclinable to <hi>vertue.</hi> For, where <hi>vertue</hi> is a stranger, <hi>vice</hi> is a dayly guest.
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>tue,</hi> the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ther, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and <hi>guide</hi> to most solide <hi>content:</hi> Containing the <hi>Appetite,</hi> euer within the circle of <hi>Sobrietie.</hi> Obseruing that the more <hi>Concupiscence</hi> is sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and fed, the more irregularly it runnes, from one voluptuous experiment to another; neuer satisfied with the admired varieties, of abhorred <hi>vanities.</hi> Men enter this life, as into a <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> or fatall <hi>Desert</hi> of <hi>changes,</hi> and <hi>miseries.</hi> And none escapeth the incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of those hideous <hi>Minotaures, Vice,</hi> or <hi>Enuy,</hi> whose dangers are as <hi>Silla,</hi> and <hi>Caribdis,</hi> by shunning the first, he fals into the second. <hi>Democritus</hi> laughed to see the folly of men: But much more might <hi>Heraclitus</hi> weepe to obserue the miseries, whereinto they are subiect to fall by <hi>Vice,</hi> or <hi>Enuy.</hi> Onely that Diuine <hi>Ariadne</hi> (<hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi>) giueth vnto euery prudent <hi>Theseus,</hi> the line of <hi>Right Reason,</hi> to cōduct him, through all the ambiguous Angles, and crooked turnings of <hi>this lifes Labyrinth,</hi> wherin <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Enuy,</hi> couch to snare &amp; surprise the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest. Common experience the Mother of best <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing</hi> reueileth this, as in <hi>the glasse of the risings and fallings, of men,</hi> which I haue endeuored, in some weake measure, in these simple <hi>Elegies</hi> to dilate: not to teach, but to put men in minde, of the vncertaintie of all estates in this mortalitie, wherein there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>safetie,</hi> or <hi>content,</hi> without adhering to <hi>Vertue,</hi> whose companion is <hi>Enuy,</hi> which euer followeth, but neuer fayleth the vertuous. <hi>Sola virtus inuicta.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Most bound vnto your Honor,
IO: NORDEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>