<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LORDS of his Majestyes Commissioners for new erected offices, and innovated fees, and to all others that are doers and lovers of justice, health and prosperity attend you in all your lawfull designes, with all encrease of honour and favour both with God and men.</title>
           <author>Puckell, Steven</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110514_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10207</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20484</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LORDS of his Majestyes Commissioners for new erected offices, and innovated fees, and to all others that are doers and lovers of justice, health and prosperity attend you in all your lawfull designes, with all encrease of honour and favour both with God and men.</title>
                 <author>Puckell, Steven</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true table of all such fees as are due to the Bishop of London : and all his depending officers, as commissaryes, registers, proctors, and apparitors, as hath been given in to his Majestyes commissioners in Starchamber under their own hands in the month of November M. DC. XXX. Whereto is added a true discovery of such fees ordinarily exacted by them upon his Majestyes good subjects contrary to this their own table and the statute laws of the land. Published by Steven Puckell and sent as a love token for his countryes good</title>
                 <author>Puckell, Steven</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LORDS of his Majestyes Commissioners for new erected offices, and innovated fees, and to all others that are doers and lovers of justice, health and prosperity attend you in all your lawfull designes, with all encrease of honour and favour both with God and men.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honorable when I considered, not onely the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which God hath furnished your Noble Persons withall, together with the power and authority putt into your hāds by his Majesty for the seeing and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring into all extorted and innovated fees, it made me to conceive your honours were the men that God had appoynted to deliver the oppressed from the hand of the oppressour, which did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me to seeke release under your honours protection, against my cruell oppressours, in which I freely confesse I found (to Gods glory be it spoken) more then ordinary successe, by your honors means, in that your honours effectually procured my peace for awhile in cōmaunding that Commissary my accuser to suspend his suite against me, in the high commssion, but yet it was but for a while, in that my busy and malicious adversary (getting something in respect of my conscience as your honours well know) insenced against mee some high Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as the Archbishop of Canterbury and Bishop of London, who (contrary to your honours order made) did forthwith pursue me with such violence, as if they thirsted for my bloud, and nothing but my life would serve their turn, for which cause I was inforced to leave my own native country, to seeke shelter in forrain parts, where through the Lords goodnes having found a place of breathing, I have thought it my duty to speak, according to my strenght, from a farre, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="3"/>
to your honours a brief discovery of some of their extortions I have taken knowledge of in their proceedings, to give your Honours occasion to dive into this mystery of iniquity, where I doubt not but your wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms wil soon finde out much more then my shallownes can extend to, yet by this little I discern and discover, they are no other then mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles oppressours, intruders upō the subjects rights and priviledges, and who is appointed under God and his Majesty to curb them, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain their inordinate &amp; lawles courses but your honours, but they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beē much fleshed by prevailing against all sorts, haply their inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, will not fear to attēpt to make an assault against yours honours in case you question them for their injustice and oppression in these or other their proceedings, yet I trust they shall not prevaile, but having begun to fall they shall fall more and more, till their usurped power (under which manie mourn) be utterly overthrowne. To call to your honours remembrance their late injustice in my own particular, I have presumed once again to renue my complaints to your honours against them, and for farther evidences, every day affoards his just complaint against them, wherever they keep their courts, or excercise authority over his Majestyes subjects in anie part of his dominion. If therefore God shall move your honours hearts to goe on with so good a work as to purge not onely them of these evills, but free the churches and people of God of these strange offices, God shall have much glory by you, the Church and people of God, much peace and freedom, the land purged of manie a crying sin, and the Kings throne established in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and righteousnes; which that your honours may be inabled to doe the God of truth and justice be with your honours, and double the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of courage, and wisedom on you, I rest at your honours service to bee commanded.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>STEVEN PVCKELL</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>