<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Godly and Chri∣stian
reader, grace and peace from
God the father, and from our Lorde
Iesus Christ. Amen.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110441_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02043</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1219</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110441</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Godly and Chri∣stian
reader, grace and peace from
God the father, and from our Lorde
Iesus Christ. Amen.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures of I.B. vpon the xii. Articles of our Christian faith : briefely set forth for the comfort of the godly, and the better instruction of the simple and ignorant. Also hereunto is annexed a briefe and cleare confession of the Christian faith, conteining an hundreth articles, according to the order of the Creede of the Apostles. Written by that learned [and] godly martyr I.H. sometime Bishop of Glocester in his life time</title>
                 <author>Baker, John, minister</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>484 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Godly and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
reader, grace and peace from
God the father, and from our Lorde
Iesus Christ. Amen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue for thy sake (gentle
reader) set forth vnto thee
briefly the meaning of al the
articles of our Christian
fayth, which are necessary
to saluation: to this ende and
purpose, that as thou hast in English an expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
vpon the ten commaundements of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
God and the Lordes prayer, to knowe
the better what they meane: so thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
haue likewise in thy mother tongue, some
opening of these Christian articles, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
well applyed to thy owne conscience by a
liuely fayth, thou shalt finde sweeter vnto thee
then either hony, or the hony combe, &amp; a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
to bee preferred before much gold, yea
the finest that may be. And because sermons
are not so common in euery parish Church, as
by the lawe of God, and the prince they should
be: thou mayest therefore vse this booke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately
in thy house when thou shalt haue lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
as vpon the Sundayes and holy dayes at
<pb facs="6"/>
after noone. The whole summe of thy faith is
here set forth so plainely, that thou mayest ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily
vnderstande it, if the Lorde shall giue his
grace to thee, &amp; open thine eyes to see: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
nothing can be easie to any man, but an
open booke shalbe as sealed vnto men, except
the spirit reueale it vnto them, which he will
doe, no doubt, if thou seeke it by humble and
earnest prayer to God, in his sonnes name. For
surely this is the cause, why many reading the
Scriptures vnderstand them not, because they
come to them with vnprepared heartes, not
subdued with humilitie, but presuming with
their naturall witte, to vnderstand the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
in them conteined. But flesh &amp; blood doth
not reueale these secret and hid thinges vnto
vs. Other reade them without prayer, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
them, other some reade them but to
dispute, and talke of them with the learned,
and not to amende their liues, being detected
by them, but onely to knowe them, and let the
practise goe. But these men so doing, can not
be blessed Luke 11. cap. Wherfore dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued
Christian, I exhort thee to reade the
scriptures, and all other bookes, that tende to
the declaration of the scriptures, with a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
eye, and penitent heart, not thinking or
presuming any thing of thy selfe, for the wind
<pb facs="6"/>
bloweth where it listeth, as our sauiour sayth,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 3. And these diuine thinges are most
commonly had from the wise and men of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,
and opened by the spirit vnto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
babes. Matth. 11. that is to such as are
humble in their owne conceyte, and in their
owne eyes. For the holy Ghost sayth: Them
that be meeke will hee guide in iudgement,
and teach the humble his waye. Psal. 26. So
then the humble shalbe exalted, and they all
that exalt them selues shalbe brought lowe.
Luk. 14. fare well (deare brother) and vse
this booke, as it was meant, to thy good and
comfort, which Iesus Christ graunt vnto
thee. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy louing Brother in the Lord,
alwayes to pray for thee. I. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>