<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Downame, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110202_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20735</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7117</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110202</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Downame, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly and learned treatise of prayer : which both conteineth in it the doctrine of prayer, and also sheweth the practice of it in the exposition of the Lords prayer: by that faithfull and painfull servant of God George Downame, Doctr of Divinity, and late L. Bishop of Dery in the realm of Ireland</title>
                 <author>Downame, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 431, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no duty more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in it self or profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to us then that of Prayer: Wherein we have sweet communion with God and free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse to the throne of grace, laying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a gracious Father all our wants and grievances, in hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to have our suits granted, our sinnes pardoned, our necessities sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, and our griefs removed and relieved. It is that hand and key which helpeth to unlock and open the treasury of all Gods graces for the enriching of our souls with all his blessings, the horsmen and chariots of the Israel of God, whereby they get victorie over all their enemies, yea
<pb facs="4"/>
they prevail with God whē he seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to oppose against them as an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and to wrestle with them that he may soil and overthrow them, as he did with Jacob. In all which and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable other respects as it is to be esteemed the chiefest exercise of a godly and Christian life, which can never be too much practiced, as the Apostle implyeth where he injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to <hi>pray continually,</hi> and <hi>in all things to give thanks;</hi> so can it never be sufficiently insisted upon in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of it, whereby we are pressed &amp; perswaded to the frequent exercise of it, and taught to perform it in a right and acceptable manner. In which regard though much already hath been excellently spoken and written upon this subject, yet let no man think it superfluous to have more
<pb facs="4"/>
published of this argument; seeing that can never be too much taught, which is never sufficiently learned and loved.</p>
   <p>The ensuing Treatises were the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of that learned, judicious and godly Divine D. <hi>Downame,</hi> late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Dery in the Realm of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, my most dear brother, which were penned with his own hand for his private use, but for the publick service of that part of Gods Church over which he was a painfull and faithfull Pastour, conteining the summe of many of his sermons which he preached on this argument. The which if he had been pleased to have polished and perfected with his own learned hand, no doubt much would have been added to their lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre and beautie. Yet seeing this was
<pb facs="5"/>
not done according to his better abilities, I thought it a dammage to Gods people, that they should lose the substance for the want of some circumstance, and have no use of a well-compacted bodie, fit to do God and his Church good service, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was not decked with gay or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments. And therefore I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented it to the view of the world, and indeavoured to perform the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a brother to him that is decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, though not to raise this spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all seed to him (for it was of his own begetting and composing) yet to give unto it birth and being in the world, without which it would have proved abortive, and so have been buried in perpetuall oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
   <p>The which service I have the
<pb facs="5"/>
more willingly undertaken for the benefit of all that will take pains to peruse this work, because I am now disabled by age and many infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to produce any further labours of mine own in this kind; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have not been wanting in my more able and mature times, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the proportion of my small ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent which my great Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster hath entrusted me with: Herein imitating the example of the weaker sex, who after they have been fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in bearing children themselves, and now being come to older age are disabled to have any more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, do some of them become midwives, who are helpfull to those who are young and fruitfull for the bringing of their children into the world.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>The Lord, whose onely blessing maketh all our indeavours profitable by giving efficacie unto them by the inward operation of his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, blesse these and all other labours of his servants that they may bring forth plentifull fruits for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his glory and the benefit of all his children, who are willing to make use of them to these ends.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord Jesus, to do thee any Christian service,</hi>
JOHN DOVVNAME.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>