<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL Sir VVilliam Hatton Knight, Sonne adopted and Heire to the right honourable Sir Christopher Hatton, late Lord Chaunceller of England, Iohn Phillips wisheth the feare of God, cōtinuance of helth, with increase of wor∣ship &amp; vertue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110452_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09596</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19876</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110452</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL Sir VVilliam Hatton Knight, Sonne adopted and Heire to the right honourable Sir Christopher Hatton, late Lord Chaunceller of England, Iohn Phillips wisheth the feare of God, cōtinuance of helth, with increase of wor∣ship &amp; vertue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vt hora, sic fugit vita. A commemoration on the life and death of the right Honourable, Sir Christopher Hatton, Knight, late Lord Chauncellor of England : Wherin triumphant trueth reuiueth his memorie from the graue: exhorting nobilitie, gentrie, and duetifull subiects, to continue their obedience to God and her Maiestie, and to preuent by pollicie the perilous practises of euery ciuil and forrain enemy. Published by Iohn Phillips</title>
                 <author>Phillips, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL</hi> Sir <hi>VVilliam Hatton</hi> Knight, Sonne adopted and Heire to the right honourable Sir <hi>Christopher Hatton,</hi> late Lord Chaunceller of <hi>England, Iohn Phillips</hi> wisheth the feare of God, cōtinuance of helth, with increase of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship &amp; vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene in all times</hi> (right worshipfull) a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple obserued, that publick and apparant vertues in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons deceased, haue neuer been buried in obliuion, but haue alwaies been recorded and left to posterities: the end only this, that they who still liue, by apt imitation, might be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of like vertues. Which in my selfe conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I concluded, that great vnkindnes to God, and iniurie to remayning Subiects should be offered, if the vertuous life and death of this right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable deceased Lord, should not be emblazoned. To God vnkind, if he, as the author, should not be acknowledged, the cause efficient of all these rich graces, wherewith he was inuested: &amp; iniurie to suruiuing subiects, if there should not be comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration
<pb facs="3"/>
of his (more then naturall vertues) as by recordation whereof, they might walke &amp; tread the same way and path. My selfe I confesse, am the least of others, and most vnable to perfourme what I wish, yet wil I not be the last that shall vse endeuour to effect what I may. (With hoping that you would accept) I presumed to thrust forth this small Pinnace, fraught with simple marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, into the harbor of your worships protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: assuring my selfe, that as the purest Emerauld shineth brightest when it hath no oile, so Trueth will delight you, though basely apparrelled. The shortest and most clowdie day, is a day as well as the longest and brightest, when the sun is in the height of his Horizon. Pardon then I beeseech you, wherein I haue presumed, and accept (I most humblie craue) what herc I haue presēted: which if your worship vouchsafe, Trueth concludes, her selfe sufficiently graced, and my selfe most happy which haue beene her pen-man. Of this resting my selfe assured, I shall continuallie pray for the increase of your worship, that both in this life you may haue your harts desire, and in the end, fruition of those ioyes that are endlesse.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Tour worships most duetifull to cmmaund</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I. Phillips.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>