<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull my sin∣guler good Maister, M. Thomas Powle Esquire, one of the sixe Clarkes of her Maie∣sties most honourable Courte of Chauncery. W. P. wisheth all happines with increase of spirituall blessinges in the greatest measure.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110196_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08893</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19172.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull my sin∣guler good Maister, M. Thomas Powle Esquire, one of the sixe Clarkes of her Maie∣sties most honourable Courte of Chauncery. W. P. wisheth all happines with increase of spirituall blessinges in the greatest measure.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most breefe, easie and plaine receite for faire writing : Wherin the author being well acquainted with the causes, which in these daies hinders it, hath for the good of his cuntrie, so distinguished and broken euery perticular letter for the true making thereof, and so perfectly and plainely shewed the ready way of true ioyning the same. Both for the roman and secretary handes, as any one of ordinarye yeres and capacity, not hindring any other busines, may at his idle times by his own priuate practise, in short time attaine to write, to serue very good vses either in office or otherwise</title>
                 <author>Panke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Perrin (Perin), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull my <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler good Maister, M. Thomas Powle Esquire, one of the sixe Clarkes of her</hi> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties most honourable Courte of Chauncery. <hi>W. P.</hi> wisheth all happines with increase of spirituall blessinges in the greatest measure.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull I haue here vndertaken a woorke, how profitable, I referre to the euent. And for that I had no better meanes then this to manifest my duetie I haue presumed to make your W. the patrone of my trauell: wherein if you shalbe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to allow me your ordinarie fauour, it will be of force sufficient not onelye to defend me from the greatest aduersarie, but also to arme and encourage me to a worke of better effect. Thus as I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to commit vnto your W. this my first croppe, so will I in my best exercises commend all your actions to be gouerned by the Lord.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your W. most bounden seruant in the highest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his duetie. W. Pank.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>