<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110088_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20663</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7065</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110088</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catalogue of the deputies of the high and mightie States Generall of the Vnited Prouinces : And of the reuerend and learned diuines, who now are met in the nationall synode. Celebrated in the citie of Dordrecht in Holland. Translated out of the Latin and Dutch copies. With a short narration of the occasions, and introduction of the said synodicall assembly</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Stratageme of the diuel.</note>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE chiefest <hi>Stratageme</hi> of the Diuell, against the Kingdom, Citie, and House of God, is, <hi>Contention</hi> and <hi>Diuision,</hi> Mat. 12. yet the Lord in his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wisdome knoweth how to exercise his children ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and to make manifest those which are approoued, 1. Cor. 11.19.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Antiochian distention.</note>This Stratageme hath beene vsed by him, euen from the beginning, vntill this crooked Age of ours. In the dayes of the Apostles no small disten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and disputation was raysed in that famous Church of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> whereof the chiefe Author was (as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> recordeth) that peruerse Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke and sonne of the diuell, <hi>Corinthus,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his disturbing of Gods house, was bruised to death by the fall of a house.</p>
   <p>It appeareth by the holy Historie written by S. <hi>Luke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Disturbers.</note> that the disturbers of the Antiochian Church, came with a faire shew, were adorned with the title of Teachers, and were called by the name of Beleeuers, no lesse then others.</p>
   <p>It is also to bee noted, that those who now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbe
<pb facs="3"/>the peace of Sion, want no titles nor faire appearance.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Parties dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbed.</note>The parties disturbed are called <hi>Brethren,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeareth, that the diuell our aduersarie, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to sow controuersies, euen amongst those, who many wayes are bound to mutuall loue and amitie.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The question.</note>The matter in question was a point of doctrine, and therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabe</hi> presently oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed themselues thereunto, with diligent enquirie and powerful Confutations: for no delay is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable in the discouering of false brethren and griping Wolues.</p>
   <p>This faithfull opposition litle preuailing,<note place="margin">Synode</note> the resolution of the Antiochian Church was, to refer the matter vnto a greater assembly or meeting of the Apostles and other beleeuers. Which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath since bin vsed in the primitiue Church with excellent successe, for our imitation.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">At Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</note>The fittest place was reputed Ierusalem, where both parties came, and liberty was giuen freely to lay open &amp; debate their Questions and opinions.</p>
   <p>The President of that holy Assembly was S. <hi>Iames</hi> sonne of <hi>Alphaeus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">President.</note> who with his brethren, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding the state of the question, examined the same on the touchstone of Gods holy Word: and finally concluded,<note place="margin">Conclusion.</note> That Saluation was onely to be sought and found in Iesus Christ, &amp;c. and not partly in the Ceremonies of the Law. Wherunto was added very sound counsell for the re-establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of peace in the Church, and for the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of future Contentions.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p> This patterne of holy meeting,<note place="margin">Imitation.</note> is now imitated by the Vnited Prouinces, being admonished ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by diuers letters of reformed Christian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but chiefly of his Sacred Maiestie of Great Brittaine, who by his owne Writings, and by the mouth of his Ambassadours hath wrought much in the furthering of this great Businesse, whereby Gods cause is faithfully defended,<note place="margin">Vtility.</note> and from whence is expected a worthy Vnion in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, to the ouerthrow of the Romish Antichrist, who since his Reuelation hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the world with the vaine glorie of Generall Councels: whereas it is manifest,<note place="margin">The abuse of Popery in Synodes.</note> 1. That Synodes were not ordained by him, to cleare or confirme any points of true Doctrine by the Word of God, but for to oppose himselfe thereunto: and for to confirme his receiued errors; yea for to coyne new Articles of faith.</p>
   <p>Besides, no libertie was graunted in those Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes to speake, vnlesse it were with danger of life, as it fell out in the Councell of Constance, where <hi>Iohannes Hus,</hi> and <hi>Hieronymus</hi> of Prage were bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for maintaining of true Doctrine against Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish errours.</p>
   <p>Finally, the meeting of Cardinals and shauen Priest is to no purpose, whereas the Pope profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth himselfe to bee the onely man, from whose breast and breath is to bee expected infallible trueth.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Place of the Synode.</note>THe place of meeting is the citie of Dort, or Dordrecht, which is reputed to be the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entest
<pb facs="4"/>of Holland, and hath the first place in the Assembly of States.</p>
   <p>A great and faire Hall is prepared, with conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Seates for those that are deputed, and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries erected for the hearers: in a place called <hi>De Doelen,</hi> that is, the Artillerie garden.</p>
   <p>The first day of Nouember was appointed for the first Session,<note place="margin">Time.</note> but it was deferred vntill the 13. of the said moneth, expecting some that were not yet arriued.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Sermons preparatory 1. Session the 13. of Nouemb.</note>The 13. at eight of the clocke in the morning two Sermons were made, the one in Dutch, the other in French, accommodated vnto the instant action, with very feruent prayers vnto God for the direction of his holy Spirit.</p>
   <p>These Sermons beeing finished: from euery Prouince were appointed two, for to conduct those forraine Diuines into their seuerall Seates,<note place="margin">Deduction to their Seates. Oration of <hi>Balthasar Lydius.</hi>
      </note> which was performed with good order and great reuerence: the order is expressed hereafter.</p>
   <p>The first person appointed to speake was <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thasar Lydius</hi> one of the Ministers of Dort, who made a worthy Oration in Latin vnto the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and a feruent prayer vnto God for the same, and concluded with thanksgiuing vnto the States generall, that they had honoured him, to let his voyce first be heard in such an honorably Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Oration of the States.</note>Whereupon one of the Deputies of the States generall rose, and made a worthy Speach vnto the Assembly, opening the causes of this meeting, and giuing thankes vnto the forraine Diuines,
<pb facs="4"/>that they were come from so farre distant places, in such an vnseasonable time: promising euer to be thankfull for the same, &amp;c. And hereupon was read the Letter of the States generall, expounding their intention and will concerning the Assembly.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Session the <hi>14.</hi> of Nouember.</note>The next day following, by secret voyces or suffrages, were chosen one President of the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, two Assistants, and two Secretaries or Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whose names are hereafter expressed.</p>
   <p>These beeing elected, they were placed in the roome or seates appointed for them: and deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in order the Letters of Credence of those that were come to the Assembly which were read in the full Audience:<note place="margin">Literae fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciales.</note> And the matter at that time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued vpon, was, that all the Ministers Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strants,<note place="margin">Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strants cited.</note> or <hi>Arminians</hi> should be cited, and that they themselues might make choice of the fittest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, for to propound, expound, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Doctrine before the Assembly, with due reuerence and order. And all this is to bee done publikely for the instruction of all those that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the Latine tongue, who from all parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort thither in great multitudes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>