<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110520_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09905</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20167</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110520</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The passionate poet : VVith a description of the Thracian Ismarus. By T.P</title>
                 <author>Powell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be, some <hi>Rhetoric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> Praelector holdes it enquirable for the Title, as professing too much of affectation thereunto. Nor do I blame him, when, conferring the importance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with our impotence, he deprehend not a reason in the very front, or first face of my Booke. It shall suffice, for thy better satisfaction, I was most inward with mine owne defects: which I studied to preserue from seuerer exposition, as thus: If any challenge me for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring a good history, which might better haue beene continuated from the beginning, it was not I, but Passion. If, that my Introduction be somewhat too prolix, in respect of the maine sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ect proposed. All this was of Passion, that once enlargde, is hardly called in and restrained. If that in many of these Plants, I obserue no strict methode or time; I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere still, it was of Passion: One that neuer speakes in numbers, neuer beginnes with a <hi>Quande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uidem,</hi> or <hi>Quemadmodum,</hi> one that respectes not the preparatiue complement of hemming or spitting, the authenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue stroaking of the beard, or your demure winking. Briefly, one of the most licentious, irregular, and vnformall Libertines of this Age, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing as cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ant for excusable, as the loosers language, or some preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricator in a learned assembly. From hence I was aduised to assume his sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pe, as a most spatious protection, which the rather I made personate in the Poet, as well for suggestion of his office, which ought to bee most conuersant in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssion out of the abuses of these times, as for conciliation of our true Diuines, whome I onely admire, and not of arrogance, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sensible of any thing in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, which might maintaine such profest im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tance. He that vrgeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> further herein, giues me cause, if vnlearned, to suspect his iudgement; if learned, his seueritie.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>