<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF Effingham, Knight of the most renowmed order of the Gar∣ter, one of hir Maiesties priuie Councell, and Lord high Admirall of England, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>L'Isle, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110840_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21662</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110840</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF Effingham, Knight of the most renowmed order of the Gar∣ter, one of hir Maiesties priuie Councell, and Lord high Admirall of England, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>L'Isle, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Babilon, a part of the Seconde vveeke of Guillaume de Saluste seigneur du Bartas, with the commentarie, and marginall notes of S.G.S. Englished by William L'Isle</title>
                 <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Watkins, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 66, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF</hi> Effingham, Knight of the most renowmed order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, one of hir Maiesties priuie Councell, and Lord high Admirall of England, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Aying how neere it concernes your Honourable Charge, what straungers passe the Seas into England, I was thereby, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise in humble duty, moued, to giue your Lordship first intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of this Gentilman, whom I haue newly transported out of Fraunce: and also thought it necessarie to craue your fauorable protection of him in this his trauell. A woorthie man is he (my Lord) in his owne country, howsoeuer here disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and one of the sonnes of that noble and diuine Poet LE SIEVR DV BARTAS; in my simple iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the properest, and best learned of them all, I am sure the best affected to England, and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Emperesse thereof: for which cause I made speciall choise of him, and doe therefore the rather hope to finde fauour on his behalfe with your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
<pb facs="3"/>
Lordship; whose loyaltie to the Crowne, the Prince by trust of so high an office, whose loue to the land, the people by ioint-consent of daily-felt vertues, haue so fully witnessed, that the fame thereof hath spred it selfe far beyond that your admirable Regiment. In so much as this gentle stranger, though he were at the first vnwilling, Vlisses-like, to leaue his natiue soile, especially now in this dangerous sea-faring time, while all the world is in a maner troubled with Spanish Fleetes; yet after he called to minde what he had heard and written of the mightie Goddesse of the English O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, and who there swaied the Trident vnder hir, trusting vpon such a Neptune, he went aboord with a good courage, &amp; doubting not at al but that the proud Spanish Caracks, if they be not yet suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently dismaid by the wracke they suffered in their former aduenture, but dare againe attempt the like, be they neuer so many more or greater than they were (if more and greater they can be) shall againe, by the grace of God, directing (as before) the courage and wisedome of Englands renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Admirall, be dispersed ouer the frowning face of our disdainfull Seas, &amp; dronken with salt waues regorge the bodies of their presumptuous Pilots.
<pb facs="3"/>
And so (my Lord) with a fauorable winde, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing directly from the French Helicon, by the safe conduit of your Honourable name, and helpe of the Muses, at length I landed my stranger in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Where since his arriuall he hath gladly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred diuers of his elder brethren, that were come ouer before, some in a princely Scottish at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, others in faire English habits; and to th' entent he might the better enioy their companie, who by this time had almost forgotten their French, he was desirous to learne English of me: therefore I kept him a while about me, was his teacher at home, and enterpreter abroad; and now that he hath gotten such a smattering of the toong, as he can (so as he can) speake for himselfe, may it please your good L. to talke with him at your leisure: though I know you vnderstand very well his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall speech, I am of opinion it wil much delight you to heare him vtter such counterfait English, as in so little time I was able to teach him. He can say som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the godly gouernment of good princes, &amp; the wicked practises of Tyrants, as well in compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing as maintaining a Scepter; both woorthy your L. hearing for the manner sake, though the matter be not vnknowne to your wisdome. But som other
<pb facs="4"/>
things he doth report verie strange, as of NIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROD, that was the first Tyrant of the world, after the time of Noah, the first Admiral of the worlde: his aspiring minde &amp; practises in seeking the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples fauour, his proud and subtle attempt in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Tower of Babel, &amp; Gods iust punishment thereof in confounding the language of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Verie truly reckoneth he (that which few do consider) the great and manifold inconueniences that are befallen mankinde by the diuersitie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> tongs. Further he can tel of speech in general, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man speake by nature, or haue but onelie an aptnes to speake by vse, &amp; whether any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture haue the like: as for seuerall speeches, he can prooue, with many goodly reasons, which is the best &amp; most ancient of them all; what altereth each toong, what continueth each in account, what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are in greatest regard now-adaies, &amp; what Authors haue most excelled in them. And vpon occasion of the English toong, my Lord, he setteth out in such maner the Queenes princely maiestie, hir learning, wisdome, eloquence, and other excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues, that I know your noble &amp; loyall hart wil greatly reioice to heare it, at the mouth of such a stranger. The rest, if it be more curious, then, for
<pb facs="4"/>
the states waightie affaires, your L. may intend to hear, I wish referred vnto those goodly yong gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemē, your noble &amp; fatherlike-minded Sons, whō after your L.I do most of all honor: there shal they find profit so blended with pleasure, learning with delight, as it may easilie winne their harts, alreadie vertuously aspiring, from the wanton and faining Cantoes of other Syren-Poets (wherewith manie yoong gentlemen, and chiefely those of greatest hope, are long and dangerously mis-led) vnto a further acquaintance with this heauenly-poeticall writer of the truth: who is now growne into such a liking of this countrey, chiefely for the peaceable gouernment thereof (blessed be that Gouernour) and free course of the Gospell (God continue it, and sende the like into Fraunce) that he is desirous to become a Freedenizen; and hoping further to to be an eie-witnes of Gods woonderfull mercies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this Land, whereof in Fraunce he spake but by heare-saie, to behold that pretious Northren Pearle, and kisse hir Scepter-bearing hand, whose woorthy praise he hath soong so sweetely, he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie beseech your gratious fauour to be enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chised, which if it may please you to graunt (my Lorde) vouchsafing also the patronage of him;
<pb facs="5"/>
that vnder seale of your honourable name he may escape the carping censures of curious fault-fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and enioy all honours, priuiledges, liberties and lawes, that belong eu'n to the naturall inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this noble Isle, my selfe will vndertake to Fine for him, at least harty praiers for your daily encrease of honour, and all such obedience, as it shall please your L. to impose:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Whose I rest euer at commaund. VVilliam L'isle.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>