<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110186_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08434</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18755</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110186</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentation of Troy, for the death of Hector : Wherevnto is annexed an olde womans tale in hir solitarie cell</title>
                 <author>Ogle, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mattes, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <l>WHilom to him (whom <hi>Morpheus</hi> God of sleepe,</l>
   <l>Made slumbring dreames his sences al to keepe,</l>
   <l>Lockt in the prison of the darke some night,</l>
   <l>When eares were deafe and eyes could see no light,</l>
   <l>When men are made the liuely forme of death,</l>
   <l>Saue onely that they softly draw a breath)</l>
   <l>Did come a Ghost, a ghost most gastly crying,</l>
   <l>Helpe me to death that haue so long beene dying.</l>
   <l>With that he wakened and with feare beholding,</l>
   <l>Saw hir lament, her armes togither folding,</l>
   <l>A pale-wan thing, and yet with wounds fresh bleeding</l>
   <l>Sodden in teares, in teares that were exceeding.</l>
   <l>He much afright began to shrinke for feare,</l>
   <l>She bad him feare not, but my story heare,</l>
   <l>I am <hi>Troys</hi> ghost that now appeares to thee,</l>
   <l>And well I know that thou hast heard of me.</l>
   <l>But now I come not what I was to tell,</l>
   <l>For what I was (alas) each one knowes wel.</l>
   <l>I come to thee to craue thy gentle ayde,</l>
   <l>To further her that hath so long beene staide</l>
   <l>From blissefull rest: because I haue not told</l>
   <l>My woes for Hector which I must vnfold,</l>
   <l>But that (alasse) am I not able euer,</l>
   <l>To shew alone without the kind endeuor</l>
   <l>Of some good wight, that can bewaile with me,</l>
   <l>And tell my tale while I shall weeping be.</l>
   <l>The churlish <hi>Charon</hi> thwarts my passage ouer</l>
   <l>Saying my soule shal neuer blisse recouer,</l>
   <l>Till I haue doone this weary taske imposed,</l>
   <l>Neuer my ghost shal be in rest reposed.</l>
   <l>O helpe me then to tell my doleful story,</l>
   <l>That I at last may cease to be so sory.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>First will I speake, and to the world declare</l>
   <l>For <hi>Hectors</hi> death mine euerlasting care,</l>
   <l>So long, til teares doe stop my faltring tong,</l>
   <l>And when I cease I pray thee tell along.</l>
   <l>He then accorded to hir pitteous sute</l>
   <l>Granting to speake when teares did make hir mute,</l>
   <l>So that she would lay open to his eies</l>
   <l>The cause and manner of hir wofull cries.</l>
   <l>Then forth with causde she vnto him appeare</l>
   <l>The forme of <hi>Troy,</hi> the persons that were there</l>
   <l>Chiefest mourners for worthy <hi>Hectors</hi> death</l>
   <l>As they then wailde when fates new stopt his breath.</l>
   <l>He then emboldende stoutly veiwd them all,</l>
   <l>And tels her tale, when she from speach doth fall.</l>
   <l>Writing their words vnto the world to shew them</l>
   <l>It was her will that he might so renew them.</l>
   <l>Yet had she rather Spencer would haue told them,</l>
   <l>For him she calde that he would helpe t'vnfold them.</l>
   <l>But when she saw he came not at hir call</l>
   <l>She kept hir first man that doth shew them all</l>
   <l>All that he could: but all can no man shew,</l>
   <l>But first she spake as after doth ensew.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>