<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all ignorant people that desire to be instructed.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110444_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09426</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19717</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all ignorant people that desire to be instructed.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The foundation of Christian religion : gathered into sixe principles. And it is to be learned of ignorant people, that they may be fit to heare sermons with profit, and to receiue the Lords Supper with comfort</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To all ignorant people that desire to be instructed.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Oore people, your manner is to soth vp your selues, as though you were in a most happy estate but if the matter come to a iust triall, it will fall out farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, For yee leade your liues in great ignorance, as may appeare by these common opinions which follow.</hi>
   </p>
   <list>
      <item>1 That faith is a mans good meaning and his seruing of God.</item>
      <item>2 That God is serued by the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the tenne commaundements, the Lords prayer, and the Creede.</item>
      <item>3 That ye haue beleeued in Christ euer since you could remember.</item>
      <item>4 That it is pitrie that hee should liue which doth any whit doubt of his saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
      <item>5 That none can tell whether he shall be saued or no certainely, but that all men must be of a good beliefe.</item>
      <item>6 That howsoeuer a man liue, yet if hee call vpon God on his death bedde, and say, <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon mee,</hi> and so
<pb facs="4"/>goe away like a lambe, hee is certainely ued.</item>
      <item>7 That if any bee strangely visited, he is either taken with a planet, or bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</item>
      <item>8 That a man may lawfully sweare when hee speaketh nothing but the troth and sweares by nothing but that which is good, as by faith and troth.</item>
      <item>9 That a preacher is a good man no longer then hee is in the Pulpit. <hi>They thinke all like themselues.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>10 That a man may repent when hee will, because the Scripture saith, <hi>At what time soeuer a sinner doth repent him of his sinne, &amp;c.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>12 That it is an easier thing to please God, then to please our neighbour.</item>
      <item>13 That yee can keepe the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements as well as God will giue you leaue.</item>
      <item>13 That it is safest to doe in religion as most doe.</item>
      <item>14 That merry ballads and bookes, as <hi>Sk<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ggin, Beuis of Southampton, &amp;c.</hi> are good to driue away the time, and to remooue heart qualmes.</item>
      <item>15 That yee serue God with all your hearts▪ and that you would be sorry else.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="4"/>
16 That a man need not heare so many Sermons, except hee could follow them better.</item>
      <item>17 That a man which commeth at no Sermons, may as well beleeue, as hee which heares all the Sermons in the world.</item>
      <item>18 That ye know all the Preacher can tell you. For hee can say nothing, but that euery man is a sinner that wee must loue our neighbours as our selues, that euery man must be saued by Christ: and all this ye can tell as well as he.</item>
      <item>19 That it was a good world, when the old religion was, because all things were cheape.</item>
      <item>20 That drinking and bezeling in the alehouse or tauerne is good fellowship, and shewes a good kind nature, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines neighbourhood.</item>
      <item>21 That a man may sweare by the Masse, because it is nothing now: and by<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Lady, because shee it gone out of the countrey.</item>
      <item>22 That euery man must bee for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and God for vs all.</item>
      <item>23 That a man may make of his owne whatsoeuer he can.</item>
      <item>24 That if a man remember to say
<pb facs="5"/>his praiers in the morning (though he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnderstand them) hee hath blessed himselfe for all the day following.</item>
      <item>25 That a man praieth when hee saith the ten commandements.</item>
      <item>26 That a man eates his maker in the Sacrament.</item>
      <item>27 That if a man be no adulterer, no theefe, no murtherer, &amp; do no man harme, he is a right honest man.</item>
      <item>28 That a man neede not to haue any knowledge of religion, because he is not book-learned.</item>
      <item>29 That one may haue a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when hee saith and doth that which is euill.</item>
      <item>30 That a man may goe to wizzards, called wise men, for counsell: because God hath prouided a salue for euery sore.</item>
      <item>31 That yee are to bee excused in all your doings, because the best men are sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</item>
      <item>32 That yee haue so strong a faith in Christ, that no euill company can hurt you.</item>
   </list>
   <p>
      <hi>These and such like sayings, what argue they but your grosse ignorance? Now where
<pb facs="5"/>ignorance raineth, there raignes sin: and where sinne raignes, there the diuell rules: and where he rules, men are in a damnable case.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ye will reply vnto me thus that yee are not so bad as I would make you. If neede be you can say the Creed, the Lords praier, &amp; the ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: and therfore ye will be of Gods beliefe, say all men what they will, and you defie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell from your hearts.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I answer againe, that it is not sufficient to say all these without booke, vnles ye can vnderstand the meaning of the words, and be able to make a right vse of the commandements, of the Creed, of the Lords prayer, by applying them inwardly to your hearts and consciences, and outwardly to your liues and conuersation. This is the very point in which ye faile.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And for a helpe in this your ignorance, to bring you to true knowledge, vnfained faith and sound repentance, heere I haue set downe the principall points of Christian Religion in sixe plaine and easie rules: euen such as the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest may easily learne: and hereunto is adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an exposition of them word by word. If yee doe want other good directions, then vse this my labour for your good instruction. In reading of it, first learne the sixe principles: and when you haue them without booke, and the meaning of the withall, then learne the exposition
<pb facs="6"/>also: which beeing well conceiued, and in some me asure felt in the heart, ye shall be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by Sermons, whereas now ye cannot: and the ordinary parts of the Catechisme, namely, the ten Commandements, the Creeds, the Lords prayer, and the institution of the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, shall more easily be vnderstood.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, <hi>William Perkins.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>