<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH, Puissant and Renowned King, IAMES by the grace of God King of great BRITTAINE, FRAVNCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Fayth. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Morgan, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110036_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07721</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18105</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110036</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH, Puissant and Renowned King, IAMES by the grace of God King of great BRITTAINE, FRAVNCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Fayth. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Morgan, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The perfection of horse-manship, drawne from nature; arte, and practise. By Nicholas Morgan of Crolane, in the countye of Kent, Gent</title>
                 <author>Morgan, Nicholas, of Crolane</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 188, 191-255, 266-272, 4, 273-288, 288-295, 295-343, 144-145, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MOST HIGH,</hi> Puissant and Renowned King, IAMES <hi>by the grace of God</hi> King of great BRITTAINE, FRAVNCE, <hi>and</hi> IRELAND, Defender of the Fayth. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all Creatures</hi> which the high and mighty Creator of the World hath form'd on Earth (most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and sacred Soueraigne) those euer haue been iustly (by all vertuous and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Spirits) crowned with the Garland of Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, by whom the knowledge &amp; glory of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, hath been best knowen and aduanced: of which, onely Man, by heauenly grace thereunto created, &amp; also by like grace, to the rule and dominion ouer all other Creatures, as to his Birth-right (purposely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained) is aboue all others in superlatiue esteeme.</p>
   <p>In like maner (amongst inferior Creatures) none
<pb facs="3"/>may enter the Listes of compare, with those whome the omnipotēt Creator hath enriched with greatest abylities for the vse and glory of man. <hi>Nam in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus est cadem Ratio, similitudinis eorum debet idem ius ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istimari:</hi> For the Verdict of Reason must passe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Euidence of Proportion. And what scrutiny can finde a Beaste more behouefull to the greatnesse of persons of Estate, and necessary to men of inferior condition then the Horse, which besides (his seruiceable obedience) is beautified with a chiefe Excellency of comely shape and couragious boldenesse. So that the glory of Princes can be by none more highly aduaunced, their Armyes more inuincibly fenced, or their Enimies more speedily subuerted. Hence it is, that Antiquity, named them <hi>Iumenta,</hi> as the chiefe Adiumēta or helpes of humane nature, that by the very name, the noblenesse, necessa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry vse and profite of them might be knowen, and the diuision betwixt the Noble and Worthy, Base and Vnworthy, manifested in fit difference: Wherevnto, none, onely the Learned and generall practise of all former Ages, but more particularly, the Statute-Lawes of this your Royall Kingdome of England do subscribe: recording them to be the maintenance of the strength &amp; preseruation of euery Kingdome: Without them, the pride of the Enemy, wanting no boldnesse to attempt, cannot but bring dishonor and detryment to Prince and Countrey. So that man cannot be so much seruaunt to his owne conceit, or so iniurious to such seruiceable Deserts, but that he must acknowledge, not onely the Excellency, but
<pb facs="3"/>also the necessity of a Creature (by inseperable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity) so lincked vnto him, that with it no Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme is vnpossible, and without it, the least exployt hardly accomplished. Now, although this your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned and flourishing kingdome be so fortunate in blessings, as neuer to haue deaffed any eares of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Countreyes, with supplication for assistance, yet forasmuch as all good Races and breed of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are therein so decayed, that neither the true shape of their primary creation, neyther their perfect and right maner of their breeding, &amp; preseruatiō in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, neither the knowledge of their natural qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyties (without proofe &amp; practise) is by fewe or none discerned, neither by writing or practise fore opened, (without which, that olde Chiualry of our English Nation cannot be continued) &amp; thereby Error and Ignorance (two inseperable Twinnes of this Age) through Custome (the Tyrant of all Ages,) more predomynate, then was the palpable darkenesse of Egypt. Who is not afrayed least the idle delightes and delicacies of this inuerted &amp; infected Age, (the first seedes of subuersions of all Kingdomes) make your Subiectes degenerate from their Auncestors happy care in this kind? seeing the Learned forbeare to practise, and the Practisers forbeare to study: each man respecting his bred-conceit and owne priuate end, more then their Mother, the Common-weale: the trueth wherof al mens eyes depose. The feeling, consideration hereof, being engrafted in the Temple of my memory, seeing the most excellent Horsemen, thunderstrucken with the feare, by vewing what
<pb facs="4"/>heeretofore was yl done, was drawen to the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that was not done, and to acknowledge <hi>Paria esse nihil fieri, et inepte aliquid fieri.</hi> Therefore, for the reuiuing of the dead senses in the liuing minds of such as shal desire knowledge how to refel al former Errors therin, I haue perfected this worke; being as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, that which is once true, remayneth true for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, neither can by art or strength be chāged into vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth no more then pure gold in deed, be no lenger gold: My selfe for the time of .xxxv. yeares past, (as to my fatal delight &amp; period of desire) giuen to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; practise of the most learned and best experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in this Subiet, was long imprisoned in the dark dungiō of their diuisions (yet alwaies gasped to sucke the thinnest Ayer of true knowledge) at length perceiued, that the searching out of trueth, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in all men, according to that saying of <hi>Isocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> to <hi>Euagoras:</hi> Artes and Sciences receiue their perfections, not by relying vpō the sayings &amp; opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men of former ages (of how great Authority soeuer) but in finding out the trueth, to correct and change whatsoeuer is found vntrue. This mooued <hi>Aristotle</hi> for the discouery of high secrets of Nature in his naturall and supernaturall Philosophy, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the error of many excellent personages: &amp; more when occasion was offered, spared not his Maister <hi>PLATO,</hi> adiudging (as himselfe affirmeth in his first Booke of Ethicks) the honor of truth to be preferred before all duties: Yet farre more easie shall I wring from <hi>Hercules</hi> his Club, then the deepe apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of olde error, suddenly lose the colour died in the
<pb facs="4"/>thicke braines of cōmon people: for, <hi>Plaebis ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia periculi rationem sui non hebet:</hi> The ignorance of cōmon people hath no apprehension of their owne danger. Who can be ignorant, that all or the moste part of your subiects, at the entry into this your king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and euer sithence haue acknowledged your sacred gifts beyond the reach of all inuention, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by sounding foorth their ioyes, eache man discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his most hearty embracement of so gratious &amp; blessed a Soueraigne? How should I, thogh the least and last of all others (if no iealous <hi>IVNO</hi> hinder the flight,) possiblye feare, (if vnworthynesse did not breede feare,) to leaue this sparke of my inwarde and loyall affection (to his naturall assention) to flye to the most Highe in highnesse, in whome the fulnesse of knowledge and practise of this Subiect doeth rest so farre beyond the rest, as Knowledge and Practise dothe or can adde to Nature, to whome FAME it selfe dareth not call an Equall: whose shadowe of perfection, by imputation ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth perfect the imperfection of this my perfection, as thinges below receiue Light or Darkenesse from aboue. This Treatise I haue drawen from the springs of Nature, Arte and Practise, whereby shall eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeere all perfection of breede, shape and exquisite action: First, to haue Commencement from Nature. Then to bee guided by generall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes and vniuersall groundes of Arte. Lastly, perfected and preserued by vse and practise. And when these bee truely vnderstoode, then, and not before, shal this, now wthiered &amp; dead Art of Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship
<pb facs="5"/>blaze this MOTTO, <hi>Hijs radijs rediuiua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resco.</hi> Your Maiesties performance heerein cannot but tende to the immortall Fame of your Person, the terror of your Enemyes, the strength of your Kingdomes, and the general applaud of your louing Subiectes, whose eyes hauing seene the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment, whatsoeuer they haue heeretofore seene, shalbe but as Stubble to lower grasse.</p>
   <p>Now, with Hart and Handes lifted vp to the King of all Kinges, I pray; That as he hath made you the greatest on Earth, so may your yeares be in this; and after, your place in the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties least and vnworthiest subiect:</hi>
Nicholas Morgan.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>