<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTVOVS AND chaste Maiden, Mistresse Eliz. G. daughter to the VVorshipfull Rob. C. Esquire, yours in seruice W.N. wisheth all fortunes smiles, with the dew of im∣mortall felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110078_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07968</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTVOVS AND chaste Maiden, Mistresse Eliz. G. daughter to the VVorshipfull Rob. C. Esquire, yours in seruice W.N. wisheth all fortunes smiles, with the dew of im∣mortall felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Barley-breake, or, A vvarning for vvantons. Written by W.N. Gent</title>
                 <author>W. N., gent</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTVOVS AND chaste Maiden, Mistresse <hi>Eliz. G.</hi> daughter to the <hi>VVorshipfull</hi> Rob. C. <hi>Esquire, yours</hi> in seruice W.N. wisheth all fortunes smiles, with the dew of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne (right vertuous) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the wise, the sillie Oaten pipe, winded by a rurall Shepheard, vnder a shadowing Hawthorne, sprouting on a champion mountaine, hath beene as highly esteemed, as the curious strained Lute, sounded by the cunning Musician in the richest chamber of the Court of the most potentate Princes, and that a sillie braunch reft from an Oliue tree, hath beene as accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as the most precious perle dragd from the sands of the Ocean. Then, seeing the zeale lyeth not in the gift, but in the giuer: I shall entreat you as gratefully to accept this my Treatise, as I deliuer it, not for the worth, but as a testimonie of the zeale and duety from me belonging, which so long time I haue studied how to manifest. And thus hoping there shall be nothing herein construed contrarie to my simple meaning, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my presumption held in disdaine, I end, though not forgetting my bounden duetie to your VVorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Parent and my very good friend, to whom if this my Pamphlet may cause mirth, as an Arbour test, it hath his desire, and my hopes accomplished.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>