<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honou∣rable
Sir Fraunces Walsingham Knight,
principall Secretarie to the Queene, her
most excellent Maiestie.</title>
           <author>P., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110356_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09213</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19523</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honou∣rable
Sir Fraunces Walsingham Knight,
principall Secretarie to the Queene, her
most excellent Maiestie.</title>
                 <author>P., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trve reporte, of the late discoueries, and possession, taken in the right of the Crowne of Englande, of the new-found landes : by that valiaunt and worthye gentleman, Sir Humfrey Gilbert Knight. Wherein is also breefely sette downe, her highnesse lawfull tytle therevnto, and the great and manifolde commodities, that is likely to grow thereby, to the whole realme in generall, and to the aduenturers in particular. Together with the easines and shortnes of the voyage. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Peckham, George, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hinde, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>74 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Sir Fraunces Walsingham Knight,
principall Secretarie to the Queene, her
most excellent Maiestie.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW much more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie</hi>
might I account my selfe,
(right honourable Sir) if I had
so well applied my time in this
Vniuersitie, as through my more
dilligent studye, I were able to
handle the matter, (which I
haue in this Treatise taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
me) as the worthynes thereof dooth meryte.</p>
   <p>Truely Sir I was for a time, drawen into a doubtfull
ballaunce, whether I should proceede therein, as my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
intised me, or leaue it off, as good discretion
aduised mee. Eftsoones haue I righte hartely wished
that some of those rype, and perfect witts, adorned with
like iudgement, (wherewith God hath plentifully blessed
this our age) woulde haue imploied their pennes, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly
to haue sette foorth thys cause: But seeing that
in wishing, I doo fynde nothing, but to wish, and
that the case so standeth, as eyther the thyng, right
woorthye bothe knowledge, and practise, shall styll
<pb facs="3"/>
lie in a slumber, or rather rest buryed in the graue
of obliuion, vnlesse I doo make publique my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and insufficiencye, and therby subiect my selfe
to the diuersitye of mens iudgements, I haue made
choyse, rather to indure the disgrace of the one, then
that my Countrey shoulde sustaine the inconuenience
of the other, trusting that your honour (who hath
hetherto beene a principall Patron of this Action) will
vpon my humble sute vouchsafe your fauourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
heereof. For wee doo reade (right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble)
that <hi>Archimedes</hi> in respecte of his grauitie and
wisedome) helde that reputation amongst the <hi>Syracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sans,</hi>
that whatsoeuer he allowed, was accounted for
good: which historye, if I shoulde apply vnto your
honour perticularlie, as both aptlie and truely I could,
I might (in the opinion of some men) incurre the sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition
of flattery, and receiue from your Honour but
the like aunswer, which King <hi>Theseus</hi> made vnto blind
<hi>Oedipus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I doo not (quoth hee) O <hi>Oedipus,</hi> honour my selfe
with other mens words, but with mine owne works.
In silence therefore will I passe your ready and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
disposition, bothe honourably to fauour, and
fauourably to further all such attemptes as seeme plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
to GOD and profitable to your Countrey, both
which (by the testimony of good writers, the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of wise men, and experience of great trauailors,
these <hi>VVesterne Discoueries</hi> doo certainly promise. In
regarde whereof, I doo the rather presume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
this Pampflet to bee Patronized by so woorthy
a personne, whereby my escapes may bee the more
easilye excused, my willing paynes the better accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="3"/>
and the voyage more effectually supplyed.</p>
   <p>Thus beeing lothe any longer to detayne your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
from your weightye affayres, I humblye take
leaue, beseeching GOD manie yeeres to lengthen
your life, with much encrease of honour. <hi>From my
lodging in</hi> Oxforde, <hi>the tweluth of</hi> Nouember.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours poore Scholler,</hi>
in all seruice to vse. <hi>G. P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>