<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Trauellers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110474_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09666</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19936</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110474</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Trauellers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pimlyco. Or, Runne Red-cap : Tis a mad world at Hogsdon</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Barley (Barlow), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Loftus (Loftis), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all Trauellers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou that weare out your liues and weary your bodies,
in <hi>Discouery of strange Countries,</hi> (bee it for
pleasure or profite) Rig out a <hi>Fleet,</hi> and make a <hi>Voi</hi>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
to an <hi>Iland</hi> which could neuer be found out by
the <hi>Portugals, Spaniards,</hi> or <hi>Hollanders,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
(and that now of late) by <hi>Englishmen.</hi> The name of it is <hi>Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyco,</hi>
Here haue I drawne a large <hi>Map</hi> of it: by this <hi>Chart,</hi> may
you in a few houres, and with little or no winde, ariue in the very
mouth of the <hi>Hauen.</hi> Some that haue trauelled thither, affirme it
to be a part of the <hi>Continent,</hi> but the better sort of <hi>Nauigators</hi>
say, it is an <hi>Iland:</hi> full of people it is, and they are very wilde, the
women beeing able to endure more, and to doe better Seruice than
the men. Diuers are of opinion, that it is an inchanted <hi>Iland,</hi> and
haunted with strange <hi>Spirits;</hi> for the people there, once euery Moone,
are either starke mad, or else loose their owne shapes, and are trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
into Beasts, yet within twelue houres, recouer their wittes
and shapes againe. The <hi>Pimlyconians</hi> are most of them <hi>Malt-men,</hi>
and exceeding good fellowes, all their delight beeing in <hi>Eating</hi> and
<hi>Drinking;</hi> they liue not long, for a man can hardly star amongest
them two dayes: if he doe, he is in great danger, by reason of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
disease, (which the <hi>Iland</hi> naturally breedes) called the <hi>Stag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi>
through which, many of them come to their <hi>Downe-fall,</hi> or
if they scape that, then are they in feare to be made away by <hi>Small<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot,</hi>
in discharging of which, the <hi>Pimlyconians</hi> are very actiue
and cunning.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
The <hi>Iland</hi> begins now to be as rich as it is populous: fish hath bin
s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ldome taken there, but flesh is better cheape then <hi>Mackrell</hi> here.
Wilde <hi>Duckes</hi> and wilde <hi>Geese</hi> flie there vp and downe in aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance:
you may haue a <hi>Goose sowe'd</hi> in <hi>Pimlyco,</hi> for the value of
twelue pence sterling. Woodcockes (in many moneths of the yeere)
are to be catched there by whole dozens. It is full of fatte pasture,
and thats the reason such multitudes of <hi>young Colts</hi> runne there.
<hi>A hot Climate</hi> it is, and by that meanes the people are subiect to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
which takes them first in the <hi>Head,</hi> and so falls downe into
their legges, and those fayling, they are (in a maner) gone. The
<hi>Gouernour</hi> of the <hi>Iland</hi> hath much adoe to <hi>keepe himselfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi>
so that he is compelled to giue those that are vnder him, often
times very <hi>Hard measure,</hi> yet are they so vnruly, that euery houre
one or other goes to the <hi>Pot.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus haue I giuen you a taste, both of the People and of the
<hi>Countrie;</hi> if you sayle thither, you may drinke of deeper knowledge.
But take heed you take a skilfull <hi>Pilot</hi> with you; be fraighted with
as much wit as you can carry aboord, for all will be little enough to
bring you from thence, and take heede what <hi>Lading</hi> you take in
there, for the commodities of <hi>Pimlyco</hi> haue suncke many
<hi>Merchants.</hi> Pay thankes for my <hi>Councell,</hi>
and thinke well of my <hi>Pimlyconian
Discouerie.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>