<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Sampson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110067_Bo1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07905</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18276</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110067</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Sampson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mirrour of mutabilitie, or Principall part of the Mirrour for magistrates : Describing the fall of diuers famous princes, and other memorable personages. Selected out of the sacred Scriptures by Antony Munday, and dedicated to the Right Honorable the Earle of Oxenford</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ballard, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome men fix their fancies on simple shado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes</hi> / esteeming <hi>Vanitie</hi> as a <hi>Vertue</hi> to vaunt of addicting their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>des to <hi>Carnall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> wishing their Bags wel st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, which is their whole pleasure. Some againe to hauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of hart, which (as they think) is a goodly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ry. Some to seek the ruinate spoyle of his <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrye</hi> to pleasure the <hi>Enemye,</hi> and thinketh his deed woorthy of eternall memory. Some to the vtter vndooing of their Neighbours, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by all meanes possible to depriue him of his honest name, hoping therby to get great cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. Some to vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>awfull liking, which moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth their vnbrideled nature to stretch beyond the bounds of loyaltie, and hopeth for prayse all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be with great infamy. Some also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in corragious Carowsing, with the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall qualities of Quaffing, the which some frequent only for the name of a Lusty <hi>Carovvser,</hi> though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>all honesty is vsed with such an <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer.</hi> And some giue themselues to sluggish <hi>Sloth,</hi> wishing rather three houres sleep▪ then one inch
<pb facs="27"/>
of profit. Of all which, seuerally in these Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before passed: I haue drawen some declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, compacting therin <hi>(The seuen deadly Sinnes)</hi> with their due obtayned hire. And now for that some occasion is offered vnto me, to proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my enterprise: I haue adioyned heerto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other exeellent Historyes, selected out of the moste sacred Scripture, desiring <hi>(Gentle Reader)</hi> thy freendly ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>erencye, although I want the rules of practised Poetrye / wherwith I might haue flaunted it more gallantly, I referre that to those of more riper excellencye, and accept this (though homely) yet offered willingly / and if I had been experienced, or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s might haue come aquainted with such eloquent spe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: be sure that I would haue then launched it out with an Emperours liberalitie.</p>
   <p>But finding my store house so far vnfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, and that trueth need not be so brauely burnished, I yeeld my self to thy gentle courtesie, &amp; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d my defence on thy freendly clemency.</p>
   <p>Sempre Amico vostro. A. Munday.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>