<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH and mighty Prince, HENRY Prince of great BRITTAINE apparent.</title>
           <author>Morgan, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110036_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07721</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18105</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110036</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH and mighty Prince, HENRY Prince of great BRITTAINE apparent.</title>
                 <author>Morgan, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The perfection of horse-manship, drawne from nature; arte, and practise. By Nicholas Morgan of Crolane, in the countye of Kent, Gent</title>
                 <author>Morgan, Nicholas, of Crolane</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 188, 191-255, 266-272, 4, 273-288, 288-295, 295-343, 144-145, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH <hi>and mighty Prince,</hi> HENRY Prince of great BRITTAINE apparent.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thrice worthy (and</hi> long decayed) Skill of Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship (right Noble Prince) whether it stande more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to your Royall inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which it is newly reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or to your practicall perfection, by which it is rarely beautified, I had rather the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of good Races and perfect Riders, then the rudenes of my Artelesse Pen should decide. And what fitter Herald can there be to diuulge your loue to our Nation, or your victorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutiō against hostile inuasions, then the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of that whereby all your Hereditary Kingdomes must be walled and enlarged, your Foes daunted, &amp; your victorious Name enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd. Heerevnto if by these my elaborate Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections
<pb facs="6"/>and experienced Obseruations, your Highnesse may bee happily incited, I make no question, but this little Iland, will furnish you with so fit places for breeding, and so sufficient Riders for managing, that your men shall not complain for want of excellent Horses, nor your Horses groane for want of worthy Riders. This pleasing Harmony, your forwarde beginnings haue giuen vs great cause to hope, and your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable proceedings will (I doubt not) afford vs the happines to see. By those was this naked Impe of mine first bred, and by these it lookes to bee still fostered, as being his first Fruits: who with his harty praiers for your endlesse happinesse, hath who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuoted his vnworthy selfe, to be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnesse most humble Seruaunt,</hi>
NICOLAS MORGAN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>