<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the KINGS most Excellent MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Standish, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110882_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12915</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23201</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the KINGS most Excellent MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Standish, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The commons complaint : VVherein is contained tvvo speciall grieuances: The first, the generall destruction and waste of woods in this kingdome, with a remedy for the same: also how to plant wood according to the nature of euery soyle, without losse of any ground; and how thereby many more and better cattell may be yeerely bred, with the charge and profit that yeerely may arise thereby. The second grieuance is, the extreame dearth of victuals. Fovre remedies for the same</title>
                 <author>Standish, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 34 pages, 2 leaves of plates (1 folded), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the <hi>KINGS</hi> most Excellent <hi>MAIESTIE.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>EXT vnto GOD, most dread Soueraigne, the loue and dutie that I owe vnto your Maiestie and Kingdome, hath imbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to Dedicate the fruits of my old age and trauell vnto your Highnesse, hoping that the subiect thereof will no way offend You. It is intended to the good of your Maiestie and your Royall Progenie, the generall good of the Common-wealth for all posteritie; and in part tendeth to your Princely
<pb facs="3"/> speech to the Parliament. What I shall herein set downe I prooue by the best Schoolemaster, which is, my long experience, hauing spent many yeares in the attaining thereunto, especially these foure last yeares, wherein I haue imployed my study and trauel through some parts of most of the Countries of this Kingdome for this purpose, oft ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conference with many of the best Commonwealths-men for my better vnderstanding; desiring by all good means to ataine to a perfect knowledge how to Plant, preserue, and maintaine the blessings of God as well in this our destroying age as they haue beene in former times, wherein was left a prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and plentie of that which is now in effect destroyed. All are giuen to take the profit present, but few or none at all
<pb facs="3"/> regard the posteritie or future times. This exercise in all ages hath beene in high account with the wisest and most worthiest, and hath beene blessed by God himselfe, (as hath appeared to the world:) and by the approbation of your Maiestie, may bee so put in execution, as the branches thereof may bee spread ouer all your Dominions, to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdening of your louing Subiects of all their grieuances present and to come. I spare to proceede any further, since your Maiestie whom God hath filled with the spirit of wisedome in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, by your ready apprehension vnderstandeth much more then I can speake heereof. Thus submitting my poore labours, or rather worthlesse mite, to the consideration of your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maiesty, hauing nothing else to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="4"/> the same withall, but my humble prayers to the King of Kings, to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply the giftes of his holy Spirit more and more vpon you, and that you may Reigne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny happie yeeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnesse most humble Subiect,</hi> Arthur Standish.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>