<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ In Commendation of the painfull Sea-men.</title>
           <author>Goddard, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110544_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11283</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21549</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ In Commendation of the painfull Sea-men.</title>
                 <author>Goddard, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The safegarde of saylers, or great rutter : Contayning the courses, distances, soundings, flouds and ebbes, with the marks for the entring of sundry harboroughs both of England, Fraunce, Spaine, Ireland, Flaunders, and the soundes of Denmarke, with other necessarie rules of common nauigation. Translated out of Dutch into English by Robert Norman hydrographer. And newly corrected and augmented by E.W</title>
                 <author>Antoniszoon, Cornelis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Astley, Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 158 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>¶ In Commendation of the painfull Sea-men.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WHo so in surging Seas, his season will consume,</l>
      <l>And meanes thereof to make his onely trade to liue:</l>
      <l>That man must surely knowe the shifting Sunne &amp; Moone,</l>
      <l>For trying of his Tides, how they doe take and giue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>So must he duely seeke the Eclipticke course of Sunne,</l>
      <l>How he from West to East his proper course doth keepe:</l>
      <l>His labour then (God knowes) as yet is but begunne,</l>
      <l>For he must watch and ward, and shake off sluggish sleepe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And haue a carefull eye, to hand that is at Helme,</l>
      <l>For many one there is, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t false his course will plye:</l>
      <l>And swelling Seas likewise, the Ship may ouer-whelme,</l>
      <l>Or set her on the shore, without the Pylots eye.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <l>When <hi>Boreas</hi> is abroad, and blustring blasts doe blowe,</l>
      <l>In season must he seeke to short in loftye sayle:</l>
      <l>For that, if not in time he very well doth knowe,</l>
      <l>That all too late indeede, no labour will preuayle.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But when the raging stormes doe swinge the ship on hye,</l>
      <l>Ofte times (against his will) he spoones before the seas:</l>
      <l>Else in goes all the sayles, and takes her from her trye,</l>
      <l>In haste to driue or hull, till God the same appease.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus when he all the night, with wearie toyle hath tride,</l>
      <l>And sees the swelling seas hath set him from his way:</l>
      <l>Then when a litle slacke of calme he hath espide,</l>
      <l>With ioyfull heart to take the height he doth assay.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>His <hi>Astrolabie</hi> then he setteth for the Sunne,</l>
      <l>Or <hi>Crosse-staffe</hi> for the starre called the <hi>Ballastile:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And thus with help of them and declination,</l>
      <l>How land doth beare of him, he knowes within a while.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then by his <hi>Compasse</hi> straight he duly sets his course,</l>
      <l>And thus he brings the ship in safetie to her Porte:</l>
      <l>Where of his hazards past he makes a great discourse,</l>
      <l>And each man (by desert) doth giue him good reporte.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If Pylots painfull toyle be lifted then alofte,</l>
      <l>For vsing of his Arte according to his kinde:</l>
      <l>What fame is due to them that first this Arte out sought,</l>
      <l>And first instructions gaue to them that were but blinde?</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. N.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>