<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE
to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Proctor, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110512_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10152</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20411</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110512</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE
to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Proctor, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The righteous mans way : Wherein are given certaine directions, how men may profitably meditate upon the Commandements of God: that so through such manner of meditation, the Lordes Commandements may finde place in mens hearts, to serve in them as guides unto all their actions and thoughts. Directions most needfull for these times, seeing most men laying the commandements of God aside, doe leade their lives in disobedience to Gods commandements; and this, not onely to the scandall of Christian religion, but also to the extreame hazard of their own salvation</title>
                 <author>Proctor, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE
to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any of Gods servants (beloved Reader) having writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
at large upon the ten cōmandements, opening them
so, as that men may in a great measure see how farr they
branch themselves, into every action, speach, &amp; thought
of Man, I thought it might be profitable to add unto
their labours, this my direction unto <hi>Meditation upon
the Commandements.</hi> For, I observe in most Men a kinde
of disposition, willingly to heare or reade of the Commandements, that
so their knowledge might be increased; but there is little evidence of any
who meditate also of them in private, that by such meditatiō upon them,
they may sink into their hearts, there to remaine as directors unto them,
in all things wherein they may haue use of them. The very Notion one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of Gods Commandements is surely profitable, as serving to informe
Men of the <hi>way</hi> they should walk in, but meditation upon them rootes
them within us; because, what our Spirit once labours upon, it will not
easily forgoe againe, but will retaine and make use of the same, and this
also to the end, wherefore the paines to meditate upon it was taken. For
if any man purpose with himselfe, and set his hearte to seeke Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
that they may serve to guide and rule him in his wayes, he
joyning private meditation, or selfe-questioning and selfe examining
with the same, his hearte will then affect and indeavour to come to the
end of its purpose. For this cause haue I chosen to direct men unto a
manner of meditation upon the Lords Commandements that so through
meditation, the Commandements of God may not rest in the bare Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but may branch themselves out in the actions, speaches, yea and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
thoughts of men. But because the streame of this worlds dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
runns violently against the man that would keepe Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
(for such is in most men the custome to erre from the wayes of
Gods commandements, that he that walks in them, shall hardly finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
man, that is not eyther against him, or at leastwise not addicted to
that way he walks in) And because our owne corrupt nature is hardly
brought in obedience, to yeeld to walke in the wayes of righteousness,
Therefore I haue purposely set my selfe to shewe, (in the first place, and
in severall chapters a parte) certaine motives or inducements, by which
men may be brought on, to take upon them, as for <hi>a light burthen, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy
yoake,</hi> the holy <hi>Commandements</hi> of God, which are as his <hi>burthen and yoak</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
which he for Mans good hath put upon us. I am not ignorant, that the
world threatens me to labour herein in vaine; for such rooting in Men
hath the pleasure of sinne taken, that it is almost unexpectable, that they
should leave to sinne those, sinnes, by which their laughter, hearts joy, &amp;
firmest bond of fellowship is commonly occasioned; but my trust is in
God, that there are thousand thousands in the world, who, not
being of the world, will not goe the way of the worlde, but, as aymers at
another world, will give diligent heede to all good directions how to
come to the glorious world which is to come, Yea, seeing there is a <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of many unto Righteousness,</hi> Daniel, 12, 3, who walked in the wayes
of unrighteousness, I cannot but hope, that many, even in the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
multitude, may yet be wonn, to bethinke themselves ere it be too
late, of the evill way wherein they walke, and of the good way of Gods
holy Commandements. Many indeede are the inducements unto sinne,
and they are also very powerfull, to move yonge, and lusty, and covetous
persons, to walk rather in the way of sinnes, then in the way of Gods Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements;
but alas, as the pleasure of a whore ends often times in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable
and loathsome disease, when yet during the pleasure there will be
no eare given to any warning of danger, so men that are overcome of the
inducements unto sinne, doe but gather more and more matter for their
own grief &amp; destruction. The way of God is peace, health, and Glory;
but the way of Satan (the miss-leader of the miss-led,) is, trouble of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
disease of body, &amp; eternal Infamy. In hope therefore that all wil not
be so evill minded as to neglect the way of God, rejecting also all Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
upon the Commandements of God, but that some will be wonn to
exercise themselves in such Meditation, that so they may reape the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
fruite of righteousness, I will now conclude this epistle,
and send my Reader to the Treatise its selfe,
where directions how to meditate
are given.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord
THOMAS PROCTO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>