<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the ryght Honorable Maister Doctor Wotton: One of the Quenes Maesties piuye Counsayle. Alexander Neuyle wysheth Health: with encrease of Honor.</title>
           <author>Nuyle, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110874_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11913</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22225</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110874</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the ryght Honorable Maister Doctor Wotton: One of the Quenes Maesties piuye Counsayle. Alexander Neuyle wysheth Health: with encrease of Honor.</title>
                 <author>Nuyle, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentable tragedie of Oedipus the sonne of Laius Kyng of Thebes out of Seneca. By Alexander Neuyle</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Colwell, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>98 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the ryght Honorable Maister Doctor Wotton: One of the Quenes Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esties p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iuye Counsayle. <hi>Alexander Neuyle</hi> wysheth Health: with encrease of Honor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen first right honorable Syr, I trauayled in the translation of this present Tragedie, Written by the moste graue, vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous &amp; Christian Ethenicke (For so doubteth not <hi>Erasmus</hi> to terme him) <hi>Lucius A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>neus Seneca:</hi> I minded nothynge lesse, than that at any tyme thus rudely transformed he shoulde come into the Prynters hands. For I to no other ende re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued hym from his naturall and loftye Style to our corrupt &amp; base,
<pb facs="3"/>
or as al men affyrme it: most barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Language: but onely to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the instant requestes of a fewe my familiar frendes, who thought to haue put it to the very same vse, that <hi>Seneca</hi> hymself in his Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pretended: Whiche was by the tragicall and pompous showe vpon Stage, to admonish all men of theyr fickle Estates, To declare the vnconstant Head of wauering Fortune, her sodaine interchaūged and soone altered face, And ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ely to expresse the iust reuenge, &amp; fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful punishmēts of horrible Crimes, wherwith the wretched worlde in these our myserable daies pyteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly swarmeth. This caused me not to be to precise in folowynge the Author worde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or worde: but som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes by Addition, somtymes by Subtraction, to vse the aptest Phrases in giuing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Sense that I
<pb facs="3"/>
coulde inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt. Wherat a great nombre I knowe wyll be more offended than Reason or Wisdom wold they shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be. Thus as I framed it to one purpose: so haue my fren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es (to whom I can not well d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ny any thyng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyps ryght may seeme iustly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre) wrested it to another effect: and by this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>anes blowen it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, by ouer rasshe &amp; vnaduised pryntyng. By whiche fonde dede I know vndoubtedly I shal receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poisoned Infamies, of a nombre of venemous tonges. Wherfore (ryght honorable Syr:) as I giue these the first Fruictes of my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle vnto you: declarynge therin the great good wyll &amp; dutie that I owe vnto your Honor, for the vertuous Liberalitie of your noble mynde: so am I driuen humbly to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>qyre your strong ayde, &amp; assured Defence against the sclaunderous
<pb facs="4"/>
assaults of such malicious mouths, whiche obtaynd: I shalbe the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encouraged agaynst an other time, to bestow my trauaile in mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of farre greater weyght and importaunce. In the meane sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son (desyryng your Honour to take these symple Attemptes of myne in good parte:) I leaue you to the tuicion of the ryght hyghe &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye GOD: Who kepe you longe in health, &amp; graunt you <hi>NESTORS</hi> yeares: With encrease of Honor.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours to cōmaund. <hi>Alexander N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>uyle.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>