<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Valorous, and worthy all title of Honor, Sr. ELIAS HICKS, KNIGHT, and one of the honorable band of His Majesties Gentlemen Pensi∣oners in Ordinarie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110325_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19501</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110325</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Valorous, and worthy all title of Honor, Sr. ELIAS HICKS, KNIGHT, and one of the honorable band of His Majesties Gentlemen Pensi∣oners in Ordinarie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Coach and sedan, pleasantly disputing for place and precedence : the brewers-cart being moderator</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Crouch (Crowch), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Paxton (Packston), Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raworth, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Valorous, and worthy all title of Honor, S<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> ELIAS HICKS, KNIGHT, and one of the honorable band of His Majesties Gentlemen Pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in Ordinarie.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>NOBLE SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I prefixe so deserving and eminent a name before such light stuffe: I doe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> more then Tavernes and Innes doe, with us heere in <hi>England,</hi> and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countreys, to credit their houses, hang up at the porch, the Pictures (for signes) of Kings; Queenes, Princes and other eminent Persons, under whose subjection they live, or unto whom they stand most affected. The Great <hi>Turk</hi> sets his own stampe upon <hi>Terra Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> an Earth, or Clay; <hi>Virgil</hi> thought his <hi>Gnat</hi> not unworthy the view of <hi>Octavius Caesar:</hi> and with the same confidence I offer thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> few lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your view; who are so belov'd at home, and honor'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ad, especially for that your memorable service
<pb facs="3"/>
somtime at <hi>Mount Auban</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> that Towne even to this day acknowledging her safety, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation to your valour onely, and whom for your resolution and forwardnesse in our late Fleete, your Noble Admirall, the Earle of <hi>Lindsey</hi> honored with the dignitie of Knighthood: If your selfe, <hi>Sir,</hi> or any else shall aske mee, If I had no better imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to set my selfe about then this, I could answere them; The wisest Counsellers and greatest Scholars have ever season'd, and sweetened their profoundest Studies, and greatest employments, with these and the like passages of inoffensive Mirth. <hi>Erasmus</hi> commended the Foole. <hi>Homer</hi> writing his <hi>Illiads,</hi> wrote also the battell betweene Froggs and Mise. <hi>Fannius</hi> extolled the <hi>Nettle</hi>; Sir <hi>Phillip Sydney</hi> made good sport with <hi>Rhombus</hi> his Countrey Schoole-master: and the like many others. Besides, wee live in that Age, wherein <hi>Difficile est Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram non scribere.</hi> But the trueth is, I being at this time in hand with a serious and laborious work for the Presse, ere long to see light; my Printer desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of mee, that hee might not sit idle in the meane time. <hi>Sir</hi> I take my leave, desiring to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and recorded among the number of those, who for your owne worth and goodnesse, truely love and honour you.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>February 19. 1636.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours ever, Mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>maxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>