<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Achelley Cyttyzen
and Marchantailour of London,
for conclusion.</title>
           <author>Achelley, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110356_Fr1_13</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09213</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19523</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Achelley Cyttyzen
and Marchantailour of London,
for conclusion.</title>
                 <author>Achelley, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trve reporte, of the late discoueries, and possession, taken in the right of the Crowne of Englande, of the new-found landes : by that valiaunt and worthye gentleman, Sir Humfrey Gilbert Knight. Wherein is also breefely sette downe, her highnesse lawfull tytle therevnto, and the great and manifolde commodities, that is likely to grow thereby, to the whole realme in generall, and to the aduenturers in particular. Together with the easines and shortnes of the voyage. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Peckham, George, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hinde, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>74 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>Iohn Achelley Cyttyzen
and Marchantailour of London,
for conclusion.</head>
   <l>IF truth and praise haue power, to make this matter gratious:</l>
   <l>VVhat neede we then extoll the thing, hath beene commended thus.</l>
   <l>And by the better sorte that wright, of truth and knowledge so:</l>
   <l>As nothing of this worke, they promised further then they know.</l>
   <l>Beleeue them for they be our freendes, and with our Counties weale:</l>
   <l>Let vs imbrase that God and truth, so loouinglie reueale.</l>
   <l>VVhereof the merrit is no lesse, then is the bruted Fame:</l>
   <l>Aske straungers and that noble minde, that did attempt the same:</l>
   <l>To whom we owe the titles, that to Vertues Nimpes are due:</l>
   <l>So good a Knight whom <hi>English</hi> men, in vertue should persue.</l>
   <l>No doubt but God will blesse th'atempt, succeed him roundly then:</l>
   <l>And in this Voyage follow fast, you that bee <hi>English</hi> men.</l>
   <l>VVith such supplie from time to time, as what is well begonne:</l>
   <l>Bee not for want of men and aide, through slackfulnes vndoone.</l>
   <l>So shall you harbour in your hartes, the seedes of magnanimitie:</l>
   <l>A vertue where with all, the <hi>Romaines</hi> did enlarge their Empery.</l>
   <l>Be you prepared for euery foe, and be couragious then:</l>
   <l>For that you slippe through negligence, will fall to other men.</l>
   <l>Enuie hath eyes to see afarre, your new attempt will whet:</l>
   <l>A number more to seeke therefore, if you your selues forget.</l>
   <l>Send foorth with speede, get footing there and make prouision:</l>
   <l>Tis ill for vs to linger thus, and talke thereof so longe.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Achelley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>