<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110279_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08838</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19121</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110279</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The palace of pleasure beautified, adorned and well furnished, with pleasaunt histories and excellent nouelles, selected out of diuers good and commendable authors. By William Painter clarke of the ordinaunce and armarie</title>
                 <author>Painter, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 135, that is 145, 201-345, that is 341, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>NOTHING in mine opinion cā be more accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table vnto thee (friendely Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der), than ofte reading &amp; dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye perusing of varietie of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, which as they be for diuersitie of matter pleasaunt and plausible, euen so for example and imitacion right good and commendable. The one doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce the wearie and tedious minde, many times inuolued with ordinarie cares, the other prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth a direct path to tread the trace of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent lyfe. VVherefore if in these newes or <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles</hi> here presented, there doe appeare any thing worthy of regard, giue thankes to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gentleman to whome this boke is dedicated, for whose sake onely, that paine (if any seme to be) was wholie imployed. Inioy therfore with him this present boke, &amp; curteously with frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delie talke report the same, for if otherwise
<pb facs="11"/>
thou doe abuse it, the blame shall light on thee, and not of me, which only of good wil did meane it firste. But yet if blaming tongues and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stayed heades, will nedes be busie, they shall sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the shame, for that they haue not yet she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen forth any blamelesse dede to like effect, as this is ment of me, which whē they doe, no blame but praise they can receyue. For praise be they well worthie for to haue, which in well doing do contend. No vertuous dede, or zelous worke can want due praise of the honest, though faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foles and youthly heades full ofte do chaūt the faultlesse checke, that <hi>Momus</hi> mouth did once finde out in <hi>Venus</hi> Slipper. And yet from faults I will not purge the same, but whatsoeuer they seme to be, they be in number ne yet in substance such, but that thy curteous dealing may sone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them or forget them. VVherefore to giue thee full aduertisment of the whole collection of these <hi>Nouelles,</hi> vnderstand that .vj. of them haue I selected out of <hi>Titus Liuius,</hi> two out of <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> certayne out of <hi>Aelianus, Xenophon, Aulus Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Plutarche</hi> and other like approued authors, Other <hi>Nouelles</hi> haue I adioyned, chosen out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Italian and French writers. VVherin I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
<pb facs="11"/>
my selfe not to be so well trained, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as the fine heades of such trauailers would desire. And yet I trust sufficiently to expresse the sense, of euery of the same. Certayne haue I culled out of the <hi>Decamerone</hi> of <hi>Giouan Boccaccio</hi> wherein be contayned one hundred <hi>Nouelles,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongs which there be some (in my iudgement) that be worthy to be condempned to perpetuall prison, but of them suche haue I redemed to the liberty of our vulgar, as may be best liked, and better suffred. Although the .vj. part of the same hundreth may full well be permitted. And as I my selfe haue already done many other of the same worke, yet for this present I haue thought good to publishe onely .x. in number, the rest I haue referred to them that be able with better stile to expresse the authors eloquence, or vntill I adioyne to this another to me, if none other in the meane time doe preuent me, which with all my heart I wishe and desire: bicause the whole works of <hi>Boccaccio</hi> for his stile, order of writing, grauitie, and sententious discourse, is worthy of intire provulgation. Out of <hi>Bandello</hi> I haue selected .vij. chosing rather to follow <hi>Launay</hi> and <hi>Belleforest</hi> the French Translators, than the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren
<pb facs="12"/>
soile of his owne vaine, who being a <hi>Lombard</hi> doth franckly confesse himselfe to be no fine <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine,</hi> or trim <hi>Thoscane,</hi> as eloquent and gentle <hi>Boccaccio</hi> was. Diuers other also be extracted out of other Italian and French authors. All which (I trust) be both profitable and pleasant, and will be lyked of the indifferent Reader.</p>
   <p>Profitable they be in that they disclose what glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, honor, and preferment ech man attayneth by good desert, what felicitie by honest attempts, what good successe, laudable enterprises doe bring to the coragious, what happie ioy and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et state godly loue doth affect the Imbracers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. Profitable I say in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they doe reueale y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of rapes and fleshly actions, the ouerthrow of noble men and Princes by disordered gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement, the tragicall endes of them that vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily doe attempt practises vicious and horrible. VVilt thou learne how to behaue thy selfe with modestie after thou hast achieued any victorious conquest, and not to forget thy prosperous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in the glorious triumphe of the same, by committing a fact vnworthy of thy valiaunce: read the first <hi>Nouell</hi> of the valiant Romane <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratius</hi>? VVilt thou vnderstand what dishonor and
<pb facs="12"/>
infamie, desire of libidinous lust doth bring, read the rape of <hi>Lucrece</hi>? VVilt thou knowe what an vnkind part it is vnnaturallie to abuse the state of thine owne countrie, read <hi>Martius Coriolanus</hi>? VVilt y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> learne what fruit is reaped of wicked lust, to dispoile virgins and maydes of their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test vertue, see the historie of <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> and sir <hi>Didaco</hi> the Spanish knight? Desirest thou to knowe, how closely thou oughtest to kepe the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of honorable mariage, peruse the historie of <hi>Candaules</hi>? Dost y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> couet to be aduertised what is true felicitie, read of king <hi>Craesus</hi> and the wise man <hi>Solon</hi>? Hath y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lady, Gentlewoman, or other of the feminine kind desire to behold a mirroure of Chastitie: let them read ouer the <hi>Nouelles</hi> of the Lady <hi>Panthea,</hi> of the Duchesse of <hi>Sauoie</hi> of the Coūtesse of <hi>Salesburie,</hi> of <hi>Amadour</hi> and <hi>Florinda</hi>? Is the noble man affected to vnderstande what happie ende, the vertue of <hi>Loialtie</hi> and fidelitie doth cōduce, the Earle of <hi>Angiers</hi> may be to him a right good example? VVill Gentlemen learne how to prosecute vertue, and to profligat from their minde, disordinate Loue, and affection; I referre them to the historie of <hi>Tancredi,</hi> and to <hi>Galgano</hi> of <hi>Siena</hi>? Is not the marchaunt contented
<pb facs="13"/>
with his goodes already gotten, but will nedes goe seke some other trade. Let him note and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the daungers wherein the aduenturer <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalpho</hi> was? Is he disposed to sende his factor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the seas, aboute his affaires, let him firste bid him to peruse <hi>Andreuccio,</hi> and then cōmaund him to beware of Madame <hi>Floredelice.</hi> If the yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man intendeth to be carefull of his businesse, meaning to reape that he hath sowen in due time let him take heede howe he repose any trust in friendes and kinnesmen, lest in haruest he be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, which <hi>Aesopes</hi> Larke doth pretelie note. If the Artificer will not faithfullie deale accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the trust reposed in him, I woulde not wish him to suffer that which <hi>Bindo</hi> did, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisedlie to reade the historie, and trustelie to accomplish that he taketh in hande. If scornefull speach or flouting sport doe flow in ripe wittes and lauish tongues of womankinde, let them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware they doe not deale with learned sorte, least Master <hi>Alberto</hi> with Physicke drougues or <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenio</hi> with Sophist arte do staine their face, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise offend them with the innocencie of their great Graundmother <hi>Eue</hi> when she was somoned frō <hi>Paradise</hi> ioy. If the pore mayden of base birth
<pb facs="13"/>
be aduaunced (by fortunes grace) to high estate: let her fixe in minde the Lady of <hi>Thurin.</hi> Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, for al states and degrees, in these <hi>Nouelles</hi> be set forth singuler documents and examples, right commodious and profitable to them that will vouchsafe to reade them.</p>
   <p>Plesaunt they be for that they recreate, and refresh weried mindes, defatigated eyther with painefull trauaile, or with continuall care, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioning them to shunne and auoyde heauinesse of minde, vaine fantasies, and idle cogitations. Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt so well abrode as at home, to auoyde the grief of VVintersnight and length of Sommers day, which the trauailers on fote may vse for a stay to ease their weried body, and the Iourneors on horseback, for a chariot or easier meane of trauaile in stead of a merie companion to shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the tedious toile of wearie waies. Delectable they be (no doubt) for all sortes of men, for the sad, the angrie, the cholerike, the pleasaunt, the hole and sicke, and for all other with what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>soeuer passion rising eyther by nature or vse they be affected. The sad shall be discharged of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinesse, the angrie and cholerike purged, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt maintayned in mirth, the whole furnished
<pb facs="14"/>
with disporte, and the sicke appaised of griefe. These <hi>Nouelles</hi> then, being profitable and pleasant histories, apt and meete for al degrees: I trust the indifferent Reader, of what complection, nature and disposition so euer he be, will accept them in good part, although perchaunce not so set forth or decked with fine and eloquent stile, as this age more braue in tongue than maners doth require, and doe pray thee to receyue them into thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous handes, with no lesse good will, (thoughe not with like regard) than <hi>Alphōsus</hi> king of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> did <hi>Quintus Curtius,</hi> out of whome be some of these selected. VVho vpon a tyme being sicke at <hi>Capua,</hi> receyuing at the handes of diuers Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians many medicines, in his greatest fitte called for the historie of <hi>Quintus Curtius,</hi> In whome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing great delight for his eloquent description of the gestes and factes of king <hi>Alexander,</hi> when he was restored to health, sayde. Farewell <hi>Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen,</hi> Adieu <hi>Hipocrates</hi> and other Phisitians, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Curtius</hi> the restitutor, and recouerie of my health. VVhereby he declared what pleasure he had in the exercise and reading of histories, not contempning for all that, the honorable science of Phisick, which in extremities he holesomely
<pb facs="14"/>
vsed. VVhat commoditie and pleasure histories doe yeld to the diligent serchers and trauailers in the same, <hi>Tullie</hi> in his fift boke, <hi>De finibus bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum et malorum ad Brutum</hi> doth declare, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that he is not ignoraunt what pleasure and profit the reading of histories doth import. And after he hath described what differēce of cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, is betwene fained fables, &amp; liuely discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of true histories, concludeth reading of his<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories to be a certayne prouocation and allurement to moue men to learne experience. If <hi>Tullie</hi> then the prince of Orators, doth affirme profite and pleasure to be in perusing of histories, then fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue I intituled this volume with the <hi>Palace of Pleasure.</hi> For like as the outward shewe of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Palaces be pleasaunt at the view and sight of ech mans eye, bet decked and garnished with sumptuous hangings and costlie Arras of splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent shewe, wherein be wrought and be with gold &amp; silke of sundrie hewes, the dedes of noble states: Euen so in this our Pallace here, there be at large recorded the Princely partes and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gestes of renowmed wights represented with more liuely grace and gorgeous sight, than Tapes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie or Arras worke, for that the one with deadly
<pb facs="15"/>
shape doth shewe, the other with speaking voice declare what in their time they were. Vpon whō doe waite (as meete it is) inferior persons, ech one vouchsafing to tell what he was; in the transito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie trade of present lyfe. VVherefore accept the same in grateful wise, and thinke vpon the minde of him that did the same, which fraughted is with no lesse plentie of good wil, than the coafers of king <hi>Craesus</hi> were, with store of worldly pelfe. And so fare well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>