<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader in generall, grace and good understan∣ding from God the Father of mercy, through Christ our Lord and Sa∣viour, Amen.</title>
           <author>Odell, T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110308_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08456</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18781</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader in generall, grace and good understan∣ding from God the Father of mercy, through Christ our Lord and Sa∣viour, Amen.</title>
                 <author>Odell, T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Isaacks pilgrimage : A briefe and short treatise, of the strife that Isaack has with his heard-men, living in the land of the Philistines, with Abimeleck and his heard-men, shadowing out the strife which Christ our Lord had with his hearders, and with the Romayne philistims, which hath continued unto this day through now in a deepe consumption. Also a testimony from the prophets, Christ and his Apostles, of the abolishment of Antichrist, the man of sinne ... By Thomas Odell Englishman</title>
                 <author>Odell, Thomas, englishman</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader in generall, grace and good understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from God the Father of mercy, through Christ our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Amen.</head>
   <p>OVR loving Lord and Saviour sitting now at the right hand of his Father, having all power in Heaven and earth, according to his promis made here on earth, powereth out of his Spirit upon all flesh in these last dayes; but not to all alike, to one he gives five tallents, another two, and to some but one, yet would not that one should be buried, for he will aske proffit of all: And his worthy Apostle and chosen vessell Paul useth these words for counsell, saying; As every one hath received, as a good disposer, distribute of the manifold giftes and graces of God. Which words with other the like in the Scripture, have emboldned me to bring that my small tallent to the banke, beseeching the Almighty to make it proffitable to his glory, and
<pb facs="4"/>
comfort to so many as it shall please him; desiring the friendly Reader to try all things by his Word, and keepe the best, and through love bare with my weakenes. And thus end the Epistle.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. ODELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>