<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author, to the Gentlemen of great BRITTAINE.</title>
           <author>M., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110036_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07721</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18105</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110036</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author, to the Gentlemen of great BRITTAINE.</title>
                 <author>M., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The perfection of horse-manship, drawne from nature; arte, and practise. By Nicholas Morgan of Crolane, in the countye of Kent, Gent</title>
                 <author>Morgan, Nicholas, of Crolane</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 188, 191-255, 266-272, 4, 273-288, 288-295, 295-343, 144-145, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_British_gentlemen">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Author, to the Gentlemen <hi>of great</hi> BRITTAINE.</head>
   <p>IT appeareth by <hi>Varro</hi> and many learned Phylosophers, that in the first Age, aswell men, as beasts did liue of those things which the vntilled earth naturally brought foorth: and that in the second Age, men began with feeding of Cattel, &amp; after to plow the ground, to take the fruits, to plant Trees, to take wilde Beastes to make them domestical: and that some Countreyes did na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally exceede others in diuersity thereof, as <hi>Phrygia</hi> for wilde Sheepe, <hi>Samocrates</hi> for Goates, <hi>Italie</hi> for Hogges, <hi>Dardania, Media,</hi> and <hi>Thracia</hi> for Bulles, and Kine: <hi>Fusia,</hi> and <hi>Cacinia</hi> for Asses, and <hi>Spaine</hi> for Horses. And after that they had made vse of all Creatures, they affirmed that <hi>Inter cetera Animal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a, Equus sensetur nobiltor, et magis ceteris necossarius, tamregibuset alijs Principibus, tempore bellorum et pacis:</hi> Amōgst other liuing creatures, the horse is esteemed more noble, &amp; more necessary then others, aswel to Kings &amp; other Princes, in the time of warre and peace: So that sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence their first vse, there is not any thing more probable then each mans necessarye vse, and inestimable estimation of Horses with all humane societie, necessarilye compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending, hath bound all men, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> onely to endeuour truely to know (according to their original nature) but also to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and preserue them in their greatest perfection: Yet such hath been the forgetfulnesse of latter Ages, that the true natural knowledge of euery other creature increasing in perfection, this onely lyeth recorded in the Role of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued memorie: For if you behold the excelling knowledge &amp; preseruation of the Oxe, the Cow, the Sheepe, the Hog, the Dogge, the Fish, the Fowle, the Frute, and all other Creatures betfit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing the vse of man, how painfully sought foorth, how louingly intertained, how diligētly preserued, how carefully increased, how painfully amongst all men
<pb facs="8"/>nourished, and how prouidently bestowed: you must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that the generall good knowledge and preseruation of all is become common to all: Againe, if you consider the restitution of good Learning, the ornamēt of all Artes and Sciences, by the diligence of mans skyll recouered; Hath not Grame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Poetry, Rhethoricke, Logicke Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Sciences, Astrologie, Cosmography, philosophy, Phisicke, Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of Chiualry, Buildings, Paintings, Musicke, Eloquence, knowledge of Lawe, and Diuinity, And all knowledge whatsoeuer, attayned greater and farre more amendment and preseruation, &amp; onely the true knowledge of the Nature, Arte and practise, with preseruation of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of this Subiect lest in darkenesse, and the men of Skill (who should ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e beautified the same,) vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the dealing, setting their soueraygne felicity other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes; so as the forbearing of the Learned to practise, and the forbearing of the practisers to study the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; practise therof, being altogether vnperfect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge and practise, (most palpable Error) is (by
<note n="*" place="margin">Matura cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limentum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suetudinem in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>enit.</note> cancred and corrupt Custome) both Mother &amp; Nurse of all practise. And yet if you first consider the naturall Valour of the Gentlemen of these Kingdomes, for fitnesse and aptnesse of Horsemanship, to vndertake without rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and performe without feare: like sire enflaming their harts to the execution of difficult deedes: Secondly, their true wisdome in materiall and waighty points, nor suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their mindes suspended in vncertainty, comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding nothing but certaine and vndoubted knowledge:</p>
   <p>Thirdly, their vertue of Temperance, to whom a Royall Scepter appertayneth, keeping their appetites and vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections of nature, in awe and gouernment, like vnto the fixed Starres, who the higher they bee, the lesse they desire to seeme. Fourthly, their laborious practise, redily assisting the power of their will and vnderstanding,
<note place="margin">Excercieus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore proficit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> consonosut.</note> not standing vpon what they borrowed of their Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esteors, but working out their owne honour. Fiftly, their comelynesse of grace, in and to all and euery their actions,
<pb facs="8"/>with their sweete affability, that can no more be seuered from them then life from the soule: and their studies such, as those that know ignorance, can neyther purchase Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour nor weild it, but that Knowledge must both guide and grace them, the onely fit &amp; naturall quallyties of good Horsemen. You Would beleeue, the Excellency of their Nature (with knowledge and practise) would make all mens harts Idolles of their delightes, and to be honoured with their oblations, whereby the beholders wouldt eyther wish them not so excellent, or at least, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> they could think them not so excellent, seeing Nature hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Nature, and Arte so hidinge Arte, as the forces of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light would be without withstanding. Lastly, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the aptnesle and fruitfulnesse of the Soyle of these Kingdomes, for the maintenance of these beautifull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (whose praises the whole world doth celebrate with admyration, acknowledging their excellencie, the renown of their Excellencies) you would presently acknowledge that the not acknowledging of our ignorance of Nature, and of our Errours in this Arte, and the want of the practise, are the onely efficient causes of the infinit number of Iades, the vtter decay of perfect Races and depriuation of true Iudgement; For vntill we shall acknowledge our owne Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, we cannot possibly assure ourselues of the true te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of Iudgement, because we can not vnderstand, or peirce into the Marrow or pyth of a thing, but that we must sticke in the bone: For
<note n="*" place="margin">Quod Serbo dictum est, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo sit negatum</note> euery humaine proposition hath as much authority as another, if Reason make not the difference; because there is not a thing so vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ersall in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as diuersity, the which apeareth in that there is no one thing wholy like or dislike to another. So as it is manifest, that the reason of man hath many visages: It is a two edged Sword, a Staffe with two Pikes: <hi>Ogni medeglia, ha il suo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerso.</hi> There is no reason, but hath a contrary reason, sayth the foundest and surest Phylosopher, And therefore, the want of the true reason and knowledge, of Nature, Arte and Practise of this Subiect, doth not onely destroy all the
<pb facs="9"/>Races of good Horses, but also to them that are naturally good, bring alcontrary vices, vnlesse some God lay his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand therevnto: Wherefore, you valorous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in whom all Heroycall partes are begotten, bred and nourished, whose inward mindes cannot be painted by any thing, but by your true shape of vertue: For although the body of Nobility consist in blood, yet the soule in the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of vertue: For asmuch then as God hath giuen vs a King, such as the Subiect neyther wanteth Iustice, nor hee obedience, whome all Nations finde so hurtlesse strong, as they haue thought better to rest in his friendship, then make trial of his enmity, who excelleth in nothing so much as in the zealous loue of his people, whose knowledge and practise of this Subiect is such, as he taketh away knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and practise, but such as he giueth backe by his shadow. Cast not a myst ouer your owne glory, but so kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle your desires and rayse your affections, as the meane and base sorte of people, may not by their ignorance or error, make you do amisse, whom God hath giuen hearts to doe well: neyther let your eyes degenerate from their creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ō, but do you endeuour the true knowledge of Nature, Arte and practise heerein; so as it may be said of you, that, as it is the greatest thing the world can shewe, yet the least thing may be praysed in you. If there were a view of all the Races and breed of Horses within his Maiesties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, I make no doubt, but to finde a hundred Royles and Iades, before one of true and perfect shape. But if a view were made of the general number of Horses that are kept within the same, it wer much easier to find 1000. Iades then one Horse perfectly, shaped, which were vnpo stible if we did see our owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>. It is truely obserued by the Learned, <hi>Nemo sibi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> erra, sed alijs erroris causa, et Author est,</hi> Error is not simply an Error to him that posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth it, but it is the cause and Author of many other errors: And besides, whosoeuer beleeueth an error, thinketh it a worke of charity, to perswade another to beleeue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>me, and that he may the better do it, he feareth not to adde of
<pb facs="9"/>his owne inuention, so much as he seeth necessary for his purpose, to supply that want and vnwillingnesse which he thinketh to be in the cōcerpt of him to whom he telleth the same And therefore, whereas other Nations publish them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues the great Maisters of this Subiect, affirming that whatsoeuer they say, should be beleued and receiued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudging and examining what they teach: Hold it for tyranicall Iustice: <hi>Nam qut a semet ipso loquitur mendax est.</hi> It is said, that in the Countrey of <hi>Pharsalia,</hi> from whence came BVCEPHALE <hi>Alexander</hi> the great his Horse, that the Mare that was kept for that Horse, broght foorth Coltes alwayes like the Syre: for which cause, <hi>Aristotle</hi> reporteth, she was called IVSTE: I will not enquire how many of our great Maisters can expresse the naturall and true reason thereof, (although I doubt not the same, and many more greater expressed in this Tractat) and yet the learned Phylosophers and Phisitions make great Dispute from whence the likenesse of yssue to their Parentes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, considering their diuersity of likenesse: neyther will I enquire of any mans particular Stable, where peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>(Asinus subfreno currere docetur)</hi> some concealed Cart-Horses are finely cloathed: Neither, at any time enquire where true practise of Horsemanship (I onely speake of riding) his Majesties Court excepted, is vsed. Who can make that cleane that commeth of vncleane seede Can a Kite bring forth a good flying Hawke? <hi>mals Coru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, malum ouum:</hi> of an euil Crow, commeth an euil egge. The long and pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full apprehension hereof (standing at the gates of my e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>res) although in the winter of mine Age, hath mere then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced me to this labour, and to present the same vnto your view, as the most noble Aire for such labour to flye in, who by consideration what as amisle done may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>o the Springs of your wisdomes, as from the Beames of your vertues, be mooued to the consideration of that is not done &amp; by your generous endeuours, in short time, make both it &amp; your sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>al samous partes &amp; all his Maiesties Kingdomes and Dominions aboue all the Kingdoms of the world in
<pb facs="10"/>greatest perfection, hauing at this day as famous Riders, as euer was <hi>Zenophon, Geouan Barardiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Colo Pagano, Frederick Gryson, John Pietro Puglano, Claudio Curto,</hi> or who soeuer. And therefore my principall labour herein, is principally to enforme &amp; guide the vnderstanding with assured know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, vndoubtedly to know from whence the perfection of shape and the naturall goodnesse of euery horse procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: <hi>vt ipso unltu Ethiopem cognoscas:</hi> That by the only view of them you may know their goodnesse, &amp; how to keepe &amp; maintaine your Races in greatest perfection nearest their originall and primary creation, &amp; to set foorth the same by probable reason, thereby to refell and confute all former Errors heeretofore written or practised, neuer by any heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fore attempted, but the contrary successiuely defended. My desire therfore is, that you would be pleased diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to read this my Tractat, wherein (I doubt not) you shall finde sufficient contentment against the oppositions of any former Writer whatsoeuer, and to do your greatest ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to place within euerye Shyre a sufficient vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Rider according to the Rule of <hi>Themystocles,</hi> that will <hi>Impetraremelius quam impetrare,</hi> preuaile by perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not by constraint: By whom all Horses fytte for seruice may be made fytte and apt for all seruices, because without such Riders, there is not one Horse of a thousand vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standingly and truely broken or made perfect. Then shall your Horses be defence of the poore, preseruation of the rich, laughter at feare, inuincible power against force, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our most renowned King, and the life of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale: The want whereof hath not onely depriued all his Maiesties Dominions of good Horses, but also hath discouraged and dismaied many valorous and noble Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen from the delight and pleasure therin, although the whole Arte &amp; euery part thereof be without offence, scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal,
<note place="margin">Temperance the rule of all pleasure.</note> damage, or preiudice of another: And without preiudice of thē selues, their honors their healthes, their leasure, their duty, or their function, if the same be taken as men do take Honuy, with the tip of the finger, not with a full hand, for
<pb facs="10"/>the fulnesse of pleasure is the bayte of iniquity.
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Degener at a robore ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te miles asiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudine volupta tem.</hi> Tacit</note> And you my natiue Countrey men of North-hampton Shire, as also you Gentlemen of Kent amongst whom I liue: (A Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey obiect to the eyes of all forreigne Nations,) because there is neyther harty desire nor true ioye in that whereof the minde is vnskilfull &amp; ignorant:
<note place="margin">Malerum esca Goluptain.</note> Let the Coles of your affections bee kindled with delight, &amp; your actions to the eares of all people blowen to a wonder, against which, let no excuse bee sufficient Armour to set in a beautifull Sample, such Workes of Horsemanship,
<note place="margin">Honus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> nus est</note> that may beeas a Glasse to the blinde eyes of al forreigne Nations to see their imperfectiōs, &amp; your actions in such perfection, at you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may getthe first possession of the keits of al honourable and vertuous mindes. But if you obiect that the Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ney of high Honor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly eth not in plaine way, and that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eate the sweet without the sower, <hi>Nam qui addit Scienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>, addit et labor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m,</hi> So may it be said on the contrary that laughter is mingled with teares,
<note place="margin">Qui serutatur est maiestatis apprim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>etur ef gleria.</note>
      <hi>Et ipsa se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>cita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>se nisi tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat pramit:</hi> Yet I pray you be not dismayed, <hi>invit virtuti, nulla est via:</hi> there is no way vnresistable to vertue: <hi>Nulla est praclusa o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> thus patet:</hi> Neither is the way forestalled, but open to all, neither is or can any thing bee so hard or difficult, but paynes and industry will effect. Be not as the standing Pooles that gather onely corruption: what mooued <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ander,</hi> to vndertake the digging downe of the high Mountayne <hi>Ischmus?</hi> Let it not be forgotten that the Learned haue said, <hi>Dissacien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e auiuuant</hi> The Diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth all vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uours. Certainely, there are so many Beauties and so many Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es in the face of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>od<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that no eye can possibly see i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> without affection, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rauishment: otherwise, where had beene the Glory of al the famous verinous &amp; worthy Actes of <hi>Alexander, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mistool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s, Epiminodas, Hearcules, Persius. Thesius, Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>on, Hanntball, Seivio, Caesar,</hi> and of infinite others, if great and difficult Labours had swallowed then glorious ence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours? <hi>Lober est materia vntutis et gler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ae, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>une qui reij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap> illas reijcis.</hi> The rewardes of Labour are vertue, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,
<pb facs="11"/>and he that refuseth Labour, refuseth the reward. This moued that worthy King <hi>Agesilaus</hi> vpon his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, to commaund, that no Image or picture of his resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance should bee made: for if I haue, said hee, any famous thing nobly done, it will beare witnesse enough for mee: <hi>Talis post exilium fama est, qualis ante exilium vita.</hi> Such as the life is, such is the Fame in death. <hi>Viui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> post funera Ʋir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> when a man is Dust his Vertue dieth not. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>it Molam, fugit Fariuam:</hi> He that burneth the Mill, hath Ashes for his meale. Now, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in my Dedicatory Epistle, I haue set open the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son Doores of my desires, I confesse beyond the degrees of mediocrity, and offred them as an incense, vpon that fire wherein my hart was sacrificed, yet so farre did the Sparkes of vnslaine Dutye preuaile in mee, that I haue reserued a poore remnant to liue in the protection of your fauours, The which,
<note place="margin">Sublime feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Gerti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera.</note> with my selfe I consecrate to your seruice: wherein, (if such happinesse I may finde,) I shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my contentment higher then the highest Rewarde that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things can bring vnto mee.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Adde manum, et cum <hi>Minerua</hi> manummoue:</q>
   </epigraph>
   <closer>
      <signed>By him that wisheth all the degrees of <hi>Nature, Arte</hi> and <hi>Practise</hi> to attend your desires to the highest.
<hi>N. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>