<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the true louers of wise¦dome Iohn Asteley, mayster of the Queenes Maiestyes Iewell house, and Iohn Harington Esquier Thomas Blun∣deuille, greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1561</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110436_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20063.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110436</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the true louers of wise¦dome Iohn Asteley, mayster of the Queenes Maiestyes Iewell house, and Iohn Harington Esquier Thomas Blun∣deuille, greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three [morall] treatises : no lesse pleasau [nt] than necessary for all men to read [e,] wherof the one is called the learned prince, the other the fruites of foes, the thyrde the porte of rest</title>
                 <author>Plutarch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1561</date>
                 <publisher>Seres, William 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>140 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <head>¶ To the true louers of wise<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome Iohn Asteley, mayster of the Queenes Maiestyes Iewell house, and Iohn Harington Esquier Thomas Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuille, greeting.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WHilst plutarks works, I gaue my self to rede</l>
      <l>So pleasant fruit me thought, I could none fid</l>
      <l>As is in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which rightly shewes in dede</l>
      <l>The waie tappease, and still thunquiete minde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For wheras since false flattring hope with whō</l>
      <l>I trauelde had, long tyme full painfully,</l>
      <l>Of comforte voide, alone me leaft to rome</l>
      <l>The barrein coste of wretched miserye:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>In stead of helping me the seas to passe</l>
      <l>Of worldly ioyes, amongst the happy sorte,</l>
      <l>In ship full fraught with fortunes giftes: as was</l>
      <l>Her vowe when first to me she did resorte:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The restles muse had made my feble brayn</l>
      <l>The forge of care, and therein daily wroughte</l>
      <l>Such dulfull domps &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eadful dreames as cleane</l>
      <l>From mirth my mind vnto despaire had brought.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>That boke did yeld such glistring beames Isay.</l>
      <l>Of comfort great and ioyfull quietnes:</l>
      <l>As draue those dumpes and sorowes all away</l>
      <l>My heauy heart which helde in great distres.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="32"/>
      <l>So as in dede from that time foorth me thought</l>
      <l>I coulde not chuse but nedes contented rest</l>
      <l>And though before vaine hope much griefe hadde wrought</l>
      <l>Yet now to think y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al was for the best.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which comfort though it grateful was to me</l>
      <l>In my conceyt yet did it not suffise:</l>
      <l>Onlesse that you my faithfull frendes might be</l>
      <l>Eke partners of the same some kinde of wise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For as the grief of one frende dothe decreace</l>
      <l>His other frendes, when they therof partake</l>
      <l>His ioye euen so he shall the more encreace</l>
      <l>If of thesame, he doth them partners make.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Into our tunge therfore this litle quaire</l>
      <l>I turned haue, and termd the port of rest</l>
      <l>And wishe eche wight, therto for to repaire</l>
      <l>with troubled sprite that feeles himself opprest.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For as the mariner, in sea whose bote</l>
      <l>With cruel stormes and tempests hath been beat</l>
      <l>And drieuē twixt whaues &amp; feareful rocks to flote</l>
      <l>Though al that while dispaire his mind did freat:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet whē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> winds their boistrous blowing ceace</l>
      <l>And he to hauen is safely come at last</l>
      <l>He than reioyceth with himself in peace</l>
      <l>And cleane forgeates al those his daungers past:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="32"/>
      <l>Euen so eche man within this litle port</l>
      <l>That shall vouchesafe at times more ydley spente</l>
      <l>To harborough a while: himselfe to sport</l>
      <l>When he perceiues his minde to sorow bent:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To warrant him I dare be bolde I saie</l>
      <l>That though he be in passing heauines</l>
      <l>Yet he thereby shall quickly learne the waie</l>
      <l>To rid his minde of all vnquietnes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Ne shall he feare the losse in time to come</l>
      <l>Of frendes, of goodes, of lyfe, or lyke distres</l>
      <l>But lyue and dye, by helpe of reasons dome</l>
      <l>In suche assured holde of quietnes:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As neyther frowarde fortunes sharpe assaultes,</l>
      <l>Nor death himself, for all his dreadfull name</l>
      <l>Ne malice eke with all her forged faultes</l>
      <l>Shall be of power to ouerthrowe thesame.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To you therefore to whom I am muche bounde</l>
      <l>And tall the rest, lo here nowe for your sake</l>
      <l>Of this my paine suche fruite as hath redounde</l>
      <l>In frendly wise I doe a present make.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whose relles though it be not halfe so swete</l>
      <l>Ne hath suche sappe of eloquence in dede</l>
      <l>As those thinges haue whereon (as meates most mete</l>
      <l>For deintie mouthes) you wonted are to fede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="33"/>
      <l>Yet doubt I not but that vouchesafe you wyll,</l>
      <l>To take it well in woorth, and speciallye</l>
      <l>Sithe Budes woordes in all this treatise styll</l>
      <l>I folowd haue in deede moste faithfullye.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whose stile I founde to be more graue then gaye</l>
      <l>And harde to turne into our vulguer speche,</l>
      <l>Yet as it is refuse not when you maye</l>
      <l>To taste thereof I humbly you beseche.</l>
      <l>For though it hap not deintye mouthes to please</l>
      <l>Weak stomakes yet thereby may find much ease.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>