<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VVELL DIS∣POSED TO READE, AND to the merry disposed to Sing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110598_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15484</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20759</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110598</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VVELL DIS∣POSED TO READE, AND to the merry disposed to Sing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pammelia : Musicks miscellanie. Or, Mixed varietie of pleasant roundelayes, and delightfull catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. parts in one. None so ordinarie as musicall, none so musical, as not to all, very pleasing and acceptable</title>
                 <author>Ravenscroft, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Walley, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>Barley (Barlow), William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VVELL DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POSED TO READE, AND to the merry disposed to Sing.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst other liberall Arts, Musicke for her part, hath alwayes beene as liberall, in bestowing her melodious gifts, as any one whatsoeuer, and that in such rare manner, for diuersitie: and ample mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, for multiplicity, as more cannot be expected, except it were more then it is respected: yet in this kind onely, it may seeme somewhat niggardly and vnkind, in neuer (as yet) publikely communicating, but alwayes priuately retaining, and as it were, enuying to all, this more familiar mirth and iocund melodie. But it may bee Musicke hath hitherto beene defectiue in this vaine, because this vaine indeed, hath hitherto been defectiue in Musicke: and therefore, that fault being now mended, this kind of Musicke also is now commended to all mens kind acceptation. This did I willingly vndertake, and haue easily effected, that all might equally pertake of that which is so generally affected. <hi>Catches</hi> so generally affected (I take it) <hi>quia non superant cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> because they are so consonant to all ordinaryie musicall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity,
<pb facs="3"/>being such indeed, as all such whose loue of Musicke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes their skill, cannot but commend, such also, as all such, whose skill in Musicke, exceedes their loue of such sleight and light fanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, cannot either contemne or condemne. Good Art in all, for the more musicall good mirth and melodie for the more Iouiall, sweet harmonie, mixed with much varietie, and both with great facilitie. Harmony to please, varietie to delight, facilitie to inuite thee. Some toyes yet musicall, without absurdity, Some very musicall, yet pleasing without difficulty, light, but not without musickes delight, Musickes pleasantnes, but not without easines, what seemes old, is at least renewed, Art hauing reformed what pleasing tunes iniurious time and ignorance had deformed. The onely intent is to giue generall content, composed by Art to make thee disposed to mirth. Accept there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore kindly, what is done willingly, and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed onely, to please good Company</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>