<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Ad Maecaenatem Prologus.</title>
           <author>Peele, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110386_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09227</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19539</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110386</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Ad Maecaenatem Prologus.</title>
                 <author>Peele, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The honour of the garter : Displaied in a poeme gratulatorie: entitled to the worthie and renowned Earle of Northumberland. Created Knight of that order, and installd at VVindsore. Anno Regni Elizabethæ. 35. die Iunij. 26. By George Peele, Maister of Artes in Oxenforde</title>
                 <author>Peele, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, Alice</publisher>
                    <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Ad Maecaenatem Prologus.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>PLaine is my coate, and humble is my gate,</l>
      <l>Thrice noble Earle, behold with gentle eyes</l>
      <l>My wits poore worth: euen for your noblesse,</l>
      <l>(Renowmed Lord, <hi>Northumberlands</hi> fayre flower)</l>
      <l>The Muses loue, Patrone, and fauoret,</l>
      <l>That artizans and schollers doost embrace,</l>
      <l>And clothest <hi>Mathesis</hi> in rich ornaments,</l>
      <l>That admirable Mathematique skill,</l>
      <l>Familiar with the starres and Zodiack.</l>
      <l>(To whom the heauen lyes open as her booke)</l>
      <l>By whose directions vndeceiueable,</l>
      <l>(Leauing our Schoolemens vulgar troden pathes)</l>
      <l>And following the auncient reuerend steps</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Of</hi> Trismegistus <hi>and</hi> Pythagords,</l>
      <l>Through vncouth waies and vnaccessible,</l>
      <l>Doost passe into the spacious pleasant fieldes</l>
      <l>Of diuine science and Phylosophie,</l>
      <l>From whence beholding the deformities</l>
      <l>Of common errors and worlds vanitie,</l>
      <l>Doost heere enioy that sacred sweet content</l>
      <l>That baser soules not knowing, not affect:</l>
      <l>And so by Fates and Fortunes good aspect</l>
      <l>Raysed; In thy heigth and these vnhappy times,</l>
      <l>Disfurnisht wholy of Heroycall spirites,</l>
      <l>That learning should with glorious hands vphold.</l>
      <l>(For who should learning vnderbare, but hee</l>
      <l>That knowes thereof the precious worthinesse,</l>
      <l>And sees true Science from base vanitie)</l>
      <l>Hast in regard, the true Philosophie,</l>
      <l>That in pure Wisedome seates hir happines.</l>
      <l>And you the Muses, and the Graces three,</l>
      <l>You I invoke from Heauen and <hi>Helicon.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>For other Patrons haue poore Poets none,</l>
      <l>But Muses and the Graces to implore.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Augustus</hi> long agoe hath left the world:</l>
      <l>And liberall <hi>Sidney,</hi> famous for the loue</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
He bare to learning and to Chiualrie;</l>
      <l>And vertuous <hi>Walsingham</hi> are fled to heauen.</l>
      <l>Why thether speede not <hi>Hobbin</hi> and his pheres?</l>
      <l>Great <hi>Hobbinall</hi> on whom our shepheards gaze.</l>
      <l>And <hi>Harrington</hi> well letter'd and discreet,</l>
      <l>That hath so purely naturalized</l>
      <l>Strange words, and made them all free-denyzons.</l>
      <l>Why thither speedes not <hi>Rosamonds</hi> trumpeter,</l>
      <l>Sweet as the Nightingall, Why goest not thou</l>
      <l>That richly cloth'st conceite with well made words,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Campion,</hi> accompaned with our English Fraunce,</l>
      <l>A peerelesse sweet Translator of our time?</l>
      <l>Why follow not a thousand that I know,</l>
      <l>Fellowes to these <hi>Apolloes</hi> fauourets:</l>
      <l>And leaue behind our ordinary groomes,</l>
      <l>With triuiall humors to pastime the world,</l>
      <l>That fauours <hi>Pan</hi> and <hi>Phoebus</hi> both alike?</l>
      <l>Why thither post not all good wits from hence,</l>
      <l>To <hi>Chaucer, Gowre,</hi> and to the fayrest <hi>Phaer</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That euer ventured on great <hi>Virgils</hi> works?</l>
      <l>To <hi>Watson,</hi> worthy many Epitaphes</l>
      <l>For his sweete Poësie, for <hi>Amintas</hi> teares</l>
      <l>And ioyes so well set downe. And after thee</l>
      <l>Why hie they not, vnhappy in thine end,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Marley,</hi> the Muses darling for thy verse;</l>
      <l>Fitte to write passions for the soules below,</l>
      <l>If any wretched soules in passion speake?</l>
      <l>Why goe not all into th' <hi>Elisian</hi> fieldes,</l>
      <l>And leaue this Center, barren of repast,</l>
      <l>Vnlesse in hope <hi>Augusta</hi> will restore,</l>
      <l>The wrongs that learning beares of couetousnes</l>
      <l>And Courts disdaine, the enemie to Arte.</l>
      <l>Leaue foolish lad, it mendeth not with words,</l>
      <l>Nor herbes nor tyme such remedy affoordes.</l>
   </lg>
   <signed>Your Honors in all humble seruice, <hi>Geo: Peele.</hi>
   </signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>