<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE TRVLY
HONOVRABLE,
Sir IOHN WRAY Knight
and Baronet, Sir CHRISTOPHER
WRAY Knight, and Master
EDWARD WRAY
Esquire.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110332_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09206</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19516</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110332</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE TRVLY
HONOVRABLE,
Sir IOHN WRAY Knight
and Baronet, Sir CHRISTOPHER
WRAY Knight, and Master
EDWARD WRAY
Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Thestylis atrata: or A funeral elegie vpon the death of the Right Honourable, most religious and noble lady, Frances, late Countesse of Warvvick : who departed this life at her house in Hackney neere unto London, in the moneth of June last past. 1634. By Henrie Peacham</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Constable, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO
THE TRVLY
HONOVRABLE,
Sir IOHN WRAY Knight
and Baronet, Sir CHRISTOPHER
WRAY Knight, and Master
EDWARD WRAY
Esquire.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Noble and Worthy Gentle-men:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have presumed, the first, to bewaile in publike, the
death of the much honoured, but more lamented
<hi>Lady,</hi> the Countesse of <hi>WARWICK</hi> your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased
A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt, so re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owmed, and beloved for her Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
and Goodnesse, that shee needeth no Memoriall
at all, and in truth, <hi>Fame profiteth not the dead,</hi> as a Poet
saith.<note place="margin">Nil juv it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sepultos.</note> But in regard she hath beene so faire a President for Posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
to imitate, and that my selfe have beene much bounden unto hee,
for her Honourable respect ever towards mee, I could not mourne to
my selfe, beside moved to the contrarie by a particular occasion. Some
few yeares agoe, her Honour sent unto me, and requested mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
far the erecting of a Monument in <hi>SNARFORD</hi> Church
for her selfe, according to the convenience of the place: I drew the
<pb facs="3"/>
Modell of one, and presented her Honour with the same, adding (as
was her desire) a plaine, but short and proper Inscription, leaving
underneath a space for an Epitaph, there to be inserted after her death,
that might containe some dozen lines or more, which (if I should
out-live her) it pleased her Honour to impose upon me to performe:
I promised her I would, though out of the naturall goodnesse, and
sweet humilitie of her minde, she never affected praise, or applause,
either in life, or after her death, for any good de<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> that ever shee did.
So that since herein I could not <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>forme my promise, her Honours
minde, for the disposing of her corps at the time of her death (for
some reasons perhaps knowne unto her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>) being altered, I tooke
mine owne time, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>entured (as drawing the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rtaine from an
excellent Picture) to shew her to the beholder at the full, and in a
faire light.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, at my little leasure would serve, it spare houres, shortly
after her death (being employed in a toilsome calling) I composed
this small Poem, which under the protection of your names (who
are so much beloved and honoured in <hi>Lincolnshire;</hi> moreover, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
her Nephewes, and Exequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tors to her last <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>)
I consecrate to her eternall Memorie, and offering (for her
sake) the same in all dutifull affection unto your Patronage, I take
leave.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours devoted in all observance, Henrie <unclear>Peacham</unclear>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>