<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most High and Mighty Prince, IAMES by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, Defendour of the Faith.</title>
           <author>Dove, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110110_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7085</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110110</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most High and Mighty Prince, IAMES by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, Defendour of the Faith.</title>
                 <author>Dove, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A persvvasion to the English recusants, to reconcile themselues to the Church of England : Written for the better satisfaction of those which be ignorant. By Iohn Doue Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Dove, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 34, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <head>To the most High and Mighty Prince, IAMES by the grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France and Ireland,</hi> Defendour of the Faith.</head>
         <opener>
            <salute>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ratious and dread Soueraigne,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I say the truth, I lie not, my conscience bearing me witnes in the Holy-ghost, that I haue with the Apostle great heauinesse, and continuall sorrow in my heart for many of my brethren and Country-men. And my hearty desire and prayer for them to God, is, that they may be saued. For I beare them recorde, that they haue the zeale of God, though not according to knowledge, which is the onely cause that mooued me to write this short Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise. And, because God of his great goodnesse hath vouchsafed your tender yeeres the education of <hi>TIMOTHIE,</hi> and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Highnesse, since your happy gouernement with princely gifts, knowledge to discerne truth, and zeale to maintaine truth, I humbly present vnto your Maiestie, these few lines, containing a subiect of so great importance. The common voyce, and hope
<pb facs="3"/> of your best affected people is, that your Highnesse hath a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intent, to make God yet better knowne in <hi>IVDA,</hi> and his name yet greater in <hi>HIERVSALEM,</hi> to bring all these your Kingdomes to the acknowledgement and profession of one truth; so that hereafter <hi>HIERVSALEM</hi> may be as a walled towne and fenced citty, which is at vnitie within it selfe: and as it was in the dayes of the <hi>IVDGES,</hi> all <hi>ISRAEL</hi> may be gathered together, as one man, from <hi>DAN</hi> to <hi>BEERSHEBA,</hi> vnto the Lord in <hi>MISHPAH.</hi> The Lord guide and prosper you in all your wayes, the Lord establish your house and kingdome, the Lord blesse you out of <hi>SION,</hi> that you may see the wealth of <hi>HIERVSALEM</hi> all the dayes of your life, that you may see your Childrens Children, and peace in <hi>SION.</hi>
         </p>
         <closer>
            <signed>Your Maiesties humble Subiect, IOHN DOVE.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>