<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the godly, and right woorshipfull Senate, the Mayre and his brethren of Sandwich in Kent, Thomas Becon vvysheth long life, continuall health, and prosperous felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110677_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06733</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1718</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110677</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the godly, and right woorshipfull Senate, the Mayre and his brethren of Sandwich in Kent, Thomas Becon vvysheth long life, continuall health, and prosperous felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The demaundes of holy scripture, with answeres to the same : wherein are defined, and declared the cheefe, and principall poyntes of Christian doctrine: very profitable for the right vnderstanding of holy scriptures: made by T. Becon, and dravven out of his great vvorkes</title>
                 <author>Becon, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the godly, and right woorshipfull Senate, the Mayre and his brethren of Sandwich in Kent, Thomas Becon vvysheth long life, continuall health, and prosperous felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O oft as I consider the blessed</hi> state of your tovvne, vvhereof God by his deuine prouidence and vnsear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheable counsell, hath made you ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vnder the Queenes Maiestie, our Soueraigne liege Lady: I am entirely prouoked and stirred vp to geue most entire thankes, to the Prince of Princesses, and Lorde of Lordes, that mighty GOD of Hostes, for his so great and singuler be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifites, so bounteously and largely poured vpon you, and other the inhabitauntes of your tovvne. For I doo not vvell knovve, yf any thing may any vvhere be found, meete to beautifie a common vveale, that iustly may be counted to lacke in you, so plentifully hath GOD poured his blessinges vpon you. VVho is able to expresse, vvhat a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ornamente, precious ievvell, and noble ouche, Christian doctrine is, to a Christian common vveale? The sage and prudent Philosophers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvyse and expert men of this vvorlde, iudged these common vveales most blessed, happy, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, most noble, beautifull, and florishing, vvhere the Princes and Rulers thereof, vvere eyther Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers, or studious of Philosophie. But hovv much is that common vveale to be counted happy and blessed, vvhere not humaine Philosophie, vvhether
<pb facs="3"/>
vve respect naturall, or morall, but diuine Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, brought from the hie Heauens, by him vvhich is the vvysdome of the father, prospereth, florisheth, triumpheth: vvhere also not vaine and curious Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers, but true, faithfull, and godly Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers raigne, and beare rule? VVhatsoeuer the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers taught, although neuer so much enforced vvith sugred eloquence, probable reasons, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent argumentes, it vvas the fruite of the earth, and of mans braine: but that vvhiche Christe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto vs, came out of the bosome of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so that looke hovve much the noble Heauens surmount &amp; passe the vile &amp; base Earth in higth, &amp; indignitie: so much, and incomparable vvyse more, doth the heauenly Philosophie, vvhereof the holy Ghost alone is the aucthour, exceedeth the earthy Philosophie, vvhereof man is the deuiser. He that cometh from an high, sayth that blessed Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist, is aboue all.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> He that is of the earth, is earthy, &amp; speaketh of the earth. He that commeth from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is aboue all, and vvhat he hath seene and heard, that he testifieth: and no man receiueth his testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. He that hath receiued his testimonie, hath set to his seale, that GOD is true. For he vvhom GOD hath sent, speaketh the vvoordes of God. VVhat other thing is this diuine Philosophie, vvher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of vve novve speake, then the holy vvoord of God? And vvhat other are these faithfull and godly Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers, then the true preachers and professours of the sacred Scriptures? All these are to be founde among you plentifully. The Christian Philosophie, I meane the vvoord of GOD, raigneth, ruleth, and triumpheth among you, so that according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="3"/>
to it, all things are ordered among you in that your Tovvne. In other places, this diuine and Christian Philosophie, is counted heresie, nevve learnyng, straunge doctrine, the mother of errours, the cause of rebellion, sedition, insurrection, &amp;c. and the plaine subuertion of common vveales: but vvith you, &amp; that most iustly it is reperted &amp; taken for the alone trueth, for the ancient doctrine of the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches, Prophets, and Apostles, for the mother of all godlynes and vertue, for the onely &amp; alone cause of vnitie, concord, quietnesse, amitie, obedience, and for the alone stay, vpholding, and maintenance of all Christean, and vvell ordred common vveales, so that vvhere this is not, there is a Chaos, and plaine confusion of thinges. This holy vvoord of GOD among you, svvimmeth not in your lippes only, but it also shineth in your lyfe and conuersation, vnto the good example of all them that are conuersant vvith you. By this vvoord, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of GOD geuen to Iosua, ye do not only frame your ovvne life, but ye also gouerne your Tovvne, and iudge al causes that come before you, as a rule, from the vvhich it is not lavvfull for you by any meanes to depart. Of this vvoord ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently talke, commune, conferre, sing, and haue continuall meditation, as your chiefe ioy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.<note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> This vvoord is vnto you, that noble treasure hydde in the Feelde, the vvhiche a man found and hydde, and for ioy thereof, goeth and selleth al that he hath, and byeth the Feelde. This vvoord is to you more svveete, then the Hony, or the Hony Combe, and more precious then Gold, or Precious stone. And as this most blessed and holy vvoorde
<pb facs="4"/>
dooth occupie the principall and highest place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you: so haue you both godly professors, and faithfull preachers of the same, vnto the great ioy aud singular comfort of all the inhabitauntes of your Tovvne. For as there can not be a greater ievvell in a Christian common vveale, then an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest faythfull, and constant preacher of the Lordes vvorde: so can there not be a greater plague among any people, then vvhen they haue raigning ouer them blind guides, dumme dogges, vvicked vvolues hypocriticall hyrelinges, popishe Prophetes, vvhich feede them not vvith the pure VVheate of Gods vvoord, but vvith the VVoormevvod of mens try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling traditions, and vvith the sovvre leauen of the Papisticall Pharisees, as Salomon sayth: VVhen the preaching of Gods vvoord fayleth, the people pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe, and come to nought. Veryly as there is not a greater blessing geuen of GOD to any nacion, then the gift of his vvoord: so I knovve, not yf a greater cursse from GOD can be cast vppon any people, then vvhen the vvoord of GOD, and the true preaching thereof is taken avvay from them, as these vvoordes of GOD spoken by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete,<note place="margin">Amos. 8.</note> doo manifestly declare. Beholde, the tyme commeth (sayth the Lorde GOD) that I shall send an hunger into the earth, not the hunger of bread, nor the thyrst of vvater, but an hunger to heare the vvoord of the LORD: so that they shal goe from the one sea to the other, yea from the North, to the East, runnyng about to seeke the vvoord of the Lorde, and shall not finde it. In this behalfe therfore, are ye the inhabitauntes of Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviche greatly blessed of the Lord our God, vvhich
<pb facs="4"/>
hath not onely very richelv geuen you his vvoorde to be preached, taught, and read among you, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so hartes to receaue and beleeue the same, as yf vve reade of Lydia,<note place="margin">Actes. 16.</note> vvhose hart (sayth blessed Luke, the Lorde opened, that shee attended to the thinges vvhich Paul spake. Out of this your feruent zeale and burnyng loue tovvard this diuine and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Philosophie, many godly and Christen fruites of Gods spirite, haue issued and plentifully come foorth, as brotherly concord, and vnfained ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie among your selues, not your selues onely, but also among all the inhabitauntes of your Tovvne, so that all contention, strife, debate, discord, emni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, variaunce, tumultes, quarelles, lavvynges. &amp;c. banished, and auoyded: beneuolence, loue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, agreement, vnitie, amitie, freendship, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, humanitie, and vvhatsoeuer maketh vnto the bond of peace, ruleth and raigneth among you, vvhich godly vnitie and concord dooth so euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare you to be of God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note> as nothing more. In this shall all men knovve, that ye are my Disciples (sayth Christe) yf one of you loue an other. As dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord bringeth al thinges to hauocke: so dooth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord conserue, keepe in good order, and make to increase vvhat so euer is good and profitable to a common vveale, or to any part thereof. As Salusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us sayth: By concord, small thinges encrease and grovve: but by discorde, mighty and great thinges decay, and come to nought. It vvas very vvittely and learnedly ansvyeared of Terence, vvhen the noble Senate of the most noble Romanes demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him after the destruction of Carthage, vvhat he thought to be the cause of the subuertion if so
<pb facs="5"/>
ample, populus, and florishing citie, vvhether the puissaunce of the Romans, vvhose force seemed to be incomparable, or the feeblenesse of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginenses not being able to resist, No, sayth he, neyther your valiance, nor our vvant of puissance, vvas the subuersion of our citie, but the discorde of the Citizens. The mightiest fortresse, and strongest Bulvvarcke, that eyther Citie or Tovvne can haue, is the concord of Citizens, vvithout the vvhich, all puissaunce, all force, all vvytte, al pollicie, all castels, all martiall armonies are vayne, and vnprofitable, verely in this behalfe, are ye also greatly blessed of God, vvhich both in godly &amp; vvorldly affaires, are of one mind, &amp; of one meaning, vvithout al diffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion among you. O blessed fruite of Gods spirite. Moreouer, hovve idlenesse that chiefe maistres of vices all, vtterly exiled, and banished out of your Tovvne? No man liueth there idlely. All degrees of persons are godly, vertuously, and profitably occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, euery man according to his vocacion and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. All studye to be quiet,<note place="margin">Luke. .3.</note> and to meddle vvith theyr ovvne businesse, and to vvorke vvith theyr ovvne hands, that they may not only eate theyr ovvne breade according to the commanndement of God, but also through those their laboures haue vvhereof they may geue vnto such as haue neede, as Saint John saith, he that hath tvvo coates, let him geue one to him that hath none. And he that hath meate, let him doo likevvise. Certes diligent, and vertuous trauaile, vpholdeth the Citie: but idle and sluggysh hands, roote vp the foundacions thereof.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, vvho can yenough prayse and suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb facs="5"/>
commende your studious, carefulnesse, and painefull trauaile, in making prouision for the poore members of Christe, vvhich haue not of them selues, vvhereof to liue? Verely yee haue a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care for your poore', that none of them should vvant. Ye count their lacke, your ovvne lack: neyther are ye lesse moued vvith theyr miseries,<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 3.</note> then yf ye your selfs vvere touched vvith the same, according to this saying of Saint Iohn. He that hath the substance of this vvoorld, and seeth his brother haue neede, anb shutteth vp his compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him, hovv dvvelleth the loue of God in him? Vnmercifulnesse tovvard the poore, vvas one of the chiefe causes, vvhy that florishing and to much vvealthy Citie Sodome (as the Prophet tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth) vvas destroyed vvith fire, an brimstone from heauen.<note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> Verely euen so contraryvvise, vvhere the vvorkes of mercie are diligently practised vpon the poore, there is the blessing of God, conseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Tovvne, or Citie, encrease of goodes, and fortunate successe in all honest and godly trauayles, as Salomon sayth: He that geueth to the poore, shall not vvant. He that lendeth to the Lorde, that shevveth mercie to the poore, and it be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to the vttermost, as our Sauiour Christe sayth: Geue, and it shalbe geuen vnto you: good measure, and pressed dovvne, and shaken togeather, and runnyng ouer, shall men geue into your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes: For he that geueth but a cuppe of cold vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Christes sake,<note place="margin">Luke. .6.</note> shall not loose his revvard. Yf thou vvylt breake thy bread to the hungry, sayth GOD by the Prophete,<note place="margin">Esay. 58.</note> and leade the needy vvay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man into thy house, &amp; couer the naked man,
<pb facs="6"/>
and not turne avvay thy face from the poore: thy lyght shall breake foorth as the mornyng, and thy health florishe right shortly: yea, thy righteousnesse shal goe before thee, and the glory of the Lord shal embrace thee. Then yf thou callest, the Lord shall aunsvvere thee: yf thon cryest, he shall say: Here I am. O blessed is the man, sayth the Psalmographe, that considereth the poore and needy: the Lorde shall deliuer him in the time of trouble. The Lorde shall preserue him and keepe him aliue, that he may be blessed vpon earth, and not be deliuered into the vvyll of his enimies. The Lorde shall comfort him, vvhen he lyeth sicke vpon his bedde, yea and make his bedde in his sieknesse.</p>
   <p>Agayne, vvhat shall I speake of your gentle and louyng enterteynement of strangers and forreners, vvhich for the testemony of Christes most glorious Gospell, and for the quietnesse of theyr conscience, that they may the more freely serue GOD vvith a pure mind, are not only content to suffer vnvvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy banishment vvith the losse of their goodes, but also day and nyght to labour vvith their ovvne handes for their liuing, that they may be no burden to any man. These most vvyllyngly and gladly ye admit, receaue, and embrace, cherishe, entertayne, and comfort. These ye lodge &amp; place among you, not as strangers, but as Citizens, not as forreners, but as your dearely beloued Christian brothers: for vvhom also ye are no lesse carefull then for your selues, that nothing be lacking vnto them, but that they may haue sufficiently of all good and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thinges. This is the true hospitalitie, I meane, the gentle enterteynement of godly straungers, vviche
<pb facs="6"/>
are afflicted for the vvordes sake. Of these speaketh GOD on this manner:<note place="margin">Exod. 22. Leuit. 19.</note> Yf a straunger soiourne vvith thee in your land, ye shall not vexe him. But the stranger that dvvelleth vvith you, shalbe as one of your selues, and thou shalt loue him as thy selfe. Of these speaketh Christ on this vvyse:<note place="margin">Matth. 25. Romans. 12.</note> I vvas har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourlesse, and ye tooke me in. Of these speaketh Saint Paul thus: Distribute to the necessitie of the Saintes.<note place="margin">Hebru. 13. Gene. 19. 1. Peter. 4.</note> Be redy to harbour. Agayne, Be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull to lodge straungers: for there by haue diuers men lodged. Angels vnvvares Of these speaketh S. Peter on this sort: Be ye harberors one to another vvithout grudging.<note place="margin">Leuit. 19. and. 23. Deut. 24. 1. Tim. 4. Titus. 1.</note> Of these speaketh Saint Iohn on this manner. Thou dooest faythfully, vvhatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou dooest to the brethren, and to the straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Of these, GOD in his lavves geueth a speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charge both to the riche men, and also to the Byshoppes and spirituall Pastors of his congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they should see to them, and make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision for them, that they lacke nothing. Highly in Gods fauour must the godly straungers be, seeing GOD geueth to his people so great charge ouer them. VVho therefore can othervvyse, then highly commend the louing gentlenesse, and gentle loue, the bounteous liberalitie, and liberall bountie, vvhich ye shevve to the poore scattered members of Christe? These be vvoorthy fruites of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. These vvoorkes shevve, that ye haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the grace of God in vayne: and that ye be not of the company of those Gospellers, vvhiche vvith their mouth professe GOD, but vvith their deedes deny him, being abominable, and disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and vnapt vnto euery good vvoorke. Such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours
<pb facs="7"/>
or rather peruersers of the Gospell, are like to that Sonne, vvhich promised his father to vvork in his Vineyard, and vvrought nothing at all. Yea they are,<note place="margin">Iude. Epist.</note> as Saint Iude termeth them in his Epistle, cloudes vvithout vvater, trees vvithout fruite, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vvaues of the sea, foming out their ovvne shame, vvandring starres, to vvhome is reserued the mist of darknesse for euer, fleshely, hauing no spirit. &amp;c. and in deede like to those fiue foolish Virgins, vvhich had Lampes,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> but in theyr Lampes no Oyle, and not vnlike to the Figge tree vvithout fruite, vvhich Christ cursed for her barrennesse.</p>
   <p>But God (right vvorshipful and dearely beloued) hath geuen you an other minde, and grafted in you a better spirite, that yee do not only knovve God, but also earnestly labour to do his holy and blessed vvill, that by this meanes, yee may be founde not only fauorers, but also follovvers, not only talkers, but also vvalkers, not only louers, but also liuers, not only professoures, but also practisers, not only vvorders, but also vvorkers of the holy scripture, and so become blessed, as our Sauiour Christ saith. If yee knovve these thinges, and doo them, blessed are yee. For not euery one that saith vnto me Lord, Lorde, shall enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he that doth the vvill of the father, vvhich is in heauen, he shal enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Yee are my freendes, yf you doo those thinges that I commaunde you. He that hath my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, and keepeth them, he it is that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me.<note place="margin">Romans. .2.</note> For in the sight of god, as The apostle saith they are not righteous, vvhich heare the lavve, but the doers of the lavve shall be iustified. If any man
<pb facs="7"/>
be in Christ,<note place="margin">Galat. 5. Ephe. 2.</note> he is a nevve creature. They truly that are Christes, haue crucified the flesh, vvith the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and lustes. VVe are the vvorkmanship of God, created in Christ Iesu vnto good vvorkes, vvhich God hath ordayned, that vve should vvalke in them.<note place="margin">Tit. .3.</note> Let our eares learne saith Saint Paul, to excell in good vvorkes, as farre foorth as neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that they be not vnfruitefull.<note place="margin">Ioan. .15.</note> Herein is my father glorified (saieth our Sauiour Christ) that ye beare much fruite, and become my Disciples. Ye haue not chosen me, but I haue chosen you, and ordayned you to goe and bring foorth fruite, and that your fruite should remaine.</p>
   <p>Goe therefore foorth (right vvorshipfull and dearely beloued) as ye haue begun, in the vvay of righteousnesse. Receaue the Gospell of Christe, vvhich is the vvorde of your saluacion, and bread of life, vvith greedy, and desirous mindes. Call on God dayly (as ye doo) vvith feruent prayer, and cease not to be thankfull vnto him, for his benefits. Be an example in life and conuersacion, to them that are vnder you. Seke the quietness, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of your Tovvne, and of the inhabitauntes of the same, rather then your ovvne gaine, and profite: study rather to be loued, then feared. To the vvicked and sinfull, be seuere and sharpe: but to the good and godly, be gentle and louing. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your goodnesses and liberalitie to the poore strangers vvhich are exiled for the testimony of the Lorde Iesus, and tender them, as your selues. Suffer not idlenesse to creepe vvithin the bounds of your tovvne, but rather prouide that al be vvell &amp; vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously occupied. Of the poore, haue diligent consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratiō,
<pb facs="8"/>
but as for the sturdy &amp; lasie lubbers, vvhich gladly lyue of the labour of other mens handes, and hate to be vvell occupied them selues: eyther com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to vvoorke, or els banishe them your tovvne. Looke diligently to the bringing vp of your youth, eyther in good letters, or els in some vertuous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercices, that in time to come, they be not vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table members of the common vveale. But aboue all thinges, see that they be brought vp in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and feare of the Lorde, and in the knovvledge of his holy vvoord, that they may learne euen from their Cradles to serue their Lorde GOD in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and righteousnesse all the dayes of the Lorde. And that this thing may the more conueniently be brought to passe, as ye haue earnestly entended, and to that end haue prouided large summes of money among your selues: so vvith al expedition prouide, that your Schoole may be erected and set vp, for the godly and vertuous education of your youth. So shall you both doo a noble sacrifyce vnto God, deserue vvell of many, and also leaue to your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie a vvoorthy monument of a most vvoorthy enterprise. And to helpe forvvarde some poynt of godly doctrine to be taught in your nevve erected Schoole. After I had finished this little treatise, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, The Demaundes of holy Scripture, I thought it not vnsitting, nor vnvvorthy our frēd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, to dedicate the same to your vvoorships, and so by you, to commend it to the Christian youth of your Schoole. In it they shall learne to knovve and vnderstand, the principall and cheefe poyntes of Gods doctrine: so that by this meanes they shal be able to render a reason both of theyr fayth, and
<pb facs="8"/>
doctrine, vvhich they professe, and not be like Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses &amp; Mules that haue no vnderstanding. The book is little, yf the number of the leaues be considered: but yf the matter therof be diligently pondered, it shalbe found both great, &amp; profitable. Thus for this present, taking my leaue of you, I vvysh to you, and to the vvhole Tovvne, all good and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous things, both for your bodyes &amp; soules, most humbly beseeching God, to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe that good vvoorke, vvhich he hath begun in you, vnto the glory of his name, &amp; vnto the profite of his holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my house at Caunterbury,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi> the fyrst of September.</hi> 1563.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>