<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument of this Poem or History.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110227_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19260</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110227</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument of this Poem or History.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nightingale vvarbling forth her owne disaster; or The rape of Philomela. Newly written in English verse, by Martin Parker</title>
                 <author>M. P. (Martin Parker)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Cooke, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="history_of_poem">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Argument of this Poem or History.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>PAndion</hi> Prince of Athens (as the Roman Poet <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> writes) had two daughters, the eldest cald <hi>Progne,</hi> and the youngest <hi>Philomela;</hi> which <hi>Progne,</hi> being espoused to <hi>Tereus,</hi> the young King of Thrace; lived in great tranquillity and happinesse for the space of five yeeres; in which time <hi>Progne</hi> (more fond than wise) desired to see her sister <hi>Philomela,</hi> and with hourely importunity filled the eares of her husband <hi>Tereus,</hi> so that he gave his consent to fetch <hi>Philome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> and having gotten the forced consent of her father (partly by her owne desire to see her sister) he carried her away, and in the ship began to attempt the conquest of her virginity; whom she resists, and strives to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime with forcible arguments: but landing, he tooke her to a Graunge house that stood in his owne Country, and there perforce both ravisht and cut out her tongue lest she should bewray his impiety; so goes home, and tells his Queene, that her sister <hi>Philomela</hi> was dead: she grieves; but he with assimulation pacifier her, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mistrusting any such inhumane action as hee had done. But <hi>Philomela</hi> by her selfe (inclosed) wrought
<pb facs="9"/>
her mind in an handkerchiefe, which by a Gentleman that came that way by chance, she sent to the Queene her sister, who conceald her spleene, till she found fit time of vindication: which occasion soone offered in this manner: Jt was an annuall custome in Thrace for women to goe strangely disguisd about the country, to celebrate the feasts of <hi>Bacchus;</hi> in this manner went <hi>Progne</hi> to the Graunge, and fetcht out her sister <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mela,</hi> whom having brought to the Court privatly, she afterwards invited her husband to a banquet, kild her young sonne <hi>Itis,</hi> who was about three yeeres of age, and dressing him for meat set it before her husband <hi>Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> who having eaten it, and the impious deed dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, the Poet will have them (as unworthy of humane shape) to be Metamorphosed into birds. <hi>Philomel</hi> into a Nightingale, <hi>Progne</hi> to a Swallow, and <hi>Tereus</hi> to a Lapwing.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Note the morall and let the fiction passe as it is.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>