<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable, &amp; my singular good Lord Syr CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lord Chauncellor of England, Knyght of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Counsell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110586_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10413</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20698.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110586</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable, &amp; my singular good Lord Syr CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lord Chauncellor of England, Knyght of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Counsell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English ape, the Italian imitation, the footesteppes of Fraunce : VVherein is explaned, the wilfull blindnesse of subtill mischiefe, the striuing for starres, the catching of mooneshine: and the secrete sound of many hollow hearts. by W.R</title>
                 <author>Rankins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, &amp; my singular good Lord Syr CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lord Chauncellor of England, Knyght of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Counsell.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lphonsus (right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble)</hi> being asked what counsellers he liked best: aunswered bookes, for they neither flatter in securitie, sooth with subtiltie, contend in time of Controuersie, grudge at Superiours, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne Inferiours. To confirme which, (saith <hi>Cicero</hi>) Oh pleasant bookes, Oh harmeles bookes, the harbourers of forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vertue, and the fosterers of Morall demeanor. These say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (right Honourable) caused me to presume that this sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Counseller should be entertained by so worthy a Counseller. Whose wisedome is, as the best is, and whose honorable curtesie matcheth the excellent type of authoritie, wherein if I should striue to say what it doth excell, I should exceed the compasse of my slender capacitie, and so carrie a burden heauier then I am aware off, and in coueting vnworthie praise, condemne mine owne disabilitie. But (right Honourable) hauing poysed the perfection of that my penne cannot reach too, and remembring your honorable acceptance of my rough cast conceit of HELL, vnloading a complaint, and loading your eares with manie fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous phrases, wherein with <hi>Alexander,</hi> you preferred good will before good wit, and thought not how it was but what it was: I knew that what I brought were it the deformitie of a beast should be embraced as the best. And though <hi>Apes</hi> haue no reason yet your Honour I know woulde supplie that want by saying: It is a Beast.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all humilitie most affectionate, W.R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>