<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110634_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11404</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21660</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110634</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The third dayes creation. By that most excellent, learned, and diuine poet, VVilliam, Lord Bartas. Done verse for verse out of the originall French by Thomas VVinter, Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord <hi>BARTAS</hi> hauing deliuered in the former <hi>Dayes-worke,</hi> an excellent discourse of the foure elements in generall, and therein more particularly comprised both the nature of the fire and the aire: doth in this third booke (which is an explanation of the third dayes creation,) descend from the superior to the two inferior elements; in the description of which, as of the former, being alway like himselfe, that is, most excellent; he doth first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the Diuine assistance; then branching his whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course into two principall parts, he doth in the former des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the manner, how the waters were assembled together for the discouerie of the drie land; how the sea is situated and restrained within his bounds, which it neither doth, nor can transgresse; and how it imbraceth the earth in his armes, which together with the more famous riuers of the world are repeated. Vnto which discourse he addeth a briefe conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of fountaines, brookes, land-flouds, and riuers; of their increase and falling into the sea, which being no whit augmented by their continuall accesse, brings much admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to those, that labour in searching the reasons of the eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and flowing of the same: which, though it be a question full of difficultie, and either meerely or nearely vnresolua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet doth he couch in a very few verses, as much as reason or probability can perswade in so abstruse a speculation. Then intreating of the saltnesse of the sea, and of the admirable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb facs="6"/>
of diuers springs and bathes, he concludes the first part of this booke with an enumeration of those singular commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which all creatures receiue by the conglobation of the earth with the water. In the second part, which is an ample and elegant description of the earth, the stabilitie and vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie therof is first deciphered; the quaking ouertures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe of the same are proposed: which together with the sea, being but a point compared to the heauens; doth giue him occasion to deduce therehence a necessarie exhortation, to withdraw the worldly minds of wretched men from the ouer greedie pursuit of these earthly things. Now forasmuch as the earth so separated from the sea, was by the heauenly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence pre-ordained to be the mother, nource, and entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hostesse of all mankind, he doth most artificially embla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the profitable beauties thereof, as being most variously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with trees, plants, hearbes and flowers of such singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and sundrie vertues for the vse of man, that they seeme to haue engrauen vpon them, and that in Capitall letters, the aboundant wisdome, and super aboundant grace of the puis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Creator. Which is amplified by the admired sympathies of diuerse creatures; by the varietie of graine, of wools, silks, cottons, flaxe, hempe, and such other commodities as the diuersified disposition of sundrie clymates produceth; all which are yearely renewed by that prouident hand, from which they receiued their originall vertues. Among other wonders of nature, he mentioneth the tree called <hi>Cocos,</hi> whose strange proprieties are almost incredible; and desiring more perfectly to anatomize the whole bodie and bowels of the earth, he rips vp her very entrailes, to find what mettals and minerals are treasured vp in that great store-house of the world. Then teaching the true vse of gold and iron, he speaketh of the admired vertue of the Load-stone, of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners
<pb facs="6"/>
compasse-needle, and sundrie sorts of earth which by experience are of themselues medicinable. Which hauing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, he greets the earth, painting out in fresh and liuely colours her deserued prayses: and by the example both of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Patriarkes, and men of great esteeme among the Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims) he blames those that contemne husbandrie, and the profitable knowledge of simples. And so with an excellent amplification of the vnmatchable pleasures and happie secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the countrie life: he conclusiuely prayeth, that he may either end his quiet dayes in the countrie, or spend them in the Court without suspition of flatterie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>