<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110875_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11914</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22226</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seconde tragedie of Seneca entituled Thyestes faithfully Englished by Iasper Heywood fellowe of Alsolne College in Oxforde</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The preface.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the fowre and twentith date of latest monthe saue one</l>
      <l>Of all the yere. when flowre and frute from fielde and tree were gone,</l>
      <l>And sadder season suche ensewde as dulls the dolefull spright{is}</l>
      <l>And Muse of men that woonted were to wander in delight{is}:</l>
      <l>And weather suche there was, as well became the pe<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ue pen</l>
      <l>With sory style of woes to wryte and eke of mischiefe, when</l>
      <l>Aurora blusht with ruddie cheekes, to waile the death agayne</l>
      <l>Of Phoebus soon: whom thunderbolt of mightie Ioue had slayne:</l>
      <l>And cloudes from highe began to throwe their dreary teares adowne,</l>
      <l>And Uenus from the skyes aboue on fryday fowle to frowne:</l>
      <l>W<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en (as at booke with mased Muse I satte and pensiue thought</l>
      <l>Deepe drownde in dumps of drousines <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> chaunge of weather wrought,)</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>I felt howe Morpheus bound my browes and eke my Temples strooke,</l>
      <l>That downe I soonke my heauy head and sleapt vppon my booke.</l>
      <l>Then dreamde I thus, that by my syde me thought I sawe one stande</l>
      <l>That downe to grounde in scarlet gowne was dight, and in his hande</l>
      <l>A booke he bare: and on his head of Bayes a Gatland greene:</l>
      <l>Full graue he was, well stept in yeres and comly to be seene.</l>
      <l>His eyes like Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ll shiende: his breathe full sweete, his face full fyne,</l>
      <l>It seemde he had byn lodged long, among the Muses nyne.</l>
      <l>Good syr ({quam} I) I you beseche (since that ye seeme to me</l>
      <l>By your attyre some worthie wight) it may your pleasure be,</l>
      <l>To tell me what and when<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. wherat a whyle he stayde</l>
      <l>Beholdyng me: an one he spake, and thus (me thought) he sayde.</l>
      <l>Spayne was ({quam} he) my natiue soyle: a man of woorthie fame</l>
      <l>Sometime I was in former age, and Sene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> my name.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>The name of Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> when I hearde then scantly could I speake:</l>
      <l>I was so gladde that from mine eyes the teares began to breake</l>
      <l>For ioy: and with what wordes I shoulde sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> him, I ne wyst.</l>
      <l>I him enbrast: his handes, his feete, and fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e full ofte I kyst.</l>
      <l>And as at lengthe my trickiyng teares me thought I might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>O blisfull daye ({quam} I,) wherin returned is agayne</l>
      <l>So worthie wight: O happie houre, that liefer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to me</l>
      <l>Then life: wherin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> me so, that I should Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> see.</l>
      <l>Arte thou the same, that whilom dydst thy Tragedies endight</l>
      <l>With woondrous wit and regall stile? O long desyred sight.</l>
      <l>And lyuste thou yet ({quam} I) in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ede? and arte thou come agayne</l>
      <l>To talke and dwell as thou wert won<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> with men? and to remayne</l>
      <l>In this ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> age? I lyue ({quam} he) and neuer shall I die:</l>
      <l>The woorks I wrote shall still preser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> my name in memorie</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>From age to age: and nowe agayne I will reuiue the same,</l>
      <l>And here I come to seeke some one that might renewe my name,</l>
      <l>And make me speake in straunger speeche and sette my woorks to sight,</l>
      <l>And skanne my verse in other tongue then I was woont to wright.</l>
      <l>A young man well I wotte there is in thyle of Brytannie,</l>
      <l>(That from the rest of all the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> aloofe in seas doth lie)</l>
      <l>That once this labour tooke in hande: him wolde I meete full sayne,</l>
      <l>To c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ue that in the rest of all my woork{is} he wolde take payne</l>
      <l>To toyle, as he in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> did. is that your wyll (quoth I?)</l>
      <l>I blusht, and sayd the same you seeke, loe, here I stande you by.</l>
      <l>If thou ({quam} he) be whome I seeke, if glorie ought thee moue</l>
      <l>Of myne to come in after age, if Senc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s name thou loue</l>
      <l>Aliue to keepe, I thee beseech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> agayne to take thy pen,</l>
      <l>In miter of thy mother tongu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> to geue to sight of men</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>My other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: wherby thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> deserue of them and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>No litle thancks: When they them selues my Tragedies shall see</l>
      <l>In Englishe verse, that neuer yet coulde latine vnderstande.</l>
      <l>With my renowne perhapps thy name shall flie throughout this lande,</l>
      <l>And those that yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> neuer knew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> shall thee bothe loue and prayse,</l>
      <l>And say God graunt this yong man well to lyue full many dayes,</l>
      <l>And many happy houres to see in life: and after graue,</l>
      <l>Rest, ioy, and blisse eternally aboue the skies to haue,</l>
      <l>That so translated hath these bookes. to him (quoth I) agayne</l>
      <l>(If any be that so with thanks accepts a yong mans payne)</l>
      <l>I wishe great good: but well I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> the hatefull cursed broode</l>
      <l>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rre greater is, that are long syns sproong vp of Zoylus bloode.</l>
      <l>That Red heard, black mouthd, squint eyed wretche hath cow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>hed euery wheare,</l>
      <l>In corner close some Impe of his that si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> to see and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>What eche man dothe, and eche man blames. nor on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e we may him s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>Come face to face, but we once gone then stoutly stepps out hee:</l>
      <l>And all he carpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> that there he fyndes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>re halfe he reade to ende,</l>
      <l>And what he vnderstandes not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, though nought he can amende.</l>
      <l>But were it so that such<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> were none, how may these youthfull dayes</l>
      <l>Of mine, in thyng so hard as this de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rue of other prayse?</l>
      <l>A labour long (quoth I) it is that riper age doothe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>aue:</l>
      <l>And who shall trauaile in thy bookes, more iudgement ought to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>Then I: whose greener yeares therby no thanks may hope to wynne.</l>
      <l>Thou seest dame Nature yet hath sette No heares vppon my chynne.</l>
      <l>
         <unclear>Craue</unclear> this therfore of grauer age, and men of greater skill.</l>
      <l>Full many be that better can, and come perhapps that will.</l>
      <l>But yf thy will be rather ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, a yong mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to proue,</l>
      <l>And thinkst that elder lerned men perhaps it shall behoue,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>In woorks of waight to spende theyr tyme, goe where Minervaes men,</l>
      <l>And finest witts doe swarme: whome she hath taught to passe with pen.</l>
      <l>In Lyncolnes Inne and Temples twayne, Grayes Inne and othe mo,</l>
      <l>Thou shalt them fynde whose paynfull pen thy verse shall florishe so,</l>
      <l>That Melpomen thou wouldst well weene had taught them for to wright,</l>
      <l>And all their woorks with stately style, and goodly grace t'endight.</l>
      <l>There shalt thou se the selfe same Northe, whose woorke his witte displayes,</l>
      <l>And Dyall dothe of Princes paynte, and preache abroade his prayse.</l>
      <l>There Sackuyldes Sonett{is} sweetely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, and featly fyned bee,</l>
      <l>There Nortons ditties do delight, there Yeluertons doo flee</l>
      <l>Well <unclear>pewrde</unclear> with pen: suche yong men three, as weene thou mightst agayne,</l>
      <l>To be begotte as Pallas was, of myghtie Ioue his brayne.</l>
      <l>There heare thou shalt a great reporte, of Baldwyns worthie name,</l>
      <l>Whose Myrrour dothe of Magistrates, proclayme eternall fame.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>And there the gentle Blunduille is by name and eke by kynde,</l>
      <l>Of whome we learne by Plutarches lore, what frute by Foes to fynde.</l>
      <l>There Bauande bydes, that turnde his toyle a Common welthe to frame,</l>
      <l>And greater grace in Englyshe geues, to woorthy authors name.</l>
      <l>There Gouge a gratefull gaynes hath gotte, reporte that runneth ryfe,</l>
      <l>Who crooked Compasse dothe describe, and Zodiake of lyfe.</l>
      <l>And yet great nombre more, whose names yf I shoulde now resight,</l>
      <l>A ten tymes greater woorke then thine, I should be forste to wright.</l>
      <l>A pryncely place in Parnasse hill, for these there is preparde,</l>
      <l>Where crowne of glittryng glorie hangs, for them a ryght rewarde.</l>
      <l>Wheras the lappes of Ladies nyne. shall dewly them defende,</l>
      <l>That haue preparde the Lawrell leafe, about theyr hedd{is} to bende.</l>
      <l>And where theyr Penn{is} shall hang full hie, and fame that erst was hyd,</l>
      <l>Abrode in Brutus realme shall flie, as late theyr volumes dyd.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>These are the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> that can display thy Tragedies all ten,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> with sug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>d sentence sweete, and practise of the pen.</l>
      <l>My selfe, I must confesse, I haue to muche alreadie doon</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>boue my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>che, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>shly once with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> I begoon:</l>
      <l>And more presumde to take in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd: then well I brought to ende,</l>
      <l>And litle volume with mo fautes, then lynes abrode to sende.</l>
      <l>And of that woorke what men reporte, In faythe I neuer wist.</l>
      <l>But well I wotte, it may be thought so yll, that litle lyst</l>
      <l>I haue to dooe the like: Wherof though myne be all the blame,</l>
      <l>And all to me imputed is, that passeth in my name:</l>
      <l>Yet as of some I will confesse that I the author was,</l>
      <l>And fawt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> to many made my sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> when I that booke let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e pas</l>
      <l>Out of my handes: so must I me excuse, of other some.</l>
      <l>For when to sygne of Hande and Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> I ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>yrst to come,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>To Printers hands I gaue the worke: by whome I had suche wrong,</l>
      <l>That though my selfe perusde their prooue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> the fyrst tyme, yet ere long</l>
      <l>When I was gone, they wolde agay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> the print therof renewe,</l>
      <l>Corrupted all: in suche a sorte, that scant a sentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rewe</l>
      <l>Now flythe abroade as I it wrote. which thyng when I had tryde,</l>
      <l>And fowrescore greater fautes then myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> in fortie leaues espyde,</l>
      <l>Small thanks ({quam} I) for suche a woorke wolde Senec geue to me,</l>
      <l>If he were yet a lyue, and shoulde perhapps it chaunce to see.</l>
      <l>And to the printer thus I sayde: within these doores of thyne,</l>
      <l>I make a vowe shall neuer more come any worke of myne.</l>
      <l>My frende ({quam} Senec therwithall) no meruayle therof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>:</l>
      <l>They haue my selfe so wronged ofte, And many things amys</l>
      <l>Are doon by them in all my woork<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, suche fautes in euery booke</l>
      <l>Of myne they make, (as well he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> it fynde that lyst to looke,)</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>That sense and latin, verse and all they violate and breake,</l>
      <l>And ofte what I yet neuer ment they me enforce to speake.</l>
      <l>It is the negligence of them, and partly lacke of skill</l>
      <l>That dooth the woorks with paynes well pend full ofte disgrace and spill.</l>
      <l>But as for that be nought abasht: the wise will well it waye,</l>
      <l>And learned men shall soone discerne thy fautes from his, and saye,</l>
      <l>Loe here the Printer dooth him wrong, as easy is to trye:</l>
      <l>And slaunder dooth the authors name, and lewdly him belye.</l>
      <l>But where thy yeares thou sayst lacke skyll, my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>doute thou not (quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h he.)</l>
      <l>I wil my selfe in these affayres, a helper be to thee.</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> tale I will expounde and other places harde.</l>
      <l>Thou shalt (nodoubte) fynde some, that will thy labour well regarde.</l>
      <l>And therwithall, oh lorde he sayde, now him I thinke vppone,</l>
      <l>That here but late to litle liude, and now from hens is gone.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>Whose vertues rare in age so green<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> bewrayde a worthy wight,</l>
      <l>And towardnesse tryde of tender tyme, how louely lampe of light</l>
      <l>He woulde haue byn, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> God had spaerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> his dayes, tyll suche tyme, whan</l>
      <l>That elder age had abled him, by grouthe to grauer man.</l>
      <l>How thankfull thyng thinkst thou (quoth he) woulde this to him haue beene,</l>
      <l>If geuen to his name he might a woorke of thine haue seene,</l>
      <l>Whome duryng life he fauourde so? but that may be:</l>
      <l>For gone he is, (alas the while) thou shalt him neuer see,</l>
      <l>Where breathyng bodyes dwell agayne: nor neuer shalt thou more,</l>
      <l>Eftsones with him of learnyng talke, as thou werte woont before.</l>
      <l>Yet wayle no more for him (he sayde) for he farre better is.</l>
      <l>His seate he hath obtayned nowe, among the starr{is} in blis.</l>
      <l>And castyng brighter beames about, then Phoebus golden glede,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>boue the skies he lyues with Ioue, an other Ganymede:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>In better place then Aquarie. suche grace did God him gyue.</l>
      <l>But though the sonne be gone, yet her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> dothe yet the father lyue.</l>
      <l>And long might he this lyfe enioye in helthe, and great encrease</l>
      <l>Of honour and of vertue bothe, Tyll God his soule release</l>
      <l>From corps to skyes: with right rewarde to recompense him there,</l>
      <l>For truthe and trusty seruice doon, to prince and contrey here.</l>
      <l>His goodnes loe thy selfe hast felte (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>) and that of late,</l>
      <l>When he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e fayled not to helpe, and su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>our thyne estate.</l>
      <l>To him it shall besceme thee well some token for to showe,</l>
      <l>That of thy dutie whiche thou dooste for his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rts him owe</l>
      <l>Thou myndfull arte, and how thou dooste thy diligence applie,</l>
      <l>To thanke as powre may serue, and wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> thy pen to sygnifie,</l>
      <l>A gratefull mynde. And though to light so litle trifle bee,</l>
      <l>To geue to him that hath so much<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>die doone for thee,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>Yet syns thou canst none otherwyse his honour yet requight,</l>
      <l>Nor yet thy yeares doe thee permit more waightie woorkes to wright,</l>
      <l>This Christmas tyme thou mayste doe well a peece therof to ende,</l>
      <l>And many thanks in volume small, as thee becomes to sende.</l>
      <l>And tell him how for his estate, thou dooste thy praiers make:</l>
      <l>And him in dayly vowes of thine, to God aboue betake.</l>
      <l>But for because the Prynters all haue greatly wronged mee,</l>
      <l>To ease thee of thy paynes therin, see what I bryng to thee.</l>
      <l>He sayde: and therwithall, began to ope the gylded booke</l>
      <l>Whiche erst I tolde he bare in hand and thervpon to looke.</l>
      <l>The leaues within were fyne to feele, and fayre to looke vppone,</l>
      <l>As they with syluer had byn fleakte, full cleare to see they shone.</l>
      <l>Yet farre the letters did eche one exceede the leaues in sight,</l>
      <l>More glorious then the glittryng golde, and in the Iye more bright.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="12"/>The featly framed lynes throughou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> in meetest maner stande,</l>
      <l>More worthy worke it was, then might be made by mortall hande.</l>
      <l>Therwith me thought a sauour sweete I felt, so fresshe that was,</l>
      <l>That bedds of purple vyolett{is}, and Roses farre did pas.</l>
      <l>No princes perfume like to it, in chamber of estate:</l>
      <l>I wiste it was some thyng diuine, did me so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</l>
      <l>I fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> my selfe refresshed mucke, well quickned were my wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>{is},</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>d often tymes of pleasure great I had so ioyfull f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>{is},</l>
      <l>That wakyng now I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, you may beleeue me well,</l>
      <l>Great hoorde of golde I wolde refuse in suche delights to dwell,</l>
      <l>As in that dreame I had. anone, me thought I asked him,</l>
      <l>What booke it was he bare in hand, that showde and smelde so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>im.</l>
      <l>These are ({quam} he) the Tragedics in deede of Seneca,</l>
      <l>The Muse her selfe them truly writ, that hight Melp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>mena.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="12"/>In Parnase printely palaice highe, she garnisshed this booke,</l>
      <l>The Ladies haue of Helicon great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>oy theron to looke:</l>
      <l>When walkyng in theyr aleys sweet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> the flowres so fresshe they treade,</l>
      <l>And in the midst of them me place, my Tragedie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> to treade.</l>
      <l>These leaues that fyne as veluet feele, and parchement like in sight,</l>
      <l>Of feate fyne Fawnes they are the skyns, suche as no mortall wight</l>
      <l>May come vnto: but with the which the muses woont to playe,</l>
      <l>In gardens still with grasse full greene, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> are full gaye.</l>
      <l>There fostred are these litle beasts, and fed with Muses mylke,</l>
      <l>Their whitest hands and feete they lycke, with tongue as softe as sylke.</l>
      <l>Theyr heare not suche as haue the hearde, of other common Deare,</l>
      <l>But silken skyns of purple hewe, lyke veluet fyne they weare.</l>
      <l>With proper featly framed feete, about the arbours green<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>They trippe and daunce before these dames, full seemely to be seene:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>And then theyr golden hornes adow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> in Ladies lappes they lay,</l>
      <l>A greate delight those systers nyne, haue with these Fawnes to play.</l>
      <l>O{is} skyns of them this par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>hment loe that shynes so fayre they make,</l>
      <l>When ought they woulde with hande of theyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, to written booke betake.</l>
      <l>This gorgeous glyttryng golden Inke, so precious thyng to see,</l>
      <l>Geue eare and wherof made it is, I shall declare to thee.</l>
      <l>Fayre trees amyd theyr Paradise, there are of euery kynde,</l>
      <l>Where euery frute that boughe bryngs foorthe, a man may euer fynde.</l>
      <l>And deynties suche as princes wont, with proudest price to bie,</l>
      <l>Great plentic therof may be seene, hang there on branches hie.</l>
      <l>The Plumme, the Peare, the Fygge, the Date, Powngarnet wants not theare,</l>
      <l>The Orynge and the Olyue tree, full plenteously doe beare.</l>
      <l>Ye there the golden Apples hang, whiche once a thyng muche worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>To ioye the weddyng day of Ioue, the soyle it selfe brought forthe.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>There Daphne stands transformde to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ret, that greene is styll to sight,</l>
      <l>That was sometyme the loued Nymphe so fayre, of Phoebus bright.</l>
      <l>Not farre from frute so rytche, that once did wakyng drago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> keepe</l>
      <l>Do the Myrtha stande, with wofull teare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> that yet dothe wayle and weepe.</l>
      <l>Her teares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ongealed hard to gumme, that sauour sweete dothe cast,</l>
      <l>It is that makes to leafe so fyne, this Inke to cleaue so fast.</l>
      <l>But with what water is this Inke thus made, now learne (quoth hee)</l>
      <l>The secrets of the sacred mounte, I wyll declare to thee.</l>
      <l>Aboue the rest a Cedre hyghe, of haughtie toppe there growes</l>
      <l>With bendyng braunches farre abrod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, on soyle that shadowe showes.</l>
      <l>In toppe wherof do hang full hie, the pennes of poetts olde,</l>
      <l>And posyes purtred for theyr prayse, in letters all of golde.</l>
      <l>In shade wherof a banquet house there stands of great delight,</l>
      <l>For Muses ioyes, the walls are made of marble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>yre in sight</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="14"/>Fowre square: an Iuery turret stands at euery corner hye,</l>
      <l>The nookes and toppes doth beaten golde, and amell ouerlye.</l>
      <l>In fulgent seate dothe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>leeyng fame, there syt full hyghe from grounde,</l>
      <l>And prayse of Pallas poets sends to starres with trumpetts sounde.</l>
      <l>The gate therof so strong and sure, it neede no watche nor warde</l>
      <l>A woondrous woorke it is to see, of Adamant full harde.</l>
      <l>With nyne sure locks wherof of one eche ladye kepes the kaye,</l>
      <l>That none of them may come therin when other are awaye.</l>
      <l>The floore within with emrawds green<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, ys paued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ayre and feate,</l>
      <l>The boorde and benches rownde about, are made of pure blacke geate.</l>
      <l>The lute, the harpe, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ytheron, the shaulme, the shagbut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>The vyall and the vyrginall, no musyke there to seeke.</l>
      <l>About the walls more woorthy woorke then made by mortall hande,</l>
      <l>The poetts paynted pyctures all in seemely order stande:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="14"/>With colours suche so lyuely layd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, that at that sight I weene,</l>
      <l>Apelles pensyle woulde beare backe, abashed to be seene.</l>
      <l>There Homere, Ouide, Horace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> full featlye purtred bee,</l>
      <l>And there not in the lowest place, they haue described mee.</l>
      <l>There Uirgyle, Lucane, Palingene, and rest of poetts all</l>
      <l>Do stande, and there from this daie foorthe. full many other shall.</l>
      <l>For now that house by manye yardes, enlarged out they haue,</l>
      <l>Wherby they myght in wyder wall the Images engraue,</l>
      <l>And paynte the pyctures more at large, of hundreds, englysshe men,</l>
      <l>That geeue theyr tongue a greatter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>race, by pure and paynfull pen.</l>
      <l>In mydst of all this woorthy woorke, there runn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> a pleasant spryng,</l>
      <l>That is of all the paradyse, the most delycious thyng.</l>
      <l>That rounde about encloased is, with wall of Iasp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r stone:</l>
      <l>The ladies let no wight therin, but euen them selues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>lone.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="15"/>The water shynes lyke golde in syght, and swetest is to smell,</l>
      <l>Full often tymes they bathe them selues, within that blysfull well.</l>
      <l>With water thereof they this In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> haue made that wryt this booke,</l>
      <l>And lycenst me to bryng it downe, for thee theron to looke.</l>
      <l>Thou maist beleeue it trewly wrote, and trust in euery whit</l>
      <l>For here hathe neuer prynters pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> made faute, nor neuer yet,</l>
      <l>Came errour here by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of man. in sacred seate on hye,</l>
      <l>They haue it wryt, in all whose woork{is}, theyr pen can make no lye.</l>
      <l>This booke shall greatly thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, to see how Prynters mys,</l>
      <l>In all my woorkes, and all theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, thou mayste correcte by thys.</l>
      <l>And more then that, this golden spryng, with whiche I haue the tolde</l>
      <l>This ynke so bryght thus made to bee, suche propertee dothe holde,</l>
      <l>That who therof the sauou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> feeles, his wytt{is} shall quickned bee,</l>
      <l>And spryghts reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ude in woondrous wyse, as now it happs to thee.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="15"/>Come on therfore whyle helpe thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> he sayde, and therwithall</l>
      <l>Euen at Thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>stes chaunced fyrst, the leaues abrode to fall.</l>
      <l>Euen here ({quam} he) yf it the please begyn, now take thy pen</l>
      <l>Moste dyre debates descrybe, of all that eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> chaunst to men.</l>
      <l>And whiche t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e godd{is} abhorde to see. The summe of all the stryfe</l>
      <l>Now harken to. Thyestes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> his brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> wyfe,</l>
      <l>And ramme with golden fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ece: but y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e Atreus frendship fayne</l>
      <l>With him, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ll tyme for fathers foode he hathe his children slayne,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd dishes drest. he sayde, and then begun to reade the booke:</l>
      <l>I satte attent, and therupon I fyxed fast my looke.</l>
      <l>Fyrst how the furye draue the spryght of Tantalus from hell</l>
      <l>To styrre the stryfe, I harde hym reade, and all expounde full well.</l>
      <l>Full many pleasant poetts tales that dyd me please I harde,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd euermore to booke so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> great regarde.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="16"/>Wherby I sawe how often tymes the Printers dyd him wrong.</l>
      <l>Now Gryphyus, Colineus now, and now and then among</l>
      <l>He Aldus blamde, with ali the rest that in his woor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s do mys</l>
      <l>Ofsence or verse: and styll my booke, I did cort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> by hys.</l>
      <l>The god of sleepe had harde all this, when tyme for him it was,</l>
      <l>To denns of slumber whence he came, agayne awaie to pas.</l>
      <l>The kercher bounde about my browes, dypt all in Lymbo lake,</l>
      <l>He strayght vnknyt, away he fleeth, and I begoon to wake.</l>
      <l>When rownde I rollde mine eyes about, and sawe my selfe alone,</l>
      <l>In vayne I Senec Senec cryde, the Poete now was gone.</l>
      <l>For woe wherof I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>n to weepe, O godds (quoth I) vnkynde,</l>
      <l>Ye are to blame with shapes so vayne our mortall eyes to blynde.</l>
      <l>What goodly gayne get you therby, ye shoulde vs so beguyle,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to lyttle whyle?</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="16"/>I Morpheus curst a thousande tymes, that he had made me sleepe</l>
      <l>At all, or ells that he me wolde, in dreame no longer keepe.</l>
      <l>And neuer were my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>oyes so greate, in sleepe so sweete before,</l>
      <l>But now as greeuous was my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, alas and ten tymes more,</l>
      <l>My selfe without the poete there, thus lefte alone to see,</l>
      <l>And all delights of former dreame, thus vanysshed to bee.</l>
      <l>Somtyme I curst, somtyme I cryde, lyke wight that waxed woode,</l>
      <l>Or Panther of hir pray depryude, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of her broode.</l>
      <l>A thousande tymes my colour goes, and comes as ofte agayne,</l>
      <l>About I walkte, I might no where, in quyet rest remayne.</l>
      <l>In woondrous wyse I vered was, that neuer man I weene</l>
      <l>So soone, might after late delights, in suche a pangue be seene.</l>
      <l>O thou Megaera then I sayde, if might or thyne it bee,</l>
      <l>Wherwith thou Tantall droauste from hell, that thus dysturbeth mce,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="17"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> my pen: with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> t'endyght,</l>
      <l>And as so dredfull thyng beseemes, with dolefull style to wryght.</l>
      <l>This sayde, I felte the furies force enflame me more and more,</l>
      <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> tymes more now chafte I was, then euer yet before.</l>
      <l>My he are stoode vp, I waxed woode, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> all dyd shake,</l>
      <l>And as the furye had me vext, my teethe began to ake.</l>
      <l>And thus enflamde with force of hir, I sayde it shoulde be doon,</l>
      <l>And downe I sate with pen in hande, and thus my verse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>