<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Praefatio.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110631_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02658</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1279</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110631</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Praefatio.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brefe comedy or enterlude concernynge the temptacyon of our lorde and sauer Iesus Christ, by Sathan in the desart. Compyled by Iohan Bale, Anno M. D. XXXVIII. Interlocutores. Iesus Christus, Angelus primus, Satan tentator, Angelus alter. Baleus Prolocutor</title>
                 <author>Bale, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Straten, Derick van der (Theodoricus Plateanus)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18+ pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Praefatio.</head>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Balcus Prolocutor.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter hys baptyme▪ Christ was Gods sonne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</l>
         <l>By the fathers voyce, as ye before haue hearde,</l>
         <l>Whych sygnyfyeth to vs, that we ones baptysed</l>
         <l>Are the sonnes of God, by hys gift &amp; rewarde▪</l>
         <l>And bycause that we, shuld haue Christ in regarde,</l>
         <l>He gaue vnto hym, the myghtye autoryte,</l>
         <l>Of hys heauenlye worde, our only teacher to be.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Now is he gone fourth, into the desart place,</l>
         <l>With the holy Ghost, hys offyce to begynne.</l>
         <l>Where Sathan the deuyll, with hys assaultes apace,</l>
         <l>With colours of craft, and manye a subtyle gynne,</l>
         <l>Wyll vndermynde hym, yet nothynge shall he wynne,</l>
         <l>But shame and rebuke, in the conclusyon fynall,</l>
         <l>Thys tokenneth our rayse, and hys vnrecurable fall.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Lerne first in thys acte, that we whom Christ doth call.</l>
         <l>Ought not to folowe, the fantasyes of Man,</l>
         <l>But the holy Ghost, as our gyde specyall,</l>
         <l>Whych to defende vs, is he that wyll and can,</l>
         <l>To persecucyon, lete vs prepare vs than,</l>
         <l>For that wyll folowe, in them that seke the truth.</l>
         <l>Marke in thys processe, what troubles to Christ ensuth.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Sathan assaulteth hym, with many a subtyle dryft,</l>
         <l>So wyll he do vs, if we take Christes part.</l>
         <l>And whan that helpeth not, he seketh an other shyft,</l>
         <l>The rulers amonge, to put Christ vnto smart,</l>
         <l>With so manye els, as beare hym their good hart.</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="2"/>Be ye sure of thys, as ye are of dayly meate▪</l>
         <l>If ye folowe Christ, with hym ye must be beate.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>For assaultes of Sathan, lerne here the remedye▪</l>
         <l>Take the worde of God, lete that be your defence.</l>
         <l>So wyll Christ teache yow, in our next Comedye,</l>
         <l>Ernestly prent it, in your quyck intellygence.</l>
         <l>Resyst not the worlde, but with meke pacyence,</l>
         <l>If ye be of Christ. Of thys herafter ye shall,</l>
         <l>Perceyue more at large, by the story as it fall.</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>