<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110172_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08256</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18591</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110172</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A straunge foot-post : vvith a packet full of strange petitions. After a long vacation for a good terme</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THe <hi>Persians</hi> were wont to keepe in their houses the Picture of an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picure</hi> ouerladen with wine, and sleeping with meate in his mouth, that by the view of such an vgly fight they might learne to be moderate, and avoyd the like excesse. The <hi>Parthians</hi> also to make their young men learne and fall into detestation of the alluring inticements of wicked women, are said to keepe in their houses a young man blinde carued very curiously; besides whome, was adioyned the Picture of a Woman, of farre more excellent perfection then the Image of <hi>Pigmalion,</hi> hauing one hand in his pocket to picke his purse, and holding a knife in the other hand to cut his throat.</p>
   <p>For eschewing the like enormities, I wish thee <hi>(Reader)</hi> in stead of the <hi>Persians</hi> Picture of an <hi>Epicure,</hi> and the <hi>Parthians</hi> Picture of an <hi>Harlot</hi> in thine house, to carry about thee this <hi>Packet</hi> in thy Pocket: Which being opened, will Present suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter vnto thee that may both make thee weane thy selfe from wanton desires, and shun the misery that followes exces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue superfluity, as also escape many other detriments that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the contempt of aduised courses.</p>
   <p>If any handling this <hi>Packe,</hi> or perusing it (as I doubt not but many will) shall by it be drawne to forsake some infectious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that it opens vnto them, I shall be glad of the recouery such sicke Patients: If others (not tainted) with the like infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities) shall onely looke on it, and laugh at it, and partly like it, the end of my labours haue a condigne counterpoise: Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine Anthony Nixon.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>