<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the righte worshipful maister Cheke, scole maister to the Kynges ma∣iestie, and prouost of his wor∣thy colledge in Cambridge, Edmund Gest wysheth enteir health both of body and soule.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110813_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01664</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11802</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110813</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the righte worshipful maister Cheke, scole maister to the Kynges ma∣iestie, and prouost of his wor∣thy colledge in Cambridge, Edmund Gest wysheth enteir health both of body and soule.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise againste the preuee masse in the behalfe and furtheraunce of the mooste hylye communyon : made by Edmund Gest. Reade gentyll reader and then iudge. M.D.XLVIII. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <author>Guest, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>184 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the righte worshipful maister Cheke, scole maister to the Kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, and prouost of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy colledge in Cambridge, Edmund Gest wysheth enteir health both of body and soule.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot wythstandynge (ryght worshipfull) I haue attempted an en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terpryce in prouynge eche parcel of the pryuye masse to dysplease god, whiche I can ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word, matier, ne reason accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynglye, and so am rather dysly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked then lyked of manye for thys my doyng, rather heady then hee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy as they suppose: Howebeyt in case the sayd persons woll wythe me earnestly respect my bounden
<pb facs="3"/> deutie in the sayd doyng, they (I doubte not (woll be rathere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented then discontēted with me for the same. For why? it is godes oppen wyll that not they alone, whom he hath mercifully delyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red ten or fyue talentes vnto,<note place="margin">Mat. xxv.</note> but they also, who haue freelye recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued at hys mercye handes, but one talent, shuld occupy the same, to hys most auauntage, &amp; not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrappe it (to his great hinderan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce) in a napkyn. Lesse he wolde therfore withdraw it from theim, and delyuer it to the well occupy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, either of the fyue or ten talen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes heretofore especyfied (A clear ensample wherof is for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning recorded ī Math. xxv) By re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sō wherof, albeit I am but slēder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledged ī scriptur matters in respect of others, whose know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is ten or fyue talentes too myne one, &amp; so am not hable to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uale and gane therwith any thīg
<pb facs="3"/> so much, as they w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thers, who ar passingly skylled in the mattiers before said: This not withstādīg I must occupy my talent &amp; auan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage so much therby vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord, as I can possyble, to the full dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my bonden dew herin, otherwise straitely charged with al.<note place="margin">luke. xvi.</note> For we must all become accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptable to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dreadful lord for our receipt &amp; stewardship.<note place="margin">luke. xvi</note> Who so sai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th Christe,<note place="margin">Math. 14.</note> is not faithful in a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is not trusty ī moch. We must al be busely occupied tyl he come, eche man in his call accordyngly No man must attempt to appear before hym whithoute hys offre,<note place="margin">Deut. xvi.</note> more or lesse, according to his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes herein, which he estemeth, and not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> value &amp; bygnes of the offredge.<note place="margin">luke. 21.</note> Though the sely poore wydowe offred but two mytes in to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes cheast, yet was she no lesse regarded of hym therfor, thē the great rych men, who offred in
<pb facs="4"/> to the same much more. Eche mā (sayeth Hierome) offreth in to the lordes house what he can, Some golde, syluer &amp; {pre}cyous stone, So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me eyther goteskinnes, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the same. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord nedeth all these, And he is egally pleased with them, who haue vnegally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffrede. In respecte wherof I haue offred vnto hym, this my symple poor myte or goate heare, trustīg he wol of hys mercye, both accept y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, &amp; occasion hereby others, to wryte more groundely &amp; clerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thys matteir, whych I haue chosen rather then an otheyr too ētreate vpon, In respecte y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> treate therof is both right avaylable &amp; nedefull to hys churche, &amp; so avā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageable to him selue, In y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth much to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> discontinuance &amp; owerthrowe of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pryuat masse, wherin we are most piteously blin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great dysworshipe bothe
<pb facs="4"/> of our sauyour &amp; hys moste holy communyō. This myne attempt (which as ye se, not of pride but of mere conscience I am ēforced to) not wythstandynge I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to the lorde: Houbeit I ensu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prayse worthy vsage of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers herein doo offre y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same to som other beside, namely to your worshipful mastership, not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> I ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iudge it a {pre}sēt, worthy your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I wold hereby opē my poore harte toward your mayster<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shyp, trustyng ye of your wonted vnspekeable gētlenes wol take it in good parte, not respectynge so muche the vylenes therof, as the good mynde of the presenter of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, who (vndoubtedly) hath {pre}<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sented, not all what he willyngly wolde, but what hym hably could theyrin. And thus I betake ye to god, whom I most enteirly be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sech to enuiron you w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hys grace
<pb facs="5"/> so to tread y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kinges maieste ī all vertue, wisdome, and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, as shalbe, fyrste to the hygh contentacion of god selue, &amp; furtherance of hys trueth, second<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to the Kinges honour and weale of hys realmes, lastelye too youre greate worshyppe name and furtheraunce A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>