<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110859_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11541</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21789</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110859</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vincentio Sauiolo his practise : In two bookes. The first intreating of the vse of the rapier and dagger. The second, of honor and honorable quarrels. Both interlaced with sundrie pleasant discourses, not vnfit for all gentlemen and captaines that professe armes</title>
                 <author>Saviolo, Vincentio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Mattes, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 17, that is 21 leaves, 250 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE meanes whereby men from time to time haue bene preferred euen to the highest degrees of greatnes and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, haue euer bene and are of two sortes, Armes and Letters: weapons &amp; bookes, as may most plainly bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of antique and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne histories. Let it not seeme strange vnto anie man that I haue placed Armes before Letters, for in truth I haue found by obseruing the course of times, and by comparing the occurrents of former ages with those which haue fallen out and followed (as it were by successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) in later yeeres, that the first Princes and patrones of people did obtaine their titles and dominions by force of Armes, and that afterwards learning &amp; vertue did (as it were by degrees) grow and succeede for the making and establishing of good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, customes, and lawes amongest them. And then did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths begin first to flourish, when their Princes were like <hi>Minerua,</hi> whom the Poets fained to bee the goddesse not onely of studies but also of Armes, inspiring wit into schollers, and fauoring those that follow warres. Wherefore knowing that such <pb facs="5"/> men as endeuour themselues to attaine vnto the excellencie of anie art or science, are worthie both of praise and preferment, because they seeke for that onely true nobilitie, which is in deede much more to be accounted of than birth and parentage. I haue beene induced (for the satisfaction of such, and other like noble spirites, desirous to imploie either their studies in the professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or their liues in the practise of the arte militarie) to bestowe my paines in the writing of this Treatise concerning the Art, exercise, and manneging of the Rapier and Dagger, together with the ordering and mouing of the bodie in those actions. A thing I confesse in shewe the least peece and practise (as a man might saie) of the arte Militarie, but in verie deed to most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, excellent, and noble practise thereof. For when I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with my selfe how some Authors doo write, that hunting, hauking, wrastling, &amp;c. are things in some sort belonging vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Militarie profession, for that men thereby doo both make their bodies strong and actiue, and also learne to marke the sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of hils, woods, lakes, and vallies, together with the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and turning courses of riuers. It seemeth vnto mee that I may with farre greater reason saie that the Arte and exercise of the Rapier and Dagger is much more rare and excellent than anie other Militarie exercise of the bodie, because there is very great and necessarie vse thereof, not onely in generall warres, but also in particular combats, &amp; many other accidents, where a man hauing the perfect knowledge and practise of this arte, although but small of stature and weake of strength, may with a little remouing of his foot, a sodain turning of his hand, a slight declining of his bodie, subdue and ouercome the fierce brauing pride of tall and strong bodies.</p>
   <p>Moreuer, it doth many times come to passe that discords and quarrels arise amongest souldiers and Gentlemen of honor &amp; account, the which (when they cannot be accorded &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <pb facs="5"/> by lawe, learning, and perswasion) must bee determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the truth thereof tried by armes and combat. And therefore he that is wise, carefull of his safetie, and prouident a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst danger, will be at all times stored and furnished with this honorable vrgent necessity, and instant shortnes of time, he shal be constrained to expose himselfe vnto euident danger.</p>
   <p>Wherefore vpon these occasions, and also for that I haue bin thereunto requested by sundrie Gentlemen my good friendes, I haue endeuoured to expresse in this discourse, and to make plain by pictures all the skill and knowledge which I haue in this art: Exhorting all men of good mindes and noble spirites to learne and purchase the same, not to the end to abuse it in insolencies and iniuries, but to vse it in cases of necessitie for the defence of iust causes, and to the maintenance of the honour of themselues and others. For whosoeuer will followe this profession must flie from rashnes, pride, and iniurie, and not fall into that foule falt and error which many men incurre, who feeling themselues to be strong of bodie and expert in this science, presuming thereu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, thinke that they may lawfully offer outrage and iniury vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to anie man, and with crosse and grosse tearmes and behauiour prouoke euerie man to fight, as though they were the onely heirs of <hi>Mars,</hi> &amp; more inuincible than
<hi>Achilles:</hi> not remembring how it hath oftentimes happened, that a little wretched man of stature by skill and reason hath ouercome a vast mightie man of person, and ouerthrowen the vnweldie masse and burthen of his bodie vpon the face of his kind &amp; liberall mother the earth. This manner of proceeding and behauiour doth plainely shew that these men (although peraduenture they haue learned the vse of the weapon) haue not yet beene fufficiently instructed in the Arte of Armes. For by the rule and precept of this Art, men are taught by how much they are resolute in courage, and skilful of the vse of the same weapon, by so much the more to shew
<pb facs="6"/> themselues vertuous, humble, and modest both in speech &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not to be liers, vanters, or quarrellers, for those which in this sort demeane themselues, (notwithstanding their skill or courage) do commonly carry away wounds and dishonor, and sometimes death.</p>
   <p>I haue seene and noted in diuerse partes of mine owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and in other places of the world, great quarrells springing from small causes, and many men slayne vppon light occasions. Amongest other things, I remember that in <hi>Liesena</hi> a citie of
<hi>Sclauonia,</hi> it was once my chance to see a sodaine quarrell and slaughter vpon very small cause betweene two Italian captaines of great familiaritie and acquaintance. There was in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie a foolish boy belonging vnto one of the Captaines, who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carelesly forward, &amp; approching neere vnto the other cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, began to touch the hilts of his sword, wherevpon the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine lent the boy a little blow to teach him better maners: The other Captaine (the boies master) taking this reprehension of his boy in worse parte than there was cause, after some wordes multiplyed began to drawe his sword, the other Captaine in like sort betaking himselfe to his rapier did with a thrust run him quite through the bodie, who falling downe dead vpon the place receiued the iust reward of his friuolous quarrell. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse the plaine truth in this point, it is not well done either of men or boyes to touch the weapons of another man that weareth them. Neuerthelesse a man ought in all his actions to seeke and endeuour to liue in peace and good agreement (as much as may be) with euerie one: and especially he that is a Gentleman and conuerseth with men of honorable quality, must aboue all others haue a great regard to frame his speech and answeres with such respectiue reuerence, that there neuer growe against him anie quarrell vpon a foolish worde or a froward answere, as it often hath and daily doth come to passe, whereupon follow deadly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treds, <pb facs="6"/> cruell murthers, and extreame ruines. Wherefore I saie and set downe as a most vndoubted truth, that it is good for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man to be taught and instructed in the Rapier and Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, not the rather thereby to grow insolent, or to commit mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to be able and ready in a case of iust necessitie to defend himselfe, either at the sodaine, or vpon defiance and in field as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed: for at that time it is too late to looke backe and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this studie, as many doo, who hauing appointed the time and place for fight, doe practise some point or other of this arte, the which being so lightly learned and in such hast, doth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in time of need proue but little helpfull or auailable vnto them. But this knowledge doeth more particularly appertayne vnto Gentlemen and souldiers that professe and followe warres, for they more than other men, will (for the credite of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the honor of Armes) dispute and determine with the point of the sword all points that passe in controuersie, especially amongest themselues, who had rather die than not to haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and satisfaction for euerie worde of preiudice and disgrace offered vnto them. Now in this case I am to exhort and aduise men of all sortes and condition, as well the skilfull as the vnskilfull, not to bee in anie wise too suspitious, nor to catch (as they saie) at euerie flie that passeth by, for in so dooing, they purchase to themselues endlesse trouble, and enter into acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons full of danger and dishonour
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> rather to shunne as much as they can all occasions of qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="6 letters">
         <desc>••••••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>id not to fight excepte (as hath bene sayde) vpon a iust cause and in a point of honor. And to the end that euerie man may know what to doo, and bee able to practise as much as hee knoweth (at the request of certaine Gentlemen my good friends, &amp; to make the world witnes of my gratefull minde towards them for the many curtesies which I haue receiued at their handes since my first comming into this Countrie) out of those preceptes which I haue learned from the
<pb facs="7"/> most rare and renowmed professors that haue bin of this Art in my time, and out of that experience which I haue obserued in diuerse fraies and fights, I haue composed and framed this little worke, containing the noble Arte of the Rapier and Dagger, the which I haue set downe in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Dialogue, &amp;c.</p>
   <figure>
      <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
   </figure>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>