<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110864_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11910</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22222</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110864</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eyght tragedie of Seneca. Entituled Agamemnon. Translated out of Latin in to English, by Iohn Studley, student in Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Colwell, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>¶ The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholde gentle Reader, howe <hi>SENECA</hi> in this present Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie hath most liuelie painted out vnto thee, the vnstabilytie of fortune, who when she hath aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the hyest hym, with whom (as the cat with the mouse) it liketh her to daly, sodeinly she t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rning her wheele, doth let hym fall to greater mysery, then was his former felicitie: wherof <hi>AGAMEMNON</hi> may be a perfect paterne, as is at large shewed in the Tragedie it selfe: whyche although it be but groslye, &amp; after a rude maner translated, contemne it not for the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>senes of the phrase, but embrace it for the excellencie of the matter therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned. And althoughe that the other Tragedies which are set furthe by <hi>Iasper Hetwood</hi> and <hi>Alexander Neuyle,</hi> are so excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well done (that in reading of them it semeth to me no translation, but e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en
<pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>SENECA</hi> hym selfe to speke in englysh) take no offence that I (beinge one of the moste that can do least) haue thus rashly attempted so great an enterprise, to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle my barbarusnes w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> others eloquencie: for when I had at the ernest requeste of certaine my familiar frendes, thus rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye perfurmed the same, they yet not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tysfyed herewith willed me, not to hyde &amp; kepe to my selfe that small talent which god hath lente vnto me to serue my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all, but rather to applye it to the vse of suche yonge Studentes as therby myght take some cōmoditie, therwith I consideringe, that keping it close it could profyte nothinge, and againe being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished it could do no hurte, trusting of thy gentlenes that thou wilt esteine this my good will, I haue presumed to set it furth thus simply and rudely: submitting it to the freindly correction of the learned. Thus desiringe thee to beare with my boldnes, &amp; pardon my ignoraūce, I leaue thee to God.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>