<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110159_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14995</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18521</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Furies· : With vertues encomium. Or The image of honour. In two bookes of epigrammes, satyricall and encomiasticke. By R.N</title>
                 <author>Niccols, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlewomen) this last and least part of my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle labour, I consecrate to you, the image of whose honour, though so excellent, that like that part of the picture of <hi>Venus</hi> left to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie by <hi>Apelles,</hi> takes away all hope of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the same; Yet to acquit my selfe of that madnesse, which the woman-hater doth indeuour to make mine, perhaps though more hastily then happily, I haue here cast off this image of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from the model of a woman, in honour of your sex. To an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer those, that say, my pen drops gall against you in the first part, I desire you to know that my <hi>Furies</hi> touch none but those Apes of yours; such I meane, who making no difference betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xt Swans and Geesse; because they haue both white feathers, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate only your fashion not your vertues. If in what followes you find my stile too harsh for so sweet a subiect, my forme too impolish for so faire an image, be pleased to know that I am limited to Epigrams, in which no pen can limme so faire a picture as your faire deserues; such as it is; if you respect it, I care not who reiect it, for, I put my selfe vnder your protection.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>