<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
TO THE PRINCE his Highnesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110082_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08122</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18483</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110082</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
TO THE PRINCE his Highnesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe relation of the discouery and plantation of Nevv England : and of sundry accidents therein occurring, from the yeere of our Lord M.DC.VII. to this present M.DC.XXII. Together with the state thereof as now it standeth; the generall forme of gouernment intended; an the diuision of the whole territorie into counties, baronries, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Council for New England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Bladen, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="2"/>
TO THE PRINCE his Highnesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S you are the height of our hopes and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednesse, next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your royall Father our Lord and Soueraigne: So, next vnto his Maiesty, are wee bound to dedicate our best endeuours
<pb facs="3"/>
to your Princely seruice. And for the Subiect of this relation, as your Highnesse hath beene pleased to doe it the honour, by giuing it the Name of <hi>New-England;</hi> and by your Highnesse most fauourable encouragement, to continue the same in life and being: So ought we to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an accompt of our proceedings, from the root thereof vnto the present growth it hath: which summarily is here done. If it shall appeare naked (as in truth it is) wee beseech your Highnesse to receiue it so much the rather for the truths sake, and with your bounty and grace to shelter it from the storms &amp; tempests of malice and enuy, by which it hath been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore dispoyled of that goodly Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it might haue had by this time.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
It is now almost able to comfort it selfe, and there is no question but by the light of your countenance, it will speedily grew, both to serue his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty with honour and profit, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply the same seruice to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in time to come, as a tribute due for the grace it receiues, by the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of a long peace and prosperity that our Nation enioyes vnder the Raigne of his sacred Maiestie, through which we haue the easier pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage to aduance the Crosse of Christ in Heathen parts, and to display his banner in the head of his Armie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst infernall spirits, which haue so long kept those poore distressed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (the inhabitants of those parts) in bondage, whose posteritie will for euer blesse the time, that the issue of
<pb facs="4"/>
your royall Ancestors, sprung from so Emperiall branches, should be the meanes to vnite the diuided Crownes in one, whereby the generous <hi>Spirits</hi> of both Nations, may haue the fairer opportunity to procure their liberties. If your Highnesse accept of what is past, we will hope of happinesse to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue; and howsoeuer, pray that all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of honour in this world, and all heauenly blessings in the world to come, may light vpon your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness as best be<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omes those that are</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse humble seruants,
The President and Councell of NEVV-ENGLAND.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>