<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Summary]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1109_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05363</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15516</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1109</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Summary]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very excellent and learned discourse, touching the tranquilitie and contentation of the minde : conteining svndry notable instrvctions, and firme consolations, most necessarie for all sortes of afflicted persons in these latter dayes. Distinguished into seven bookes, 1. Against covetousnes. 2. Against ambition. 3. Against anger. 4. Against envie. 5. Against pleasure. 6. Against curiositie. 7. Against feare. Written in French by the famous and learned M. I. De L'Espine, and newly translated into English by Ed. Smyth</title>
                 <author>L'Espine, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kitson, Abraham.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>11, 199, 101-106, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>❧ A COMPENDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>and short summe of this whole</hi> discourse touching the contentation of the mind: <hi>distinguished into seuen bookes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Verie man naturally endeuoureth by all means possible to liue quietly,<note place="margin">All men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to liue happely.</note> &amp; seeketh continually to settle himselfe in that estate, which he imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be most to his liking and contentation: and to this end tendeth all his labour, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells, deliberations, thoughtes, actions, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and enterprises whatsoeuer. Which though it be most true, yet doe they not take one, &amp; the selfe same course to attaine vnto their wished end: for some thinking felicitie to consist in riches, doe seeke for nothing else as long as they liue, but to gather wealth: others hunt after honour, and promotion, and some after pleasure, and delight: this man is best pleased with goodly and stately buildings, and that other with trauelling into farre Countries: and euerie one applieth himselfe vnto that, which fitteth his humour and agreeth with his liking. But there is no man so fortunate as to find that which he seeketh, neither is there any but complaineth of his owne estate and condition: and that in such sort, as wee may eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perceiue his vnquietnes, and discontentment. The reason whereof is this: They seeke for that in this world which cannot possib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be found: for this tranquillitie and repose of the minde is laide vp in heauen, and in the kingdome of God, and is bestowed onely vpon them, who hope to attaine vnto it by the meanes of Christ Iesus: for the contentation, whereof wee now speake, is nothing else, but that blessed, and happie estate, which he hath purchased vnto vs by his obedience, which he reserued for vs, vntill such time, as he appearing
<pb facs="10"/>vnto all the worlde in his glorie, shall make it manifest vnto all men. And yet I will not say, but that it may appeare in some sort, and be attained vnto evē in this life: &amp; that true &amp; vnfained Christians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing illuminated and regenerated, perceiuing the vanitie of this world, and the corruption of all thinges therein, may so lift vp their hearts and mindes vnto God, and by a consideration of his goodnesse and bountie, finde such quiet and assured rest, as they could neuer before attaine vnto. And to the ende that men may the better come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this quiet aend peaceable estate, I haue in these seuen bookes set downe the meanes that bringeth them thereto: to the end that they, by reading and endeauoring to follow those rules which are deliuered, may in processe of time by the grace of God obtaine their desire. And though the end be long and difficult, yet is it very excellent, pleasant, and profitable, and so greatly to be desired, that we ought to spare no trauell or labonr whatsoeuer, to attaine it. For it is so precious a lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, as the least part and peece thereof, is sufficient to recompense all our trauels, and paines.</p>
   <p>Now, that we may the better vnderstand wherein the contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde especially consisteth, wee must first search out those things, which doe most trouble and disquiet it. For as in corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diseases, it is very requisite to know the causes whereof they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, to the end we may the sooner cure them: so is it conuenient, the better to appease the trouble some passions of the minde, to knowe what those things are that haue ingendred them.</p>
   <p>Of these, some are externall: as pouertie, disbonour, losse, iniurie, enmitie, and such like: and some internall. And of these there are two sorts: for some haue relation onely to the hodie, as hurts, and diseases: and some to the minde, as passions, and affections, which are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, and carrie the greatest sway in the mouing of our spirits. For as we see the power of the windes in the motion and stirring of the aire, the waters, and the trees especially to preuaile, for that their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are moueable, and subiect to euerie motion: so likewise the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why euerie accidentall, and casuall chance doe trouble, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest vs, is, for that our mindes are incombred with vnstable, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering passions: and therefore it is verie expedient, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this treatise we set downe the meanes that may purge vs of these passionate humours.</p>
   <p>But first of all it is to be vnderstood, that that which shalbe spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="10"/>against these trouble some passions of the minde,<note place="margin">Against the opinion of the Stoikes which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men vnsensible.</note> will not make any thing for the proofe, and approbation of that Stoicall opinion, which maintaineth a senselesse and blockish nature, voide of all humanitie, and vnderstanding: for affections are as necessarie for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of humane societie, and preseruation of mutuall concord among men, as bread and drinke are conuenient for their vse. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as skilfull Phisitians, who take vpon them to heale a disease, doe not purge the bodie of all moisture, but onely of that which is corrupt and putrified, and seeke to reduce the rest to a good and conuenient temperature: so likewise we must not labour to extinguisb all affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our nature, but to weede (as out of a garden) those onely, which are euill: and manure and husband the rest, to the end they may bring forth some good and wholsome fruite.</p>
   <p>Secondly, we must note,<note place="margin">A remedie against the passions of the mind.</note> that there are no remedies more fit and conuenient to heale the diseases of the mind, then words, reasons, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, discourses and demonstrations, which doe liuely and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally set foorth both vice and vertue, in shewing the beautie of the one, to the end to make vs in loue with it, and contrariwise in declaring the detestable and foule euill fauourednes of the other: thereby the more to make vs hate and loath it. We must obserue then, that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke is not good, vnlesse it be for such as take it, and for those whose natures are well prepared before to receiue the operation therof: and therefore if the reader will obtaine any profite hereby, he must reade diligently, and carefully lay vp in his minde those reasons which shalbe alledged, and earnestly craue at the handes of God, that these things may be effectuall to his good: for it is he alone that must giue the encrease to these our labours, which otherwise will be altogither vnprofitable and vnfruitfull. We are like vnto them, who shewe and teach other the way they should trauell in: they tell them right, and where they ought to turne: but if they fall lame, or waxe wearie by the way, they can not giue them new legges or sufficient strēgth to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell out their iourney. Wherefore seeing all dependeth vpon the grace of God, both the knowledge of them who inflruct others, and the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnesse of those who are taught, to put in practise, and to execute the counsels of them who teach them: let vs commend our selues vnto him &amp; humbly be seech him to giue vs grace that we may both vnderstād, and studie earnestly to doe our diligence and endeuour.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>