<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In laudem Authoris.</title>
           <author>O., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110060_Fr1_4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18202</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110060</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In laudem Authoris.</title>
                 <author>O., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>New English Canaan or New Canaan : Containing an abstract of New England, composed in three bookes. The first booke setting forth the originall of the natives, their manners and customes, together with their tractable nature and love towards the English. The second booke setting forth the naturall indowments of the country, and what staple commodities it yealdeth. The third booke setting forth, what people are planted there, their prosperity, what remarkable accidents have happened since the first planting of it, together with their tenents and practise of their church. Written by Thomas Morton of Cliffords Inne gent, upon tenne yeares knowledge and experiment of the country</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Greene, Charles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>188, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>In laudem Authoris.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>' Excuse the Author ere the worke be shewne</l>
   <l>Is accusation in it selfe alone,</l>
   <l>And to commend him might seeme over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight,</l>
   <l>So divers are th' opinions of this age,</l>
   <l>So quick and apt, to taxe the moderne stage,</l>
   <l>That hard his taske, is that must please in all</l>
   <l>Example have wee from great Caesars fall,</l>
   <l>But is the sonne to be dislik'd and blam'd,</l>
   <l>Because the mole is of his face asham'd,</l>
   <l>The fault is in the beast not in the sonne</l>
   <l>Give sicke mouthes sweete meates fy they relish none,</l>
   <l>But to the sound in censure he commends,</l>
   <l>His love unto his Country his true ends,</l>
   <l>To modell out a Land of so much worth,</l>
   <l>As untill now noe traveller seth forth,</l>
   <l>Faire Canaans second selfe, second to none,</l>
   <l>Natures rich Magazine till now unknowne,</l>
   <l>Then here survay, what nature hath in store,</l>
   <l>And graunt him love for this, he craves no more.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. O. Gen.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>