<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           <author>L., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110823_Fr10_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21651</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110823</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>L., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Du Bartas his deuine weekes and workes translated: and dedicated to the Kings most excellent Maiestie by Iosuah Syluester</title>
                 <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 697, 6, 698-819, 47, 87, 9 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, portraits (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="455"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erceiuing our diuine <hi>du BARTAS</hi> so gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally applauded, euen of the greatest and the grauest of this Kingdome; and all <hi>His workes</hi> so welcome vnto all: to make the same (<hi>in this second Edition</hi>) more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, I haue presumed to annex <hi>This Peece;</hi> indeed no part of his incomparable <hi>WEEKS</hi> (neither heer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralled by the same Workman) yet doubt-les a Child of the same Parent, and (if I be not deceiued) one of his first borne: which arriuing long-since in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was there (among the rest) royally receiued, and thus (as you see) suited, somewhat to that Countrie fashion. Whose <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> and <hi>Orthography</hi> (considering vnder what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie it was first published, &amp; now the rather respecting our happie vnion by the same established) I haue not dar'd at all to alter. Accept it therefore (gentle Reader) as it is: and allow at least of my good will; who, wishing thee the profit of these happy labours, haue aduentured (to doo thee pleasure) to incur (I doubt) double displeasure.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine, H. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>