<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Admonitions to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110036_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07721</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18105</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110036</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Admonitions to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The perfection of horse-manship, drawne from nature; arte, and practise. By Nicholas Morgan of Crolane, in the countye of Kent, Gent</title>
                 <author>Morgan, Nicholas, of Crolane</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 188, 191-255, 266-272, 4, 273-288, 288-295, 295-343, 144-145, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>Admonitions to the Reader.</head>
   <p>FIrst read, but not with preindicate opinion, remembring that he which hastily iudgeth, speedily repenteth: <hi>Tamen si iudicare velis, sic iudica, quasi mox ab alioiudicandus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. Secondly, read all from the first word to the last, and do it not cursorily or speedily, but aduisedly and with deliberation: for a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sory and tumultuary reading, doth euer make a confused memory, a troubled vtterance, and an incertaine iudgement: and therefore he that will mount high, must ascend by degrees.</p>
   <p n="3">3. Thirdly, read not with much intermission of time, neither at any time much, least when ye read the last part, you haue forgotten the first. <hi>Nam quo se plus recepit animus, hoc se magis laxat:</hi> for the more the minde sudainly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, the more it looseth and fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth it selfe.</p>
   <p n="4">4. Fourthly, read it often although you finde <hi>Paruum in magno,</hi> when it should haue bene <hi>magnum in paruo:</hi> because <hi>Ars longe, vita breuis,</hi> a great taske but a short time: which don, make
<pb facs="14"/>practise of your knowledge, for eueryman must first study before he begin to dispute.</p>
   <p n="5">5. Fiftly, esteeme not your selfe to know all when you know a litle: for the Synecodoche &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue knowledge (taking part for the whole) is no other then to haue the tongue only tipped with the words of Art, but no iudgement in the Art, for it fareth with mens fantasie, as it doth with their eie sight in an vnequal distance from the obiect, which being far remoued from their grosse and narrow capacitie, it commeth into their conceit as things of little moment; which if their dim &amp; weake sight were able in the visial line to behold in the deuine nature, they would confesse the surpassing excellency, &amp; exceeding difficulty: but the not acknowledging their own ignorance, is the depriuation of the true testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dgement.</p>
   <p n="6">6. Sixtly, because this whole worke taketh his grounds from nature, how to know the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the primary creation, how to breed thē acordingly, &amp; to preserue them in their perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō, &amp; thereby refelleth the errors in the whole Art and practise of Horsemanship, I haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely omitted to ad any marginal directious to stand as Mercuries statues in high waies of olde
<pb facs="14"/>pointing the finger to consequents, or to make any Index or table therof: therefore raise thy hopes (thy only sweet and firme Companion) it is the last thing that leaueth thee and the highest thinges it promiseth thee: it maketh all labors supportable, and all difficulties conquerable, and will euermore remaine vnto thee a sweete Nurse to suckle thy memory till it be strongin it selfe to carry about it the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull burthen of knowledge.</p>
   <p n="7">7 Seauenthly and lastly, it may seeme that I haue made too large a discourse heerein; the cause thereof is, for that no former writer hath euer vnfolded the true secrets of Nature. The same being darke &amp; enigmatical to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō sence, I was enforced to manifest the same by reasons, the which being manifested, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vnderstanding, &amp; then vnderstanding set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth opinion, the which opinion being able to definecertainty of truth, there followeth true iudgement, without which al reading is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Pro capta lectoris habeat sua fata libellis.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>