<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL MY VERY GOOD Brother in Law Tho. Pelham, of Laughton in the Countie of Sussex Esquire, Iustice of the Peace, and one of his Maiesties De∣putie-Leiutennants there: And to my deare Sister in Law Marie Pelham his wife.</title>
           <author>Bright, Timothie</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110958_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15782</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22426</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110958</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL MY VERY GOOD Brother in Law Tho. Pelham, of Laughton in the Countie of Sussex Esquire, Iustice of the Peace, and one of his Maiesties De∣putie-Leiutennants there: And to my deare Sister in Law Marie Pelham his wife.</title>
                 <author>Bright, Timothie</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>VVitts nevv dyall: or, A schollers prize</title>
                 <author>Sherley, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL MY VERY GOOD Brother in Law <hi>Tho. Pelham,</hi> of <hi>Laughton</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Sussex</hi> Esquire, Iustice of <hi>the Peace, and one of his Maiesties De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie</hi>-Leiutennants there: And to my deare Sister in Law <hi>Marie Pelham</hi> his wife.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue bound me so infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely</hi> vnto you (deare Brother and Sister) that I cannot (for shame) but make some meanes to pay part of the debt: That which I owe to your exceeding kindnesse towardes mee is very great: yet behold (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming you will beare with my good will, at least with my abilitie) I lay downe no more but this, which is very little: Such portion of Witte as it is, I freely bestow vpon you. This infant of my Braine was begot and deliuered vnder your owne roofe; it is therefore fittest there to be nurst vp: and for that purpose I sende it to you both. My louing Sister hath been the mother of seuen Children, and therefore knowes the better how to
<pb facs="3"/> handle this: I pray be neither of you cruell to it, for your good worde, or good looke, makes it prosper; a frowne kils it. I giue you many thankes for my entertainement at your house at <hi>Hawleland,</hi> where (at your cost) I spent almost a yeere, and at mine idle howers, drew this Picture of Poesie. If the cullours be ill layde on, beare with them, for that I am but newly bound to the trade: yet not bound neither; for if you like not my workmanship, I will for euer giue it ouer. Thus hoping you will receiue this poore Gift with as free a hand as I send it, I commende you to God. <hi>Hawleland</hi> this. 18. of October. 1604.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most affectionate Brother in Law, Anthony Sherly.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>