<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧Sir William Pelham
Knight, in commendation of the
discourse following.</title>
           <author>Pelham, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110356_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09213</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19523</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧Sir William Pelham
Knight, in commendation of the
discourse following.</title>
                 <author>Pelham, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trve reporte, of the late discoueries, and possession, taken in the right of the Crowne of Englande, of the new-found landes : by that valiaunt and worthye gentleman, Sir Humfrey Gilbert Knight. Wherein is also breefely sette downe, her highnesse lawfull tytle therevnto, and the great and manifolde commodities, that is likely to grow thereby, to the whole realme in generall, and to the aduenturers in particular. Together with the easines and shortnes of the voyage. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Peckham, George, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hinde, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>74 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>❧Sir William Pelham
Knight, in commendation of the
discourse following.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LIke as the Fishes, breeding in the deepe,</l>
      <l>Through all the Ocean are allowed to raung:</l>
      <l>Nor forst in any certaine boundes to keepe,</l>
      <l>But as their motions carry them to chaung.</l>
      <l>To men like libertie, dooth reason giue:</l>
      <l>In choise of soile, through all the world to liue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To valiaunt mindes each land is a natiue soile,</l>
      <l>and vertue findes no dwelling place amis.</l>
      <l>Regard of honour measures not the toyle,</l>
      <l>To seeke a seat wherein contentment is.</l>
      <l>That seat, that soile, that dwelling place of rest:</l>
      <l>In this discourse, most liuelie is exprest.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Our forren neighbours bordring hard at hand,</l>
      <l>Haue found it true, to many a thousands gaine:</l>
      <l>And are inritcht by this abounding land,</l>
      <l>While pent at home, like sluggard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s we remaine.</l>
      <l>But though they haue, to satisfie their will:</l>
      <l>Inough is left, our cofers yet to fill.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then <hi>England</hi> thrust among them for a share,</l>
      <l>Since title iust, and right is wholie thine:</l>
      <l>And as I trust the sequell shall declare,</l>
      <l>Our lucke no worse, then theirs before hath beene.</l>
      <l>For where the attempt, on vertue dooth depend:</l>
      <l>No doubt but God, will blesse it in the ende.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>VVilliam Pelham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>