<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right VVorshipfull,
his verie good friend and Benefactor, M. Henrie
Mordant, sonne and sole heire to the right Hono∣rable
the Lord Mordant, Francis Sabie
wisheth full fruition of externall
and internall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Sabie, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110764_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11269</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21535</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110764</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right VVorshipfull,
his verie good friend and Benefactor, M. Henrie
Mordant, sonne and sole heire to the right Hono∣rable
the Lord Mordant, Francis Sabie
wisheth full fruition of externall
and internall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Sabie, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fissher-mans tale : of the famous actes, life and loue of Cassander a Grecian knight. Written by Francis Sabie</title>
                 <author>Sabie, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right VVorshipfull,
his verie good friend and Benefactor, M. Henrie
Mordant, sonne and sole heire to the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
the Lord Mordant, Francis Sabie
wisheth full fruition of externall
and internall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bashed (right Worshipfull) at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie
of your greatnesse, astonished
at the reporte of your prudence: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted
notwithstanding, at the remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance
of your acustomed clmencie: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated
at the consideration of your
excellent vertue: more confidentlie doe I present vnto
your Worship these few vntutord lines, the trauell of
my rude Mule, and vntimelie fruites of my first spring.
The ground where they grew, as it needed much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuring,
and diligent tillage, euen so the Gardener to
make amendes, was none of the skilfullest, but lacked
that cunning which riper yeares and longer experience
might peraduenture haue supplyed, whereby the fruit,
which otherwise would haue bene delicate, be changed
and turned to meere wildings. Yet considering that the
stomacke ouercloyd with daintie and sweete iunkets, is
oft times very much recreated with meaner and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher
meats: So your Worship sometime wearied with
high and serious affaires, may at length vouchsafe to
cast a glaunce vpon these my vnlettered poemes, which
<pb facs="3"/>
wil perhaps bring no lesser content than delectation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
your graue and stayed mind, vnto whome, and vnto
whose noble predecessours, I do acknowledge me and
my weake parentes so much to bee and haue bene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted,
that should the gods allot vnto the tearme of my
life, <hi>Nestors</hi> yeares, bestowe vpon me <hi>Croesus</hi> wealth,
and endue me with <hi>Tullies</hi> elequence, yet were I neunr
able with long endeuour, incessiue giftes, or finenesse
of Oratorie, to make satisfaction, requite, or set foorth
halfe that praise and dutie, which is of me, to you to be
perfourmed, for so great and so many inestimable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites:
should I goe about to rehearse them, I shoulde
vndertake a matter as hard to be compassed, as is <hi>Aetna</hi>
to be remooued. These rude lines, penned at vacant
houres, partly to shun the vntolerable crime of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
partly to make known in some measure, my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
dutie, I haue presented to your Worship, praying
you to vouchsafe them your acceptance', as <hi>Alexander</hi>
did of a cup of cold water, offered vnto him of a simple
man, which not doubting of, I hope hereafter I shall be
better able to present your Worship with some polisht
and profitable peece of my trauell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships euer at
comandement
FRANCIS SABIE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>