<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110019_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07627</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18021</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110019</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>1607 Lamentable newes out of Monmouthshire in VVales : Contayning, the wonderfull and most fearefull accidents of the great ouerflowing of waters in the saide countye, drowning infinite numbers of cattell of all kinds, as sheepe, oxen, kine and horses, with others: together with the losse of many men, women and children, and the subuersion of xxvi parishes in Ianuary last 1607</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, when these newes were brought, &amp; an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie vsed to me, that I would giue thē some forme, &amp; bestow an exhortation on them, I was vnwilling, both in regard of that short space (of lesse then one day which was limited to vndertake the matter) and also in respect of the vsual vnfaithfullnes of men ordinarily in reporting of such accidents as these bee: whereby it often falleth out, that the relater of them reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much discredit. But when I could not haue these iust excuses taken, I began and finished this businesse, as the shorte
<pb facs="3"/>
space wold permit me. And now I offer it vnto thee, read it with that good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherewith I doe present it, and I am sure, it both may and will profit thee by putting thee in remembrance why God doth punish others, that so thou maist thy selfe in time looke vnto thine own courses, least he proceed in the same or some more grieuous maner with thee: for our vices are the serpēts of our soules, stinging them to death, vnlesse we looke vp vnto him that was nailed vppon the Crosse, that so we may be cured of them, &amp; be brought to forsake and relinquish them. Well then, seeing that it is meere wickednesse to change or alter good lawes, to awake strife, or wilfully to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it; to abate nobility, &amp; exalt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; to banish gods seruants, and to
<pb facs="3"/>
honour the gracelesse; to loue flatterers and dispraise the vertuous &amp; plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; to imbrace delights and pastimes, &amp; neglect works of duty and office, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count vanitie a mother, and pure religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a step-mother; &amp; in a word to regard nothing but idlenesse, riot, and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; and that the Lord vseth from time to time, to reueale his wrath from heauen against these and such like impieties: the Lord of his goodnes purge our land dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more and more, from such of them as doe beare anye rule in it: that so Gods indgements bring auerted, wee may haue his mercies continually mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed vpon vs and ourpost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eritie, vnto the worlds end.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>Farwell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>