<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110483_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09766</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20032</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110483</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The secrets and wonders of the world : A booke right rare and straunge, containing many excellent properties, giuen to man, beastes, foules, fishes and serpents, trees, plants &amp;c. Abstracted out of that excellent naturall historiographer Plinie. Translated out of French into English</title>
                 <author>Pliny, the Elder</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere hast thou gentle Reader, set forth vnto thee this Booke, named <hi>The Secrets and wonders of the Worlde,</hi> abstracted out of the sixteene first Bookes of that excellent naturall Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher <hi>Plinie,</hi> for the straungenesse and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse thereof, I referre thee to thine owne iudgement, requesting thee to take this in good part, &amp; shortly shalbe by Gods grace, set forth vnto thee three worthy and learned bookes, the first is of the Cituation of the world, writte by <hi>Pomponius Mela,</hi> The second is a perfite Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grination and true discouerie of <hi>Graecie, Turkey, Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Siria,</hi> with the maner of their Cities, and their Antiquities: The third is, <hi>Iulius Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Pollihistorie,</hi> the which bookes thou shalt finde both to be pleasant and profitable, And thus I bid thee farewel in Christ, who keep vs. Amē.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>