<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VVORTHY and Iudicious Gentleman, ROBERT GARSET Esquire.</title>
           <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110169_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08255</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18590</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110169</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VVORTHY and Iudicious Gentleman, ROBERT GARSET Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scourge of corruption. Or A crafty knaue needs no broker. Written by Anthony Nixon</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Holmes (Houlmes), William 4</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VVORTHY and Iudicious Gentleman, ROBERT GARSET Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, if you onely looke vpon the Title of this little Booke, you will (perhaps) maruell that I am so bold to make pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of it vnder your Name, it brings so harsh a name with it: But if you be pleased to looke further into the substance, I hope you will giue it a kinde intertainement. For I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that course in it, not to be offensiue to any. But if (through mistaking) some shal thinke themselues touched: it proceedeth rather from their owne corruption, then plaine meaning: and in this humble tender of my loue vnto you, I doe but play the ill debtor, who kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that hee is scarce able to ensconce himselfe against beggery, yet goes wilfully into further dangers, in hope to finde pitty at the hands of his Creditors, trusting vpon mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation or forbearance, till hee bee better able to make sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: Euen so as I confesse my selfe bound to you, for some benefits receiued; and being vnable to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence I haue aduentured to cast my selfe into further perill; in hope to be relieued by your wonted fauour, and
<pb facs="3"/>
to haue my boldnesse remitted by your generous respects, to which I wholy submit my selfe.</p>
   <p>For I set before your eies a mixt banquet of sweet, and sower, mirth and mourning, <hi>Seria cum iocis.</hi> If it be not so good as you deserue, nor so rich as I could wish it, I must intreat you to blam the vanity of our times, which affoord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> no better <hi>condimenta</hi> or seasonings: I know you loue to reade▪ for that you know to censure: Reade then, as it is writ (willingly) and censure as it is sent (in loue:) Beare with the hard fauourdnesse of the Title: For <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> are not vnderualued by their roughnesse when they are vncut. Nor can it be shame to gather a violet, though it grow close to the ground. As I haue better, you shall enioy it; Such as it is, if you be pleased to embrace it, I shall rest▪</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>In the best of obseruantes deuoted yours</hi> Anthony Nixon,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>