<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE MOST EXCEL∣lent and most mighty Princesse Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of England Fraunce and Ireland QVEENE, Defendresse of the Fayth, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110231_Fr2_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08452</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18777</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110231</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE MOST EXCEL∣lent and most mighty Princesse Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of England Fraunce and Ireland QVEENE, Defendresse of the Fayth, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The valiant actes and victorious battailes of the English nation: from the yeere of our Lord, one thousand three hundred twentie and seuen: being the first yeare of the raigne of the most mightie Prince Edvvard the third, to the yeere 1558. Also, of the peaceable and quiet state of England, vnder the blessed gouernement of the most excellent and vertuous Princesse Elizabeth: a compendious declaration written by C.O. And newly translated out of Latine verse into English meeter. By I.S</title>
                 <author>Ocland, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE MOST <hi>EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and most mighty Princesse</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>by the</hi> grace of God, of England Fraunce and Ireland QVEENE, <hi>Defendresse of the Fayth, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Enowmed Nimph, of <hi>Britaine</hi> land, the guidance great, &amp; staie,</l>
      <l>Which dost most glorious shine in peace, &amp; true religious waie</l>
      <l>Which glittering in thy liues deserts, &amp; manners radiant light,</l>
      <l>Exceld'st <hi>Zenobia,</hi> or if one excelled her, by right,</l>
      <l>In rule which <hi>Iuno, Uenus</hi> faire in forme, <hi>Minerue</hi> in art</l>
      <l>Expressest, and more virtue shrinst, then female sexe in hart:</l>
      <l>Come fauorable, happie slide, to these attempts of myne,</l>
      <l>Thy gratious looke (O goddesse) shall, as power of godhead shine.</l>
      <l>The worke is hard, I may not prop so huge, and vast a molde,</l>
      <l>Lesse with thy friendly aspect, thou (mee goddesse) do behold</l>
      <l>Looke friendlye, (goddesse bright) and see, what hard exploites of yore.</l>
      <l>Thy great forefathers haue atchieu'd, three hundred yeares and more.</l>
      <l>Whose royall chaier, and Diademe, since thou (O nimphe) sustaines,</l>
      <l>Their glory wonnne in bruntes of Mars, vnto thy laude remaines,</l>
      <l>Nor tis vnmeete fearce battailes, to a virgin to expresse,</l>
      <l>Then pleasaunt peace, the brunts of wars did <hi>Pallas</hi> please no lesse.</l>
      <l>Therfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> this work (most worthy Queen) with gratious coūtenāce take,</l>
      <l>Thy iudgement settes mee bolt vpright, or fondred flat doth make,</l>
      <l>Though all men mee abiect, and spurne, I nought them all regarde,</l>
      <l>It is inough, if from my <hi>Muse</hi> thy liking bee not bard,</l>
      <l>God graunt that longe in natiue peace, thou maist enioy the crowne,</l>
      <l>And eke excell thine auncestours, in glory, and renowme.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Your Maiesties most humble and dutifull subiect,</p>
   <p>C. O.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>