<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In the most iust praise of Musicke, this praise∣worthy Worke, and my deare, vertu∣ous, and right pert friend, the most iudicious Author.</title>
           <author>Davies, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110612_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10477</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20756</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In the most iust praise of Musicke, this praise∣worthy Worke, and my deare, vertu∣ous, and right pert friend, the most iudicious Author.</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discourse of the true (but neglected) vse of charact'ring the degrees, by their perfection, imperfection, and diminution in measurable musicke, against the common practise and custome of these times : Examples whereof are exprest in the harmony of 4. voyces, concerning the pleasure of 5. vsuall recreations. 1 Hunting, 2 hawking, 3 dauncing, 4 drinking, 5 enamouring. By Thomas Rauenscroft, Bachelor of Musicke</title>
                 <author>Ravenscroft, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 22, 2, 56 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>In the most iust praise of <hi>Musicke,</hi> this praise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy <hi>Worke,</hi> and my deare, vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>pert friend, the most iudicious <hi>Author.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe ten-fold <hi>Orbes</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> are said to moue</l>
      <l>By <hi>Musicke;</hi> for they make <hi>Harmonious din:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And all the <hi>Powres subordinate</hi> aboue</l>
      <l>Spend <hi>Time,</hi> nay, spend Aeternity therein.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>If <hi>Musicke</hi> then, moue all that <hi>All</hi> doth moue;</l>
      <l>That's not compriz'd in <hi>ALL</hi> that spights her State:</l>
      <l>If not in <hi>ALL,</hi> it's nought; which who doth loue</l>
      <l>is worse then nought, to loue what Heau'n doth hate:</l>
      <l>For, <hi>NOVGHT</hi> is nothing; sith it was not made</l>
      <l>By that great <hi>WORD,</hi> without which made was nought:</l>
      <l>Then, if that nought but <hi>NOVGHT</hi> doe her inuade,</l>
      <l>Like God, her goodnesse is surmounting <hi>THOVGHT!</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But no man is so ill that hath no good;</l>
      <l>So, no man in the <hi>Abstract</hi> can be nought:</l>
      <l>Then 'tis no man that hates sweete <hi>Musickes</hi> moode,</l>
      <l>But Some-thing worse then all that can be thought.</l>
      <l>A <hi>Beast?</hi> O no: A <hi>Monster?</hi> neither. Then</l>
      <l>Is it a <hi>Deuill?</hi> Nothing lesse: for, these</l>
      <l>Haue <hi>Beings</hi> with an <hi>Angell,</hi> or a <hi>Man;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But that exists not, that sweete <hi>Notes</hi> displease.</l>
      <l>FORMES, Essence giue to <hi>Man, Beast, Fish, &amp; Fowle;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Then <hi>Men WERE</hi> not, had they no <hi>Soule</hi> (their <hi>Forme</hi>)</l>
      <l>But <hi>Musickes</hi> haters haue no <hi>Forme,</hi> nor <hi>Soule;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>So, they (like <hi>Sinne</hi>) exist but to enorme,</l>
      <l>For, had they <hi>Soules</hi> produc'd in <hi>Harmony,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Or rather Are it selfe (some <hi>Wise</hi> auouch)</l>
      <l>They would be rauishe with her <hi>Suauity,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And turn'd <hi>Coelestiall</hi> with her Heauenly <hi>Touch!</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But, let them goe as more than mortall <hi>Sinne</hi>
      </l>
      <l>'Gainst <hi>Wisedomes</hi> Spirit, not to be forgiuen:</l>
      <l>While thou dost wooe the Soules, which thou dost winne</l>
      <l>With thy sweet <hi>Notes</hi> (deere Friend) to <hi>mind but Heau'n.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Thy <hi>Nature, Manners,</hi> and thy <hi>Notes</hi> doe make</l>
      <l>A Three-fold-Cord, to drawe all hearts it gaines:</l>
      <l>Thy <hi>Musickes Cordes</hi> hold Eares and Eyes awake</l>
      <l>(Yet lullaby in pleasure) with their Straines.</l>
      <l>So, then this latter <hi>Musicke</hi> (though alone)</l>
      <l>'Twixt <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>Thee</hi> doth make an <hi>Vnison,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Through which consent, though <hi>Deaths</hi> clouds thee o'rerun</l>
      <l>Thy glory still shall shine, and cloud the <hi>Sun.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Io: Dauies. Heref:</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>