<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Dauies of Hereford in praise of the Author, and Translator.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110833_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11402</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110833</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Dauies of Hereford in praise of the Author, and Translator.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second day of the First vveeke of the most excellent, learned, and diuine poet, VVilliam, Lord Bartas. Done out of French into English heroicall verse by Thomas VVinter, Maister of Artes</title>
                 <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Shaw, James</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Iohn Dauies</hi> of Hereford in praise of the Author, and Translator.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>WInter,</hi> a man would thinke thy works are cold,</l>
      <l>That did but heare thy name, or know thy kind,</l>
      <l>But yet such heate this worke of thine doth hold,</l>
      <l>As in a Sommers day we scarce shall find</l>
      <l>Among our hote-brain'd <hi>Poets.</hi> Thou hast hit</l>
      <l>Vpon that heate (though with another fire)</l>
      <l>That did enflame the rarest <hi>Poets</hi> wit,</l>
      <l>That ere in <hi>France (worlds</hi> garden) did respire.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Bartas,</hi> the bosome of whose blessed <hi>Muse</hi>
      </l>
      <l>With <hi>Homers</hi> sacred fire (refin'd) did burne:</l>
      <l>Did (as should seeme) into thy breast infuse</l>
      <l>That fire by touching him; for thou dost turne</l>
      <l>His heate to thine, and thine to his, if so</l>
      <l>Both in this Tract translated thou dost show.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>His opinion Touching translators, and translation.</head>
      <l>TO turne one tongue t'another is a tricke</l>
      <l>That many tongues-men can in prose performe;</l>
      <l>But when the tongues on numbred feete do sticke,</l>
      <l>It's hard two tongues discordant to conforme.</l>
      <l>Who word for word, and phrase for phrase translates</l>
      <l>In verse, may vaunt he earnes his <hi>Authors</hi> fame:</l>
      <l>But, but few tongues are tyde t'our English pates,</l>
      <l>That can with ease directly do the same.</l>
      <l>Many translators haue we, but not many</l>
      <l>That turne not th' Authors meaning with his words.</l>
      <l>Famous were England if she had not any,</l>
      <l>That to them selues such libertie affords.</l>
      <l>To translate so, is to adulterate:</l>
      <l>And all Adulterers God and men do hate.</l>
   </lg>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Omne bonum, Dei donum.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>