<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A priuate Epistle of the Author to
the Printer.</title>
           <author>Nashe, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110095_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08006</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18373</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110095</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A priuate Epistle of the Author to
the Printer.</title>
                 <author>Nashe, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pierce Penilesse his supplication to the diuell. Written by Tho. Nash, Gent</title>
                 <author>Nash, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_printer">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A priuate Epistle of the Author to
the Printer.</head>
   <argument>
      <p>Wherein his full meaning and purpose (in publishing
this Booke) is set foorth.</p>
   </argument>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aith I am verie sorrie (Sir) I am thus
vnawares betrayed to infamie. You
write to me my book is hasting to the
second impression: he that hath once
broke the Ice of impudence▪ need not
care how deepe he wade in discredit. I
confesse it to be a meer toy, not deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
any iudicial mans view: If it haue
found any friends, so it is, you knowe
very wel that it was abroad a fortnight ere I knewe of it, &amp;
vncorrected and vnfinished, it hath offred it selfe to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
scorne of the world. Had you not beene so forward in
the republishing of it, you shold haue had certayne Epistles
to Orators and Poets, to insert to the later end; As namely,
to the Ghost of <hi>Macheuill,</hi> of <hi>Tully,</hi> of <hi>Ouid,</hi> of <hi>Roscius,</hi> of <hi>Pace</hi>
the Duke of Norfolks Iester; and lastly, to the Ghost of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert
Greene,</hi> telling him, what a coyle there is with pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
on him after his death. These were prepared for <hi>Pierce
Penilesse</hi> first setting foorth, had not the feare of infection
detained mee with my Lord in the Countrey.</p>
   <p>Now this is that I woulde haue you to do in this second e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;
First, cut off that long-tayld Title, and let mee not
in the forefront of my Booke, make a tedious Mountebanks
Oration to the Reader, when in the whole there is nothing
praise-worthie.</p>
   <p>I heare say there bee obscure imitators, that goe about to
frame a second part to it, and offer it to sell in Paules Church-yard,
and elsewhere, as from mee. Let mee request you (as
euer you will expect any fauour at my hands) to get some bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to write an Epistle before it, ere you set it to sale againe,
importing thus much; that if any such lewde deuise intrude
it selfe to their hands, it is a coseanage and plaine knauery of
him that sels it to get mony, and that I haue no manner of
interest or acquaintance with it. Indeed if my leysure were,
such as I could wish, I might haps (halfe a yeare hence) write
<pb facs="3"/>
the returne of the <hi>Knight of the Post</hi> from he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, with the <hi>Deuils</hi>
answer to the <hi>Supplication:</hi> but as for a second part of <hi>Pierce
Penilesse,</hi> it is a most ridiculous rogery.</p>
   <p>Other news I am aduertised of, that a scald triuial lying pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet,
cald <hi>Greens groats-worth of wit</hi> is giuen out to be of my
doing. God neuer haue care of my soule, but vtterly renoūce
me, if the least word or sillable in it proceeded from my pen,
or if I were any way priuie to the writing or printing of it. I
am growne at length to see into the vanity of the world more
than euer I did, and now I condemne my selfe for nothing so
much, as playing the dolt in Print. Outvpon it, it is odious,
specially, in this moralizing age, wherein euery one seeks to
shew himselfe a Polititian by mis-interpreting. In one place
of my Booke <hi>Pierce Penilesse</hi> saith, but to the Knight of the
Post, <hi>I pray how might I call you,</hi> &amp; they say I meant one <hi>Howe,</hi>
a Knaue of that trade that I neuer heard of before. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti
quaries are offended without cause, thinking I goe about
to detract from that excellent profession, when (God is my
witnesse) I reuerence it as much as any of them all, and had
no manner of allusion to them that stumble at it. I hope they
wil giue me leaue to think there be fooles of that Art as well
as of al other; but to say I vtterly condemne it as an vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
studie, or seeme to despise the excellent qualified partes
of it, is a most false and iniurious surmise. There is nothing
that if a man list he may not wrest or peruert, I cannot forbid
anie to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nke villainously, <hi>Sed caueat emptor,</hi> Let the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter
beware: for none euer hard me make Allegories of an
idle text. Write who wil against me, but let him look his life
be without scandale: for if he touch me neuer so litle, Ile be
as good as the Blacke Booke to him &amp; his kindred. Beggerly
lyes no beggerly wit but can inuent: who spurneth not at
a dead dogge? but I am of anothermettal, they shall know
that I liue as their euil Angel, to haunt them world without
end, if they disquiet me without cause. Farewell, and let me
heare from you as soone as it is come forth. I am the Plagues
prisoner in the Country as yet: if the sicknesse cease before
the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>irde impression. I wil come and alter whatsoeuer may
be offensiue to any man, and bring you the latter ende.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend, Tho. Nash.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>