<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Christian Reader is intreated by the Author, be∣fore he reade these Treatises, to amend with his pen the faults which in his absence have escaped in the printing of them.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110126_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20732</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7114</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110126</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Christian Reader is intreated by the Author, be∣fore he reade these Treatises, to amend with his pen the faults which in his absence have escaped in the printing of them.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The covenant of grace or An exposition upon Luke 1. 73.74.75. By George Downame Doctour of Divinity, and Bishop of Dery</title>
                 <author>Downame, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 414, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="214"/>
   <head>The Christian Reader is intreated by the Author, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he reade these Treatises, to amend with his pen the faults which in his absence have escaped in the printing of them.</head>
   <p>The letters l. af. doe signifie, linea a fine, &amp; there you are to reckon from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the page.</p>
   <p>PAge 2, Line 15. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p 4. l .8. <hi>Moses.</hi> p. 9. in the title of the page. The <hi>Parties to.</hi> p. 11. l, 13. oath. l. 20.. Christ. p. 13. in the title of the page. The <hi>end of Gods Oath.</hi> l. a fine 8. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 14. l, 14. sinning: l. 11. we see it <hi>practised</hi> by. p. 19. l. af. 5. us, <hi>as</hi> that. p. 21. l. 22. who <hi>were</hi> not. p. 25. l. 5. the keeping. l. 7, <hi>suck.</hi> l. af 6. to hope. p, 28. l. 6. The thing p. 29. l, 17. that as men <hi>deprived</hi> l. 19. Covenant, by p. 31. l ult. spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. p. 32. l. 20. captivatum. l, 21. adiutum{que} l. a f. 5. was, <hi>because he did</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 37. l. 10. they also are his <hi>sonnes,</hi> p, 39. l. af 4. enimyes. p. 40 l. 21. God: p. 41. ad lin. penult. adde in Margin. 1. Cor. 1.30 p. 42 l. 7 re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived: p. 43. l. a f, 4. Deus est: l. penult. therefore without measure if it were possible, <hi>we ought to love him. But though we cannot doe so,</hi> yet we ought to love him withall our heart. p. 49. l. 6.5.4.5. p. 55. l. ult that we shall p. 58. l. 17. fruit: p. 59. Dele <hi>Chap. V l.</hi> p. 60. l. a f. 11. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 65. and 66. and 67. in the title of the pages <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. p. 68. in the title and l. 1. read Chap. 7. p. 71. l. 14. <hi>cōmending</hi> l. 13. feare of God. p 75. l. 2. by w. y p. 77.78.79.80, 85.86.87.88.89.90.91. in the title <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. p. 93. l. 5. Apostles l. ult. or of Know l. p. 99. l. 10 when <hi>men</hi> p. 101. l. a f 4. <hi>formall</hi> syll. p. 104. l. af. 10. exception. p. 106. l. 5. Si credit—non sicut corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra —Non l. 10. <hi>Epist.</hi> l. af. 6. conclusions, p. 108. in marg. l. 8. Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. 3.18. l. 10. Iohn 20,28. l. 18. untruth: p. 113. l. 6. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> 14.2. p. 115. l. 6. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, 118. l. 10. <hi>meere</hi> vanityes. p. 122. l. 9. Emeth 123. l. 9. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete, l. 11.2. Chron. 15.12. p. 136. in marg. l. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 142. l. 14. Inferiors p. 143. l. 3. as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> stat, p. 144. l. 12. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>he</hi> p 153. l. li. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. 7. revellings (<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. 16. Evill) all within thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> parenthesis should have ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>set in the margent. And in the texts after revellings these words should have immediately followed <hi>or rather ryotings,</hi> l 15. (and so l. 18. compotations) all within this parenthesis should also have bene set in the margent, l. 18. and such like, of p. 163. l. 16. drawing <hi>forth</hi> p. 164. l. af. 5. <hi>an</hi> instr. p. 174. l. 2. seeming <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oath</hi> to p. 177. l 18, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffect. p. 181. l. 10, <hi>there</hi> is l. af. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 182. l. 10. a moto p. 183. l. af. 11. then p. 188. l. a. f. 12. pretended p. 192. l. af. 3. for <hi>perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y</hi> read <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssiduity</hi> p. 193. l. af. 12. corrept. in marg. l. 8. De Corrept. l. 15. deleta l. 16. iniquitate p. 197. l. 3. since I wrote this discourse, there l.
<pb facs="215"/>
16. sanctification. p. 198. l. 1. properly l. 5. omit I say, l. 7. order p. 201. l. af. 10. As therefore men are first conceived before they be borne, and they are borne before p. 203. l. af. 6. fide <hi>spe</hi> l. af. 4. Genev. in marg. l. 4. regenerari. p. 208. l. 19. actuall possession l. 21. hathever l. af. 7. are actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally 212. l. af. 3. thus it seemeth to be used Iohn 14.1. p. 216. l. 17. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they <hi>have</hi> not l. af. 4. et 5. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 217. l. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 220. l. 18. Hereupon p. 222. l. 3. in their owne <hi>sence</hi> l. af. 12. matter. p. 223. l. 4. to <hi>this</hi> newe l. 10. salvation. p. 224. l. penult. dele <hi>for</hi> p. 225. l. 8. how <hi>the</hi> ibid. direction l. af. 9. him p. 226. l. ult. <hi>truth</hi> marg. l. 1.1. Ioh. 2.1. l. 3. Iohn 5.33. p. 227. l. 14. oppose, l. 19. thereof. p. 228. l. 4. dele <hi>of</hi> l. af. 4. who, as l. penult. Papists 229. l. 17. er l. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 231. l. 5. actus. Pag. 236. l. 11. <hi>and</hi> yet l. 16, Convertuntur l. af. 3. fig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e 238. marg. l. 13. crescendo l. ult. marg. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 239. l. af. 13. Christians, l. af. 12. or not. Marg. l. 1.2. Tim. 1.9. p. 241. marg. l. 6. Pro. 10.30. l. 13. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erint. l. af. 5. avolent p. 242. marg. l. 3. decedere l. af. 12. solidari 243. marg. l. 6. diceretur l. 14. filiorum l. af. 14. rudib. l. af. 9. operis imperfecti, l. af. 3. for 11. in the text note * marg. l. af. 3. Moral. p. 244. marg. l. 1. sterni l. 6. sanctitatem l. 10. ut quis l. 12. amittat p. 245. Marg. l. 1. Gen. 4.26. &amp; 6.2. p. 246. marg. l. 17. vivificavit l. 18. <hi>aut</hi> ab eo <hi>ipso,</hi> aut l. af. 8. whether p. 247. l. 6. <hi>as</hi> well. penul. or c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lling p. 249. l. 4. deserved. p. 250. marg. l. 6. vocavit, l. 8. caepit p. 251. ad lin. 12. pone in Margen. Act. 11.18. l. 14. salubrem l. ult. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. af. 3. in the text read 2. Tim. 1.9. p. 252. marg. l. 21. &amp; 24. quisquam l. 22. perit p. 253. marg. l. 11. perseverantia l. af. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>7. rectè ad lin. 11. in marg. pone <hi>Moral.</hi> in ipsa lin. 11. Charitie marg. l. a f. 10. De triplici cohaerent. p. 255. l. af. 4. vessels. marg. l. 7.9 Eph. 1.4. l. 10. Prosper p. 256. marg. l. 2. Lam. 3.22. p. 257. l. 3. Psalmist marg. l. 7, Lam. 3.33. l. penult. Lam. 3.32. l. ult. Habac. 3. 2. p. 258. l. 9. saved. p. 259. l. a f 7. perished p. 260. l. 4. repentāce l. af. 13. quod non ita p. 261. l. 18. worldly marg. l. af. 4.1. Iohn, 2.16. l. penult. Col. 3.5. p. 263. l. af. 5. <hi>u</hi> this marg. l. 6. art. 12. p. 264. l. 4. fides <hi>est</hi> id. l. 6. signification p. 265. l. af. 9. is <hi>noe</hi> l. a f. 7. <hi>is</hi> it. l. af. 5. have <hi>this</hi> marg. l. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. 7. Theoph. Oecum. l. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. 11. apud Oecū. l. af. 7. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. af. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. af. 4. <hi>de</hi> quo l. penult. Gennadius apud Oecum in 1. Cor. 13.2.266. l. 14. conversation. p. 267. l. 3. as if there l. 13. spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall. l. 15. threatnings. p. 268. l. af. 3. <hi>God.</hi> l. ult. <hi>or</hi> too * p. 268. l. af. 4. haec verba (I say some, vnto the word Arimathea) inclusive in the 3d. liue of pag. 269, ponenda sunt in margine. p. 269. l. 3. <hi>of</hi> the rulers. l. 8. with Iohn, 12.42, 43. p. 270. l; 15. faith. p. 271. l. 5.10 pur. p. 272. l. 13. forth <hi>fruit</hi> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g. l. 8. Gal. 5. p. 273. marg. l. 7. credere p. 274. l. af. 12.
<pb facs="215"/>
dele <hi>was</hi> p. 276. l. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> l. 11. his <hi>fall</hi> l. 14. concussum non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussum l. af. 10. of the members marg. l. 2.2. Tim. 1.6. p. 277. l. 5. dele <hi>same</hi> marg. l. af. 4. doctrine facundia p. 278. l. 11. ever. marg. l. 9, nequa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> quam. l. 15. 1. Iohn, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.27. p. 282. marg. l. 11. <hi>ex</hi> Deo. l. 18. verè p. 283. marg. l. 17. Rom. 6.14. p. 284. l. 10. the same he nilleth l. 11.12. nilleth l. 20. sinne. p. 286. l. 6. perpetrated p. 287. l. af. 3. agritudines marg. l. 2. Rom. 8.7. p. 288. l. af. 13. or <hi>of</hi> part. p. 289. l. af. 14. howsoever p. 290. l. af. 7. intercision p. 292. l. af. 13. transient. 295. l. 4. <hi>be</hi> a totall 296. l. 14. heads. p. 296. l. af. 13. <hi>too</hi> w, l. af. 7. Augustine p. 297. l. 3. power: p. 298. marg. l. 5. chap. 2.5.4. p. 299. marg. l. 5. p. 272. l 13. Abraham l. ult. arescit. ad lin. 16. in marg. pone Moral. lib. 25. c. 7. p. 300. l. af. 5. <hi>of</hi> the H. p. 301. l. 6. removed l. af. 10. Iohn, 3.16. l. af. 11. Pet. 2.20. p. 302. l. 13. according l. ult. <hi>in</hi> g. marg. l. penult perdurent p. 303. l. af. 10. sonne marg. l. 5. dona l. ult. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 304. l. af. 15. but I will marg. l. 4: De bono persever. l. 2. c. 2. talis ac tantus erit tunor meus p. 305. l. 15. dryed up. p. 306. l. 3. <hi>in respect whereof</hi> dele comma. p. 307. marg. l. 2. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens p. 309. l. af. 8. separate marg. l. 2. &amp; 3. lib. 4. c. 3. §. Altera l. 4. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus l 9. Iohn, 17. l. 11. orat. 4. contr. Arian. l. ult. c. 12. p. 310. l. af. 7. life, these p. 311. l. ult. afflictiō marg. l. 2.12. p. 313. l. 11. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 317. l. 6. as we p. 318. l. af. 4. once marg. l. 11. Ascet. lin. 2. cap. 9. p. 319. l. 11. ad finem marg. l. 12. quaest. 52. ad Orosium. p. 321. l. 11. exclude p. 323. l. 3, faithfull. l. 8. throughly and wholly marg. l. 3. chap. 7. §. 3. p. 324. marg. l. 2. Mar. 16.16. p. 325. marg. l. 4. Iohn. 6.54. p. 327. l. 3. <hi>we</hi> proving marg. l. 1. chap. 3. §. 1. p. 329. l. af. 5. Charitie marg. l. 6. chap. 6. §. 2. p. 330. l. 6. away. yea p. 345. l. 8. gifts l. penult. which is <hi>the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> of the elect. marg. l. 6. afferant l. 10.1. Iohn. 2.19. l. ult. 22.24. p. 346. l. af. 4. cooling p. 356. l. 15. chap. 3. §. 1. p. 357. l. 12. never had marg. l. 1 chap. 3. §. 6. p. 358. l. af. 14. to have <hi>lost</hi> justif. marg. l. 14. Espencaeus l. 16. conscientia p. 366. l. 14. away from God dele <hi>fall</hi> p. 367. l. 5. remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>with</hi> us marg. l. pen. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 368. marg. l. pen. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>69. marg. l. 4. forma p. 370. l. 12. within him p. 372. marg. l. af. 6. cap. 9. p. 377, l. af. 3. diseased members. p. 379. l. 8. cadant: p. 380. l. 9. cantu{que} p. 381. marg. l. 15. <hi>vidit</hi> p. 382. marg. l. 3. Moral. lib. 25. cap. 16. p. 386. marg. l, 6. <hi>eos</hi> p. 390. l. 11. <hi>or</hi> by p. 391. l. af. 12. Mediation p. 393. l. 4. Elect <hi>onely</hi> marg. l. 11. dimittit p. 394. marg. l. 2.1. l. 11. in Ps. 77. l. af. 8. sunt p. 397. l. 9. habits 399. l. 2. to <hi>the</hi> l. 7. transgressions l. af. 10. made p. 402. marg. l. 4. c. 3.404, marg. l. 8. illel. 12 c. 23. p. 408, l. 11. perseverance and salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of p. 409. l. af. 12. we doe not.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>