<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader</title>
           <author>Nicholl, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110152_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14999</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18532</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110152</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader</title>
                 <author>Nicholl, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An houre glasse of Indian newes. Or A true and tragicall discourse, shewing the most lamentable miseries, and distressed calamities indured by 67 Englishmen, which were sent for a supply to the planting in Guiana in the yeare. 1605 : VVho not finding the saide place, were for want of victuall, left a shore in Saint Lucia, an island of caniballs, or men-eaters in the West-Indyes, vnder the conduct of Captain Sen-Iohns, of all which said number, onely a 11. are supposed to be still liuing, whereof 4. are lately returnd into England. Written by Iohn Nicholl, one of th aforesaid company</title>
                 <author>Nicholl, John, emigrant to Guiana</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, albeit I might be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent how thou censure my doings here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, forasmuch as I haue the thousand strong of my conscience to witnesse with me, that I published this pamphlet with no worse intention then with the verie best namely to make knowne vnto the world the greatnes and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, miraculously shewed vnto vs: yet if it would please thee to think the best, thou shouldst adde vnto my ioy, without any detraction from thy selfe, nay by shewing thy selfe to haue <hi>bonum animum,</hi> thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest perswade me that thou hast <hi>bonam mentem,</hi> for <hi>bona mens, bonus animus,</hi> a good minde, a good thought. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me intreate thee to be one houre in thy life so idle as to abide the running out of this Houre-glasse. Many things wee felt which heere are not to be found, by reason that the desperatenesse of our case deliuered them to neglect, and neglect to obliuion. This that is heere is the iust account of a perfect memorie, tending not to discourage any from attempting the like, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to encourage with the munition of prouidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Praemonitus, praemunitus,</hi> forewarned, well armed. Thus requesting you that my wants may bee supplied in thy gentlenesse: adding then strength to thy goodnesse, when thou meetest with my weakenesse, I bid the heartily farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine to the best of his power:</hi> Iohn Nicholl.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>