<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Orthodoxall and reue∣rent Corrector of staring haires, the sincere &amp;
finigraphicall rarifier of prolixious rough bar∣barisme,
the thrice egregious and censoriall animad∣uertiser
of vagrant moustachios, chiefe scauinger of
chins, and principallquasi conuersant about heads. Head-man of the parish where∣in
he dwells, speciall superuisor of all excrementall su∣perfluities
for Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge, and
(to conclude) a not able and singular benefactor to all
beards in generall, Don Richardo Barbarossa de Cae∣sario;
Tho: Nashe wisheth the highest Toppe of his
contentment and felicitie, and the Shortning of all his
enemies.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110085_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08003</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18369</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110085</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Orthodoxall and reue∣rent Corrector of staring haires, the sincere &amp;
finigraphicall rarifier of prolixious rough bar∣barisme,
the thrice egregious and censoriall animad∣uertiser
of vagrant moustachios, chiefe scauinger of
chins, and principallquasi conuersant about heads. Head-man of the parish where∣in
he dwells, speciall superuisor of all excrementall su∣perfluities
for Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge, and
(to conclude) a not able and singular benefactor to all
beards in generall, Don Richardo Barbarossa de Cae∣sario;
Tho: Nashe wisheth the highest Toppe of his
contentment and felicitie, and the Shortning of all his
enemies.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Haue vvith you to Saffron-vvalden. Or, Gabriell Harueys hunt is vp : Containing a full answere to the eldest sonne of the halter-maker. Or, Nashe his confutation of the sinfull doctor. The mott or posie, in stead of omne tulit punctum: pacis fiducia nunquam. As much to say, as I sayd I would speake with him</title>
                 <author>Nash, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>168 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Orthodoxall and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Corrector of staring haires, the sincere &amp;
finigraphicall rarifier of prolixious rough bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barisme,
the thrice egregious and censoriall animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiser
of vagrant moustachios, chiefe scauinger of
chins, and principall<note n="θ" place="margin">quasi conuersant about heads.</note> Head-man of the parish where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
he dwells, speciall superuisor of all excrementall su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities
for Trinitie Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and
(to conclude) a not able and singular benefactor to all
beards in generall, <hi>Don Richardo Barbarossa de Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sario</hi>;
<hi>Tho: Nashe</hi> wisheth the highest <hi>Toppe</hi> of his
contentment and felicitie, and the Shortning of all his
enemies.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Cute &amp; amiable Dick,
not <hi>Dic mihi Musa
virum,</hi> Musing Dick,
that studied a whole
yeare to know which
was the male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male
of red herrings:
nor <hi>Dic obsecro,</hi>
Dick of all Dickes,
that in a Church where the Organs were defac'd,
came and offred himselfe with his pipe and taber:
nor old Dick of the Castle, that vpon the newes
<pb facs="3"/>
of the losse of <hi>Calis,</hi> went and put a whole
bird-spit in the pike of his buckler: nor Dick
Swash or Desperate Dick, that's such a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Cutter at a chyne of beefe, and deuoures
more meate at Ordinaries in discoursing of his
fraies and deep acting of his sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shing and hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
than would serue halfe a dozen Brewers
Dray-men: nor <hi>Dick of the Cow,</hi> that mad
Demilance Northren Borderer, who plaid his
prizes with the Lord <hi>Iockey</hi> so brauely: but
paraphrasticall gallant Patron Dick, as good a
fellow as euer was Heigh fill the pot hostesse:
curteous Dicke, comicall Dicke, liuely Dicke,
louely Dicke, learned Dicke, olde <hi>Dicke</hi> of
<hi>Lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>field, Iubeo te plurimum saluere,</hi> which is
by interpretation, I ioy to heare thou hast so
profited in gibridge.</p>
   <p>I am sure thou wondrest not a little, what
I meane to come vppon thee so straungelye,
with such a huge dicker of Dickes in a heape
altogether: but that's but to shew the redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of thy honorable Familie, and how af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluent
and copious thy name is in all places,
though <hi>Erasmus</hi> in his <hi>Copia verborum</hi> neuer
mentions it.</p>
   <p>Without further circumstance to make <hi>short,</hi>
(which to speake troth is onely proper to thy Trade)
<pb facs="3"/>
the short and long of it is this, There is
a certaine kinde of Doctor of late very pittifully
growen bald, and thereupon is to be shauen im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,
to trie if that will helpe him: now
I know no such nimble fellow at his weapon in
all <hi>England</hi> as thy selfe, who (as I heare) standst
in election at this instant to bee chiefe <hi>Crowner</hi>
or clipper of crownes in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and yet no
defacer of the Queenes coyne neither: and it is
pittie but thou shouldst haue it, for thou hast
long seru'd as a Clarke in the <hi>crowne</hi> office, and
concluded syllogismes in <hi>Barbara</hi> anie time this
sixteene yeare, and yet neuer metst with anie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall,
except it were some few <hi>french crownes,</hi>
pild Friers crownes, drye shauen, not so much
worth as one of these Scottish horne crownes:
which (thy verie enemies must needes confesse)
were but <hi>bare</hi> wages, (yea as bare as my nayle I
faith) for thy braue desert and dexteritie: &amp;
some such <hi>Thinne</hi> gratuitie or <hi>Haire-loome</hi>
it may be the Doctor may present thee with,
but how euer it <hi>falls,</hi> hath his head or his
hayre the falling sicknesse neuer so, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
more delay, <hi>Of or on,</hi> trimm'd hee must
bee with a trice, and there is no remedie but
thou must needes come and ioyne with me to
giue him the terrible cut.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Wherefore (good <hi>Dick</hi>) on with thy apron, &amp;
arme thy selfe <hi>to set him downe</hi> at the first word:
<hi>Stand to him</hi> I say, and <hi>take him a button lower,</hi>
feare not to shew him a<note n="θ" place="margin">Barbers knacking their fingers.</note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nacke</hi> of thy occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and once in thy life let it be said, that a Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
weares thy<note n="λ" place="margin">Theyr lousy naprie they put about mēs neckes, whiles they are trīming.</note>
      <hi>cloth,</hi> or that thou hast cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d
him to doo pennance, and weare <hi>Haire-cloth</hi> for
his sinnes. Were he as he hath been (I can assure
thee) he would clothe and adorne thee with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
gracious gallant complements, and not a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
tooth that hangs out at thy shop window,
but should cost him an indefinite Turkish armie
of English <hi>Hexameters.</hi> O, he hath been olde
dogge at that drunk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n staggering kinde of verse,
which is all vp hill and downe hill, like the way
betwixt <hi>Stamford</hi> and <hi>Beec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>feeld,</hi> and goes like
a horse plunging through the myre in the deep of
winter, now soust vp to the saddle, and straight
aloft on his tiptoes. Indeed, in old King Harrie
sinceritie, a kinde of verse it is, hee hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oft
in from his minoritie, for as I haue bin faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
informed hee first cryde in that verse in the
verie moment of his birth, and when he was but
yet a fresh-man in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> he set vp<note n="θ" place="margin">
         <hi>Siquis</hi> a bill for any thīg l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st.</note>
      <hi>Siquis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi>
&amp; sent his accounts to his father in those i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Heroicks. Come, come, account of him as
you list, by <hi>Poll</hi> and <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dipoll</hi> I protest, your
<pb facs="4"/>
noble Science of<note n="θ" place="margin">For diuisiō &amp; contraction.</note> decision and contraction is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortally
beholding to him, for twice double his
Patrimonie hath he spent in carefull cherishing &amp;
preseruing his pickerdeuant: and besides a deuine
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>icarly brother of his, called <hi>Astrologicall Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi>
some few yeares since (for the benefit of his
countrey) most studiously compyled a <hi>profound
Abridgement vpon b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ards,</hi> &amp; therein copiously
dilated of the true discipline of peakes, &amp; no lesse
frutelessely determined, betwixt the Swallowes
taile cut, &amp; the round beard like a rubbing brush.
It was my chaunce (O thrice blessed chaunce) to
the great comfort of my Muse to peruse it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
it came but priuately in Print: and for a
more ratefied pasport (in thy opinion) that I haue
read it and digested it, this title it beareth, <hi>a</hi>
      <note n="λ" place="margin">Therfore belike hee gaue it that title, because it was most of it short <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aire his father made ropes of.</note>
      <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of short haire against Synesius and Pieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi>
or rather in more familiar English to expresse
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, a Dash ouer the head against baldnes, verie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
to be obserued of al the <hi>looser</hi> sort, or <hi>loose</hi>
haird sort of yong Gentlemen &amp; Courtiers, and
no lesse pleasant and profitable to be remembred
of the whole Common-wealth of the Barbars.
The Pos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e theretoo annexed, <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> est breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
sua,</hi> as much to say, as Burne Bees and haue
Bees, &amp; hair the more it is cut the more it comes:
lately deuised and set forth by <hi>Richard Haruey,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
the vnluckie Prophet of prodigies. If this may
not settle thy beleefe, but yet thou requirest a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
token to make vp euen money, in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
Dedicatorie thereof to a great Man of this
Land, whom he calls <hi>his verie right honourable
good Lord,</hi> he recounteth his large bounties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed
vppon him, `and talkes of the secret fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours
which hee did him in his Studie or Closet
at Court.</p>
   <p>Heare you Dick, marke you here what a iewell
this learning is: how long wil it be, ere thou stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
thy selfe to the like preserment. No reason I
see, why thou being a Barber shouldst not bee as
<hi>hair-braind</hi> as he. Onely for writing a booke of
beards, in which he had no further experience, but
by looking on his father when he made hairs, hair
lines I meane, and yet not such <hi>lines</hi> of life as a
hangman hath in his hand, but haire lines to hang
linnen on: for that smal demerit (I say) is he thus
aduanced and courted, &amp; from Astrological Dick
raised to bee fauorite Dick. And verie meete it is
he should be so fauored and raisd by high Persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
for before he was as low a Parson or Vicar, as
a man could lightly set ey on.</p>
   <p>With teares be it spoken, too few such lowly
Parsons &amp; Preachers we haue, who laying aside all
worldly encumbrances, &amp; plesant cōuersing with
<pb facs="5"/>
Saint <hi>Austen, Ierome, Chrisostome,</hi> wilbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt
to read a Lecture as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ath done <hi>de lana ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prina,</hi>
(almost as slender a cast subiect as a Catts
smelling haires,) or trauerse the subtile distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
twixt <hi>short cut and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ng taile.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Fie, this is not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ortieth dandiprat part of
the affectionate <hi>Items,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee hath bequeathed on
your mysterie, with fiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>housand other doctrinal
deuotions, hath he adopted himselfe more than a
by founder of your trade, conioyning with his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid
Doctor Brother in eightie eight browne
Bakers dozen of Alman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s.</p>
   <p>In euerie of which fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ous Annals of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oure
windes, vnfallible rules are prescribd for men to
obserue the best time to breed loue-lockes in, and
so to<note n="θ" place="margin">So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e holde, that any place of a mans chin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eeing rubd with a gold rīg beeing heated, will so harden the skin, that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere shall neuer anie haire grow there more.</note> ringle a thorugh hayre for rooting, that
it shall neuer put foorth his sn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yles hornes again:
as also vnder what Planet a man ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e with least
danger picke his tee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to catch the Sun
in such a phisicall Signe, that one may sweat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and
be not a haire the worse.</p>
   <p>But these am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lifications adiourned to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Returne, all the deuoyre Diamond Dick,
which I am in this Epistle of thy daintie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
to expostulate, is no more but this,
that since vnder t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y-redoubted patronage and
<pb facs="6"/>
protection my workes are to haue their royall
<note n="θ" place="margin">
         <hi>Bestellein,</hi> the royallest Passe in Germanie that may bee, onely for Dukes &amp; great princes.</note>
      <hi>Bestellein</hi> and more than common safe conduct
into the world, and that for the Meridian of thy
honour and magnificence they are chiefely eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
&amp; erected, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wouldst brauely mount thee
on thy barbed steed, <hi>alias</hi> thy triumphant barbers
Chaire, and girding thy keene <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ermo</hi> rasour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o
thy side, in stead of a tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>chant Turkish semito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
and setting thy sharpe pointed<note n="λ" place="margin">A lāce an instrumēt to let bloud with.</note> launce in his
rest, be with them at a haires bredth that backbite
and detract me.</p>
   <p>Phlebothomize them, sting them, tutch them
Dick, tutch them, play the valiant man at <hi>Armes</hi>
and let them bloud and spare not; the Lawe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
thee to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it, it will beare no action: and
thou beeing a Barber Surgeon, art priuiledgd to
dresse flesh in Lent, or anie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hing.</p>
   <p>Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>it this be not suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cient to coole the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of
their courage, serch them in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>other vaine, by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging
thy pocket dag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> against them, and let
them smart for it to the proofe.</p>
   <p>Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le thy painted May<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>▪ or more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to tearme it, thy redoubted rigorous horsmans
staffe (which at thy dore as a manifest <hi>signe</hi> thou
hangst forth of thy martiall p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owesse and hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)
on their insolent creasts, that maligne and
despise me, and forbeare not to bring forth all thy
<pb facs="6"/>
brasse p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eces against them. It is well kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>n
thou hast been a Commaunder and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>walkt the round,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d dealt verie <hi>short</hi> and <hi>round</hi>
with all those tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me vnder thy f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngers: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
through the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> deepe, and skirmisht on
the <hi>downes:</hi> wherefore if thou ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>'st them not
downe soundlie, with a hey downe and a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rry,
and doost not s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uffle and <hi>cut</hi> with them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>usti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
<hi>actum est de pudicitia,</hi> I aske of God thou
maist light vpon none but bald-pates till thou di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est.
But I trow thou wilt carry a better pate with
thee, and not suffer any of these indigent old fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shiond
iudgements to carry it away: whose wits
were right stuffe when those loue-letters in rime
were in request &amp; whose capacities n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
their pace, since <hi>Pace</hi> the Duke of <hi>Norfolkes</hi>
foole died. As for the decaied Proctor of <hi>Saffron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walden</hi>
himself, if he wander within the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
of thy indignation, I make no question but of thy
owne accord without any motion of mine, thou
wilt be as ready as any <hi>catchpoule,</hi> out of all <hi>scotch
&amp; notch</hi> to torment him, &amp; deal as <hi>snip snap</hi> snap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishly
with him, as euer he was delt withall since
he first dated letters from his gallerie in <hi>Trinitie
Hall,</hi> not suffring a lowse that belongs to him to
passe thy hands without a <hi>powling</hi> penny, and yet
<pb facs="7"/>
as I shrewdly presage, thou shalt not finde many
powling pence about him neither, except he rob
<hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>le,</hi> empouerish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is spiritual Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car
brother to helpe to pay for his powling, and
he alas, (dolefull foure nobles Curate, nothing so
good as the Confeslo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r of Tyburne, or Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent
of <hi>Pancredge</hi>) hath nitti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ide himselfe
with a dish <hi>rotundè profundè</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ny time this four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene
yeare, to saue charges of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eep-shearing: &amp;
not to make of a thing more than it is, hath scarce
so much Ecclesiasticall liuing in all, as will serue to
buy him cruell strings to his booke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪ and haire
buttons.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I passe not if in tender cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itie and
commiseration of his estate, I adde ten pound &amp;
a purse to his wages and stipend, canuaze hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and
his Angell brother <hi>Gabriell</hi> in ten sheetes of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
and so leaue them to goe hang themselue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪ or
outright to hang draw and quarter them al vnder
one, I care not if I make it eighteen: on that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
in their last wil &amp; restament they bequeath
me eighteene wise words in the way of answere
betwixt them.</p>
   <p>I dare gine my word for them, they will neuer
doe it, no not although it were inioynd to them
in stead of their neck-verse: their whole stock of
wit when it was at the best, beeing but ten Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
<pb facs="7"/>
Hexameter <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> and <hi>a Lenuoy:</hi> where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous</hi>
Dick (without hum drum be it spoken) I
vtterly despai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of them, or not so much despaire
of them, as count them a paire of poore ideots,
b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing not only but also two brothers, two block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads,
two blunderkins, hauing their braines stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t
with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ought but balder-dash, but that they are
the verie botts &amp; the glanders to the gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
the dead Palsie and Apoplexie of the Presse,
<hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he Sarpego</hi> and the <hi>Sciatica</hi> of the 7. Liberall
Sciences, the surfetting vomit of Ladie Vanitie,
the sworne bauds to one anothers vain-glorie: &amp;
to conclude, the most contemptible <hi>Mounsier
Aiaxes</hi> of excrementall conceipts, and stinking
ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nel-rakt vp inuention, that this or anie Age
euer afforded.</p>
   <p>I pry thee surmounting <hi>Don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>el Dick,</hi> whiles
I am in this heate of Inuectiue, let me remember
thee to do this one kindnes more for me, <hi>videli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet,</hi>
when thou hast frizled and scrubd and tickled
the haires sweetly, and that thou hast filcht thy
selfe into an excellent honourable assembly of
sharpe iudiciall fierie wits and fine spirites, bee it
this winter at an Euening tearme, or where-euer,
with all the thundring grace and magnanimous
eloquence that thou hast, put vp this heroycall
Grace in their behalfe, if thou bee not past grace.</p>
   <q>
      <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
         <body>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="8"/>
               <head>A Grace put vp in behalfe of the Harueys.</head>
               <head type="sub">SVpplicat reuerentiis vestris, per Apostrophen, &amp;c.
In English thus.</head>
               <p>MOst humblie sueth to your Reuerences, the reprobate
brace of Brothers of the <hi>Harueys:</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wit, witlesse
<hi>Gabriell</hi> and ruffling <hi>Richard;</hi> That whereas for anie
time this foure and twentie yeare they haue plaid the
fantasticall gub-shites and goose-giblets in Print, and
kept a hatefull scribling and a pamphleting about earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,
coniun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions, inundations, the fearfull blazing
Starre, and the fors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orne Flaxe-wife: and tooke vpon
them to be false Prophets, VVeather-wizards, Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellers,
Poets, Philosophers, Orators, Historiographers,
Mountebankes, Ballet makers, and left no Arte vndefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
with their filthie dull-headed practise: it may please
your VVorships and Masterships, these infidell premisses
considered, &amp; that they haue so fully performed all their
acts in absurditie, impudence, &amp; foolerie, to grant them
their absolute Graces, to commence at <hi>Dawes crosse,</hi> and
with your general subscriptions confirm them for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundest
<hi>Arcandums, Acarnanians,</hi> and Dizards, that
haue been discouered since the Deluge: &amp; so let them passe
throughout the Queenes Dominions.</p>
            </div>
         </body>
      </floatingText>
   </q>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Purposely that space I left, that as manie as I
shall perswade they are <hi>Pache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>es, Poldauisses,</hi>
and <hi>Dringles,</hi> may set their hands to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitiue
sentence, and with the Clearke helpe
to crye <hi>Amen,</hi> to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ternall vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>andsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
   <p>Plie them, plie them vncessantly <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ico Dick,</hi>
euen as a Water-man plies for his Fares, and insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate
and goe about the bush with them, like as
thou art wont to insinuate and go about the griz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
bushie beard of some sauage Saracen Butcher,
and neuer surcea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e flaunting and sirking it in fusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,
till vnder the Vniuersities vnited hand &amp; seale
they bee enacted as <hi>Obsolaete</hi> a case of Cockes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combes,
as euer he was in <hi>Trinitie Colledge,</hi> that
would not carrie his Tutors bow into the field,
because it would not edifie: or his fellow <hi>qui quae
codshead,</hi> that in the Latin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Tragedie of <hi>K. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi>
cride <hi>Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rbs, ad vrbs, ad vrbs,</hi> when
his whole Part was no more, but <hi>Vrbs, vrbs, ad
arma, ad arma.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Shall I make a motion, which I would not
haue thee thinke I induce to flatter thee ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
thou being not in my walke, whereby I
might come to wash my handes with thee a
mornings, or get a sprinkling or a brushing
for a brybe: wilt thou commence, and make
<pb facs="9"/>
no more ado, since▪ thou hast almost as much lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and farre more wit, than the two Brothers,
or eyther of those profound <hi>qui mihi Discipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasses</hi>
aboue mentioned.</p>
   <p>Now merely (I perswade mee) if thou wouldst
attempt it, not all the <hi>Gabriels</hi> betwixt this and
<hi>Godmanchester</hi> put together, wold make a more
perpolite cathedral Doctor than thy selfe: for all
languages at thy fingers ende thou hast as perfect
as <hi>Spruce,</hi> and nere a <hi>Dicke Haruey</hi> or cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall
Doctor of them all, can read a more smooth
succinct <hi>Lipsian</hi> Lecture of short haire, than
thou ouer thy Barbars Chaire, if thou bee so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed,
nor stand and encounter all commers so
constantly.</p>
   <p>Dick, I exhort thee as a brother, be not a horse
to forget thy own worth, thou art in place where
thou maist promote thy selfe, do not close-prison
and eclipse thy vertues in the narrow glasse lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne
of thy Barbers shop, but reflect them vp
and downe the Realme, like to those prospectiue
glasses which expresse not the similitudes they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
neere hand, but cast them in the ayre a farre
off, where they are more clerely represented.</p>
   <p>Commence, commence I admonish thee, thy
merits are ripe for it, &amp; there haue been Doctors
of thy Facultie, as Doctor <hi>Dodipowle</hi> for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
<pb facs="9"/>
and here in <hi>London</hi> yet extant <hi>viu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> voc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> to
testifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Doctor Nott and Doctor Powle,</hi> none
of which in <hi>notting</hi> and <hi>powling</hi> go beyond thee▪
To vtter vnto thee my fancie as touching those
Neoterick tongues thou professest, in whose pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation
old <hi>Tooly</hi> and thou varie as much, as
<hi>Stephen Gardineer</hi> and <hi>Sir Iohn Cheek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> about
the pronunciation of the Greeke tongue: loe,
for a testifying incouragement how much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wish
thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ncrease in those languages, I haue h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> took<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> paines to nit and louze ouer the Doctours
Booke, and though m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> chol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ricke Cookes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<hi>London</hi> in a mad rage haue dismembred it,
and thrust it piping hot into the ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n vnder the
bottomes of do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ts, and impiously prickt the
torne sheetes of it for basting paper, on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
of Geese and ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sting Beefe, to keepe them
from burning▪ yet haue I naturally cherisht it
and hugd it in my bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome, euen as a Carri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r
of <hi>Bosomes Inne</hi> dooth a Cheese vnder his
arme, and the purest <hi>Parm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n</hi> magget Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
therein, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ll'd and pickt out to pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent
thee with.</p>
   <p>Read and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ruse them ouer as di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s
thou wouldst doo a char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e against the tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache:
for this I can gospelly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uouch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o sleight
paynes hath the Doctour tooke in coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>g
<pb facs="10"/>
them, consulting a whole quarter of a yeare with
<hi>Textors</hi> Epithites (which he borrowd of a frend
of mine in Poules Churchyard) onely to pounse
them out more poetically.</p>
   <p>Be not self-wild, but insist in my precepts, and
I will tutour thee so Pythagoreanly how to hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band
them in al companies, that euen <hi>VVilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>
himselfe thy fellow Barber in <hi>Cambridge,</hi>
(who hath long borne the bell for finicall descan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
on the <hi>Crates</hi>) shalbe constrained to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
and offer to thee.</p>
   <p>Abruptly to breake into the bowels of this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex</hi>
of bald inkhornisme, what saist thou for all
thou art reputed such an<note n="θ" place="margin">A rag borrowd from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>wne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>aenigmaticall linguist,</hi>
(vnder the Doctors <hi>terme probatorie</hi> license bee
it spoken, being a terme with him as frequent as
standing vpon termes among lawiers) canst thou
enter into the true nature of <hi>villanie by conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ence?</hi>
I hold a groate thou canst not conster it.
A word it is, that the Doctor lay a whole weeke
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd a day &amp; a night entra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed on his bed to bring
forth, and on the Munday euening late, causd all
the bels in the Parish where he then soiournd, to
be rong forth, for ioy that he was deliuerd of it.</p>
   <p>Repent, and be ashamed of thy rudenesse: O
thou that hast made so manie men winke whyles
thou cast suds in their eyes, and yet knowest not
<pb facs="10"/>
what <hi>Conniuence</hi> meanes. Plodding and dunsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
like a clowne of <hi>Cherry-hinton</hi> basely thou
beseechest them to winke, whiles thou mak'st a
Tennis-court of their faces, by brick-walling thy
clay-balls crosse vp and downe their cheekes:
whereas if thou wert right orthographizd in the
Doctors elocution, thou wouldst say in stead of
I pray Sir winke I must wash you, Sir, by your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
I must require your <hi>conniuence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, it is thy custome being sent for to some
tall old sinckanter, or stigmaticall bearded Master
of Arte, that hath been chin-bound euer since
<hi>Charles</hi> the ninths massacre in <hi>France,</hi> to rush in
bluntly with thy washing bowle and thy nurse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloutes
vnder thy cloake, and after a few scraping
ceremonies, to aske if his Worship bee at leasure
to be recreated.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A malo in peius,</hi> that is the meanest salutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
that ere I heard: vtterly thou bewrayest thy
<hi>non-proficiencie</hi> in the Doctors Paracelsian rop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethorique.
What a pestilence, a yong braine and
so poore and penurious in <hi>Conges?</hi> Rayse thy
conceipt on the trees, or rather than faile new
corke it at the heeles, before it should thus walke
bare-foote vp and downe the streetes.</p>
   <p>Hence take thy Harueticall <hi>exord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um,</hi> if thou
wouldst haue thy conceit the worlds fauourite at
<pb facs="11"/>
first dash <hi>Omniscious and omnisufficient Master
Doctor,</hi> (for so hee calls <hi>Cornelius Agrippa)
will it please you to bee cosmologizd and smirkt.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Suppose a Bishop come to the Vniuersitie, as
the Bishop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> somtimes to visit <hi>Kings
Colledge,</hi> and the Bishop of <hi>Ely Saint Iohns,</hi>
(whiles there was euer a Bishop there) a playne
Bishop (like <hi>Marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>) at euerie word thou wilt
terme him, whereas if thou wert but one hower
entred commons in <hi>Haruey de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ratore, A
great, Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tife or Demy-god in omnisufficiencie</hi>
thou wouldst enstall him.</p>
   <p>But to appose thee more dallyingly and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly.
It is giuen out amongst Schollers, that thou
hast a passing singular good wit, now so trie whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thou hast so or no, let me heare what change
of phra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es thou hast to describe a good wit in, or
how in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dagogue <hi>Tragotanto</hi> Doctors english
thou canst florish vpon it.</p>
   <p>I feele thy pusses beat slowly alreadie, although
thou beest fortie mile off from mee, and this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent
answere (with much adoo) droppes from
thee, euen as sweate from a leane man that drinks
lacke; namely, that thou thinkest there cannot
much extraordinarie descant be made of it, except
it be to say, such a one hath an admirable capacitie,
an incomparable quick inneution, and a surmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="11"/>
rich spirit aboue all men. <hi>Hah, ha,</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute
poore fellow art thou, and hast mist mee
nine score: goe, goe, get thee a caudle and keepe
thy selfe warme in thy bed, for out of question thy
spirit is in a consumption.</p>
   <p>A rich spirit quoth a? nay then a spirit in the
way of honestie too: loe this it is, to bee read in
nothing but in <hi>Barnabe Riches</hi> workes. Spend
but a quarter so much time in mumping vppon
<hi>Gabrtelisme,</hi> and Ile be bound bodie and goods,
thou wilt not anie longer sneakingly come forth
with a rich spirit and an admirable capacitie, but
<hi>an entbusiasticall spirit, &amp; a nimble entelechy.</hi> In
the course of my Booke a whole catalogue thou
shalt finde of all these <hi>Guiny</hi> phrases, to which in
zealous care of thy reformation, I referre thee.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Dii boni boni, quid porto?</hi> What a large Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocesse
of Epistling haue I here progrest through?
The Summons to a generall Councell with all
the reasons moouing thereunto, or <hi>Tindalls</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
before the New Testament, are but short
Graces before meate, in comparison of this my
immoderate Dedication. But the best is, if it be
too long, thou hast a combe and a paire of scissers
to curtall it; or if thou list not stand so long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
it, with a <hi>Trinitie Colledge</hi> rubb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r thou
maist epitomize it extempore.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>Marrie if thou long to heare the reason why I
haue so stretcht it on the tenter-hookes, forsooth
it is a garment for the woodcocke <hi>Gabriel Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ucy,</hi>
and fooles ye know alwaies for the most part
(especiallie if they bee naturall fooles) are suted in
long coates, whereupon I set vp my rest to shape
his garments of the same size, that I might be sure
to sit on his skirts.</p>
   <p>Dick, no more at this time, but <hi>Nos-da diu ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tawhy,</hi>
and all the recompence I can make thee for
being like a Chancery Declaration so tiring trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome
vnto thee, is this, if thou wilt haue the
Doctour for an Anatomie, thou shalt; doo but
speake the word, and I am the man will deliuer
him to thee to be scotcht and carbonado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d: but
in anie case speake quickly, for heere he lies at the
last gaspe of surrendring all his credit and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy Frend <hi>Tho: Nashe,</hi>
if thou beest fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Dick</hi> to
all the generation of
the <hi>Harueys.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>