<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Postscript]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110054_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07792</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18169</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110054</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Postscript]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>New-England. Or A briefe enarration of the ayre, earth, water, fish and fowles of that country : With a description of the natures, orders, habits, and religion of the natiues; in Latine and English verse</title>
                 <author>Morrell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 24, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <p>EXcuse this <hi>Postscript,</hi> perchance more profitable than
the <hi>Prescript.</hi> It may be a necessary Caveat for many
who too familiarly doe <hi>Serò sapere.</hi> The discreet artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer
is not onely happie to vnderstand what may f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yrely and
infallibly further his duly considered designes and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations:
but to discover and remoue what obstacle soever
may oppose his well-advised purposes, and probable conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
I therefore, desiring that every man may be a <hi>Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius,</hi>
not an <hi>Epimethius,</hi> haue here vnderwritten such
im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ediments as I haue observed wonderfully offensiue to all
Plantations; <hi>Quae prodesse qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ant &amp; delectare legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>First therefore I conceiue that far distance of plantations
produce many inconveniences and disabilities of planters,
when as severall Colonies consist but of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, or thirtie,
or about that number, which in a vast vncommanded Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,
makes them liable to many and miserable exigents,
which weakens all vnion, and leaues them difficultly to be
assisted against a potent or daily enemy, and dangerously to
be commanded; when as some one Bay well fortified would
maintaine and inrich some thousands of persons, if it be
planted with men, able, ingenious, and laborious, being well
furnished with all provisions and necessaries for plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Besides, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f one Bay be well peopled, its easily defended,
surveyed, disciplined, and commanded, be the seasons never
so vnseasonable, and all their Forces in few houres readie in
Armes, either offensiuely to pursue, or defensiuely to subsist
convenient numbers ever at sea, and sufficient ever at
home for all service, intelligence and discoverie.</p>
   <p>Secondly, Ignorance of seasons, servants, situation, want
of people, provisions, supplies, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> courage and
patience, in and against all opposition, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and affliction.
<pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>Vincit patientia durum.</hi> Fishermen, manuall artificers,
e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>geners, and good fowlers are excellent servants, and onely
fit for plantations. Let not Gentlemen or Citizens once ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
that I preiudize their reputations, for I speake no word
beyond truth, for they are too high, or not patient of such ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice:
though they may be very necessary for Martiall disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
or excellent, (if pious) for example to the seditious
and inconsiderate multitude.</p>
   <p>Boats with all their furniture, as sayles, hookes, and lines,
and other appendences, afford the painefull planter both va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie
of comfort, and a sufficient competent, and an happie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state.
Good mastiues are singular defences to plantations, in
the terrifying or pursuing of the light-footed Natiues. Hogs
and Goats are easie, present, and abundant profit, living and
feeding on the Ile-lands almost without any care or cost.</p>
   <p>Plantations cannot possibly, profitably subsist without chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels
and boats, which are the onely meanes for surveying and
conveying both our persons and provisions to the well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
scituation. Without these, plantations may with much
patience, and well fortified resolution indure but difficultly,
though with much time flourish and contentedly subsist. For
when men are landed vpon an vnknowne shore, per adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
weake in number and naturall powers, for want of boats'
and carriages; are compelled to stay where they are first lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
having no meanes to remoue themselues or their goods,
be the place never so fruitlesse or inconvenient for planting,
building houses, boats, or stages, or the harbours never so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
for fishing, fowling, or mooring their boats. Of all which,
and many other things necessary for plantation, I purpose to
enforme thee hereafter. Wishing thee in the <hi>interim</hi> all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance,
all fortunatenesse.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
   <pb facs="17"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>