<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Smith, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110828_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12529</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22851</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110828</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Smith, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Noahs dove, or Tydings of peace to the godly : A comfortable sermon preached at a funerall. By Samuel Smith minister of Gods word at Prittlewel in Essex</title>
                 <author>Smith, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Archer, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 52 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, as it hath euer bin the practice of wicked men to make their prosperity an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods fauour, reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after this manner: Is it likely that I should inioy so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny blessings from God if my conuersation were not pleasing in his sight, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.2.</note> Not conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="3"/> that these common gifts are giuen alike both to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man and to the sinner: And that <hi>Esau</hi> though he was a man hated of God, yet enioyed the fatnesse of the earth as well as <hi>Iacob.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 9.2.</note>
   </p>
   <p>So the children of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the outward prosperity of the wicked, and their owne miserable condition here in this life, haue hereby beene much troubled; and haue beene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to call Gods Iudgements into question, how it could stand with his Iustice that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men should so abound in wealth that <hi>Rebelliously transgresse.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 12 1. Psal. 37.</note> This prooued a
<pb facs="3"/> sore temptation vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> insomuch that he confessed that his <hi>steps had wel-nigh slipt.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 73.2.</note> And the same thing perplexed the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> that hee was bold euen to reason the case with God, saying;<note place="margin">Ier. 12.1</note>
      <hi>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked prosper, &amp; why are they in wealth that rebelliously transgresse?</hi> Many of Gods seruants are not a little affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herewith, not vnderstāding the reason, how the Lord will not suffer his children in this life to goe vnchastised for their sinnes, but thereby brings them to a greater measure of humiliation: As for the wicked,
<pb facs="4"/> the Prophet assigneth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their prosperity, namely this,<note place="margin">Ier. 12, 3.</note>
      <hi>That thou maiest pull them out like beasts for the slaughter, and prepare them for the day of Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> This truth is most cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set downe in the seauen and thirty <hi>Psalme,</hi> a portion whereof I haue handled in the Sermon following, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire herein is to comfort Gods people, that notwithstanding their present condition may seeme to bee miserable, yet the Lord doth euer vpholde his in time of greatest danger, and of this they shall be sure, that their <hi>later end shal be peace.</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> I wish thee comfort by it, and by all other holy helpes. And so remayne</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in euery Christian office,</hi> Samuel Smith.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Prittlewel,</hi>
         <date>this <hi>8. of April, 1619.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>