<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Arthur Hawkins in com∣mendation
of this Treatise.</title>
           <author>Kempe, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110356_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09213</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19523</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Arthur Hawkins in com∣mendation
of this Treatise.</title>
                 <author>Kempe, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trve reporte, of the late discoueries, and possession, taken in the right of the Crowne of Englande, of the new-found landes : by that valiaunt and worthye gentleman, Sir Humfrey Gilbert Knight. Wherein is also breefely sette downe, her highnesse lawfull tytle therevnto, and the great and manifolde commodities, that is likely to grow thereby, to the whole realme in generall, and to the aduenturers in particular. Together with the easines and shortnes of the voyage. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Peckham, George, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hinde, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>74 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>Arthur Hawkins in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
of this Treatise.</head>
   <l>MY freendes, if at <hi>Th'exchaunge</hi> a man shoulde goe and tell,</l>
   <l>that such, and such commodities he had to sell.</l>
   <l>VVhereof we stood in neede and scarcelie to be founde,</l>
   <l>VVhereby a quicke returne with profit woulde redounde.</l>
   <l>I doubt not ere I past, but you would craue the sight,</l>
   <l>Of these commended wares, and buy them if you might.</l>
   <l>Y'are proferd at this time, fayre Grapes to make your wine,</l>
   <l>The pleasaunt fruites of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Figs and Orenge fine.</l>
   <l>The speckled <hi>Russian</hi> Furres, that <hi>Esterlings</hi> vs sendes,</l>
   <l>The Rosen, Pitch, and Deales that <hi>Dansk</hi> and <hi>Denmarke</hi> lendes.</l>
   <l>The Mettall heere is showne that with a quenchles fire,</l>
   <l>Inflames our thirsting hartes vnstaunched in desire.</l>
   <l>A bargaine may you haue, t'is put into your handes,
Of all commodities you haue from other landes.</l>
   <l>And at so easie price you can not choose but gaine:</l>
   <l>A trifle is the most, together with your paine,</l>
   <l>But what is that some sayes? our Englishmen giues eare,</l>
   <l>Onelie to gaine, God shielde it shoulde be true I heare.</l>
   <l>If we religious be, lets rigge our shippes with speede,</l>
   <l>And carry Christ to these poore souls, that stande in neede,</l>
   <l>VVhy pause yee therevpon? the fraight will quite the charge,</l>
   <l>For what is doone for God, dooth finde rewarde full large.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>