<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
Honorable and truely Noble-mind∣ed,
Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight, Lord Maior
of the Citie of London, Sir Thomas Middleton,
and Sir Iohn Iolles, ALDERMEN,
his Brethren.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110403_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09203</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19513.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110403</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
Honorable and truely Noble-mind∣ed,
Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight, Lord Maior
of the Citie of London, Sir Thomas Middleton,
and Sir Iohn Iolles, ALDERMEN,
his Brethren.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The period of mourning : Disposed into sixe visions. In memorie of the late prince. Together vvith nuptiall hymnes, in honour of this happy marriage betweene the great princes, Frederick Count Palatine of the Rhene, and the most excellent, and aboundant president of all virtue and goodnes Elizabeth onely daughter to our soueraigne, his Maiestie. Also the manner of the solemnization of the marriage at White-Hall, on the 14. of February, being Sunday, and St. Valentines day. By Henry Peacham, Mr. of Arts</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Helme (Helmes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Wedding pamphlets</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
Honorable and truely Noble-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight, Lord Maior
of the Citie of London, Sir Thomas Middleton,
and Sir Iohn Iolles, ALDERMEN,
his Brethren.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIght Honourable, and worthy Senators.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was an auncient custome, no
whit discommendable, among
the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Princes, amid
their Feasts and Royall Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets,
to haue the head of a
dead man laid in Earth, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
the first to the Table; in abundance of Mirth
to put them in minde of <hi>Mortalitie.</hi> Though I haue
euer beene a sworne enimie to Superstition, I seeme
to imitate them thus farre, who vnseasonably at
the solemnitie of this Royall <hi>Marriage,</hi> offer againe
to view the Image of our dead deere and neuer to be
forgotten <hi>Prince, Henrie.</hi> Affection is liable to
none account, and this Sorrow, to sound harts can
<pb facs="3"/>
neuer come out of season, yet thus much for my selfe;
My loue to his excellent vertues, and person, to
whom I was so many wayes engaged, drew, some
while since these teares to their head, which encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
with a contrary passion of Ioy, for the happy
<hi>Marriage</hi> of his Most-like <hi>Sister</hi> the <hi>Princesse</hi>
my most gracious Lady; like fire and water (stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
for praedominancie) I was enforced to make
both way euen to mine owne preiudice. What I haue
done, my Honourable Lord, in regard of the fidelity
the <hi>Citie</hi> hath euer borne to the <hi>State,</hi> the true har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
loue you carry in your owne particulars to his
<hi>Maiestie,</hi> and the Progenie Royall, and lastly that
you are knowne out of your Noble and owne Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
inclination to goodnes, to fauour all Learning
and Excellencie, whereby beyond your praedecessors
you gaine a double Honour, I humbly offer vp to
your Honourable protection: expecting onely Time
and Occasion wherein I may really manifest how
fast I am tyed in Zeale and dutifull Affection to so
worthy a <hi>Maior,</hi> and so Honourable a <hi>Citie.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours
and Worships, truely deuoted
<hi>Henry Peacham.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>