<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Fennor, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110749_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11118</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21385</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Fennor, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hell's broke loose</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Loftus (Loftis), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this vn-weeded Garden of the</hi> World, hath sprung vp through al ages of the same, most innumerable euen of all sorted kindes, that haue been oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to <hi>Vertue,</hi> and pursuers of <hi>Vice;</hi> Such as haue with great trauell and labour taken paynes to goe to Hell, and runne the broade way path with Hindes feete, in all poasting speede that the Diuell could employ them. Amongst the rest of this fearefull race runners (of their variable qualities) here is a description of the most notorious Rebels and Heretiques of <hi>Europe,</hi> certaine <hi>Germane</hi> Anabaptistes, such as would haue all things common, and all men at freewill and libertie to do what they list, without controwle of any Authoritie: euery mans Will Law▪ and euery ones Dreame Doctrine.</p>
   <p>Before the comming of our <hi>Sauiour Christ; Theudas,</hi> and <hi>Iudas Galilaeus,</hi> two seditious fellowes of factious spirit, sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>Iewes:</hi> The first of them saying, that hee was a Prophet sent from God for mans g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>od; and that by his owne powerfull word, hee could deuide the waters of <hi>Iordan</hi> in as admirable
<pb facs="4"/>
sort, as <hi>Ioshua</hi> the seruant of the Lord had done. The other, did earnestly promise to enlarge the <hi>Iewes</hi> from the seruitude and yoke of the <hi>Romans:</hi> both of them by these meanes, dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing after them great multitudes of people; and both of them comming vnto deserued destruction: For <hi>Fatus</hi> the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Iury</hi> ouertooke <hi>Theudas,</hi> and sent his head as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument to <hi>Ierusalem:</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> likewise perished, and all his following confederates were dispersed.</p>
   <p>After our <hi>Sauiour Christ,</hi> in the time of his blessed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer mightely withstood the proceeding of <hi>Paule</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas,</hi> sowing the seed of Heresie in the minde of <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> Deputie: but the iudgement of God ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke him, and he was strucken with blindnesse. Not long after him, in the raigne of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour, arose an other cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bencocha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> that professed himselfe to be the <hi>Messias,</hi> &amp; to haue descended from Heauen in the likenes of a Starre, for the safetie &amp; redemption of the people: by which fallacie, he drew after him a world of seditious people; but at last, hee and many of his credulous route were slaine, and was called by the <hi>Iewes</hi> (in contempt) <hi>Bencozha</hi> (that is) the Sonne of a lie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Manes,</hi> of whom the <hi>Maniches</hi> tooke their name and first originall, forged in his foolish braine a fiction of two Gods,
<pb facs="4"/>
and two beginners; and reiecting the old Testament, and the true God, which is reuealed in the same; published a fift Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of his owne forgerie, reporting himselfe to be the <hi>Holy Ghost:</hi> When he had thus with diuulging his diuelish Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies and Blasphemies infected the world, being pursued by Gods iust iudgement, hee was for other wicked practizes taken, and his skinne pulled ouer his eares aliue.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Montanus</hi> that notorious blasphemous wretch, of whom the <hi>Montanists</hi> tooke their ofspring, denyed <hi>Christ</hi> our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to be GOD, saying: Hee was but Man onely, like other men, without any participation of Diuine essence: Hee called himselfe the Comforter, and Holy spirit, which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to come into the world; and his two Wiues <hi>Priscilla</hi> and <hi>Maximilla,</hi> he named his Prophetesses, and their writings Prophesies: yet all their cunning could not preuent nor fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell a wretched and desperate end which befell him; for after he had of long time deluded the world, in imitation of <hi>Iudas,</hi> hee hanged himselfe.</p>
   <p>Infinite are the examples that may be collected out of the registers of foregone ages, touching the lamentable euilles, slaughters, blood, and death, that haue ensued from the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable heriticall Instruments of the Diuel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; and how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="5"/>
(affecting Nouelties, and Innouations) haue concurred from time to time, with the pl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tters endeuours, Histories are full of their memories. Most Rebellions <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> pretende Religion for them selues: No Villaine but dare turne a good outside to the eye, though the inside be as bad, as heart can imagine.</p>
   <p>These infamous <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Heretiques</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> pretended Religion; they would be reformer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the Church, and State: new Doctrine of their owne frantick<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> conceites: no Childred should be Baptized: all thinges should be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, &amp; no Magistrate to gouerne, but euery man at his owne libertie to do<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> what he list; take whatsoeuer he stood in need of, without pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: pluralitie of Wiues: no recouerie of wrongfull d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tayned Goodes, and such like villanous roguish stuffe, that neuer a The<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fe in the world would refuse to subscribe vnto it.</p>
   <p>This was no sooner taught by <hi>Iohn Leyden,</hi> alias <hi>Yoncker Hans</hi> a Dutch Taylor, <hi>Tom Mynter</hi> a parish Clarke, <hi>Knip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ulling</hi> a Smyth, and <hi>Crafteing</hi> a Ioyner; but it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by thousandes of the Boores, and vulgar illiterate Clownes, who in great companies dayly resorted vnto them fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>th o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all Townes and Villages: A most rude rascall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie that regarded neither Gods feare, nor mans fauour, euen HELLE BROKE LOOSE.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>In their outragious madnes, they attempted much villanie, omitting to put nothing in practize that stood with their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours lyking; as good Commons Wealths men, as <hi>Iacke Straw, Watt Tyler, Tom Myller, Iohn Ball,</hi> &amp;c. in the raigne of <hi>Richard the 2.</hi> and as sound Diuines for Doctrine, as <hi>Hackets</hi> Disciples, that preached in <hi>Cheapeside</hi> in a Pease-cart: Yet they found of their owne fraternitie to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the Diuels affayres; and mustering themselues togeather, all composed of the scumbe and waste worser-sort could be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, they proceeded so farre, that they tooke the Towne of <hi>Munster,</hi> and there for a time, domineerd as if they had been Electors apeece to the <hi>Emperour;</hi> vntill beeing beleagerd by the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> they were taught to taste how Extremitie did sauour, finding the bitternesse of their rash and gracelesse attemptes, to punish them most seueerely in the end: For when Cattes, Dogges, Rattes and Myce, grew scarce and daintie, (No common dish, but choyce dyet for <hi>Iohn Leyden,</hi> and the Lordes of his counsaile <hi>Knipperdulling</hi> the Smyth, <hi>Crafteing</hi> the Ioyner, and <hi>Tom Mynter</hi> the Clarke;) They were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayned to frie old greasie Busse leather Ierkins, and Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Coouers of Bookes, Bootes in Steakes, and Stew-pottes of old Shoes, till in the end being famished as leaue as dryed
<pb facs="6"/>
Stock-fish, they were subdued: and <hi>Leyden</hi> (who had tearmed himselfe <hi>King of Munster</hi>) with his Nobles, made of <hi>Smyth, Ioyner,</hi> and <hi>Parish Clarke,</hi> were according to the iust re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of all Rebels, put to death, with great torture: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, their bodyes were hang'd in Iron Cages vpon the toppe of the high Steeple in <hi>Munster,</hi> called <hi>S. Lamberts Steeple,</hi> for an example to all of Rebell race: Their Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates in great multitudes hauing perished with the Sword and famine, may togeather with all Traytors witnesse to the world throughout all ensuing ages, how GOD with vengeance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes all such State-disturbers, and factious Rebels.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>