<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the truely and wel affected Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Puckell, Steven</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110514_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10207</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20484</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the truely and wel affected Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Puckell, Steven</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true table of all such fees as are due to the Bishop of London : and all his depending officers, as commissaryes, registers, proctors, and apparitors, as hath been given in to his Majestyes commissioners in Starchamber under their own hands in the month of November M. DC. XXX. Whereto is added a true discovery of such fees ordinarily exacted by them upon his Majestyes good subjects contrary to this their own table and the statute laws of the land. Published by Steven Puckell and sent as a love token for his countryes good</title>
                 <author>Puckell, Steven</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the truely and wel affected Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>CHristian Reader God by his wise providence ordering all things to his owne glory, hath bene pleased after many and sore trialls to bring me the unworthyest of his servants to a place of more rest and safety in respect of my present condition, then I either had, or possibly could look for in myne owne land; I therfore seriously consideringe by how many bonds I stand bound to Almighty God for those many great mercys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nge delyverances which I have received from his mere goodnes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, as also well considering, how nearly my soule is k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt to you my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Countrymen: I could not but out of pitty to your pres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt estate, and conscience of myne owne duty to God, and you all, answer your reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble requests and earnest expectation in adventuring to put thes few lines to the open view of the world, the which thing God who knowes my hart, knowes I aime not at any mans person, neither have I added any thing but have taken a true coppy of all the fees as they were presented before his Magesties Comissioners in Starchamber, confirmed under every of their owne generall hands, without adding any thing therto, by the which the wise and discrete reader may in some sort from his owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience (who is the best scholemaster) playnly see how trēblingly these shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and posts by the which the kingdome of Antichrist is yet upheld in our Kingdom of England do tyranise, not onely over the soules and consciēces, but over the bodyes and goods of his Magistyes loving subjects, their Cannons and Constitutions, Iniunctions and Decrees, tending to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose but onely to be snares and gins to the soules and bodyes of men: thus those who would be thought to be the prophets of England are all like those prophets in Israel: <hi>Hosea</hi> 9. 8. the suare of a fowler is in all their wayes, all their projects being how to grow great and maintayn their pomp and state, allthough it be with the blood of the poore fatherlesse &amp; widdow; yea though it be to the overthrow of King and state, which I wil indeavour to clear by thes propositions. For proofe wherof I will appeall to none other but to thyne owne experience. First who seeth not that all their Cannons and Decrees both new and ould tend to no other end but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralling of the soules and bodyes of Gods people, and the bringing of them under an Antichristian yoke, wich appeares first that since the yeare 1624. they have changed the oath of Curchwardens and sidemen (as they call them) into that forme that it is now become nothing ells but a rack for the consciences of men and may truly be called an injurjous and blooddy oath 2. What else is the ground, why they have taken away all those Cannons
<pb facs="4"/>
that respect them selues, that the people cannot see them, but that they might more peaceably and freely prey on the bodyes and soules of men at their owne pleasures. 3. What is the reason they doe of late use so many shiftes and trickes to maintayne their standings as they do by devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all the inchrochments upon the liberty of the subject, the like whereof cannot beparalelled by robbing of the nobility of their honorus, tytles, offices, and dignityes, and conferring them on their owne heades or the heades of their favorites; yea is it not matter enough (if not a friend to the prelacy) for any (though otherwise deserving never so well) to stand like a beakon on the top of a hill not respected. 4. who seeth not, that all the good and whollesomme lawes of the Common wealth is by them turned upside downe, &amp; like a leaden wand bowed to every end that suits them selues, be it right or wrong; thus like horses are they prepared to battell with strong unresistible power to beare downe all before them that doth but mute against their cursed usurpations. 5. what ranke or order of men comes not under their tyranny and oppression in their matchles extortions? they sleight the rich in the height of their pride, they regard not the cryes of the widdow and fatherlesse, but like men voyd of compassion or bereft of humanity wring and wrest from all men in all causes abundantly more then is alowed them by their owne Cannons and Ecclesiasticall lawes; and especially in the probats of wills and administrations they are as the Proph. Zeph saith. 3. 3. Like the evening wolfs that leave not the bones un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the morning, my brethre may not the Lord cōplaine against us as against his owne people. Ier. 5. 26. that among his people are found wicked men that lay wait as he that setteth snares, they set a trap to catch men; as a cage is full of birdes, so are their howses full of deceyt, therfore they are become great &amp; wax rich, also they Judg not the cause of the fatherlesse, but as in the 29. shall not the Lord visit for these thinges? shall not his soule be avenged on such a nation as this? Therfore brethren and loving coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen considering these things, let me in a word speak to you all under these two ranks, other as you are the called of God, or as yet uncalled by him. And first to you that are called of God, let me speak to you in the words of the Lord by the Prophet Ierem. 2. 18. <hi>What have you to doe in the way of Aegypt, to drink the waters of Sihor? or what hast thou to doe in the way of Assyria, to drink the waters of the river?</hi> Or for the fear of man to bee found in the way of Gilgall, for all their wickednes is in Gilgall, there doth the Lord hate them, and for their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quityes wil in his time arive them out of his house; therfore come not at their courts, obey not their summons sent out in their own names against
<pb facs="4"/>
the law of the land and honour of the King, so that if the Kings Majesty were not very patient towards them, and those that submit to their usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations where were they? Trust God with your goods and lives, he is able to recompence all wth better, ad not fire then to this altar of Baal, neither by purse nor presence, <hi>Walk not after these commaundemens of men lest Ephraim like, ye he oppressed and broken in judgment, and the Lord become to you (as to him) a moth, or as he was to Iudah rottenes, Hosea</hi> 5. 11. 12. My brethren be not affraid of man in Gods cause, consider what the Apostle saith to Timothy 2. epist. 1. 7. <hi>God hath not given to us the spirit of fear, but of power, of love, of a sound minde,</hi> Where observe, this fear of man for the prevailing power therof, is called the spirit of feare, and is opposed to the spirit of God, as power, and love and a sound minde, whence then we may learn. That where ever his fear of man is residing in the strength and power of it, there no sound power of godlines, nor soundnes of judgment, nor power of action, is to be looked for. Besides this fear of man will be a snare to you, for <hi>the fear of man bringeth a snare, but who so trusteth in God shalbe sure.</hi> Prov. 29. 25. Besides there is a lake prepared for the fearfull, say not then wth the fainthearted spyes, there be giants, and walls up to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and we shall never overcome, for we overcome in sufferring. Consider also, that God, the Gospell, and the people of God, are more beholding (if I may so speak) to one constant sufferrer sent of God, then to ten thousand fainthearted apostates and backsliders, therefore my brethren looke what Gods worthyes have done, and doe likewise, as Paule to Timo. 2. epist. 1. 8. so I speak to you all in his words, <hi>Be not you therefore ashamed of the testimonie of our lord, nor of me his prisonner, but be you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the afflictions of the Gospell, according to the power of God who hath saved us and called us with an holy calling.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And to you my countrymen that are yet uncalled what shall I say? to sett you a worke about the works of a living mā that have not a principle of life in you, were but a vain thing, I therefore say no more to you but thus, Take courage to your selvs as you are men, and know your own priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and stand to them, consider the laws of a kingdome are the subjects in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and no subject can be deprived of them without manifest inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, therfore suffer not your selvs to be gulled in these things, looke the Statute for the probate of wills and testaments, observe the penaltyes upon all that shall extort upon the same, the lawe saying directely in these words <hi>That if a Bishop or Archbishop or anie other ecclesiasticall juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction shall extort or take of anie of his Mayestyes subjects, either</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>more or greater fees then is allowed them by law, they shall forfeit to the party wronged three times that they take to the party grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and over and above they shall forfeit to the King ten pounds the which shalbe levyed by way of trespasse, or of debt recovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by lawe in anie of his Majestyes courts of record, against which action there shalbe no appeale nor act of errour to be graunted but the monies so levyed shalbe one half to the King, and the other half to the partye wronged. Or els thou must maintain thy right by an inditement at the common sessions of the quarter where the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was committed.</hi> Thus in as few words and as punctually as I can I have commended these small labours of mine to thee, which I desire may be to Gods glory and thy direction, and then let God deale wth mee as seemeth good in his owne eies. Farewell in the Lord farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my lodging in Amsterdam</hi>
         <date> the 6. <hi>of December</hi> 1631.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>STEVEN PVCKELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>