<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable Sir Peregrin Bartue knight, Lord of Willoughby and Earsby, al increase of Honor and true happinesse.</title>
           <author>O., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110186_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08434</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18755</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110186</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable Sir Peregrin Bartue knight, Lord of Willoughby and Earsby, al increase of Honor and true happinesse.</title>
                 <author>O., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentation of Troy, for the death of Hector : Wherevnto is annexed an olde womans tale in hir solitarie cell</title>
                 <author>Ogle, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mattes, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable Sir <hi>Peregrin Bartue knight, Lord of Willoughby</hi> and Earsby, al increase of Honor and true happinesse.</head>
   <p>I Haue presumed (Right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) vpon these three reasons to present this vnworthy pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet vnto your honors courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous view, and fauourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. The first is from your own noble wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse, for that you are, and are so thought, the onely <hi>Hector</hi> of <hi>Albion</hi>: and therfore most worthy to protect <hi>Hector.</hi> The second, for that it was the wil and desire of the Ghost, of the woful Ghost of <hi>Ilion</hi>: that in hir teares you might behold the sorrows of your owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey whensoeuer iniurious fates shoulde cause you miscarrie. The third and last is (my good Lord) mine owne priuate affection, wherein I haue long honoured you, and hauing no place to make it knowne, haue long desired to finde some opportunitie to shew the same. I hope
<pb facs="3"/>
your Lordship will pardon me, for that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a most veniall offence. And if heerein I doe not honour your Lordship so much as you are worthy, and I earnestlie wish, yet please it you to fauour and pardon this first, and as time and yeares shall enable me with a more experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced iudgement and knowledge, I will studie and endeuour that, which shal be more worthy your honours fauourable protection. Please it you accept, and I am graced, and my labour richly rewarded. I cease to trouble your Lord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ship further at this time, I vow my selfe to your Lordships seruice, and so most humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humbly at command, <hi>I. O.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>