<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110157_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08178</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18513</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110157</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The olde mans dietarie : A worke no lesse learned then necessary for the preseruation of olde persons in perfect health and soundnesse. Englished out of Latine, and now first published by Thomas Newton</title>
                 <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶To the friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE godlie trauailes and learned paines ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kē by sundry our Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen to acquaint the noble Art of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke with our vsuall phrase, and to inuest it with English attyer, occasioned mee at the first to translate out of Latine into English, a learned worke of Doctor <hi>Gratarolus,</hi> and to publish the same in the yeere <hi>1574.</hi> vnder the title of <hi>A Direction for the health of Magistrates &amp; Studients &amp;c.</hi> Which, being of the wise &amp; learned not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together misliked, J hoping for the like good successe, was afterwards easily entreated by a worshipfull Gentleman my very friend, eft soones to tread the like path, and to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>Leuinus Lemnius</hi> his notable worke <hi>De Crasi:</hi> which first came abroad, vnder the title of <hi>The Touchstone of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions,</hi> in the yeere <hi>1576.</hi> Since which tyme, I haue not greatly dealt in any workes of this excellent, Arte otherwise then for
<pb facs="4"/>
myne owne priuate studie, wherein I haue found both ease and delight. Jt may not seeme straunge to haue Phisicke bookes in English, neither ought any man in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be thereat discontented. The very fathers of Phisicke <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene</hi> with others beeing Grecians, wrate their workes in the Greeke tongue: which to them was the mother tongue, as the English is now to vs. The Romaines wrate in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine beeing their proper language, and the Arabians, as <hi>Auicen,</hi> in the Arabicke speech: and others of other Countreis, in the language that there was vsuall. And wee cannot (without the note of more then sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage ingratitude) but confesse and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the great benefite and furtheraunce that wee still enioye by the painfull pennes and English treatises of many our owne Countreymen, aswel in Phisicke as Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie. As namely, of that worthy Knight Sir Thomas Eliot, of Master Doctor Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, of Maister D. Record, of Maister D. Phaer, of Maister D. Cunningham, of Maister D. Bulleyn, of Maister D. Cald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, of Maister D. Iohnson, of Maister D. Iones, of Maister D. Boord, Maister
<pb facs="4"/>
Traheron, Maister Bright, Maister Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, Maister Securis, Maister Lyte, Maister Carye, Maister Coxe, Maister Hill, Maister Gale, Maister Baker, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Banister, Maister Hall, Maister Clowes, Maister Moore, Maister Paynell, M. Ʋicars, M. Hester, M. Basebridge. and some others, whose works J either haue not yet seene, or at this present come not to remembrance. If therfore herein I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred blame (which I trust with all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent &amp; vnaffectionate persons I haue not) yet should it bee to mee some mitigation of griefe, to march in rancke with so worthie, excellent and painfull men. If it be obiected, that this studie sitteth not with my profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: surely I therein rest resolute, that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie as Ladie and Maistresse, refuseth not (nay of duetie, claymeth &amp; chalengeth) the seruice of all the other Artes, and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: so as I thinke the surliest and waywar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest Areopagite will not denye. Howsoeuer it is, thy curteous construction and friendly acceptance shall effectually satisfie my desire, and throughly counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile my trauaile.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell. <hi>Thomas Newton.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>