<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110480_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09765</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20031</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110480</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summarie of the antiquities, and wonders of the worlde, abstracted out of the sixtene first bookes of the excellente historiographer Plinie, vvherein may be seene the wonderful workes of God in his creatures, translated oute of French into Englishe by I.A</title>
                 <author>Pliny, the Elder</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Translator to <hi>the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuch (gentle Reader) as the works of God are maruelous, not onelye in vs his creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, whom he hath fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned and formed like to his similitude, but also in others, as beastes, foules, fishes, trées, plantes, &amp; such like, whose miraculous works, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vnto vs some things séeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible: yet if we did consider y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie of God, vnto whom nothing is vnpossible, doubtlesse we should not runne into so many daungers of sinne as we daily do. And therfore I thought good somwhat to profite my countrey, with that small talent that God hath lent me, in translating out of French, into our Englishe tongue, parte of the Secretes of that notable Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Plinie,</hi> abstracted out of the sixtene
<pb facs="3"/>
first bookes of his natural history wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is contained wonderfull &amp; straunge things (vnto vs) of the diuersitie of coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, the commodities thereof, wyth the most monstrous, and vggly shape of men inhabiting the said countreys, which though it some vnto vs as fables &amp; lyes, yet (as I sayd before) nothing is impossible vnto god. For as his hande hath made all things, yea and straunge things, which vnto vs is wel knowen: so can he also make forraine thinges, which vnto vs are vnknowē. But least it shoulde seeme to the Reader, that I shoulde affirme that whiche I doe not knowe, therefore I referre it vnto the learned reader, to this end, that he may iudge the truth. And whereas <hi>Plinie</hi> commendeth the notable wit, pollicie, strength, and memorie of dyuers Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines: so might I in like case, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our owne countrey, whose nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pollicie, tried strength, sharpenesse of witte, and perfect memorie, vnto vs is well knowen, to be equal with those
<pb facs="3"/>
Romaines, of whom <hi>Plinie</hi> doth recite. But I omitte that for prolixitie, folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine aucthour. (neyther adding nor diminishing) As touching the rest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in this booke, whereof we haue heard, &amp; somewhat séene by experience, I doubt not, but the Readers will veref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the same. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I refer al things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gentle Reader, whome I desire to iudge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differētly.</p>
   <closer>Fare well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>