<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VERTV∣ous and worshipfull Ladie, the Ladie MARGARITE MORGAN, wife vnto Sir IOHN MORGAN of Chilworth in the Countie of SVRREY Knight, and Cap∣taine of her Maiesties horsemen in the same Shire.</title>
           <author>T., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110501_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16304</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3216</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110501</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VERTV∣ous and worshipfull Ladie, the Ladie MARGARITE MORGAN, wife vnto Sir IOHN MORGAN of Chilworth in the Countie of SVRREY Knight, and Cap∣taine of her Maiesties horsemen in the same Shire.</title>
                 <author>T., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Orlando inamorato the three first bookes of that famous noble gentleman and learned poet, Mathew Maria Boiardo Earle of Scandiano in Lombardie. Done into English heroicall verse, by R.T. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Boiardo, Matteo Maria</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and worshipfull Ladie, the Ladie MARGARITE MORGAN, wife vnto Sir IOHN MORGAN of <hi>Chilworth</hi> in the Countie of SVRREY Knight, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of her Maiesties horsemen in the same Shire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Madam, the manifolde courtesies, and exceeding great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, which not onely mine elder brother, but also mine owne poore selfe, haue receiued and founde at Chilworth, is the occasion and cause we are so much bound and beholding vnto you: In signe whereof, I shall desire you to accept this small testimonie of my duetious good will, towardes your worthie Howse, vntill better satisfaction shall follow to make some amendes for the same: It is a Nouell Matter, &amp; therefore I send it vnto you as a New-yeers gift these Hollidayes, resembling herein the fashion of some cunning Drapers, who when they would vtter a
<pb facs="3"/>
badde piece of doth, carrie the same vnto the falsest &amp; darkest window they haue, thereby to make the badde colour shew thee better: So I, desirous that this my simple Translation might passe the safer, haue sent it vnto you these short dayes in Christmas, that reading the same by candle light, you may the lesse perceiue the faults thereof: yet howsoeuer it is, I doubt not but your Ladiship will accept fauourably of it, and at some idle houre or other, reade it ouer. And thus (good Madam) crauing pardon for my boldenesse, and fauour for such faultes as may be committed in the same, I wish vnto you, all such happie contentment, as eyther your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie selfedoth desire, or your vertuous Thoughtes any way deserue: and so I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships most deuoted. R. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>