<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Worshipfull Ma: Henry Prannell Esquire, the true Friend and Fauourer of all laudable Professions.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110268_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15427</idno>
           <idno type="STC">257</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110268</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Worshipfull Ma: Henry Prannell Esquire, the true Friend and Fauourer of all laudable Professions.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hecatonphila. The arte of loue : Or, loue discouered in an hundred seuerall kindes</title>
                 <author>Alberti, Leone Battista</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Leake, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 40 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Worshipfull Ma: <hi>Henry Prannell</hi> Esquire, the true Friend and Fauourer of all laudable Professions.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, the stranger may these my sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations seeme vnto ye, in that I being a Stranger and neuer treading on English ground till this instant, make choice of you for my first En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainer, intruding my selfe as a guest, whereas yet I haue no acquaintance at all. But if you
<pb facs="3"/>
shall deeme me blame-worthy heerein, (as I will not greatly stand in maintaining anie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption) the fault indeed is a kinde Countrimans of yours, who would needes haue mee leaue my honourable Friends in <hi>Italy,</hi> and those great prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alotted me in <hi>France,</hi> to trie the aire &amp; climate of faire <hi>Englands</hi> Maiden Kingdome. And whereas diuers others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated me to honorable habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, yea, as great places of reckoning as anie mine owne natiue Soile affoorded me: yet the perswasions of this your wel-wishing Friend hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled
<pb facs="3"/>
me, to lay all my fortunes at your feete, &amp; either by your fauour to liue here for euer, or by your discountenance to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe disgraced. The rude English I speake, I learnd it of him: the danger I may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, I impose vpon him: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (for his friendly association in my trauell) if you allow me anie grace, bestow it on him. For, as his affection to you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth that of manie: so, (in mine opinion) if you trie him, you shall finde him as forward to your welfare as anie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships to bee commaunded:</hi> Hecatonphila.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>