<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110574_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10354</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20634</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The discouerie of the large, rich, and bevvtiful empire of Guiana : with a relation of the great and golden citie of Manoa (which the spanyards call El Dorado) and the prouinces of Emeria, Arromaia, Amapaia, and other countries, with their riuers, adioyning. Performed in the yeare 1595. by Sir W. Ralegh Knight, captaine of her Maiesties Guard, Lo. Warden of the Sannerries [sic], and her Highnesse Lieutenant generall of the countie of Cornewall</title>
                 <author>Raleigh, Walter, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>BEcause there haue been diuers opinions conceiued of the gold oare brought from <hi>Guiana,</hi> and for that an Alderman of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and an officer of her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties minte, hath giuen out that the same is of no price, I haue thought good by the addition of these lines to giue answere as wel to the said malicious flaunder, as to other obiectiōs. It is true that while we abode at the Iland of <hi>Trinedado,</hi> I was in formed by an Iudian, that not farre from the Port, where we ancored, there were founde certaine minerall stones which they esteemed to be gold, and were the reunto perswaded the rather for that they had seen both English, and French menga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and imbarque some quantities thereof: vppon this likly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode I sent 40. men &amp; gaue order that each one should bring a stone of that mync, to make triall of the goodnesse, which be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing performed, I assured them at their returne that the same was <hi>Marcasite,</hi> and of no riches or value: Notwithstanding diuers trusting more to their owne sence, then to my opinion. kept of the saide <hi>Marcasite,</hi> and haue tried thereof, since my returne, in diucrs places. In <hi>Guiana</hi> it selfe I neuer sawe <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casite,</hi> but all the rocks, mountaines, all stones in the plaines, in woodes, and by the riuers side are in effect tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row shining, and appeare marueylous rich, which being tried to be no <hi>Marcasite,</hi> are the trew signes of rich minerals, but are no other then <hi>El madre del oro</hi> (as the Spanyards terme them) which is the mother of golde, or as it is saide by others the scum of Gold: of diuers sortes of these manie of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie brought also into England, euery one taking the fayrest for the best, which is not generall, For mine owne parte, I did not countermand any mans desire, or opinion, &amp; I could haue a
<pb facs="7"/>
forded them little if I shoulde haue denied them the pleasing of their owne fancies therein: But I was resolued that golde must be found either in graines separate frō the stone (as it is in most of the riuers in <hi>Guiana</hi>) or else in a kinde of hard stone, which we call the white Sparre, of which I saw diuers hils, &amp; in sundrie places, but had neither time, nor men, nor instruments fit to labour. Neere vnto one of the riuers I founde of the saide white Sparre or flint a very greatledge orbanke, which I endeuored to breake by all the meanes I coulde, bicause there appeared on the out side some small graines of gold, but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no meane to worke the same vpon the vpper part, seeking the sides and circuit of the sayd rock, I founde a clift in the same from whence with daggers, and with the head of an axe, we gotte out some small quantitie therof, of which kinde of white stone (wherein golde in gendered) we fawe diuers hils and rocks in euery part of <hi>Guiana,</hi> wherein we trauelled. Of this there hath beene made many trialls, and in London, it was first assaide by Master <hi>Westwood</hi> a refiner dwelling in wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street, and it helde after the rate of 12000 or 13000 pounds a tunne. Another sort was afterward tried by Master <hi>Bulmar</hi> and Master <hi>Dimocke</hi> assay master, &amp; it held after the rate of 23000 poundes a tunne. There was some of it againe tried by Master <hi>Palmer</hi> comptrollor of the minte, and Master <hi>Dimocke</hi> in gold smiths hall, and it helde after 26900 pounds a tun. There was also at the same time, and by the same persons a triall made of the dust of the said mine which held 8. pound 6. ounces weight of gold, in the hundred: there was likwise at the same time a triall made of an Image of Copper made in <hi>Guiana,</hi> which helde a third part gold, besides diuers trialls made in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and by others in London. But because there came of ill with the good; and belike the said Alderman was not presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the best, it hath pleased him therefore to scandall all the rest, and to deface the enterprize as much as in him ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. It hath also been concluded by diuers, that if there had been anie such oare in <hi>Guiana,</hi> and the same discouered, that
<pb n="3" facs="7"/>
I woulde haue brought home a greater quantitie there of: first I was not bounde to satisfie anie man of the quantitie, but such onely as aduenured, if any store had beene returned thereof: but it is verie true that had all their mountaines beene of massie Golde, is was impossible for vs to haue made anie longer sfay to haue wrought the same: and whosoeuer hath seene with what strength of stone, the best golde oare is inuironed, he will not thinke it easie to be had out in heapes, and especially by vs who had neither men, instrumentes, nor time (as it is saide before) to performe the same: There were on this discouerie. no lesse then 100 performes, who can all witnesse, that when we past any braunch of the riuer to yewe the land within, and staied from our boates but six houres, wee were driuen to wade to the eyes, at our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: and if we attempted the same the day following, it was impossible either to forde it, or to swim it, both by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the swiftnesse, and also for that the borders were so prestred with fast woods, as neither bote nor man could finde place, either to land or to imbarque: for in Iune, Iuly, August and september, it is impossible to nauigate any of those riuers, for such is the furie of the <hi>Current,</hi> and there are so many trees and woods ouerflowne, as if anie boate but touch vppon any tree or stake, it is impossible to saue anie one person therein: and ere we departed the land it ran with that swiftnes, as we draue downe most commonly against the wind, little lesse then one hundred miles a day: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides our vessels were no other then wherries, one little barge, a small cockboate, and a bad Galiota, which wee framed in hast for that purpose at <hi>Trinedado,</hi> and those little boates had nyne or ten men apeece, with all their victuals, and armes. It is further true, that we were about 400. miles from our ships, and had bene a moneth from them, which also we left weakly mande in an open roade, and had promised our return in 15 daies. Others haue deuised that the same oare was had from barbery, and that we caried it with vs into <hi>Guiana</hi>: surely
<pb facs="8"/>
the singularitie of that deuice, I do not well comprehend, for mine owne part, I am not so much in loue with these long voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, as to deuise, thereby to cozen my selfe, to lie hard, to fare worse, to be subiected to perils, to diseases, to ill sauours, to be parched and withered, and withall to sustaine the care and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of such an enterprize, excepte the same had more cōfort, then the fetching of <hi>Marcasite</hi> in <hi>Guiana,</hi> or bying of gold oar in Barbery. But I hope the better sort will iudge me by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, &amp; that the way of deceipt, is not the way of honor or good opiniō: I haue herein consumed much time, and, many crowns, &amp; I had no other respect or desire thē to serue her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty &amp; my Country thereby. If the spanish natiō had beene of like beleefe to these detractors, we should little haue feared or doubted their attempts, wherewith we now are daily threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But if we now consider of the actiōs both of <hi>Charls</hi> the fist, who had the Maydenhead of <hi>Peru</hi> &amp; the abundant treasures or <hi>Atabalipa,</hi> together with the affaires of the Spanish king now liuing, what territories he hath purchased, what he hath added to the actes of his predecessors, how many kingdoms he hath indaungered, how many armies, garrisons, &amp; nauies, he hath &amp; doth maintaine, the greate losses which he hath repaired, as in 88 aboue 100 sayle of great shippes with their attillery, and that no yere is lesse vnfortunate but that many vessels, treasures, and people are deuoured, &amp; yet notwithstanding he beginneth againe like a storme to threaten shipwracke to vs all, we shall finde that these abilities rise not from the trades of sackes, and Ciuil Orenges, nor frō ought else that either Spaine, Portugal, or any of his other prouinces produce: It is his Indian Golde that indaungereth and disturbeth all the nations of Europe, it purchaseth intelligence, creepeth into Councels, and setteth bound loyalty at libertie, in the greatst Monarchies of Europe. If the spanish king can keepe vs from forraine enterprizes, and from the impeachment of his trades, eyther by offer ofinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, or by beseiging vs in Britayne, Ireland, or else where, he hath then brought the worke of our perill in greate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes.
<pb n="4" facs="8"/>
Those princes which a bound in treasure haue great aduantages ouer the rest, if they once constraine them to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensiue warre, where they are driuen once a yeare or oftner to cast lots for their own garments, &amp; from such shal al trades, &amp; entercourse, be taken away to the general losse &amp; impoucrith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of the kingdom, &amp; cōmon weale to reduced besides when men are constrained to fight, it hath not the same hope as whō they are prest &amp; incouraged by the desire offpoyle and riches. Farther it is to be doubted how those that in time of victorie seem to affect their neighbour natiōs, wil remaine after the first view of misfortunes, or ill successe; to trust also to the doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a battel, is but a feareful and vncertaine aduenture, seeing therein fortune is as likely to preuaile, as vertue. It shall not be necessary to alleage all that might be said, and therfore I wil thus conclude, that what soeuer kingdom shal be inforced to defend it selfe, may be compared to a body daungerouslie diseased, which for a season may be preserued with vulgar me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, but in a short time, and by little and little, the same must needes fall to the ground, and be dissolued. I haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore laboured al my life, both according to my small power, &amp; perswasiō, to aduance al those attempts, that might eyther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise return of profit to our selues, or at last be a let &amp; impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the quiet course, &amp; plentiful trades of the Spanish nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who in my weake iudgment by such a warre were as easily indaungered and brought from his powerfulnes, as any prince in Europe, if it be considered from how many kingdoms and nations his reuenews are gathered, and those so weake in their own beings, and so farre seuered from mutuall succor. But because such a preparation and resolution is not to be hoped for in hast, and that the time which our enimies embrace, can not be had againe to aduantage, I will hope that these prouinces, and that Empyre now by me discouered shall suffice to inable her Maiesty, and the whole kingdome, with no lesse quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of treasure, then the king of Spayne hath in all the Indies, east and west, which he possesseth, which if the same be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered and followed, ere the Spanyards, enforce the same, &amp;
<pb facs="9"/>
if her Maiesty will vndertake it, I wil be contented to lose her highnes faueur and good opinion for euer, and my life withal, if the same be not found rather to exceede, then to equal what soeuer is in this discourse promised or declared. I will nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the reader to the following discourse with the hope that the perilous and chargeable labors and indeuours of such as thereby seeke the profit and honor of her Maiesty, and the English nation, shall by men of quallitie and vertue receiue such construction, and good acceptance, as themselues would looke to be rewarded withall in the like.</p>
   <byline>W: R.</byline>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>