<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH RE∣spected Friend, Mr. I. P.</title>
           <author>G., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110454_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09810</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20074</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110454</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH RE∣spected Friend, Mr. I. P.</title>
                 <author>G., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A relation or iournall of the beginning and proceedings of the English plantation setled at Plimoth in New England, by certaine English aduenturers both merchants and others : With their difficult passage, their safe ariuall, their ioyfull building of, and comfortable planting themselues in the now well defended towne of New Plimoth. As also a relation of foure seuerall discoueries since made by some of the same English planters there resident. I. In a iourney to Puckanokick ... II. In a voyage made by ten of them to the kingdome of Nawset ... III. In their iourney to the kingdome of Namaschet ... IIII. Their voyage to the Massachusets, and their entertainment there. With an answer to all such obiections as are in any way made against the lawfulnesse of English plantations in those parts</title>
                 <author>Bradford, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected Friend, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>I. P.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Friend: As wee cannot but account it an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blessing of God in direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our course for these parts, after we came out of our natiue countrey, for that we had the happinesse to be posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of the comforts we receiue by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of one of the most pleasant, most health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and most fruitfull parts of the world: So must wee acknowledge the same blessing to bee multiplied vpon our whole company, for that we obtained the honour to receiue allowance and approbation of our free possession, and enioying thereof vnder the authority of those thrice honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Persons, the <hi>President</hi> and <hi>Counsell</hi> for the affaires of <hi>New-England,</hi> by whose boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and grace, in that behalfe, all of vs are ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to dedicate our best seruice vnto them, as those vnder his Majestie, that wee owe it vnto: whose noble endeuours in these their
<pb facs="3"/>
actions the God of heauen and earth mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply to his glory and their owne eternall comforts.</p>
   <p>As for this poore Relation, I pray you to accept it, as being writ by the seuerall Actors themselues, after their plaine and rude manner; therefore doubt nothing of the truth thereof: if it be defectiue in any thing, it is their ignorance, that are better acquainted with planting then writing. If it satisfie those that are well affected to the businesse, it is all I care for. Sure I am the place we are in, and the hopes that are apparent, cannot but suffice any that will not desire more then enough, neither is there want of ought among vs but compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to enioy the blessings so plentifully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon the inhabitants that are here. While I was a writing this, I had almost forgot, that I had but the recommendation of the relation it selfe, to your further consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and therefore I will end without saying more, saue that I shall alwaies rest</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>PLIMOTH</hi> in New-England.</dateline>
      <signed>Yours in the way of friendship, <hi>R. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>