<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Censure of a friende, concerning this worke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110654_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10867</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Censure of a friende, concerning this worke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nevv yeeres gift : The courte of ciuill courtesie: fitly furnished with a plesant porte of stately phrases and pithie precepts: assembled in the behalfe of all younge gentlemen, and others, that are desirous to frame their behauiour according to their estates, at all times, and in all companies: thereby to purchase worthy praise, of their inferiours: and estimation and credite amonge theyr betters. Out of Italian, by S.R. Gent</title>
                 <author>S. R. (Simon Robson)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 18, 18-38, that is 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Censure of a friende, concerning this worke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>OVr Parents well deserue the pricke of price,</l>
      <l>Who giue vs life which we had not before.</l>
      <l>The teachers care deserues great thanke likewise,</l>
      <l>Who traines the childe, and giues the learned lore:</l>
      <l>Immortall praise we ought giue him therefore.</l>
      <l>Some strife hath bin in respect of these things,</l>
      <l>Who best deserues of these two Noble springs.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Though one giue life, the other learning lendes,</l>
      <l>Let reason rule, let wit this matter scan.</l>
      <l>And things are iudgde, according to their endes,</l>
      <l>And prouerbe olde sayes manners makes the man.</l>
      <l>The vitall sprite must yeeld to learning than.</l>
      <l>Wherfore you youthes, sprunge vp from gentle line,</l>
      <l>Vnto this Court your courteous eares incline.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ This Court, the which of Curtesie takes name,</l>
      <l>Declares what port eche Gentill shall insue.</l>
      <l>At all assayes how he himselfe shall frame,</l>
      <l>To follow what, and what for to eschue.</l>
      <l>Thrice happie he whom God shall so indue.</l>
      <l>A thing of weight, and wun for simple price,</l>
      <l>Reiect by fooles, but purchast by the wise.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>