<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>Robinson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110698_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10839</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21112</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110698</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Oberuations diuine and morall : For the furthering of knowledg, and vertue. By Iohn Robbinson</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 324, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>IN framing these myne OBSERVATIONS, Christian Reader, I have had as is meet, first and most regard to the holy Scriptures; in which respect I call them DIVINE: next to the memorable Sayings of wise &amp; learned men, which I have read, or heard, and carefully stored up as a pretious treasure, for mine own, and others benefit; and lastly, to the great volume of mens manners, which I have diligently obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and from them gathered no small part thereof; having also had, in the dayes of my pilgrimage, speciall opportunitie of conversing with persons of divers nations, estates, and dispositions, in great varietie. The names of the authors, specially known, out of whom I gathered any thing, I have, for the most part, expressed: partly to give them their due; and partly, that the authoritie of their persons might procure freer passage for their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and wise sayings, with others: and make the deeper impression of them, in the readers heart. In the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod I have been neyther curious, nor altogether negligent▪
<pb facs="3"/>
as the reader may observ. Now as this kinde of study, and meditation hath been unto me full sweet, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull; and that wherein I have often refreshed my soul, and spirit, amids many sad, &amp; sorrowfull thoughts, unto which God hath called me: so if it may finde answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance with the christian Reader, and a blessing from the Lord; it is that which I humbly crave, specially at his hands, who both ministreth seed to the sower, &amp; fruit to the reaper.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN ROBBINSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>