<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Poem]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110823_Ba4_1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21651</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110823</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Poem]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Du Bartas his deuine weekes and workes translated: and dedicated to the Kings most excellent Maiestie by Iosuah Syluester</title>
                 <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 697, 6, 698-819, 47, 87, 9 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, portraits (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <lg>
      <l>VVHen <hi>Izrell</hi> was in quiet rest and peace,</l>
      <l>And fruitfully the ground gaue her encreise,</l>
      <l>Which seauenty yeer vntilled lay beforne,</l>
      <l>And nothing bare but thistle, weed and thorne;</l>
      <l>It pleased God (vpon his iust correction)</l>
      <l>T'awake his owne, that were of his election;</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="3" facs="462"/>Least that the longsom peace should them withholde,</l>
      <l>And dull their spirits, as doth the warriour bolde,</l>
      <l>Who spoyls his horse with pampring in the stable,</l>
      <l>That makes him for the manaige more vnable▪</l>
      <l>He spred their land with bands of enemies stout,</l>
      <l>Whose cloudes of shot bedimd their land about.</l>
      <l>Their <hi>Hoaste,</hi> with arrowes, pikes, and standards, stood<note place="margin">The Army of Holopherne.</note>
      </l>
      <l>As bristle-pointed, as a thorni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> wood.</l>
      <l>Their multitude of men, the riuers dri'd,</l>
      <l>Which throw the wealthy <hi>Iuda</hi> sweet did slide:</l>
      <l>So that flood <hi>Iordane</hi> finding dry his banke,</l>
      <l>For shame he blusht, and down his head he shrank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>For woe that he his credit could not keep,</l>
      <l>To send one waue, for tribute to the deep.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Scarse had the Haruest-man, with hook in hand,</l>
      <l>Dispoylde the fruit and let the stubble stand:</l>
      <l>Scarse had the hungry Gleaner put in bindc</l>
      <l>The scattered grain, the Shearer left behinde:</l>
      <l>And scarse the flapping flaile began to thresh,</l>
      <l>When vnto <hi>Iacob,</hi> newes was brought afresh,</l>
      <l>That <hi>Holophern</hi> his frontiers did inuade,</l>
      <l>And past all Rivers, straits, and murders made</l>
      <l>So vile, that none he left that drew the breath;</l>
      <l>But olde and young, he put to sodain death:</l>
      <l>The sucking babes, vpon their mothers knee,</l>
      <l>His cruell cut-throates made them all to dee.</l>
      <l>Then like a flock of sheep, that doth beholde</l>
      <l>A wolfe come from the wood vpon their fold,</l>
      <l>Shapes no defence, but runnes athwart the lands,</l>
      <l>And shortly makes of one, a hundreth bands:</l>
      <l>So <hi>Isaaks</hi> sonnes, indreading for to feel</l>
      <l>This tyrant, who pursued them at the heel,<note place="margin">The Hebrews</note>
      </l>
      <l>Dissundring fled, and sought their liues to saue</l>
      <l>In hils, and dales, and euery desert caue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The sheep heard of his flocke had now no care:<note place="margin">Fear of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</note>
      </l>
      <l>But fearing death, fled to som mountain bare.</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="4" facs="463"/>The Crafts man now his lumes away hath layde:</l>
      <l>The Marchant lest his traffike and his trade,</l>
      <l>To hide himself more safely in a vault,</l>
      <l>Then in a Rampier, to sustain th' assault.</l>
      <l>The Lords esteemde them selfes in surer holde</l>
      <l>In Dennes of beasts, then castles gilt with golde.</l>
      <l>Fear lent the wings for aged folke to flie,</l>
      <l>And made them mount to places that were hie.</l>
      <l>Fear made the wofull women for to bear</l>
      <l>Their cradles sweet to hilles that highest were:</l>
      <l>Fear made the wofull childe to waile and weep,</l>
      <l>For want of speed, on foot and hand to creep:</l>
      <l>All where was nothing heard but hideous cries,</l>
      <l>And pitious plaints that did the harts agrise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O Lord (sayd they) wilt thou still, day by day,</l>
      <l>The arrowes of thine anger neuer stay?<note place="margin">Affliction causeth pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Wilt thou that <hi>Calde</hi> conquere vs again?</l>
      <l>Shall <hi>Iuda</hi> yet the <hi>Heathen</hi> yoke sustain?</l>
      <l>Wilt thou again that they make every towne,</l>
      <l>But stony heaps of houses casten down?</l>
      <l>Again shall sacrilegious fire deuoure</l>
      <l>Thy holy house where we do thee adore?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then <hi>Ioachim</hi> the priest of God most hie,</l>
      <l>Who ouer <hi>Iuda</hi> then had chief degrie,</l>
      <l>Stood like a Pylot stout in tempest great,</l>
      <l>Who seeing winde and weather for to threat,</l>
      <l>Yet to his mates, his fear no terrour drawes,</l>
      <l>Nor leaues his ship vnto the wrackfull wawes;</l>
      <l>But, with disguising fear, his face vp casts,</l>
      <l>And stoutly doth gain-stand the balefull blasts:</l>
      <l>Right so this prudent prelate sent, in haste,</l>
      <l>Two hundreth men to passe where men were plac't</l>
      <l>In places strong, and thence commanded them</l>
      <l>For to repair vnto <hi>Ierusalem.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Now since th' Erernall did reueale his will,</l>
      <l>Vpon the sacred top of <hi>Syna</hi> Hill,</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="5" facs="463"/>The Arke of God which wisedom more did holde,</l>
      <l>In Tables two, then all the <hi>Greeks</hi> haue tolde;</l>
      <l>And more then euer <hi>Rome</hi> could comprehend,</l>
      <l>In huge of learned books that they pend:<note place="margin">Sam. 1. 4.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Long wandred it throw trybes, throw kin and kin,<note place="margin">Sam. 2. 6.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And found no certain place of resting in.</l>
      <l>Yea, somtime it the shamefull spoyl hath been</l>
      <l>To sacrilegious hands of <hi>Palestine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Vntill that time, that <hi>Iessies</hi> holy race,</l>
      <l>For euer lodged it in <hi>Iebus</hi> place.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But, for that <hi>Dauids</hi> hands with blood were fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d,<note place="margin">Ierusalem.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Throu infinits of humains he had kild;</l>
      <l>The king of peace would haue a king of rest</l>
      <l>To build his <hi>Temple</hi> farre aboue the best:<note place="margin">Sam. 2. 7.</note>
      </l>
      <l>His house, whose front vpreard so high and eaven,</l>
      <l>That lightlied earth, and seem'd to threat the heaven,</l>
      <l>Vntill that wicked time a tyrant vile,</l>
      <l>Of name and deed that bare the semble stile,<note place="margin">Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar.</note>
      </l>
      <l>That did this king, that building braue he wrackt,</l>
      <l>And to the sacred ground all whole it sackt.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet when, long after, <hi>Abrahms</hi> holy race,</l>
      <l>Of <hi>Tyger</hi> banks had left the captiue place,<note place="margin">Esd. 6.</note>
      </l>
      <l>With combers great they redified with pain,</l>
      <l>That most renowmed house of God again.</l>
      <l>Which though vnto the first it seemd as small,</l>
      <l>As to a Princes house, a shepheards hall:</l>
      <l>And though the hugenes were not as it was,</l>
      <l>Yet sure the height and beauty did surpas</l>
      <l>And overseilde the famous work of <hi>Pharie,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Ephesus</hi> Temple, and the tombe of <hi>Carie,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The <hi>Rhodian Collos,</hi> and the <hi>Caldean</hi> wall,</l>
      <l>That <hi>Semirame</hi> set vp with tourrets tall.</l>
      <l>Also the wondrous work of this same Temple</l>
      <l>Might serue a <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>esiphon</hi> for his exemple:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lysippus</hi> eke to carue by square and line,</l>
      <l>Or guide <hi>Apelles</hi> pensile most divine.</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="6" facs="464"/>Heer in this place, all <hi>Izrel,</hi> most deuoute,</l>
      <l>Withdrew themselues to <hi>Salem</hi> round about;</l>
      <l>As when the Heav'n his sluces opens wide,</l>
      <l>And makes the floods vpon the ground to glide,</l>
      <l>The brooks that breaks adoun from diuers hils</l>
      <l>With course impetuous till one deep distils.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Amongst the Dames, that there deuoutest were</l>
      <l>The holy <hi>Iudith,</hi> fairest did appear:</l>
      <l>Like <hi>Phoebus</hi> that aboue the starre doth shine:</l>
      <l>It seem'd that she was made on moulde diuine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This primate then assisted with the kinne</l>
      <l>Of great <hi>Eleazar</hi> (priests whose head and chinne</l>
      <l>Was neuer shav'n) deuoutly on he preast:</l>
      <l>A pearled Myter on his balmed creast,</l>
      <l>And with a holy Alb, with garnettes spred,</l>
      <l>And golden Belles, his sacred bodie cled:</l>
      <l>And slew, and burnt, the bulks (as was the guise)</l>
      <l>Of many a kid, and kalfe for sacrifise:</l>
      <l>And with their blood, the Altars hornes he dyed,</l>
      <l>And praying thus, to God immortall cryed.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>"O Lord of Hoastes, we com not vnto thee,<note place="margin">Prayer.</note>
      </l>
      <l>"To wey our merits with thy maiestie:</l>
      <l>"Nor to protest before thy heauenly might,</l>
      <l>"That sacklesly, thy scourge doth on vs light:</l>
      <l>"But rather we confesse (as true it is)</l>
      <l>"Our sinnes haue iustly merite more then this.</l>
      <l>"But Lord if thou thy couenant would forget,</l>
      <l>"Which thou with <hi>Abrahm</hi> made, and so wilt set</l>
      <l>"For mercy great, thy iustice most seuear,</l>
      <l>"Thou should a greater plague vpon vs rear.</l>
      <l>"Change then our proces from thy iustice seat,</l>
      <l>"And saue vs at thy throne of mercy great.</l>
      <l>"Forgiue vs Lord, and holde, farre from vs all,</l>
      <l>"These plagues, that on our heads are like to fall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Alas, what helpeth vs thy heavy stroke,</l>
      <l>To binde our necks to such a servile yoke,</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="7" facs="464"/>Wherewith th' <hi>Assyrian</hi> tyrants long haue grieved</l>
      <l>Thine <hi>Izak</hi> till their bondage thou relieved;</l>
      <l>If so this natiue ground that new is tild,</l>
      <l>If so these Hostries new with folke refild,</l>
      <l>If so (alas) our chaste and modest Dames,</l>
      <l>Our infants young, our Virgins good of fames,</l>
      <l>Should be a pray to <hi>Ammon,</hi> and to <hi>Perse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>To <hi>Calde,</hi> and the mutine <hi>Parthian</hi> fierse;</l>
      <l>If that we see this Altar made prophane,</l>
      <l>And witches it abuse with Idols vain:</l>
      <l>Yet Lord if thou no pittie on vs take,</l>
      <l>At least great God, do (for thy glories sake)</l>
      <l>Haue pitie on this holy building now,</l>
      <l>Where not a God hath sacrifice but thou:</l>
      <l>Where not a God but thou hast residence,</l>
      <l>To feel the sauour sweet of frankensence.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Hold back (O Lord) the <hi>Caldean</hi> cressets bright</l>
      <l>From these rich <hi>Cedar</hi> vaults of stately hight.</l>
      <l>Preserue these vessels, ornaments of gold,</l>
      <l>From sacrilegious hands of neighbours bolde:</l>
      <l>And let the blood of beasts before thy face,</l>
      <l>Thy Iustice stay, and grant thy seruants grace.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This prayer done, the people went their way,</l>
      <l>Then <hi>Ioachim</hi> conuen'd, that present day,</l>
      <l>The princes all of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and them praid,</l>
      <l>Gainst this mischief for counsell, and thus sayd:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Companions, if your former zeal remain,</l>
      <l>If ardent loue to God ye still retain:</l>
      <l>If wife, or childe, may cause your care or loue,</l>
      <l>Which should the Centers of your senses moue:</l>
      <l>If in your brests a noble hart doth bide,</l>
      <l>Let deed bear witnes at this wofull tide.</l>
      <l>For, sauing God and your foresight, in deed</l>
      <l>Tis done, tis done with vs, and all our seed:</l>
      <l>And after this, th' <hi>Immortall</hi> shall not see</l>
      <l>This altar fume before his maiestee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="8" facs="465"/>
      <l>When th' <hi>Air</hi> is calme, and still; as dead and deaf,<note place="margin">Comparison.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And vnder Heav'n quakes not an aspin leaf,</l>
      <l>When Seas are calme, and thousand vessels fleet</l>
      <l>Vpon the sleeping seas with passage sweet,</l>
      <l>And when the variant winde is still and lowne,</l>
      <l>The cunning Pylot never can be knowne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But when the cruell storme doth threat the Bark</l>
      <l>To drowne in deeps of pits infernall dark,</l>
      <l>While tossing tears both father, mast, and sail,</l>
      <l>While mounting seems the Azur sky to skail,</l>
      <l>While driues perforce vpon som deadly shore,</l>
      <l>There is the Pylot knowen, and not before.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Alas, I pray you then what care and strifes</l>
      <l>Haue we to keep our honours, goods, and lifes?</l>
      <l>Forget not then the care of this same place,</l>
      <l>Your countreyes weale, Gods glory and his grace:</l>
      <l>But humbly giue your selues into the hand</l>
      <l>Of God most high, and with a holy brand</l>
      <l>"Repurge your spirits from euerie hatefull sinne,</l>
      <l>"Which causeth God his Iustice to begin:</l>
      <l>And see what may to God be agreeable,</l>
      <l>For <hi>Iacobs</hi> weal, and for you profitable.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This said: an ancient traytour, from his youth,</l>
      <l>Who fostred gall in hart, with hony in mouth,</l>
      <l>Enforcing from his eyes som fained tear</l>
      <l>(To cloke his malice) spacke as ye shall hear:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>My tongue me fails, my hair for dread vp-starts,</l>
      <l>My heavy spirit from pensiue corps departs,<note place="margin">The oration of a subtill worldling.</note>
      </l>
      <l>When I be think me of yone tyrant stout,</l>
      <l>Who hath bed round the world with bloud about,</l>
      <l>Approching threats our townes with fiery flames,</l>
      <l>Our selfs with death, dishonour to our Dames:</l>
      <l>Yet when I call to minde the curtsie great,</l>
      <l>That this great Lord doth vse, who doth intreat▪</l>
      <l>Not onely those that beastiall are become,</l>
      <l>And haue their hope in brutall Idols <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>▪</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="9" facs="465"/>But euen to zealous folke who do embrace</l>
      <l>The faith, and law (like vs) of <hi>Abrams</hi> race:</l>
      <l>Who, being well aduisde, did humbly sue</l>
      <l>His pardon, and escap't his vengeance due;</l>
      <l>Then thanke I God, who sends vs such a foe,</l>
      <l>As plagues the proude, and lets the humble goe:</l>
      <l>For we assoone shall vanquish him with teares,</l>
      <l>As will be long to wrack him with our weares.</l>
      <l>Then whil'st we may haue choise of eitherstate,</l>
      <l>Of peace or warres, his fauour or his hate;</l>
      <l>Let vs not follow (seeing skath at hand)</l>
      <l>The follie of our fathers, to gainstand:</l>
      <l>But rather let vs beare another saile,</l>
      <l>And serue his king as best for our availe.</l>
      <l>But think not yet, that I this counsell giue</l>
      <l>For craft, or warrant forthy selfe to liue:</l>
      <l>For I haue els my daies so neerely spent,</l>
      <l>That for to dye I could be well content.</l>
      <l>Th' <hi>Assyrian</hi> neede not in my brest to strike</l>
      <l>His fethred Dart, nor yet his trembling pike:</l>
      <l>Yea, if my youth to me should eft returne,</l>
      <l>And make my youthly bloode within me burne,</l>
      <l>So honour I my God, and country deare,</l>
      <l>That for to dye for them, I would not feare,</l>
      <l>As <hi>Sampson</hi> did, if so my death might yield</l>
      <l>The victory of the <hi>Uizroy,</hi> and the field.</l>
      <l>But most I (feare) least we, with curious zeale,</l>
      <l>Fight for the lawe, yet fight against her weale,</l>
      <l>Against our selfs, to bring so great a wrack,</l>
      <l>That proud, and cruell tyrants shall vs sack,</l>
      <l>And grow in pride (suppressing <hi>Iudas</hi> strength)</l>
      <l>For to contemne the glory of God at length.</l>
      <l>For, <hi>Israell</hi> being lost, who shall ensue,</l>
      <l>To render here to God deuotions due?</l>
      <l>What people spars<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d on this earthly ball</l>
      <l>From <hi>Indian</hi> shoare to where the Sunne doth fall,</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="10" facs="466"/>Or from the Climate of the northren blast,</l>
      <l>Vnto that place where sommer ay doth last;</l>
      <l>Hath God elect, save <hi>Israell</hi> for his owne</l>
      <l>Vpon this Hill to have his glory showne?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>At this the valiant <hi>Cambris</hi> of renowne,</l>
      <l>With righteous rage grew pale and gan to frowne,</l>
      <l>And brake the silence with a vehement stile,</l>
      <l>His courage mov'd the Princes all the while.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nay rather where I stand let ope the ground</l>
      <l>(Quoth he) to swallow me in pit profound:</l>
      <l>Yea rather righteous Heav'n let firy blast</l>
      <l>Light on my head that thou on <hi>Sodom</hi> cast,</l>
      <l>Ere I my malice cloke or oversile,</l>
      <l>In giving <hi>Izac</hi> such a counsell vile.</l>
      <l>For, if the Leader of this folk profane</l>
      <l>Vpon our bodies onely sought to raigne,</l>
      <l>Although that we haue dearely bought alway</l>
      <l>Our freedom from our first maternall day</l>
      <l>(Which dearer is then gold for to be kept)</l>
      <l>I would assent, the holy Church except:</l>
      <l>But since more pride this tyrants heart enroules</l>
      <l>To lay a greater burden on our soules,</l>
      <l>Who are the vassels of that onely King,</l>
      <l>That Thunder sends and scepters down doth thring:</l>
      <l>'Should we forget him who made vs of nought,</l>
      <l>'More then all wondrous things that he hath wrought,</l>
      <l>Who treats and loues vs like our Father &amp; King,</l>
      <l>Still vnder shadowes of his wondrous wing?</l>
      <l>Will he that we receiue a Prince ambitious?</l>
      <l>For God, a gods contemner, <hi>Nemrode</hi> vitious?</l>
      <l>Whose beastly life is of so vile a fame,</l>
      <l>That of a man he merits not the name?</l>
      <l>Goe to, goe to, let men for men assaye</l>
      <l>With sword and shot to deale it as we may:</l>
      <l>The victory lies not in mortall hands,</l>
      <l>Nor barded horse, nor force of armed bands.</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="11" facs="466"/>These are but second instruments of God;</l>
      <l>Who, as him list, may send them euen or od.</l>
      <l>But if our soueraigne God willes such annoy;</l>
      <l>That folke vncircumcis'd our land destroy,</l>
      <l>Because we him offend while we haue breath;</l>
      <l>Alas, yet honour, honour him in death:</l>
      <l>And if we lose and all be ouercome,</l>
      <l>Let patience winne the glory of martyrdome.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Forsooth, though <hi>Assurs</hi> soldiers braue and bold</l>
      <l>Extinguish quite the race of <hi>Izak</hi> old,</l>
      <l>Yet shall they not deface the liuing Lorde,</l>
      <l>As these <hi>Apostats</hi> falsly do afforde.</l>
      <l>For he, who peopled first this world so round,</l>
      <l>But with one man, from whom the rest abound:</l>
      <l>And who long after, in an arke of wood,</l>
      <l>Repaird the waste, made by the genrall flood;</l>
      <l>May he not eke transforme the hardned stone,</l>
      <l>To people who will honour him alone?</l>
      <l>And may not he do now, as he hath donne,</l>
      <l>Who gaue to <hi>Abrams</hi> barren wife a sonne?</l>
      <l>Them giuing Children moe, then in the heauen</l>
      <l>Are starrie Circles, light as firie leauen:</l>
      <l>And mo, then Northren windes (that driues the Rack)</l>
      <l>Of <hi>Cyrene</hi> sands in number can compack;</l>
      <l>Who will obserue his lawe an hundreth folde</l>
      <l>More zealously then wee, who should it holde.</l>
      <l>'Then, fathers chose you warres: for better tels,</l>
      <l>'To lose like <hi>Iewes,</hi> then winne like infidels.</l>
      <l>'Let not the greede of gaine your hearts attame,</l>
      <l>'To leaue the right: preferre not feare to shame.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Scarce enden was th' Oration of this Lord,</l>
      <l>When all the Princes (with a sound accord)</l>
      <l>By word and deed confirmde his good aduise.</l>
      <l>The chiefe Priest, gladdest of this enterprise,</l>
      <l>Vnto the heauen held vp his hands and face,</l>
      <l>And sayd, I thanke the Lord, who of his grace</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="12" facs="467"/>'Conioynes no lesse our wils, then bolds our harts:</l>
      <l>'A sure presage, that God is on our parts.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This done, vnto his princes he diuides</l>
      <l>The tribes and townes, and ordaines them for guides;</l>
      <l>For feare least some of them led with ambition</l>
      <l>In <hi>Izrell</hi> might stirre-vp some sedition.</l>
      <l>So they withdrew, and stoutly did prouide,</l>
      <l>This furious storme of <hi>Mars</hi> for to abide.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then as ye see sometime the honie Bees<note place="margin">Comparison.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Exerce themselfs on buddes of sweetest trees,</l>
      <l>Where they sometime assault the buzzing waspe,</l>
      <l>That comes too neere, their flowrs away to claspe;</l>
      <l>Or when they hony draw from smelling Time,</l>
      <l>Or from the palme, or Roses of the prime:</l>
      <l>And how they draw their wax with wondrous art,</l>
      <l>Obseruing iointure iust in euerie part,</l>
      <l>Both vp and downe they build ten thousand shops,</l>
      <l>With equal spaceful fild vpto the tops:</l>
      <l>Or where the master Bee, of thousand bands,</l>
      <l>Conducts the rest in legions throw the lands,</l>
      <l>Who daily keeps within their Cities wall:</l>
      <l>Their house, their work, their lawes and maners all:</l>
      <l>So thus the sonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> ply'd their paine,</l>
      <l>VVith hote desire their quarrell to sustaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Some built the breaches of their broken town,<note place="margin">Preparations of defence.</note>
      </l>
      <l>That Heaven, and <hi>Panim</hi> yre, had casten down.</l>
      <l>Some other found a cautell, gainst the Ramme,</l>
      <l>To saue the wall vnbroken where it camme.</l>
      <l>Thus <hi>Iacobs</hi> towns on all sides had their flanks,</l>
      <l>VVith <hi>Gabions</hi> strong, with bulwarks and with banks.</l>
      <l>Some others busie went and came in routs</l>
      <l>To terrace towers, some vnder baskets louts:</l>
      <l>Some others also wanting time and might</l>
      <l>To strength their towns, yet vs'd all kinde of slight,</l>
      <l>To dig vp ditches deepe, for cisterns good,</l>
      <l>To draw them to the best and neerest flood.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="13" facs="467"/>
      <l>While th' Armorers with hammers hard and great</l>
      <l>On sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hies strong the sturdy steel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eate,</l>
      <l>And makes thereof a corpslet or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>acke,</l>
      <l>Sometime a helme, sometime a mace doeth make,</l>
      <l>While sheepherds they enarme vnus'd to danger,</l>
      <l>While simple birds, and whiles the wandring stranger;</l>
      <l>Thetilling Culter then aspeare was made,</l>
      <l>The crooked Sithe became an euened blade:</l>
      <l>The people foode forgets, no ease they take,</l>
      <l>Some on a horse, some on his proper backe,</l>
      <l>Some on a Cart, some on a Cammell beares</l>
      <l>Corne, wine, and flesh, to serue for many yeares;</l>
      <l>As done these <hi>Emets,</hi> that in sommer tide,<note place="margin">Comparison.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Comes out in swarmes their houses to prouide:</l>
      <l>In haruest time (their toyle may best be seene</l>
      <l>In paths where they their cariage bring betweene)</l>
      <l>Their youth they send to gather-in the store,</l>
      <l>Their sick and old at home do keep the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>kore,</l>
      <l>And ouer grainels great they take the charge,</l>
      <l>Oft turning corne within a chamber large</l>
      <l>(When it is dight) least it do spro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te or seede,</l>
      <l>Or come againe, or weevels in it breede.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>