<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH
AND MIGHTY KING, IAMES
BY THE GRACE OF GOD KING
of great Brittaine, Fraunce and Ireland, de∣fender
of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Downame, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110203_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20736</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7118</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110203</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH
AND MIGHTY KING, IAMES
BY THE GRACE OF GOD KING
of great Brittaine, Fraunce and Ireland, de∣fender
of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Downame, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures on the XV. Psalme : read in the cathedrall church of S. Paule, in London. Wherein besides many other very profitable and necessarie matters, the question of vsurie is plainely and fully decided. By George Dovvname, Doctor of Diuinitie. Whereunto are annexed two other treatises of the same authour, the one of fasting, the other of prayer</title>
                 <author>Downame, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 362, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH
AND MIGHTY KING, IAMES
BY THE GRACE OF GOD KING
of great Brittaine, Fraunce and Ireland, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender
of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR Maiesties gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
acceptance of
my Treatise concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Antichrist, hath
emboldened me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat
these my labours
vnto your Highnesse,
which are in no other
respect worthie of your royall patronage, but
that they haue bene imployed in the expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of an excellent Psalme of the royall
Prophet <hi>Dauid;</hi> whose writings the holy
Ghost hath the rather commended to poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
that by his example Kings and Princes
might be admonished to spend part of their
time, which they may spare from their royall
administration, in heauenly meditations, and
spirituall exercises: whereby they might ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="3"/>
assurance to themselues, that after their
earthly kingdome is ended, they shall inherit
an euerlasting kingdome in heauen: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
it be a singuler fauour of God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed
vnto them, that they should so beare the
image of his power and authoritie amongst
men,<note place="margin">Psal. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 6.</note> as that they should bee called Gods:<note place="margin">Exod. 22. 28.</note>
yet godly and Christian kings, are not so
much to glorie in the fruition of their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
crownes and kingdomes; as to solace
themselues in the comfortable expectation
of that incorruptible crowne of glorie, which
is laid vp for them in heauen: For which
cause King <hi>Dauid</hi> thought it to be his dutie,
to giue all diligence (as <hi>Peter</hi> since hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted
vs all) to make his calling and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
sure:<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 10.</note> and by vndoubted testimonies
and infallible tokens, to gather assurance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
himselfe, that hee was the true child of
God. And that he should not take his marks
amisse, (as men are apt to deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selue
in this point) he intreateth the Lord in
this Psalme to reueale vnto him the vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
marks of the sons &amp; heires of God: which
hauing learned by the information of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Ghost, he publisheth them, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
good of the Church: Shewing as it
<pb facs="3"/>
were from the Oracle of God, that not all
that professe the true religion, nor all that are
able to discourse therof; but those that walke
worthie of their calling, that behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
as it becōmeth the children of the light,
that is, that liue vprightly, worke righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
speake the truth from their hearts, &amp;c.
are the sound members of the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
vpon earth, and shall bee inheritors of
glorie in the Church triumphant in heauen.
The meditation and practise of which things
I do so much the more boldly commend to
your Maiestie, because it euidently appeareth
by your former both studies in priuat, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
speeches in publicke, and writings publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
you haue propounded <hi>Dauid</hi> to your
selfe as a patterne for imitation. And now as
a Minister of God, I exhort your Highnesse
to immitat him still, as in speaking and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
so especially in the conscionable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
of Christian duties: that you may bee
more and more (as he was) a man according
to Gods owne hart, walking before the Lord
as he did in truth, and righteousnesse,<note place="margin">1. King. 3. 6.</note> and
vprightnesse of heart; and gouerning and
guiding the people of God, according to the
integritie of his heart,<note place="margin">Psal. 78. 71. 72.</note> and the singuler wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="4"/>
of his hands. So shall the Lord take
pleasure in you, as he did in him, and will not
onely giue your Highnesse long and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous
dayes, but will also blesse your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie
after you, and establish them in the
throne of these kingdomes for euer, to the
euerlasting glorie of his name, and the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
good of his Church: which mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
the Lord graunt for his
Christs sake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <signed>Your Maiesties
obedient and loyall subiect,
<hi>George Downame.</hi>
   </signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>