<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the christi¦an Reader euerlastynge gretynge in the Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110813_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01664</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11802</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110813</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the christi¦an Reader euerlastynge gretynge in the Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise againste the preuee masse in the behalfe and furtheraunce of the mooste hylye communyon : made by Edmund Gest. Reade gentyll reader and then iudge. M.D.XLVIII. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <author>Guest, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>184 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the christi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an Reader euerlastynge gretynge in the Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Volde god (dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re reader) soch a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son had attempted, and attempted, had perfected, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, had openly publyshed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worthy disclose and disproue of the vnsufferable abhominatiō of the popysshe priuate pryuye masse, an enterpryse no lesse ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deful than auayleable at al sea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons, and for all personnes, and namely at thys present, whyche is, thanke be vnto the lord God, so fauourable and benefyciall to the furtherāce of the gospell truth, and so preiudicial &amp; hurt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="6"/> to the hinderance of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: who for hys worthy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege perfectly knew, worthely &amp; conninglye, for hys hartie zeale wolde earnestlye, for hys bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes durst openly, and for his elo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quence wold eloquently, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly handel, and discouer the sayd vngodlynes, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kemanly paynt the same before thyne eyes. For why as it is ryghte conuenable &amp; behouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that as eche vngodlye, and exchueable vice, so the hertofore mencyoned ydolatrie, or ymage worshyppe must of force be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, and sensyblye dysclosed, not onely for that it is a doying both haynouse and wycked, but by reason it is also pretensed &amp; cloked, wtyh the pretence and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped
<pb facs="6"/> name of the Euāgelicall truthe, &amp; recompted in maner of eche man, (thee more pytye) for the worthyest vertue, and for a worshyp not to man alone, but to God also, mooste seruiceable and acceptable. To murder a gyltlesse personne, is a defaulte full greuouse, and thy selfe besy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, moch more greuouse, but not thy selfe alone, and an other but a greate compaignye of innocē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes wythall, that is mooste gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouse of al. What sayd I moost greuouse? Noo not so. For thee sayde murder compared wythe the slaughter of one poore seely soule, is in respecte thereof, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge greuouse at all, By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son as one soule sourmounteth,
<pb facs="7"/> and passeth in worthines an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynite number of bodies, so the slaughter of one soule is more greuouse, thā the murder of an vnnumerable sorte of bodyes: Howbeit the murder of sondrie soules is more greuouse thā of one, &amp; so consequētly the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of an infinite sorte is passin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge greuouse In respect wherof, Oh what a greuouse cruel dede is our solytary and alone mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe, whych doeth murder not the bodies alone (a wycked and a cruel dede), but which is most greuouse and wycked of al) the soules also, not for a tyme, but for euer: not to be without plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure and greuance, but to be in endeles wofulnes, not of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn of the worshippers &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teners therupō, but of eche one wythout restraynt, onlesse he in
<pb facs="7"/> tyme become repētant, whether he be a pryue masser or a pryua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te masse helper, whether he bee an hartie hearer or proctour of the sayd masse,<note place="margin">Roma. 1</note> so that in effecte he be a solytarye masse worship<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, for as S. paule auoucheth not euyll workers alone, but theyr approuers and mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for that they be lyke myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, shalbe lyke punyshed, Yf the eatyng of an apple in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyse dyd worthely and merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouslye slaye as questionles it dyd not bodely only, but ghoste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly also, not Adam alone but his wyfe also, &amp; not thē alone but al theyr posterite, and that not for a tyme, but euerlastinglye, for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it was directely agaynst the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse commandemente of god, otherwyse beyng nothing dero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatorye to God or preiudiciall
<pb facs="8"/> to man: Certaynlye then oure alone massynge, for so moch as it is not onelye a breache of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des open and holye commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente, as the eatynge of thee inhibited forbydden apple was, but an open ymage worshyp al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, and a forged made seruice of god, whych is a default, no lesse haynouse than the sayd breache, yea, and more too: doeth moche more murder, aswel ghostely as bodely, not onelye the doers and kepers of thee pryuate Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, but thee vpholders also, and worshyppers there vpon, onlesse they hartelye, and that in thys presente lyfe repent them selues for the same. For a double fault, deserueth a double death a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dampnatyon aswell of thee as
<pb facs="8"/> agreers and fauourers thereof, as of the authors, and doers, of the same, Is it not a wicked doy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge to endamage an innocente bodye? and is it not a mysdede moche more wycked, to murder the same? yes verely. Thā reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyles here vpon gatherable, it is oure alone massing is a wycked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vncomparable, By reason therein Christes bodye, whyche passynglye surmounteth all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delye creatures, bothe in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes dignitie, and in acceptan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce wythe Godde is assayde daye by daye of thee alone Massers, to be mortefyed &amp; done to death. In consideration (wherof) good Christian reader, I beseche thee by the precyouse deathe of oure alone Sauiour Iesu Christ em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brase lowe and frequent onelye,
<pb facs="9"/> the most sacred cōmunion chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes owne ordynaunce the true masse, the true sacrament exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiue of christes body &amp; bloud, the verye ghostely nurryture &amp; foode both of oure bodyes and soules, into lyfe euerlastynge, &amp; vtterly eschue auoyde, &amp; deteste the pryuate masse, thee vsurped and false named communiō, or masse, the pretēsed &amp; conterfayte sacrament, mans ordynaunce &amp; tradycyon, the presente poyson both of our bodies and soules, into death not temporal alone, but eternal also. What is sacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge that vnsyttyng haynouse and abhominable vyce, but an embecilmente and stelthe of an holy thing out of an holy place, whych is adiuged the more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ful haynouse and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble in respect of thee more holye
<pb facs="9"/> thynge embecilled, and stollen out of the more holy place wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon it formally argueth oure pryuate massing is a sacriledge moost vnsytting, haynouse and detestable. For asmoch as it is a stelth of holye thinges, not of the basest sute as candelstickes sencers, crosses and chalices be, but of the holyest and chiefeste kynde, namely of christe, of the holy ghost, of true relygyon, of fayth, of godlynes, reposed and placed not in a stony temple or aulter but in a christian &amp; faith, ful hart which is iustly estemed more preciouse and holy than a thousād stone tēpels or aulters whych after thee report of paul is the temple of the holy ghoste &amp; the mansyon place of the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed trynitie,<note place="margin">i, Cor, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Iohan, 14</note> as christe hym selfe wytnesseth in Iohā. The more
<pb facs="10"/> preciouse marriage, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more hay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouse default is the breach ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. What marriage is in worthy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to be compared wyth the spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall marryage, that is betwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne christ and vs? Verely none at all, By reason wherof our alone massinge muste remedilesse be a moost haynouse trespace, For that it disseuereth the sayd mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and enforseth vs to whore with false goddes agaynst christ the lyuinge God oure spirituall husbande. Oh Lorde what an vnspeakeable and vncompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vyce is thee Pryuee Masse. In case she dyd but murder mēs soules &amp; bodies she were to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but sythe she attēpteth thee, slaughter of the blessed bodye of christ, sythe she embecilleth &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out of our hartes christ the holy ghost, &amp; theyr body &amp; soule
<pb facs="10"/> sauing frutes, sithe she fōdereth and diuorseth the marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene christ &amp; vs: she must no re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medy be vncomparably &amp; vnspe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keably wycked. Is it not a lamē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table fyght, to behold how hygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men esteme this pryuate mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se whych mothereth so manyfol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and haynouse vyces? Is it not great pytye to see how she is suffered and frequented emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geste vs? Is it not a deadely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse to respect the worthy cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in thys realme, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greate number of them, and yet not one to wryte agaynste hyr? Who yf they wold, could handle &amp; vtter hyr accordīgly? Yeas truli. Wel sythe they (who perfectly cā) wyl not wryte agaynst the sayd mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, sythe it is nedefull, that her synfulnes to longe dyssembled, shoulde be openly vttered, sythe
<pb facs="11"/> sythe I am enforced in conscien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce in thys greate vnseasonable sylence emong y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great dyuines in this behalf, to declare my sto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke agayn here, I wil by god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des grace vndertake to wrytte agaynst the hertofore mencyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned masse, notwithstāding I am nothing fyt or suffycient to the ful perfourmaunce of so greate an enterpryse occasyoned so to do,<note place="margin">luke. 23</note> through this the sayinge of christ, yf my dysciples wyl hold theyr peace the stones shal spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke wherby he doeth vs to wyt y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, it is hys wyl &amp; prouidence that whan the learned refuse to sette forth hys truthe, the vnlearned shulde further and promote it? Better it is somewhat to wryte and enueyghe agaynst the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyshe masse, and that grosly thā not so godly nothing at al. Bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="11"/> it is that the rude ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple shuld by my talke perceaue somwhat of the sinfulnes of the sayd masse, than through my sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence nothynge at all, Better it is that the sayd people shuld be somewhat wythdrawē frō theyr receaued masse errour, thā that they shuld wholy after theyr ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>costumed wonte endure in thee same. In respect wherof that what I cā possible deuise to the vtterāce and reprofe of the faultes incidēt to thee pryuate masse euē now by gods assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance do I wryte. Therfore good reader gyue heedy attendaunce therto:</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>