<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORshipfull, Sir Thomas Smith of Hough, in the Countie of Chester, Knight; Francis Pilkington Batchelor of Musicke, and Lutenist, wisheth all happines in this life, and eternall felicity in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Pilkington, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110423_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09654</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19923</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110423</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORshipfull, Sir Thomas Smith of Hough, in the Countie of Chester, Knight; Francis Pilkington Batchelor of Musicke, and Lutenist, wisheth all happines in this life, and eternall felicity in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Pilkington, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first set of madrigals and pastorals of 3. 4 and 5. parts. Newly composed by Francis Pilkington, Batchelor of Musicke and lutenist, and one of the Cathedrall Church of Christ and blessed Mary the Virgin in Chester</title>
                 <author>Pilkington, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Browne, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <distributor>Barley, William, Assignee(s etc.) of</distributor>
                            <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                            <distributor>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>118 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<seg rend="sup">shipfull,</seg> Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> of Hough, in the Countie of Chester, Knight; <hi>Francis Pilkington</hi> Batchelor of Musicke, and Lutenist, wisheth all happines in this life, and eternall felicity in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, there is held an infallible opinion, that the sacred Art of <hi>Musicke</hi> (being chiefly illustrated by Voyces) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all Artists, in respect of the compasse and quality of voyces and instruments, doe limit it within scales and other certaine dimensions, is in it owne nature INFINITE; reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the base Earth (being as it were the GAM-VT or ground) to the highest E. LA. of the incomprehensible hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens: For demonstration whereof, GOD to his great Glory, doth diuersly and wonderfully enable his creatures thereunto, teaching man vpon earth, not onely in mellifluous Notes to chant; but also vpon variety of Instruments sweetly to expresse the hidden secrets of that sacred Science, &amp; not leauing the vast Ayre empty of his glory; he instructeth the early Larke to warble forth his prayse; who, (as some hould) learneth his layes from the musicall motions of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spheares, and from thence to transcend vp to the seate of the most highest, the elected Saints and Angels doe in heauenly Himmes, sing perpetually <hi>Te deum</hi> to the holy Trinitie, sitting on the Throne of most Maiesticke glorie.</p>
   <p>In which quality of Musicke (Right worshipfull) hauing spent a great part of my time, I haue now (after some others) of late produced this small peece of worke; which albeit for the insufficiency thereof, I doe hold to be too vnworthie to be presented to your Worship, yet in regarde of the many and manifold fauors, which I haue receiued at your hands, and your exquisit skill, both in the Theorique and Practique of that excellent Art; I doe presume to tender it to your Patronage and protection, chusing rather to be censured for ouer-boldnesse, then to be taxed with ingratitude or forgetfulnesse. And so humbly desiring your Worship to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this, and to shield it from all pragmaticall and stigmaticall detractors; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till my best skill and endeauour, shall incite my weake Muse to performe some worke of better worth, I craue pardon for my bouldnesse, and commit your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and the good Lady your wife, to the blessed tuition of the GOD of Israell.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my mansion in the Monastery of Chester</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the</hi> 25. <hi>day of September</hi> 1612.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your worships in all obseruancy <hi>Francis Pilkington.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>