<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110758_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11257</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21520</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110758</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A ievvell for gentrie : Being an exact dictionary, or true method, to make any man vnderstand all the art, secrets, and worthy knowledges belonging to hawking, hunting, fouling and fishing. Together with all the true measures for winding of the horne. Now newly published, and beautified with all the rarest experiments that are knowne or practised at this day</title>
                 <author>T. S.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Helme (Helmes), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Oliffe (Olive), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Games and recreations</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Collection (Gentle Reader) how euer in former Impressions dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and rob'd of his best lynaments by an vnskilfull Register, or a more ignorant workeman (both being farre to seeke in the Arts, and in the Antiquitie of the the Phrase) was notwithstanding in it's first birth the childe of the most excellentest Father that euer begot, in memory, any worke of this nature, and was for the glory thereof the first booke that euer was Printed in this Kingdome, as may appeare by the record of Bookes then Printed at Saint <hi>Albons.</hi> Now for as much as the defects were so grosse that <hi>Trestram</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe would hardly haue knowne so neare a kinsman, I haue for the worlds generall satisfaction reduc't it so truely to the naturall beautie of his owne Parents, that not the seuerest, but with much content would willingly imbrace it. And whereas the alterations, and begettings of times haue brought forth many notable and famous experiments, vnknowne or assayed by our first Ancestors, I haue also gathered them together,
<pb facs="4"/> and so made to their excellent grounds the rare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of latter wits, that the most curious shall not neede to seeke further for any necessary knowledge in any of these seuerall recreations: for hee shall learne heereby both absolutely to doe and speake whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beseemes the person of such a professor: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it hath beene gathered with Care, imbrace it with Loue, and I will wish thee what I would haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen giue mee; The name of a good man.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>