<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The Honor of him, to whom the Noble Fraternity of Drapers, his Worthy Bro∣thers haue Consecrated their Loues, in costly Triumphs; the Right Honorable, MARTIN LVMLEY, Lord Maior of this Renowned City.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110011_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07516</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17901</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110011</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The Honor of him, to whom the Noble Fraternity of Drapers, his Worthy Bro∣thers haue Consecrated their Loues, in costly Triumphs; the Right Honorable, MARTIN LVMLEY, Lord Maior of this Renowned City.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of integrity : A noble solemnity, performed through the city, at the sole cost and charges of the Honorable Fraternity of Drapers, at the confirmation and establishment of their most worthy brother, the Right Honorable, Martin Lumley, in the high office of hi Maiesties Lieutenant, Lord Maior and Chancellor of the famous City of London. Taking beginning at his Lordships going, and perfecting it selfe after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow after Simon and Iudes Day, being the 29. of October. 1623. By Tho. Middleton Gent</title>
                 <author>Middleton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO The Honor of him, to whom the Noble Fraternity of <hi>Drapers,</hi> his Worthy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue Consecrated their Loues, in costly Triumphs; the Right Honorable, MARTIN LVMLEY, Lord Maior of this Renowned City.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy Descent Worthy, (Fortunes Early Grace)</l>
   <l>Sprung of an Antient, and most Generous Race</l>
   <l>Mac'ht with a Vertuous Lady; iustly may</l>
   <l>Challenge the Honor of so Great a Day.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Faithfully deuoted to the Worthines of you Both,</hi> The. Middleton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>