<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Richard Smith in praise of the Aucthor.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110696_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68662</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21121.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110696</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Richard Smith in praise of the Aucthor.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rewarde of wickednesse : discoursing the sundrye monstrous abuses of wicked and vngodlye worldelinges: in such sort set downe and written as the same haue béene dyuersely practised in the persones of popes, harlots, proude princes, tyrauntes, Romish byshoppes, and others. VVith a liuely description of their seuerall falles and finall destruction. Verye profitable for all sorte of estates to reade and looke vpon. Nevvly compiled by Richard Robinson, seruaunt in housholde to the right Honorable Earle of Shrovvsbury. A dreame most pitiful, and to be dreaded</title>
                 <author>Robinson, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Williamson, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ Richard Smith in praise of the Aucthor.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>YE <hi>Muses</hi> all of <hi>Thespyas,</hi> with sacred Songes that sing,</l>
      <l>Novv staie your steppes geue eare a while, and harke what newes I bring.</l>
      <l>Your Sonne that lately did indite with sacred siluer quill,</l>
      <l>In Forest here is fled awaye, vnto <hi>Pernassus</hi> hill.</l>
      <l>VVhere hee among the <hi>Muses</hi> there, and Ladies of great Fame,</l>
      <l>Contrites the time both daye and night, in seruice of the same.</l>
      <l>Beholding of these Goddesse face, with bewtie shining bright:</l>
      <l>Like to <hi>Diana</hi> with her traine, Resplendishing by night.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Ambrosia</hi> is his foode, sweete <hi>Nectar</hi> is his drinke,</l>
      <l>VVhat pleasures are not reaped there, that mortall heart can thinke?</l>
      <l>I doe him deeme in deede, to bee sir <hi>Orpheus</hi> Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>▪</l>
      <l>VVho made the stones to vnderstande, and senceles Trees to heare.</l>
      <l>The sauage Beastes of sundrye kinde, came thrusting in a throng,</l>
      <l>And went out of the vvilsome woodes, to heare his sacred song.</l>
      <l>Suche grace the <hi>Muses</hi> geue to some, for to delight the eare,</l>
      <l>And to allure the mortall mindes, enchaunted as it were.</l>
      <l>A Diamonde for daintie Dames: For Peeres a precious Pearle,</l>
      <l>This <hi>Robinson</hi> the <hi>Rubi red,</hi> a Iewell for an Earle.</l>
      <l>Suche Pearle can not bee bought I knowe, for all the Golde in Cheap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>The graces heare haue powrd their giftes togeather on an heape.</l>
      <l>Suche giftes can not bee graft no doubt, vvithout some power deuine:</l>
      <l>Suche cunning hyd in one mans head, as <hi>Robinson</hi> in thine.</l>
      <l>If I might vewe thy pleasaunt Poemes, and Sonettes that excell,</l>
      <l>Then shoulde I not thirst for the floodes of <hi>Aganippes</hi> vvell.</l>
      <l>Thou profered prise at <hi>Olimpias,</hi> and gotte the chiefest game,</l>
      <l>And through the schoole of cunning skill, hast scalde the house of Fame.</l>
      <l>VVhere thou on stage alone, dost stande Triumphantlye,</l>
      <l>About thy head a Garlande gaye, of liuelye <hi>Laurel</hi> Tree.</l>
      <l>VVhich that these Noble <hi>Nimphes</hi> thought good for blasing theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme,</l>
      <l>In token of this learned Lore, adorned vvith that Crowne.</l>
      <l>If I should penne this praise, as thou doest vvell deserue.</l>
      <l>It vvere a <hi>volume</hi> for to make, and time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> vvould not serue.</l>
      <l>For vvhat needes vvater to bee brought, to powre into the Seas,</l>
      <l>Or vvhy doe I vvith Penne contend about this <hi>Robins</hi> praise?</l>
      <l>VVhome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>umpe of truth hath blowen abroade, that hilles and Dales re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soundes▪</l>
      <l>VVith <hi>Eccoes</hi> from the earth below, vp to the skie reboundes.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶ <hi>Quoth</hi> Richard Smith, <hi>Clark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>