<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Edwarde More to hym that wrothe the booke called the Schole howfe of women.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S110037_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07676</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S110037</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Edwarde More to hym that wrothe the booke called the Schole howfe of women.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A lytle and bryefe treatyse, called the defence of women : and especially of Englyshe women, made agaynst the Schole howse of women</title>
                 <author>More, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>King (Kyng), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ Edwarde More to hym that wrothe the booke called the Schole howfe of women.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF thy name were knowen, that wrytest in thys sorte,</l>
      <l>By womenkind vnnaturally, gyuyng euil reporte,</l>
      <l>(Whom al men ought both yong &amp; old, defend with all theyr might,</l>
      <l>Considering what they do deserue, of euery lyuing wyght</l>
      <l>As in there trauayle taken, sometymes with losse of lyfe,</l>
      <l>To brig such wretches to this world, which make not only strife</l>
      <l>But beyng come to perfyte age, can skant gyue &amp; a forde,</l>
      <l>Unto theyr dāmes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ue thē such, so much as one good word.)</l>
      <l>ywys thou shulde exiled be, from women more and lesse,</l>
      <l>And not without iust cause, thou must thy selfe confesse,</l>
      <l>Onles as in thy booke, so now thou lyst to lye,</l>
      <l>Where are nothinges but rayling iestes of the pore femynye.</l>
      <l>Thy booke intytled is the Scholehouse of women,</l>
      <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ous thyng for them to reade, not pleasant vnto men:</l>
      <l>The style therof declareth no lesse, but that thou art right sage,</l>
      <l>And lyued hast so longe perdye, that now thou dotest for age,</l>
      <l>Lesse meruayle then it is, that if thy othe be spent.</l>
      <l>And of eche one reiected arte and hated as the lent:</l>
      <l>Though thy melancoly, thou canst not els assuage,</l>
      <l>No kynde of way but only thus, on women for to rage.</l>
      <l>Pean to be a folysh worke, thou dost testyfye</l>
      <l>Whych lyke a learned poet, by the fygure onomatopei,</l>
      <l>Trāsformed thou hast into pecock, as proude of hys longe tayle,</l>
      <l>Marck I pray the well, how much there thou doest fayle,</l>
      <l>Pean is more lyke in sounde in our mother tonge</l>
      <l>To pehen then pecock, whose tayle is not so longe,</l>
      <l>Nor set with sundry colors, nor of so pleasaunt hewe,</l>
      <l>That she doth boast &amp; brag theryn, is not thys ryght kewe?</l>
      <l>All men that learned be, allowe the in no case,</l>
      <l>All women eke that wytty be haue cause to curse thy face</l>
      <l>All maydens that vyrgynytye, do couet styll to kepe,</l>
      <l>Through thy accusacyons, haue now iust cause to wepe</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>
All yongmen that intende, to lyue in Uenus lawe</l>
      <l>I meane in matrymony, hauyng of god the awe</l>
      <l>May well deryde &amp; mock thy folyw &amp; lewde pranck</l>
      <l>Wherin, I dare be bold to say, thou had more payne then thank</l>
      <l>In married men such feare there is, and such contynuallawe</l>
      <l>That moost of them beleue ywys they be of moyses lawe</l>
      <l>And fynaly to conclude, the beste and eke the wourst,</l>
      <l>For thys thy foolysh entrepryse, may hold the well accurst.</l>
      <l>Repent therfore repent I say, acknowledge ones thy fact,</l>
      <l>Recant I rede the, &amp; confesse, thy lewde &amp; synfull act,</l>
      <l>Which doth not hurte to one, but all of eche degree</l>
      <l>Haue cause to b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd theyre browes therat, as oft<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> as they it see</l>
      <l>Although to call it in agayne, it be now past thy hand</l>
      <l>yet to recant ease thou shalte fynd, I wyl thou vnderstand</l>
      <l>For yf that Iudas perdan had asked by and by</l>
      <l>Of god he had obtayued it, as scriptures testifye</l>
      <l>Now to conclude and make an end, I wyll apply my wytt</l>
      <l>In writing for good women all as is moost meete and fitt.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>