<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NO LESSE EXCELLENT THEN HO∣NORABLIE DESCENDED Gentlewoman, Mistresse Anne Herne.</title>
           <author>T., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111433_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13797</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111433</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NO LESSE EXCELLENT THEN HO∣NORABLIE DESCENDED Gentlewoman, Mistresse Anne Herne.</title>
                 <author>T., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Alba : The months minde of a melancholy louer, diuided into three parts: by R.T. Gentleman. Hereunto is added a most excellent pathetical and passionate letter, sent by Duke D'Epernoun, vnto the late French King, Henry the 3. of that name, when he was commanded from the court, and from his royall companie. Translated into English by the foresaid author</title>
                 <author>Tofte, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>146 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE NO LESSE EXCELLENT THEN HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLIE DESCENDED Gentlewoman, Mistresse Anne Herne.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>PVre Lampe of Vertue, burning alwaies bright,</l>
      <l>VVho, Grace in me (vnworthie) dost infuse:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Cleere Sunne</hi> that driu'st each doubtfull Mist from sight,</l>
      <l>The firm'st Maintainer of my crased Muse;</l>
      <l>Lo I this <hi>mournfull Verse</hi> in sable weede,</l>
      <l>From sorrowes Cell, do send thee for to reade.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Daine thou with cheerfull looke, what my sad eye</l>
      <l>Distils from Lymbeck of a bleeding Hart;</l>
      <l>Fruits of True Loue disdainde most wrongfully,</l>
      <l>Vouch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>afe of me (as of my Dutie) part,</l>
      <l>A Wofull Wight, indebted paieth thee so,</l>
      <l>Bankroutes in pleasure, can but pay with woe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As often as the Moone doth change her course,</l>
      <l>And Sunne to nouell Signe doth enter in:</l>
      <l>So often I do call still for remorse,</l>
      <l>Whilst endles sorrow doth new Griefe begin.</l>
      <l>Once I each Month to CRVEL ALBA make,</l>
      <l>A MONTHS MIND, yet no pitie she doth take.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Thou art the SHADOVV of her SVBSTANCE faire,</l>
      <l>Resembling her most perfectly in Shape:</l>
      <l>Ah then but smile, and it shall ease my care,</l>
      <l>Though stint it cannot, her nere dying hate:</l>
      <l>Grant me this <hi>Boone,</hi> and neuer shall my Verse</l>
      <l>Leaue, of thy Christall BROOKE praise to rehearse.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Humbly deuoted vnto your matchles Vertues. <hi>R. T.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>