<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111823_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05569</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15691</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111823</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iohn Huighen van Linschoten. his discours of voyages into ye Easte &amp; West Indies : Deuided into foure bookes</title>
                 <author>Linschoten, Jan Huygen van</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 197, 4, 198-259, that is 295, 3, 307-462, 2 pages, 12 plates (some folded), maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Vcian</hi> in one of his <hi>Dialogues</hi> intituled <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or <hi>Surueyers,</hi> writeth of <hi>Charon</hi> the old <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie-Man</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> that vpon a great desire which he had conceiued to view this world and the <hi>Actions</hi> of men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hee begged leaue of <hi>Pluto,</hi> that hee might haue a playing day, and bee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent from his boat, to the end he might satisfie his thirsty humor, that troubled him so eagerly. Meeting with <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie</hi> his fellow <hi>Boatswayne,</hi> (for he also conducteth Soules in <hi>Charons</hi> Barge) they two concluded together, like the two <hi>Sonnes</hi> of <hi>Alcëus,</hi> to clap the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Pelius</hi> vpon <hi>Mount Ossa,</hi> and when they found that they were not high i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to take the surueigh, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Mount O Eta</hi> vnto them, and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> ouer them all. Vpon the toppe wherof, hauing setled themselues, they did at leysure and pleasure take a view not onely of the <hi>Seas,</hi> and <hi>Mountaines,</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> of the world: but also of the Inhabitants therof, together with their Speeches, Actions and Manners. The same <hi>Author</hi> in another <hi>Dialogue</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Icaro-Menippus</hi> discourseth of the <hi>Cinike Menippus,</hi> who being troubled with the same humor tooke vnto him the right wing of an <hi>Eagle,</hi> and the left wing of a <hi>Vulture,</hi> and hauing fastened them to his body with strong and stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thongs, mounted vp first to the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cropolis</hi> or <hi>Capitol</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> and then from <hi>Hymettus</hi> by the <hi>Gerania</hi> to <hi>Acro-Corinthus,</hi> and so to <hi>Pholoë,</hi> and <hi>Eryman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Taygetus,</hi> and at last to <hi>Olympus:</hi> where he grew somewhat more bragg and audacious, then before he was, and soared higher vpwards till he had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Moone, and then the Sunne, and from thence the Habitation of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> and the rest of the Gods: a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent flight (as he saith) for a well trussed <hi>Eagle</hi> to performe in a day. There he rested himselfe, and discouered all the world and euery particularity thereof, to the end he might the more freely &amp; like a <hi>Scoggan</hi> taunt &amp; scoffe at the <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of men in their seuerall kinds. But to leaue these <hi>Poeticall Fictions,</hi> and vaine Fables, which doo but declare the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man to bee desirous of Nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and curious to know those things whereof he is ignorant; let vs come to those that being neither coniured out of hell, nor rapt into the heauens, but of their owne honourable disposition and instinct of Nature, haue not onely compassed Sea and Land in their own persons to learne and beholde <hi>Nations, Realmes, Peoples</hi> &amp; <hi>Countries</hi> vnknowne, for the augmentation of their owne priuate skill and cunning, but also haue committed their knowledge and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to writing for the propagation of the seruice and glorie of God in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> places, and the great pleasure, profit &amp; commodity of their <hi>Countrymen.</hi> Of this kinde and sort of famous men, there hath beene great store in al ages, but specially at the first, <hi>Homer, Anaximander, Hecataeus, Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus, Eudoxus, Timaeus, Eratosthenes, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybius, Possidonius, Dionysius, Strabo, Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Pomponius Mela, Maximus Tyrius, Ptolomée,</hi> &amp; an infinite number of other ancient <hi>Authors,</hi> that haue imployed
<pb facs="4"/>
their wits &amp; industries in this behalf to the singular benefit of our later times, wherein there haue beene most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and exquisite followers of them, as <hi>Munsters, Mercators, Theuets, Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Ortelies, Villamonts,</hi> &amp; many moe, that by the light and good meanes of those their Predecessors, haue run be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde them many degrees, and disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered such New worlds as were neuer knowne to our Fathers &amp; Forefathers; and therefore doo deserue the greater commendation. No doubt, it is very troublesome and laborious to iourney by land for the attaining to this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: but to trauell by <hi>Sea,</hi> is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly most dangerous, but also in a maner almost a desperate estate, considering especially the great perils wherevnto it is hourely subiect, as namely, <hi>Rockes, Flats, Sandes, Gulphes, Stormes, Tempests,</hi> besides the continuall Watching and care in obseruing the <hi>Poles Arctike,</hi> and <hi>Antarctike,</hi> the <hi>Aequinoctiall Line,</hi> the <hi>Altitude</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> of the <hi>Meridian,</hi> the <hi>Circle</hi> of the <hi>Zodiake,</hi> the <hi>Horizon,</hi> the <hi>Tropikes,</hi> the <hi>Longitude</hi> and <hi>Latitude</hi> of Heauen and earth, the <hi>Paralleles,</hi> the <hi>Hemisphere,</hi> the <hi>Zenith,</hi> the <hi>Centre,</hi> and a Rablement of such curiosities, that are able to breake the braines of the soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest man aliue. To these if you will add the intollerable paines, and infinite dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases that doo spend their bodies, you must needs say, that they are the most miserable <hi>Creatures</hi> of the worlde: So that you cannot choose but bee of the opinion of <hi>Anacharsis</hi> that Noble Philosopher, who beeing demaunded whether Number was the greater, that of the dead or that of the Liuing, did redemaund againe, <hi>In which Number do you recken those that trauell on the Sea?</hi> Signifiyng thereby, that such as trauell vpon the Sea are in so great danger of death, that they doo continually dye liuing, and liue dying. And therefore well sayd <hi>Bias</hi> (one of the seuen <hi>Sages)</hi> that <hi>Saylers vppon the Sea were alwayes within two ynches of their death</hi>: &amp; true it is, which the <hi>Latyn Lyrike Poet</hi> writeth, <hi>That</hi> Man <hi>had a Hart of Oke, and was fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with a triple Corslet of Brasse, that first aduentured to commit a slender Boat to the raging Sea.</hi> A Type and <hi>Patterne</hi> of all which miseries, together with the cunning and skilfull Art of <hi>Nauigation,</hi> is comprised in this <hi>Volume</hi> which wee haue in hand, being a most perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West Indies,</hi> or (as they are commonly called) the <hi>Portugall</hi> and <hi>Spanish Indies</hi>: A Worke assuredly very profitable, and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for all such as are desirous &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious louers of Nouelties.</p>
   <p>Of these <hi>Indies,</hi> though not in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished tearmes of <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> sundry <hi>Historiographers</hi> and <hi>Authors</hi> of the old <hi>World</hi> haue made an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mention, &amp; left an exceeding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation thereof, for the wonderfull and rare matters, that were discouered by the seuerall Trauels &amp; Nauigation of diuers famous Captains: as namely, <hi>Alexander the great, Seleucus, Antiochus, Patrocles,</hi> and <hi>Onesicritus,</hi> who had been all in the saide <hi>Indies,</hi> insomuch as one of them held them to be the <hi>Third part</hi> of all the Land that is inhabited, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the great <hi>Prouinces,</hi> puissant <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and vnmeasurable <hi>Ilands</hi> that are found therein: all very fruitfull, and yeelding such treasure and rich Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, as none other place of the whole world can afford. And althogh the curiosity and labour of these aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients was very great, yet greater hath beene the trauell and industry of those which of late time, and in our age hath beene imployed therein. For the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Trauellers had in deede a certain kind of knowledge of this <hi>Countrey</hi> and <hi>People</hi>; but it was very vncertaine and vnperfect: Whereas we in our times are thoroughly learned and instructed by our owne experience, in the <hi>Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Cities, Riuers, Hauens</hi> and <hi>Trafficks</hi> of them all: So that nowe it is become knowne to the whole world. First the <hi>Portingalls</hi> (being great Merchants by reason of their skil in <hi>Nauigation,</hi> which in our dayes is growne to a more full perfection, then euer it hath beene in times past:) they I say first discouered
<pb facs="5"/>
the <hi>Wast</hi> and <hi>Desert Part</hi> of the <hi>Indies,</hi> caused their <hi>King</hi> to be entertayned &amp; honoured among the <hi>People,</hi> encreased and enhaunsed their credit and Name exceedingly, and the sundry commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of their seuerall fruits and spices haue dispersed &amp; communicated not onely to their owne Countrymen, but also to all Nations vnder the <hi>Sunne.</hi> But here the Matter stayed not: For then came the <hi>English</hi> (a <hi>People</hi> that in the Art of <hi>Nauigation</hi> giueth place to none other) and they were incited to take this <hi>Indian Voyage</hi> in hande, and to make it generally knowne vnto their <hi>Island</hi>: &amp; therevpon Syr <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> &amp; Master <hi>Thomas Candish</hi> did not only sayle into the sayde <hi>Indies,</hi> but also tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled round about the world, with a most happy and famous successe. Whose examples diuers honourable Gentlemen and valiant <hi>Captaines</hi> of <hi>England</hi> haue followed, to their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakeable praise and commendation, &amp; the exceeding glory of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: as namely the Right Honourable <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> Syr <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> Syr <hi>Martin Frobisher,</hi> Syr <hi>Richard Greenefield,</hi> Syr <hi>Iohn Hawkins,</hi> and Syr <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> with diuers others named and mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this Booke, And last of all, the <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Lowe-Countreys</hi> beeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed by the diligent search and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of the <hi>English Nation,</hi> fell to the like trafficke into <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he <hi>Indies,</hi> and haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed many Honourable and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Voyages. Among whom the Author of this B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oke, <hi>Iohn-Hugh Lins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chote</hi> of <hi>Harlem</hi> was one, that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>India</hi> for the most part of nine yeares, and had good oportunity of sure and certaine intelligences by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of his seruice vnder <hi>Vincentius da Fonseca,</hi> a <hi>Fryer Dominican,</hi> &amp; by <hi>K. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> created <hi>Archbishop</hi> of all <hi>India.</hi> This Man <hi>Hugh Linschote</hi> behaued himselfe so honestly and warily during the time of his abode there, that he was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in high fauour of his Lord and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, but he was also singularly and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally beloued of all the Inhabitants of the places where hee was most resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. He did most diligently and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderately obserue and collect together all occurrents and accidents that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in his memory &amp; knowledge, and the same hath committed to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the <hi>Dutch Tongue</hi> with all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, to his owne euerlasting praise, and to the benefit of his Countrey, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the seuerall <hi>Mappes</hi> and descriptions of the <hi>Countreys, Cities</hi> and <hi>Townes,</hi> &amp; all the commodities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belonging. Which <hi>Booke</hi> being commended, by Maister <hi>Richard Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luyt,</hi> a man that laboureth greatly to aduance our <hi>English</hi> Name and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Printer</hi> thought good to cause the same to bee translated into the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> Tongue.</p>
   <p>The Volume conteyneth in it foure seuerall Treatises: <hi>The First is,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The First Booke.</note> The <hi>Voyage</hi> or <hi>Iourney by Sea</hi> of the sayde <hi>Hugh Linschote</hi> the <hi>Author,</hi> into the <hi>East</hi> or <hi>Portingall Indies,</hi> together with all the <hi>Sea-Coasts, Hauens, Riuers</hi> and <hi>Cre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>kes</hi> of the same, their <hi>Customes</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> their <hi>Policie</hi> and <hi>Gouernement,</hi> their <hi>Marchandises, Drugges, Spyces, Hearbs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Plants,</hi> the vertues whereof are expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>Annotations</hi> of <hi>Doctor Palu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus,</hi> the learned <hi>Phisitian</hi> of <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>khuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen</hi>: And last of all, a <hi>Memoriall</hi> of such <hi>Accidents</hi> as fell out during the <hi>Authors</hi> aboade in <hi>India.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Second</hi> Treatise <hi>is,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Second Booke.</note> The Descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of <hi>Guinea, Manicongo, Angola, Monomotapa, &amp;c.</hi> with a discouery of the great <hi>Island</hi> of <hi>Madagascar,</hi> and all the <hi>Shallowes, Cliffes</hi> and <hi>Islands</hi> of the <hi>Indian Seas:</hi> The most part whereof was collected before by one <hi>Pigafetta</hi> from the mouth of <hi>Edward Lopez,</hi> and published in <hi>English</hi> the last yeare.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Third</hi> Treatise <hi>is,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Thi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Booke.</note> The <hi>Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Portingales</hi> into the <hi>East In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies:</hi> &amp; from thence to <hi>Malacca, China, Iapon, Iaua</hi> and <hi>Sunda:</hi> And from <hi>China</hi> to the <hi>Westerne</hi> or <hi>Spanish Indies,</hi> and all the <hi>Coast</hi> of <hi>Brasilia, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Fourth and last Treatise is,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Fourth Booke.</note> A most true &amp; exact <hi>Summarie</hi> of all the <hi>Rents, Demaynes, Tolles, Taxes, Imposts,
<pb facs="5"/>
Tributes, Tenths, Third-pennies,</hi> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all the Reuenues of the King of <hi>Spayne,</hi> arising out of all his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Lands, Prouinces</hi> and <hi>Lordships,</hi> as well of <hi>Portugall</hi> as of <hi>Spayne,</hi> collected out of the <hi>Originall Registers</hi> of his seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Chambers</hi> of <hi>Accompts:</hi> together with a briefe description of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>Pedegree</hi> of the <hi>Kinges</hi> of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I doo not doubt, but yet I doo most hartely pray and wish, that this poore Translation may worke in our <hi>English Nation</hi> a further desire and increase of Honour ouer all <hi>Countreys</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and as it hath hitherto mightily aduanced the Credite of the Realme by defending the same with our <hi>Wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Walles</hi> (as <hi>Themistocles</hi> called the Ships of <hi>Athens</hi>·) So it would employ the same in forraine partes, aswell for the dispersing and planting true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Ciuill Conuersation therein: As also for the further benefite and commodity of this Land by exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of such thinges wherein we doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and importation of those <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities</hi> whereof we stand in Neede: as <hi>Hercules</hi> did, when hee fetched away the <hi>Golden Apples</hi> out of the <hi>Garden</hi> of the <hi>Hesperides</hi>; &amp; <hi>Iason,</hi> when with his lustie troupe of couragious <hi>Argonautes</hi> hee atchieued the <hi>Golden Fleece</hi> in <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chos.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>