<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Maden, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111890_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06732</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17179</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111890</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Maden, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs love and affection towards Jerusalem : Delivered in sundry sermons out of his words and carriage when he came unto her, as they are recorded, Luke 19. 41, 42. Wherein are handled, 1 Christs teares which he shed for Ierusalem, and the matter of singular observation i them. 2 The will of God touching mans salvation, as it is generally propounded and revealed in teh Gospell. 3 The sin and misery of Ierusalem, because she would not know the time of her visitation. 4 The day of grace, wherein salvation is offered to the sons of men. 5 The worth of that peace, whic Christ and the Gospell bring with them. 6 The sin and misery of those who liv</title>
                 <author>Maden, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 255, 15 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more availeable for the rectifying of the judgment and understanding of a man in the mysteries of salvation, than a right apprehension and conceit, touching the will of God; to wit, what God is willing to doe for him, and what hee willeth and requireth him to doe for the obtaining of it. The cleare understanding of this, it rectifies a mans faith in matters to be beleeved, either concerning God, or himselfe: it regulates his obedience in things to be done, teaching him how to pray aright with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be heard, and that is, when he asketh any thing according to the will of God<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 5.14.</note>, directing him to walk aright in the way of life; and that is, when he is neither mis-led in his way, nor negligent in his work, but applyes himselfe to God in a wise and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly cariage, suitable to that course of providence that he hath taken for his good.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Touching this will of God, there is something de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in this ensuing Treatise, by which every one may take a true scantling of the good will and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that God beares unto him, by those warme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of love which he finds in the Gospell. Much more might have beene said in this argument, and perhaps in time may.</p>
   <p>Mean while, for the preventing of all mistakes in that which is said already, be pleased (Courteous Reader) to take notice, that it is no part of my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and intention, in any part of these following dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses &amp; meditations, to enter the lists of that dispute and controversie which is now in agitation amongst the learned Divines of the reformed Churches, touching the will of God in the decree of Election. The heat of that contention hath already troubled and disquieted the peace of the Church too much, and want of moderation in some on both sides, through the indiscreet handling, of that unsearchable depth, doth still beget ill bloud in the veins of that body, that should grow up unto an holy Temple in the Lord. As in all other Controversies, so in this, the right stating of the matter in question, helps much for the clearing of the truth; and if that be first done, (I hope) it willfully appeare, that the conclusion here maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned touching the will of God, doth no wayes border upon that controversie; for the matter there in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, is, Whether the decree of Election, as it is terminated, and pitched upon particular persons, be absolute, and irrespective, or out of a consideration of fore-seene faith and perseverance: that is, whether God doe equally will the salvation of all, and have
<pb facs="8"/>
no absolute and irrespective purpose of saving one more than another, before he looke at different qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications in them. It is freely confessed<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ames. Antisy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodal. Amstelod.</hi> 1633. <hi>art.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 130. Non est in quaestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, utrum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us verè sincere, seriò intendat hominis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versionem; sed an pari modo intendat ac procuret om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, &amp;c. qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um praedicatur, conversionem ac salutem.</note> by one that is no stranger to that controversie, nor any wayes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially addicted to the Lutheran side, but in his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and opinion strong enough against it, that the question of it be rightly stated, is not, whether God doe truely, sincerely, and seriously intend the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of that man whō he outwardly calls, but whether he do equally and indifferently intend &amp; procure the conversiō &amp; salvation of all those to whō the Gospel is preached; implying, that both sides agree upō this, that God doth seriously will the salvation of all those to whom he makes an offer and tendry of it in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery of the Word; and that neither part main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains any such decree or purpose in God, touching mans salvation, as is repugnant and contrary to that will of God which is revealed in the Gospell, but sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate unto it. And when he doth positively, and professedly set downe<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 250. Asfirmamus Deum, non pari modo, &amp; gradu, velle &amp; operari ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedenter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versionem eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, qui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertuntur, &amp; qui non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertuntur.</note> the position and conclusion which himself and others hold and maintain against their adversaries, hee makes this expression of it, namely, That God doth not antecedently will the conversion of such as die in their sins, after the same manner, and in the same degree as he doth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of others, whom in time he converteth; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he work equally and indifferently in them both, but that by an antecedent purpose, independent upō any thing in the creature, he absolutely intēdeth, and so accordingly effectually procureth the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of some, leaving others, who lie equally in the same condition with them, and are no wayes inferior
<pb facs="9"/>
unto them, save onely in that previous purpose of speciall love, which he is pleased of himselfe, and for his owne sake, to shew to one more than to another. And this seems to be the mind of those learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in the Synod of Dort<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Act. Synodal. art.</hi> 2. <hi>reject. erro.</hi> 6. Qui impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, et appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, ut incau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp;c. instillēt Deum, quantū ad se attinet, omnibus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, ex aequo voluisse ea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia cōferre, quae per mortē Christi acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur: quod autē quidā prae aliis, participes fiant remissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis peccatorū, et vitae aeternae, discrimen illud pendere, ex libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro eorū arbitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o, se ad gratiam indifferenter oblatam appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cante, non autē ex singulari mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scricordiae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, efficaciter in illis operan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, ut prae aliis gratiam illam sibi applicent.</note>, who speaking of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Christs death and passion, when they come to that distinction of impetration and application, they shew, that they doe not simply and altogether mislike it; and therefore they qualifie their censure thus farre, that they doe reject it onely in this sense, to wit, as it is used to further and lead in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, that God, in respect of himselfe, is willing to bestow the benefits purchased by the death of Christ, equally and indifferently upon all; and that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why some are made partakers of remission of sins, &amp; eternal life, rather than others, it is not primarily from any greater good will in God towards them, or any speciall mercy peculiarly shewed to them before others, but from their own freedome &amp; liberty, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they apply themselves to God more than others, in making after that grace and mercy which is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently offered to both. From whence it appeares, that the matter in question amongst the learned, is onely touching the Decree of Election, how man is conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and looked upon, when God passeth that decree upon him, whether barely and nakedly, as abstracted from all qualifications and conditions which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the covenant of grace, or cloathed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested with such preparatorie gifts of grace, as doe by vertue of Gods promise, intitle him to eternall life. This question I purposely wave, and meddle not withall in this ensuing Treatise, but take that which
<pb facs="9"/>
is generally granted by the more moderate, and best learned on both sides: to wit, that all mankind are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of salvation, upon such terms and conditions as are expressed in the Covenant of grace: that is, if they repent of their sinnes, and beleeve in Christ, and that when God offers life and salvation to all and every one in the ministery of the Word, he is truely willing, and doth seriously intend to bestow the same upon thē, in that way that he hath commanded them to seek it, and according to that course of providence that he hath taken for their good: that is, if they will apply themselves unto him, and follow the counsell and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection that he gives them. And this, if I mistake not, is the general doctrine of the ancient Fathers, the learned Schoolmen, and many modern Divines: both Papists and Protestants, Lutherans and Calvinists, there is none that is well read &amp; versed in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that can much doubt or question the judgement of any of them, save only of those who follow and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Calvins</hi> way, and build upon his foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and yet amongst them (over and besides those that are mentioned in the Treatise it selfe) these two or three testimonies may serve to shew that many of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good note amongst them, are clear in this point:</p>
   <p>First, it appeares by <hi>Musculus</hi> in his Common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the redemption which is purchased by Christ, is upon some condition applyable to the whole world, and to every particular man from the first to the last<note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Muscul. loc. de redemp. generis humani.</hi> Profite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur titul{us} redēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem generis humani, genus autem humanū cōplectitur non unam aut alterā gentem, sed mū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dū universum, omnes videlicet totius orbis na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, cunctos homines à pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo us{que} ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vissimum, &amp;c. ergo quae hic in considerationē veniunt, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ad omnes homines: Scim{us} non omnes fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri hujus redēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, verum illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rū perditio, qui non servantur, haud quaquam impedit, quo minus universalis vocetur redemptio, quae non est uni genti, sed toti mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do destinata, &amp;c. Quod illam homines reprobi non accipiant, neque defectu fit gratiae Dei, neque justum est, ut illa propter filios perditionis gloriam ac titulum universalis redemptionis amittat, cum sit parata cunctis, &amp; omnes ad illam vocentur.</note>: that is, according to the report made in the
<pb facs="10"/>
generall offer of it; for though all be not made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of it, yet their ruine and destruction, which is of themselves, doth not any wayes prejudice or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the generall good will of God towards man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, nor hinder, but that the benefit of redemption may be thus farre termed universall, as that it is in some sort intended for all, and upon some conditions appliable unto all: and he illustrates this by two simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes: First, of the Sun, which may be said to send forth a generall light and influence into all places, and all creatures, and to make them fruitfull, though many of them remaine barren, because the defect and hinderance is not in the nature of the sun, but in other letts and impediments which hinder the effectuall working of it: Even so (saith he) it is with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption purchased by Christ; that Reprobates and wicked men doe not receive it, it is not for want of good will in God towards them; nor through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of that grace he offereth to them, for it is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all, and in the preaching of the Gospell are all invited to it: &amp; therfore it is not fit that it should for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the title of a generall benefit, because the sons of perdition, through their owne fault, deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of it: for as a Medicine may be said to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall, though it doe not actually cure all diseases, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it hath such a vertue in it, that it would heale them, if it were rightly and orderly applyed unto them: Even so the bloud of Christ may be termed an universall medicine, because it hath sufficient vertue in it to heale the sins of the whole world, though it doe actually cure none, but such onely to whom it is applyed.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>The other similitude which he bringeth for the illustration of this point, is drawne from a custome which was used amongst the Iewes, who in the yeare of Iubile, proclaimed a generall liberty to all ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whosoever would, might goe out free, though many remained still in their former bondage, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the benefit of liberty when it was freely offered and tendered unto them: even so in the Gospell, there is a Proclamation published of a generall pardon pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased by Christ, which is offered and tendered to all and every one, upon such conditions as are expressed in the Covenant of grace. The reason why many misse of it, is not for want of mercy in God, but because they are wanting to themselves, and doe not seek for it according to his will.</p>
   <p>Another<note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Paul. Testard. Synops. Doctr. de nat. &amp; grat. thes.</hi> 298. Voluntas antecedens ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralis, est vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas dandi Christum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorem, vocā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ad commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem Christi per media apta et in se suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, dandi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini peccatori, posse si velit, servari.</note> affirmes, that besides that special and particular good will which God beares to some, there is a generall good will which he beares to all, out of which he was moved to send Christ into the world, and out of a consideration, and for that, which Christ hath done and suffered, to crect and set up a throne of grace, and from thence to offer grace, and that by meanes which in themselves are apt, and some wayes sufficient to bring a man to life and happinesse, if they be not hindered by a carelesse neglect on his part.</p>
   <p>And this is plainly delivered by another Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor<note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Ames. Antisy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. p.</hi> 256. <hi>ar.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4 Seriam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam Dei inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem quae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiritur ad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diorum dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sationē, ab illa dispensatione non separamus.</note> mentioned before, when he tells us, that the serious purpose and intention of God, which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the outward meanes, is never to be separated from them; that is, in the administration of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes, there is alwayes a vertuall purpose in
<pb facs="11"/>
God<note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 259. Non simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter negam{us} De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um intendisse in ipsis fidem efficere, est e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim intentio quaedam Dei virtualis et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretativa, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem efficiendi in omni, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, quae sua natura faciunt ad fidem inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerandam. <hi>Et paulo ante,</hi> Non negamus Deū vel intendisse efficere in ipsis quicquam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinens ad fidē: qualiscun{que} n. cognitio ista veritatis fuit, quam hauserūt ex concionibus Prophetarum: pertinebat ad fidem tanquam antecedens praerequisitum, et praeparatio, et Deus candem in illis efficiebat.</note> of doing that, which the meanes in their owne nature lead unto. And again he doth freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that those generall helps which God affords to the men of this world, &amp; those inferior gifts of the Spirit that he works in them, though they be but common works, and common graces, yet they doe in some sort belong to a saving and justifying faith, as previous dispositions preparing and making way for it, and that Gods purpose and intention in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them, is to afford them some more generall helps, which they ought to make use of, for their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance, in the way of their conversion: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God did seriously will their salvation.</p>
   <p>I will adde but one witnesse more in this matter, and that is the testimony of a learned Professor in one of the Vniversities beyond the Sea<note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Jo. Camero. S. theol. in Academ. Salmuriensi Professor. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>praelect. in Misellan: de satisfactione Christi, pag.</hi> 575. Quomodo pro singulis est orandum, eodem modo singulorum salutem vult Deus, at pro singulis orandum est cum conditione, &amp;c. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 576. Ita describit nobis Scriptura, amorem Dei ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentem, ut in eo gradus quosdam inesse doceat, &amp;c. respectu primi gradus, Deus dicitur dedisse Christum pro vita mundi, velle omnium salutem, quatenus nimirum vocat omnes ad poenitentiam. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 584. Rectius faciunt qui Christum pro impiis, sufficienter (ut loquuntur) satisfecisse docent, (quae mea sententia est) quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam sufficientiae vocabulum, mihi amplius quiddam videtur in hoc argumento sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificare, quam multi arbitrantur. <hi>Jbid pag.</hi> 577. Qui hominum amicitiam sibi student conciliare, ii movent quidem affectus, sed (quatenus fieri potest) beneficiis, precibus, hortationibus, significatione amoris, &amp;c. quibus si nihil promovetur, penes eos est culpa, qui se flecti noluerunt: certè qui haec omnia adhibuit, et extra culpam est, et partibus suis ita defunctus est, ut nihil omisisse censeatur. Deus igitur, hominum more, cum hominibus et agit et loquitur, &amp;c.</note>, who thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon those words of the Apostle, God will have all men to be saved, and come to the knowledge of the truth, &amp;c. so as men are bound to pray for the salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all men, so doth God will it: that is, not abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely,
<pb facs="11"/>
but conditionally; for whatsoever God abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely willeth, that is alwayes effected, and cannot be hindered by any thing in the creature; but what he willeth onely upon condition, that may be hindered, because such as faile in the condition by a voluntary neglect, do thereby hinder and keep away good things from them. And thus should every one pray for the salvation of others, not absolutely that God would bring them to salvation, whether they repent or no, but that he would blesse the meanes unto them, and worke grace in them, whereby they may repent and turne unto him, in that way of obedience, that leads to life.</p>
   <p>And againe, he sheweth that the Scripture doth so describe the antecedent love of God towards Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, as that there are certaine degrees of love to be acknowledged in it, whereof the first is more generall, and belongs to all, and out of this love he sends Christ into the world, to pay a sufficient price for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of all, and by that payment to make them capable of salvation, upon such conditions as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in the new Covenant: and out of this love it is that he wills the salvation of all, and so according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calls them to repentance, that they might be saved. As it is amongst men, he that useth all fitting and convenient meanes to gaine another mans good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of him, and to draw his love and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and for that end, makes a signification of the good will and affection he beares him, and shews himselfe ready upon all occasions to doe any good of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for him; and withall, shews him such arguments and reasons, such motives and inducements, as are
<pb facs="12"/>
in their owne nature apt to perswade him thereunto, he may be truly said to desire his love and friendship; though he doe not prevaile with him for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, he hath sufficiently managed and officia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his part, without omitting of any thing that was fit and requisite for him to doe: and the fault and hinderance lies wholly in him that was so inflexible, that no meanes could prevaile with him, or move him to imbrace such a friendly motion. Even so the case stands betweene God and man, in respect of that generall good will and affection that God beares to him: God speakes unto him, and deales with him, as with a reasonable creature; and if he doe not prevail with him, the fault is not in God, or in the meanes that are used by him, but onely in man, who will not apply himselfe unto God, and serve his providence in that way and course that is taken for his good: and he illustrates this by two similitudes: First of the Sun<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 579. Sol 1ste, qui lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet omnibus, dormienti, aut sponte oculos claudenti, certè non lucet, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo tamen solis vitio id accidit: sed illi{us} qui so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis beneficio non utitur. Ita Christus pro omnibus mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus est, sed eos demum illa mors facit beatos, qui vera fide eam amplectuntur. <hi>Ibi. pa.</hi> 585. Captivos redemit quidam nihil minus cogitantes, pretiū numeravit, addidit hanc legē, si eorum quispiam libertatem, libertatisve authorem, aspernatus fuerit, eodem loco esto, ac si <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> non foret pro eo persolutum, ita finge, &amp;c.</note>, which affordeth and sendeth forth suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient light to all, and yet gives no light to those that wink with their eyes, and shut those windows against the light, not through any defect, or want of light in the Sun, but onely through his fault, who will not make use of that benefit which is afforded to him; so it is with the benefits of Christs death and passion, which though they be upon some condition applyable unto all; yet are they effectuall for the salvation of none, save onely those who doe imbrace and lay hold on them by a lively faith.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>The other similitude he useth, is drawne from a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or bondslave, who hath a friend, who layes down such a summe of money for his ransome, but withall addes this caution, that he shall then come to enjoy the benefit of this Ransome, when he comes to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the kindnesse that such a friend hath done for him, and humbly sues, and seeks that he may enjoy it: but if he value his liberty at so low a rate, that he contemneth and despiseth that which hath beene done for him, then it is so ordered, that he shall be in the same place and condition with those that are not redeemed at all. Even so it is here, there is a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent price laid downe by Christ for the redemption of all Man-kinde: now if any one undervalue this mercy, and make light of it, he may be justly upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with this benefit: and though he cavill and quarrell that hee is not redeemed, for as much as he still lies in prison, yet will this availe him little, because the reason why he continues still in prison, is not for want of a sufficient ransome to release him thence, but for want of looking after it: even so it is here; all men are by nature captives and bondslaves: Christ hath laid downe a sufficient price for their ransome, but with this caution, that the benefit of it shall accrue onely to such as doe repent of their sinnes, and beleeve in him.</p>
   <p>The reason why so many misse of that benefit, is, because they will not beleeve in him, nor lay downe their weapons of rebellion, which they have taken up against him.</p>
   <p>Now from all these testimonies, it is plaine and evident, that amongst those who are most opposite to
<pb facs="13"/>
the <hi>Lutherans</hi> opinion in the matter of Election, yet many of them doe so conceive of Gods purpose therein, as that it includes nothing in it contrary to that will which is revealed, and generally propounded in the Gospell. All sides grant, that life and salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is generally offered to all in the new Covenant, and that God seriously intends to give it to all and every one, upon such conditions as are there expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and that is all I contend for in this ensuing Treatise.</p>
   <p>Now that God may be said seriously to will the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of any, there are two things necessary:</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1</hi> That there be in God a reall purpose and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of giving life unto him.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> That the conditions required for the obtaining of it, be some wayes possible, not by the strength of nature, or the power and ability of his own free-will, but by and through those gracious helps which are afforded unto him in the ministery of the Word.</p>
   <p>To have made up the Treatise full and compleat, it had beene requisite to have handled this second point, which I could easily have supplyed, out of some notes and meditations that lie by me: and it was more than once in my thoughts so to have done; but my second thoughts resolved against it, because the laying open of that point, would require a larger dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course than could well have beene concluded within the bounds or limits of a reason or proofe, (as here it must have been) as also in regard that the former point onely was insisted upon, when that Sermon was preached. If thou shalt receive any profit or benefit by that which is here delivered, it is that onely which I
<pb facs="13"/>
have principally endeavored and aymed at. If I misse of my purpose, and the successe be not answerable to my desire, yet let it finde that acceptance at thine hands, which thou art ready to afford to all such as unfainedly wish thy welfare.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>And so I rest, <hi>Thine in our Lord and common Saviour, RI: MADEN.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>