<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111986_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01260</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11374</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111986</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French herald : svmmoning all trve Christian princes to a generall croisade, for a holy warr against the great enemy of Christendome, and all his slaues. Vpon the occasion of the most execrable murther of Henry the great. To the Prince</title>
                 <author>Loiseau de Tourval, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 49, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Herald, whose very phrase bewraies him enough to be french, though he neuer spoke his owne french yet; and who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chose, vpon, so vrgent a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, to speake ill &amp; in a strange language, then not at all; now most rightly presents himselfe first vnto your highnes: because aswell by your merit, as by your fortune, you are one of the chiefest (if not euen the first) vpon whome he calls for the performance of the greatest, most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and most royall duty that euer was yeelded, to the greatest person deceased, to the greatest persons li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. It is no lesse then the cause of God, no lesse then the cause of the Gods; seing, Princes are stiled so, by him that onely is so, and who, by a most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fashion, aboue all other men, after his owne Image made them so: And what a more godly ground for all Christians to take the crosse on them, against him that vnder a gawdy show of many false crosses, the more<pb facs="3"/>crossely because closely, crosseth the onely and true Crosse of Christ? Wherein, if it be not your selfe (vnder the happy auspices of your glorious father, or rather hee himselfe by you) then I see no <hi>Generall</hi> in the world, when our Christian Army must come into the field. An other reason I haue more especially and wholy to apply to your highnes, that which is intended to many; A most speciall and holy zeale to your Princely seruice, which euen eight yeares agoe, brought me into your Country, and still working in my hart, now enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces me rather to giue you a small touch ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, how meane soeuer, then it should be longer hid from you, how much I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>YOVR HIGHNES Most humble, most obedient, and most ready to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded seruaunt, ✚</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>