<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO¦norable Sir Henry Compton Knight, Lord Compton of Compton.</title>
           <author>D., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111775_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21162</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7517</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111775</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO¦norable Sir Henry Compton Knight, Lord Compton of Compton.</title>
                 <author>D., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The paradyse of daynty deuises : Conteyning sundry pithy preceptes, learned counsels, and excellent inuentions, right pleasant and profitable for all estates. Deuised and written for the most part, by M. Edwardes, sometimes of her Maiesties Chappell: the rest, by sundry learned gentlemen, both of honor, and worship, whose names hereafter folowe</title>
                 <author>Edwards, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Disle (Disley, Dizle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>50, that is 44 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norable Sir Henry Compton Knight, Lord Compton of Compton.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONORABLE, AND</hi> my verye good Lord, (presuming vpon your curtesy) I am bolde to present vnto your honor, this smale volume Entituled The Paradise of deyntye deuises, being pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by diuers learned Gentlemen and collected togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the trauell of one, both of vvorshippe and credite, for his priuate vse: who not long sine departed this life, vvhich vvhen I had perused ouer, not vvithout the aduise of sundry my freendes, I determined by their good motion, to set thē in print, who therunto great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye perswaded me, vvith these and like vvords: The vvryters of them, were both of honor and worshippe, besides that our ovvne country men, and such as for their learning and grauitie, might be accompted of among the wisest. Furthermore, the dittis both pithy &amp; pleasant, as wel for the inuentiō as meter, and vvill yeelde a farre greater delight, being as they are so aptly made to be sette to any song in .5. partes, or song to instrument. VVhich well considering, I porposed not to forsake so good an occasion, bese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching your honor to accept it in good parte, cheefely for the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours sake: who thoughe some of them are departed this life, yet their worthy doings shall continue for euer: for like as the shadow folovveth the body, so praise foloweth ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: and as the shadow goeth somtimes before, and sometimes behind, so doth praise also to vertue: but the later it commeth, the greater it is. &amp; to be the better esteemed. Thus fearing to offend your honor with these my rude speaches, I ende, wishing your L. many yeeres of ioy</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your good Lordships wholy to <hi>commaund.</hi> H. D.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>