<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Dowriche, Hugh</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111947_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20782</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7160</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111947</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Dowriche, Hugh</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The iaylors conuersion : Wherein is liuely represented, the true image of a soule rightlye touched, and conuerted by the spirit of God. The waightie circumstances of which supernaturall worke, for the sweete amplifications, and fit applications to the present time, are no set downe for the comfort of the strong, and confirmation of the weake. By Hugh Dowriche Batch. of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Dowriche, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 26, that is 28 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is dayly preaching, and daily printing of good Sermōs, and good Bookes, and yet there is little profiting, and little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment seene to follow, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in words or workes. We haue had precept vpon precept, Sermon vpon Sermon; in euery corner, here a little, and there a little, and yet <hi>Egypt cannot speake the language of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naā. <note place="margin">Esay. 8 13. Esay. 19. 18.</note>
      </hi> Some professors cannot see what is belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their profession, &amp; liue there after.<hi>The Vineyeard yeeldeth but briers &amp; thornes.</hi> The companie of vaine, Papisticall, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <note place="margin">Esay. 27. 5. Ierem. 7. 11</note> and Machiauelion professors, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come cōpanions to theeues, they are euen found to be the den and the sinke of loth some hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie; which the eye of Christ viewed, his heart lothed, his whip purged. The swords edge is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated to them, it cannot <hi>Pearce: the shaft is shot in vaine, it cannot sticke.</hi> The force of
<pb facs="7"/> the Gospell, is become now so weake, it cannot moue them.<hi>The bellowes are burnt, the ledde is consumed in the fire, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Ierem. 6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> hath melted in vaine.</hi> The preachers haue lost their labours, and the Printers haue spent their care, their time, their strength in nothing, for <hi>The wicked yet still wrestle against God, like wild Buls tumbling in a <note place="margin">Ierem. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> net:</hi> yea, they haue made a new couenant with death, and with hell: they haue clapped hands vpon a new bargaine. As Sathan told Eua she should not die so our lying fancies haue told vs, that,<hi>No plague shall come neere vs.</hi> Long peace and wealth hath brought vs to wanton <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> Babels estate: we are a virgine not to be oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by any; we are tender and delicate, the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse of felicitie; we are a Lady of kingdomes, with a perelesse prosperitie, in the middest of <note place="margin">Esay. 47. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> our neighbours miseries, wee neuer feared of our owne calamities, our necke is framed of yron sinewes, it cannot bow; our browes are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-plated <note place="margin">Esay: 48. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> with brasse, they cannot blush. The trumpe hath blowen, yet can bee not bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine them that <hi>Were lost in the land of Assiria:</hi> Though the preachers with their Cornets haue seuen and seuen times compassed Iericho, yet the cursed wals fal not; though the
<pb facs="8"/> voice, the crie, and the force of the Gospell, of signes and wonders haue beene heard and felt in euery corner, yet the weedes ouertoppe the Corne: the soule lost in the sincke of error and land of transgression, returnes not againe: the Papists deceiued by the full flesh pots of Egypt are not yet reclaimed; the Atheists, Brownists, Anabaptists, Libertines, and carnall, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, and dissolute professors, that are for their sinne suffered to be led into heresies, are not yet contented to ioyne in one godly vnitie to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and serue the Lord in the mount of Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, the vision of peace. We doe not yet see that blessed time, when Ephraim shall be are no euill will to Iuda; nor Iuda vexe Ephraim, when preachers shall not wrangle for trifels and bee deuided one from an other, but all ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to flie vpon the shoulders of the Pihlistins the common enemies of the Gospell. All our preaching cannot draw on that happie time, when, <hi>Iuda and Israel, shall walke both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> When all preachers and professors that now hate, backbite, and slaunder one an other shall so ioyne hands and hearts together, that neither of thē walke or continue any longer in the hardnesse of their froward harts. It was a certaine signe of Gods heauie plague against
<pb facs="8"/> Iuda, and a sure token that their destruction was at hand, when the peoples eares began to be <hi>Vncircumcised, when they could not patiently harken to the truth; and when the word was to thē as a reproch, &amp; that they could not delighte in it.</hi> If the same to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens may be now any way á signe to England of her destruction, as it was to Ierusalem, then may Englands Musicke, be well turned into Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahes mourning, and say,<hi>Woe bee vnto me, Woe is me now,</hi> My heart, my health, my hope, my helpe and all is gon from me. It were a lamentable thing, that our wilfull and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sinnes, (dayly crying for vengeance to fall vpon vs, from the seate of God,) our couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, vsurie, drunkennesse, whordome, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, periurie; contentions, pride, enuie, &amp; disobedience, should giue our Corne to be meate for our enemies, and the fruite of our labours, to refresh strangers, while we our selues famish: yet thus it hath beene in time, and thus it may bee againe.</p>
   <p>Some thinke there be too many Books, too many Sermons, too much preaching, too much Printing: and I thinke there is too little of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riesort. There is no fault found with too much ease, too much pleasure, too much negligence,
<pb facs="9"/> too much wantonnesse in behauiour, too much pride in apparell, too much loue to imitate new Apish toyes and strange fashions: we are neuer cloyed with these, come as thicke as they can, but the poore dispised word sounds too oft, &amp; comes too thicke vpon vs. O sinne, O Sathan, Papisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call enuie saith, euery boye is become a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: euerie foole is become a writer. Iosua en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiously murmureth against Eldad and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad, for prophecying in the Tent: The Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <note place="margin">Num. 11. 28 Mark 9. 38. Luke. 9. 48 Iohn. 3. 26.</note> of Iohn, enuied at Christ for working of Miracles, but I say with meeke Moyses, I would all the people of God did prophecie, I woulde all were learned, I would all were preachers, I would all were so perfectly taught of God, that euery man were able to preach to himselfe, to teach and instruct himselfe and his charge in all things, that wee might indeede neede lesse preaching, and lesse writing.</p>
   <p>Some woulde haue no Bookes written, but such onely as did wade into the depth of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and contained the marrow, and quintes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of learning; such as did profoundly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle deepe points, &amp; suttle quiddities of Diuine or Phylosophicall controuersies; and such as in a manner shoulde speake that which was neuer spoken before.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p> This is the verie pollicie of Sathan, to take from the simple people, their greatest comfort, (next vnto preaching) that they enioy, which is, the reading or hearing, at leasure times some plaine exposition or familiar Sermon, penned to their capacitie, wherin many and many take great and singular comfort, delight and profit. Many there be, that for age, troubles and other occasions, cannot often come to heare Sermons, where and when they would, which hauing at home some good Booke, supplies often times the want of a better meanes, to bring them to the knowledge, and loue of God.</p>
   <p>I speake not this to patronise any lewd, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or foolish Pamphlets, which tend not to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but rather to destruction; neither yet to prefer or compare reading, or writing with preaching, which is the blessed, and ordinarie meanes of our saluation, but onely to crop the blossomes of their proud Enuie, that despise their weake brothers gifts, in respect of theyr own surmised perfections: &amp; which think, that some profit may not redound to the simple, by the most simple gift, that euer was bestowed of God vpon the most simple man.</p>
   <p>I detest the fantastical humor of them that write or publish any booke, to hunt for any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
<pb facs="10"/> praise, glorie, or profit to themselues, and not with a single, and simple intent to seeke onely the glorie of God, the furderance of the Gospell; and the knowledge, comfort and sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Gods childrē, &amp; the weake brethren. With this intent and no other, (as he knowes that knowes my hart) I haue perswaded my self to suffer these plaine &amp; Countrie notes, to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect themselues to the curious eyes, to the sharpe conceites, and the quicke iudgements of the learned Readers of this age, not intended or adorned for the learned, but onely vowed and plotted in the lowest kinde, for the capacitie of the simple and ignorant.</p>
   <p>It may bee that I haue studied more, to bee plaine, briefe and perspicuous, then some haue to flie aloft in the mistie cloudes of rolling elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; be cause I seeke the edification of the simple, not the praise of my selfe.</p>
   <p>If I should vauntingly flie so high, as the wings of fancie would carrie but a meane Schollers reache, I might neither in dutie doe that I should; nor in conscience, performe that which I would.</p>
   <p>Let the Iaylors and keepers of Prisons in these daies, accounte this example the chiefe flower in their garland, that there hath beene
<pb facs="10"/> so honest a man, an vndoubted childe of God found in their Corporation: of whome, I would they would all learne, to be more mercifull and courteous to their poore brethren that are in bands, to consider the cause of their imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: not to hepe miserie vpon miserie, but in their punishments to see the anger of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their owne sinnes: to bee sorrie for them that are in Captiuitie, to thanke God for their owne freedome: not to insult ouer them, whom God hath cast downe, but in a charitable mind to comfort them that are in heauinesse, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the wants of the poore and needie, to their powers. So God (with this Iaylor) shall blesse them with the true knowledge of their saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ioyfull spirite of regeneration: So shall the Lord comfort them in their distresse, and deliuer them from the prison and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt which their sins haue deserued. This is the wourst I wish thē, this the Lord graunt them. And so I commit thee, gentle Reader, to Gods mercifull protection. From Honiton in Deuon this 30. day of Iune. 1596.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, Hugh Dowriche.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>