<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST NO∣BLE LADY, A BRANCH OF the auncient and illustrious house of Oxford) the Right Honorable, SVSAN, Countesse of Mountgomery, Grace, and Glory.</title>
           <author>Taylor, Augustine</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111343_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23720</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111343</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST NO∣BLE LADY, A BRANCH OF the auncient and illustrious house of Oxford) the Right Honorable, SVSAN, Countesse of Mountgomery, Grace, and Glory.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Augustine</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diuine epistles : Dedicated. to right honble. &amp; worthy guests inuited to ye nuptialls of the great Kings sonne. &amp;c By Augustin. Taylor. preacher at Hawarden</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Augustine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>202 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE LADY, A BRANCH OF <hi>the auncient and illustrious house of</hi> Oxford) the Right Honorable, SVSAN, <hi>Countesse of</hi> Mountgomery, <hi>Grace, and Glory.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Thrice Honorable Lady,</salute>
   </opener>
   <l>VEre euer loued veritas so well,</l>
   <l>And to all vertues gaue such countenance,</l>
   <l>That sacred truth for euer vowes to dwell,</l>
   <l>In your Breast to be safe from ignorance,</l>
   <l>Enuy, and error; and hath warned me,</l>
   <l>That where I find vere, challenge there to be</l>
   <l>A lodging due to her, (I'dmir'd) and then</l>
   <l>Shee sayd to me (as Christ did to the men</l>
   <l>He sent to fetch the asse) if they refuse,</l>
   <l>The fauours I intreate, make thou but vse,</l>
   <l>Of my name vnto them with mild regard,</l>
   <l>And thou shalt find my lodging straight prepar'd.</l>
   <l>Great Lady with great reuerence I present,</l>
   <l>To your Religious view, and gracious eyes</l>
   <l>A legacy, a Heauenly or nament,</l>
   <l>With the Messias pleas'd to sacrifice,</l>
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <l>And send vnto his spouse, to moue her, come</l>
   <l>To warne her, call her, and command her home,</l>
   <l>Vnto his Heauen; I wish you would accept</l>
   <l>My loue and seruice, and this offering take,</l>
   <l>As Princes do Imbassadours respect,</l>
   <l>Not for their owne, but for their maisters sake</l>
   <l>I am ordain'd Gods messenger, t'intreat,</l>
   <l>His chosen number to his Heauenly feast.</l>
   <l>And you both being truely good and great,</l>
   <l>Hath a faire seate prepar'd among the blest,</l>
   <l>Your pious bounties, princely beauties, and</l>
   <l>Religious wisedome, (which is honors nurse.)</l>
   <l>Are guides to lead you vnto Gods right hand;</l>
   <l>And likewise motiues caused me disburse,</l>
   <l>My loue and seruice in this measure: take it,</l>
   <l>My worke's Diume, and my free will doth make it</l>
   <l>A perfect offering, t'helpe gamst death and doombe,</l>
   <l>Regard this frame, for't will out-last your toombe.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Willing and ready to do your Honor the best seruice, that is in the power of</hi> Augustine Taylor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>