<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111995_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06872</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17305</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111995</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fruitful sermon necessary for the time : preached at the Spittle vpon the Tuesday in Easter weeke last, by Frauncis Marbury. Published by direction of authoritie</title>
                 <author>Marbury, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>86 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rethren, when I saw how Satan had preuailed by his latter temptations, to adde a further miserie to those e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils which he had contriued by his former: I desired that by some good hand he might be resisted. And for a good space (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) I haue inclined to aduenture my selfe in opposing him. I foresaw how vnacceptable it would be to some, and reuolued it with such anxietie of minde, as I could not remooue by mine own strength. But it was the Lords worke that I set aside discouragements, and fell to waighing the matter. Three things I principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pondred. First, that this vndutifull alienation did grieuously displease God, and was a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous iudgement of it selfe. Secondly, that it had no ground but the <hi>tradition of Satan;</hi> so I call the information which is giuen to men, that are strangers to the secrets of a cause, by those that are parties to the action Thirdly, that the effect of this alienation, if it were too much inueterat would be formidable to all, and chiefly to gods Church. Hereupon I resolued to wait some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to performe this duty, and to endure mine owne losse for the gaine of others. In this corruption of nature it is not possible to do any thing exactly wel, and by that verie thing doth the Lord aduantage his glorie: for so he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth
<pb facs="3"/>the instruments of the best things. How beit he giueth grace to his children to attaine to vndoubted synceritie, and to propound his glory to their enterprises in the singlenesse of their harts. The falsenesse of mans hart (if he set himselfe seriously before God) cannot so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, but he may discerne whether he haue had a care to auoid euil and to glorifie God. In this care I haue had my part from my first cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to preach at the Spittle. And if men wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me otherwise,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.36.</note>
      <hi>my conscience will make her a garland of their reports,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> saith. I doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that after I was called to that place, I thought my selfe qualified in some measure for this very purpose, vpon these grounds, 1. I stood well affected to my countrimen, whom I desired to reforme. 2. I presumed that they had entertained a perswasion that I affected soundnesse in deliuering Gods word. 3. I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood the cause with the distinctions. 4. I vnderstood out of my innumerable obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the still continuing dispositions and words of men in the cause, to be verie sinfull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, notwithstanding all their distinctions. And I proportioned the reprehensiō of an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall sin to an vniuersall assembly. 5. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that the wound being cured betweene God and man, and between man and man, we should all be fit to ioine against the Diuell, and leaue failing both in dutifulnes and wisedome.</p>
   <p>I haue (being required thereto) deliuered a faithfull report of that Sermon. I haue not (the
<pb facs="3"/>Lord is witnesse) set downe one word to diuert y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sense of any one point frō that which I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the deliuerie, but haue striuen to attaine to the words. My conscience is vpright so farre as I can discerne it in the course. If the great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of state had called me to preach before them, I would either haue insisted in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the common duties of christianitie, or els would haue held it my duty to haue left this, and to haue followed the other relatiue. To haue done it now, had been preposterous.</p>
   <p>As touching <hi>politike vertues,</hi> which I holde <hi>more excellent for the profit of the commonwealth in true christian princes, then their morall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues be;</hi> doe me right in vnderstanding me as I expressely spake it, and as I wrote it (vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion) more then once before, I spake it <hi>of true christian princes.</hi> Otherwise I hold a <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in his defectiuenesse of policie (if he be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise truly religious) a fitter king thē a <hi>Ieroboam</hi> being an enemy of religion, with all his irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious policies. Conceiue also the largenes of the name of politike vertues,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> that in deed it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth in the scripture phrase (which I thoght of) to a mans carriage in common with others be he priuate or publike;<note place="margin">Act. 23.1. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> 1 Reg. 8.23. 2. cro. 20 6. Psal. 42.4 &amp; 122.</note> insomuch that <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth his conscionable seruice of God in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersing amongst the Iewes <hi>his politike carriage.</hi> And therfore in princes it extendeth to all their duties, as they bee princes, euen to their verie praiers as they are the mouths of their people, as it sometimes fell out, and to their resorting
<pb facs="4"/>to the publike worship of God as guides to the people, these are politike duties, as they are don in a politike respect for gouernments sake, for the name of policie is abusiuely put for vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable craftinesse.</p>
   <p>If there were any ambitious intention in me,<note place="margin">1 Thess. 4.11.</note> it was <hi>S. Pauls</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. I was ambitious of loue and quietnesse in my countrey. Other sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises are vaine; for though I desire to exercise my ministerie with the ayde and countenance of authoritie for the repulsing of vngodly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, yet I may affirm with all truth of hart that I haue as much mind to turn my endeuors from the painful preaching of the Gospel to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, as <hi>Barzillai</hi> had to be a Courtier. Wel,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.35.</note> the Lord enforme you all with all profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and conuenient truth, and frame your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections thereafter. And the Lord giue vs all grace to turne all our vnnecessarie medlings with Counsels and States, to prayers &amp; thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings for our blessed Lady Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>F. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>