<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MOST EXCELLENT MA∣JESTIE, Charles BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING OF Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111832_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10231</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20508.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MOST EXCELLENT MA∣JESTIE, Charles BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING OF Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Purchas his pilgrimage. Or Relations of the vvorld and the religions obserued in all ages and places discouered, from the Creation vnto this present : Contayning a theologicall and geographicall historie of Asia, Africa, and America, with the ilands adiacent. Declaring the ancient religions before the Floud ... The fourth edition, much enlarged with additions, and illustrated with mappes through the whole worke; and three whole treatises annexed, one of Russia and other northeasterne regions by Sr. Ierome Horsey; the second of the Gulfe of Bengala by Master William Methold; the third of the Saracenicall empire, translated out of Arabike by T. Erpenius. By Samuel Purchas, parson of St. Martins by Ludgate, London</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 242, 241-636, 635-1047, 37 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MOST EXCELLENT <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTIE,</hi> Charles BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING OF Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, Defender of the <hi>Faith, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Maiesties goodnesse hath inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this boldnes, in accepting my late Voluminous Twinnes of <hi>Pilgrimes;</hi> then also vouchsafing to aske of this my <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> whether it were there annexed, and wherefore it was not (a sufficient prouocation to This Edition and Dedication;) that I mention not Your Pietie, which cannot denie hereditarie respect, where your Royall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (of euer blessed memorie, the King of learned and Learnings kings) manifested so much fauour, as to make it Ordinarie of his Bed chamber; where vpon occasion of those later Volumes then presented, he questioned the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and professed freely that he had read this worke se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times, giuing thereof a present testimonie in his learned discourse and censure. No lesse did hee promise touching
<pb facs="3"/> the <hi>Pilgrimes,</hi> which he made his Nightly taske, till God called him by fatall sicknesse to a better <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> and of a more enduring Kingdome; euen the last day in which that Sunne yeelded his present rayes to this Citie, sending an Honourable messenger with a fauourable message of his gentle approbation and incouragement. Such a testimonie is a King of Testimonies, and no lesse reward to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, then commendation of the Worke to his worthy Heire, and to all English Readers. Once; it hath produced this my present aduenture on your Maiestie, being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise ambitious, that as my selfe, so all mine may there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge subiection and reference. I might adde also that some Additions here inserted, had more fitly beene ranked in those <hi>Pilgrime files,</hi> which in more speciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie attended your Royall standerd. And although these times seeme more to sauour of Armes then to fauour Arts <hi>(inter arma silent Musae)</hi> yet Our Muse is not of the softer socke, but more Masculine, an armed <hi>Pallas,</hi> not bred in Poeticall mysterie, but borne a reall Historie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining actions, factions, fractions of Religions and States through the whole World of Place and Time; not nicer effeminate fictions of idle-busie fancifull braines.</p>
   <p>Howeuer, may it please your Maiestie to accept his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intended indeuours, who hath borrowed of thousands to furnish this one Worke of and to the World, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Pilgrimes</hi> heartie acclamation of ioy, ioy, to Your happie Inauguration, with prayers that the vertuous good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of King IAMES may be succeeded and exceeded in the greatnesse and vertues of Great Britaines Great <hi>Charles.</hi> AMEN.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your vnworthy Subiect,</hi> Samuel Purchas.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>