<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Proheme of Nicholas Machiauell, Cite∣zein and Secretarie of Florence, vpon his booke of the Arte of warre, vnto Laurence Philippe Strozze, one of the nobilitie of Florence.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111854_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06716</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17164</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111854</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Proheme of Nicholas Machiauell, Cite∣zein and Secretarie of Florence, vpon his booke of the Arte of warre, vnto Laurence Philippe Strozze, one of the nobilitie of Florence.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of warre, written first in Italia [n] by Nicholas Machiauell, and set forthe in Englishe by Peter Whitehorne, studient at Graies Inne: with an addicio [n] of other like marcialle feates and experimentes, as in a table in the ende of the booke maie appere</title>
                 <author>Machiavelli, Niccolò</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>England (Ingland), Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>England (Ingland), Nicholas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, c ix, 13, 48, 4 leaves, folded plates, illustrations (woodcuts), diagrams, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="proem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Proheme of Nicholas Machiauell, Cite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zein and Secretarie of Florence, vpon his booke of the Arte of warre, vnto Laurence Philippe Strozze, one of the nobilitie of Florence.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here haue Laurence, many h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lde, and do holde this opiniō, that there is no maner of thing, whiche lesse agreeth the one with the other, nor y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> is so much vnlike, as the ciuil life to the Souldiours. Wher by it is often seen, that if any determin in thexercise of that kinde of seruice to preuaile, that incontinent he doeth not only chaunge in apparel, but also in custome and maner, in voice, and from the facion of all ciuil vse, he doeth alter: For that he thinketh not meete to clothe with ciuell apparell him, who wil be redie, and promt to all kinde of violence, nor the ciuell customes, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages maie that man haue, the whiche iudgeth bothe those customes to be effeminate, and those vsages not to be agreable to his profession: Nor it semes not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for him to vse the ciuill gesture and ordinarie wordes, who with fasing and blasphemies, will make afraied other menne: the whiche causeth in this time, suche opinion to be moste true. But if thei should con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sider thauncient orders, there should nothing be foūde more vnited, more confirmable, and that of necessitie ought to loue so much the one the other, as these: for as muche as all the artes that are ordeined in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, in regarde or respecte of common profite of menne, all the orders made in the same, to liue with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare of the Lawe, and of God, should be vaine, if by
<pb facs="6"/> force of armes their defence wer not prepared, which well ordeined, doe maintain those also whiche be not well ordeined. And likewise to the contrarie, the good orders, without the souldiours help, no lesse or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise doe disorder, then the habitacion of a sumptuous and roiall palais, although it wer decte with gold and precious stones, when without being couered, should not haue wherewith to defende it from the raine. And if in what so euer other orders of Cities and Kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, there hath been vsed al diligence for to maintain men faithfull, peaceable, and full of the feare of God, in the seruice of warre, it was doubled: for in what man ought the countrie to seke greater faith, then in him, who must promise to die for the same? In whom ought there to bee more loue of peace, then in him, whiche onely by the warre maie be hurte? In whome ought there to bee more feare of GOD, then in him, whiche euery daie commityng himself to infinite pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles, hath moste neede of his helpe? This necessitie considered wel, bothe of them that gaue the lawes to Empires, &amp; of those that to the exercise of seruice wee apoincted, made that the life of Souldiours, of other menne was praised, and with all studie folowed and imitated. But the orders of seruice of war, beyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together corrupted, and a greate waie from the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēt maners altered, there hath growen these siniste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous opinions, which maketh men to hate the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like seruice, and to flie the conuersacion of those that dooe exercise it. Albeit I iudgeing by the same, that I haue seen and redde, that it is not a thyng impossible, to bryng it again to the auncient maners, and to giue it some facion of the vertue passed, I haue determined to the entente not to passe this my idell time, without doyng some thyng, to write that whiche I doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande, of the arte of warre, to the satisfiyng of those, who are louers of auncient actes. And although it be a hold thing to intreate of the same matter, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of
<pb n="ij" facs="6"/> otherwise I haue made no profession, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I beleue it is no errour, to occupie with wordes a degree, the whiche many with greater presumpcion with their deedes haue occupied: for as muche as the errours that I maie happen to make by writing, may be without harme to any man corrected: but those the whiche of them be made in doyng, cannot be knowen without the ruine of Empires. Therefore Laurence you ought to consider the qualitie of this my laboure, and with your iudgemēt to giue it that blame, or that praise, as shall seeme vnto you it hath deserued. The whiche I sende vnto you, as well to shewe my selfe gratefull, although my habilitie reche not to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, which I haue receiued of you, as also for that beyng the custome to honour with like workes them, who for nobilitie, riches, wisedome, and libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie doe shine: I knowe you for riches, and nobilitie, not to haue many peeres, for wisedome fewe, and for liberalitie none.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>