<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most worthy Gent.
Sir William Russell, Knight, accomplish∣ment
of his honorable desire.</title>
           <author>Whetstone, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111682_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25339</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most worthy Gent.
Sir William Russell, Knight, accomplish∣ment
of his honorable desire.</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The honorable reputation of a souldier : with a morall report, of the vertues, offices, and (by abuse) the disgrace of his profession. Drawen out of the liues, documents, and disciplines, of the most renowned Romaine, Grecian, and other famous martialistes. By George Whetstone, Gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most worthy Gent.
Sir William Russell, Knight, accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of his honorable desire.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, hauing (I may truly saye) with</hi>
much labour compiled a booke, Intituled.
<hi>The English Mirour:</hi> the first part setting
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orth, <hi>The Conquests of Enuy:</hi> cōtaining,
ruine and subuertion of the auncient M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies
and common weales, &amp;c. The
second part, shewing <hi>Enuy</hi> to be conquered by <hi>Vertue:</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing
the peaceable victories of her Maiestie, to Gods <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ye
glorie and vniuersall wonder. The third part, intituled, <hi>A
Fortresse against Enuy:</hi> wherin euery good cōmon wealths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
may see the true offices, vertues, and (by abuse) the
disgrace of his profession: But because, the booke is of some
volume, I cannot haue it speedily printed: and for that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casiō
now (at this present) maketh passadge for this Subiet,
being a member or si<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all parcell of the fore-recited booke:
Therefore, as a testimonie of the zeale which I beare to
your worship, and euery worthy person, whose profession is
Martiall, I reuerently submit my trauell, to be censur'd by
your able iudgement, which medleth no whit with <hi>Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie
execution,</hi> but altogether with <hi>Morall goue<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nmēt,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie
for a perfect Souldier. For, if I my selfe, which haue
béene brought vp among the Muses, in our English (onely)
peaceable and happy gouernmēt, should take vppon mee to
set forth the order of battailes, th'aduantages of places, the
benifits of stratagems, with many other Millitary regards,
both offenciue and defenciue, I might for my hyre iustly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue,
the scoffe that <hi>Hamball</hi> gaue vnto the Philosopher
<hi>Phormio:</hi> who (vpon such an indiscrete discriptiō) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ould him
<pb facs="3"/>
that, <hi>The Art millitarie was sooner learned of Souldiers in
the brode fields, thē of Philosophers in close scoles.</hi> And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly,
<hi>Haniball</hi> aunswered more like▪ Philosopher, then
<hi>Phormio</hi> reasoned like a Souldier: for, Experiēce is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true
Teacher of all Artes: and therefore (that honorable part of
a Souldier, which containeth Martiall execution) I leaue
to the report of the well experiēced Captaine: and no doubt,
among the worthie English Capt<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nes, there are some, that
can vse both <hi>Caesars</hi> pen and sword. My trauell (which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
betweene fire and frost (as I haue saide) onely contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth:
<hi>The Moral vertues &amp; honorable Reputatiō of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</hi>
And certainly, two of the greatest partes therof, <hi>Caesar</hi>
setteth forth, i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that which bee calleth his chiefest glorie,
which was: <hi>Mamillus,</hi> vpō occasiō asked <hi>Caesar,</hi> what thing
hee had done, wherein hee held him selfe most honored?
<hi>I sweare vnto thee MAMILLVS, by the immortall
Gods (sayd CESAR) that I haue done nothing whereof
I hould my selfe so much honored and happy: as, for that I
haue liberally rewarded those which haue serued mee, and
mercifully haue forgiuen such as haue offended me.</hi> Words
and vertues, beseeming <hi>Caesar,</hi> and without which, <hi>Caesar</hi>
could neuer haue beene Monarcke of the whole worlde: for
the Captaine that lib<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rally rewardeth his Souldiers, shall
haue his souldiers resolute in execution, and who showeth
mercy to his Enimie, shal conquer millions with loue.</p>
   <p>The Spainiard is so insolent, and outragious where he
ouercommeth, as hee is hated to death of those which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>baye
him for f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>are: I haue séene ample experience therof, both in
the Duchy of <hi>Millaine,</hi> and kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi> And (your
god fauour and patience desired) I shall show no imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
example. In the yeare 1580. in which year the Pope
and his confederates, hoped to haue had a great day in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi>
whose expectation God alwayes frustrate, my selfe
with one other English Gentleman (who in this commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
will haue his name concealed) were at <hi>Thurin</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained
into the companie of a worthy Gentleman of
Picardie, named <hi>Monseur Dobart,</hi> who was then ready to
<pb facs="3"/>
trauell into <hi>Italy:</hi> and being all lodged one night in a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
town, in the Duchy of <hi>Millain,</hi> neare vnto the Riuer of
<hi>Poo,</hi> at the middest of supper, a haughtie proude Spaniard,
came and sat him downe by vs. <hi>Monseur Dobart</hi> (bearing
an affectionate zeale vnto her Maiestie, &amp; the state of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
as well for that he was an earnest protestant, as for
that his sister and other frends, were honorably vsed in the
Court of <hi>England,</hi> in the former troubles of <hi>Fraunce</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded
of the Spaniard, what might bee the cause, that
the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> had that yeare raised so great an Army?
The Spaniard forthwith made this proude &amp; insolent aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere:
<hi>Ah Sir, the time nowe draweth neare, that we shall
haue the spoile of rich England▪ that we shall embrace their
faire wiues, and make hauocke of their lōg gathered riches:</hi>
And disco<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ering that there was an Englishman in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
that tolierated these hie wordes, hee beganne spitefully
to bra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e him: But on <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he soden, the spaniard sound the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
of the English-mans fingers: so that shame, to repaire
his disgrace, compelled the Spaniard to offer combat: <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seur
Dobart</hi> very honorably vndertooke that the English-Gentleman,
should the next morning by six of the clocke, be
ready to crosse the Riuer of <hi>Poo,</hi> with the spaniard, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
eithers cause to God, and their swords This was mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
agréed vpon, but by breake of the daye, the spaniards
brags vanished like bubbles, &amp; be himselfe slipt away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
giuing any <hi>bon-giorno,</hi> so that the English Gentleman
could haue no further reuenge, sauing that in the place of
this controuersie, finding this Italian sentēce to be writtē:
<hi>Le parole son femine, &amp; i fatti son maschi.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in dispight,
wrote vnderneath: <hi>Donques gli spanioli son femine, et gli
Inglese son maschi:</hi> and truly the h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aste of the house, with
many dispightful words of the spaniards proude &amp; naughty
behauiour, to his perpetual blame, hath faithfully promised,
that the subscription should not be rased out, without being
secretly new written againe: But the spaniard had reuēge
inough by the Gentlemans owne contrymen: for <hi>Monseur
Dobart</hi> (as hee thought to honour him) imparted this acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="4"/>
to certaine Englishmen at <hi>Bologna:</hi> among whome,
there were that so posted the matter to <hi>Rome:</hi> as when the
poore Gent. arri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es there, hee was stayed at the gate, nowe
called <hi>Porto del populi,</hi> and there was kept eight daies, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
no other bed but the bare ground, and well neare star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
for want of foode: In fine, all his other <hi>Bollitines</hi> and
<hi>Warrants</hi> to trauell being taken away. On the s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>daine the
<hi>Stappado</hi> was hanged forth, and the Gentleman vpō paine
thereof▪ commanded presently to depart: to whome was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
a Vollitine for <hi>Naples.</hi> What violence hee further
sustained, his humour will not agree to open it: for I am
sure, he hath bene seldome hard to pursue any mās disgrace,
and neuer knowne publikely to bem<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne his owne hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,
which haue beene many, and violent: And albeit, his
name be here concealed, yet if any exceptiō be taken against
this report) let me be in all places reproued, if he euery way
approue not the same. And albeit Sir, the matter be in some
sort perticuler: yet (as I haue sayde) it showeth what hatred
the insolencie of the Spaniard eng<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ndreth where he ruleth,
which can establish no gouernment: Besides, by his lauish
words, it may be seene what hauock he would make: if hee
could execute his prowde desires: But if the Englishman
farre frō succour, feareth him not in his owne dores, I hope
(I truely prophesie his discomfiture, vppon an euen hande:
I leaue the rest to the vewe of your best leasure: and if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the greatnes of your honorable desire, you may
haue libertie to aduenture your person, in this honorable
seruice, I beseech God to blesse all your attempts,
ioyn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tly with all those that shall
vndertake the
same.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships by bounden dutie.
<hi>George Whetstone.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>