<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, GEORGE, Duke, Marquesse, and Earle of BVCKINGHAM, Viscount VILLIERS, Baron of WHADDON, Lord High Admirall of ENGLAND, Iustice in Eyre of all his MAJESTIES Forests, Parkes, and Chaces beyond Trent; MASTER of His MAIESTIES Horse, KNIGHTof the m Noble ORDER of the GARTER, and One of His MAIESTIES most Honorable Priuie COVNCELL.</title>
           <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111862_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A71307</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20509</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, GEORGE, Duke, Marquesse, and Earle of BVCKINGHAM, Viscount VILLIERS, Baron of WHADDON, Lord High Admirall of ENGLAND, Iustice in Eyre of all his MAJESTIES Forests, Parkes, and Chaces beyond Trent; MASTER of His MAIESTIES Horse, KNIGHTof the m Noble ORDER of the GARTER, and One of His MAIESTIES most Honorable Priuie COVNCELL.</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Purchas his pilgrimes : In fiue bookes. The first, contayning the voyages and peregrinations made by ancient kings, patriarkes, apostles, philosophers, and others, to and thorow the remoter parts of the knowne world: enquiries also of languages and religions, especially of the moderne diuersified professions of Christianitie. The second, a description of all the circum-nauigations of the globe. The third, nauigations and voyages of English-men, alongst the coasts of Africa ... The fourth, English voyages beyond the East Indies, to the ilands [sic] of Iapan, China, Cauchinchina, the Philippinæ with others ... The fifth, nauigations, voyages, traffiques, discoueries, of the English nation in the easterne parts of the world ... The first part</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4 volumes (v 1, 36, 186, 10, 468, 479-642, 645-748, 24 pages (first leaf blank), 2 leaves of plates (1 folded), volumes 2, 4, 749-857, 860-1270, 1269-1860, 40 pages, volumes 3, 28, 668, 699-1006, 1009-1140, 68 pages, 3 folded leaves of plates, volumes 4, 8, 1141-1234, 1237-1973, 41 pages 2 folded leaves of plates), illustrations, maps, tables, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, GEORGE, Duke, Marquesse, and Earle of BVCKINGHAM, Viscount VILLIERS, Baron of WHADDON,</hi> Lord High Admirall of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> Iustice in <hi>Eyre of all his MAJESTIES Forests, Parkes, and Chaces beyond</hi> Trent; <hi>MASTER</hi> of His <hi>MAIESTIES</hi> Horse, <hi>KNIGHT</hi>of the <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Noble ORDER of the GARTER, and One of</hi> His <hi>MAIESTIES</hi> most Honorable Priuie <hi>COVNCELL.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing presented to the Princes Highnesse a World of Histories composed into a <hi>Historie of the World,</hi> I durst not set saile with so great a Fleet of Sea-voyages (a principall part thereof) before I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came humble Sutor to Your Grace for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense from the Admiraltie. Pardon this presump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on, which Your Greatnesse requireth, Your Goodnesse inuiteth and the nature of the Worke exacteth. His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, <hi>the breath of our nosthrils,</hi> the Life and Rule of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hth by many graces otherwise, and by exemplarie dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tatht Others Bookes there to seeke delightsome shaddow, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s gaue so glorious light.</p>
   <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther may any Name stand so neere That of His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, oecially in a Booke of Sea and Land Trauels, as His
<pb facs="3"/>
who hath beene so late and faithfull a Traueller with Him by Sea and Land; Nor the Kings honor (here aymed at) bee more welcome to any then the <hi>Kings Friend, whom the King will honour;</hi> Nor can acts of Nauigation bee any where more sutable then to a Noble mind, now fixing his best and blest thoughts on discouering a neerer passage to the remoter World, and vnder whose Charge the Nauie Royall more flourisheth then euer. By some of Yours also the Author was encouraged to vndertake this great worke, which now therefore <hi>returneth</hi> to your Grace, as that <hi>Sea</hi> whence the <hi>Springs</hi> first flowed. May it please your Graces taste (more from such employments cannot be expected) to incite inferior appetites: and I hope that to such sweetnesse of Nature, this <hi>Historie of Nature</hi> will not be altogether distastfull. God Almightie blesse and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper your Grace, and all your Loyall seruices to His Maiestie, with increase of Diuine, Royall, and Princely fauour.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces lowly Orato
SAMVEL PVRCHAS</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>