<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull his most worthy and highly honoured Friends, Sir Hugh Hamersley Knight, and Mr. Alderman Park∣burst, Two of the principall Gouer∣nours of Christs-Hospitall; I: V: wisheth the Kingdome of Grace heere, and the King∣dome of Glory hereafter.</title>
           <author>Vicars, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111549_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24697</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111549</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull his most worthy and highly honoured Friends, Sir Hugh Hamersley Knight, and Mr. Alderman Park∣burst, Two of the principall Gouer∣nours of Christs-Hospitall; I: V: wisheth the Kingdome of Grace heere, and the King∣dome of Glory hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Vicars, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands hallelu-jah. Or, Great Brittaines gratefull retribution, for Gods gratious benediction : In our many and most famous deliuerances, since the halcyon-dayes of euer-blessed Queene Elizabeth, to these present times. Together, with diuers of Dauids Psalmes, according t the French metre and measures. By I:V</title>
                 <author>Vicars, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="38"/>
   <pb facs="38"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull his most worthy and highly honoured Friends, Sir <hi>Hugh Hamersley</hi> Knight, and Mr. <hi>Alderman Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burst,</hi> Two of the principall <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> of <hi>Christs-Hospitall; I: V</hi>: wisheth the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> heere, and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter.</head>
   <p>THis <hi>Poeme</hi> (Right Wor:) being inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a promoueing <hi>Spurre</hi> and <hi>incitemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> to that most excellent and amiable duty of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> of which, sweetly sayeth St. <hi>Augustine, Quid melius animo geramus, aut ore promamus, ant calamo pingamus, quam Graetias? Hoc, nil bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius dici, nil suauius andiri, nec fructuosius ab bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus agi potest. What (sayes Hee)</hi> can wee better beare in our minde, or vtter with our tongue, or set-forth with our pen? than <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing</hi>: a man can speake <hi>nothing</hi> more succinct, heare <hi>nothing</hi> more sweet, nor doe <hi>any thing</hi> more aduantageous, than <hi>This</hi> of <hi>Thankefulnesse.</hi> I, therefore (most worthy Sirs) knowing my Selfe deeply indebted to your Worships for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny former <hi>Fauours</hi> and continued <hi>Courtesies</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards


<pb facs="39"/>
me, was duly incited yea stimulated to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend this fit and faire oportunity to intimate my long obliged <hi>Gratitude,</hi> by an humble <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of this small <hi>Symboll</hi> of my sincere <hi>Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse</hi> to your good Worships. Which (had not the malignity of the <hi>Times</hi> prohibited) was intended for the yeere of your, as pious as pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent honourable <hi>Maioralty</hi> of <hi>this Citty,</hi> whose <hi>Gates,</hi> at this day, doe blesse you (as <hi>Ierusalems</hi> did good <hi>Nehemiah</hi>; Nehem: the 13.22.) for your (then) honourable and godly care of the <hi>Lords</hi> sacred <hi>Sabboth.</hi> Accept (worthy Sirs) <hi>I</hi> humbly pray you, This poore <hi>Presentation</hi> of my obliged seruice (now) for, though it comes <hi>lately,</hi> yet it comes <hi>loyally</hi>; and from his heart, who, in all <hi>due</hi> and <hi>true</hi> obseruance desires most respectiuely to Rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your good Worships, euer to bee commanded,</hi> Iohn Vicars.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>