<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>S., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111076_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20954</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7333</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111076</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>S., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Oppositions of the VVord of God, together with the doctrine of the Romane Church : Moreouer, what points are held by the same Church, which she hideth from those whom shee meaneth to draw to her faction. Written by Peter Mouleine, minister of the word of God in Paris, and translated by A.S</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moore (More), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 17, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, both the Argument of this short Treatise (the better part of which consisteth in Oppositions, which the more plainely they bee set downe, the more clearely they appeare) and the purpose of the Author (who made it for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned) hath made me to abstaine from the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of Rhetorique in the translation thereof, wholy applying my selfe to expresse the Authors meaning, as knowing that there is nothing heere but for the simple, who ought rather to be instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted then delighted in matters of Religion. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Translater hereof, that hee nameth not himselfe, since that he had rather purchase profit to others, then vaine-glory to himselfe. The name of the Author is a sufficient patronage for the booke, who is so acute, and subtill in controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of Religion, that he neuer disputeth, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he refuteth. Many bookes haue beene written of this Subiect, but none as yet so fitted to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie of the vulgar, neither comprehended in so
<pb facs="3"/> fewe leaues. Here are no nice distinctions to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract the ignorant, but onely those Papisticall errours are here shewed, which are repugnant to the written verity. Let intention accompanie thee in reading, discretion in iudging, gratulation in profiting: and if thou beest profited, then shall I count my selfe to haue well translated. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine or not thine, A. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>