<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111832_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10231</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20508.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Purchas his pilgrimage. Or Relations of the vvorld and the religions obserued in all ages and places discouered, from the Creation vnto this present : Contayning a theologicall and geographicall historie of Asia, Africa, and America, with the ilands adiacent. Declaring the ancient religions before the Floud ... The fourth edition, much enlarged with additions, and illustrated with mappes through the whole worke; and three whole treatises annexed, one of Russia and other northeasterne regions by Sr. Ierome Horsey; the second of the Gulfe of Bengala by Master William Methold; the third of the Saracenicall empire, translated out of Arabike by T. Erpenius. By Samuel Purchas, parson of St. Martins by Ludgate, London</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 242, 241-636, 635-1047, 37 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND now, READER, The PILGRIME comes vnto thee the fourth time, with whom hee dares be somewhat bolder. Being, I know not by what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination, addicted to the studie of Historie, my heart would sometimes obiect a selfe-loue, in following my priuate delights in that kinde. At last I resolued to turne the pleasures of my studies into studious paines, that others might againe, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull studie, turne my paines into their pleasure. I heere bring <hi>Religion</hi> from <hi>Paradise</hi> to the <hi>Ark,</hi> and thence follow her round about the World, and (for her sake) obserue the World it selfe, with the seueral Countries and Peoples ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; the chiefe Empires and States: their priuate and publique Customes; their ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifold chances and changes; also the wonderfull and most remarkeable effects of Nature; Euents of Diuine and Humane Prouidence, Rarities of Art; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer I finde by Relations of Historians, as I passe, most worthie the writing. <hi>Religion</hi> is my more proper aime, and therefore I insist longer on the description of whatsoeuer I finde belonging thereto; declaring the Religion of the first Men the corrupting of it before and after the Floud; the Iewish obseruations; the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, Idolatries, Temples, Priests, Feasts, Fasts, Opinions, Sects, Orders, and sacred Customes of the Heathens; with the Alterations and Successions that haue therein happened, from the beginning of the World hitherto.</p>
   <p>This Worke I diuide into foure parts. This first exhibiteth the Relations and Theologicall discouerie of ASIA, AFRICA, and AMERICA: The second when God will, shall doe the same for EVROPE: The third and fourth, in a second visitation, shall obserue such things in the same places as I holde most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable in the Christian and Ecclesiasticall Historie, and that according to the same Method; which is squared in the <hi>Whole</hi> by order of <hi>Place,</hi> going still out of one Countrie into the next; in each particular part and seuerall Countrie, by the order of <hi>Time,</hi> deducing our Relations, so farre as we haue Others foot-prints to guide vs, (though not exactly naming the day and yeere, and determining que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions in Chronologicall controuersies, yet in some conuenient sort) from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times, and by degrees descending to the present.</p>
   <p>If thou demandest what profit may be hereof; I answere, that heere Students of all sorts may finde matter fitting their studies: The naturall Philosophers may obserue the different constitution and commixtion of the Elements, their diuers working in diuers places, the varietie of heauenly influence, of the yeerely sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, of the Creatures in the Aire, Water, Earth: They which delight in State-affaires, may obserue the varietie of States and Kingdomes, with their differing Lawes, Polities, and Customes, their Beginnings and Endings. The Diuine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the former, may heere contemplate the workes of God, not in Creation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but in his Iustice and Prouidence, pursuing sinne euery where with such dreadfull plagues; both bodily, in rooting vp and pulling downe the mightiest Empires; and especially in spirituall Iudgements, giuing vp so great a part of the
<pb facs="6"/> World vnto <hi>the efficacie of Errour in strong delusions, that hauing forsaken the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of liuing waters, they should dig vnto themselues these broken Pits that can hold no water;</hi> deuout in their superstitions, and superstitious in their deuotions; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing all in this, that there should bee a Religion, disagreeing from each other, and the TRVTH, in the practice thereof.</p>
   <p>Likewise our Ministers may be incited vnto all godly labours in their function of preaching the Gospel, seeing otherwise, for outward and bodily ceremonies, the Turkes and Iewes (in their manifold deuotions in their Oratories euery day) and other Heathen would conuince vs of idlenesse. And let mee haue leaue to speake it for the glory of God, and the good of our Church; I cannot finde any Priests in all this my Pilgrimage, of whom wee haue any exact History, but take more bodily paines in their deuotions, than is performed by not preaching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, especially in Countrie-villages, where on the weeke dayes they cannot haue occasion, or company, for publique prayers &amp; therfore if they read only the Seruice on holy dayes, and neuer studie for more (which I would it were not the idle practise of some) euen the Heathen shall rise vp in iudgement against them. I subscribe with hand and practice to our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> but not to such <hi>Lethargie:</hi> whose darkenesse is so much the more intollerable, in this Sun-shine of the Gospell, wherein wee haue a gracious <hi>King,</hi> so diligent a frequenter of Sermons; and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Bishops</hi> (notwithstanding other their weighty Ecclesiasticall employments yet) diligent Preachers.</p>
   <p>The studious of Geographie may somewhat be helped in that kinde: not that we intend an exact Geographie, in mentioning euery Citie with the degrees of Longitude and Latitude, but yet limiting euery Countrie in his true situation and bounds; and performing happily more then some, which take vpon them the title of Geographers, as their chiefe profession: and more then any, which I know hath done in our language.</p>
   <p>He which admireth and almost adoreth the Capuchine, Iesuite, or other Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists, for selfe-inflicted whippings, fastings, watchings, vowes of obedience, pouertie, and single life, and their not sparing their limmes, and liues for their <hi>will-worships,</hi> may see, in all these, the Romanists equalled by Heathens, if not out-stripped, euen by the reports of the Iesuites and other their Catholiques. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily exercise profiteth little,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note>
      <hi>but Godlinesse is profitable vnto all, and hath the promise of this life and that which is to come.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Here also the Reader may see most of their Popish Rites, deriued out of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean, Egyptian, and other Fountaines of Paganisme, as in the later taske we shall haue more occasion to shew. Heere euery English man may see cause to praise God continually for the light of his truth, communicated to vs: whereas it is (in comparison) but a small part of the World, that soundeth <hi>the sacred name of</hi> Iesus; and of those that professe it, how infinit are the sects and superstitions? <hi>God hath shewed his Word vnto our IACOB</hi> (THE DEFENDER OF HIS FAITH) <hi>his Statutes and his Iudgements vnto</hi> this ISRAEL of Great Brittaine. Hee hath <hi>not dealt so with euery Nation, neither haue the Heathen,</hi> nor scarcely, if scarcely, any other Christian Nation, so much <hi>knowledge of his iudgements.</hi> And yet how sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious are some? how prophane are others? how vnthankfull the most? That beastly Sinne of Drunkennesse, that biting Sinne of Vsurie, that Deuillish Sinne of Swaggering, ruffling in deformitie of clothes, like monstrous <hi>Chimaeras,</hi> and barking out a multiformitie of oathes, like hellish <hi>Cerberi,</hi> as if men could not be <hi>Gallants,</hi> vnlesse they turned <hi>Deuils.</hi> These are the paiments wee returne vnto the Lord, in stead of prayers for, and loyaltie to his Maiestie; peaceablenesse and charitie to each others; modestie and sobrietie in our selues.</p>
   <p>For the forme, I haue sought in some places, with varietie of phrase, in all, with varietie of matter, to draw thee along with mee in this tedious Pilgrimage. Some names are written diuersly, according to the differing Copies which I followed, which thy discretion will easily conceiue. I doe not in euery question set downe
<pb facs="6"/> my censure; sometimes, because it were more then needes; sometimes because of the difficultie. I mention Authors sometimes of meane quality, for the meanest haue sence to obserue that which themselues see, more certainly then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations and <hi>Theorie</hi> of the more learned. I would also acknowledge the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the meanest. I haue laboured to reduce Relations to their first Authors, setting their names to their Allegations: the want whereof hath much troubled mee, whilst the most leaue out their Authors, as if their owne assertion were suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient authoritie in things borrowed. I haue (to my great paines) contracted and Epitomized whole Volumes (and some very large) into one Chapter; a thing vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all through these Relations. Where I haue found plentifull discourse for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (my chiefe aime) I am shorter in other Relations; and where I haue had lesse helpes for that discouerie, I insist more on the wonders of Nature, and discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by Sea and Land, with other remarkeable accidents. These Rarities of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I haue sometimes suted in a differing phrase and figure of speech; not that I affect a fantasticall singularitie; but that these Diuine workes might appeare in Robes, if not fitting their Maiestie, yet such as our Word-Robe did willingly without any great affectation or studie, affoord: not without example of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which vseth to bring in the mute Creatures, speaking and performing (as it were) other personall offices; nor without this effect to make the Reader stay a while with obseruation and wonder; besides that, variety of it selfe is delightsome.</p>
   <p>If any mislike the fulnesse in some places, and the barrennesse of words in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; let them consider, we handle a World, where are Mountaines and Vallies, fertile habitations, and sandy desarts: and others steps, whom I follow, hold me sometimes in a narrower way, which elsewhere take more libertie. I touch here and there a <hi>Controuersie;</hi> both for illustration of Historie; and in season, and out of season, to shew my affectation to the Truth.</p>
   <p>Now if any man thinke, that it were better these rotten bones of the passed, and stinking bodies of the Present superstitions were buried, then thus raked out of their graues; besides that which hath beene said, I answere, That I haue suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient example in the Scriptures, <hi>which were written for our learning to the ends of the World,</hi> and yet depaint vnto vs the vgly face of Idolatry in so many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of the Heathens, with the Apostasies, Sects, and Heresies of the Iewes, as in our first and second booke is shewed: and the Ancient Fathers also, <hi>Iustin, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Clemens, Irenaeus, Origen,</hi> and more fully, <hi>Eusebius, Epiphanius, Philastri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Augustine,</hi> haue gone before vs in their large Catalogues of Heresies and false Opinions.</p>
   <p>I appeale vnto any indifferent Reader (for some not Readers, nor indifferent, I respect not, whose Authoritie, perhaps, would be but indifferent, if they must first win it by being Authors of so big, I dare not say, so great volumes) if there be any, either Idolatries, or other impieties, in this worke of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne expressed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond theirs which heere out of the Scriptures are mentioned; Stewes in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, humane Sacrifices to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>loch, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>muz</hi> his mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ning, Sodomites, Incests, with other fleshly, worldly, beastly, Deuillish monst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s of iniquitie, obtruded vnder Religions Sacred Mantle, amongst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Amorites, Egyptians and Iewes, before the comming of Christ: or greater darkenesse and more hellish then when the <hi>Light</hi> it selfe was made manifest, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d <hi>the Darkne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e comprehended it not: Herods</hi> butcheries, <hi>Iudas</hi> his treacherie, the blasphemie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the Scribes, Priests, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises, and the crucifying of the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>od <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y men, for men: or since, if as stin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, loathsome, monstrous abuses h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> beene offered to the Christian Name in worse impostures and pollutions, by the Nicholaitans, and other incarnat De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, recorded by those Fathers and other Ecclesiasticall Authors, then any of those heere in this booke obserued: to which, if that which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> hath written of the Gnostikes alone, fully and particularly, be considered, all these Ethnike and Mahumetan superstitions would comparatiuely be <hi>iustified:</hi> So true is that olde saying, <hi>Corruptio optimi pessima;</hi> and of the Truth it selfe, <hi>Sodom and her daughters</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> not comparable to <hi>Ierusalem with hers;</hi> and of the iustest Iudge, that <hi>it shall bee easier at the day of Iudgement</hi> for Those then These. And what indeede doth more set forth the glory of Gods grace, then in pardoning; his power, then in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; his justice, then in giuing men vp to such delusions? Are not these the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees and glorious victories of THE CROSSE OF CHRIST, that hath sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted the Temples, Oracles, Sacrifices, and Seruices of the Deuill? And maist not thou see herein, what <hi>Man</hi> is, and thou thy selfe maist bee, if God leaue thee to thy selfe? Read therefore, with prayses vnto GOD, <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thy light;</hi> and prayers for these Heathens, that GOD may bring them out of the <hi>snare of the Deuill,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Christ</hi> may be <hi>his saluation to the ends of the World.</hi> And let me also obtaine thy prayers in this my <hi>Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage,</hi> to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in directed, to the glorie of GOD, and good of my Countrie. Euen so LORD IESVS.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>