<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Induction to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111678_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15033</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111678</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Induction to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English myrror : A regard wherein al estates may behold the conquests of enuy: containing ruine of common weales, murther of princes, cause of heresies, and in all ages, spoile of deuine and humane blessings, vnto which is adioyned, enuy conquered by vertues. Publishing the peaceable victories obtained by the Queenes most excellent Maiesty, against this mortall enimie of publike peace and prosperitie, and lastly a fortris against enuy, builded vpon the counsels of sacred Scripture, lawes of sage philosophers, and pollicies of well gouerned common weales: wherein euery estate may see the dignities, the true office and cause of disgrace of his vocation. A worke safely, and necessarie to be read of euerie good subiect. By George Whetstones Gent. Malgre. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Seton, Gregory.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 180, 10, 201-249, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="87"/>
   <head>Induction to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit, that peace is a most precious blessing of God, a large testimonie of a gratious Prince, and the perfect image of a well gouerned common wealth: yet the euill, which abuse whatsoeuer is good (as the Spider draweth hony from the purest flower) of these good causes, beget such foule effects, as God in reward of his blessings, is dishonored, persecuted, and blasphemed. The gratious Prince, for his or her protection, is neither dutifully reuerenced, nor truely obeyed: and what is sowen for publike benefite, groweth to the ruine of the Countries prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Vpon the experience of the good gouernement of</hi> Athens <hi>and other florishing Commonwealthes corrupted, or to speake more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confounded, by such vile persons, as their principall Cities foste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: warranted the graue</hi> Socrates, <hi>being demaunded what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased the wealth, of a Commonwelth, to answere, that peace was the inricher thereof: being demaunded on the contrarie part, the chiefe cause of pouertie, in a Common wealth, semblablie aunswered that peace was the meane thereof. Being asked his reasons, said, that in the time of peace Armes giue place to Lawes, and good Lawes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministreth both plentie and prosperitie, to such Countries as receiue and obay them: on the other side he alledged, that wealth the blessing of peace, bread many vices in her owne bowels, of the nature of Mothes in cloath, or canker rust in yron, which by the consuming of their suckers destroy themselues: and questionles the wheele of peace painted on either side with these fiue spokes, Peace bringeth plentie, Plentie causeth pride, Pride raiseth enuie, Enuie soweth sedition, and Sedition hatcheth pouertie, is rather the deuise of some Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers setled iudgement, than the toy of a Painters variable fancie: the Embleame, so truely portrayeth the change of all happie gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But some more quicke of wit, then in discretion perfect, will suggest, that where Law hath her full voyce, these Cankers can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer grow to the consumption of the heart: to which question I thus aunswere, that Law may haue a free passage, and yet Iustice scanted of her due course: for Lawe will not, or cannot punish an apparant trespas without an open presentment: and Iustice would chasten the concealed fault, if she could commaund the Law, and such is the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi>
      <pb facs="88"/>
      <hi>of pollitike Lawe breakers, that where the ignorant are han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for stealing of a sheete, they will haue the Lawe to strengthen them, in the robbing of a mans inhearitance, and therefore is Lawe likened to a backe sworde, eadged and sharpe, to chasten the simple offender, and blunt when the subtill shoulde bee corrected. Vppon which reason, quoth</hi> Diogines, <hi>what auaileth it to haue profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lawes, when the good readeth them not, and the euill cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, or care not for them: but although</hi> Diogines <hi>spake truelie as touching the naturall humors of men, for vnto the good their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences are in steede of Lawes, and with the lewde, no bridle is a restraint from euill: Yet grounding my reasons vppon larger authorities, I graunt</hi> Necessitie inuentris <hi>of all policies hath founde good Lawes so necessarie, as I holde those Realmes, Regions, Cities, and Townes which are not gouerned by Lawes, rather to bee forrestes of wilde beastes, than places habitable for men: for there where Lawes are musled, Iustice goeth masked, might mastereth right, Theft is reputed honest gaine, and murther lawfull reuenge: Treasou woulde enter the priuie Chamber, and to bee short the wealthie, shoulde go to wracke, and the inferiour would order, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they had disordered all good gouernement. These open outrages, are suppressed by the paines of Lawe, although the awe of chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cannot keepe some raskall persons from offending in secreat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Heraclites <hi>saith,</hi> absque legibus nullo pacto possit ciuitas esse incolumis, sed absque menibus possit, <hi>without Lawes a Cittie by no meanes can be in saftie, but without walles it may. And</hi> Forteskew <hi>saith,</hi> Lex est sanctio sancta Iubens honesta, &amp; prohibens contraria. <hi>Law is an vncorrupt holines commaunding things that are honest, and forbidding those that are contrarie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Therefore I doe reuerence good Lawgiuers, and (as deuine</hi> Plato <hi>saieth) repute all Lawes, that are made for the wealth and sauegarde of mankinde, to bee of GOD, although they bee deuised by men. This onely lacketh to set foorth the glorie of good Lawes, and to possesse the Common wealth with their true benefites:</hi> The administrators of Lawes, are nothing so carefull to finde out the offender as they are readie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Sentence of the offence: <hi>agreeing with an olde tale of a Viccar of</hi> Croyden, <hi>who of a peece of his Vicreage made an</hi>
      <pb facs="88"/>
      <hi>Ale-house, and there kept an harlotte: for in those dayes the Lawe of the Church forbadde Priestes to marrie, and yet the awe of hell coulde not subdew their lustes: this smoge Chaplaine, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the lesson, long before giuen vnto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> the Cleargie,</hi> Si non caste, tamen Caute: <hi>as hee thought to take away all suspition of his misbehauiour, made a vehement Sermon against</hi> Lecherie, <hi>and agrauated the vengeaunces of that sinne, with all the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which hee coulde recite in the Scripture: earnestlie exhorting his Parishioners, to cleanse the towne of that damnable and filthie iniquitie: whereuppon one of the Church-wardens (that knewe the Viccar had violated his vowe) cryed out Master Viccar if you will giue vs example, by purging of the Church-yarde, wee will bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to cleanse the rest of the Parish: the Viccar smelling the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Church-warden, pleasantlie to huddle vp the matter, replied that the Church-warden spake without reason: for quoth he, the Church-yarde is the appointed place to receiue the most filthie Carrion of the worlde, and withall wished the people not to mistake him, for hee onely spake of the sinne, but medled not with the sinner. A great part of the meane officers of Iustice at this day, doe as the Viccar saide.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Penall Lawes (which are manie, and yet no more than are necessarie: Vice is growne to so great a strength) are solemnely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in euerie Sise, Session, and Leete, the offenders manie, and many times present at the repetition of their Trespasses, and yet seldome or neuer bee presented, that they may feele the scourge dew to their Trespasses, when the Trespasser, by his fault is as well knowne to the Iustice, Iurie, Steward, or other officer, as to his owne conscience which offendeth: and howe commeth this barre of Iustice? forsooth by this straining of curtesie: the Iudge will punish but what the Iurie findeth: the Iurie will finde but what is presented, fewe will present without inforcement: and thus good Iustice, which was wont to bee so quicke, as men portrayed her with a paire of wings, is nowe so slowe, as shee needeth a spurre. And shee that was likened vnto fire, which being naturall, both cherisheth and consumeth, by the coldnesse of mens Conscienses, may nowe bee compared to painted fire, which neither comforteth the good, nor wasteth the lewde.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="89"/>
      <hi>But this defect is not so properly to be applyed to Iustice, as to the infirmitie of her administrators, who (as</hi> Gordian <hi>saith) ought to be so free from partialitie, as in the seruice of Iustice, they must for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the affection of a Father, a husband, a kinseman, and a friende. This</hi> Gordian <hi>was a graue Senatour of</hi> Rome, <hi>who in the time of the dissolute and beastly raigne of the most vicious Emperour</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liogabalus, <hi>made sute to be discharged of the authorities which he bore in the common wealth: not for that he grew weary of the serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which he did vnto his Countrie, but in that he abhorred to slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reuerence dew vnto a Iudge, with iniust sentenses, which the priuiledges of the wicked, would inforce him vnto. He would verie often say, that a good Common wealthes man, applyeth all the parts of a well proportioned creature, whose hands are bound behind him: his eyes are no lesse occupied to prie into the doings of the lewd, then his eares attentiue, to heare the complaints of the good: his tongue is mute neither for feare, nor fauour, and by his leagues he presenteth a continuall trauel to do his countrie seruice, his handes bound behind him, sheweth him as well bound vnto all these offices, as free from briberies: and doubtlesse the authorised Maiestrate which is thus diligent, and no lesse free from corruption, shall aswell be busied to chasten the offences which he findeth himselfe, as to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish such as be discouered by others. Truely there be a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of right worthy Maiestrates in this happie gouernement of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, who with the eyes, eares, tongue, and legges of</hi> Gordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>common wealthes man, both foresee the actions of naughtie persons, and prouide to frustrate their determinations, and as the Amners of Gods blessings, especially bestowed vppon this happie Realme, since the first houre of her sacred Maiesties most prosperous raigne, haue both stopped the passages of forraine practises and ciuill conspiracies, and without bloodsheading, onely armed with deuine and morall vertues, ouercommeth these enimies with their owne swordes, as a concaue Mirror daunteth the assailer with his proper weapon, so that all Nations by the impressions of their owne sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, as well as through knowledge of our happinesse, with the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite they admyre her Maiestie and good Maiestrates prudent go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, doe enuie the peace, plentie, and protection of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior subiects.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="89"/>
      <hi>Now some will say, by the searching wisedomes of her Maiestie and graue senate, prosperitie, in all her dominions is administred, and the enimies thereof, of their purposes are defeated, and referre all this to a needlesse purpose. There are rare monuments, to eter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ise the vertues of the Queene, Counsell, and chiefe Maiestrates, and in the rest no notable vice generally to bee reprooued. But with sorrowe I reporte, and their doings approoues it: Vice is as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally imbraced of the multitude, as vertue is especially cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed of the better sorte: since the case so standes, who will not say, that that buylding is out of order, whose spares are rotten, whose windowes are broken, and whose roofe is vncouered: although the groundworke bee stronge, and principall timbers sounde. Surelie a happie common wealth, resembleth a faire building, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whereof is the Prince, the principals are the chiefe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestrates, the sparres, the Inferiour officers, the windowes, the Nobilitie and Gentilitie: the Tiles that couereth the same, are the Citisens and multitude: and the faire roomes within the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, are the liberties of the Cleargie, who are priuiledged to blame sinne in all estates, but the punishment appertaineth to the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, and sworde of the Prince: all which partes firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnited together, doe strengthen one another, and the corruption of the least, by the sufferance of Time, will turne to the confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the greatest, and therefore by the Lawe of Nature, the meanest person, in his vocation is sworne to trauell for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like benefite of his Countrie. It is no excuse sufficient for him that is not authorised to chasten offences, to suffer offenders to liue vnder his nose vnpresented, that the Maiestrate may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish, nor yet no good discharge of his duetie, that is authorised to leaue an offence vnpunished, vntill information bee giuen by others, when his owne knowledge is able to condemne the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: euerie man is bounde for his owne safetie to discouer an euill liuer, and euerie man that hath authoritie, is bounde both to correct the offence, and to enquire after the offender. If euerie man in his calling woulde thus truely doe the office of a good Common wealthes man: Enuie and all euill, woulde bee easilie withstoode: men woulde soone looke into the dueties of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vocation, for feare that others looked into the abuses thereof.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="90"/>
      <hi>I haue with the authoritie of the wise and learned, set downe what is needefull for euerie man to consider of his calling, if they will striue against vertue, and the credite of their vocations, they are worthy of double punishment, both for the fault, and for wilfulnesse, being warned of which, I hope the godly reader will be admonished.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>