<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR FRANCIS BARRINGTON Knight and Baronet, my much honored and worthy friend: And to the no lesse vertuous then religious Lady, the Lady BARRINGTON his Wife, continuance with increase of happinesse heere, and eternall happinesse hereafter.</title>
           <author>Maunsell, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111781_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15815</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26077</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111781</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR FRANCIS BARRINGTON Knight and Baronet, my much honored and worthy friend: And to the no lesse vertuous then religious Lady, the Lady BARRINGTON his Wife, continuance with increase of happinesse heere, and eternall happinesse hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Maunsell, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Soueraigne comforts for a troubled conscience : Wherein the subtilties of Satan are discouered, his reasons and obiections fully answered. And further, the truth laid open and manifested, to the great consolation and strengthening of such as are distressed and afflicted in minde. Written by the late faithfull seruant of the Lord Mr. Robert Yarrow. And now published for the benefit of such as groning vnder the burthen of an afflicted conscience desire comfort</title>
                 <author>Yarrow, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rounthwait, Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 438 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR FRANCIS BARRINGTON Knight and Baronet, my much honored and worthy friend: And to the no lesse vertuous then religious Lady, the Lady BARRINGTON his Wife, continuance with increase of happinesse heere, and eternall happinesse <hi>hereafter.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> and <hi>good Madam,</hi> though not as I <hi>would,</hi> yet as I <hi>can,</hi> I shal euer be ready to testifie my <hi>respect</hi> and <hi>thankfulnes</hi> for your <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>kinde fauours</hi> towards me;
<pb facs="3"/>whereof till the Lord shall be pleased to giue further means, <hi>accept</hi> (I pray you) <hi>this,</hi> which as it is a <hi>publike,</hi> so my desire is, it may bee a <hi>perpetuall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I <hi>present</hi> you here with the <hi>labours</hi> of <hi>another,</hi> which comming to my hands some few yeeres since, gaue mee then so good content, that when I restored the <hi>originall</hi> to the owner, it left another <hi>same</hi> behinde it: <hi>That</hi> not long since, beeing <hi>required</hi> at my hands to bee sent abroad to the <hi>publique view,</hi> after some <hi>consideration</hi> thereof had, and the <hi>owner</hi> to whom it more
<pb facs="3"/>properly belonged <hi>made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted</hi> therewith: and the <hi>originall</hi> of the <hi>Authors</hi> owne hand-writing <hi>commended</hi> and <hi>committed</hi> vnto <hi>mee</hi> to that end and purpose, I <hi>condiscen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:</hi> And that as for <hi>their sakes</hi> who groning vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of a <hi>troubled spirit,</hi> may by the <hi>blessing</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <hi>benefit</hi> hereby: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise and much the rather for <hi>yours,</hi> to whom I did <hi>destinate</hi> the same, from the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant that the request vvas made.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Vouchsafe</hi> therefore (I pray you) to let it passe into the world, vnder the <hi>TITLE</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>of your <hi>NAME,</hi> which as it will bee a <hi>shelter</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> it against the <hi>detraction</hi> of <hi>ill dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed</hi> persons; so will it bee likewise as <hi>an oyntment powred out,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> yeelding a <hi>sweet sauour</hi> to make it <hi>pleasing,</hi> not so much to the <hi>nostrils,</hi> as the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>minds</hi> of the <hi>well affected,</hi> and more <hi>godly</hi> sort of Christians.</p>
   <p>And thus <hi>commending you</hi> to that our good <hi>God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32.</note>
      <hi>and to the Word of his Grace,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10.</note> that is <hi>not vnrighteous to forget your worke and labour of loue, which yee haue shewed towards his Name, in that ye haue</hi> beene so farre from being <hi>ashamed of the Gospell of his Christ,</hi> that to the
<pb facs="4"/>good <hi>example</hi> of the <hi>godly,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</note> and the <hi>shame</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> yee haue <hi>profest</hi> the same in <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>sinceritie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</note> and beene <hi>blamelesse and harmelesse, the Children of God without rebuke, in the mids of a crooked and peruerse Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, among whom yee shine as lights in the world:</hi> I take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all due, and Christian respect, <hi>Iohn Maunsell.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>