<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE FAIRE READER, OF THE FAYRER SEX.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111643_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14878</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111643</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE FAIRE READER, OF THE FAYRER SEX.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasant and delightfvl historie of Curan, a prince of Danske, and the fayre Princesse Argentile, daughter and heyre to Adelbright, sometime King of Northumberland : Shewing his first loue vnto her, his succeslesse suite, and the low deiections he vnderwent for her sake. His second loue to the same lady vnknowne, taking her for a poore countrie damsell. She (by reason of the vnkindnesse of King Edell her vnckle and gardian) hauing forsooke the court, and vndertooke the profession of a neatheardes mayde. His constant loue (after her long continued vnkindnes) rewarded with her wished consent, their happie nuptials, and mutuall reioycings, his valour and victorious warre with King Edell: and lastly, his peacefull installment in the kingly throne. Enterlacte with many pritty and pithie prayses of beauty, and other amorous discourses, pleasing, smooth and delightfull. By William Webster</title>
                 <author>Webster, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Higgenbotham, Richard 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE FAIRE READER, OF THE FAYRER SEX.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>YOu louely <hi>DAME,</hi> whose beautie is as much</l>
      <l>As was this louely Dames, faire <hi>Argentile:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>For in the world, where should wee looke for such,</l>
      <l>If not where shee was bred, in this faire Ile.</l>
      <l>For breeeding such, our Clime; then other Climes</l>
      <l>More fertile is, our times, then former times.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You are the very same, yea, you are shee,</l>
      <l>Whose Beautie in this Booke is so commended:</l>
      <l>And though your Name not <hi>Argentile</hi> it be,</l>
      <l>Yet know your selfe is shee that's here intended.</l>
      <l>These lines were writ for you, of them make vse,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Beauties</hi> praises to your selfe reduce.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You liuing, louely <hi>Dame,</hi> t'was for your sake,</l>
      <l>That this insuing taske I vndertooke:</l>
      <l>Not hers, shee'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> dead, shee'l no requitall make,</l>
      <l>But at your hands (at least) for thankes I looke.</l>
      <l>To grace what graceth you, I here haue sought,</l>
      <l>Then deigne to grace me with a gracious thought.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You are faire (as was shee) but be not tho,</l>
      <l>Coy (as was shee) O varry you in this:</l>
      <l>I would not for the world you should be so,</l>
      <l>For then as good that you the world did misse.</l>
      <l>Vnlesse your kindnesse should (as hers) at last,</l>
      <l>Make large amends, for your vnkindnesse past.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Had I prays'd Bountie(so)perhaps my paine,</l>
      <l>Might haue bene recompenced with reward:</l>
      <l>Then let me not praise Beauty (thus) in vaine,</l>
      <l>Afford me in requitall some regard.</l>
      <l>You I haue sought to please, and I from you,</l>
      <l>Due thankes, and due respect, expect: Adue.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>