<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The godly Fathers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111197_Ba1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19533</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5963</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The godly Fathers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short summe of the whole catechisme : wherin the question is propounded and answered in fewe wordes, for the greater ease of the common people &amp; children. Gathered by M. Iohn Craig, minister of Gods word, to the Kinges Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Craig, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 49, that is 56, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authorities">
   <p>I Thought good to adde for the better confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this confession, the iudgement of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and Godlye Fathers, concerning the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie <pb n="53" facs="57"/>
      <hi>of the holy scriptures, vpon the which only they grounded their faith and religion, and by the same onely confuted and condemned all contrarie doctrine and religion, in their time, as their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings do testifie to vs. And next I laye downe the open and shameles blasphemies of the late Papists spued out, and written in contempt of the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and praise of mens traditions aboue the word of God, the which traditions they reuerence equally with the Scriptures, as it shall appeare by their owne wordes.</hi>
   </p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The godly Fathers.</head>
      <q>
         <bibl>Irenaeus lib. 3. cap. 8.</bibl>
         <p>THe Apostles haue put in writing the things, that were to be the foundation and piller of our faith.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Idem Cap.</hi> 11.</bibl>
         <p>The piller and groundworke of the Church, is the Gospell, and the spirite of life.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Origenes, lib. 1. cap. 17. in Epist. ad Roman.</bibl>
         <p> Out of the scriptures onely our interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should be taken.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem in prim. Hieremie.</bibl>
         <p> Our iudgements and expositions haue no credite without the testimonie of the scriptures.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <pb facs="58"/>
         <bibl>Idem Homil. 25. in Matth.</bibl>
         <p> For confirmation of all those wordes we speake in our teaching, we should first alleadge the iudgement of the Scripture, as a confirmation of that thing we declare vnto you.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Ciprianus, de Baptismo Christi.</bibl>
         <p> Out of the scriptures must come all rule of teaching.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Basilius, epist.</bibl>
         <p> 8. The scripture is a perfect rule and line, and admitteth no addition.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, ibidem.</bibl>
         <p> Let vs stand to the iudgement of the scripture, inspired by God, &amp; let the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of truth be giuen to them, whose doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is agreeable to the heauenly oracles.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Cyrillus in Johan. lib.</bibl>
         <p> 12. All things, that our Lord did, are not written, but the Apostles wrote the things, they iudged to bee sufficient for our maners and doctrine.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Basilius, de vera Fide.</bibl>
         <p> It is pride, to reiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing the Apostles haue written, or to adde any thing to their writings, &amp; bring in things not written.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Theophilus, epist. 9. cap. vlt.</bibl>
         <p> They that offer any thing, except the doctrine of the Apostles, they bring in slanders, heresies, &amp; dissentions.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Ambrosius.</bibl>
         <p> We iustly damne all newe things, which Christ did not teach, because Christ is the waye to the faithfull.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, primo officiorum.</bibl>
         <p> Thinges that wée <pb n="54" facs="58"/> finde not in the scripture, we may vse as wee please.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Hieronimus, Psal.</bibl>
         <p> 86. Take heed what they say that were, and not that are now: for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer thing is spoken without the doctrine of the Apostles, let it be put away, and haue no authoritie.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem in Aggaeum.</bibl>
         <p> The worde is Gods sworde wherewith all these things are cutte off, which without the testimonie and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Scriptures men of their owne head do inuent and faine, as traditions of the Apostles.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Chrisostomus, opere imperfecto. Homil.</bibl>
         <p> 49. In no way can the true Church of Christ be knowne, but by the scriptures onely.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, in sancto &amp; adorando Spiritu.</bibl>
         <p> If anye thing be obtruded without the Gospell, vnder the title of the spirite, let vs not beleeue it.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, opere imperfecto, Homil.</bibl>
         <p> 49. Wee should in no case giue credit to the Church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they speake and do the things, that are consonant to the Scriptures.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Augustinus, de vnitate Ecclesiae, cap.</bibl>
         <p> 2. The Scripture doth shew Christ in the Church.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem in Iohan. tract.</bibl>
         <p> 96. When the Lord hath not reuealed these thinges, which of vs <pb facs="59"/> can say: these, or these things are: and if any man will affirme this, or that to be, how doth he proue it?</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem. de Pastoribus cap.</bibl>
         <p> 14. I enquire at the voice of the Pastour, to reade me it out of the Prophet, reade it out of the Psalme, recite it out of the law, recite it out of the Gospel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite it out of the Apostle.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Ibidem, lib. 2. cap. 85. contraliteras Petiliani.</bibl>
         <p> Whether we are Schismatikes, or ye, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I, nor thou shall be iudge, but let Christ be demaunded, that he may shewe his owne Church.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Tertullianus, de praescriptione contra haereticos.</bibl>
         <p> The Heretickes deny, that Christ and the Apostles reuealed all things to all, but some thing openly, some thing secretly.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Athanatius orat. 2. contra haereticos,</bibl>
         <p> Doth testifie, that the <hi>Arrians</hi> glorted in reuelations and in the spirite without the word.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Augustinus, de natura &amp; gratia.</bibl>
         <p> 61. I am bound to giue consent, onely to the canonicall Scriptures, without any excuse.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Epiphanius. lib. 1. Haeresi.</bibl>
         <p> 38. Affirmeth, that <hi>Caiani an Heretike,</hi> saide, that they recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their errours, by traditions without the Scriptures.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Irenaus, lib. 3. cap.</bibl>
         <p> 2. The Heretikes when <pb n="55" facs="59"/> they are rebuked by the Scriptures, they turne to the accusation of the Scriptures, as if they were corrupt, or had not authoritie, and that they are spoken sundrie waies, and that the truth cannot be found by them, if we want the traditions.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>1. Leo, Epist. 83. ad Palest.</bibl>
         <p> Ye are armed with the name of the Church, and therwith do fight against the Church.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Cyprianus, de simplicitate Prelatorum.</bibl>
         <p> The diuell hath found a new deceit, that vnder the title of Christian people, he may deceiue them that are not warie and heedfull.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Augustinus de sermone Domini in monte.</bibl>
         <p> The sheepe should not cast away her skin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause wolues and todes sometimes hide them selues vnder it.</p>
      </q>
      <p>Papists acknowledge here your owne words, against the Scriptures, agreable to the olde heretikes your fathers.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>THis was the doctrine of the Fathers, and Faith of the Church, for the space of 500. yeares, after the assension of Christ. The which doctrine &amp; faith, did piece by piece decaye, as the Romaine Antichrist did growe to his high estimation, where through the true handling of the Scriptures was altogither neglected, and his</hi>
         <pb facs="60"/>
         <hi>traditions placed in their roome, &amp; so the Pope with his creatures were placed aboue the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to make Scriptures lawfull, or vnlawfull, &amp; to be the onely Iudge of all interpretations, &amp; their sentence to be without all errour, and so all men bound to it, without any contradictions, as the his<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Church do plainly declare, but chiefely the bloud of the Saintes of God shed for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this doctrine of the Fathers against their errours.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>Wherfore I desire the diligent Reader, to marke these blasphemies following, which the slaues of that pestilent seate haue spued out against the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, the Fathers iudgement, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the primitine Church.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The second Head, concerning the blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Papists, against the worde of God.</head>
      <q>
         <bibl>Cusanus Cardinal Epist. 2. ad Bohemos.</bibl>
         <p>THe scriptures must follow the church, and not the church the scriptures.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem. Ibidem.</bibl>
         <p> I say, the precepts of Christ are of no strength, except the church admitte them for such.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Hosius Cardinalis, de expresso verbo Dei.</bibl>
         <p> It is <pb n="56" facs="60"/> vaine labour that is spent vpō the scriptures, we will rather waite for Gods sentence out of heauen.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, Ibidem.</bibl>
         <p> What the Church doth teach, that is the expresse word of god, what is taught against the mind and consent of it, is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse word of the Deuill.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, Ibidem.</bibl>
         <p> If a man haue the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> albeit he seeth not how it agreeth, or disagreeth with the text, this man hath the very expresse word of God.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Eckius, multis in locis,</bibl>
         <p> The scripture is the blacke Gospell, and diuinitie of Inck.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Herwaeus, de potestate Papae,</bibl>
         <p> The Pope is the whole Church in power.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Uerractus,</bibl>
         <p> The determination of the church is called the Gospell.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Piggius, de caelesti Hierarchia.</bibl>
         <p> The Church hath power to giue to some Scriptures a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall authoritie, which they neither haue of them selues, nor yet of their authours.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, Ibidem,</bibl>
         <p> The scriptures are like a nose of waxe, which may be turned in what shape and forme thou please to forme and drawe it.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Idem, Ibidem,</bibl>
         <p> The Apostles wrote some thinges, not that these writings should be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours to our faith, but rather that our faith should be superiour to them.</p>
      </q>
      <pb facs="61"/>
      <p>NOw let all men iudge, what spirite mooued these godlesse writers, to blaspheme the Scriptures of God so shamefully. But some will say, they were priuate men, and not the Pope: nor his Councell. I answere: They were gladly heard, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorised, and well rewarded by the Pope and his corrupted Synagogue. And <hi>Io. Hus, Hiero. de Praga,</hi> with sundrie others of our brethren cruelly were persecuted with fire and sword, for speaking against their blasphemies.</p>
      <p>It is true, the late Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to iudge more reuerently of the Scriptures, when they hid their venom vnder some faire and generall termes. But which of them was offended when they heard the Bishop of <hi>Poytiers</hi> in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation call the Scriptures, <hi>a voyde &amp; dumbe law, &amp;c?</hi> And likewise, who accused the prophane Priest of <hi>Laterane,</hi> which in all their presence, called the Scriptures <hi>dead Luk. &amp;c?</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>Andradius</hi> writing in the defence of that prophane Councell, doth plainlye testifie, that they in their mindes did throughly agree with these blasphemies, but yet durst not speake so plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against the Scriptures, least they should haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the common people against them.</p>
      <p>And therefore to bleare the eies of the people for a time, they ioyne the Scriptures and their vnwritten traditions togither in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="61"/>But in the meane time, they arme and send out certaine vile slaues, and godlesse runnegates to speake and write against the written worde, who doe call it <hi>a dead Letter, obscure, vncertaine, insufficient, the occasion of all heresies, written without the commandement of Christ, and vnprofitable to the people</hi> labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hereby to bring the consciences of men from the worde of life to their diuellish traditions.</p>
      <p>Let all men therefore that loue the trueth of God, flee farre from this deceitfull and diuellish companie, which God in his wrath hath raised vp to blind this vnthankeful age, and to trie our faith and patience, vnto the time of our full victory, through <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> our Lorde. To whom with the Father and the holy Spirit, be all honour, praise, and Maiesty, for euer and euer. So be it.</p>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>