<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS AND MOST NOBLE PRINCESSE, the Lady FRAN∣CIS, Duchesse of RICHMOND and LENOX.</title>
           <author>Smith, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111882_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22790</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS AND MOST NOBLE PRINCESSE, the Lady FRAN∣CIS, Duchesse of RICHMOND and LENOX.</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The generall historie of Virginia, New-England, and the Summer Isles : with the names of the adventurers, planters, and governours from their first beginning. an⁰: 1584. to this present 1624. With the procedings of those severall colonies and the accidents that befell them in all their journyes and discoveries. Also the maps and descriptions of all those countryes, their commodities, people, government, customes, and religion yet knowne. Divided into sixe bookes. By Captaine Iohn Smith sometymes governour in those countryes &amp; admirall of New England</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Reeve (Reave), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 96, 105-248 pages, 6 plates (4 folded), portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS AND MOST NOBLE PRINCESSE, the Lady FRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIS, Duchesse of RICHMOND and LENOX.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it please your <hi>Grace,</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>This History, as for the raritie and varietie of the subiect, so much more for the judicious <hi>Eyes</hi> it is like to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, and most of all for that great <hi>Name,</hi> whereof it dareth implore Protection, might and ought to haue beene clad in better robes then my rude military hand can cut out in Paper Ornaments. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, of the most things therein, I am no Compiler by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, but haue beene a reall Actor; I take my selfe to haue a propertie in them: and therefore haue beene bold to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge them to come vnder the reach of my owne rough Pen. That, which hath beene indured and passed through with hardship and danger, is thereby sweetned to the <hi>Actor,</hi> when he becometh the <hi>Relator.</hi> I haue deeply hazarded my selfe in doing and suffering, and why should I sticke to hazard my reputation in Recording? He that acteth two parts is the more borne withall if he come short, or fayle in one of them. Where shall we looke to finde a <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> whose at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuments shine as cleare in his owne Commentaries, as they did in the field? I confesse, my hand, though able to weild a weapon among the Barbarous, yet well may trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="4"/>
in handling a Pen among so many <hi>Indicious</hi>: especially when I am so bold as to call so piercing, and so glorious an <hi>Eye,</hi> as your <hi>Grace,</hi> to view these poore ragged lines</p>
   <p>Yet my comfort is, that heretofore honorable and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Ladies,</hi> and comparable but amongst themselues, haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred me rescue and protection in my greatest dangers: even in forraine parts, I haue felt reliefe from that sex. The beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady <hi>Tragabigzanda,</hi> when I was a slaue to the <hi>Turkes,</hi> did all she could to secure me. When I overcame the <hi>Bashaw</hi> of <hi>Nalbrits</hi> in <hi>Tartaria,</hi> the charitable Lady <hi>Call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mata</hi> supplyed my necessities. In the vtmost of many extremities, that blessed <hi>Pokahontas,</hi> the great Kings daughter of <hi>Virginia,</hi> oft saved my life. When I escaped the crueltie of Pirats and most furious stormes, a long time alone in a small Boat at Sea, and driven ashore in <hi>France,</hi> the good Lady <hi>Madam Chanoyes,</hi> bountifully assisted me.</p>
   <p>And so verily these my adventures haue tasted the same <hi>influence</hi> from your <hi>Gratious hand,</hi> which hath given birth to the publication of this <hi>Narration.</hi> If therefore your <hi>Grace</hi> shall daigne to cast your eye on this poore Booke, view I pray you rather your owne <hi>Bountie</hi> (without which it had dyed in the wombe) then my <hi>imperfections,</hi> which haue no helpe but the shrine of your <hi>glorious Name</hi> to be sheltered from cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorious condemnation. Vouchsafe some glimpse of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable <hi>aspect,</hi> to accept these my labours; to protect them vnder the shadow of your excellent <hi>Name</hi>: which will ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them to be presented to the <hi>Kings royall Maiestie,</hi> the most admired Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>Bohemia</hi>: your sweet Recommendations will make it the worthier of their good countenances. And as all my endevours are their due tribute: so this Page shall record to posteritie, that my service shall be to pray to <hi>God,</hi> that you may still continue the renowned of your sexe, the most honored of men, and the highly blessed of <hi>God.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your</hi> Graces <hi>faithfull and devoted servant,</hi> IOHN SMITH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>