<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>  To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111832_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10231</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20508.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>  To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Purchas his pilgrimage. Or Relations of the vvorld and the religions obserued in all ages and places discouered, from the Creation vnto this present : Contayning a theologicall and geographicall historie of Asia, Africa, and America, with the ilands adiacent. Declaring the ancient religions before the Floud ... The fourth edition, much enlarged with additions, and illustrated with mappes through the whole worke; and three whole treatises annexed, one of Russia and other northeasterne regions by Sr. Ierome Horsey; the second of the Gulfe of Bengala by Master William Methold; the third of the Saracenicall empire, translated out of Arabike by T. Erpenius. By Samuel Purchas, parson of St. Martins by Ludgate, London</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 242, 241-636, 635-1047, 37 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="517"/>
   <pb facs="517"/>
   <head>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, I here present vnto thee in a later seruice, that which deserued a fitter place in another Worke; and which I had sought with much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie before, without successe. I am ashamed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> againe to tell thee with what little effect my Russian labours for Intelligence were seconded: but since my <hi>PILGRIMES</hi> published, Sir <hi>Ierome Horseys</hi> kindnesse offered me (without seeking) better Intelligence then any others could haue giuen; for the times of <hi>Iuan</hi> and <hi>Feodore,</hi> with the politike prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of <hi>Boris</hi> vnto the Muscouian Empire: a Story whereof I was so <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> much more desirous, to publish, because our Age (if euer so short a time in any Age or any State) can hardly parallel the like practises of humane Policies, to couetous, cruell, ambitious ends, ended in the Authours and Actors owne Tragedies; God taking the wise in their craftinesse, and iustly spoyling the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust spoylers, of their spoyles, liues, states, yea, rooting out their whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the greatnesse and glory whereof they had sought to aduance by such wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked courses; and withall punishing the wickednes of the people by so frequent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> forreigne Inuasions and intestine Combustions: that wee may out of others e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils learne this good, <hi>Discite iustitiam moniti,</hi> the true vse of all Historie. I had out of <hi>Alexander Gwagninus, Paulus Oderbornius</hi> and others collected some Relations of <hi>Iuan Vasiliwich</hi> and his Sonnes, but those could see but the out-sides of things, and giue vs but huskes, shels, and rumours,<note place="margin">See my <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes,</hi> Part. 3. l. 4. c. 9.</note> (which often are vncertaine, sometimes false) but here wee present an Eye-witnesse, which tooke not vp Newes on trust by wonted Bils and Tales of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, but was admitted vnto the Mysteries of that State, in the Historie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> of the Imperiall Acts written in their Records; and in his owne personall and honourable Employments betwixt Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of glorious Memory, and the Russian Emperours. And indeed want of the Languages of remote Regions hath hatched many imperfect Histories, the blind leading the blind into errour; wherein as I haue euer loued truth, so was I glad to rectifie our Russian Relations by opportunitie of so worthy a Guide; whose Papers had before furnished Doctor <hi>Fletcher</hi> with the best peeces of his Intelligence.<note place="margin">See <hi>Purchas</hi> his <hi>Pilgrims,</hi> Part. 3. l. 3. c. 1.</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> here also I was straitned in time, the Presse pursuing me so fast, that I had not leisure to transcribe at large the Authours Danish, Polish and Germane
<pb facs="518"/> Relations; nor to adde forme or beauty from Arte: and perhaps this natiue nakednesse in a Iournall or Trauelling Method will be to some most accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Author and matter addes better lustre to the Worke then my words can; the one so full of varietie and weight, the other an experienced and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Knight, employed in many and honourable Seruices of State, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring the Name and Family of the <hi>Horseys,</hi> with his Acts, Arts, and good Parts. Who had long since also dedicated this Worke to that Honourable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triote Sir <hi>Francis Walsingham.</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
   </p>
   <p>Now for Master <hi>Methold,</hi> I had spared some of <hi>Frederikes, Balbies,</hi> and <hi>Fitches</hi> Relations, if these had comne in time, which so many times I had both by messages and in person sought, and by reason of the Authours absence or businesses was frustrate. But the Reader will finde his labour and cost re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compensed in the Rarities of matter, and stile also trauelling beyond the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pace of a Merchant-Traueller. The Relation is correspondent to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, it entreates of a Mine of Diamants, and is a Mine of Diamants it selfe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Gemmes may bee put on after the whole bodie (so I call my former large Worke) is attired and after that full repast, as Indian Drugs vsed in second Seruices, it will second thee with a new, and refresh thee with a fresh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian appetite, and present vnto thee (like Spectacles after great Feasts) such a muster of Indian Elements, affaires, men, arts, Religions, customes, and other varieties, as before we were not able to bring on our Stage. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/>
      <hi>Vale &amp; fruere.</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>