<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his valiant and deserving friend, Captaine IOHN SMITH.</title>
           <author>Jorden, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111906_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12471</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his valiant and deserving friend, Captaine IOHN SMITH.</title>
                 <author>Jorden, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true travels, adventures, and observations of Captaine Iohn Smith, in Europe, Asia, Affrica, and America, from anno Domini 1593. to 1629 : His accidents and sea-fights in the straights; his service and stratagems of warre in Hungaria, Transilvania, Wallachia, and Moldavia, against the Turks, and Tartars ... After how he was taken prisoner by the Turks, sold for a slave ... and escaped ... Together with a continuation of his generall History of Virginia, Summer-Iles, New England, and their proceedings, since 1624. to this present 1629; as also of the new plantations of the great river of the Amazons, the iles of St. Christopher, Mevis, and Barbados in the West Indies. All written by actuall authours, whose names you shall finde along the history</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Reeve (Reave), James.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 60 pages, folded plates, illustrations (engraving, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To his valiant and deserving friend, Captaine IOHN SMITH.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>MOngst <hi>Frenchmen, Spanyards, Hungars, Tartars, Turks,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And wilde <hi>Virginians</hi> too, this tells thy works:</l>
      <l>Now some will aske, what benefit? what gaine?</l>
      <l>Is added to thy store for all this paine?</l>
      <l>Th' art then content to say, content is all,</l>
      <l>Th'ast got content for perils, paine and thrall;</l>
      <l>Tis lost to looke for more: for few men now</l>
      <l>Regard Wit, Learning, Valour; but allow</l>
      <l>The quintessence of praise to him that can</l>
      <l>Number his owne got gold, and riches, than</l>
      <l>Th' art Valiant, Learned, Wise; <hi>Pauls</hi> counsell will,</l>
      <l>Admire thy merits, magnifie thy skill.</l>
      <l>The last of thine to which I set my hand</l>
      <l>Was a <hi>Sea Grammar</hi>; this by Sea and Land,</l>
      <l>Serves us for imitation: I know none,</l>
      <l>That like thy selfe hast come, and runne, and gone,</l>
      <l>To such praise-worthy actions: bee't approu'd,</l>
      <l>Th'ast well deserv'd of best men to be lou'd:</l>
      <l>If <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Spaine,</hi> or any forren soile</l>
      <l>Could claime thee theirs, for these thy paines and toile,</l>
      <l>Th'adst got reward and honour: now adayes,</l>
      <l>What our owne natives doe, we seldome praise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Good men will yeeld thee praise; then sleight the rest;</l>
      <l>Tis best praise-worthy to have pleas'd the best.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Tuissimus ED. IORDEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>