<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Poem]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111947_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20782</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7160</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111947</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Poem]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The iaylors conuersion : Wherein is liuely represented, the true image of a soule rightlye touched, and conuerted by the spirit of God. The waightie circumstances of which supernaturall worke, for the sweete amplifications, and fit applications to the present time, are no set downe for the comfort of the strong, and confirmation of the weake. By Hugh Dowriche Batch. of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Dowriche, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 26, that is 28 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>Vaine floting blastes of worldly blisse, that neuer stay,</l>
      <l>Are smoke-like, mounting spied, but quickly quite decay.</l>
      <l>Like vewes of fawning shades, that plant alluring baytes,</l>
      <l>Erre fully come, their farwell shewes, their hid deceytes.</l>
      <l>No trust, in trustlesse trash, no faith in friendly shewes,</l>
      <l>Truth quailes in Hectik fits, whilst falshoode greenely growes.</l>
      <l>Yea, masking visars fraude, great grace, in gracelesse findes,</l>
      <l>No place, for naked truth, No time, for fraudlesse mindes,</l>
      <l>Esteemed vice soores high, on gales of witlesse windes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Knocke</hi> VVisedome <hi>while she faint, on rocke of flintie hart,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>No answere, but, I will not come, you may depart,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>If supreame voice, to</hi> Conscience <hi>call, to counte for sinne,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Greene Figleaues, grace defects, as sinne had neuer binne.</l>
      <l>Hygh Cedars stoutly vaunt, that fruitlesse haruest yeelde,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Volgo, <hi>bright, yet good, for neither fish nor feelde.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Let not false Susis springs, finde poores in Corkie hart,</l>
      <l>Yeelde not to loose the truth, though clad in carefull smart,</l>
      <l>Establish vertues throne, And say to sinne, depart.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>