<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Conclusion]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1538</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111493_Ba1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21313</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Conclusion]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dictionary of syr Thomas Eliot knyght</title>
                 <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1538</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>424 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Linguistics and philology</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="conclusion">
   <p>
      <hi>THIS AT THIS TYME</hi> shall be sufficient for the declaration of poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sis and mesures. And he that desireth a more ample and exquisite triall of them, let him diligently rede the bokes of Georgius Agricola, and Robertus Senalis, who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge last of all other in that kind of matter, haue found dyuers thinges, which were nat before of other remēbred, as it dayly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in all kyndes of writing. I knowe well that Budeus, Alceatus, and Portius are men of excellent lernynge, and their bokes to be made with an exact study &amp; diligence: But Agricola beinge a great phisition, and therfore more accustomed to rede the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Galenus, than the other, whyche in their profession be lawyers: semblablye the warkes of other, whiche wrate of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases of cattel, and remedies for them, more ouer attaynyng the bokes of Cleopatras, a noble and great lerned woman, whiche also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f measures, specially pertaininge to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>: no meruail though that he more perfitly hath determined that thing, which among the other was in contencion. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably Senalis an honorable bysshop, folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing Agricola, and approuyng his diligēce by makynge true conference betwene hym and the other, and more ouer beinge welle lerned in the hebrue tunge, and consequētly in holy scripture, trieng out studiousely the poyses and mesures to the hebrues pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: hath happily brought vnto lyght that whiche the other hath remembred, or elles nat vnderstandyng substancially the hebrue tounge, they purposely omitted. For these causes I haue preferred the computation of these two before any other, exhortynge nat withstanding al them that do vnderstād latine, that they do not therfore neglect the others bookes, but to imbrace and read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them studiously, as in whom they shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> meruailous knowledge, which els {per}chaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> they shal lacke. And as concerning my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, whiche I haue done with moche study and incredible labour for the profit of other, if I haue therin any thyng fayled, as I trust that I haue not (although the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in breking of numbers callid fractions, is a thinge subtyll and meruailous harde to obserue alway truly) I hartily pray al gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll reders, fyndyng it by an exquisite tryall to correct it without indignation: and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse all the resydewe of the dictionarye preceding, and frendely communicate with me their labours, for the which I wyll giue vnto them moste harty thankes, not leauing vnremembred, god gyuing to me lyfe, their honest labours, being benesyciall vnto this theyr countrey.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>