<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Anthony de Adamo to the Christian rea∣ders desyreth health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111869_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17200</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111869</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Anthony de Adamo to the Christian rea∣ders desyreth health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An anatomi, that is to say a parting in peeces of the mass : Which discouereth the horrible errors, and the infinit abuses vnknowen to the people, aswel of the mass as of the mass book, very profitable, yea most necessary for al Christian people. VVith a sermon of the sacrament of thankesgyuyng in the end, whiche declareth whether Christ be bodyly in the sacrament or not. By Chrystes humble seruant Anthoni de Adamo</title>
                 <author>Mainardi, Agostino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kopfel, Wolfgang, Heirs of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Strasbourg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>140, 151-159, 170-264, that is 246, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="3"/>
   <head>Anthony de Adamo to the Christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders desyreth health.</head>
   <p>Do exhort yow (ò Christians) to read and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sider well this short booke, which treateth of the Masse and of the Masse booke, for without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t readinge and well considering it, you shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ow what the one and the other is, and it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ient, seing this Masse is so greatly haunted, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in such honour and pryce almost of all men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, estemed as the chefe and principall way to ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ur god in the Christian religion. (It is fit I say) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>at it be well knowen what it is, wheather it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ofitable or hurtfull, good or euell, pleasinge or if pleasing to god. Manye, yea the more parte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>en without anye manner of knowledge in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rs of Christian religion, not considering the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rtaunce therof, followe the multitude, Custome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d the common sort of men, thinkinge that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>end not but that they do well, and an acceptab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e worke to god, doinge as other men doo, but they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> disceaued, for in the honouringe of god and
<pb facs="4"/>
doinge to him a thākefull dede,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.</note> It is necessary tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> we folow his worde as a light that may guide vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it were trauelars that iorney by night, we ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> not to be ruled nor gouerned, in a matter {per}tainin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge to oure saluation, either by oure oune fantasi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and seming, or els by any other mens. For yf we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> so we shall leaue the light and walke in darknes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> in the end fall into a headolngnes and euerla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sting downfall. Who is that good seruant that ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uith his lord or master as liketh himself? surely no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne: but the good serueth as his lord willeth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeth, otherwise he shuld not be good but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cked and stubborn. God wold aboue althings hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> obedience according to this saing,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 15. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 4. <hi>Esa.</hi> 29.</note>
      <hi>Melior es obediētia quā uictima</hi> that is to say obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence is better thē sacrifice. And Eccles. saith, Obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence is better then fooles sacrifices, who know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> the euel they doo. God threateneth that heauie se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence written in Esaie, and alleadged by Christ i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> S. Mathew,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.</note> This people (saith he) doth honour m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> with there lippes, but there harts are far from m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> they honour me vainely teaching the doctrine an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> commaundements of men. Lo I will work a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> wonder toward this peple for the wisedom of the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re wyse men shall perish, and the vnderstanding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> of the wittye shalbe darkened, the which sentenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="3" facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>y the iust iudgement of god, from a certeine tyme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e her to is come vpon vs: Because that (leauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e word of god) we haue imbraced the teachings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nd fantasies of men, estiminge them more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he holy scripture, and therfore oure accompted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>yse and witty mē, haue greatly erred, and as blin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e men haue led the rest of vs (being also blinde in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>hat tyme) into the pit of innumerable and most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eadly errours. And I protest here before god and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>sus Christ before whose throne we must all appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and render accompt of oure doings at the last <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ay that no priuat affection hath moued me to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e this enterprise in hand, but onely an ernestnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>owards gods glory and Iesus Christs, and for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>roffit of the Christian people, and I desyre euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e that shall fynde any fault in this oure writing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>at he will openly in writinge confute it and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>are it. But let him doo this by the word of god, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>en as hetherto I haue endeuored my self (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ng to my vnderstanding and habilitie) to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ainly appere by the same worde of god the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rrours and the infinit abuses that be in this Masse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nd Masse booke: I mistrust not, but there will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>me and vndoubtedly many, who lyue not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ease by this there accustomed marchandyse of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e Masse but also do fleshly triumphe on poore
<pb facs="5"/>
mens costs that will condempne this oure labour and will crye with a loud voyce, doune with him, doune with him, but without any auaylable reason and with out gods worde, alleadging onely the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and authoritie of mē, saing, how is it possible that the churche with so great a nombre of learned mē, should haue erred so long tyme, as though any certeine multitude which is commonly holden and taken for the trew churche were Christs church in deed, whose crye I litle care for, if they bring no other matter then the customes and words of men▪ But yf they can with the holy scripture and with liuely reasons grounded on the same confute this and defend there Masse and there Masse booke (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> which I think yea I beleue verili thei shal not) I sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> rest most bound vnto them and yeld thē my harty thanks. And because that this oure iudgement to some of small vnderstanding, may seme straunge and a new matter, ye they shall iudge it rather a wicked rashenes, I therfore do warne ād geue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Christian man to vnderstand, that none ought to be moued, either by the lōg custome or authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of any maner of man, whether he be holy or ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for in gods matters, we ought to take hede not to Customs, not to the continuance of tyme, not to the multitude, nor the authority of oure elders, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="4" facs="5"/>
to the onely worde of god,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezech.</hi> 20.</note> as Ezechiell the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet saith, Walk not in the commaundements of youre fathers nor kepe not there iudgemēts, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>here Idoles defyle not your selfs, I am the lord your god, walke in my commaundemēts and kepe any iudgements and do them,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Leuit.</hi> 13.</note> And in Leuiticus it is written. Kepe my commaundements, be not desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to do those things that they haue done which haue bene before you, nor defyle not your selfe in them: I am the lord your god.<note place="margin">Ciprian in his second booke of his epistels the <hi>3.</hi> chaptre.</note> And S. Cyprian to Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cilius in his second book of Epistels, the third cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter saith, that Christ ought onely to be herde, the father also from heauen hath testified the same, (saing) this is my welbelowed sonne, in whome I am wel pleased, here him. Wherby yf onely Christ be to be herde, we ought not to regarde, what any man before hath thought mete for vs to doo, but what first Christ hath done who is before all. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we ought not to folow men but the trueth of god. And he saith in diuers other places that we ought to follow the worde of god and not the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious of mē, and likewyse to Pompey against Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens Epistle he saith: That the Custome which was entred among many ought not to make that the trueth, should not preuayle and ouercome, for Custome without trueth is an oldnes of errours.
<pb facs="6"/>
Wherfore, leauinge the errour, let vs follow the trueth. I will let passe a nombre of the auncient fathers, as Austē, Hierom, Ambrose, ād other, who wold we should stick to the onely worde of god ād not to custome nor to ani other authoritie of mā. It hath bene alwaies that the more parte of men haue bene in errour, yea, and euē of thē that were called the people of god. Let the prophets be red and it shall apere that I say the trueth: for, whye were the prophets persecuted, euel handeled and in the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> put to death, yf not, for because they reproued the errours and abuses of there tyme, which were amōg the people? whye hath Christe and his Apost<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les suffered persecution, and in the end death, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> not, for that they reproued the false faith, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trew worshippings, and the counterfet religion of there tyme? And for what cause thē shall we now maruell, that the Christian people should be myred and drowned in so many abuses corruptions, Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latries and other infinit errours?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>et</hi> 3.</note> hath not Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> fore tolde vs, in his secōd epistle, that there should come false teachers that wold bringe in deadly sects, ād that in the latter dayes there sholud come begylers and deceauers?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.</note> And Paule in his second to the Thessalonians, doth, not he declare that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re should come a forsaking (as I vnderstand it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="5" facs="6"/>
the faith) that is to say that men should goo from the faith, and that god wold send forth a mightines of gyle and deceyte, so that men should beleue lyes, and that because they haue not loued the trueth? And to Timothi in his first Epistle doth not he say that in the latter tymes som should departe from the faith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> geuing heed to the spirits of errour and doctrines of deuels?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 3.</note> And in the second also he saith that in the latter dayes should be perilous ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and men full of vyces: and among other things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he saith that they should haue shewes of religion but in dede they should denye the might therof. What hath bene preached to the people of a long tyme hetherto, but onely the teachings of men? so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me preached the Poets, some Aristotle, Auerroes, Plato, and other heathen philosophers, some prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the lawes some vnproffitable questions of Scotus, Alexander of Hales, of Bonauentura of Thomas of Aquine, the whiche as it is manifest in there doctrine and opinions: the one of then gayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd the other in open pulpit, the black against the graie the grey against the black, the Augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fryer against them both, and so we may say of the rest, some held one opinion some an other: and and what assurednes of trew doctrine could the poore people haue in so great a diuersitie and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fusion?
<pb facs="7"/>
who was he that preached the holy scriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and the gospell purely? And shall we then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruel, that errours are entred in among the Christiā people? shall we then say, how can it be possible that god wold haue left his churche so long tyme in erroure? Naye yf we had but a spark of witt and reason, we should say quyte contrary, that is, how is it possible to be otherwyse, but that the more par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of mē haue bene ād yet are in most grosse blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes couered with the dark mist of innumerable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours? and it could not be otherwyse.</p>
   <p>There is amōg the rest one very great disorder, a cause of innumerable euels, that none of them to whome it belonged to teache and preach to the people hath done his office. It is well knowen that the office of preaching the worde of god belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the busshoppes, and who was he, yea we may now say, who is that bisshop that doth preach and feed the flock of Christ with the word of god? yea who is he, that disdaineth not to preache and doo that office which the Prophets the Apostles, ye and the sonne of god himself Christ Iesu god and man, hath done, and the godliest dewtie of all, that is to say the greatest and highest, which is to teach the word of god to the people, these oure great lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des doo not vouchafe it, but haue left it and yet do
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
leaue it for other to do. It suffiseth them to haue the title, the rents and the honoure of a busshop, as in effect they wold declare that they be no busshop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes (as in dede they be not) except onely in name, and in dede yf they were trew busshoppes, they wold not be ashamed to doo theire office, as Austi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, Ambrose, Ciprian, Chrisostom, Basile, Gregory, and other holy fathers were not ashamed, the which taught and preached the word of god. This is the trew fedinge which Christ commaunded Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in S. Ihon the last chapter,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.21. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</note> and the same Peter also in his first Epistle the <hi>5.</hi> chapter saith, feede so muche as in you is (that is to say) so much as you can and according to youre habilitie, the flock of Christ, or els as the other text saith, feed the flock of Christ which is in you, that is to say, which is com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted ād geuē to you in charge. Of this disorder it commeth to passe that the cleane, pure and trew doctrine of the gospel and of the word of god doth want among the people, and as thorow a wide and large gate, be entred abuses, superstitions and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours among the Christiā flock. There is none thē that hath witt or reason that will say any more, how is it possible that oure elders (or let it be the church) and so many teachers, haue erred, God hath suffered by his iust iudgement this horrible
<pb facs="8"/>
decay in his chyrche, and it is a most singular gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of god, that yet in a few (albeit euell handeled of the world) who be in dede the true church the faith doth remaine, Yea, I say that if the world in temporall gouernements had not had better rule and order then the estate called Ecclesiasticall, it should haue run̄ into an vtter confusion and deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye. Sew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rly it is trew that there be many disorders in worldly princes doings, but yet they doo in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me parte there dewtye: they minister iustice after a certein maner, they chastice the fauters, they pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nisch theft, murder, blaspemie and other faults, they cause by there officer euery mans awne to be restored hym, they geue themselues to doo right as there calling is. But in the Ecclesiasticall state, who hath done, or yet doth his office? begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the highest degre, which is a busshopship, and see how that is handeled, and therebie lett the rest be iudged. The bissoppes attend to euery other thing, except preaching, yea they hinder by all meanes they can whom so euer wold doo this offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce trewly (that is) wold declare the gospell and the word of god purely, And they will not suffer it to be done but raginglye persecute the teachers of the trueth, they condemne them, they imprison them, they torment them, and in the ende they kill
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>
thē. And what is this, but, to shew plainely to the whole worlde, that they be raueninge wolues and not shepherdes of Christs flock? yea that they be ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry antichristes? And the worshipfull inquisitours, what els be they but antichristes Catchpoules cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weller thē Neroes, so that it were better to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of Turks and Mores without compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rison then into thers. Besyde that they are vtterly ignorant of the holy scripture, they are skilled in none other learning but in the skotish and sophisti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call mouldines. And these (as you see) are appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to order the matters of oure faith, and in there handes, are the goods, the honoure and the lyues of poore soules, whom miserably they put to death, by pretence of the faith, although they be enemies of it and of all godlines. I am desyrous to make this discours to open there eies, Which fault not by ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ice, but by ignorāce, and to make them vnderstand that they should not maruell, that I reproue the Masse and the Masse booke, saing that they be full of falshod abuses ād many other errours, as it may plainly be sene in this present booke. Wherfore I de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>yre (for the dere loue of Iesus Christ) all the louers of the trueth, and those that tēder godlines, to read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nd well consider this my labour, for without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>oubt they shall fynde trew that I say. Praye to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>od for me, God be with yow.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>