<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶A Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111418_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13665</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23950</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111418</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶A Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The new found vvorlde, or Antarctike : wherin is contained wo [n] derful and strange things, as well of humaine creatures, as beastes, fishes, foules, and serpents, trées, plants, mines of golde and siluer: garnished with many learned aucthorities, trauailed and written in the French tong, by that excellent learned man, master Andrevve Theuet. And now newly translated into Englishe, wherein is reformed the errours of the auncient cosmographers</title>
                 <author>Thevet, André</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hacket, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 138, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶A Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering vvith my selfe hovv much the</hi> long experiēce of things, &amp; faithfull obseruation of many countries and nations, also their orders and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lyfe, bringeth or causeth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to man, although there were no exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise more cōmendable by the which a man may sufficiently decke his spirite with all kinde of Heroicall vertue and science: biside my first &amp; formal Nauigation into the countrey of <hi>Leuant,</hi> in <hi>Grecia,</hi> in <hi>Turkie, Egypte,</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> the which in times paste I haue put to light, I haue againe vnder the protection and sauegard of the great gouernor of the vniuersal worlde, seing it hath pleased him to shew me so much fauor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left to the discretion and mercy of one of the most vnconstant Elements, &amp; least assured that is among the rest, with small vesselles of wood so fraile that many times there was more hope of death than of life, for to sayle toward the <hi>Pole Antartike,</hi> the which was neuer discouered nor found out by the elders in times past, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth by the writings of <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> and others, also ours of <hi>Septentrion,</hi> to the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> and therefore it was thought to be vnhabited. And we sayled so long that at the laste we came to <hi>India America,</hi> aboute the <hi>Capricorne,</hi> a mayn land of good temperatnesse and inhabited, as we will particularly &amp; more at large hereafter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, the which I haue taken in hande at the
<pb facs="7"/>
instant request of many great personages, of whō the gestes more than Heroical &amp; high enterprises celebrated by the Histories, cause them to lyue for euer in perpetual honor and immortall glory. What hath prouoked the great Poet <hi>Homer</hi> so vertuously to celebrate in his writings <hi>Vlysses,</hi> but onely his long peregrination and far trauell that he made in diuerse places, with the experiēce of many things aswel by sea as by land after the spoyle of <hi>Troye?</hi> What moued <hi>Virgill</hi> to write so worthily of the <hi>Troyan Aeneas</hi> although that he according to the writing of some Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers had most trayterously betrayed his natiue countrey in to the hands of his enimies, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that he had vertuously resisted the furie of the raging waues, and other inconueniences of the sea, he had sene &amp; endured many sharpe shou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and finally he came into <hi>Italie?</hi> Euen so as the soueraigne creator hath made man of twoo sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāces the one differing or exceding the other, the one elementary &amp; corruptible, the other celestiall; diuine and immortall. Also he hath put al things in his subiectiō, that is contained vnder the scope or circuite of the Firmament, to the ende that he might know asmuch as to him was necessary for to attaine to the soueraigne gift, leauing him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse some difficultie &amp; varietie of exercise. Man then although that he be a creature marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously accomplished, yet he is neuerthelesse an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of vertuous actes, of the which God is the original, so that he may electe such an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt as pleaseth him for to execute his plesure, be
<pb facs="8"/>
it by sea or by land. But it may so chaunce as it is cōmonly sene come to passe, that some vnder this pretexitie make it a custome to abuse the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master by an auarice and an vnsatiable appetite of some particular and temporall appetite, ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parding themselues vndiscretely &amp; as wickedly, (as <hi>Horace</hi> in his epistles doeth manyfestly shew) that he is worthy of prayse, that for the beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eluminating of his spirite, &amp; in the fauor of the common wealth doth willingly offer and put forth him selfe. This rule or meane <hi>Socrates</hi> the wise Philosopher knew how to practise, and after him <hi>Plato</hi> his disciple, (bothe the which) not onely contented to haue traueled and made voyages into strange countreys for to attaine to the full perfection &amp; knowledge of Philosophie, but also to declare it openly without hope of any reward or recompense. Did not <hi>Cicero</hi> send his sonne <hi>Marke</hi> to <hi>Athens?</hi> partely for to heare <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tippus,</hi> and of him to lerne Philosophie, and partly also for to lerne the maners and lyuing of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisens of <hi>Athens. Lysander</hi> being elected for his magnanimitie &amp; worthinesse gouernor ouer the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> hath so worthily atcheued so many faire enterprises against <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> a man prewe and valiant, and <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Lieutenant on the sea, that what losse or detrimēt so euer did chāce, his heart and manly courage did neuer faile him, but pursued his enimie by sea &amp; by lande, so that in the ende he brought <hi>Athens</hi> to his obedience. <hi>Themistocles,</hi> not lesse experte in the feate of warre thā in Philosophie, for to shew what a feruēt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
<pb facs="8"/>
he had to ieoparde his lyfe for the libertie of his countrey, persuaded the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that the siluer that was gathered in the mynes the which they were wonte to distribute to the people, was turned and bestowed to furnishe and make ships and galleys against <hi>Xerxes,</hi> who for that he had partly distressed him, and almost put to flight, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to appointment after this happie victorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the order of an enimie, made him present with three of the beste Cities of his Empire. What hath caused <hi>Seleucus Nicanor,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Augustus Cesar,</hi> and many Princes and noble men to beare in their pendens and standarts the Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin and the anker, but onely to giue instruction to al their posteritie, that Nauigation is the first and of al others the most vertuous. Here therfore without any long discourse is an example of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigatiō: as al things the more excellent they are, the more difficile or harde is the way to attaine to them, as after the experience <hi>Aristotle</hi> witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, speaking of vertue. And that the nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is alwaies folowed with peril, as a body is with his shadowe, the which in times past was shewed by <hi>Anacharsis</hi> the Philosopher, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had demaūded of what quantitie or thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse were the plācks or side of a ship: it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, not aboue four fingers: so much (said he) is the lyfe of him from death that sayleth with ships on the water. Now gentle Reader in that I haue alleged so many excellent personages, it is not to compare, much lesse to thinke my selfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to them, but I am persuaded that the great
<pb facs="9"/>
power of <hi>Alexander</hi> hath not letted his successors to attempte yea the very extremitie of fortune. Also the deepe knowledge of <hi>Plato</hi> did nothing at all feare or abashe <hi>Aristotle,</hi> but that at his owne pleasure he hath treated of Philosophy. For this intent therefore not to be found ydle and slacke among others, no more than <hi>Diogenes</hi> was amōg the <hi>Athenians,</hi> I haue thought good to set out in writing many notable things that I haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obserued in my Nauigation betwene the South and the Weast, that is to wit, the situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and disposition of places, in what clymat, zone or paralegie it be, aswel of the sea costes, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes, and mayne land, the temperatnesse of the ayre, the forme and maner of liuing of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, the forme and propertie of beasts of the earth and of the sea, also of trees and roots with their frutes, mines and precious stones, shewing it liuely and truely as neare as is possible. As touching the reste I wold thinke my selfe happie if that it would please you to accepte and receiue this my little labor with as willing a heart as I doe present it: as for the rest I am assured that it wil be agreable if the Reader thinke well and way in his minde the long and dangerous pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grination that I haue taken in hand, for to see with the eye &amp; to bring to light those things most memoriall that I cold note and gather together, as hereafter shalbe sene.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>