<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧The Argument of the whole Historye.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111725_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15045</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111725</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧The Argument of the whole Historye.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The right excellent and famous historye, of Promos and Cassandra : deuided into two commicall discourses. In the fyrste parte is showne, the vnsufferable abuse, of a lewde magistrate: the vertuous behauiours of a chaste ladye: the vncontrowled leawdenes of a fauoured curtisan. And the vndeserued estimation of a pernicious parasyte. In the second parte is discoursed, the perfect magnanimitye of a noble kinge, in checking vice and fauouringe vertue: wherein is showne, the ruyne and ouerthrowe, of dishonest practises: with the aduauncement of vpright dealing. The worke of George Whetstones Gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧The Argument of the whole <hi>Historye.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Cyttie of <hi>Iulia</hi> (sometimes vnder the dominion of <hi>Coruinus</hi> Kinge of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and <hi>Boemia</hi>) there was a law, that what man so euer commited Adultery, should lose his head, &amp; the woman offender, should weare some disguised apparrel, during her life, to make her infamouslye noted. This seuere lawe, by the fauour of some mercifull magistrate became little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, vntill the time of Lord <hi>Promos</hi> auctority: who conuicting, a yong Gentleman named <hi>Andrugio</hi> of incontinency, condemned both him, and his minion to the execution of this statute. <hi>Andrugio</hi> had a very vertuous, and beawtiful Gentlewoman to his Sister, named <hi>Cassandra: Cassandra</hi> to enlarge her brothers life, submitted an humble petition to the Lord <hi>Promos: Promos</hi> regarding her good behauiours, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasyng her great beawtie, was much delighted with the sweete order of her talke: and doyng good, that euill might come thereof: for a time, he repryu'd her brother: but wicked man, coming his liking vnto vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull lust, he set downe the spoile of her honour, raunsome for her Brothers life: Chaste <hi>Cassandra,</hi> abhorring both him and his sute, by no perswasion would yeald to this raunsome. But in fine, wonne with the importunitye of hir brother (pleading for life:) vpon these condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, she agreede to <hi>Promos.</hi> First that he should pardon her brother, and after marry her. <hi>Promos</hi> as feareles in promisse, as carelesse in performance, with sollemne vowe, sygned her conditions: but worse then any Infydel, his will satisfyed, he performed neither the one nor the other: for to keepe his aucthoritye, vnspotted with fauour, and to preuent <hi>Cassandraes</hi> clamors, he commaunded the Gayler se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly , to present <hi>Cassandra</hi> with her brothers head. The Gayler, with the outcryes of <hi>Andrugio,</hi> (abhorryng <hi>Promos</hi> lewdenes, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, prouided thus for his safety. He presented <hi>Cassandra</hi> with a Felons head newlie executed, who (being mangled, knew it not from her brothers, by the Gayler, who was set at libertie) was so agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="5"/>at this trecherye, that at the pointe to kyl her selfe, she spared that stroke, to be auenged of <hi>Promos.</hi> And deuisyng a way, she concluded, to make her fortunes knowne vnto the kinge. She (executinge this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution) was so highly fauoured of the King, that forth with he hasted to do Iustice on <hi>Promos:</hi> whose iudgement was, to marrye <hi>Cassandra,</hi> to repaire her crased Honour: which donne, for his hainous offence he should lose his head. This mary age solempnised, <hi>Cassandra</hi> tyed in the greatest bondes of affection to her husband, became an earnest suter for his life: the Kinge (tendringe the generall benefit of the cōmon weale, before her special ease, although he fauoured her much) would not graunt her sute. <hi>Andrugio</hi> (disguised amonge the company) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
         <desc>…</desc>
      </gap>ing the griefe of his sister, bewrayde his safetye, and craued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. The Kinge, to renowne the vertues of <hi>Cassandra,</hi> pardoned both him, and <hi>Promos.</hi> The circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this rare Historye, in action lyuelye foloweth. (∴)</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>