<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader whosoeuer.</title>
           <author>W., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111808_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15503</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25768</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader whosoeuer.</title>
                 <author>W., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The commendation of cockes, and cock-fighting : VVherein is shewed, that cocke-fighting was before the comming of Christ</title>
                 <author>Wilson, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Ockould, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tomes, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader whosoeuer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, in regard that I haue alwayes been greatly affectioned to the most pleasant sport of Cock-figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I haue thought good to shewe vnto thee (in this following treatise) the excellent nature, rare qualities, stout courage, vndaunted resolution, and the most admirable vertues, that are in fighting Cockes, and withall to discribe, and shew forth the manner, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, and good order that is obserued and vsed in the pleasing pastime of Cock-fighting, with a briefe repetition of the high commendations that learned writers, and mighty princes, as <hi>Themistocles, Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch, Plinie, Caesar, Marke Anthony,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great personages haue giuen vnto them, not onely to satisfie and please mine owne humor ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but to fulfill the earnest request and expectation of diuers men of great account, who haue longe time labored with me, &amp; often incited me to doe it. Wherfore considering with my selfe, that although many men in this Realme, hold it in most high esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, yet there are not, nor haue been any, that euer gaue it any publike commendation. I thought good to shew my simple skill in the discribing of
<pb facs="4"/> it; which description although it be farre inferiour to the worthinesse of my subiect: yet I intreat thee to accept it kindely, or else to amend it quickely: but if thou wilt neither accept of it, nor amend it, but scorne my worke, and contemne mee for my good will, then the care is taken: and I am constant in my resolution. Thus kindly commending both my selfe and my Booke, to the curtesie of all cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Readers, I bid thee farewell. From <hi>Wretton</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Noffolke.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in what he may, G. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>