<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the right Honorable and most graue personadges the temporall maiestrates of England in their waightie counsels, the assistance of Gods holie spirit.</title>
           <author>Whetstone, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111678_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15033</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111678</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the right Honorable and most graue personadges the temporall maiestrates of England in their waightie counsels, the assistance of Gods holie spirit.</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English myrror : A regard wherein al estates may behold the conquests of enuy: containing ruine of common weales, murther of princes, cause of heresies, and in all ages, spoile of deuine and humane blessings, vnto which is adioyned, enuy conquered by vertues. Publishing the peaceable victories obtained by the Queenes most excellent Maiesty, against this mortall enimie of publike peace and prosperitie, and lastly a fortris against enuy, builded vpon the counsels of sacred Scripture, lawes of sage philosophers, and pollicies of well gouerned common weales: wherein euery estate may see the dignities, the true office and cause of disgrace of his vocation. A worke safely, and necessarie to be read of euerie good subiect. By George Whetstones Gent. Malgre. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Seton, Gregory.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 180, 10, 201-249, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="86"/>
   <pb facs="86"/>
   <head>❧To the right Honorable and most graue personadges the temporall maiestrates <hi>of England in their waightie counsels, the assistance</hi> of Gods holie spirit.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost honorable and graue Maiestrates, it may seeme vnto your wisedomes that I flattered my wit, with a foolish singularitie, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed your fauors with an arrogant presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if of my owne braine I should vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take (and lay before your iudgements) thys waightie building, which containeth the true offices, the worthines, and (by abuse) the disgraces of euery mans voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which labor I entitle <hi>A fortresse against Enuy.</hi> But (most reuerend) as I haue composed my first booke, called <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests of Enuy,</hi> of the examples and ouerthrowes of the most ancient, renowmed and florishing common weales, for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy only maketh warre with things of the greatest glory, and haue continued my second booke, entituled, <hi>Enuy conquered by vertue,</hi> with the admiration of her Maiesties peaceable victories, obtained by diuine prouidence, and her highnesse pretious vertues, the one incomprehensible, and the other without sample: So right honorable, this third booke (which I reuerently submit vnto your graue censors) I (semblably) build vpon sacred, morall, and politike counsels: the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions are set downe by holy Prophets, Apostles, learned Philosophers, and graue common wealthesmen. The collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and labor to place them, as they may serue for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall instruction, is only due vnto me: and (with your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fauors) I thinke the law of the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> (which I take for my platforme) is a most sure defence against Enuy: for by this lawe of King <hi>Amazis,</hi> (which was, that euerie man shoulde put his name in a common booke, and at the yeeres ende shoulde acquainte the Gouernour neere his abiding, with the trade and order of his liuing.) Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and excesse (the great nourishers of Enuy) were
<pb facs="87"/>
either banished or punished, euery man entertained a setled vocation, and no man enuied the pomp of another mans calling, which he knew not how to gouerne: and certainly, if men would indifferētly consider of all vocatiōs, they should find there is no calling so base, but that the vse therof is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, &amp; of honest credit in a common wealth: and withall no dignity so hye, but vnto the same is annexed a number of displeasures, and therevpon it is rightly said, <hi>That the chiefest place in the administration of iustice, is to the executioner a bondage:</hi> your wisdoms know the same better by experiēce, then I by obseruance, so that whatsoeuer the booke cōtaineth of graue gouerment, I acknowledge might better haue been deriued from your liuely vertues, then frō other mens writtē coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels: but for that men can hardly praise the liuing without flattery, and the dead without an honest zeale, I haue made choise to labor more for my credit then aduantage: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I am in a maner vnknowne to most of you graue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestrates that liue (of which in this respect I am glad, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnworthy of your knowledge, for any speciall quality, I am at no time brought <hi>Coram vobis</hi> for any criminall tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe) yet those worthy personages which in my time are deceased, haue had the second life of their vertues bruted by my Muse: but as my trauels heerein cōmended the dead, and instructed the liuing: with the like hope, I haue builded this fortresse against Enuy, of the counsels of the dead, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to instruct the liuing in their proper vertues. Vertue as <hi>Diogenes</hi> saith, only withstandeth Enuy, yea, vertue conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Enuy, and vertue set apart, no pollicy preuaileth against the stratagemes of Enuy. To withstand this common foe of prosperitie, I labour (by the grauest mens directions) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint euery man with the vertues of his vocation: but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally I do beseech God to blesse them with his feare, the beginning of wisedome, and confusion of Enuy and all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse, vnto whose gratious protection I humbly commit your right honorable Lordships, and all other godly Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates whatsoeuer: at whose commandement I faithfully remaine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>George Whetstons.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>