<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ THE LIFE OF VIRGIL, written by Tiberius Claudius Donatus, as Servius in his commentarie upon Virgil relates it.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111557_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14487</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24809</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111557</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ THE LIFE OF VIRGIL, written by Tiberius Claudius Donatus, as Servius in his commentarie upon Virgil relates it.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The XII Aeneids of Virgil, the most renowned laureat-prince of Latine-poets; translated into English deca-syllables, by Iohn Vicars. 1632</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 418, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ THE LIFE OF VIRGIL, written by <hi>Tiberius Claudius Donatus,</hi> as <hi>Servius</hi> in his commentarie upon <hi>Virgil</hi> relates it.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ublius Virgilius Maro</hi> was (as antiquity testifies) born of mean parentage, especially on the fathers side, whose name was <hi>Maro,</hi> who, as some say, was by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession a potter. He was (as many suppose) at first, servant to a certain wandring wizard or southsayer; and by his sedulous industrie in ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ick affaires, husbandrie, keeping of catt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll, working in woods, and tending of bees, raised up his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rs small means to a good estate, and afterwards marrying his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, became his masters sonne in law. He was born the <hi>15.</hi> day of October in a countrey village called <hi>Andes,</hi> neare <hi>Mantua,</hi> in the yeare of the consulship of <hi>Cneins Pompey</hi> the great, and <hi>Marcus Licinius Crastus,</hi> and was a citizen of <hi>Mantua,</hi> as saith <hi>Servius M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urus Honoratus,</hi> a learned Grammarian. His m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a,</hi> being great with childe of him, dreamed that she was delivered of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> branch, which being set in the ground, grew up immediately into a great spreading tree, fairely fraught with variety of fruit and fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>grant flowers: And the next day she and her husband walking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the next neighbouring countrey, she stepping aside, was delivered of him in a ditch. It is said, that being born, he never cried; but was of such a sweet and amiable countenance, that he gave great hope of a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st flourishing future condition. His infancie, till the age of about seven yeares, was spent in <hi>Cremona.</hi> From <hi>Crem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>na</hi> he went into <hi>Millain,</hi> and from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nce shortly after passed over into <hi>Naples,</hi> where with great indu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rie and utilitie studying the Greek and Latine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ongues, he addicted himself principally and most seriously to the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Physick, and of the Mathematicks, and in both exceeded all others of his time, insomuch that he planted himself in <hi>Rome;</hi> where falling into f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>miliaritie and acquaintance with the master of the horse to <hi>Augustus</hi> the emperour, he cured many of his horses disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, who rewarded him with a dayly allowance of bread, as to the rest of the officers of his stable.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Afterward the <hi>Cretonians</hi> presented to the emperour a gallant colt, which in the opinion of all the beholders was like to prove a nagge of rare spirit and pace: but when <hi>Virgil</hi> saw him, he told the master of the horse that it was bred of a very faultie mare, and would prove neither quick spirited nor nimble paced: which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fell out so indeed. Which the master of the horse relating to <hi>Augustus,</hi> he commanded that <hi>Virgils</hi> allowance of bread should be dayly doubled. Again, certain hounds being sent as a present out of <hi>Spain</hi> to the emperour, <hi>Virgil</hi> told both of what kinde they came, and how they would prove dogs of admirable use and swiftnes: which also being made known to <hi>Augustus Cesar,</hi> he again gave order that his allowance of bread should be re-doubled. Shortly after, <hi>Augustus</hi> growing doubtfull of himself whether <hi>Octavi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> were his father, and perswaded that <hi>Virgil,</hi> who so well knew the nature and kinde of hounds and horses, could also resolve this doubt, separating all other companie, and retiring into a private room, he taks <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil</hi> with him, and askes him alone, whether he knew who he was, and what power h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> had to make men honourable and happie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he answered, I know that thou art <hi>Augustus Cesar,</hi> and that thou hast power almost equall to the immortall Gods, and that thou can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t happifie whomsoever thou pleasest. Surely, said <hi>Cesar,</hi> I have now a minde and purpose to make thee most happie and honourable, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u canst give a full answer to my request unto thee. Sir, sayes <hi>Virgil,</hi> I wish it were in my power to tell you the certainty of whatsoever your majesty could demaund of me. Some men (sayes <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi>) think that <hi>Octavius</hi> was my father, others think some body else: Whereunto <hi>Virgill</hi> with a smile, thus replied, Sacred sir, if I may freely and with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut offence answer your majesties demaund, I am perswaded I shall easily resolve this doubt. <hi>Cesar</hi> hereupon assured him with an oath, that whatsoever he spake he would not take it amisse, and that withall, he would not leave him unrewarded. Now then <hi>Virgil</hi> fixing his eyes seriously on the emperours face, said; It is easie in other creatures (by rules of philosophie and the mathematicks) to discern the qualities and conditions of their prog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itours and parents, but in man it is not so easie a matter; yet as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your sacred majestie, I am able to make some probable conjecture what profession your father was of. Hereat <hi>Cesar</hi> began to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ten the more attentively what he would say. Then sayes <hi>Virgil;</hi> So farre forth as I can collect and understand, thou wast a bakers sonne. The empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hereat amazed, presently began to wonder within himself how
<pb facs="5"/>
that could be. But <hi>Virgil</hi> instantly interrupting his thoughts, said; Hearken sir, I beseech you, on what ground I build this my opinion: Your majestie knows, that when I formerly foretold diverse things which could not be seen into nor foreshown, but by men of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and understanding, that your majestie the great monarch of the world again and again rewarded me with a lot and allowance of bread, which surely is the propertie eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r of a baker or a bakers sonne. This facetious conceit pleased the emperour wondrous well: who thereupon said unto him, Thou shalt now be no more rewarded by a baker, but by a munifice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t and magnificent king: and ever after the emperour highly esteemed him and commended him to <hi>Pollio.</hi> He was big of body, and tall of stature, of a shallow complexion, hard favoured and of a sickly constitution, a moderate drinker, and of a spare diet. It is reported that he was given to the filthie and lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>full love of boyes, but the honestest sort of men of his dayes were perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he loved them no otherwise then as <hi>Socrates</hi> loved <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> his schollars: and that above all other he loved <hi>Cebetes</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> best, whom in the second Eclog of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Bucoiicks he termed <hi>Alexis,</hi> whom <hi>Asinius Pollio</hi> gave unto him. And it is reported also that he kept <hi>Plotia Hieria,</hi> but <hi>Asconius Pedianus</hi> affirms the contrarie from <hi>Virgils</hi> own s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rious d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>niall thereof. In all other demeanours of his life he was both in speech and conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion so honest and upright, that throughout all <hi>Naples</hi> he was called Virginity; and if at any time (as that was but seldome) he walked the streets of <hi>Rome,</hi> and observed himself to be noted and followed by any in the streets, he would retire himself immediately into the next house he came unto. He in his moderation of riches refused the goods and estate of a banished man, which <hi>Augustus Cesar</hi> profered to him; having a good competent estate of his own, and a house in <hi>Rome</hi> in the <hi>Exsquiliae</hi> neare <hi>Mecoenas</hi> his gardens. He used much, and most frequently, to retire himself into <hi>Campania</hi> and <hi>Sicil.</hi> In any request to <hi>Cesar</hi> he never had deniall. He was annually helpfull to his parents in great measure, who died when he was himself grown to a ripe age; his father being blinde ere he died. His two brethren <hi>Silo</hi> and <hi>Flaccus</hi> being dead, he bewailed under the name of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phnis. Melissus</hi> reports, that he was slow of tongue and sparing of speech, as if he hadbeen a very ignorant and illiterate man. When he fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t addicted himself to poetry, he made this distich upon one <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lista</hi> a master of fence, who f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r report of robberies was covered with a heap of stones:
<q>
         <pb facs="5"/>
         <l>Monte sub hoc lapidum tegitur <hi>Balista</hi> sepultus;</l>
         <l>Nocte, die tutum carpe, viator, iter.</l>
         <l>This heap of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ones, <hi>Balista's</hi> corps interre;</l>
         <l>Then night or day passe safely, passenger.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>After this he wrote <hi>Moretum, Priapus,</hi> Epigrams, <hi>Dirae, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex,</hi> and other Poems, when he was but about sixteen yeares of age. He wrote <hi>Aetna</hi> also: and after that, writing of <hi>Romane</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, yet misliking the sharpnes and rigidnes of the matter and names thereof, he fell upon his <hi>Bucolicks:</hi> especially to celebrate the names of <hi>Asinius Pollio, Alphenus Varius,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Gallus</hi> his great friends. Afterward he wrote his <hi>Georgi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ks</hi> in honour of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coenas.</hi> Last of all, he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ok these <hi>Aeneïds</hi> in hand, a work of a vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and multifarious argument, and in a manner, resembling both <hi>Homers</hi> works. When he wrote the <hi>Georgicks,</hi> it is reported, that every morning he was accustomed to write a certain number of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which he would all the day long overlook and so abridge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them into a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w, that it might not be unfitly said, that he brought forth verses <hi>ursino more,</hi> as the female-be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re doth her young, bringing them into due form by licking. This his work called the <hi>Aeneïds,</hi> he wrote first in twelve books in prose (as some think) and afterward digested it into verse; and some think, that had he lived he would have enlarged it unto twentie foure books, even unto the time of <hi>Augustus.</hi> Of his <hi>Aeneïds</hi> (scarcely yet begun) there was spread such a fame, that <hi>Sextus Propertius</hi> doubted not thus to write of them;
<q>
         <l>Cedite <hi>Romani</hi> scriptores, cedite <hi>Graii</hi>;</l>
         <l>Nesciò quid majus nascitur <hi>Iliade.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Give place, give place <hi>Greeks, Romane</hi> writers wise;</l>
         <l>Some worthi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r work then <hi>Ilias</hi> now doth rise.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>When <hi>Augustus Cesar,</hi> who by chance was absent from the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabrick</hi> expedition, requested <hi>Virgil,</hi> partly by intreating, partly by merrily m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nacing letters, to send him, if it were but a very little, or (as his own words are) some one perfect sentence of his <hi>Aeneids,</hi> he refused it: but afterward, when it was fully perfected, he recited to him three of the books, namely the second, the fourth, and the sixth, and this especially for <hi>Octavia's</hi> sake, who being there present at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citall of those verses of her sonne, <hi>Tu Marcellus eris &amp;c.</hi> Thou shalt <hi>Marcellus</hi> be, it is reported she fell into a swound with sorrow: and being with much adoe recovered, she commanded that <hi>Virgil</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
should have to the value of five pound for every verse. He read his book also to diverse, but not often, and those places onely, whereof he made any scruple or doubt; thereby to heare mens judgements of them. He fully perused his <hi>Bucolicks</hi> and <hi>Georgicks:</hi> and when he was about <hi>52</hi> yeares old, with a desire to finish his <hi>Aeneids,</hi> he resolved to have withdrawn himself into <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Asia,</hi> and there to have spent three whole yeares in correcti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g and perusing it, that he might bestow the remainder of his dayes onely in the studie of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie. But being in his journey, at <hi>Athens</hi> he met <hi>Augustus</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the East-countreys towards <hi>Rome;</hi> whereupon he purposed to have returned home again with the emperour: but travelling to <hi>Megara,</hi> a town neare <hi>Athens,</hi> onely to see it, he took a sicknesse there, which with continuall travell by sea so increased till he came to <hi>Brundusium,</hi> that within few dayes after he there died, on the <hi>22</hi> of <hi>Septemb. Cneius Plautius</hi> and <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Lucretus</hi> being Consuls. When he felt himself sick unto the death, he called often and very earnestly for his desk, that he might burn his <hi>Aeneids:</hi> which being denyed him, he notwithstanding▪ order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his last will and testament, that it should be burned, as a work both faultie and imperf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ct. But <hi>Tucca</hi> and <hi>Varrus</hi> told him that <hi>Augustus</hi> would by no means suffer it. Whereupon he bequeathed that work and his other writings to <hi>Varius</hi> and <hi>Tucca,</hi> upon this condition, that they should set forth nothing but that which he would have set forth; and such verses as were imperfect, to leave so still. He desired that his bones should be translated to <hi>Naples,</hi> where he had lived long and merrily; which at <hi>Cesars</hi> command was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly performed, and he buried in the way to <hi>Puteoli.</hi> Vpon his tombe, at the second stone was engraven this distick, made by himself,
<q>
         <l>
            <hi>Mantua</hi> me genuit, <hi>Calabri</hi> repuêre; tenet nunc</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Parthenope</hi>; Cecini pascua, rura, duces.</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Mantua</hi> gave life, <hi>Calabria</hi> death, a grave</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Parthenop:</hi> I sang fields, lands, captains brave.</l>
      </q>
      <hi>Plotius Tucca</hi> after <hi>Virgils</hi> decease (as he had requested) at <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars</hi> command, corrected the <hi>Aeneids;</hi> for no man judged them to be burnt; whereof these verses of <hi>Suspitius</hi> the <hi>Carthaginian,</hi> are extant.
<q>
         <l>Jusserat haec rapidis aboleri carmina flammis</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Virgilius, Phrygium</hi> quae cecinere ducem.</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Tucca</hi> vetat, <hi>Variusque</hi> simul: tu maxime <hi>Caesar,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Non sinis; &amp; <hi>Latiae</hi> consulis historiae.</l>
         <l>Infelix gemino cecidit propè <hi>Pergamos</hi> igni,</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="6"/>Et penè est alio <hi>Troia</hi> cremata rogo.</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Virgil</hi> these verses vow'd to fires fierce flame,</l>
         <l>Which sweetly sang the <hi>Trojan</hi> princes fame.</l>
         <l>But <hi>Tucca, Varius, Cesar,</hi> to his glorie,</l>
         <l>The fact forbad, preserv'd th'<hi>Italian</hi> stori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</l>
         <l>Vnhappie <hi>Troy,</hi> twice (neare) with fire consum'd;</l>
         <l>Neare <hi>Pergame</hi> perisht had, to fire twice doom'd.</l>
      </q>
There are extant also many other and most excellent verses written by <hi>Augustus Cesar</hi> himself, to the same effect: which begin thus;
<q>
         <l>Ergóne supremis potuit vox improba verbis</l>
         <l>Tam dirum mandare nefas? Ergò ibit in ignes,</l>
         <l>Magnáque doctiloqui morietur Musa <hi>Maronis</hi>?</l>
         <l>And must so vile a voice of last-will stand,</l>
         <l>And such a foule nefarious fact command?</l>
         <l>Must <hi>Maro's</hi> marrow of pure poëtrie,</l>
         <l>Most learned lines in furious fire so frie?</l>
      </q>
And a little after;
<q>
         <l>Sed legum servanda fides; suprema voluntas</l>
         <l>Quod mand at fieríque jubet, parere necesse est.</l>
         <l>Frangatur potiùs legum veneranda potestas,</l>
         <l>Quàm tot congestos noctésque diésque labores</l>
         <l>Hauserit una dies, &amp;c.</l>
         <l>But law, and what last-will doth will, must stand,</l>
         <l>And that must be obey'd which laws command:</l>
         <l>Nay rather we'le infringe laws awfull power,</l>
         <l>Then such rare nights and dayes toiles in one houre</l>
         <l>Suffer to suffer shipwrack, &amp;c.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pedianus</hi> reporteth, that <hi>Virgil</hi> was very courteous, and a lover of all good and learned men, and so unspotted with the foot of envie, that if he heard or saw any thing wittily or worthily said or done by any others, he as much rejoyced therein, as if it had been his own: That he used not to dispraise any man, but ever praised good men; and that he was so courteous and affable, that there was none (except he were most rudely and barbarously inclined) but both much favoured, and most ardently affected him. He seemed utterly unglued from strict <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m;</hi> for his librarie stood still as open to the schollars, as to himself, and oftentimes used that old adage of <hi>Euripides,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Communia amicorum esse omnia,</hi> All things are common among friends. And therefore he so lovingly respected all the poëts of his time, that when they were emulously and enviously
<pb facs="7"/>
jarring and snarling at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e another, yet they all with an unanime consent ever loved and reverenced him, as <hi>Tucca, Varius, Horace, Gallus,</hi> and <hi>Propertius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He so much despised glorie, that when some had ascribed and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated to themselves certain of his verses, and were therefore had in the greater reputation for their learning, he not onely shewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self no way discontented therewith, but much rejoyced at it. For when once he made a couple of v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rses containing the praise and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie of <hi>Cesars</hi> emperie, which were set upon the gates without name, (these were the verses;
<q>
         <l>Nocte pluit tota, redeunt spectacula mane,</l>
         <l>Divisum imperium cum <hi>Iove Caesar</hi> habet.</l>
         <l>All night it rains, next morn sights glut the eye:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Cesar</hi> with <hi>Jove</hi> hath equall emperie.)</l>
      </q>
      <hi>Cesar</hi> having made enquirie for the authour of them, yet could not know him, at length <hi>Bathyllus</hi> a certain plain poët (when none would father them) took upon him to be the authour of them; and was therefore both well rewarded and much respected by <hi>Cesar.</hi> But <hi>Virgil</hi> not taking this very well, set upon the same gates, this begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his conceit fouretimes, <hi>Sic vos, non vobis,</hi> which <hi>Augustus Cesar</hi> would have had made up: but when many had fruitlessely e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured it, <hi>Virgil</hi> himself rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yed thus to the foresaid distich:
<q>
         <l>Hos ego versiculos feci, tulit alter honores.</l>
         <l>Sic vos non vobis nidificatis, aves:</l>
         <l>Sic vos non vobis vellera fertis, oves:</l>
         <l>Sic vos non vobis mellificatis, apes:</l>
         <l>Sic vos non vobis fertis aratra, boves.</l>
         <l>These verses I did make,</l>
         <l>Others my palm did take.</l>
         <l>So you not for you, birds, build nests in trees:</l>
         <l>So you not for you, sheep, wooll-fleeces beare:</l>
         <l>So you not for you gather honey, bees:</l>
         <l>So you not for you, beeves, plow-yokes do weare.</l>
      </q>
This thus known, <hi>Bathyllus</hi> was for a long time an occasion of jest and laughter to the whole citie of <hi>Rome.</hi> Once <hi>Virgil</hi> having in his hand the works of <hi>Ennius,</hi> and being demanded by one, what he did with them, he answered, that he gathered gold out of <hi>Ennius</hi> his dung: for that author expressed worthy sentences and matter under homely words and phrases. <hi>Augustus Cesar</hi> asking him how a citie might be best governed, he answered, If the wisest men were placed
<pb facs="7"/>
at the helm of government, and good men authorized to over-rule the bad; and that thus men of desert might have their due honour, and men of mean condition not oppressed w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th injurie. <hi>Mecoenas</hi> also asking him what it is that procures least loathsomenesse and tedious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to a man, he answered, The multitude and similitude of all things offends every mans appetite and affection, except of understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Mecoenas</hi> asked him again, how a man might conserve from ruine a faire and flourishing estate? To whom <hi>Virgil</hi> answered, If he excell others as much in liberalitie and goodnesse, as in riches and in honour. He was accustomed to say, that none of all the vertues was more laudable or more profitable for a man then patience; and that no estate or fortune could be so terrible or untoothsome, but that a wise man by discreet sufferance might overcome it. Which he excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently urgeth in the fifth of his <hi>Aeneïds,</hi> thus;
<q>
         <l>Nate Dea, quà fata trahunt, retrahúntque, sequamur;</l>
         <l>Quicquid erit, superanda omnis fortuna ferendo est.</l>
         <l>Fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Goddesse sonne, let's follow fates where s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ere;</l>
         <l>Worst state or fate by bearing let's o'rebeare.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>There are many other worthy and memorable things written by this authour, of this our poet, and his other excellent works; which, partly to avoid prolixitie, partly also as not being peculiarly pertinent to this work, I have of purpose pretermitted, and referre the reader, for farther satisfaction (if he require it) to <hi>Donatus</hi> himself in <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> his Commentarie upon that our Prince of Poëts, <hi>Virgil.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>