<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the chrysten reders.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1536</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111371_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">421.17</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111371</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the chrysten reders.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very true pronosticacio [n], with a kalender, gathered out of the moost auncyent bokes of ryght holy astronomers : for the yere of our lorde M. CCCCC. xxxvj. And for all yeres here after perpetuall. Translated out of latyn in to Englysshe by Ioh⁻n Ryckes preest. Cum priuilegio Regali</title>
                 <author>Brunfels, Otto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Byddell, alias Salisbury, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1536</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <head>¶ To the chrysten reders.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>O good reders, here may you se, what the cause is of all the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshmentes, plages, &amp; myseryes that god sendeth vpon vs: that is bycause we do not obserue the lawes of god / nor do not lyue accordynge to his worde. And not as many bothe do thinke and saye, that these newe lawes &amp; newe lernynges are the causes. Is not this newe lernynge the very trewe worde of god? Elles let them cōme and proue the contrary. But now that lyght is cōme in to this worlde: they that haue be brought vp in darknes, loue better darknes than lyght / yea rather they hate the lyght, and wyll not cōme at it / leest theyr ypocrysye and theyr cerymonyous good workes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the inuencions of men, sholde appere
<pb facs="30"/> nought, and worthy to be reproued.</p>
   <p>Those sorte wolde I exhorte to cōme whyles they haue lyght, and beleue in it, leest (remaynynge here in theyr inwarde darknes) they be kest in to the outwarde darknes, where shall be euer sorowe and mysery. ¶ An other sorte there is (the more pytye) that seme to fauour y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyght of goddes worde, and folowe and fauour the preachers therof: but they seke the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the flesshe, and not of the spirite, lyuynge after theyr fleshly lustes, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the noughty fashyon of the worlde, in couetousnes / ambicion / pryde, with infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte other euylles / onely sekyng for theyr owne profytes and pleasures / though it be to theyr chrystyan brothers greate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment. This cōmeth of inordynate loue that men haue to them selues: whiche is cause of moche other euyll: and neuer can bryng forth good frute of fayth / thus con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuynge to the ende of theyr lyfe, ledde contynually ferre out of charite, through
<pb facs="30"/> theyr propre loue: yet they thynke than to be saued by their fayned fayth. Whiche I feare me, for lacke of testimony of good workes, shall be disalowed at the daye of iudgement, whan Chryste shall saye. I was hungry / and ye gaue me no meate, and so forthe. This sorte lette that other sorte from cōmynge to the lyght. And it is to be feared, that these cōmunycacions in this pronosticacion, shall fall vpon vs / not bycause we forsake obedyence to the bysshop of Rome and his lawes, whiche hathe ledde vs in to darknes, and out of the ryght way to godwarde / nor bycause of this newe preachynge after the very worde of god: but bycause the worde is now so often, and so playnly preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs / and we remayne styll after the olde fashyon / as the cityes dyd, where Chryst preached, Corosayn, Betzayda, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum / whome he reproued and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, bycause they receyued not his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, so often shewed vnto them.</p>
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <p>The grounde that is well tylled &amp; sowen and hath often rayne in season / and yet brynge forth no good frute (sayth saynt Paule) is cursed of the owner. Therfore let vs so heare the trewe worde of god / that we may chaunge our lyuynge / and lyue accordynge vnto his worde: and I doubte not, we shall obtayne his mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promyses, and benedictions, that he promyseth to the kepers of his lawes, and lyue after his worde, by the grace of Chryst, by whose merytes and helpe we may bryng all thynges well to passe / and haue not onely these tēporall blessynges / but also spirituall / true fayth / remyssyon of synnes / preseruacion in grace / and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suraūce of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kyngdome of heuen. whiche I beseche hym to graunte vs. Amen.</p>
   <p>¶ This treatyse or pronosticacion is seen, redde, and examyned by me Iohn̄ Hylsey bysshop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>