<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONrable COMPANIE OF VIRGINIA.</title>
           <author>Waterhouse, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111598_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14803</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25104</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111598</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONrable COMPANIE OF VIRGINIA.</title>
                 <author>Waterhouse, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of the state of the colony and affaires in Virginia : With a relation of the barbarous massacre in the time of peace and league, treacherously executed by the natiue infidels vpon the English, the 22 of March last. Together with the names of those that were then massacred; that their lawfull heyres, by this notice giuen, may take order for the inheriting of their lands and estates in Virginia. And a treatise annexed, written by that learned mathematician Mr. Henry Briggs, of the Northwest passage to the South Sea through the continent of Virginia, an by Fretum Hudson. Also a commemoration of such worthy benefactors as haue contributed their Christian charitie towards the aduancement of the colony. And a note of the charges of necessary prouisions fit for euery man that intends to goe to Virginia. Published by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Waterhouse, Edward, colonist</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 54, 2, folded leaf, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HON<seg rend="sup">rable</seg> COMPANIE OF VIRGINIA.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable and Worthy:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE fame of our late vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy accident in <hi>Virginia,</hi> hath spread it selfe, I doubt not, into all parts abroad, and as it is talked of of all men, so no question of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and of most, it cannot but be misreported, some carryed away with ouer-weak lightnesse to beleeue all they heare, how vntrue soeuer; others out of their disaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction possibly to the <hi>Plantation,</hi> are desirous to make that, which is ill, worse; and so the truth of the Action, which is only one, is varied and misreported. I haue thought it therefore a part of some acceptable seruice in me towards you,
<pb facs="3"/>
whose fauors haue preferred me to be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your <hi>Company,</hi> to present you with these my poore labours, the Collection of the truth hereof, drawne from the relation of some of those that were beholders of that <hi>Tragedie,</hi> and who hardly escaped from tasting of the same cup, as also from the Letters sent you by the <hi>Gouernour</hi> and other <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of quality, and of the <hi>Councell</hi> in that Colonie, read openly here in your Courts: That so the world may see that it was not the strength of a professed enemy that brought this slaughter on them, but contriued by the perfidious treachery of a false-hearted people, that know not God nor faith. No generous Spirit will forbeare to goe on for this accident that hath hapned to the Plantation, but proceed rather chearfully in this honorable Enterprize, since the discouery of their bruitish falshood will proue (as shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this Treatise following) many waies aduantageable to vs, and make this forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a forearming for euer to preuent a greater mischiefe.</p>
   <p>Accept it from me, I most humbly beseech you, as the first fruits of my poore seruice.
<pb facs="3"/>
Time may happily make me able to yeeld you some other worke whose subiect may bee Ioy, as this is a Theame of Sadnesse: Meane time, I commit You and the <hi>Noble Colony</hi> to Gods good blessing, as he that shall alwaies be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>A true Votarie for your happinesse, and seruant to your commands,</hi> EDVVARD WATERHOVSE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>