<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111870_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00275</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10389</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111870</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>To my faythfull brethren now afflycted : [and] to all those that vnfaynedly loue the Lorde Jesus, the Lorde guyde vs with his holy spret, that we maye always serue hym bothe in body and mynde in all syncereyte to oure lyues ende</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Erve, Egidius (Gillis) van der (Gellius Ctematius)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Emden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>TO my faythfull Brethren, we geue thankes to God for your constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and vpryght delynge in this gret controuersie now raysyd by packynge of enemys about the wearinge of popish ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and as ye haue well begonne, ther is no doubt, but the Lorde in mercy shall kepe ye pure and blameles to the ende. It hathe byne no small ioye and comfort to many godlye and good Churches, which dayly and howerly prayeth for your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuerāce, and that it wolde please God to ease it, whē his good will and pleasure is. So on the other syde muche lamentynge the blyndnes of those that goeth about to defende it: but especiallye those that are become persecutors of their godly &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren: but as charite requireth, we desyre God neuer laye it to theyr charge, but geue them grace to ryse agayne vnto whom we leue them wether they stande or falle. Let Lottes wyfe be a warnynge in tyme to take hede. Moses that blessyd ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uant of God wolde not alter the valew of a curten, or a lytill pyne in the Arche, so ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous was he in the Lordes worke: nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer brought any thynge out of his owne heade to the people: But had always the
<pb facs="19"/>
warrant of the worde for hym, to cōclude, what so euer may be obiected agaynst the refusars of those ydolators garmētes, for what so euer they brynge, may be redused into this poyntes, that Godly men ether nede not or ought not to be scrupulous in so small a matter, which answer ye shall vnderstand as folowith with an answere to a question at the end hereof. The Lord for his Christ sake make Ephrahim and Manassis agre, that we maye all with on hart and mynde vnfaynydly seke Godes glorye, the edificacion of his people, that we may lyue in all godly peace, vnyte, and concord. This grant, o Lorde, for Christ Jesus sake, to whom, with the, and the Holy goste, be all prayse, glory, and honor for euer and euer.</p>
   <closer>Fare ye well deare Brethren.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>