<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To hys moste deretly beloued bretherne the faythull worshyppers of oure Lorde Ie∣sus Christe / Theodore Bibliander wyssheth grace and peace from God the father.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111613_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16125</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3047</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111613</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To hys moste deretly beloued bretherne the faythull worshyppers of oure Lorde Ie∣sus Christe / Theodore Bibliander wyssheth grace and peace from God the father.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly consultation vnto the brethren and companyons of the Christen religyon : By what meanes the cruell power of the Turkes, bothe may, and ought for to be repelled of the Christen people, Theodore Bibliander beinge the author. Thow shalt also fynde here (most gentle reader) of the reasons wherwyth a firme and sure concorde and peace in the Churche, and the Christen publyke weale may be constytuted, and of the fyrst begynnynge and increacementes of the Turkes domynyon, and also of the superstytyous and damnable lawe of the Mahumetanes, and of other certen thynges moste worthy truly to be red and consydered</title>
                 <author>Bibliander, Theodorus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 <publisher>Bonifante, Radulph, pseud.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crom, Matthias</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>clx leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="ij" facs="2"/>
   <head>To hys moste deretly beloued bretherne the faythull worshyppers of oure Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christe / Theodore Bibliander wyssheth grace and peace from God the father.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen of late dayes the sadde tydynges of the destruccyō of hūga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye had brought greate sorowe vnto all good men: that thinge which Christē godlynes dyd requier / and that I coulde onely do in suche greate calamytyes I dyd it / that is to weit I was very sory for the mysfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of oure men. And I besought the Lord he wolde spare his people / whiche he had redemed with te bloud of his onely begot tē sonne / &amp; that he wolde not procede on styl to be reuenged vpon vs / accordinge to oure deseruinges: Afterwarde I dyd be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynne to consider in my mynde one thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of an other / by what meanes we might resyste these euylles waxynge feruent &amp; so to heale the woūde receyued / that here after more deadely woundes be not gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen vnto vs: Wherfore when all the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of te vulgare people was cōsumed in these vrgēt euylles. And the cheiffe men
<pb facs="3"/> &amp; rulars of cytyes dyd holde manye coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cells to conserue the publycke weale / I dyd suppose it not to be a thinge alienate &amp; agen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>yce of those men that do applye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and namely the holy scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture yf they dyd descrybe some firme &amp; sure reasons of holdynge warre agaynst the Turkes lying so greuously ouer Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many / that is to saye the towre of Christē<note place="margin">Mathema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters are whych be cunnyng in Aulgry me / Musy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry ād Astrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye.</note> dome. Although the Mathematycall cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes and masters of Astronomye do take vpon them the fore knowlege of warres thorow the trientall &amp; Quincuncial aspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes of Iupiter / Saturne / and Mars / &amp; of other Planetes / and expresse the causes &amp; chaunces of them / and accomplisshe the same wyth a natural sharpenes of wytte / &amp; as men experte in some certē vse of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: yet wold Alexāder dyscrete &amp; sharpe<note place="margin">Alexāder.</note> in correction the moste noble Prynce in the feates of warre / cheifely vse the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the olde excercysed souldioures: Neuer the lesse I do iudge moche better councels: to be requyred by ryght of those men that be studyous of deuyne scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For the deuyne lawes befuge forth the Leuyte euen the mynyster of relygyō in to the former parte of the hoste / &amp; they<note place="margin">Nume. i. Deute. xx Nume. x.</note> do sett hym betwene the multytudes now standynge rownde aboute in theyr araye / and wyth the hoorse sounde of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pettes
<pb n="iij" facs="3"/> they do mynister a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ce to the warres waxyng whote / that it may be prynted in the hartes of all good men / not to be chaunce and blynd fortune / not to be inconstant or slypper Mars whych<note place="margin">Mars is fayned of poetes to be the god of battell and it is also one of the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>netes.</note> rasshely myxeth togyther the troubles of warre / but that it is God the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of heauē and erth / which by iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment &amp; sure reason gyueth vnto some mē merye victorye / &amp; turneth an other sorte vnto flyght: And that religiō wyth oute the whiche no thynge can be gouērned well and happely hathe in batell the che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feste vse / as in the moste daunger of the publyk weale: Also many sermones of the Prophetes dispute of the causes &amp; chaūce of warres: and euē thys matter as a thing propre or specyally pertaynyng vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynyte doth Hieremye knowlege vnto Hananiah the sonne of Azur / saying / the prophetes which were before me and the / <note place="margin">Hiere. xxviij.</note> from the begynnynge / &amp; dyd prophecye vpon landes and greate kingedomes / of warre and troble and honger / or ells of peace / were proued by thys / yf God had sent them in very dede whē the thynge came so to passe whiche the Prophet tolde before: More ouer many mynysters of<note place="margin">Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</note> holy doctryne / after the comynge of oure lorde dyd not abhorre from the pollytyck rules of kepynge warre: for that I may
<pb facs="4"/> passe by: How that in the tētes of Constā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyne<note place="margin">Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne.</note> the greate / euerye pauylyon of the souldyers had lerned mē in holy thinges how▪ Bernharde the abbot was the author<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> of bearynge harnes agaynste the Sarace<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cens: That I may holde my peace of the Innocencianes / and the Eugenianes and soche other trōpet blouwers of oute lādysh warres: Saynte Augustyne the greateste<note place="margin">Augusty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> master of diuinite in his questions to the booke of Iosue doth allmoste explicate the whole reason to kepe battell godly: saynt Hierome also writynge in Bethlem the<note place="margin">Hierome</note> same tyme wherein the Turkes dyd wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste moste cruelly the lesser Asia / &amp; a parte of Syria / and at the laste had kylled all Syria / Arabye and Egypte with feare / dyd showe that the synnes of the Christen people were the cause of that plage / and that there was no sure victorye ād health to be looked for / before there were a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto vertu and righteousnes: The councel of the whche moste wyse and also moste holy man if oure fore fathers wolde haue vsed a great whyle ago: We sholde haue had all Germanye fre at thys daye from all the feare and weapons of the Turkes and also all Europe. Neyther sholde the secte of Mahumet haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the greateste parte of the worlde
<pb n="iiij" facs="4"/> inhabyted. And Christe the wisdome / righteousnes &amp; power of God / sholde ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue bene preached in those places / where as now lyinge falshed and madde supersti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion doth excedingly reioyse and triūphe: Therfore I folowyng the exāple of soche men all though wyth a lōge space betwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / haue iudged it a proffitable thinge / if I sholde bringe vnto my bretherne not so moche a new coūcell as to renue an olde: Whiche thynge shall worthely haue now the more weyght or be the better ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after that it is knowne by a proffe so manye euylles beynge ouercomme what skill it is to obey hym that gyueth good warnynge. But my oration was to be ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyed some thinge more nerer vnto ower tymes / and the descriptiō was to be made of those reasons / with the whyche a sure and contynu all concorde myght be consti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuted in the Christen congregation. Of the firste begynnynge and increasynges of the Turkes dominion / of the superstici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of Machumet / and of other certen thinges: so that my oration hathe recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a lōg measure and is largely drawne in length whyche thynge neuer the lesse the greatenes of the busynes did requier. But if the speche or style ther of shall se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto any man to be vneloquent / let the same parsone consider that it was not my mynde here for to tryfle wyth the
<pb facs="5"/> flours of Rethorycke / but to brynge ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faythfull then paynted glytterynge councel vnto thinges afflicted. Bitter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes or tauntes do some where offende and rype putrifyed botches are launced with an harde knyfe / but necessite dyd re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quier it. Or ells I am not so ignorant of thinges that I know not what the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of some men desyre to heare and what a swete mischeffe flatterye is / the<note place="margin">Flatery is a swete mischeif.</note> very destruction of Kinges and of the pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licke weale / as Arrianus saythe. And I<note place="margin">Arrianus</note> am indued with soche a naturall inclinaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and fortune that my desyer is to haue the good will and fauor of euerye man. But yet for all that theyr dyseases muste nedes be tolde them that the medicyns may the trulyer be ministered lest some so den destruction sholde fall vpon vs / why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les yet we crye peace peace daubynge a walle with vntempred mortar whiche the<note place="margin">Iere. viii. Ezec. xiii.</note> ouerflowynge waters of the lordes wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the may ouerthrowe. Neuerthelesse what so ouer be the spryte or mynde of this wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge / I will be iudged of godly men / so that they whiche haue any better reasons let them gentely distrybute them: And they that haue not / let them gladly vse these with me in sylence and hope taryin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and abydinge the sauinge healthe of oure lorde God.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Fare you well / frō Zurik <date>1542.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>