<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOVR TO THE PIOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111891_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06736</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17181</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111891</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOVR TO THE PIOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fuga sæculi. Or The holy hatred of the world : Conteyning the liues of 17. holy confessours of Christ, selected out of sundry authors. Written in Italian by the R. Fa. Iohn-Peter Maffæus of the Society of Iesus. And translated into English by H.H</title>
                 <author>Maffei, Giovanni Pietro</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 352, 169-383, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOVR TO THE <hi>PIOVS READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N things vvhich at first sight are vvont to bee considered in any VVorke vvhatsoeuer, it seemes the <hi>Intention</hi> of the Authour, and <hi>Trace,</hi> or <hi>Method</hi> are the principall. VVhence I, to giue a breife accompt of eyther, say first;</p>
   <p>My <hi>End</hi> in this vvorke to haue been, to make a choyce of <hi>Liues,</hi> not led so much in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, as in Community; and of Examples also, not so miraculous, or stupendious, as vertuous, and (vvith diuine Grace) not vneasy to bee
<pb facs="5"/>
imitated.</p>
   <p>Next, in the manner of proceeding I haue taken lycence to cut of al superfluityes, to reduce scattered Narrations to the order of <hi>Tymes,</hi> or <hi>Kinds;</hi> and finally to modify those passages, vvhich transferring the thoughts to things dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest or hurtfull (as somtymes it happens) the chaster <hi>Eares,</hi> or more delicate <hi>Consciences,</hi> in some manner, come to be offended: But yet is all endeauoured in such sort, as the substance and truth of the Historyes remayne (vvhat possible) entire, sincere, and vncorrupted.</p>
   <p>Such in summe, my designe in this present vvriting hath beene: VVhich if, in so great an infinity of Bookes, it proue not to be super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous or vnprofitable; the vvhole Glory therof shall be ovving to our <hi>Lord:</hi> And vvhen the <hi>Effect</hi> likevvise, shall not ansvvere the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire,</hi> at least the <hi>Good-Will,</hi> I trust, shall be had in reguard.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>