<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To as many as can Read, (though but reasonably) it makes no great matter whe∣ther they under∣stand, or no.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111401_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23766</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To as many as can Read, (though but reasonably) it makes no great matter whe∣ther they under∣stand, or no.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iuniper lecture : With the description of all sorts of women, good, and bad: from the modest to the maddest, from the most civil, to the scold rampant, their praise and dispraise compendiously related. Also the authors advice how to tame a shrew, or vexe her</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Lee (Ley), William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 167, 188-236 pages, plates, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To as many as can Read, (though but reasonably) it makes no great matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, or no.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere's a strange Lecture to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, (my towardly, or untowardly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) for here shall be found many things worthy your observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I know you
<pb facs="3"/>
have heard of a <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Lecture</hi> before now: and shall very shortly heare of a <hi>Crab-tree Lecture</hi> also: But for a <hi>Juniper Lecture</hi> (although the phrase or stile be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, yet the matter is new:) And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it doth take, &amp; is liked so well, I have inlarged it in many places, with many new Lectures
<pb facs="3"/>
to it: But why is it called a <hi>Juniper Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>? Marry for sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry small reasons; why a Lecture, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Verse, indeed for no reason at all.</p>
   <p>But as the gagling tongue of a scold leapes and skippes (like a Squirrell from one twigge or branch to another, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither Method or Measure) so doth
<pb facs="4"/>
this various discourse and description of the good &amp; bad qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of women, skip from the vicious to the vertuous, &amp; back againe from the best to the worst. It is said that <hi>Iuniper</hi> being on fire is the most lasting wood in the World, and that if the fire of it be rak'd up in the Embers, or Ashes, it will not be
<pb facs="4"/>
extinguished in a yeare or more, which may bee alluded to some revengeful wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who being once offended, the fire of their malice will hardly be quenched in their Ashes, or Graves. <hi>Juniper</hi> is hot and drye in the third Degree, (as <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> saith) and the tongue of a scold is altogether combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stible:
<pb facs="5"/>
It is full of prickles, so are a curst womans words very piercing to the eares, and sharpe to the heart. <hi>Juniper</hi> hath also some qualities and vertues of good women, for as it may be used, it is a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-poison against a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one that is enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed; so a vertuous woman is the honor &amp; preservation of her
<pb facs="5"/>
husbands person and estate: the Berries &amp; Gumme is likewise good against gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings and gnawings in the stomacke; so is a good wife a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable helpe to a mans aking heart: It hath a good savour, and so hath the good name of a worthy woman, the Gumme of it is called <hi>Lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> or <hi>Teares,</hi> and for
<pb facs="6"/>
Teares, women (for the most part) have them at command; but the best is, they are like <hi>April</hi> showres, wet and dry in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But as every woman is not a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Grissel,</hi> so she is a rare Wonder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst women, that neither hath the skil, or the desire to scold. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>