<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right Honourable Sir
Thomas Bromley Knight, Lord
Chaunceler of England, and of her Maiesties
moste Honorable priuie Counsell,
George VVhetstones, wisheth long
continuaunce of honour,
health and happines.
(∵)</title>
           <author>Whetstone, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111683_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15043</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25345</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111683</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right Honourable Sir
Thomas Bromley Knight, Lord
Chaunceler of England, and of her Maiesties
moste Honorable priuie Counsell,
George VVhetstones, wisheth long
continuaunce of honour,
health and happines.
(∵)</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A remembraunce of the precious vertues of the right honourable and reuerend iudge, Sir Iames Dier, Knight, Lord cheefe Iustice of the Common Pleas : who disseased at great Stawghton, in Huntingdon shire, the 24. of Marche, anno. 1582. The reporte of George VVhetstons, gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right Honourable Sir
Thomas Bromley <hi>Knight, Lord
Chaunceler of</hi> England, <hi>and of her Maiesties</hi>
moste Honorable priuie Counsell,
<hi>George VVhetstones,</hi> wisheth long
continuaunce of honour,
health and happines.
(∵)</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable,</hi>
so blessed hath beene the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
of this little Realme,
since the hower of her sacred
Maiesties moste prosperous
raigne, as it hath beene a
question, whether the people
of forraigne nations, doo
bemone their owne callamities, or enuie our felicitie
moste: and as the godly wise, inserte the miseries of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
people, to the vengeaunce of God, executed vppon
their owne bowels, through the tyranie of their Kings,
together with the ambytion and enuie of their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
Maiestrates: so doo they also acknowledge, that
our especiall happines, proceedeth from the deuine
blessing of the hiest, who in the heate of percicution
gratiouslie sent vs, a moste gratious Princes, led by a
spirit, onely composed of pietie, bountie, and pittie, and
further, strengthened her highnesse with a Senate, and
other needefull maiestrates▪ so graue and pollitique, as
establish wholesome lawes, for the publique benefit of
her Maiesties Subiects, and withall, with lynxes eyes
<pb facs="3"/>
so prie into forraine practises, that by their wisdomes,
in the beginning, they returne the weapons prouided
for our mischeefes, into the practisers owne entrailes, so
that more for feare then loue (beeing through the world
for our prosperitie enuied) we haue free passage in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
nations, and finde the seale of peace, vppon the
Gates of our owne Citties▪ which duly considered, that
English subiect may iustlie be proclaimed enimie to
grace &amp; humanitie, that rendreth not hartie thankes
vnto God, dutifull obedience vnto her Maiestie, and
reuerent loue and affection vnto the Maiestrates, for
this peace plentie, and protection, and seeing forraigne
writers, that haue their Colledges enuironed with
Armes, finde meanes to present the world, with the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies
of their Maiestrates, oppressions of the people,
and ruines of their Citties. English Historiographers
which haue quiet recorse vnto the Muses, are bound to
eternise the memories of the good maiestrates dissea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
(who were the instruments of our blessings, that the
dead may haue their right, and the liuing incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to vertue. Right honorable, bound by these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations,
to discharge the office of a poore writer, in
monuments extant, I haue regestred the liues of manie
woorthie personages disceased, and at this present moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
with the passion of a common sorrow, to showe the
reuerēt zeale I bare vnto Iustice, I haue made a weake
remembraunce of a fewe of the pretious vertues, which
gouerned the good Lord <hi>Dyer,</hi> late cheefe Iustice of
the Common Pleas, which I humblie laie before your
Lordships searching iudgement, no better garnished
then Diamonds set in Brasse, assuring my self that your
<pb facs="3"/>
honour will reade his full merrit, if not in my woords,
in the woorking of your owne vertues, who with the
wings of this iust Iustiser, are mounted into the soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
seate, of Iustice Capitoll, where poore iniured
sutors zealouslie praie, long to enioie your countenaūce
whose conscience is the ease of their oppressions, so that
knowing that my indeuor, shall finde grace in your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
sight, being the dew of this good Maiestrate, and
a testimonie of the seruice I vowe vnto your vertues.
I boldelie approche your presence with this simple pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
leauing the view thereof to your good Lordships
moste conuenient leasure, the 17. of Maie. 1582.</p>
   <signed>Your Honours bounden
<hi>to doo you seruice.
George VVhetstones.</hi>
   </signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>