<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST Sacred Majesty of CHARLES the first, Monarch of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111904_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06782</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17219</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST Sacred Majesty of CHARLES the first, Monarch of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Romulus and Tarquin. First written in Italian by the Marques Virgilio Malvezzi: and now taught English, by HCL</title>
                 <author>Malvezzi, Virgilio, marchese</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Benson, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 299, 1 page, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST Sacred <hi>Majesty</hi> of CHARLES the first, <hi>Monarch of Great Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>IVE me leave, SIR, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, to present your <hi>Majestie</hi> with a Glasse,
<pb facs="4"/>
wherein you may see your Soule: A good face may bee discerned in a Glasse of Jeat; and if <hi>contraria juxta se po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sita,</hi> doe <hi>magis eluces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>;</hi> if contraries doe best appeare, when most directly opposed; how can CHARLES <hi>the Gratious</hi> be better drawn to the Life, than by the description of TAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUIN <hi>the Proud?</hi> How can the unparallel'd, CHARLES <hi>the Chaste,</hi> be better portraited, than by the deciphering of
<pb facs="4"/>
TARQUIN <hi>the foule Ravisher?</hi> How can the happinesse your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties</hi> Realmes enjoy (and long may they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it) under your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties</hi> blessed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, better appeare, than by the making knowne what Miseries and Slavery the <hi>Romans</hi> endured under the Rule of TARQUIN <hi>the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant?</hi> And how, SIR, can your Pietie, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Zeale, bee better manifested, than by the selfe-deification of RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MULUS?
<pb facs="5"/>
who though it be true, he had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being the first Founder of a <hi>Famous People,</hi> yet <hi>Non minor est virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> quam quaerere, parta tueri.</hi> Wherein to shew <hi>Your Majesties</hi> Wisdome and Vigilancie, I need not to expatiat my selfe. This Glasse, SIR, is ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally <hi>Italian,</hi> and those your <hi>Majestie</hi> knowes are much better than ours of <hi>England,</hi> as made by better Workmen, and of more refined Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials. This, SIR, is but
<pb facs="5"/>
the Copy of a Principal, which, I must confesse, deserves to be copied by a much more skilfull hand; but as it is, SIR, I humbly beg your <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</hi> gracious Patronage of it, and your pardon for my so doing, to</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Majesties
Humble and Loyall Subject, and therein most happie,
ICL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>