<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Preface of foure Poynts.</title>
           <author>Smith, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111882_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22790</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Preface of foure Poynts.</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The generall historie of Virginia, New-England, and the Summer Isles : with the names of the adventurers, planters, and governours from their first beginning. an⁰: 1584. to this present 1624. With the procedings of those severall colonies and the accidents that befell them in all their journyes and discoveries. Also the maps and descriptions of all those countryes, their commodities, people, government, customes, and religion yet knowne. Divided into sixe bookes. By Captaine Iohn Smith sometymes governour in those countryes &amp; admirall of New England</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Reeve (Reave), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 96, 105-248 pages, 6 plates (4 folded), portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ A Preface of foure Poynts.</head>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His plaine History humbly sheweth the truth; that our most royall King <hi>Iames</hi> hath place and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to inlarge his ancient <hi>Dominions</hi> without wronging any; (which is a condition most agreeable to his most iust &amp; pious resolutions:) and the Prince his <hi>Highness</hi> may see where to plant new Colonies. The gaining Prouinces addeth to the Kings Crown: but the reducing Heathen people to ciuilitie and true Religion, bringeth honour to the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. If his Princely wisedome and powerfull hand, renowned through the world for admirable government, please but to set these now Estates into order; their composure will be singular: the counsell of divers is confused; the generall Stocke is consumed; nothing but the touch of the Kings sacred hand can erect a Monarchy.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Most noble Lords and worthy Gentlemen, it is your <hi>Honors</hi> that haue imployed great paines and large expence in laying the foundation of this State, wherein much hath beene buried vnder ground, yet some thing hath sprung vp, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you a taste of your adventures. Let no difficulties alter your noble intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The action is an honour to your Country: and the issue may well reimburse you your summes expended. Our practices haue hitherto beene but assayes, and are still to be amended. Let your bountie supply the necessities of weake begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and your excellent iudgements rectifie the proceedings; the returne can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not choose in the end but bring you good Commodities, and good contentments, by your aduancing shipping and fishing so vsefull vnto our Nation.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Yee valiant and generous spirits, personall possessors of these new-found Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, banish from among you Cowardise, covetousnes, iealousies, and idlenes, enemies to the raising your honours and fortunes; vertue, industry, and amitie, will make you good and great, and your merits liue to ensuing Ages. You that in contempt of necessities, hazard your liues and estates, imploying your studies &amp; labours in these faire endevours, liue and prosper as I desire my soule should prosper.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> For my selfe let emulation and enuie cease, I ever intended my actions should be vpright: now my care hath beene that my Relations should giue every man they concerne, their due. But had I not discovered and liued in the most of those parts, I could not possibly haue collected the substantiall truth from such a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of variable Relations, that would haue made a Volume at least of a thousand sheets. Though the beginning may seeme harsh in regard of the Antiquities, breuitie, and names; a pleasanter Discourse ensues. The stile of a Souldier is not eloquent, but honest and iustifiable; so I desire all my friends and well-wishers to excuse and accept it, and if any be so noble as to respect it, he that brought <hi>New England</hi> to light, though long since brought in obscuritie, he is againe to be found a true servant to all good designes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>So I ever rest yours to command, IOHN SMITH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>