<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument in briefe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111279_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12954</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23248</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111279</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument in briefe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cinthia's reuenge: or Mænanders extasie</title>
                 <author>Stephens, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Roger</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Argument in briefe.</head>
   <p>CINTHIA's Altars be neglected by the chiefe estates of
<hi>Sparta;</hi> both King and Councels adiudge her diuine sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,
religion, vowes, worship and adoration to appertaine
especially, if not punctually, to the weake order of women;
because they are subiect to changeable toyes, which take their
primitiue deriuation of <hi>Luna:</hi> Shee therefore inflamed
with resolution to qualifie this error, as to informe how farre
from iudgement so ir-religious opinions did arise, doth first
possesse the humor of exalted subiects, with manifest ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
breach of duty, and allegeance, libidinous concupiscence,
flattery, faithlesse engagements, which in themselues fauour
of <hi>Cinthia's</hi> large instability. <hi>Pheudippe</hi> (on whom the Kings
loue reflected with more extreame zeale) she averts from his
obedience to rebellion, by the power of pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dominance.
<hi>Manander</hi> noting a change so manifest doth (by collection)
attribute <hi>Pheudippe's</hi> false-hood to her suggestion; resolued
confidence begat his rage; his rage, blasphemy; which blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy
doth againe exaspcrate the Goddesse: her indignation
followes, which with violence brake forth inyong <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nanders</hi>
vehement madnesse. A stares-man, old <hi>Euphorbus,</hi> doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passionate
his agony, and for a second purpose, counterfets an
artificiall extasie, whil'st conceited humor makes <hi>Manander</hi>
follow (like <hi>Cinthia</hi>) diuersity of shapes: from Poet he fals to
a Player, then to <hi>Aiax,</hi> from thence to <hi>Mercury,</hi> in whose
habit, assuming the most sacred essence of a substance incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriall,
hee enioynes <hi>Euphorbus</hi> to make some experiment
heereof by his pouiard, being perswaded hee was impenetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:
<hi>Euphorbus</hi> easily induced by temptation, as pretending
to establish a new Monarch, doth oppose and kill this euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
deluded King: A generall approbation doth thanke his
pollicy, which made a finall <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of madnesse; and so
reuenge is pacified.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>