<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Ant. Holborne in commendation
of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111843_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07753</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18133</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111843</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Ant. Holborne in commendation
of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and easie introduction to practicall musicke : set downe in forme of a dialogue: deuided into three partes, the first teacheth to sing with all things necessary for the knowledge of pricktsong. The second treateth of descante and to sing two parts in one vpon a plainsong or ground, with other things necessary for a descanter. The third and last part entreateth of composition of three, foure, fiue or more parts with many profitable rules to that effect. With new songs of, 2. 3. 4. and .5 [sic] parts. By Thomas Morley, Batcheler of musick, &amp; one of the gent. of hir Maiesties Royall Chappell</title>
                 <author>Morley, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Hoskins, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 183, 35 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Ant. Holborne in commendation
of the Author.</head>
   <l>TO whom can ye, sweet <hi>Muses,</hi> more with right</l>
   <l>Impart your paines to praise his worthy skill,</l>
   <l>Then vnto him that taketh sole delight,</l>
   <l>In your sweet art, therewith the world to fill.</l>
   <l>Then turne your tunes to <hi>Morleys</hi> worthy prayse,</l>
   <l>And sing of him that sung of you so long:</l>
   <l>His name with laud and with dew honour rayse,</l>
   <l>That hath made you the matter of his song.</l>
   <l>Like <hi>Orpheus</hi> sitting on high Thracian hill,</l>
   <l>That beasts and mountaines to his ditties drew,</l>
   <l>So doth be draw with his sweete musicks skill</l>
   <l>Men to attention of his Science trew.</l>
   <l>Wherein it seemes that <hi>Orpheus</hi> he exceeds,</l>
   <l>For he wyld beasts, this men with pleasure feeds.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>