<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument of the COMOEDIE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111416_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13611</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23895</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument of the COMOEDIE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Andria : the first comoedie of Terence, in English. A furtherance for the attainment vnto the right knowledge, &amp; true proprietie, of the Latin tong. And also a commodious meane of help, to such as haue forgotten Latin, for their speedy recouering of habilitie, to vnderstand, write, and speake the same. Carefully translated out of Latin, by Maurice Kyffin</title>
                 <author>Terence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flasket, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Linley, Paul.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Argument of the COMOEDIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hremes &amp; Phania (two brethren) were citizens of Athens:
which Chremes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his iourney into Asia, left Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula (as then his
onely daughter) to the charge and safe keeping of his brother Phania: but not
long after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there ensued in Greece so great sturre and
tumult of warre, as that Phania determining to folow his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into Asia,
did therefore embarke himselfe (and his little Neece Passibula) for that
voyage: But, a sore tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest arising, he susteined shipwrack in
such sort, as both he and his forenamed Neece, were cast on shore at
the Ile of Andros, where he chaunced into the house of a certain dweller in
that countrie, by whome he was gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued and relieued, &amp; in whose
house shortly after he died. After whose death, the good man of the
house changed the name of the young childe, calling her by the name of
Glycerie: and when he had by the space of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine yeeres, brought her vp
with like care, and in like knowledge, as he did bring vp his owne daughter
Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis, he likewise ended his lyfe. Chrysis (perceiuing her selfe
bereft of Father and friends, &amp; being also pinched with pouertie) toke
Glycerie with her, and sayled to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. In which Citie, during a small
season, she earned her liuing by Wooll and making Cloth: but afterward,
being haunted by certain youths, who fed her with guifts and faire promises,
she (ouercome by those men, and by these meanes) yelded the vse of her
bodie for gaine. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other younkers, Pamphilus the sonne of Simo, a well
minded young man, dyd oftentimes resort to the house, not for her sake,
but onely for the great loue and <pb facs="10"/> liking he bare vnto Glycerie: by
whome Glycerie, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while,) proouing to be with childe, he made
faithfull promis vnto her, that he would make her his wife. By this time,
Chremes (hauing long since returned home to Athens,) had an other daughter
become marriageable, named Philumena, whome he much desired to match in
marriage with Pamphilus, in respect of the good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that generally went
of him: Wherevpon, by his owne seeking vnto Simo for the same, the match
with consent of both parents, is made vp, &amp; vtterly vnawares vnto
Pamphilus, a day is appointed for the marriage.</p>
   <p>In the meane season Chrysis dyeth, by which meanes Simo came
first to knowledge that his sonne is in loue. For at the buriall of
Chrysis, Glycerie for pure griefe and sorrow being about to haue throwen
her selfe into the fire with the coars, was so speedely stayed, and
so louingly recomforted by Pamphilus, as thereby their wonted loue and
familiaritie was manifestly bewrayed. Herevpon Chremes reuoked his former
offer, declaring how he had certaine intelligence that Pamphilus vsed this
strange minion for his wife: little thinking that she whome he termed by
so vile a name, was his owne daughter.</p>
   <p>Pamphilus (at length) perceiuing that Chremes brake of the
marriage, was very ioyfull: Simo on the other side was exceeding sorry. The
day once appointed for the wedding, is come. Simo therfore of meere craft and
pollicie (determining to feele the mynde of his sonne Pamphilus) pretendeth
notwithstanding all this, that the marriage shall bee made out of hand:
with intent that if his sonne should refuse to marrye, that thereby hee
might haue good occasion to reprehend him, which till then hee could not well
doo. But contrarywise, yf his sonne should consent to marry, than hee
hoped to obteyne his desire at Chremes hands, and so to make vp 
<pb facs="10"/> the marriage presently. Therefore meeting with his sonne,
(who little minded any such matter) he spake thus vnto him: Pamphilus, go
home and make thee ready, thou must be married to day.</p>
   <p>Pamphilus soddeinly amased with these woords, knew neither
what to say, nor what to doo: But Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus (a craftie knauish seruant)
smelling out the drift and deuise of the olde man, comes to Pamphilus and
shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by circumstance of tyme, place, and persons, the great
vnlikelyhood of the marriage.</p>
   <p>In this very time Carinus (a young man of Athens) exceedingly
enamoured on Philumena, and heareing she should be furthwith married vnto
Pamphilus, dyd therefore come to him and prayed him for Gods sake, as he
tendred his lyfe, that either he would not marry her at all, or at least
wise, that he would put of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage for a few dayes longer.</p>
   <p>Pamphilus on the other side being wonderfully in loue with
Glycerie, desires nothing more than that he might haue quite and cleane
ryddance of this same mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage pretended for him, and so made aunswere
vnto Carinus accordingly. To this ende therefore, Dauus aduiseth Pamphilus to
saye vnto his father, that he is willing to marry (though he ment nothing
lesse) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereby both to satisfie the minde of Simo, and withall
to continue still loue and familiaritie with Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, hauing no
mistrust in the world that Chremes would euer be induced to match his
daughter Philume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vnto Pamphilus, whome he had once before reiected for his
sonne in lawe. But Pamphilus folowing this deuise of Dauus, is notably
ouertaken, when and where he least thought of: for Simo so much preuailed
with Chremes by earnest intreatie, as that contrarie to all expectation, the
marriage matter is brought to that passe, euen to haue bene made out of
hand: <pb facs="11"/> so as Dauus, hauing no other meane to shift of this
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, causeth the childe, whereof Glycerie the same day was deliuered,
to be layed before Simoes dore: which, when Chremes saw, and vnderstoode to
be the childe of Pamphilus, he straight way falls of againe from perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
of the marriage. Heerevpon ensueth great sturre and hurleburly, till that
by the comming of Crito from Andros to Athens, (by meere chaunce) euen the
whole difficulty of the Comoedie is dissolued: for thorough him, Chremes
comes to certaine knowledge that Glycerie is his owne daughter, sometime
called by the name of Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibula: And so with great ioy and contentation
of all parts, he giues Glycerie in marriage vnto Pamphilus, and Philumena to
Carinus.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Some wil haue it consist of 4. &amp;
thē the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first.</note>¶The Comoedie consists of
three parts: to witte: 
<q>
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </q> Which in Latin are
signified by these three woords: 
<q>
         <hi>Propositio, Intentio, Conuersio.</hi>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.
<hi>Propositio.</hi>
      </note>The first, is <hi>Proposition,</hi> conteining the
first Act and the beginning of variety of Speakers, some entring, some
remaining on the Stage, and some departing away.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.
<hi>Intentio.</hi>
      </note>The second is <hi>Intention</hi> or <hi>Full
Sway,</hi> conteyning the growing on &amp; continuance of all the hot sturre,
trouble and difficult state of the Comoedie.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.
<hi>Conuersio.</hi>
      </note>The third and last part, is <hi>Conuersion,</hi> in
the which all is turned to a ioyfull ende, and the whole matter made
knowen.</p>
   <p>By heedfull reading, and diligent marking, the due
<hi>Decorum</hi> obserued by Terence in his Comoedies, the <pb facs="11"/>
scholer shall gather verie much pleasure and profit, as for example, in
this Comoedie of Andria, he opposeth seuerall speakers, of seuerall
natures, and contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions, one to another: as, Simo beeing hot and
testy, is opposed vnto Chremes, a milde and moderate man. Pamphilus, a
stayed and shamefast young man, is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto Carinus, a harebraind
fellow voyde of discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Dauus, a slye and suttle seruant, is
opposed vnto Byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, a slouthfull and rechles fellow. Mysis, a sober
maide, is opposed vnto Lesbia, a drunken Gossip. Crito, honest and
poore, is opposed vnto Chrysis, dishonest and rich.</p>
   <p>These persōs, are of set purpose thus placed by Terence,
to the end that the vndue demeanor in the one, may the sooner be seen by
the contrarie in the other.</p>
   <p>Very singuler also is the eloquence of the Author, in
setting downe the moane and complaint of Pamphilus, The Narration,
Consultation, and Reprehension of Simo: From which places, are to be
learned choice woords, apt figures, and right order of speaking Latin.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>