<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONEST AND gentylle readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1538</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111493_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21313</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONEST AND gentylle readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dictionary of syr Thomas Eliot knyght</title>
                 <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1538</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>424 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Linguistics and philology</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>TO THE HONEST AND gentylle readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O THE MORE playne declaration of these tables folowynge, briefely compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of the bokes of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orgius Agricola, and Rober<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus Senalis, whiche wrate last and most exactly of poises &amp; measures, It shal be expedient to the reder to haue in remembrance these thynges folowynge.</p>
   <p>FYRST whan he redeth in any boke of poyses, coynes, and measures, to consyder whither they be of Rome, Grece, or of the Hebrues, and than to seke the columnes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the which those countreys ar written, &amp; there shal he fynd that which he seketh for.</p>
   <p>Also to remember the valuation of all our coyns, as they be rated at this present time, and accompt .xii. <abbr>d.</abbr> to a shylling .xi. grotes &amp; ii. <abbr>d.</abbr> to an oūce .xx. s. to a pound .xiii. s. iiii. <abbr>d.</abbr> to a marke .xii. ounces to a pounde, as well of measure as of poyse.</p>
   <p>Moreouer that euery ounce or ynch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure quadrate as a dye, is diuyded into the same minutes or porciōs, that an oūce poise is, and .xii. ounces in measure, concernynge vesselles, is not callydde there a foote, but a pounde measure.</p>
   <p>Also that the vesselles or receptories are first counted by measure, bicause that therin it is more certain than poise, as a poise ofice of honye is not in quantitie lyke to a poyse ounce of wyne or oyle. wherfore <hi>Vncia red</hi> in old authors without addicion of <hi>pondus,</hi> is to be taken for the measure ounce, as ye shall fynde more aboundantly in the bokes of the sayde Agricola and Senalis.</p>
   <p>Item in the redyng the mesures of greke, yf ye fynde them not here declared, ye must alway remember, that the englishe pynte is xxiiii. ounce measures, the pynte of Rome callyd Sextarius, is .xx. ounce mesures, the greke pynte callyd also Sextarius, and the hebrue pynte callid Log, is but .xviii. ounce mesures, &amp; accordyng to that rate, ye muste make calculation in conferrynge togyther all other measures.</p>
   <p>And this I trust shall at this tyme suffise, for the vnderstanding of this matter, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by the reders, as well of olde hystories, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Tulli, as also ancient phisitions, &amp; the bokes of holy scripture callyd the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, shall apprehende more vnderstandinge, with singular dilectatiō and plesure. For the whiche I shall require them to giue praises to god, of whom it hath chiefely proceded, and thankes to our most excellent souerayn lorde, by whose most gracious comfort and ayde, I haue perfourmed it, and to pray to god to gyue me grace and tyme, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyshe suche warkes, as I haue purposed for the cōmoditie honour and weale of this my naturall countrey.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>