<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his truly deserving friend, Captaine IOHN SMITH.</title>
           <author>Tanner, Salo.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111906_Fr1_15</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12471</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his truly deserving friend, Captaine IOHN SMITH.</title>
                 <author>Tanner, Salo.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true travels, adventures, and observations of Captaine Iohn Smith, in Europe, Asia, Affrica, and America, from anno Domini 1593. to 1629 : His accidents and sea-fights in the straights; his service and stratagems of warre in Hungaria, Transilvania, Wallachia, and Moldavia, against the Turks, and Tartars ... After how he was taken prisoner by the Turks, sold for a slave ... and escaped ... Together with a continuation of his generall History of Virginia, Summer-Iles, New England, and their proceedings, since 1624. to this present 1629; as also of the new plantations of the great river of the Amazons, the iles of St. Christopher, Mevis, and Barbados in the West Indies. All written by actuall authours, whose names you shall finde along the history</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Reeve (Reave), James.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 60 pages, folded plates, illustrations (engraving, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To his truly deserving friend, Captaine IOHN SMITH.</head>
   <l>CAn one please all? there's none from <hi>Censure</hi> free,</l>
   <l>To looke for't then it were absurd in thee;</l>
   <l>It's easie worke to censure sweetest Layes,</l>
   <l>Where <hi>Ignorance</hi> is <hi>Iudge</hi> thou'd have no praise:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Wisdome</hi> I know will mildly judge of all,</l>
   <l>Envious hearts, tongues, pennes, are dippt in Gall.</l>
   <l>Proud malignant times will you now bring forth</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Monsters</hi> at least to snarle at others worth;</l>
   <l>O doe not so, but wisely looke on him</l>
   <l>That wrought such <hi>Honours</hi> for his <hi>Countries King</hi>▪</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> thou hast wonne the field,</l>
   <l>The great <hi>Bashaw</hi> his <hi>Courage</hi> thou hast quel'd;</l>
   <l>In the <hi>Hungarian warre</hi> thou'st shewd thy <hi>Arts,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Prou'd thy <hi>Selfe</hi> a <hi>Souldier</hi> true in all parts:</l>
   <l>Thy <hi>Armes</hi> are deckt with that thy <hi>Sword</hi> hath wonne,</l>
   <l>Which mallice can't out-weare till day be done:</l>
   <l>For three proud <hi>Turks</hi> in single fight thou'st slue,</l>
   <l>Their Heads <hi>adorne</hi> thy <hi>Armes,</hi> for witnesse true;</l>
   <l>Let <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Neptune</hi> both with <hi>Pregnant</hi> wit,</l>
   <l>Extoll thy due deserts, He pray for it.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>SALO. TANNER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>