<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Post scr.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111264_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12782</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23089</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111264</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Post scr.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The shepheardes calender : conteyning tvvelue æglogues proportionable to the twelue monethes. Entitled to the noble and vertuous gentleman most worthy of all titles both of learning and cheualrie M. Philip Sidney</title>
                 <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 52 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <head>Post scr.</head>
   <p>NOvv I trust M. Haruey, that vpon sight of your speciall frends and fellow Poets doings, or els for enuie of so many vnworthy Quidams, vvhich catch at the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lond, vvhich to you alone is devve, you vvill be persvvaded to pluck out of the hateful darknesse. those so many excellent English poemes of yours, vvhich lye hid, and bring thē forth to eternall light. Trust me you doe both them great wrong, in depriuing them of the desired sonne, and also your selfe, in smoothering your deserued prayses, and all mer generally, in withholding from them so diuine pleasures, which they might conceiue o your gallant English verses, as they haue already doen of your Latine Poemes, which it my opinion both for inuention aud Elocution are very delicate, and superexcellent. An thus againe, I take my leaue of my good Mayster Haruey. from my lodging at London thys 10. of Aprill. 1579.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>