<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Michael Phettiplace, William Phettiplace, &amp;
Richard Wisfing, Gentlemen, and
Souldiers vnder Captaine Smiths
Command: In his deserued
honor for his Worke,
and worth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111023_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22788</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111023</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Michael Phettiplace, William Phettiplace, &amp;
Richard Wisfing, Gentlemen, and
Souldiers vnder Captaine Smiths
Command: In his deserued
honor for his Worke,
and worth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A description of New England: or The obseruations, and discoueries, of Captain Iohn Smith (admirall of that country) in the north of America, in the year of our Lord 1614 : with the successe of sixe ships, that went the next yeare 1615; and the accidents befell him among the French men of warre: with the proofe of the present benefit this countrey affoords: whither this present yeare, 1616, eight voluntary ships are gone to make further tryall</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke (Clerke), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 61, 5 pages, folded plates, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>Michael Phettiplace, William Phettiplace, &amp;
Richard Wisfing, Gentlemen, and
Souldiers vnder Captaine Smiths
Command: In his deserued
honor for his Worke,
and worth.</head>
   <l>VVHy may not we in this Worke haue our Mite,</l>
   <l>That had our share in each black day and night,</l>
   <l>When thou <hi>Virginia</hi> foildst, yet kept'st vnstaind;</l>
   <l>And held'st the King of <hi>Paspeheh</hi> enchaind.</l>
   <l>Thou all alone this <hi>Saluage</hi> sterne didst take.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Pamunkes</hi> king wee saw thee captiue make</l>
   <l>Among seauen hundred of his stoutest men,</l>
   <l>To murther thee and vs resolued; when</l>
   <l>Fast by the hand thou ledst this Saluage grim,</l>
   <l>Thy Pistoll at his breast to gouerne him:</l>
   <l>Which did infuse such awe in all the rest</l>
   <l>(Sith their drad Soueraigne thou had'st so distrest)</l>
   <l>That thou and wee (poore sixteene) safe retir'd</l>
   <l>Vnto our helplesse <hi>ships.</hi> Thou (thus admir'd)</l>
   <l>Didst make proud <hi>Powhatan,</hi> his subiects send</l>
   <l>To <hi>lames</hi> his Towne, thy censure to attend:</l>
   <l>And all <hi>Virginia's</hi> Lords, and pettie Kings,</l>
   <l>Aw'd by thy vertue, crouch, and Presents brings</l>
   <l>To gaine thy grace; so dreaded thou hast beene:</l>
   <l>And yet a heart more milde is seldome seene;</l>
   <l>So, making Valour Vertue, really;</l>
   <l>Who hast nought in thee counterfet, or slie;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>
If in the sleight bee not the truest art,</l>
   <l>That makes men famoused for faire desert.</l>
   <l>Who saith of thee, this sauors of vaine-glorie,</l>
   <l>Mistakes both thee and vs, and this true storie.</l>
   <l>If it bee ill in Thee, so well to doe;</l>
   <l>Then, is it ill in Vs, to praise thee too.</l>
   <l>But, if the first bee well done; it is well,</l>
   <l>To say it doth (if so it doth) excell!</l>
   <l>Praise is the guerdon of each deere desert,</l>
   <l>Making the praised act the praised part</l>
   <l>With more alacritie: <hi>Honours</hi> Spurre is <hi>Praise;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Without which, it (regardlesse) soone decaies.</l>
   <l>And for this paines of thine wee praise thee rather,</l>
   <l>That future Times may know who was the father</l>
   <l>Of this rare Worke (<hi>New England</hi>) which may bring</l>
   <l>Praise to thy God, and profit to thy King.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>