<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the constant, mighty, and wor∣thie friends, the Commities, Assistants vnto his Maiesties Councell for the Colonie in VIRGINEA-BRITANNIA.</title>
           <author>Strachey, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111283_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13057</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23350</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111283</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the constant, mighty, and wor∣thie friends, the Commities, Assistants vnto his Maiesties Councell for the Colonie in VIRGINEA-BRITANNIA.</title>
                 <author>Strachey, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>For the colony in Virginea Britannia. Lavves diuine, morall and martiall, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Virginia</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 41, that is 89), 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the constant, mighty, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie friends, the Commit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies, Assistants vnto his Maiesties Councell for the Colonie in VIRGINEA-BRITANNIA.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I went forth vpon this voyage, (Right worthy Gentlemen) true it is, I held it a seruice of dutie, (during the time of my vnprofitable seruice, and purpose of stay in the Colonie, for which way else might I adde vnto the least hight of so Heroicke and pious a building) to propose vnto my self to be (though an vnable) Remembrancer of all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, occurrences, and vndertakings thereunto, <hi>aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiall:</hi> In most of which since the time our right famous sole Gouernour then; now Lieutenant Generall Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gates</hi> Knight, after the ensealing of his Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion hasted to our fleete in the West, there staying for him, I haue both in the <hi>Bermudas,</hi> and since in <hi>Virginea</hi> beene a sufferer and an eie witnesse, and the full storie of both in due time shall consecrate vnto your viewes, as vnto whom by right it appertaineth, being vowed patrones of a worke, and enterprise so great, then which no obiect nor action (the best of bests) in these times, may carry with it the like fame, honour, or goodnesse.</p>
   <p>Howbet since many impediments, as yet must detaine such my obseruations in the shadow of darknesse, vntill I shall be able to deliuer them perfect vnto your iudgements,


<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> I shall prouoke and challenge) I do in the meanetime present a transcript of the <hi>Toparchia</hi> or State of those duties, by which the<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> Colonie stands regulated and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that such may receiue due chicke, who maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and desperately heretoforè haue censured of it, and by examining of which they may be right sorie so to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulked from vs as if we liued there lawlesse, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to our Countrey, or obseruancie of Religion to God.</p>
   <p>Nor let it afflict the patience of such full and well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed iudgements, vnto whom many of these constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Lawes Diuine or Marshall may seeme auncient and common, since these grounds are the same constant, Asterismes, and starres, which must guide all that trauell in th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se perplexed wayes, and paths of publique affairs; &amp; whosoeuer shall wander from them, shall but decline a hazardous and by-course to bring their purposes to good effect.</p>
   <p>Nor let another kind quarrell or traduce the Printing of them to be deliuered in particular to officers and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Souldiers for their better instruction, especially vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Company for the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, vnsetled and vnfurnished, since we know well how short our memories are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and vnwilling to giue sto<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge to the better things, and such things as limit and bound mankind in their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessariest duties.</p>
   <p>For which it transcends not the reach of his vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, who is conuersant, if but as for a festiuall exercise, (euery <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Moone</hi>) in reading of a booke, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and ed<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cts for manners or ciuill duties, haue vsually beene fixed vpon ingrauen Tables, for the Commons dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ouerlooke: a custome more especially cherished by


<pb facs="5"/>
those not many yeeres since in Magnuza who haue resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as I m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> say) after so great a floud and rage of abused goodness<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, all Lawes, literature and Vertue againe, which had well nigh perished, had not the force of piety and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred reason remaining in the bosomes of some few, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it selfe against the fury of so great a calamity, of whom it is an vndenyable truth, that the meanes and way wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they reduced the generall def<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ction, was by printing thereby so houlding vppe those inuolued principles, and Instructions wherein (as in a mirror, the blind and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering iudgement might suruaye, what those know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges were, which taught both how to gouerne, and how to obey, (the end indeed of sociable mankinds Creation) since without order and gouernment, (the onely hendges, whereupon, not onely the safety, but the being of all states doe turne and depend) what society may possible subsist, or commutatiue goodnesse be practised. And thus law<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s being published, euery common eye may take suruey of their duties, and carrying away the tenour of the same, meditate, &amp; bethinke how safe, quiet, and comely it is to be honest, iust, and ciuill.</p>
   <p>And indeed all the sacred powers of knowledge and wisedome are strengthned by these two waies, either by a kind of diuine nature, which his happy creation hath bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him with, the vertue whereof comprehendeth, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeth and vnderstandeth the truth and cleerenesse of all things: or by instruction and tradition from others, which must improue his wants, and by experience render him perfect, awaking him in all seasons a vigilant obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of ciuill cautions and ordinances, an excellent reason inforcing no lesse vnto the knowledge of him that will shine a starre in the firmament, where good men moue,


<pb facs="6"/>
and that is, that no man doth more ill then hee that is ignorant.</p>
   <p>For the auoiding of which, and to take away the plea of <hi>I did not know</hi> in him that shall exorbitate or goe aside with any delinquencie which may be dangerous in exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or execution, albeit true it is how hee is indeede the good and honest man that will be good, and to that needeth fewe other precepts. It hath appeared most necessary vnto our present <hi>Ethnarches</hi> Deputy Gouernor <hi>Sir Thomas Dale</hi> knight Marshall, not onely to exemplifie the olde Lawes of the Colony, by Sir <hi>Thomas Gates</hi> published &amp; put in execution by our Lord Generall <hi>Laware</hi> during his time one whole yeere of being there, but by vertue of his office, to prescribe and draw new, with their due pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltyes, according vnto which wee might liue in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony iustly one with another, and performe the generall seruice for which we first came thither, and with so great charges &amp; expences, are now setled &amp; maintained there.</p>
   <p>For my paines, and gathering of them, as I know they will be right welcom to such young souldiers in the Colony who are desirous to learne and performe their duties, so I assure me, that by you I shall bee encouraged to go on in the discharge of greater offices by examining and fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my good intention in this, and in what else my poore knowledge or faithfulnesse may enable me to be a seruant in so beloued and sacred a businesse. And euen so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to your still most abstract, graue and vnsatisfied carefulnesse, both it and my selfe, I wish returne of seuen fold into such his well inspired bosome, who hath lent his helping hand vnto this new <hi>Sion. From my lodging in the blacke Friers.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>At your best pleasures, either to returne vnto the Colony, or to pray for the successe of it heere.</hi> WILLIAM STRACHEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>