<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the Queenes Maidens OF HONOR.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111807_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15498</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25764</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the Queenes Maidens OF HONOR.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tragedie of Tancred and Gismund : Compiled by the gentlemen of the Inner Temple, and by them presented before her Maiestie. Newly reuiued and polished according to the decorum of these daies. By R.W</title>
                 <author>R. W. (Robert Wilmot)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Robinson, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A Preface to the Queenes Maidens OF HONOR.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>FLowers of prime, pearles couched all in gold,</l>
      <l>Light of our daies that glads the fainting hearts</l>
      <l>Of them that shall your shining geamls behold,</l>
      <l>Salue of each sore, recure of inward smarts,</l>
      <l>In whom Vertue and Beautie striueth so,</l>
      <l>As neither yeelds, behold here for your gaine</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Gismonds</hi> vnluckie loue, her fault, her wo</l>
      <l>And death, at last her cruell Father slaine</l>
      <l>Through his mishap, and though you do not see,</l>
      <l>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t reade and rew their wofull Tragedie.</l>
      <l>So Ioue, as your high vertues done deserue,</l>
      <l>Grant you such pheeres, as may your vertues serue</l>
      <l>With like vertues, and blisfull Venus send</l>
      <l>Vnto your happie loues an happie end.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Another to the same.</head>
      <l>
         <hi>GIsmond,</hi> that whilome liu'de her fathers ioy</l>
      <l>And died his death, now dead, doth as she may</l>
      <l>By vs praie you to pittie her annoy.</l>
      <l>And to requite the same, doth humbly pray,</l>
      <l>Heauens to forefend your loues from like decay.</l>
      <l>The faithfull Earle doth also make request,</l>
      <l>Wishing those worthie knights whom ye imbrace,</l>
      <l>The constant truth that lodged in his breast.</l>
      <l>His hartie loue, not his vnhappie case,</l>
      <l>Befall to such astriumph in your grace.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>The King praies pardon of his cruell hest,</l>
      <l>And for amends, desires it may suffice,</l>
      <l>That by his bloud he warneth all the rest</l>
      <l>Of fond fathers, that they in kinder wise,</l>
      <l>Intreat the Iewels where their comfort lies.</l>
      <l>We, as their messengers, beseech ye al</l>
      <l>On their behalfes, to pittie all their smarts,</l>
      <l>And for our selues, (although the worth be small)</l>
      <l>We praie ye, to accept our humble hearts</l>
      <l>Auoud to serue with praier and with praise,</l>
      <l>Your Honors, all vnworthie other waies.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>