<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111401_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23766</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iuniper lecture : With the description of all sorts of women, good, and bad: from the modest to the maddest, from the most civil, to the scold rampant, their praise and dispraise compendiously related. Also the authors advice how to tame a shrew, or vexe her</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Lee (Ley), William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 167, 188-236 pages, plates, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <l>
      <hi>I</hi> Sing the praise and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praise of that Sex</l>
   <l>That gives men cause of comfort, or to vex:</l>
   <l>His joy or care, his blessing or his curse.</l>
   <l>His weale, his woe, his Saint, or Divell, or worse.</l>
   <l>You vertuous worthy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (few that be)</l>
   <l>I know you'le be so good to pardon me;</l>
   <l>And yet what pardon need I crave of them,</l>
   <l>Whom I will not offend, nor yet condemne.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>If women that are bad I doe offend,</l>
   <l>It is the cause why these my lines are pend.</l>
   <l>And if they be not angry, I dare say,</l>
   <l>That all my labour's lost, and cast away.</l>
   <l>Thus (free from feare or flattery) on I runne,</l>
   <l>To please or displease, when my taske is done.</l>
   <l>Our Grandam <hi>Eve</hi> (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence) I omit,</l>
   <l>(But yet she plaid the foole, for want of wit)</l>
   <l>And her weak follies incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity,</l>
   <l>She left unto her fraile po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>It is the earthly portion that we have:</l>
   <l>From womb, to tombe, from cradle to the grave.</l>
   <l>A woman was sins mother, but another</l>
   <l>Most blessed woman was a Saviours mother.</l>
   <l>And therefore it may well be understood,</l>
   <l>As millions may bee bad, there's thousands good.</l>
   <l>As some are <hi>Furies,</hi> that do men torment,</l>
   <l>So some are <hi>Fairies,</hi> that gives some content:</l>
   <l>As some are <hi>Destinies,</hi> and fatall shrowes,</l>
   <l>(Like <hi>Clotho, Lachasis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Atropos</hi>)</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="8"/>To spin and reele our lives with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ares and moanes.</l>
   <l>And cut our threads at last with sighes and groanes</l>
   <l>Yet for our comfort there are <hi>Graces</hi> three</l>
   <l>T'affront those <hi>Fates</hi> (<hi>faith, hope,</hi> and <hi>charity.</hi>)</l>
   <l>As there are witches that in mischiefe swell,</l>
   <l>And <hi>Syrens, Furies, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies,</hi> Hagges of Hell:</l>
   <l>Yet <hi>Prudence, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Justice, Fortitude,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Are vertues with such mighty force endu'd,</l>
   <l>That those that doe pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse them are so arm'd,</l>
   <l>They cannot bee by Hell, or Hell-hounds harm'd.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>