<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to all true Christi∣ans, and loyall subiects.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111364_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13171</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23466</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111364</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to all true Christi∣ans, and loyall subiects.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blessings on Mount Gerizzim, and the curses on Movnt Ebal. Or, The happie estate of Protestants : compared with the miserable estate of papists vnder the Popes tyrannie. By M.S. Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Hebb, Andrew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 384 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface to all true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and loyall subiects.</head>
   <p>HOw often the Spaniard and Pope, and their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents haue attempted by secret practises to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inate the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> I doubt not (my deare countrimen and friends) but you haue heard. The rebellion in the North-part of <hi>England, an. 1569.</hi> the pretence of the Duke of <hi>Guise, an. 1584.</hi> the diuers rebellions and troubles of <hi>Ireland:</hi> the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises of <hi>Parrie, Patrick Collein, Williams</hi> and <hi>York</hi> to kil the Queen: of <hi>Lopes</hi> &amp; <hi>Squire</hi> to impoyson ber: of <hi>Babing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and <hi>Ballard,</hi> and diuers other Masse-priests, and Masse-louing Papists to subuert the State, are yet fresh in memory. And to forbeare to speake of such secret practises, they haue endeuoured by open warres also to preuaile against the State. In the yeare 1588. they prouided against <hi>England,</hi> not onely great land-forces, but also a great fleete, in their owne conceit inuincible, yet by Gods grace easily vanquished and disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. Likewise <hi>anno 1597</hi> and <hi>1598.</hi> they made two attempts, or rather offers, of some enterprise against the State. In the first one <hi>D. Stillington</hi> and other Masse-priests English and Spanish miscaried, the Spanish fleete being wracked on the rockes of their owne country, so that they could not come to sing Masse in <hi>England.</hi> The other was disappointed by stormes and contrary winds, so that no effect came of it.</p>
   <p>The noise of these preparations and menaces comming into <hi>England,</hi> and being bruited abroade, partly by letters, and partly by a proud proclamation set forth in print by the <hi>Adelantado</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> wherein he plainly discouereth, that
<pb facs="6"/>
he meant no lesse then to cut all our throates if he could: it is no maruell if the State, and diuers men well affected to their countrey, did prepare themselues to make resistance. Among the res̄t Sir <hi>Francis Hastings,</hi> a man of auncient nobilitie, and one that hath adorned the honour of his parentage with excellent vertues, and namely with true pietie, loue of his countrey, fortitude and magnanimitie, scorning to heare, that so base a rabble of <hi>Marranes</hi> and <hi>Bisognos</hi> as were assembled first at <hi>Lisbone,</hi> and then at the <hi>Groyne,</hi> should either talke or thinke of the conquest of <hi>England,</hi> which the <hi>Adelantado</hi> in his bragging <hi>Rodomonts</hi> stile did threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, he armeth himselfe, and prepareth his friends and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen to make resistance. Perceiuing also the securitie of some, and slacknesse of others, especially such as were tainted with the pestilent infection of Italian atheisme, or Spanish Marranisme, but commonly titled Cacolike or popish reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; he publisheth a little treatise, called <hi>A watch-word,</hi> giuing warning to the secure, and stirring vp such as seemed euill affected, to resist manfully, and to withstand the Spanish incrochments and pretences.</p>
   <p>This booke crossing the desseines of <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> and his consorts, who by all meanes sought to set <hi>England</hi> in combustion, that they might triumph in the ashes, and sing Masse in the funerals of their natiue countrey; we may perceiue by the sequele, that it touched his cause and faction very nearely, and therefore was taken by him very tenderly. For presently he taketh pen in hand, and writeth a most scornefull and bitter treatise against her Maiesties procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, against Religion and all that professe it, railing against Sir <hi>Francis</hi> and the professors of the truth, and commending in the best sort he could, both the professed enemies, and the secret vnderminers of the State. Wherein, if we would but note the mans singular impudencie, or rather his audacious
<pb facs="6"/>
foolerie, it were argument sufficient to confound all his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. For at what time the <hi>Spaniard</hi> lay with forces at the <hi>Groyne,</hi> and by a Proclamation set forth in print, threatned fire and sword against the Realme; <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> like a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous traitor, in his <hi>Ward-word</hi> talketh of nothing but peace, and would make vs beleeue, that both the Pope and Spaniards are our good friends. Where Iesuites, and Masse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priests, and malcontent Papists were brewing of sedition, and preparing themselues to ioyne with forreine forces: this good fellow would make vs beleeue, that traitors are good friends, and that there was no hurt by them meant to the Queene or State. Finally, this babling <hi>Warder</hi> doth addresse all his discourse to the Lords of the Councell, and chiefe dealers in matters of State; albeit the same tended wholly to the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the State.</p>
   <p>And yet when I consider the practises of the enemies of the State, I must cōfesse that he had great reason to enter into this shamelesse course. For albeit there was no colour of truth in his discourse, yet he supposed, if the same were shewed to her Maiestie, that it would make her stay her preparatiues. He thought also, it would proue a faire pretence to those that were loth to spend their money, to forbeare to make resistance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the enemy. Further, he saw that the same would bleare mens eyes, while both forreine enemies and secret traitors sought to cut our throates. And finally, the same being full of railing, scorning and scurrilitie, he doubted not but the same would deterre others, or at least make them slow to take vpon them the defence of the common cause. For what man considering the smal encouragement that forward men did find at the hands of friends, and the rude entertainment they receiue at the hands of enemies, would not leaue the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of the State to those, that haue most interest in publike gouernement?</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>All this notwithstanding, sir <hi>Francis</hi> considering the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that Christians haue to maintaine sincere religion, &amp; that bindeth true harted subiects to defend their country, hath published an Apologie, both in defence of the common cause, and of his owne reputation, against the scurrilous and railing libell, which <hi>Parsons</hi> calleth <hi>A warde-word:</hi> expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, no doubt, reward at the hands of God, rather then mā: and respecting rather his own dutie, then the praise of others. But before either the booke came forth, or that I knew the Knights resolution, the impudencie of the man so boldly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling traitors and forreine enemies, together with his singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar arrogancy despising his own nation, and his foolish speakes for the Popes cause stollen out of others, and put forth as his wont is, in his owne name, had extorted from me a reply to his <hi>Wardword.</hi> Which certes might haue bin wel spared, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the sufficiencie of the Knights apologie, if I had seene it before I had ended my reply. For what is there in the <hi>Wardword</hi> worthy of answer, seeing the same consisteth wholy of lies, and patches, and old ends stollen from others, &amp; often refuted before? And what answer can be deuised so slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that counteruaileth not such a hochpotch of words?</p>
   <p>To these replies published by vs, after long silence we see that <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> hath purposed to set forth a reioynder. For we haue already receiued two parts of nine, but so fraught with calumniations and lies, malicious and scornful termes, odious and filthy reproches, that it seemeth he hath spent all his store of poison, and despaireth to perfect the rest.</p>
   <p>This booke, albeit most contemptible, containing nothing but disgracefull matter against her Maiesties proceedings, that is lately deceased, and childish disputes for some few points of poperie, yet haue I thought good to handle; not for any worth, that can be in any such packe of pedlary stuffe, set to sale by this petit merchant, but for that iust occasion is
<pb facs="7"/>
thereby giuen vnto me, to insist vpon the cōmendatiō of our late Queene for her heroical vertues and happy gouernment, by this wicked traitor and vnworthy swad wickedly disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and especially for her singular pietie and zeale in resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring religion, and abolishing Poperie. O that she had bene so happy to keepe out the Ministers of Antichrist once expulsed, as at the first to expulse them, and put them out of her king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome! but what by yeelding to intreatie of some about her by this generation foully abused, and what by tolerating of such as were sent in by forreine enemies to practise against her life and kingdome, and what drawne backe by those that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained intelligēce with publike enemies, she was perswaded to slacke execution of lawes, if not to suspend them, to her owne great trouble, and to the hazard of Religion and the State, but that God by his prouidence supplied the defects of mē. By the aduersaries <hi>Warne-word,</hi> I haue also bene warned to discourse of the miserable and dangerous estate both of kings and their subiects, that liue vnder the thraldom of the Pope: and that both in regard of matters of State, and of Religion. Finally, albeit <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> hitherto hath vsed scurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous railing for his warrant &amp; protection against those, that haue dealt with him: and like as a foxe pursued with hounds with the filthy stench of his stile endeuoureth to make them giue ouer the chase; yet I shall so touch him for his impietie, making a iest at Scriptures and Religion, for his scurrilitie railing without wit or modestie, for his doltish ignorance committing most grosse and childish errors, for his lies and forgerie vsing neither respect of truth nor common honestie, that I hope I shall turne his laughing into another note. If I speak roundly to him and his consorts, yet I do not, as he doth, speake falsly. Sharpnes he ought not to mislike, hauing begun this course. Neither can others iustly reproue me, considering my aduersaries audacious impudencie. <hi>Si falsa dicimus</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
(saith <hi>Hilarie) infamis sit sermo maledicus. Si verò vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersa</hi>
      <note place="margin">Contra Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant.</note>
      <hi>haec manifesta esse ostendimus, nō sumus extra A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicā libertatem &amp; modestiā. If we tell matters false, then let our sharpe speech be infamous. If all we report be manifestly proued, then are we not out of the limites of Apostolical libertie and modestie.</hi> Howbeit what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure is to be required in him; that is to incounter a man of such vnmeasurable and outragious behauiour? In the first booke the honor of her Maiestie late deceassed, and her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the alteration of religion is defended. In the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the grieuances of Christians vnder the Popes gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both in matters of conscience and their temporal estate are plainely discouered. In the last we are to incounter with the ridiculous manner of <hi>Parsons</hi> behauior and writing, left he might per case thinke himselfe wise therein. God turne all to his glorie, to the manifestation of truth, the detection of errors, and the shame of the shamelesse patrons thereof.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>