<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author to his Patron.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111643_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14878</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111643</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author to his Patron.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasant and delightfvl historie of Curan, a prince of Danske, and the fayre Princesse Argentile, daughter and heyre to Adelbright, sometime King of Northumberland : Shewing his first loue vnto her, his succeslesse suite, and the low deiections he vnderwent for her sake. His second loue to the same lady vnknowne, taking her for a poore countrie damsell. She (by reason of the vnkindnesse of King Edell her vnckle and gardian) hauing forsooke the court, and vndertooke the profession of a neatheardes mayde. His constant loue (after her long continued vnkindnes) rewarded with her wished consent, their happie nuptials, and mutuall reioycings, his valour and victorious warre with King Edell: and lastly, his peacefull installment in the kingly throne. Enterlacte with many pritty and pithie prayses of beauty, and other amorous discourses, pleasing, smooth and delightfull. By William Webster</title>
                 <author>Webster, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Higgenbotham, Richard 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Author to his Patron.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>T To wish your hapinesse, if that could giue</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>H Happinesse vnto you, I'de make you blest</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>O On Earth, so long as you on Earth shall liue,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>M May you bee euen of Earths best things possest,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>A And may you ioyes enioy when this life's ended,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>S Such as can but by Saintes be apprehended.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>E Euer may you, and your Posteritee,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>V Vntill dissolu de shall be this mortall frame:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>E Euen till this world shall cease a world to bee,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>R Retaine the lustre of this ancient Name.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>A And be chiefe Pillors to support the same,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>R Repaire and grace that House, from whence to mee</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>D Deriued is (in part) my Pedegree.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>