<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Compositor to the Auctour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111413_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13666</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23952.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Compositor to the Auctour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short inuentory of certayne idle inuentions : the fruites of a close and secret garden of great ease, and litle pleasure. By C.T</title>
                 <author>Thimelthorpe, C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 68, 2 leaves, illustrations (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="compositor_to_the_reader">
   <head>The Compositor to the Auctour.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>AS tyme doth teach and rule the roming mynd,</l>
      <l>So tyme hath brought thy toyling taske to ende:</l>
      <l>As tyme hath licenst vs to seeke and fynd,</l>
      <l>So tyme doth warne vs compt thee as a frend:</l>
      <l>And s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th thou toyes thy Golden tyme to spend</l>
      <l>For Countries sake some profite pure to be,</l>
      <l>Tyme warnes vs all due thankes to render thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who merits fame, renowne, or lasting prayse</l>
      <l>But onely those that toyle in Countryes cause▪</l>
      <l>Who beares the bell in these our dismall dayes,</l>
      <l>But they which can discribe the curious clause?</l>
      <l>Therfore post on my pen and do not pause.</l>
      <l>Till thou hast playd with speede a thankeful part</l>
      <l>To lawde and prayse the Authors willinge h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rt.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="79"/>
      <l>You musing myndes that murmur in delight,</l>
      <l>Come lend your Eares to heare a word or twayne,</l>
      <l>Turne backe one leafe, cast of all hateful spyte,</l>
      <l>To learne this lesson do not now disdayne:</l>
      <l>Do you not know what hateful wordes do gayne?</l>
      <l>Be of good cheere O <hi>Thimelthorpe</hi> I pray,</l>
      <l>Passe not a pin what prating Parrats say.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thou sowed hast the seede for vs to reape,</l>
      <l>We of thy toyle the sugred sweete do taste:</l>
      <l>And sith it comes to all of vs so cheape,</l>
      <l>Therof we wil not wantonly make wast:</l>
      <l>A friendly looke in fayth the wyse will cast,</l>
      <l>For that is all I know that thou dost craue,</l>
      <l>A thousand thankes therfore be sure to haue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For Memus mates, or for their fury fell,</l>
      <l>Passe not a whit, esteeme them as they are:</l>
      <l>Let them goe bathe in Lymbo lake of hell:</l>
      <l>Thy fame shall liue for euer take no care:</l>
      <l>And if that I could learnedly prepare</l>
      <l>My pen to paynt out verses pure and braue,</l>
      <l>Thy name should liue when corps lye cloesd in graue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet I which haue but weake and simple skill,</l>
      <l>Can well discerne the good from bad I know,</l>
      <l>The wyser sort when they haue viewd their s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ll</l>
      <l>And tost this Pamphlet ouer too and froe,</l>
      <l>I ken my selfe what count'naunce they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> show:</l>
      <pb facs="79"/>
      <l>The faultes therein the'il not impute to thee,</l>
      <l>But iudge the Printers presse in part to be,</l>
   </lg>
   <div type="to_the_reader">
      <head>To the Reader,</head>
      <lg>
         <l>Good Reader, syth thou hast perus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e the same,</l>
         <l>And mayst agayne at pleasure thyne behould</l>
         <l>It faultes thou fynd the Auctor do not blame,</l>
         <l>No furious word agaynst him do vnfold,</l>
         <l>But (vse thy pen) in mending ought be bould,</l>
         <l>A wryter sure as yet he is but young,</l>
         <l>Therefore to laude him exercise thy toung.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>So wilt thou win the worthy prayse of all</l>
         <l>That here among graue wryters do remayne.</l>
         <l>Of gentle bloud accompt thee sure wee shall,</l>
         <l>Flye far from taunts which still thy name doth staine,</l>
         <l>And from the face of false enuyous trayne,</l>
         <l>Eke call to mynd what Volumes still we see,</l>
         <l>That safe from faultes can not excused bee.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>The Learned man will see, and litle say,</l>
         <l>The witles w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ght his toung lyes neuer still.</l>
         <l>A good report if wyse men shew alway,</l>
         <l>Let prating peysauntes prattle what they will.</l>
         <l>When they their venim haue spewd out their fyll,</l>
         <l>The wyse will iudge what folly merits then</l>
         <l>And who doth purchase prayse the best of men.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <trailer>Finis, R S.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>