<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worthy and vertuous Ladie; the La: Carey.</title>
           <author>S., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111266_Fr5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12774</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23078</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111266</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worthy and vertuous Ladie; the La: Carey.</title>
                 <author>S., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Complaints : Containing sundrie small poemes of the worlds vanitie. VVhereof the next page maketh mention. By Ed. Sp</title>
                 <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Orwin, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>184 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="74"/>
   <pb facs="74"/>
   <head>To the right worthy and vertuous Ladie; the La: <hi>Carey.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost braue and bountifull La: for so excellent fauours as I haue receiued at your sweet handes, to offer these fewe leaues as in recompence, should be as to offer flowers to the Gods for their diuine benefites. Therefore I haue determined to giue my selfe wholy to you, as quite abandoned from my selfe, and absolutely vowed to your seruices: which in all right is euer held for full recompence of debt or damage to haue the person yeelded. My person I wot wel how little worth it is. But the faithfull minde &amp; humble zeale which I beare vnto your La: may perhaps be more of price, as may please you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and vse the poore seruice thereof; which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth glory to aduance your excellent partes and noble vertues, and to spend it selfe in honouring you: not so much for your great bounty to my self,
<pb facs="75"/>
which yet may not be vnminded; nor for name or kindreds sake by you vouchsafed, beeing also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardable; as for that honorable name, which yee haue by your braue deserts purchast to your self, &amp; spred in the mouths of al mē: vvith vvhich I haue also presumed to grace my verses, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your name to cōmend to the vvorld this smal Poëme, the vvhich beseeching your La: to take in vvorth, and of all things therein according to your vvonted graciousnes to make a milde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, I humbly pray for your happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your La: euer humbly;</hi>
         <hi>E. S.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>