<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A praeface to
the Christian
Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111889_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00283</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10395</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111889</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A praeface to
the Christian
Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and plaine declaration, concerning the desires of all those faithfull ministers, that haue and do seeke for the discipline and reformation of the Church of Englande : which may serue for a iust apologie, against the false accusations and slaunders of their aduersaries</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 148 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A praeface to
the Christian
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy Prophets hauing
oftentymes,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 9. 10.</note> * but searched
vvhen and at vvhat time the
foreseeing spirit of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
vnto them the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
afflictions and troubles
of the church to come; haue
therevpon entered into great lamentations for
the same: And haue not onely vvept and fasted
them selues,<note place="margin">Lamen. 1. 2 3. 4.</note> * but haue compiled for the church
vvhole bookes of lamentations; therein instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
them what vvay to take,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.</note> for appeasing the
fierce wrath of God breaking out against them.
VVhich dutie in semblable maner should novv
long agoe haue beene done of vs, did not the
hope vvee conceiue in the middest of manye
tempestes, confirme vs in such expectation of
her maiestie and her most honourable counsell,
as that according to their clemencie tovvardes
the poore ministers and their families, but most
especially according to their holye and zealous
care, vvhich ought to abound for the cleane dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
out of the Cananites, and planting, hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
pruning, and continuall preseruing of the
Lord his vineyard, from Foxes, yea little Foxes,
<pb facs="3"/>
this ciuill vvar, as a man may say, of the church
vvherein so much of that bloud<note place="margin">Act. 20. 26.</note> * (vvherof Paule
speaketh) is powred to the grounde, shoulde by
their holie and iuste authoritie, fully bee ended.
Now, vvhen as vve at this time, are subiect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moste
vnto all the afflictions vvhich can come
vnto a church, blessed of God vvith such a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
and happie regiment; as to the prophane
scoffing of the *<note place="margin">Neh. 4. 2. 3. 4</note> Hammonits at the buylding of
the church,<note place="margin">Neh. 4. 7.</note> as at a vval vvhich a Fox should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy;
to the conspiracies of the Arrabies and
those of Ashod; to the false<note place="margin">Neh. 6. 5. 6.</note> * charges of sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
contempt of all good lavves and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges,
like to that of Sanballat; yea to the<note place="margin">Neh. 10. 11. 12</note> * pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes
them selues, vndermining, nay reuiling,
displacing, and grieuouslye afflicting the Godly
and learned ministerie, &amp; so consequently pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
the Church vvith that plague vvherby<note place="margin">Ioel. 1. 9.</note> * the
priestes may mourne,<note place="margin">Amos. 8. 11. 12. 13.</note> because there is no offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
and the people perishe, euen the yong men
vvith the famine of hearing the vvorde of God
preached: when I say, we are subiect to al these,
vvee can thinke of no vvaye for reconciling the
brethren at variance, &amp; after a most sure &amp; holy
vnion of both their forces, for a couragious set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
vpon the common aduersary, then the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
peaceable and reasonable vvay following.
VVhich is, that vvhereas both by bookes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
written, and by treatizes latelye and novv
published, it may appeare vve seeke that vvhich
at the least in the iudgement of all true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
hath no small probabilitie (as vve iudge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie)
of trueth out of the scriptures: it maye
please her most excellent maiestie and their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
<pb facs="3"/>
to appoynt on both sides the best learned,
most Godly &amp; moderate men to debate all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
of vvaight betweene them and vs. So
that first vpon sufficient consideration, the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions
to be debated be vvithout all ambiguitie
set downe, the reasons of both sides vvithout all
out-goynges shortly and plainely deliuered in
vvriting each to other, that after vpon sufficient
examination the reasons of both be continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
confirmed and resolued, till eyther by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence
of truth one part yeeld vnto the other;
or the folly and madnes of those vvhich gayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say it, do in equall iudgement become manifest,
in regarde of the contradictions and absurdities
vvhereto they shall bee dryuen by the force of
Gods vvorde. VVhich vvay though it shoulde
come naked vnto vs can not well be refused, but
beeing richly attyred vvith all robes and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
vvhich the scripture giueth vnto the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodicall
assemblyes for such conferences: as
namely that there bee<note place="margin">Act. 15. 7.</note> * much searching of the
trueth by sufficient reasoning vvithout all by
matters, quarrels, euasions and colours vvhatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer,
that there be much<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 13. 32.</note> * order, vvhen the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
of euerye prophet shall be subiect vnto the
spirits of the other prophets, &amp; the iudgement of
al shalbe sufficiently heard, vvithout stopping of
free &amp; sufficient answere, without Lordly carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
away of the matter with no substāce of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
vvhere no authoritie, pregnancie of vvit,
plausible perswasion of mans vvisedome, shall
turn the truth aside, but al shal stand in the<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 4.</note> * eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
demonstration of Gods spirite: lastly that
there be<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 33</note> * peace without all bitternes, reuilinges,
<pb facs="4"/>
suspicions, chargings of men dead &amp; aliue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
affections are mooued, iudgement blinded,
and men driuen as vvith a mighty streame from
the loue of the truth: vvhen it commeth thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned
vve thinke, that vvhich we labor to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
to be so honorable<note place="margin">Act. 14. 16.</note> * not only before God,
but also before men, that none can iudge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise
of it then vve doe. For if any shall obiect,
that the graue authoritie of Archbishops &amp; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppes
shall receiue a checke, whilest they are
brought to deale with those, whome they iudge
fewe, young, vnlearned, and not comparable to
them selues: or that it is a challenge not much
vnlike the Papistes: or lastly, that it shall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall
to the estate of gouerment established:
It maye please their wisedomes vvho are to bee
iudges, to consider what vvee haue to aunsvvere
vnto these things: which, if they haue the truth
of God his word, containe the safest &amp; best way
in such cases, tend to the full quieting of all, and
the remoouing of the plagues vvhich are vppon
vs, and are like dayly further to come, euen from
the cōmon aduersary: VVe may boldly yet most
humbly vppon our knees requyre them before
God and all his elect Angels no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to cast it away.
VVherfore for the first, let vs grant the great
difference vvhich they make of yeares and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
yet the speech of Elihu giueth them suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
answere,<note place="margin">Iob. 32. 7. 8.</note> that this vnderstanding is not ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to such outvvard respectes but to the<note place="margin">Iob. 32. 21. 22.</note> * reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of Gods spirit, and to accept in such cases
the persons of men, or to giue titles, is but to
prouoke God to destroy vs. Yea let the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
examples of<note place="margin">2. Chro. 30. 1 5. 23. ver.</note> * Ezechias and the priestes: of
<pb facs="4"/>
      <note place="margin">Actes. 15. 23.</note> the Apostles in their counsels, of *<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 1.</note> Paule in his
Epistles, and euen of *<note place="margin">Act. 11. 1. 2. 3 4. &amp;c.</note> Peter in yeelding to the
challenge of some not so well instructed mooue
them, vvho not onely not refused the Leuites &amp;
Elders; but accepted the people in some maner
to be heard to speake, and to authorize their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations
and writings: at least let their own
opinion, that, in interpreting the scriptures and
deliuerye of doctrine,<note place="margin">D. VVhit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifts booke. page. 389.</note> we are equall vvith them,
persvvade them, not to refuse those, vvho if they
coulde straine their consciences to subscribe to
the Archbish. articles, they would gladly receiue
them to be the Ambassadors of Iesus Christ. As
for the fevvnes it may bee, if the ignorant mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,
the varietie of other which subscribe, some
doing it vvith this limitation &amp; some vvith that,
some holding their former iudgement as not
gaine sayd by their subscription, some lamenting
their slip in that behalfe vvere deducted, the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of the one vvoulde not so greatly surmount
the other. As for the challenge of the Papistes
knit vp vvith the consideration of the estate, the
difference may be considered in the matter and
maner. Concerning the matter, they make it in
the substaunce of religion vvhich hath in diuers
assemblies abroad and at home beene disputed,
resolued, and novv publikly maintayned for our
true &amp; holy faith. VVe in maters concerning the
gouernment of Christ of great moment indeed,
yet neuer thus handled, nor vrging the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but perfection of the estate of the Church, &amp;
further good of the common wealth, vvhilst by
this means amongst many other things of great
importance, the ignorant ministery, &amp; by it po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie,
<pb facs="5"/>
&amp; by popery rebellion should be auoyded,
vvhich by the other are most manifestly bred &amp;
nourished. Concerning the maner, they call it to
a sudden and tumultuous reasoning, vvhere the
readiest vvit, the best memorye, the moste filed
speech, shall carry avvaye the truth, at least mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailously
moue the vngrounded harers. VVe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
that where both sides may vpon mature &amp;
sufficient deliberation be beard vvithout any of
these shewes, and the matter deliuered vnto her
maiestie, their Hh: and vvhomsoeuer they shall
chuse, to receiue and examine the allegations of
both sides: So that it neede not be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
vnto the people, vntill the manifest light of
truth appeare first vnto them. And if this so safe
and reasonable an offer, cannot be liked in the
respect of the last obiected consideration, vve
thinke it impossible, but the persons vvhich de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
a vvay so sound, peaceable and dutifull, shall
recouer this fauor that vvith safety of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences,
they shall exercise their ministery vvith
that libertie, vvhich is meet for those, vvho shall
be tyed in all thinges to haue especiall regard to
the peace of the Church and publique orders.
VVherefore most christian Reader, vvhen thou
shalt by these sevve, take knovvledge of these
things, pray vnto God for vs, and as thy place is,
solicite and further so iust a cause, to this ende
onely, that Christes kingdome may be perfectly
established, the consciences of al the godly qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted,
and the happy regiment of her maiestie
honored, vvith much peace ioye and quietnesse
at home.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>