<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST
Illustrous and most excellent Prince
CHARLES,
Prince of VVales, Duke of Cornwall,
Earle of CHESTER, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Malynes, Gerard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111905_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06785</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17221</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST
Illustrous and most excellent Prince
CHARLES,
Prince of VVales, Duke of Cornwall,
Earle of CHESTER, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Malynes, Gerard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The center of The circle of commerce. Or, A refutation of a treatise, intituled The circle of commerce, or The ballance of trade, lately published by E.M. By Gerard Malynes merchant</title>
                 <author>Malynes, Gerard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 32, 35-139, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST
Illustrous and most excellent Prince
CHARLES,
Prince of VVales, Duke of Cornwall,
Earle of CHESTER, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>It may please your Highnes.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Oracle of Apollo at Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi>
being demanded why <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi>
should be the chiefest of the
gods, sith <hi>Mars</hi> was the best
Souldier: Answered, <hi>Mars</hi> is
valiant, but <hi>Iupiter</hi> wise; concluding by this,
that Councell and Policy are of more force to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
then Valour; <hi>Parua sunt Arma foris, nisi
sit Concilium domi,</hi> saith <hi>Cicero:</hi> but foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
that neither wisdome nor valour can well
subsist without treasure, since Moneys haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
the title of the sinowes of war, and the life
<pb facs="3"/>
of Commerce: I hope that the accumulating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
may properly be called <hi>The Praeheminent
study of Princes,</hi> when the same is procured by
Trade: which is the sole peaceable instrument to
inrich Kingdomes and Common-weales.</p>
   <p>This Trade is performed betweene vs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine
Countries vnder three simples, namely
<hi>Commodities, Moneys, and Exchanges for
Moneys,</hi> which being ioyntly and distinctly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered
in their proper natures, will cause our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed
Trade to flourish: but because one <hi>Edward
Misselden</hi> did omit to handle the <hi>Praedominant
part of Trade</hi> (in a Treatise Dedicated vnto
your Highnes, Intituled) <hi>Free Trade,</hi> viz. the
<hi>Mistery of Exchanges,</hi> and that not without an
aspersion laid vpon me I was moued to make an
answer thereunto, shewing his maine scope to be,
to haue the moneys of the Realme inhaunced, and
the forreine Coyne to be currant at an equall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue:
which was to reforme things by a Remedy
worse then the disease; for the inhauncing of our
Moneys wil increase the prices of all things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
the Kings most Excellent Maiestie shall become
the greatest loser in the reuenewes of the Crowne,
and the Nobility and Landed men also: and to
<pb facs="3"/>
make forreine Coyne currant within the Realme,
will ouerthrow his Maiesties Mint, and abrogate
<hi>a marke of Soueraignty,</hi> the Coyning of Moneys.</p>
   <p>Hereupon hauing in the Epistle Dedicatory of
the said Treatise vnto his sacred Maiestie, intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<hi>The Maintenance of Free Trade:</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the same vnto the Little Fish mentioned by
<hi>Plutarch,</hi> swimming before the Great VVhale:
because I had then vnder the Presse a great vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume
of <hi>Lex Mercatoria,</hi> Dedicated likewise vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his Maiestie, and both presented vnto your
Highnes.</p>
   <p>The said <hi>Misselden</hi> (carping at the <hi>Simile,</hi>
and directing his course from your Highnes) hath
lately published an opposition to the said Bookes,
called the <hi>Circle of Commerce,</hi> copious of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuill
speeches, whereby (in respect of priuat cause)
I haue great occasion to implore his Maiesties fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
against him; As <hi>Homer</hi> did <hi>Ptolome</hi> the
great King of Aegipt, against the rayling cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries
of <hi>Zoylus.</hi> But the matter concerning the
Publike, and being of farre greater consequence
then a centention for Learning, I am compell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d
humbly to beseech your Highnes to intercede for
me vnto his sacred Maiestie, to be well pleased to
<pb facs="4"/>
peruse this my third Booke, intituled <hi>The Center
of the Circle of Commerce,</hi> wherein the meanes
to prouide his Kingdomes and Dominions with
<hi>Bullion</hi> &amp; <hi>Moneys</hi> are more distinctly declared,
according to the said <hi>Center of Cōmerce,</hi> which
is (<hi>gaine,</hi>) without which his <hi>Circle</hi> is (<hi>vaine.</hi>)</p>
   <p>To make <hi>A Definition of the Center of the
Earth</hi> is difficult euen amongst learned Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers
and Schoolemen, considering <hi>Aristotle</hi> his
Doctrine grounded vpon <hi>Leuity</hi> of things ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
and <hi>Grauity</hi> of things falling to their <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi>
and the opinion of <hi>Copernicus,</hi> or rather of
the <hi>Pithagorians,</hi> ascribing <hi>a Stability</hi> to the
Heauens, and <hi>a Mobility</hi> to the Earth; But to
make a <hi>Definition</hi> of this <hi>Center (gaine)</hi> is easie,
and engraffed in euery mans iudgement.</p>
   <p>This <hi>Center</hi> maketh a perfect <hi>Orbe,</hi> inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
all <hi>Geometricall proportions,</hi> and can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere
all <hi>Mathematicall Problemes of Trade,
for the doubling of the Cube of Solids, and
the Quadrature of the Circle in Plaine,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<hi>Platos</hi> Exposition, or <hi>Misseldens</hi> conceited
<hi>Ballance of Trade:</hi> for all the weight of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce
falleth within the <hi>Circuit of the Circle of
this Center (gaine:)</hi> insomuch, that if the due
<pb facs="4"/>
consideration hereof be neglected in the course of
Trade, nothing can be expected but the decay of
Trade, and destruction of Common-weales, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the <hi>Demonstration</hi> of the following <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi>
to a diseased body naturall so that States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
and Politicians are to bend their iudgements
in all publike causes to this <hi>Center (gaine,</hi> which
beareth the sway in all humane actions,) thereby to
finde out all fallacies and misprisions of Trade, to
the increase of the Kingdomes stocke, without pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
regard of particular Merchants making their
benefit by the generall losse of the Kingdome: there
is no man so simple but will auoide a losse if he can,
and on the contrary, procure a gaine where he may
or can; Shall it be imagined then that <hi>Bullion</hi> &amp;
<hi>Moneys</hi> will be imported when the bringer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
becommeth a loser, or that moneys will remaine
within the Realme, when so great a gaine can be
had by the exportation thereof? Or will any man
think that Trade can be driuen conueniently with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
moneys and Exchanges? will not the want of
it make a dead Trade within the Realme when
this <hi>Vitall spirit of Commerce</hi> faileth? surely
it is questionles in euery mans vnderstanding.</p>
   <p>Your Highnes therefore may be pleased to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance
<pb facs="5"/>
the establishing of this <hi>Center</hi> in the course
of Trade, whereby his Maiesties Kingdomes and
Dominions will flow with <hi>Bullion</hi> and <hi>Moneys,</hi>
and infuse life thereunto, which will be felt by the
<hi>Pulces, the Hammers of the Mint:</hi> vpon my
life and reputation of knowledge, which time and
occasion seeme to further by the price of Exchange,
inclining thereunto since this Treatise hath beene
vnder the Presse. If any thing therein shall seeme
impertinent to the <hi>Grauity of the Center,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
your Highnes to attribute the same to the
<hi>Leuity of the Circle,</hi> the rather because <hi>Nugae
seria ducunt.</hi> Thus with all humblenes taking
leaue, I shall continue my feruent Prayers to the
Almighty, to preserue your Highnes in health and
happinesse, to his glory, and your eternall felicity.
<hi>London the 20. of Nouember.</hi> 1623.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnes most
obedient Seruant
<hi>GERARD MALYNES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>