<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the knowing Reader.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111358_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13444</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23750</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111358</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the knowing Reader.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eighth vvonder of the vvorld, or Coriats escape from his supposed drowning : With his safe arriuall and entertainment at the famous citty of Constantinople; and also how hee was honourably knighted with a sword of King Priams. With the manner of his proceeding in his peregrination through the Turkish territories towards the antient memorable citty of Ierusalem. By Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the knowing Reader.</head>
   <p>NOw sir, it is a common customary vse in these times, to salute you with somewhat; as Honest, Kinde, Curteous, Louing, Friendly, or Gentle: but all these Epithites are ouer-worne, and doe, as it were, stinke of the fusty garbe of Antiquity. Besides, if I should come vpon you with any of these claw-backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tearmes, I might chance to belye you. But if your kinde disposition doe merit to bee called kinde, I pray let me finde it in your fauourable censure. Some will (perhaps) dislike that I do dedicate my bookes to <hi>Archy,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and such like: To them I answere, that my sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect beeing altogether foolish, I were very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd to thinke that any wise man would be my Patron: And it were mere folly for me to make a hotch-potch, in seeking to compound wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and folly together. But howsoeuer thou
<pb facs="4"/>
esteemest it, it thrusts it selfe into thy view; wherin (if thou beest not too much drowned in Melancholy) thou wilt shew thy teeth (if thou hast any) with laughing. And as my lines are somewhat defective in their shape, so I pray thee, do not hacke them, nor hew them with thy stammering, to make them worse, nor Buzzard-blast them with thy calumniating mewes, tushes, and scuruyes. Thus leaning thee to thy selfe, and my selfe vnto thee, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine thine as thou respects me,</p>
   <signed>Iohn Taylor.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>