<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his most loued louing, and welbeloued, no matter whom.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111332_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13841</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24148.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111332</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his most loued louing, and welbeloued, no matter whom.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Laugh and lie dovvne: or, The worldes folly</title>
                 <author>Tourneur, Cyril</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To his most loued louing, and welbeloued, no matter whom.</head>
   <p>YOu Sir, hoping that you vvill take well, that is not worse ment, hauing nothing else, to giue you: I heere present you vvith a booke, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I haue vvriten as you see, vvhat it is you may Iudge, a strange course of an odde straine, in vvhich if you finde no matter to make you merry, feede fatte vvith your melancholy, till you be as madde as he that hath no more vvit, then he needes to occupie: There are many passages, to little purpose, to him, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands them not, &amp; yet he that hath both his eyes, may see more then a blinde man: I hope you are none of them, if you be, God help you, for I cannot, for thogh many can make lipp-salue, yet, vvit-salue is past my skill: preceptes there are none, for I doe not keepe a schoole, excepte it bee of had-I-vviste, and then if I should set vp my bill, <hi>I</hi> should haue too many Scholers: my meaning vvas, to be merry vvith my selfe, and if in mine humor, <hi>I</hi> haue made any angrie, if he cannot
<pb facs="4"/>
haue patience, he must fret, till he be vveary: such as are vvise, vvill smile at their conceit, and the foole, for lack of vvit vvill finde fault, vvith he knovves not vvhat. Ten, to one, <hi>I</hi> shall not please all men, and Tvventy to one, <hi>I</hi> do not desire it: yet, loath to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please any, <hi>I</hi> leaue it indifferently, to euery one, intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing good minds to giue it good vvords, and for the <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>I</hi> leave them to their bad humors: So, loath to tel <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vvhat follovves, <hi>I</hi> leaue my vvorke to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e of your Good vvill: and so rest as <hi>I</hi> finde cause.</p>
   <p>Your louing Friend,</p>
   <p>C. T.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>