<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONO∣RABLE AND VER∣tuous Lady, the Lady Dorothee Stafford widdow, one of the La∣dies of her Maiesties bed-chamber, Simon Stafford wisheth all honor and happinesse in this life, and in the life to come, perpetuall glorie and rest.</title>
           <author>Stafford, Simon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111010_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19716</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6134</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONO∣RABLE AND VER∣tuous Lady, the Lady Dorothee Stafford widdow, one of the La∣dies of her Maiesties bed-chamber, Simon Stafford wisheth all honor and happinesse in this life, and in the life to come, perpetuall glorie and rest.</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Simon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The care of a Christian conscience : Ten sermons on the 25 psalme, preached in Tewkesburie in the countie of Gloucester, By Richard Curtis</title>
                 <author>Curteys, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>216 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE AND VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady, the Lady Dorothee <hi>Stafford widdow, one of the</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of her Maiesties bed-chamber, Simon Stafford wisheth all honor and <hi>happinesse in this life, and in the life to come, perpetuall glorie and rest.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE straight and dutifull considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of so many great fauors, with which your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable disposition hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed to grace me, vnworthie the least of them, hath compelled me thus presumptuously to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate these Christian models (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb facs="3"/> the talent of another mans zealous inuention, yet as the tithe of my poore Printing-presse) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your honourable patronage; hoping, that in regard of their worth, and not of my deserts, you will likewise peruse them at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient seasons. The vtilitie of them I neede not rippe vp, seeing that your owne deepe-grounded wisedome wil hereafter by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced perusall find out the same far better, then either my simple mind can imagine, or my pen lay down. Onely this I humbly craue of your Honour, that my good deuotion herein bee acceptable vnto you: for our Sauior Christ preferred the poore widdowes mite, before the golden offerings of the rich. And is it not written,
<pb facs="3"/> that Artaxerxes a Pagan King, daigned to receiue a cup-full of cold water at the hand of poore Synetes? Whose president I imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, am emboldened to regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster your Heroicall name in the forefront of this booke, intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Care of a Christian Conscience,</hi> nothing doubting at all, but that your Honours name is registred in the Booke of life, for the Christian Care which you haue extēded to many of the poore distressed members of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ. Thus ceasing, I beseech the Lord to cōtinue you in your godly course, &amp; endue you with all blessings which eyther this earth affords, or heauen contains.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London, <date>Aprill 20. 1600.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honours most bounden, <hi>Simon Stafford.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>