<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right VVorshipfull and vertuous Ladies, the L. Anne Graie, &amp; the Ladie Marie Peter, long health of bodie, with qui∣et of minde, in the fauor of God and men for eer.</title>
           <author>Wilmot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111807_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15498</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25764</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right VVorshipfull and vertuous Ladies, the L. Anne Graie, &amp; the Ladie Marie Peter, long health of bodie, with qui∣et of minde, in the fauor of God and men for eer.</title>
                 <author>Wilmot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tragedie of Tancred and Gismund : Compiled by the gentlemen of the Inner Temple, and by them presented before her Maiestie. Newly reuiued and polished according to the decorum of these daies. By R.W</title>
                 <author>R. W. (Robert Wilmot)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Robinson, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right VVorshipfull and vertuous Ladies, the L. Anne Graie, &amp; the Ladie <hi>Marie Peter,</hi> long health of bodie, with qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>of minde, in the fauor of God and men for e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>er.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is most certaine (right vertuous and wershipfull) that of all humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Poetrie (how contemptible so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is in these daies, is the most anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) and in Poetrie, there is no argument of more antiquitie and elegancie than is the matter of Loue; for it seemes to be as old as the world, &amp; to beare date from the first time that man &amp; woman was: therfore in this, as in the finest mettall, the freshest wits haue in all ages shown their best workmanship. So amongst others these Gentlemen, which with what sweetnesse of voice and liuelinesse of action they then expressed it, they which were of her Maiesties right Honorable maidens can testifie.</p>
   <p>Which being a discourse of two louers, perhappes it may seeme a thing neither fit to be offered vnto your Ladyships, nor worthie me to busie my selfe withall: yet can I tell you Madames, it differeth so farre from the ordinarie amorous discourses of our daies, as the manners of our time do from the modestic and innocencie of that age.</p>
   <p>And now for that wearie winter is come vpon vs, which bringeth with him drouping daies and tedious nights, if it be true, that the motions of our mindes follow the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the aire wherein we liue, then I thinke, the perusing of some mournfull matter, tending to the view of a notable example, will refresh your wits in a gloomie day, &amp; ease <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> wearines of the louring night. Which if it please yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ye also for a solemne reuell against this Festiuall time, for <hi>Gismunds</hi> bloudie shadow, with a little cost, may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated in her selfe-like person to speake to ye.</p>
   <p>Hauing therfore a desire to be knowen to your W I deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed this waie with my selfe to procure the same, persuading my selfe, there is nothing more welcome to your wisedomes, then the knowledge of wise, graue, &amp; worthie matters, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d instructions of youths, of whom you are mothers.</p>
   <p>In this respect therefore, I shall humblie desire ye to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow a fauour able countenance vpon this little labor, which when ye haue graced it withall, I must &amp; will acknowledge my selfe greatly indebted vnto your Ladyships in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: neither shall I amongst the rest, that admire your rare vertues, (which are not a fewe in Essex) cease to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this vndeserued gentlenes.</p>
   <p>Thus desiring the king of heauen to increase his graces in ye both, granting that your ends may be as honorable, as your liues are vertuous, I leaue with a vaine babble of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny needlesse wordes to trouble you longer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships most dutifull and humble Orator <hi>Robert Wilmot.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>