<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To all the young Gentlemen of England, to whose perusing this Booke shall happen: George Whetstons wi∣sheth both health and good hap.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111731_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15046</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25348</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111731</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To all the young Gentlemen of England, to whose perusing this Booke shall happen: George Whetstons wi∣sheth both health and good hap.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rocke of regard : diuided into foure parts. The first, the castle of delight: wherin is reported, the wretched end of wanton and dissolute liuing. The second, the garden of vnthriftinesse: wherein are many swéete flowers, (or rather fancies) of honest loue. The thirde the arbour of vertue: wherein slaunder is highly punished, and vertuous ladies nad gentlewomen, worthily commended. The fourth, the ortchard of repentance: wherein are discoursed, the miseries that followe dicing, the mischiefes of quareling, the fall of prodigalitie: and the souden ouerthrowe of foure notable cousners, with diuers other morall, natural, &amp; tragical discourses: documents and admonitions: being all the inuention, collection and translation of George Whetstons Gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walley (Waley), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 128, 121, that is 123, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To all the young Gentlemen of England, to whose perusing this Booke shall happen: <hi>George Whetstons</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth both health and good hap.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Gentlemē, I haue presented vnto your friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceptaunce, a worke so worthlesse, (in respect of the homely handling thereof) as will (I feare) neither content you in reading, nor any wayes commend my paines in writing: &amp; yet I am right wel assured (curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous contentment set apart) it importeth necessarie matter of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for vnstayed youth, who hauing the raines at libertie, are so hote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n expence, as that they be many times surfited with incumberan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yea, tyred out right with prodigalitie, before they be brought into any perfect order of spending. For whose behalfe and forewarning, I haue collected together a number of my vnlearned deuises (inuented for the most, of experience) and more boldly, then well aduised, haue guarded them, with the title of the Rocke of regarde: not for that it conteineth only needefull matter, but for that you, hauing noted the discommodities of the vnnecessarie, might reade the necessarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations with more regard. And for that it behooueth the maister of euery feast, to prouide diuers dishes, to please the diuers appetites of his diuers guestes: the like consideration now moueth me, who hauing inuited a number to peruse my vnpolished labours, as neare as I can to vse such <hi>Decorum</hi> in my doings, as euerie desire may be satisfied. And sure I hold it necessarie, that matters of aduise (to worke atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō) be sometimes mingled with delight: and further, for that I know the most part of youth (to whome I chiefly dedicate the fruite of my trauell) are so carelesse of their commoditie, as they set light of sound aduise, vnlesse such persuasions be sauced (in some respect) with their owne desires, so that to win them to the reading of that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, I haue likewise presented them with matter of honest plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. And yet, least they lighting on some discourse of worth, shoulde by and by be led away, with the sight of some wanton deuise, I haue published my trauell, vnder these foure following titles.</p>
   <p>The first is, the <hi>Castle of delight.</hi> Wherin (to ioyne commoditie,
<pb facs="3"/>
with the readers pleasure) are many morall and needefull considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For who so noteth there, the issue of the Countesse of <hi>Zelants</hi> hate, may happely feare to execute a strumpets bloudie reuenge. In <hi>Cressids complaint,</hi> the subtilties of a Courtisan discouered, may forwarne youth from the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>̄panie of inticing dames. The aduentures of <hi>Rinaldo</hi> (which may verie well be termed a Laberynth of loue) discourseth the inconueniencies of iealousie: and by the ouerthrowe of <hi>Frizaldo,</hi> is showne the reward of lawlesse lust and trecherie.</p>
   <p>Some there be, that hauing eyed my former vnthriftinesse, doe gape (percase) to viewe in this booke, a number of vaine, wanton, and worthlesse Sonets, in some respectes I haue satisfied their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, moued to suffer the imprinting of them, not of vaine glorie, but of two good considerations: the one to make the rest of the booke more profitable, and (perhaps) lesse regarded, the better saileable. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; chiefest, in plucking off the visard of self conceit, vnder which I somtimes proudly masked with vaine desires. Other yong gentlemē may reforme their wanton liues, in seing the fond &amp; fruitles successe of my fantasticall īmaginations, which be no other then Poems of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest loue: and yet for that the exercise we vse in reading louing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, sildome (in my conceit) acquiteth our paines, with any thing beneficiall vnto the common weale, or verie profitable to our selues, I thought the <hi>Garden of Vnthriftinesse,</hi> the meetest title I could giue them.</p>
   <p>The third is, the <hi>Arbour of Vertue,</hi> the which I chiefly publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, for the delight of vertuous Ladies and Gentlewomen: and yet (my lustie Gent.) it conteineth matter very needfull for you to note: As in making choice of a wife, rather in owed with vertue, then mony, as Syr <hi>Vlrico</hi> did. And in reading the complaint of <hi>Alberto</hi> and <hi>Vdislao,</hi> you may see how foule a fault it is, rashly to iudge ill of womens behauiours.</p>
   <p>The fourth is, the <hi>Ortchard of Repentance,</hi> the which for the most part, I planted with experience: the fruits therin growing (think I) be hoalsome, although to curious appetites, not greatly toothsome. But what for that? the smarting wound is cured with fretting plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. Euen so, abuse is to be refourmed with sharpe reprehension, then sure it were not <hi>Decorum,</hi> in inueying against a Cousener, Cheter, Dicer, Quareler. &amp;c. (who for the most part) liue without good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb facs="3"/>
to vse any milde and plausible kinde of writing. The inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that rise of these professions, are the fruites of forewar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g, that my Orchard (gallant Gentlemen) affordeth: and yet to afforde you a good peniwoorth, it marreth the markets of a great many. The Cous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner will chafe to see his practises published: the Cheter will f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me▪ to see his crosbiting and cunning shiftes decyphered: the Dicer will sweare to heare his cogging &amp; foysting aduauntages discouered: the Quareler will stampe to heare his braules and brables bayted at: the Merchaunt will storme to see his new kinde of Vsuries reuealed: the Lawyer wilbe in a wonderfull heate, to heare his double dealings, his dilatorie delayes, and vnconscionable aduauntages disclosed: al these mens displeasures haue I hazarded, in opening (for your behoues) their mischiefous subtilties: and trust mee, not one of these sortes of men, but his teeth watereth with the desire of your lyuinges, yea hee daily studieth to bring you in lash: so that it behoueth you to looke warily into your estates, else you shall light into the snarts, of some of their daungers.</p>
   <p>Now, worthy Gentlemen, haue you heard my honest intent as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the imprinting of this my booke, mine was the paine in framing the plots, wherin these fruits &amp; flowers grow, yours is the pleasure &amp; profite of both, marr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> if you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>suse my welmeaning so farre, that you (where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ea roume serueth you to auoyde the sandes of wanton loue) wil wilfully run vpon the rockes of vnlawful lust, the folly is yours, &amp; no fault in me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or if you (wher you may gather frendly friuts of admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, that wil cure your woundes of prodigalitie, &amp; preserue you frō the infection of cousening cutthrots) will continually be smelling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnthriftie flowers, you not onely vamly spend your time, but worke a discredite vnto my painfull labours. Wherefore I earnestly require you, that you vse the first increase of my baren braine so rightly, as I may be incouraged hereafter to bente my head about some matter of more worth, rather then by the misuse of them, to be discouraged, from attempting any honest labour. And thus wishing good successe in your vertuous enterprises, I commit you to the pleasure of the hyest. From my lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>orne the 15. of October 1576.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>