<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the frendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111606_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14822</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25118a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111606</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the frendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hekatompathia or Passionate centurie of loue : diuided into two parts: whereof, the first expresseth the authors sufferance in loue: the latter, his long farewell to loue and all his tyrannie. Composed by Thomas Watson Gentleman; and published at the request of certaine gentlemen his very frendes</title>
                 <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cawood, Gabriel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, xcviii, 1, xcix-c, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the frendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, if anie thing herein either
please or profitte thee, afforde me thy good
worde in recompence of my paines: if ought
offend or hurt thee, I desire that thou forget
the one, and forgiue the other. This toye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
liked, the next may prooue better; being
discouraged, wil cut of the likeliehood of my trauaile to come▪
But by that meanes all will be well, and both parties pleased.
For neither shall I repent my labour in the like, nor thou be
anie more troubled with my faultes or follies.</p>
   <p>Yet for this once I hope thou wilt in respect of my trauaile
in penning these louepassions, or for pitie of my paines in
suffering them (although but supposed) so suruey the faultes
herein escaped, as eyther to winke at them, as ouersightes of
a blinde Louer; or to excuse them, as idle toyes proceedinge
from a youngling frenzie; or lastlie, to defend them, by say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
it is nothing <hi>Praeter decorum</hi> for a maiemed man to halt in
his pase, where his wound enforceth him, or for a Poete to fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
in his Poëme, whē his matter requireth it. <hi>Homer</hi> in mētio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the swiftnes of the winde, maketh his verse to runne in
posthaste all vpon <hi>Dactilus:</hi> and <hi>Virgill</hi> in expressing the stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
downe of an oxe, letteth the end of his hexameter fall
withall, <hi>Procumbit humibos.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore if I roughhewed my verse, where my sense was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setled,
whether through the nature of the passion, which I
felt, or by rule of art, which I had learned, it may seeme a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie
fault; or if it were so framed by counsell, thou mayest
thinke it well donne; if by chaunce, happelie.</p>
   <p>Yet write I not this to excuse my selfe of such errours, as are
escaped eyther by dotage, or ignorance: but those I referre to
thy gentle curtisie and fauourable construction, or lay manie
of them vpon the Printers necke, whom I would blame by his
owne presse, if he would suffer me.</p>
   <p>As for any Aristarchus, Momus, or Zoilus, if they pinch
me more then is reasonable, thou courteous Reader, which
arte of a better disposition, shalt rebuke them in my behalfe;
<pb facs="4"/>
saying to the first, that my birdes are al of mine own hatching,
and that my onelie ouermuch hast made <hi>Sol</hi> angrie in theire
Birthday; to the second, that although <hi>Venus</hi> be in my verse,
yet her slipper is left out; to the last and worst, that I rather
take vpon me to write better then <hi>Chaerilus,</hi> then once suppose
to imitate <hi>Homer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I am ouer long, as well for the feare I had to be bitten by
such as are captious, as for the desire I haue to please thee that
art frendlie. But since I now wel remember me, that nothing is
more easlie let flowne, nothing soner dispersed, nothing later
recalled backe againe, then the bitter blast of an euill spoaken
man, and that he, whome it shall hurt, hath no recure but by
patience; I will set it behinde my heele, as a hurt remedilesse,
or els, when it comes, salue it vp with patience.</p>
   <p>In the meane space (curteous Reader) I once againe craue
thy fauourable iudgement: and so, for breuitie sake, abruptlie
make an end; committing the to God, and my worke to thy
fauour.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine, as thou art his,</hi>
Thomas Watson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>