<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and vertuous Ladie, Christiana, wife to the Right Worshipfull Sir Iohn Leueson Knight: grace from God, both temporall, and etnall.</title>
           <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111515_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14008</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24317</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111515</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and vertuous Ladie, Christiana, wife to the Right Worshipfull Sir Iohn Leueson Knight: grace from God, both temporall, and etnall.</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true trial and turning of a sinner. Or, three plaine and profitable sermons : teaching the search and triall of our waies, repentance of sinne, and true turning vnto God. The summe whereof was preached at Feuersham in Kent Aug. 3. 1606. By Thomas Tuke</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 128, 139-186 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and vertuous Ladie, <hi>Christiana,</hi> wife to the Right Worshipfull Sir <hi>Iohn Leueson</hi> Knight: grace from God, both temporall, and et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nall.</head>
   <p>MAdame, rare and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable are the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors which we haue receiued of the Lord, &amp; by his grace enioyed now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most fiftie yeares together. He hath giuen vs his Word and Gospel, his lawes and statutes: hee hath planted a
<pb facs="3"/>
Vineyard amongst vs, and sent his Prophets vnto vs. Hee hath brought vs out of captiuitie from vnder Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne <hi>Babylon,</hi> and dispelled the Egyptian-like darknesse of Romish superstitions. Hee hath not dealt so with euery Nation. Moreouer, hee hath imparked vs with the pales of Peace, and hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs about with the Lawrells of Prosperitie. He doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h fill our barnes with plentie, &amp; causeth our cups to runne ouer. He hath put the Palmes of victorie into our hands, the Garlands of triumphs about our heads,
<pb facs="3"/>
and hath made our verie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies seeke to be at peace with vs. Hee hath turned our speares into spades, our swords into sythes, and our pikes into pennes; yea to make a perfect and plenary demonstration of his loue vnto vs, and hatred of our Aduersaries, he hath of late vouchsafed to vs both Prince and People,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Neuem.</hi> 5. 1605.</note> a verie wonderfull and great Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, from a most bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and vniuersall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, plotted, and almost performed by the children of <hi>Babel,</hi> the Minians of that purple Harlot. But
<pb facs="4"/>
how doe we remonstrate our thankfulnesse and loue to him? Alas, our ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is too-too manifest. Our sinnes doe testifie the same to our faces. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Oathes, Prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Lords day, Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, yea and palpable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Gospell, and of Gods faithfull and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Embassadours, with many other grieuous and transcendent enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, do so swell &amp; abound in the multitude, as that if they were not by force held in with the piles of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some lawes, and the banks
<pb facs="4"/>
of gouernmēt, they would quickly ouerflow, &amp; beare and beate down all before them. So that the Lorde may say of vs, as <hi>Moses</hi> som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times said of <hi>Israel</hi>:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 15.</note>
      <hi>But hee that should haue bene vpright, when he waxed fatte, spurned with his heele, and forsooke God that made him, and regarded not the strong God of his saluation</hi>: not much vnlike wee are (for the most) to the yong <hi>Hindes</hi> mentioned in the booke of <hi>Iob,</hi> who when they are waxed fatte, and growne vp with corne, <hi>Goe from their dammes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 39. 7.</note>
      <hi>and returne no more vnto them. Iosephus</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
writeth, that the Riuer <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> doth carrie the Fishes so long sporting themselues, and floting aloft, till at length it casts thē headlong into the <hi>Dead Sea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mare mortuum.</note> where they perish: so it seemes our prosperity, through the corruption of our heartes, hath trained vs on so long, that wee haue fallen into a Sea of sinnes, and a gulfe of wickednesse. What can we now expect of God, besides the complement of that dreadfull minace vpon vs, with which, the declining church of <hi>Ephesus</hi> was som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times threatned:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Reue.</hi> 2. 5.</note> to wit, the
<pb facs="5"/>
remouing of her <hi>Candlestick</hi> out of his place vnlesse she did repent? If we therefore desire the continuance of the Gospell among vs, and of all outwarde blessings, which attend vpō the true professors and embracers of it, we must in the feare of God, <hi>Search &amp; trie our waies, and turne againe vnto him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your waies and your works</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>and I will let you dwell in this place.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 3.</note>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 9.</note>
      <hi>The Lord our God is gracious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and will not turne away his face from vs, if we conuert vnto him. Pliny</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. cap. <hi>26.</hi>
      </note> that the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-horse</hi> feeling himself too
<pb facs="6"/>
fatte,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi>
      </note> &amp; ouermuch grown, pricketh a veine in his legge with some sharpe reede newly cut, and by letting himselfe blood, doeth so helpe himselfe, and preuent the daunger, which he was subiect before to fall into: so when wee swell with pride and selfe-loue, and when we waxe grosse spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, and fatte at heart, and when the corrupt humors of our soules abound, our best phisicke is, to prick our hearts with true compunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of spirit, and remorse of conscience, and to let our selues blood of those
<pb facs="6"/>
corrupt humours by true repentance, and godlye sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. If wee neglect the performance of these du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wee may iustly feare, that the Lord will remoue his fauours from vs, &amp; giue them to a people that will bring forth better fruites. To helpe forwarde this godly practise, I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled, penned, and now published, these sequent exhortations: which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate and offer vnto your Ladishippe, especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I knowe you loue this Doctrine, &amp; the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practisers of the same.
<pb facs="7"/>
Thus taking my humble leaue, I recommend you to the grace of God.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Cuxton.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>March.</hi> 25. 1607.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Ladiships in all dutie,</hi> Thomas Tuke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>