<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Margery Quiet of Tame, in Oxford-shire, to her Ingenious friend, the Author, she acknow∣ledging him to be a well-wisher to all good wo∣men.</title>
           <author>Q., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111401_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13461</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23766</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Margery Quiet of Tame, in Oxford-shire, to her Ingenious friend, the Author, she acknow∣ledging him to be a well-wisher to all good wo∣men.</title>
                 <author>Q., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iuniper lecture : With the description of all sorts of women, good, and bad: from the modest to the maddest, from the most civil, to the scold rampant, their praise and dispraise compendiously related. Also the authors advice how to tame a shrew, or vexe her</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Lee (Ley), William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 167, 188-236 pages, plates, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>Margery Quiet of Tame, <hi>in</hi> Oxford-shire, to her Ingenious friend, the Author, she acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him to be a well-wisher to all good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</head>
   <l>MEn have the Art of flattery, to commend</l>
   <l>That most, whereto their vaine affections bend.</l>
   <l>Our beauties they extoll unto the skies,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>In prose and verse, with many thousand lyes;</l>
   <l>With tongue and pen our prayses they repeat.</l>
   <l>How faire, how fine, how proper, and how neate:</l>
   <l>How handsome, and how bony, and how gay,</l>
   <l>How delicate and dainty every way</l>
   <l>We silly women are, with tooth and naile:</l>
   <l>Mens flattery still our weaknesse doth assaile.</l>
   <l>And wee (alas) beleeve them too too much,</l>
   <l>And what they say, wee strive still to be such.</l>
   <l>For cause they praise us for those things we see,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>Wee give our whole en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours so to be.</l>
   <l>To paint, pounce, frounce, kemb, curle, purle, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der sleeke,</l>
   <l>And all new fashions to search out and seeke,</l>
   <l>To please our praysers: But if men could find,</l>
   <l>What 'twere to praise the vertue of the mind,</l>
   <l>What honour doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to chastity,</l>
   <l>What merit doth pertain to modesty:</l>
   <l>If goodnesse with mens praises were but grac't,</l>
   <l>We should bee then more modest, and more chast.</l>
   <l>But thou (the Author of
<pb facs="10"/>
this following book)</l>
   <l>Ingenious, just, impartiall paines hast tooke:</l>
   <l>Thou dost commend the good, condemne the ill,</l>
   <l>For which all women, of all sorts shall still</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Remaine thy friends and foes.</hi> M.Q.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>