<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my dearely affectionate friend Mr. RICHARD ZOVCHE.</title>
           <author>Yong, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111819_Fr1_3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26130</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111819</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my dearely affectionate friend Mr. RICHARD ZOVCHE.</title>
                 <author>Yong, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doue: or Passages of cosmography : By Richard Zovche ciuillian, of New Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Zouch, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Norton, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To my dearely affectionate friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. RICHARD ZOVCHE.</head>
   <l>THy worke hath tongue, for vs t'admire thy worth,</l>
   <l>Silence, the voyce of an admiring minde</l>
   <l>Should then best fit my pen; but Loue breaks forth</l>
   <l>And will needs speake what in thy booke I finde,</l>
   <l>And wrestingly, out of my wonted lynes</l>
   <l>It makes me shuffle in these hobling rymes.</l>
   <l>Though t'were not thine, it's good, but hauing birth</l>
   <l>From thee, it's excellent; who in an houre</l>
   <l>Flyest o're the forrest of the spatious earth,</l>
   <l>And of each Eden dost cull out some flowres,</l>
   <l>And leau'st out nothing, (this is admirable)</l>
   <l>Which to a setled eye can be remarkeable,</l>
   <l>And in so narrow lines could be discouer'd</l>
   <l>Of so much World;) but thy penne hath vtterr'd,</l>
   <l>And for this Truth, which men best-bred do know</l>
   <l>Didst but into the Muses garden goe.</l>
   <l>Who fearing danger dares not crosse the Sea,</l>
   <l>And of the Earth desires to know the frame,</l>
   <l>Let him but read thy worke, and he shall see</l>
   <l>The worlds faire Symstry by distinguisht names,</l>
   <l>And by thy Art, his ignorance may know</l>
   <l>For which most men by Land and Sea doe row:</l>
   <l>And let him blesse thy wit, and prayses sing</l>
   <l>that thus with ease dost him such knowledg bring.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>Ingenious ZOVCHE, liue thy Verses long,</l>
   <l>Fly faire, and far thy Doue, with her smooth song:</l>
   <l>Of thy all-Noble name for Armes long knowne,</l>
   <l>These Lettred times haue thee design'd their owne.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Louer and friend, <hi>Richard Yong.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>