<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the ryght woorshipfull Syr Wylliam Garerd Knyght, and Maister Thomas Lodge, Aldermen of the Citie of London, and gouer∣nours of the honorable Felowship or Societie, as well of certayne of the Nobilitie, as of Merchants Aduen∣turers, for the discouery of Lands, Territories, Ilands, &amp; Signories vnknowen, and not before their fyrst aduenture or enterpryse by Sea or Nauiga∣tion commonly frequented.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111167_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19376</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5802</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111167</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the ryght woorshipfull Syr Wylliam Garerd Knyght, and Maister Thomas Lodge, Aldermen of the Citie of London, and gouer∣nours of the honorable Felowship or Societie, as well of certayne of the Nobilitie, as of Merchants Aduen∣turers, for the discouery of Lands, Territories, Ilands, &amp; Signories vnknowen, and not before their fyrst aduenture or enterpryse by Sea or Nauiga∣tion commonly frequented.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of nauigation : conteyning a compendious description of the sphere, with the making of certayne instruments and rules for nauigations, and exemplifyed by many demonstrations. Written by Martin Cortes Spanyarde. Englished out of Spanishe by Richard Eden, and now newly corrected and amended in diuers places</title>
                 <author>Cortés, Martín</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Watkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 83, 1 leave, folded plates, woodcut illustrations, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To the ryght woorshipfull Syr Wylliam Garerd Knyght, and Maister Thomas Lodge, Aldermen of the Citie of London, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the honorable Felowship or Societie, as well of certayne of the Nobilitie, as of Merchants Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers, for the discouery of Lands, Territories, Ilands, &amp; Signories vnknowen, and not before their fyrst aduenture or enterpryse by Sea or Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion commonly frequented.</head>
   <head type="sub">And to the ryght Worshipfull the Consulles, Assistents, and Comminaltie of the same Societie, RICHARD <hi>EDEN</hi> Wysheth health and prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat so euer he was (right Honorable and Woorshipfull) that first beleeued that the frame and coaptation of the body of man, with the functions, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and dueties of the partes and members of the same, knit togeather in a certayne vnitie to a common mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration, did represent a liuely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage &amp; similitude of a perfect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth: I thinke that he was a man of no vulgar iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or obiect minde, but rather of singuler wisedome and prudence, in the contemplation of diuine &amp; humane things. For he sawe, that as in the small natiue seede of all growing or liuing things, is conteined the fourme that bringeth them to theyr perfection: so in certayne small and obscure mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Common wealth, consisteth no small encrease to the perfection of the whole. He saw lykewise, that heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as in the body of man, representing the partes and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the world (as I haue sayde) are dyuers parts of diuers and sundry actions &amp; motions, greatly differing in fourme,
<pb facs="4"/>
number, and quantitie, yet all the same to be so knit togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and so to consent in one vniformitie, to the common profit of the whole, that a greater concord &amp; harmonie can not be imagined, then is proportioned by the friendly vnitie of diuers and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rary. He saw likewise in the same, such a mutuall compassion of part to part, and member to mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, by one common sense exi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tent in them all, that no one part or member can feele eyther ioy or payne, but that in manner all the other are partakers thereof more or lesse, yf they be liuely members, and not withered, or otherwise vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensate by reason of dead flesh, which only by cutting and burning ought to be diuided from the sound and whole. But as in man (whome <hi>Plato</hi> calleth the lesse world) the vigour and agilitie of the immortall soule and minde neuer ceasseth from continuall moouing, but is euer exercised in excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; inuentions of great things (herein resembling God, whose caract it beareth) by prouidence foreseeing, and by intelligence vnderstanding, and deuising what is to be done, and what to be eschewed, doth immmediatly mooue and rayse vp the faculties, powers, and members of the body to execute the same: Euen so, in the greater world, the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, and vniuersall counsayle and consent of men, hath elected &amp; appoynted certayne principall men, to beare like rule &amp; aucthoritie in the body of the Common wealth, as hath the intellectiue soule in the members of our body to mooue and commaund the same. To Princes therefore, Counsaylours, Rulers, Gouernours, and Magistrates, as to the most intellectiue and sensitiue partes of the societie of men, hath God and Nature geuen preeminence and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the Common wealth, that by their prouidence, wisedome, and ayde, it may vniuersally florishe, not only by iust administratiō of good lawes, with due correction of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactours, but also by lyberall rewarding of suche as haue well deserued, and especially by maynteinance of such Artes and Sciences, as the Common wealth can not well be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. And to drawe nearer to the applying of my simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, I say, that what so euer Vertue, what so euer Arte.
<pb facs="4"/>
or the ingenious industry of men, hath to this day inuented, all the same is to be imputed to the beneuolence and libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of such as haue honorably mainteyned, and freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded the trauayles, paynes, and charges of them that haue spent theyr lyues, goodes, and wits (as many haue done) in the inuentions of necessarie and profitable Artes and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For euen as wholesome and temperate ayre, with sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable weather, and fauourable influence of the heauens and planets, causeth fruitefulnes on the earth, and contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, barrennes by the contrary: Euen so the fauour of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Magistrates, nourisheth, augmenteth, and amplify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, all Artes and Sciences by liberalitie, and extinguisheth the same by miserable couetousnes and parcimonie. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in some men of rare and noble nature, the desyre of honor and fame, only for vertues sake, and studie towarde their Countrey and Common wealth, haue mooued them (in maner to their owne vndoing, through their great losse and hinderance) to set foorth and inuent diuers thyngs for the commoditie of the common wealth, and other, rather then for their owne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yet vndoubtedly, who so well consyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and indifferently wayeth that I haue sayd, shall fynde and see by dayly experience, that in maner onely munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, liberalitie, and reward, or the hope thereof, geueth spurres to them that attempt great and vertuous enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, as I could more largely proue by so many testimonies of hystories, both holy &amp; prophane, that the rehearsall therof should be but tedious, and not greatly necessary for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, especially writing vnto your Honors and Worships, of whose munificence, and liberalitie, I haue had great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, both in my selfe, and others, who by your ayde and mayntenance, haue attempted, &amp; perfourmed many good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inuentions, vyages, nauigations, and discoueries of lands and seas, heretofore vnknowen. Wherein, what great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges you haue susteyned, and how liberall and constant you haue bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in furthering the same, doth well declare, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t hytherto you are rather losers then gayners thereby. The whcih thing doubtlesse, is more to your commendation, in
<pb facs="5"/>
that it may heereby appeare that you haue attempted the same, rather for knowledge and vertues sake, then for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetousnesse of gaynes: as is furthermore well knowen by your fyrst vyages of discouerie attempted to <hi>Cathay,</hi> by the Northeast seas, vpon certayne losse and detriment, for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne hope eyther of gaynes, or of any such way to be found, otherwise then by certayne likely coniectures: not much vnlike to the shining flowres of Marchasytes, which outwardly appearing in minerall mountaynes, are signes and tokens whereby is coniectured what metall is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein, and whether the same be to be folowed or not. And although it sometime so chaunce, that such signes are fayleable, shewing more in apparance, then they contayne in substance: yet are not such signes, tokens, or shewes to be contemned, but rather earnestly to be folowed, for as much as it hath been often prooued, and found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that by folowing the same, haue been found great and ryche mynes of mettalles, as <hi>Georgius Agricola</hi> in his bookes <hi>De rebus metallices,</hi> dooth largely declare and prooue by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples. But to write at large what great things haue proceeded of small and obscure beginnings, and in manner meere coniectures, it would so farre exceede the measure of an Epistle or Preface, that it would rather encrease to the iust quantitie of a booke. For in manner all the late disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryes both of the Spanyards and Portugales, had theyr be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of such small coniectures, with vncertayne hope (as it were <hi>praeter spem sub spe</hi>) vntyll God and good happe, by the constant trauayle and valiant minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f such as fyrst attempted the same, gaue them to enioy that they hoped for. But what so euer they haue obteyned, and do enioy, this may I boldly say in your behalfe (right Honorable and Worshypfull) that there hath not lacked in you, eyther the lyke or greater promptnesse of minde, forwardnesse in attempting, magnificence in expences, or liberalitie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> For besyde the great charges, and losses that you haue been at otherwyse, what should I speake of the great giftes that you haue sent to the Emperour of Russia? What
<pb facs="5"/>
of your last chargeable vyage of discouerie among the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Rockes, Ilandes, and moueable mountaynes of yse in the frosen sea, by innumerable lands and Ilands vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the Antiques, euen vnder and farre within and beyond the circle Articke, where they thought that no ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng creature coulde drawe breath or lyfe for extreeme colde? whereas neuerthelesse the same hath been by you discouered, euen vnto the mightie ryuer of <hi>Ob,</hi> that falleth into the Scythian Ocean, or <hi>Oceanus Hyperborei,</hi> not farre from the mountaynes called <hi>Hyperboreus,</hi> so named, because they are situate almost vnder the North Pole, and thought therefore to be inaccessible. A voyage doubtlesse of suche difficultie, and in maner impossibilitie, that considering the infinite dangers thereof (as I haue learned by the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Steuen a Burrough,</hi> that was then the chiefe Pilot of the same voyage) it may seeme impossible that they should euer haue escaped, except the mightie hand of God, by the expert skylfulnesse of so excellent a Pilot, had deliuered thē from those dangers. And although in deede (as religion bindeth vs) it is conuenient in all things to geue all honour, glory, and thanks to God: yet are we not thereby restray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be thankefull to such men, as by theyr arte, ingenious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, trauayle, and diligence, haue dese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ued both iust com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, and large rewarde. And therefore referring the reward to you (right Honorable &amp; Worshipfull, to whome it apperteyneth) if I should not heere geue him at the least such commendation as in my iudgement he hath well deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I might seeme both to defraud him of his woorthy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts, and also to forget the friendship and good will I beare him, only for his vertues and excellencie in his profession. For certainely when I consider how indigent and destitute this Realme is of excellent and expert Pilottes, I can doo no lesse of conscience, then, in respect of your owne commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, yea rather for the commoditie of the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stie, and the whole Realme, to exhort you, and put you in remembrance (although I may heerein seeme to put the Spurr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s to a running Horsse, as sayth the Prouerbe) so to
<pb facs="6"/>
regard hym, and esteeme hym, and his faithfull, true, and paynefull seruice toward you, that he may thereby be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encouraged, and not discouraged, eyther for lacke of mayntenance, or otherwise by the iniurious assaults of such his enimies, as onely his vertues and excellency haue moued to beare him displeasure: as enuie doeth euer follow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as sayth the Latine Prouerbe, <hi>Virtuti comes inuidia.</hi> And how true a sentence this is, is well verified by the saying of a certayne Philosopher (whose name I do not remember) who hearing one vaynely reioyce that he had no enimies, answeared, that that was a token he had done little good: meaning thereby (as dayly experience p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oueth) that if he had excelled in any vertue, he could not haue lacked some enimies. And hauing here touched <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o speake of enuie, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that when I was a young Scholler, I haue read in the Poet <hi>Hesiodus</hi> of two kyndes of enuie, whereof the one is called <hi>Inuidia,</hi> and the other <hi>Aemulatio,</hi> which is more tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable then the first, for that it is ioyned with some vertue, and enuyeth that any should excell him in any excellent qualitie that he professeth. But for asmuch as this enuie of emulation proceedeth of some singuler vertue of them that are so maliced, they may herein reioyce, that they shall euer haue a hundred freends for one enimie: yea, and although they had none, yet is vertue a reward to it selfe, and to bee embraced for it selfe onely, as the Philosophers affyrme. What then shall we say to such, as forgetting this reward of vertue, do not onely fauour, but rather hynder the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mayntenance of such expert men, more estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming certayne Fyshermen that goe a trawling for fysh in Catches, or Mongers, and Dradgies for Oysters about the sandes, betweene the South furland and Wyntertonnesse, and the sandes about Temmes mouth, then they doo suche excellent Pilotes as are able without any Rutter or Carde of Nauigation, not onely to attempt long and farre vyages, but also to discouer vnknowen lands and Ilandes, as haue done of late yeeres many excellent men, to the great honor and enriching of theyr Prince and Countrey. But as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rrough,</hi> the chiefe Pilot of your vyages of discouery, it may hereby well appeare, that he is neyther malitious nor enuious of his Arte and Science, in that hee desireth the same, for the common profite, to be common to all men: and for the same inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t was the first that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued certayne Worshipfull of your company, as Syr <hi>Wyllyam Garrerd,</hi> Mayster <hi>Wyllyam Mericke,</hi> Mayster <hi>Blase Sanders,</hi> and Mayster <hi>Edward Castlen,</hi> to haue this worke translated into the Englishe tongue: Who of theyr owne good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, fauouring all vertuous studies, and the professours of the same, did soone enclyne to his ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>st request heerein, and therewith not onely desired me, but also with liberall rewarde enterteyned me, to take in hand the translation. Which beyng now finished as well as my poore learning may perfourme, I desyre your Honors, and Worships, to accept in good part, as I haue meant heerein to grat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e you, and doo such seruice as my abilitie may suffice. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thys woorke of the Art of Nauigation, being publyshed in our v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lger tongue, you may be assured to haue more store of skilfull Pilots. Pilots, (I say) not Pirots, Rulers, nor Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, but such as by their honest behauiour and conditions, ioyned with art and experience, may do you honest and true seruice: Which is not to be looked for of such as being desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute aswell of the feare of God, as of all morall vertues, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabound in all notorious vices, accompting desperatnesse for boldnesse, rashnesse for hardines, impudencie for stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and crueltie for manhood. What other thing (I say) is to be looked for of such, then of such trees, such fruites, <hi>Et mali corui, malum o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um.</hi> But f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rasmuch as these haue no place appoynted them in the body of our common wealth, which we haue here before compared to the members of the body of man: therefore are they no otherwise to be estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then as excrements of the body, to whome Nature hath appoynted no place in the same, but lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ureth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to cast th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> foorth diuers wayes, least by their filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse they should infect the other members, euen as the pompe of the Shyp, if it be not auoyded, is noyous to the
<pb facs="7"/>
Ship, and all that are therein. But the wise and honest Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte, fyrst hauing before his eyes the feare of God, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his chiefe trust in him, shall secondarily trust in his Arte and Science, without any such vaine obseruations, as the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persticious Horoscopers (Astrologiers I meane, and not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stronomers) are accustomed to vse in the elections of houres, times, and dayes, by constellati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ns and aspectes of the Starres and Planets, as many fond men haue done, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng thereby to haue escaped such dangers, as they haue thereby the rather fallen into, through contempt of Arte and Science, by foolish confidence in superstitious Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: which for the vani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie and vncertaintie thereof, the ryght Worshipfull, and of singuler learning in all Sciences, Syr <hi>Thomas Smyth,</hi> in my time the flowre of the Vniuersitie of Cambridge, and sometyme my Tutor, was accustomed to call <hi>Ingeniosissimam artem mentiendi,</hi> (that is) The most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious arte of lying. Omitting therefore the superstitious and phantasticall obseruations of the iudicials of Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, it shalbe better and more necessarie for all Pilottes that desyre to excell in their profession, to learne and obserue the principles of this Booke, whereby they may haue such knowledge of the Sphere, as may instruct them the making and vse of diuers goodly Astronomicall instruments pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the arte of Nauigation, by knowledge of the moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings of the Sunne and Moone in their Spheres, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Planettes and fyxt Starres: thereby to attayne to the true knowledge of houres, tymes, and tydes, with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of the Compasse, and many other goodly naturall obseruations of weather, tempestes, and calmes, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne infallible signes and tokens of the same, very necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be obserued, and this by the true principles of Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie, and not of Astrologie. And this is the true Astrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, whereof the diuine Philosopher <hi>Plato</hi> hath written so diuine a sentence, that I haue thought the same heere woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be alleaged, that by the aucthoritie of so famous an aucthour, we may know what is true Astronomie, with the vse and commoditie thereof. Therefore in his booke enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Timeus vel de Natura,</hi> these are his words.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Rerum autem optimarum cognitionem, nobis oculi attulerunt. Nam haec que de mundo disputantur, nunquam inuenta fuissent, si neque Sydera, neque Sol, neque Coelum, suscipe potuissent. Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio vero diei ac noctis, ab oculis orta, fecit vt dimensione quadam mensium, annorumque ambitus metiremur, tempus cognosceremus, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vniuersae naturae ordinem scrutaremur. Quibus ex rebus, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophiam adepti sumus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That is to say, Our eyes haue brought vnto vs the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of most excellent things. For whatsoeuer is disputed of the world, had neuer been inuented, if neyther the Starres, neyther the Sunne, neyther Heauen, could haue been seene. For the knowledge of the day and nyght, taking beginning at the eyes, cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed vs, as it were by certayne limits and boundes, to measure the circuites of monethes and yeeres, whereby we came to the knowledge of tymes, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of vniuersall nature. And heereby also we obteyne the knowledge of Philosophie. &amp;c. And thus by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of diuine <hi>Plato,</hi> (whome for his excellencie <hi>Cicero</hi> called <hi>Deum Philosophorum,</hi> that is, the God of Philosophers) we may vnderstande, that the true Astronomie, is the perfect knowledge of the miraculous mouings of the Planets, Stars, and heauens (and especially of the Sunne and Moone) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is caused the varietie of times, and diuersitie of all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things, by natural causes: as by the qualities of Elemēts, as hote, colde, moyst, and dry, which are augmented or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minished by the more or lesse influence of these two Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, as they come neere vnto vs at sometimes, or depart farther frō vs at other times, with diuers motions in diuers climates, which causeth not only varietie of tymes in sundrie climates, but also the varietie of dyuers complexions, fourmes, and disposit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ons of all creatures vnder the face of heauen, none other accidentall, contingent, voluntarie, or violent cause, to the contrary notwithstanding. And this is it that <hi>Plato</hi> meaneth by these woords, <hi>Vt tempus cognosce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus ac vniuersae naturae ordinem, &amp;c.</hi> That is, to knowe the tymes and vniuersall order of nature. And doubtlesse,
<pb facs="8"/>
who so well consydereth the marueylous effectes that are caused, especially by the variable moouing of the Sunne in the Zodiacke, must needes acknowledge it to be the chiefe instrument and meane that God vseth in the generation, preserua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion, and alteration of all creatures that are contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the world of generation and corruption. And for this consyderation, certayne of the auncient Philosophers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it the soule of the world: Other, the eye: and other also the hart of the world. <hi>Plato</hi> also affyrmeth, that the soule of the world is the Sunne, and that all other lyuing things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue lyfe from thence. And hereof commeth the saying of the Philosopher, <hi>Sol &amp; homo, generant hominem:</hi> (that is) the Sunne and man, beget man. And therefore (as wryteth <hi>Marcilius Ficinus</hi>) of all Idolaters they are most tollerable that honor the Sunne for God. The which, although it be not, yet vndoubtedly are his effects so great and wonderfull in this inferiour world, that it may seeme in manner to be Gods Vicegerent, Liefetenant, and Viceroy, in all the works of nature, except where and when it pleaseth him in any thing miraculously, otherwise then by the common order and course of nature, to commaund the contrarie.</p>
   <p>And if it may not be tedious vnto you (right Honorable and Worshipfull) it shalbe a pleasure vnto me, for the better declaration hereof, to make a briefe discourse of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueylous and strange effects that are caused by the Sunne: which perhaps few haue done, otherwise then dispearsedly here and there, as occasion hath serued. Fyrst therefore let vs consyder what it hath done ouer the Equinoctial lyne, and vnder both the Poles at one instant, diuersly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traryly the one to the other. For so hath the infinite wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the great God of nature, the supreame Architec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the vniuersall world, disposed all things in such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect order, that to them that are vnder the Equinoctial, and haue theyr Horizon passing by the two Poles, the day is of twelue houres, and the nyght as much, and theyr yeere also is deuided into twelue monethes: But they that dwell iust and perpendiculerly vnder our Pole, and that haue theyr
<pb facs="8"/>
Horizon passing ouer the sayd lyne, haue the day of the sixe monethes: That is to say, beginning from the tenth day of March, when the Sunne commeth ouer the sayde Horizon, vntill it returne to passe vnder the same at the tenth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. And contrarywyse, one night of sixe moneths haue the inhabitantes vnder the Pole An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>articke: whose yeere (that is to say, all the course that the Sunne maketh by the twelue signes of the Zodiacke) is accomplished in one day and one nyght: a thing doubtlesse most wonderfull and marueylous. Lykewise, when we haue sommer, they that are vnder our Pole, haue the day of sixe monethes, and they of the opposite or contrary Pole, haue their night of the same length. Againe, when it is winter with vs, then vnder our Pole is the night of the said sixe monethes, and vnder the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite Pole, is the day of the same length. So that, as it were, course by course, when we haue the night, they haue the day: and contrarywyse, whē we haue the day, they haue the night. The which, although it be so long, &amp; of so great space of time, yet is it not continually obscured with darkenesse. For the Sunne maketh his course in such order, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that part, liue not during that time altogeather in darknesses, as Moles liue vnder the ground, but as other creatures that liue vpon the globe and face of the Earth, they haue such lyght as may suffyse to susteyne and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne their life. For the body of the Sunne declyneth no more either beneath the Equinoctial line, either aboue the same line (which is the Horizon to both the Poles) then 23. degrees, that is to say, no lower or higher then the Tropikes, which are no more then 23. degrees, or there about, from the sayd Equinoctial, that is their Horizon, as is aforesayd. And yet in these 23. degrees, he maketh not his course by the opposite Diameter, but goeth continually round about in circuite: so that his beames reuerberating heauen, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent such a manner of lyght, as wee haue in Sommer two houres before the Sunne rise. And this example whiche we haue taken of the diuersitie of the Horizons of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial, and vnder the two Poles, is to demonstrate the
<pb facs="9"/>
marueylous effect that the Sunne maketh, departing from the xij. houres of the Equinoctiall (that is to say, from <hi>Aries</hi> to <hi>Libra</hi>) and comming by lytle and lytle, illuminating the Globe of the earth, and so reducing the yeere of xij. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes, into one onely day, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d one night, as is sayd before. Vnder the infinite varietie of the which course, sometyme with long dayes, and sometime with short, all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the world are fourmed and disposed, of such strength and complexion of body, that euery of them are proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of the Climate assigned vnto them, be it hote or colde, and may dwell and abide there, as in their naturall place and temperament, not lamenting, or desiring to dwell else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, so great a loue resteth in them to their natiue situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But not to depart from the vyage which the Sunne maketh in one whole yeere, as sometime approching neere vnto vs, and sometime departing from vs, I say, that at one selfe same time, in diuers partes vpon the round Globe of the earth, it causeth the Spring, Sommer, Autumne, and Winter. And neuerthelesse, at the same instant and punct of time, it maketh day and high noone in one place, and nyght and midnight on the opposite part. The which varietie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it appeare incomprehensible to the slendernesse of our wits, yet beholding the same with the eyes of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, and therewith considering the vnestimable moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that the Sunne maketh continually, we shall fynde it to be true, hauing respect to the diuers situations of the earth, as it is continually illuminate more or lesse by the Sunne. And this varietie is made with such a harmonie and consonancie, and such a lawe perpetuall and immutable, that yf any poynt or pricke thereof should fayle, it is to be doubted lest the Elements should be confounded together, and returne to their first <hi>Chaos.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And to haue sayd thus much of the wonderfull effects of the course of the Sunne, it may suffise for an example to prooue how necessary a thing it is, not onely for all Pilots and Sea men to haue the knowledge heereof, but also for all other such as shall attempt great and farre voyages in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen
<pb facs="9"/>
lands, and strange countreys, as did of late Maister <hi>Ienkinson,</hi> a worthy Gentleman, set foorth by you, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined at your charges, more like an Ambassadour sent from any Prince or Emperour, then from a company of Merchant men. Wherein, what commendation you haue deserued, to the increase of your perpetuall fame and honour, I referre it to that I haue sayd before. And as touching Maister <hi>Ienkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> what trauayles, paynes, and dangers he hath susteyned, and hardly escaped, and what diligence and arte he hath vsed in the searching of strange countreys, and in the description of those his voyages, it were but in vayne for me to wryte much vnto you, vnto whome the same is better knowen then to me. And therefore to conclude, with rendering iust commendations both vnto you and him, I can say no more, but as <hi>Plato</hi> wryteth in his Booke <hi>De Legibus, Decens est eos ciues laudibus ornare, qui corporis vel animi viribus, res arduas praecláras que gesserunt, &amp; legibus libenter paruerunt.</hi> That is to say, It is decent to commend those Citizens, that by theyr industry of body and minde, haue done great affayres, and haue wyllyngly obeyed good lawes. And thus eftsoones de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siryng your Honors and Worships to accept in good part whatsoeuer I haue sayd of good will and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you and your proceedings, and with your shield of iustice and auctoritie, to defend me against the assaults of such as are enimies to vertue, and captious of other mens doings, I rest at your commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the vttermost of my power, to do you what seruice I may.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>