<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Henrichard, Ia.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111374_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13071</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111374</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Henrichard, Ia.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The curtaine of Church-povver and authoritie in things called indifferent : Drawne and laid open, to shew the many infectious sores and maladies they bring in, and cover. Together with sundry infallible reasons, proving that the service of God, and the generall good of th Church and common wealth require that they should be abolished. By Ia: Henric</title>
                 <author>Henric, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 107, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>VVEe may see cleerly how it oft fareth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Christ and the Churches, by that which he said against the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises, when he proved that in divers particulars they had made the word of God of none effect through theire tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Church of Rome hath in that evill exceeded them,<note place="margin">Marc. 8.6. to 14.</note> Bellarmin, in his <hi>4</hi> book of the unwritten word of God Chap. <hi>2.</hi> making three sorts of traditions, calleth one <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> which he saith <hi>are introduced from ancient customes by the Prelates, or by the people, and creepingly, by the si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and unquestioning agreement of the people, have gained as it were strength of law:</hi> with such are wee to deale.<note place="margin">Sess. 21. Chap. 1.2.</note> The Councell of Trent declareth that <hi>this power hath the Church alwayes had in ministring of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> (haveing their substance) <hi>to ordaine or alter that which she judged to be most expedient for the vtilitie of those that receive them.</hi> I could wish the Church of England, at least in her practise, had never incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to such kind of opinions and traditions. But conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how things goe there, I thought my selfe so much bound to Christ, my Saviour, that I must discover the mischeivous wounds and soares they bring in and cover; that by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God and care of them that are sensible of the hurts, there may happily be found <hi>balme in Gilead to cure them.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 8.22 Lame. 1.12</note> For <hi>stay</hi> and consider <hi>all ye that passe by,</hi> If the Church of England, like the man m the Gospel, that <hi>went downe from Ierusalem to Iericho,</hi> be not fallen <hi>among theeues,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc 10.30 31.32.</note> that have stripped her of her raiment &amp; wounded her; whether many Priests and Levits have not come downe <hi>that way,</hi> and seene her, and <hi>passe by on the other side.</hi> Whether I, seeing the wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re herein manifested,<note place="margin">Vers. 37.</note> could doe lesse
<pb facs="3"/> then have compassion on her; whether I have not, as far as God hath enabled me, <hi>bound</hi> them vp, and powred into them the wine of his law and the <hi>oyle</hi> of the Gospel: whether I had not reason to complaine of them, that have so cruelly hurt her: and if in ought I have donne the part of a <hi>neighbour;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what our Lord saith, <hi>goe thou &amp; doe likewise.</hi> Be not of them <hi>that cover with a covering,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai. 30.1.</note>
      <hi>but not of Gods Spirit.</hi> But rather remember Christs words, <hi>beware of false Prophets, that come to you in sheepes clothing, but inwardly are ravening wolves: ye shal know them by theire fruits.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 7.15. &amp; 16.18.</note>
      <hi>Doe men gather grapes of thornes, or figs of Thistles? A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.</hi> The presbiterie and the hierarchie may bee theese two trees, which thou shalt know by theire fruits, he that seekes the good hath adversaries about the bad. I may find such in this worke: but he that shall judge both them and me is able to defend it. If then they constraine me to say with my Leader. <hi>I have laboured in vaine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 49.3.</note>
      <hi>I have spent my strength for nought,</hi> I shal adde, <hi>yet surely my jugment is with the Lord and my worke with my God.</hi> To his grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and protection, I must commend it, and rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord: <hi>IA: HENRIC.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>