<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the freendly Readers in generall, and specially to all young Gentlemen of Eng∣lande, which most honourably attempteth to get renowne and honour, in thys most famous and renowned exercise: Gyles Clayton sendeth greeting, health to your persons, and happinesse to all your honourable attempts.</title>
           <author>Clayton, Gyles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111148_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18959</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5376</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111148</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the freendly Readers in generall, and specially to all young Gentlemen of Eng∣lande, which most honourably attempteth to get renowne and honour, in thys most famous and renowned exercise: Gyles Clayton sendeth greeting, health to your persons, and happinesse to all your honourable attempts.</title>
                 <author>Clayton, Gyles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The approoued order of martiall discipline : with euery particuler offycer his offyce and dutie: with many other stratagemes adioyning to the same. Whereunto is adioyned a second booke, for the true ordering and imbattelling of any number so euer, with the proportions of euery battell, which best serueth in these our dayes of seruice. Newlie written by Gyles Clayton</title>
                 <author>Clayton, Gyles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Kitson, Abraham</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 83 pages, 4 leaves of plates (some folded), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the freendly Readers in generall, and specially to all young Gentlemen of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, which most honourably attempteth to get renowne and honour, in thys most famous and renowned exercise: <hi>Gyles Clayton</hi> sendeth greeting, health to your persons, and happinesse to all your honourable attempts.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (freendlie Readers,) you thinke my labours might haue beene verie well spared, in wryting any matters appertayning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to warres, for that euery man is desirous to liue in securitie of peace: but freendly Readers, you are to vnderstand, that this blessed peace cannot be maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and kept secure, without the vse and practise of warlike weapons, and Martiall discipline. For we are to consider, the ambition of the world is such, that it is vnpossible for a Realme or Dominion, long to continue in quietnes &amp; safegard, where the defence of the sworde and Mtiarall feates of warre is not exercised and practised with discipline. For as the <hi>Greckes</hi> thinking themselues to be in peace and secure, applyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in tryfling matters, taking pleasure in Comaedies, and such like toyes, altogether laying aside Martiall discipline and the exercise of warlike weapons: which gaue occasion to <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> King of <hi>Macaedonia,</hi> father to <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse and to bring them in seruitude vnder his subiection. I could alledge many more which hath beene suppressed, onelie for lacke of the vse of warlike weapons, and thinking thēselues to be in most securitie and peace, as the <hi>Assirians, Persians, Athenians,</hi> &amp; such like. And the Cittie of <hi>Rome,</hi> which might haue beene perpetuall, but thought themselues in peace, and fell to inordinate ryot and pastimes, not doubting nor fearing any thing which was hurtfull vnto them or their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale: which thing was to theyr great ruine and ouerthrowe. Euen so where ouermuch libertie is giuen, men may be troden down vnder foote, and brought to most horrible miserie &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie:
<pb facs="4"/>
if they giue thēselues only to pastimes &amp; pleasures, and forsake the vse and exercise of warlike weapons, which are the defence both of Prince, Country, Religion, iustice, lawes, and subiects: the which are altogether maintained, and protected by Armes onely. And therefore the most famous Conquerers and mightie Captaines did deuise, with most dilligence, all maner of waies, to bring their men to be perfect in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all manner of things appertayning to the warres. As manifestly appeareth, by the warlike Games which the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Grecia</hi> ordained vpon the Mount <hi>Olimpus.</hi> And also by the orders and exercise that the auncient Romans vsed in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places, and specially in <hi>Campo Martio,</hi> and in theyr sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Theaters, which chiefely they builded for that purpose: whereby they made their Souldiours of such experience, that they obtained with small company in fight, against a great multitude of enemies, such wonderfull and meruailous victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as in many credible Histories are mencioned. And also by the same meanes, their stragling people which followed the Campes, gotte such vnderstanding in those actions of Armes, that they in the day of battaile, beeing lest destitute of succour, were able without any other helpe, to sette themselues in good order of battaile, for theyr owne defence against the enemie, and in such times of seruice, they haue doone theyr Countrey great seruice. So that the antiquitie esteemed nothing more happy, then to haue the Country full of men of vnderstanding and knowledge, in warlike actions, and Martiall discipline. Which thing is least regarded in this Realme, &amp; most neede of it: for that we haue so many euill &amp; pestiferous enemies roūd about vs: which are ready continually, if oportunity serue thē, to worke our ruine and decay. Wherfore stirre vp your selues euery man with courage, and boldnes of minde, to the exercise of your warlike weapons, which is honourable, and most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be preferred before all exercises. For the vse heere of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid aside, breedeth more sedicions and warres, then if they were daily had in vse, &amp; so perfectly practised: for experience in seruice, doth much more preuaile, then many multitudes of
<pb facs="5"/>
people, beeing without vnderstanding and knowledge in this most honourable seruice. Wherefore, sith the necessity of this seruice of warre, and Martiall exercise is so great, and also the necessary vse of them so manifest, that euen peace herselfe, in manner, doth challenge her cheefe defence &amp; protection, such is the worthines of Martiall exercises: for as by proofe wee see, that the glory thereof cannot easily finde roote, but in the harts of such most worthy men, which continually exerciseth themselues in these warlike weapons, for the glory of their Prince &amp; Country, and also for their own honour and magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie. Wherfore these exercises being of such force, which bringeth all those that exercise the same to such honour and fame, both of Prince and Countrey, that I would in hart, that all English men, might shewe their good will in the exercise thereof. But hauing so fewe men of experience in these dayes, we see that euery one hauing serued but a yeere or two, it is a great matter. Nay, if he but crosse the Seas, and make hys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode but one month, he is accounted a Souldiour. But for my part, I haue serued these sixteene yeeres in Ireland, and in the Low Countries, and haue seene many peeces of seruice in both places, and yet I dare not account my selfe a Souldiour. For the name of a Souldiour is most honourable, and those that beare the name or title thereof, shoulde be men of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and knowledge, and well experienced in warre, &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall discipline.</p>
   <p>Doe we not find in many places of the holy Scripture, both in the bookes of Moses, in the booke Numbers, in the booke of Iosua, and in diuers other places of the Scripture, where they vsed no little regard, not onely in chusing of theyr Captaines and leaders, but as well in prescribing of Lawes and Martiall discipline of warres, the which in times past were appointed by the Almighty God himselfe: moreouer promised gyfts to those which could perswade the children of Israell. As by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in the booke of Numbers, as I remember, in the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene chapter, howe God promised with his owne mouth to rewarde <hi>Caleb,</hi> for his constancie, &amp; couragious perswasion
<pb facs="5"/>
to the children of Israell. And <hi>Dauid</hi> beeing a man of small ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count among the great Warriours, yet for his worthines and famous behauiour, in killing and ouerthrowing <hi>Goliah:</hi> what great riches and rewards receiued hee, with the Daughter of King <hi>Saul?</hi> But in Englande, we neuer consider, neyther of hys actions, nor of his knowledge and experience: but most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, our Captaines are chosen, more for fauour then for knowledge: more for freendship, then for experience: for if they haue a good opinion in him, they neuer consider his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, whether he be a man able to discharge his place or no. But I haue no doubt, that euery manshalbe hereafter better looked vnto, both for theyr knowledge, as also for their experience &amp; desert. And <hi>Ʋarro</hi> sayth, there be three things not to be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, a wise man vnder the gouernaunce of a foole: a liberall man in subiection to a caytife: and a foole sette in authoritie. Wherfore it is most commonly seene, where good order &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce faileth, obedience decayeth, boldnes increaseth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit escapeth, iniuries preuaileth, auarice corrupteth, and the estate of a Weale publique soone after decayeth. But least I should offend, I will conclude with a fewe other examples, as in Spayne, in Fraunce, in the Low Countries, and many other places, what great intentions are among theyr Princes &amp; Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, the which is a great perrill, and an endangering to their Princes and their Common wealth &amp; Countrey, in an euil and dangerous estate. Wherefore let vs be thankfull to God, for giuing vs so louing and gracious a Princesse, who foreseeth such euill intentions, least they should breede to such incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient sores which may not be cured. For her Maiestie consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, that the strength of her Realme, is the freendship and loue of her people. And <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> sayth, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces liue more safely, in gathering to them men of good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and knowledge, then with theyr treasures of money: for the loue of a Princes Subiects to theyr Prince, is the whole strength of the Lande. And as <hi>Hermes</hi> sayth, vnhappy is that Prince, that esteemeth himselfe happy, to haue his Cofers full of treasure, and his counsaile full of men of euill and corrupt
<pb facs="6"/>
liuing. Also let vs remember the woorthy saying of <hi>Socrates,</hi> who sayth, that if a Prince be mercifull, liberall, and louing, his estate shall prosper, and his wisedome shall helpe him in hys neede. If he be iust, his subiects shall reioyce in him, his Realme shall prosper, &amp; his estate continue: for glorious is that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Common wealth, and fortunate is that Prince, that is Lord of young men to trauaile, and olde sage persons at home, to giue graue and wise counsaile.</p>
   <p>Thus hauing spoken sufficient, I will conclude, most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseeching God, so to blesse her Maiestie, with long life to raigne ouer vs, that wee may by her gracious proceedings be long gouerned. God confound her foes, and bring to lyght all traiterous Conspiratours against her most excellent Maiestie. God so blesse her honourable Counsaile with increase of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that all theyr consultations, may redownd to the safe keeping and honour of this most famous England. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Gyles Clayton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>