<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, William EARLE OF PEMBROKE, Lord Steward of his Majesties most Honourable Houshold. Robert EARLE OF LINDSEY, Great Chamberlaine of ENGLAND. Henrie Lord Hunsdon, Vicount Rochford, Earle of Dover. And all your Honourable Friends and Well-willers.</title>
           <author>Smith, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111906_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12471</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, William EARLE OF PEMBROKE, Lord Steward of his Majesties most Honourable Houshold. Robert EARLE OF LINDSEY, Great Chamberlaine of ENGLAND. Henrie Lord Hunsdon, Vicount Rochford, Earle of Dover. And all your Honourable Friends and Well-willers.</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true travels, adventures, and observations of Captaine Iohn Smith, in Europe, Asia, Affrica, and America, from anno Domini 1593. to 1629 : His accidents and sea-fights in the straights; his service and stratagems of warre in Hungaria, Transilvania, Wallachia, and Moldavia, against the Turks, and Tartars ... After how he was taken prisoner by the Turks, sold for a slave ... and escaped ... Together with a continuation of his generall History of Virginia, Summer-Iles, New England, and their proceedings, since 1624. to this present 1629; as also of the new plantations of the great river of the Amazons, the iles of St. Christopher, Mevis, and Barbados in the West Indies. All written by actuall authours, whose names you shall finde along the history</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Reeve (Reave), James.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 60 pages, folded plates, illustrations (engraving, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, William EARLE OF <hi>PEMBROKE,</hi> Lord Steward of his Majesties most Honourable Houshold. Robert EARLE OF <hi>LINDSEY,</hi> Great Chamberlaine of ENGLAND. Henrie Lord <hi>Hunsdon,</hi> Vicount <hi>Rochford,</hi> Earle of <hi>Dover.</hi> And all your Honourable Friends and Well-willers.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lords:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR <hi>Robert Cotton,</hi> that most learned Treasurer of Antiquitie, having by perusall of my Generall Historie, and others, found that I had likewise un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone divers other as hard hazards in the other parts of the world, reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted me to fix the whole course of my passages in a booke by it selfe, whose noble desire I could not but in part satisfie; the rather, because
<pb facs="4"/>
they have acted my fatall Tragedies upon the Stage, and rac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked my Relations at their pleasure. To prevent therefore all future misprisions, I have compiled this true discourse. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie hath taxed me to have writ too much, and done too little; but that such should know, how little I esteeme them, I have writ this, more for the satisfaction of my friends, and all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and well disposed Readers: To speake only of my selfe were intolerable ingratitude; because, having had so many co-partners with me; I cannot make a Monument for my selfe, and leave them unburied in the fields, whose lives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got me the title of a Souldier; for as they were companions with me in my dangers, so shall they be partakers with me in this Tombe.</p>
   <p>For my <hi>Sea Grammar</hi> (caused to bee printed by my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy friend, Sir <hi>Samuel Saltonstall</hi>) hath found such good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment abroad, that I have beene importuned by many noble persons, to let this also passe the Presse. Many of the most eminent Warriers, and others, what their swords did, their penns writ: Though I bee never so much their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, yet I hold it no great errour, to follow good examples; nor repine at them, will doe the like.</p>
   <p>And now my most Honourable good Lords, I know not to whom I may better present it, than to your Lordships, whose friendships, as I conceive, are as much to each others, as my duty is to you all; and because you are acquainted both with my endevours, and writings, I doubt not, but your honours will as well accept of this, as of the rest, and Patronize it under the shadow of your most noble vertues, which I am ever bound in all duty to reverence, and under which I hope to have shelter, against all stormes that dare threaten.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours to be commanded, <hi>IOHN SMITH.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>