<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST IL∣LVSTRIOVS AND euery waies accomplisht Prince, George, Duke of Buckingham, Viscount Villers, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of England, Iustice in Eyre of all his Maiesties For∣rests, Parkes, and Chases beyond Trent, Master of the Horse to his Maiestie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maiesties Bed-Cham∣ber, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most honourable Priuie Coun∣sell of England and Scotland.</title>
           <author>Marceline, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111979_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06875</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17308</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111979</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST IL∣LVSTRIOVS AND euery waies accomplisht Prince, George, Duke of Buckingham, Viscount Villers, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of England, Iustice in Eyre of all his Maiesties For∣rests, Parkes, and Chases beyond Trent, Master of the Horse to his Maiestie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maiesties Bed-Cham∣ber, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most honourable Priuie Coun∣sell of England and Scotland.</title>
                 <author>Marceline, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Epithalamium Gallo-Britannicum : or, Great-Britaines, Frances, and the most parts of Europes vnspeakable ioy, for the most happy vnion, and blessed contract of the high and mighty Prince Charles, Prince of Wales, and the Lady Henrette Maria, daughter to Henry the fourth, sirnamed the Great, late King of the French and Nauarre, and sister to Levvis the thirteenth: now king of the said dominions. Manifesting the royall ancestors and famous progenitors of the mighty Prince Charles, and the most illustrious princesse, the Lady Henrette, explaining the sweete interchanges of mariages, as haue beene betweene France and Great Britaine. Presaging the destruction and ruine of Antichrist, the establishment of the true faith, the propagation of the Gospell, the restitution of the Palatinate, the ouer-throwing of the enemies designes, the erection of peace, the increase of plentie, and the generall well-fare of all christendome</title>
                 <author>Marcelline, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 142, 2 pages, folded plates, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MOST IL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVSTRIOVS AND euery waies accomplisht Prince,</hi> George, <hi>Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>Viscount</hi> Villers, <hi>Baron of</hi> Whaddon, <hi>Lord High Admirall of</hi> England, <hi>Iustice in Eyre of all his Maiesties</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests, Parkes, and Chases beyond <hi>Trent,</hi> Master of the Horse to his Maiestie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maiesties Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most honourable Priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of England and Scotland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost honoured Prince; let it be no wonder vnto your Grace, why I doe implore your Ioynt Patronage with your Prince, of these my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb facs="6"/>sith you are his <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and haue beene a companion and faithfull friend vnto him in all his Trauells; manifesting your selfe to bee as faithfull to that Sonne, as you were fauoured of the Father. As therefore you were his Associate in his Peregrination, so ioyne with him in the Patronizing of this worke: Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as you were a chiefe instrument of hindring the mariage with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and furthering this with <hi>France,</hi> by which meanes, you brought happinesse vnto this Iland, for the which, it yeeldeth vnto your Grace; so also you are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this worke, and a ioynt Subiect of it; vouchsafe therefore to be a ioynt Patron of it.</p>
   <p>A fourth Motiue which encourageth me in this request, is, that as you are the chiefe Fauourite of our King on earth, and of God the King of Kings, so you are aprincipall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer of all good and worthy proceedings, by which your name is embalmed with fame, and your memory will bee immortall. Not doubting therefore but you will grace this worke with milde acceptance, though not for the manner of writing, yet the matter written of in it, I cease to trouble you, but alwaies rest an humble suiter to your grace for accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb facs="6"/>and to God, for the continuance of your happinesse in the present, and your increase of it in the future, that you may bee blessed inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, externally, and eternally, and that the highest would multiplie all temporall and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces vpon your Grace.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your humbly deuoted,</hi> George Marceline.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>