<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Abraham Fleming vppon G. Whetstons worke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111731_Fr1_3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15046</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25348</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111731</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Abraham Fleming vppon G. Whetstons worke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rocke of regard : diuided into foure parts. The first, the castle of delight: wherin is reported, the wretched end of wanton and dissolute liuing. The second, the garden of vnthriftinesse: wherein are many swéete flowers, (or rather fancies) of honest loue. The thirde the arbour of vertue: wherein slaunder is highly punished, and vertuous ladies nad gentlewomen, worthily commended. The fourth, the ortchard of repentance: wherein are discoursed, the miseries that followe dicing, the mischiefes of quareling, the fall of prodigalitie: and the souden ouerthrowe of foure notable cousners, with diuers other morall, natural, &amp; tragical discourses: documents and admonitions: being all the inuention, collection and translation of George Whetstons Gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walley (Waley), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 128, 121, that is 123, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>Abraham Fleming vppon G. Whetstons worke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>Who wisheth with pleasure refreshed to bée,</l>
      <l>A Castle of comfort and passing delight,</l>
      <l>Erected of purpose, (loe) here hée may sée,</l>
      <l>And painted with colours of pure blacke and white,</l>
      <l>No bulworcke, no fortresse more strongly prepard,</l>
      <l>And therefore well named the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Regard.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who wisheth for vauntage, to vewe and behold,</l>
      <l>Unthriftines Garden where wéedes do abound,</l>
      <l>Hée hath leaue to enter, and is not controld,</l>
      <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>