<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honourable VVilliam Earle
of Darby, Lord Stanly, Lord Strange, of Knocking
and of the Isle of Man, and Knight of the most noble Order
of the Garter. Francis Pilkington wisheth health, with increase
of Honour in this life, and Eternitie heereafter.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111835_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09653</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111835</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honourable VVilliam Earle
of Darby, Lord Stanly, Lord Strange, of Knocking
and of the Isle of Man, and Knight of the most noble Order
of the Garter. Francis Pilkington wisheth health, with increase
of Honour in this life, and Eternitie heereafter.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of songs or ayres of 4. parts : vvith tableture for the lute or orpherian, vvith the violl de gamba. Newly composed by Francis Pilkington, Batcheler of Musick, and lutenist: and one of the Cathedrall Church of Christ, in the citie of Chester</title>
                 <author>Pilkington, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right honourable VVilliam Earle
of Darby, Lord Stanly, Lord Strange, of Knocking
and of the Isle of Man, and Knight of the most noble Order
of the Garter. <hi>Francis Pilkington</hi> wisheth health, with increase
of Honour in this life, and Eternitie heereafter.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ristoxenus</hi> (thrice noble Lord) held that
the Soule of man was Musicke: But that
the being thereof was framed of Bumbees,
as the Pithagorians affirme: But for that it
is the subiect and obiect of all harmonicall
concents: Intimating heereby the dignitie
and high renowne of that Art, which des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
from so noble a stemme, seeketh by
all meanes possible to nobilitate the same,
and that man to bee vnfit for the society and commerce of men, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth
not so worthy a Jewell for the life of man. Which opinion verely
is worthy <hi>Aristoxenus,</hi> that is to say, a noble Philosopher, yet how litle
squaring with the time, experience a perfect Mistresse of truth hath a
long time taught. For who regardeth the melodius charmes of <hi>Orpheus,</hi>
or enchanting melodie of <hi>Arion?</hi> surely but a few, <hi>Quos aequus ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit
Iupiter dijs geniti, aut ardeus euexit ad aethera virtus.</hi> Of which
rancke seeing your Lordship hath giuen vndoubted testimonies of your
honour to bee one: Musitions should commit an vndiscreet part of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude
not to acknowledge so great a fauour. For mine owne part (who
am meanest of many which professe this diuine skill, though not meanest
in good will &amp; humble affection to your Honor) I must confesse my selfe
many waies obliged to your Lordships familie, not onely, for that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
and Brother receiued many graces of your Honours noble Father,
whom they followed, but that my self had the like of your most honorable
Brother, euen from the first notice he chanced to take of mee. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
(most honourable Lord) I haue heere presented this oblation, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
meane, a token of mine affectionate good will Loue, yea onely
deuoted to your Lordship, which if it may gaine your gracious acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
will feare neither <hi>Zoilus</hi> nor <hi>Momus</hi> his reprehension.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all dutie</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>