<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIP∣full his louing Brother Nicho∣las Turberuille Esquire.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111446_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14024</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24330</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111446</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIP∣full his louing Brother Nicho∣las Turberuille Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tragicall tales translated by Turberuile in time of his troubles out of sundrie Italians, with the argument and lenuoye to eche tale</title>
                 <author>Turberville, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>200 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full his louing Brother Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Turberuille Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit your many and great curtesies bestowed on me, deserue sundry, and no slender thankes from me: Neuerthelesse mine insufficiencie pleading for mine excuse, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sabilitie dealing in my behalfe, doe hope to receiue from you no lesse good liking for a small req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>all, than he that ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lds you a treble recompence. Let it suffise that J liue no vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>indfull man of your goodness, nor will be found vngratefull for your gentle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness,
<pb facs="3"/>if euer fortune fauour my desires or allow me mean to make leuell with your good desarts. Till when, I present you this little boke, as well the vndoubted badge of my good remēbr̄ace, as the gretest par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of my slender substance. Following herein seabeaten soldiers, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable mariners, who in auncient age aster their happy ariuals, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stomed to hang vp in the temple before their sacred Goddes, their brokē oares, &amp; ragged sayles, with such like reliks, the assured monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their lametable fortunes and persit pledges of late escaped dangers. Which cōmendable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome
<pb facs="3"/>of those thankefull Ethnicks I both alow for good, and follow at this instant as fully apperteyning to my present <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>late, in dedicating to you these few Poeticall parers, and pensine Pamphlets, the rusul records of my former trauel, in the sorowful sea of my late misa duen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: which hauing the more spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily by your carefull and brotherly endeuour, ouerpassed &amp; escaped could not but offer you this treatise in lieu of a more large liberalitie, &amp; in steed of a greater gift, presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of good acceptance at your hādes, who haue alwayes been my most assured shielde, and strongest
<pb facs="4"/>slay in all my life. Wherefore take these (I pray you) in no worse part than meane them, and at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure for your pleasure peruse them, excusing my lacke of learning, and brooking my want of cunning, both which defaults and imperfections, might haue bene sufficient to haue staied my hastie hande: but that J euer chose rather to be reputed of straungers vnskilfull, than to be condemned of my best friendes for vngratefull: for the one proceedes for lacke of industrie, but that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther growes for want of humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. J leaue to trouble you further, recomending you to the Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> delight you, I pray you peruse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> aught offend you, eftsoone refuse it: if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny history deserue reading▪ of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie respect it: if any seeme vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, doe boldly reiect it. J fauour not the best so well, as J will wish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your trouble in surneying the euill whose indeuour was onely to this ende, to doe you pleasure and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, for your auncient goodness<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> towardes me, that am your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den brother, and wholy to rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yours during life.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>George Turberuile</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>