<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111423_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13441</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23748</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111423</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dog of vvar, or, The trauels of Drunkard, the famous curre of the Round-Woolstaple in Westminster : His seruices in the Netherlands, and lately in France, with his home returne. By Iohn Taylor. The argument and contents of this discourse is in the next page or leafe</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>AN honest, well-knowing and well-knowne Souldier, (whose name for some Reasons I conceale) dwelt lately in <hi>VVestminster</hi>), in the round Woolstaple, he was a man onely for Action, but such Action as Loyalty did alwayes iustifie, either for his Prince, Countrey, or
<pb facs="4"/>
their Deere and neere Freinds or Allies; in such noble designes Hee would and did often with courage, and good Aprouement em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy himselfe in the Low-Countreys, having alwaies with him a little blacke Dogg, whom hee called <hi>Drunkard</hi>; which Curre would (by no meanes) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forsake or leaue him. But lately in these French Warrs, the Dogg being in the Isle of <hi>RHEA,</hi> where
<pb facs="4"/>
his Master (valiantly figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) was vnfortunately slaine, whose death was grieu'd for by as many as knew him; and as the Corps lay dead, the poore louing Masterlesse Dogg would not forsake it, vntil an English Souldier pulld off his Masters Coate, whom the Dog followed to a Boat, by which meanes he came backe to Westminster, wher hee now remaines. Vpon whose fidelity, (for the
<pb facs="5"/>
loue I owed his deseased Master) I haue writ these following lines, to expresse my Adiction to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb, <hi>Loue me and loue my Hound</hi>; I haue a little rubb'd our Gull-gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Roarers ouer the Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combes, and withall I haue not forgotten our nose-wise Prescisians: If the Dogg <hi>Drunkard</hi> doe a little snap at them, I hold it their wisest way to be silent and put it vp, but if they
<pb facs="5"/>
will bee maundring, let them expect what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>