<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Mighty and Graci∣ous King, IAMES the first, King of great Brittaine, and of Ireland.</title>
           <author>Langford, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111072_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20944</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7322</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111072</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Mighty and Graci∣ous King, IAMES the first, King of great Brittaine, and of Ireland.</title>
                 <author>Langford, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Catholicke faith : contained in the booke of the most mightie, and most gracious King Iames the first, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, defender of the faith. Against the answere of N. Coeffeteau, Doctour of Diuinitie, and vicar generall of the Dominican preaching friars. Written in French, by Pierre Du Moulin, minister of the word of God in the church of Paris. Translated into English according to his first coppie, by himselfe reuiewed and corrected</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke (Clerke), Martin.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 187, 190-493, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the most Mighty and Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>King,</hi> IAMES <hi>the first, King</hi> of great Brittaine, and of Ireland.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S your greatnesse, no way needeth our ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, so your exquisite learning wants not any defence. For your greatest enemies, to whom your power is redoubtable, haue your learning in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But were it so that you had vse of any mans pen; yet should you haue litle cause to seeke further then your owne kingdomes, since amongst your subiects there is so great a number of learned men to whom we are in all regards inferiour. Yet notwithstanding, we haue held it necessary to declare vnto the world, that that religion which you defend, is the same which we professe, and that it befits vs to make resistance to such as in your particuler person assault the generall truth. This vndertaking of mine is great, and my abilities but ordinarie; besides, my vocation very laborious; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="4"/>is a tempest a fit time to write in, or a banke of an vnquiet torrent, a fit place for serious meditation. But <hi>SIR,</hi> the perfection of your worke may supply my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for to fight after you cannot be properly termed fighting, but the pursuite of your victory; for though the point of truth be euer sharpe, yet it entreth and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth more or lesse, according to the force, and vigour of the arme. It is not then to be maruelled if it strike cleane through errors, being guided by so strong and powerfull a hand. To you then <hi>SIR</hi> belongs the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this holy worke, to vs remaines the good, and benefit of following your example: for the easiest way to speake well for you, is to speake that which we haue learned of you: neither is it possible, that any one should write well in your defence, that writes not in your imitation. Wherein these my paines, can no way merit to be compared. For your Maiesty poureth out largely with a royall hand into the Threasury of the Sanctuary, whilest I like the poore widow make offer of my mite: the which I do with the more affection, &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, in respect that our Kings participate with you in the cause, and that we do see our crowne already foiled, and our kings life endangered for want of considering those things which your Maiesty in your booke propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: and God grant that your Maiesties warnings be not prophesies, and that our good, mercifull, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious king, who flourisheth equally in peace, as he is fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in warre; being endued with an admired vigor both of body and mind, may be long preserued amongst vs; who hauing had so good experience, and in so many places of our fidelity, will not we hope be displeased with
<pb facs="4"/>this our liberty in defending of our religion, to which we are not drawne by the hatred of any, but by our zeale to the cause of God, and through compassion of the poore peopla: who being carried along with the streame of custome, thinke they do God good seruice to hate vs, yea so farre are they transported as they are become iealous and suspitious of the holy Scriptures, fearing lest by the word of God they should be mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and seduced: for the saluation of whose enthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led soules we would willingly expose our liues: and will not cease daily to pray to God, to enlighten them in the truth: whom we likewise pray that he will preserue your Maiesty from all euill, and blesse your person, and kingdomes, and the Church that liueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the shade and quiet of your gouernment: with praier from my heart I recommend to God, remaining</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From Paris</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the 20. of Ianuary 1610.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble and most obedient seruant, <hi>P. D. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>