<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right ho∣norable
Lorde, Iohn Dudley, Lorde
Lisle, Earle of Warwike, and maister
of the horse to the kynges maiestie: your
assured to commaund Thomas
Wilson.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111753_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15530</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25799</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right ho∣norable
Lorde, Iohn Dudley, Lorde
Lisle, Earle of Warwike, and maister
of the horse to the kynges maiestie: your
assured to commaund Thomas
Wilson.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of rhetorique : for the vse of all suche as are studious of eloquence, sette forth in English, by Thomas Wilson</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 118, leaf 117, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
Lorde, Iohn Dudley, Lorde
Lisle, Earle of Warwike, and maister
of the horse to the kynges maiestie: your
assured to commaund Thomas
Wilson.</head>
   <p>WHen Pyrrhus Kynge of
the Epirotes made battayle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste
the Romaynes, &amp; could
neither by force of Armes, nor
yet by anye Policye wynne cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
stronge holdes: he vsed cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munely
to send one Cineas (a no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble
Oratour, and sometimes scholer to Demost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes)
to perswade with the Capitaynes &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
that were in them, that they shoulde yelde vp
the sayde holde or townes without fyght or resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce.
And so it came to passe, that through the
pithye eloquence of this noble Oratoure, diuers
stronge Castels and Fortresses were peaceablye
geuen vp into the handes of Pirrhus, whyche he
shoulde haue founde verye harde and tedious to
wynne by the sworde. And this thinge was not
Pirrhus himselfe ashamed in his commune talke
to the prayse of the sayde Oratoure, openlye to
confesse: allegynge that Cineas throughe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence
of his tongue, wanne moe Cityes vnto
him, then euer him selfe shoulde els haue bene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
by force to subdue. Good was that Oratour
<pb facs="4"/>
whiche coulde do so muche: &amp; wise was that king
which woulde vse suche a meane. For if the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines
of eloquēce may moue vs, what worthier
thing can there be, thē with a word to winne ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
&amp; whole coūtries? If profite may perswade,
what greater gayne can we haue, then withoute
bloudshed to achiue a conquest? If pleasure may
prouoke vs, what greater delite do we know, thē
to se a whole multitude with the onely talke of a
man rauished &amp; drawen whiche waye him liketh best
to haue them? Boldly then may I aduenture
and without feare steppe forthe to offer that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
your Lordeshyppe, whiche for the dignitye is
so excellente, and for the vse so necessarye: that no
man oughte to be withoute it, whiche either shall
beare rule ouer manye, or muste haue to do wyth
matters of a Realme. Consideringe therfore
your Lordshyps hyghe estate, &amp; worthy callyng,
I knowe nothyng more sittynge wyth your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure,
then to the gyfte of good reason and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandynge,
wherwith we see you notably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,
to ioyne the perfection of Eloquente vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce.
And because that aswell by your Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppes
moste tender imbracynge of all suche as
be learned, as also by your right studious exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
you do euidently declare, not onely what esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
you haue of all learnynge and excellente
qualities ingenerall, but also what a speciall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre
and affection you beare to eloquence: I ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
commende to youre Lordeshyppes tuition
and patronage, thys traictise of Rhethorique, to
<pb facs="4"/>
the ende that both ye maye get some furtheraūce
by the same, &amp; I also be discharged of my faithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
promyse this laste yere made vnto you.</p>
   <p>For where as it pleased you emonge other talke
of learnynge, earnestlye to wyshe that ye myghte
one daye see the Preceptes of Rhetorique sette forthe
by me in Englyshe, as I hadde erste done
the Rules of Logique: hauynge in my Countrey
thys laste Somer a quiet time of vacation wyth
the ryghte worshypfull sir Edwarde Dymmoke
Knyghte: I traueyled so muche as my leasure
myghte serue therunto, not onelye to declare my
good harte to the satisfiynge of youre requeste in
that behalfe, but also throughe that your mocion
to helpe the towardnes of some other, not so well
furnished as your Lordeshyppe is. For as
touchinge your selfe, by the tyme that perfect ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
of manifolde and weyghtye matters of
the commune weale, shall haue encreased the elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
whyche alreadye dothe naturallye flowe
in you: I doubt nothing but that you wil so farre
be better then this my boke, that I shal not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
blowshe to chalenge you for a Scholer, in
the Arte of Rhetorique, by me rudelye sette for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the:
but also be driuen to sette this simple Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
to your Lordshyppe to Schole, that it may
learne Rhetorique of youre daylye talke, fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge
you suche an Oratoure in your speach, as
greate Clarckes do declare what an Oratoure
shoulde be.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>In the meane season I shall ryghte humblye
beseche your good Lordshippe so to be a Patrone
and defendoure of these my Laboures to you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated:
as I shal be a continuall peticioner
vnto almyghtye God for your preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
and longe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>