<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable my
very good Lord Edward de Vere, Earle
of Oxenford, Vicount Bulbecke, Lord
of Escales, and Badlesmere, and Lord High
Chamberlaine of England, all
happinesse.</title>
           <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111606_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14822</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25118a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111606</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable my
very good Lord Edward de Vere, Earle
of Oxenford, Vicount Bulbecke, Lord
of Escales, and Badlesmere, and Lord High
Chamberlaine of England, all
happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hekatompathia or Passionate centurie of loue : diuided into two parts: whereof, the first expresseth the authors sufferance in loue: the latter, his long farewell to loue and all his tyrannie. Composed by Thomas Watson Gentleman; and published at the request of certaine gentlemen his very frendes</title>
                 <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cawood, Gabriel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, xcviii, 1, xcix-c, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable my
very good Lord Edward de Vere, Earle
of Oxenford, Vicount Bulbecke, Lord
of Escales, and Badlesmere, and Lord High
Chamberlaine of England, all
happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander</hi> the Great, passing on a
time by the workeshop of <hi>Apelles,</hi>
curiouslie surueyed some of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings:
whose long stay in viewing
them, brought all the people into so
great a good liking of the painters
workemanship, that immediatelie after, they bought vp
all his pictures, what price soeuer he set them at.</p>
   <p>And the like good happe, (<hi>Right Honorable,</hi>) befel
vnto mee latelie, concerning these my <hi>Loue Passions,</hi>
which then chaunced to <hi>Apelles,</hi> for his Portraites.
For since the world hath vnderstood, (I know not how)
that your Honor had willinglie voutchsafed the acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance
of this worke, and at conuenient leisures fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie
perused it, being as yet but in written hand, many
haue oftentimes and earnestly called vpon mee, to put it
to the presse, that for their mony they might but see,
what your Lordship with some liking had alreadie peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.
And therewithall some of them said (either to yeeld
<pb facs="3"/>
your Honour his due prayse, for soundnes of iudgement;
or to please me, of whome long since they had conceiued
well) that <hi>Alexander</hi> would like of no lines, but such
as were drawen by the cunning hand, and with the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
pensill of <hi>Apelles.</hi> VVhich I set not downe here to
that end, that I would conferre my Poemes with <hi>Apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi>
Portraites, for worthinesse; albeit I fitlie compare
your Honors person with <hi>Alexanders,</hi> for excellencie.
But how bold soeuer I haue bene, in turning out this my
pettie poore flocke vpon the open Common of the wide
world, where euerie man may behold their nakednesse, I
humbly make request, that if any storme fall vnlooked
for (by the fault of malicious high foreheads, or the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of euill edged tongues) these my little ones maye
shrowde themselues vnder the broad leafed <hi>Platane</hi> of
your Honours patronage. And thus at this present, I
humbly take my leaue; but first wishing the continuall
encrease of your Lordships honour, with abundance of
true Friends, reconciliation of all Foes, and what good
soeuer tendeth vnto perfect happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships humbly at commaund
<hi>Thomas VVatson.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>