<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Honorable the Nobilitie of this florishing Realme of Englande, accomplishment of ae desires.</title>
           <author>Whetstone, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111678_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15033</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111678</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Honorable the Nobilitie of this florishing Realme of Englande, accomplishment of ae desires.</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English myrror : A regard wherein al estates may behold the conquests of enuy: containing ruine of common weales, murther of princes, cause of heresies, and in all ages, spoile of deuine and humane blessings, vnto which is adioyned, enuy conquered by vertues. Publishing the peaceable victories obtained by the Queenes most excellent Maiesty, against this mortall enimie of publike peace and prosperitie, and lastly a fortris against enuy, builded vpon the counsels of sacred Scripture, lawes of sage philosophers, and pollicies of well gouerned common weales: wherein euery estate may see the dignities, the true office and cause of disgrace of his vocation. A worke safely, and necessarie to be read of euerie good subiect. By George Whetstones Gent. Malgre. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Seton, Gregory.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 180, 10, 201-249, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Honorable the Nobilitie of this florishing Realme of Englande, accomplishment of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e desires.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Honorable, the long continuance of her Maiesties most happie gouerment, fullie witnesseth the saying of morall</hi> Diogenes, Vertue onely conquereth Enuy, <hi>for if force or fortune were antidotes against her infections, the ancient monarks had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her venome, and (contrary to other poysons) her breath had not shroonke vp their large Empires, into the length and breadth of their Tombes.</hi> Basill <hi>in his sermon of Enuy, saith, that this passion bendeth her forces against the glorie of God, the peace of Princes, and obedience of subiects, feedeth vppon lamentable chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and pineth to behold the prosperitie of vertue.</hi> Basill <hi>to confirme his censure, had the subuersion of large Empires, ruine of florishing common weales, and (in former ages) the spoile of diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane blessings, whose woonderfull conquests I haue set foorth for three considerations: the first, to shew the mightye prouidence of Almightie God, in defending this little Realme from sundrie the assaultes of so furious an enemie: the second, to inlarge, or rather eternize the glorie of manie her Maiesties peaceable victories a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this bloodie Enuie: the third, to counsell her good subiects by waightie examples, to arme their happinesse with vertue, the onely meane to withstand the puissance of Enuie. They may hardly pleade ignorance, hauing the commandements of sacred scripture, the lawes of sage Philosophers, and policies of good common wealthes men, to instruct euerie of them in the offices and duties of theyr vocation, Right Honorable, this is in effect the reach of my trauell, which I hope will entertaine the discreete Reader with many other perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar benefites. Vnto you most noble Lords, I reuerently direct this first part, which (some wayes) medleth with the sword, and the rest</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>I present according to the qualitie of the subiete: which considered by the morall substance, may (with your fauour I say it) be a Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of gouernement for all good subiects. The further censure thereof, I humblie submit to your Lorships leysurable reading: and for your health, honor, and prosperitie, as the bewtie and strength (next vnto God and her Maiestie) of this happie gouernment, my daily prayers shall not be forgotten.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At vvhose right Honorable Lordships commaundements I humblie remaine.
George Whetstones.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>