<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honorable my singular good Lorde Sir Nicolas Bacon Knight, Lord keper of the great seale of England.</title>
           <author>Digges, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111670_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20458</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6858</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111670</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honorable my singular good Lorde Sir Nicolas Bacon Knight, Lord keper of the great seale of England.</title>
                 <author>Digges, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A geometrical practise, named Pantometria : diuided into three bookes, longimetra, planimetra, and stereometria, containing rules manifolde for mensuration of all lines, superficies and solides: with sundry straunge conclusions both by instrument and without, and also by perspectiue glasses, to set forth the true description or exact plat of an whole region: framed by Leonard Digges gentleman, lately finished by Thomas Digges his sonne. Who hathe also thereunto adioyned a mathematicall treatise of the fiue regulare Platonicall bodies, and their Metamorphosis or transformation into fiue other equilater vniforme solides Geometricall, of his owne inuention, hitherto not mentioned of by any geometricians</title>
                 <author>Digges, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>260 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honorable my singular good Lorde Sir Nicolas Bacon Knight, Lord keper of the great seale of England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Alling to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie right honourable, and my singular good Lorde, the great fauour your Lordship bare my father in his life time, and the conference it pleased your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to vse vvith him touching the Sciences Mathematicall, especially in Geometrical mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surations, perusing also of late certaine volumes that he in his youthe time long sithens had compiled in the English tongue, among other I found this <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall practise,</hi> vvhich my father (if God had spared him life) minded to haue presented your Honoure vvithall, but vntimely Death preuenting his determination, I thought it my part to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish the same, asvvell for the satisfaction of his desire, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to shevve my selfe not vnmindfull of so many good turnes as your honor from time to time most aboundantly hath bestovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on me, hauing therfore supplied such partes of this treatise as
<pb facs="3"/>
vvere left obscure or vnperfect, adioyning therunto a Discourse Geometricall of the fiue regulare or Platonicall bodyes, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning sundry Theoricall and practicall propositions of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde proportions arising by mutuall conference of these solides <hi>Inscription, Circumscription</hi> or <hi>Transformation,</hi> and novv at the last fully finished the same, I am bolde to exhibite and dedicate it to your honor, as an eternall memoriall of your Lordshippes great fauoure tovvardes the furtherance of learning, and a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like testimonie of my bounden duetie: hoping your honor vvill rather respect the good vvill vvherevvith it is presented, than the vvorthinesse of the present, not agreeable I confesse to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent knovvledge vvhervvith your Lordship is indued, euen in the very fountains thēselues vvhence these conclusions as springs or braunches are deriued. And yet suche as I nothing dout your honor vvill both accept in good parte, and also at vacant leysure from affaires of more importance, delite your selfe vvithall, the rather for that it containeth sundry suche nevve inuented <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remes,</hi> and other straunge conclusions, as no Geometers haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, in any language published. Wherby your Lordship shall not only incourage me heereafter to attempt greater matters, but also as it vvere vvith a soueraigne medicine preuent the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned infection of enuious backbiting tongues: for as the veritie of these experimentes and rules shall neuer be impugned, being so firmely grounded, garded, and defended vvith Geometricall demonstration, against vvhose puissance no subtile Sophistrie or craftie coloured arguments can preuaile, so think I there is none so impudently malitious, as vvill or dare reproue them for vaine or improfitable, vvhen they shall perceiue your Lordshippe, (vvhose learned iudgement, grauitie and vvisedome is sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knovven to the vvorld) doth allovv and accepte them as fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grante floures selecte and gathered out of the pleasant gardynes Mathematicall, meete to delite any noble, free, or vvell disposed minde, and profitable frutes seruing most commodiouslye to sundry necessary vses in a publike vveale, and suche as shall ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="3"/>
receyue pleasure or commoditie, muste of duetie yelde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne thankes vnto your Lordshippe, vnder vvhose protection and patronage I haue not feared to sende abroade (as a vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring pilgrime) this Orphane and fatherlesse child, the vvhich as I perceiue of your Honour fauourably accepted, so meane I, God sparing life, to imploy no small portion of this my shorte and transitorie time in storing our natiue tongue vvith Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall demonstrations, and some suche other rare experiments and practicall conclusions, as no forrayne Realme hath hytherto been, I suppose, partaker of. In the meane time I leaue longer to detayne your honour vvith my rude and homely tale, from more seriouse and vvaygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affayres, committing youre Lordshippe to the tuition of the Almightie, vvho graunte you a long healthfull honorable life, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed vvith perfecte felicitie,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours moste bounden <hi>Thomas Digges.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>