<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Lyly to the Authour his friend.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111606_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14822</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25118a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111606</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Lyly to the Authour his friend.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hekatompathia or Passionate centurie of loue : diuided into two parts: whereof, the first expresseth the authors sufferance in loue: the latter, his long farewell to loue and all his tyrannie. Composed by Thomas Watson Gentleman; and published at the request of certaine gentlemen his very frendes</title>
                 <author>Watson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cawood, Gabriel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, xcviii, 1, xcix-c, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="Lyly_to_author">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Iohn Lyly to the Authour his friend.</head>
   <p>MY good friend, I haue read your new passions, and they
haue renewed mine old pleasures, the which brought
to me no lesse delight, thē they haue done to your selfe
commendations. And certes had not one of mine eies about se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
affaires beene watchfull, both by being too too busie had
beene wanton: such is the nature of persuading pleasure, that
it melteth the marrowe before it scorch the skin, and burneth
before it warmeth: Not vnlike vnto the oyle of Ieat, which
rotteth the bone and neuer ranckleth the flesh, or the Scarab
flies, which enter into the roote and neuer touch the rinde.</p>
   <p>And whereas you desire to haue my opinion, you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
that my stomake is rather cloyed, then quesie, &amp; therfore
mine appetite of lesse force thē mine affection, fearing rather
a surfet of sweetenes, then desiring a satisfying. The repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of Loue, wrought in me a remembrance of liking, but ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
the very vaines of my hearte, I could finde nothing but
a broad scarre, where I left a deepe wounde: and loose stringes,
where I tyed hard knots: and a table of steele, where I framed
a plot of wax.</p>
   <p>Whereby I noted that young swannes are grey, &amp; the olde
white, yoūg trees tender, &amp; the old tough, young mē amorous,
&amp; growing in yeeres, either wiser or warier. The Corall in the
water is a soft weede, on the land a hard stone: a sworde frieth
in the fire like a blacke ele, but layd in earth like white snowe:
the heart in loue is altogether passionate, but free from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire,
altogether carelesse.</p>
   <p>But it is not my intent to inueigh against loue, which womē
account but a bare word, &amp; that mē reuerence as the best God:
onely this I would add without offence to Gentlewomen, that
were not men more supersticious in their praises, thē womē are
<pb facs="5"/>
constant in their passions: Loue would either shortly be worne
out of vse, or men out of loue, or women out of lightnes. I cā cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
none but by cōiecture, nor commend any but by lying,
yet suspicion is as free as thought, and as farre as I see as neces<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sary,
as credulitie.</p>
   <p>Touching your Mistres I must needes thinke well, seeing
you haue written so well, but as false glasses shewe the fairest
faces, so fine gloses amēd the baddest fancies. Apelies painted
the Phenix by hearesay not by sight, and Lysippus engraued
Vulcan with a streight legge, whome nature framed with a
poult foote, which proueth men to be of greater affection then
iudgement. But in that so aptly you haue varied vppon wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
I will not vary from you, for confesse I must, and if I
should not, yet mought I be compelled, that to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oue were the
sweetest thing in the earth: If women were the faithfullest, &amp;
that women would be more constant if men were more wise.
And seeing you haue vsed mee so friendly, as to make me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
with your passions, I will shortly make you pryuie to
mine, which I woulde be loth the printer shoulde see, for that
my fancies being neuer so crooked he would put thē in streight
lines, vnfit for my humor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, necessarie for his art, who setteth
downe, blinde, in as many letters as seeing.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>