<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the most vertuous lady and most gratious Queene Marye, doughter vnto the most victorious and most noble prynce, Kynge Henry the eyght, kyng of Englande, Fraunce and Ireland. &amp;c. Thomas Paynell wysheth moste prosperous helth and felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1558</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111448_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14009</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24318</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111448</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the most vertuous lady and most gratious Queene Marye, doughter vnto the most victorious and most noble prynce, Kynge Henry the eyght, kyng of Englande, Fraunce and Ireland. &amp;c. Thomas Paynell wysheth moste prosperous helth and felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine godly and deuout prayers. Made in latin by the Reuerend father in God, Cuthbert Tunstall, Bishop of Durham, and translated into Englishe by Thomas Paynell, clerke</title>
                 <author>Tunstall, Cuthbert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1558</date>
                 <publisher>Cawood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harvey, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the most vertuous lady and most gratious Queene Marye, doughter vnto the most victorious and most noble prynce, Kynge Henry the eyght, kyng of Englande, Fraunce and Ireland. &amp;c. Thomas Paynell wysheth moste prosperous helth and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> euen from youre tender age hetherto, hath euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and continuallye geuen youre selfe to all kynd of vertue &amp; prayer, the pure refection, and fode of the spirite and soule of man: I your graces dayly orator, to encreace (yf it may be encresyd) and augment your deuotion, and spirituall meditations, haue transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted these fewe and compendious prayers, written in laten, most deuoutly and lerned<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, by the reuerend father in god, Cutbert Tunstall, for the spirituall consolation of
<pb facs="3"/>
all deuout christians, christianly to accept and embrace thē, &amp; with celestial meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vertuosly to vse thē. For in these orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; prayers, is nothing else cōprised, but the sincere &amp; true word of God, our mooste consolatiō &amp; comfort, with a certen general confession, so christianly &amp; deuoutly indy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; knit together, that no mortall mā (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte he be stonye hartyd) can rede it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out teares &amp; remorse of cōscience. I would wyshe therefore (yf I may be so bold as to wyshe your grace a good tourne) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> youre hyghnes with the whole company of your vertuous ladics, &amp; chaste damselles, youre graces most beautifull &amp; pleasant maydēs, wold whan oportunitie of tyme shal serue, pervse these heuenlye prayers, deuoutelye rede them, &amp; continually mynd and record them: For they wel waide and considered: shalbe vnto the spirituall reder an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall comforte both of bodye &amp; soule, and to your grace a heuenly consolation and pleasure. Thus our Lorde Iesus preserue your grace. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>▪</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>