<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Master Vaughan the Author of
the Golden-groue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111527_Fr1_13</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14293</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24610</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111527</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Master Vaughan the Author of
the Golden-groue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden-groue : moralized in three bookes: a worke very necessary for all such, as would know how to gouerne themselues, their houses, or their countrey. Made by W. Vaughan, Master of Artes, and student in the ciuill law</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>416 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To Master Vaughan the Author of
the Golden-groue.</head>
   <l>WHile thou in sacred studies dost bestow</l>
   <l>Thy watchfull houres these thanklesse times among,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>
Frō learnings root three vertuous brāches grow,</l>
   <l>Charming the pow'rs of euery Muses song</l>
   <l>To leaue their two-topt hill, and for a space</l>
   <l>In thy fresh Groue their mutual selues embrace.</l>
   <l>Thy Golden-groue, thy euer-blooming spring,</l>
   <l>Thy vertues nurserie, thy wits deere brood,</l>
   <l>Where like the Graces dauncing in a ring stroue,</l>
   <l>Three sciences inuite the publike good.</l>
   <l>Needs must the Groue, where these fair vertues</l>
   <l>Be thought a precious and a golden Groue.</l>
   <l>The morall Nymph with deep discretion goes,</l>
   <l>The Oeconomick with a carefull eye;</l>
   <l>The Politike the state of kingdoms knowes;</l>
   <l>Treating of Nations, counsels, maiestie.</l>
   <l>The seuerall places of their best renowne,</l>
   <l>And obiects are the heart, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> house, the crown.</l>
   <l>Now let the heart estraunged at the last,</l>
   <l>(If any such the Golden-groue inherite)</l>
   <l>Behold the seat where Equity is plac'd</l>
   <l>With due regard of an impartiall spirit.</l>
   <l>And so preferre an honest Ethicke praise,</l>
   <l>Before he come to Politike essayes.</l>
   <l>Then let this house for Occonomicks worth</l>
   <l>Deserue the title, which it long hath borne.</l>
   <l>No drossie excrement from gold comes forth;</l>
   <l>Then golden as it is, O let it scorne,</l>
   <l>That any dregs or blemishes be found</l>
   <l>To spring frō out that Groue, &amp; fruitful groūd.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>
Let Policie defend the lawfull right,</l>
   <l>Since Countries perish by the hand of wrong.</l>
   <l>Vaughan, the world in censure is vpright,</l>
   <l>Esteeming thee amongst the learned throng.</l>
   <l>If any stonie friend vniustly deale,</l>
   <l>Tis no true Diamond in golden seale.</l>
   <l>Thy worke shall liue, so shal thy Brothers fame,</l>
   <l>But much the more, if he regard thy paine,</l>
   <l>And gratifie thy Muse, that makes his name</l>
   <l>The note of all eternitie to gaine.</l>
   <l>Three ages Nestor liu'd; now (as they be)</l>
   <l>The Muses giue thy Legend three times three.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Storer, Master of Arts.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>