<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE LOYALL AND Generous minded for his Prince and Countries service, the hopefull Mr. EDMOND ELLISON, the Master and Commander in the ship and fight hereafter related.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111380_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13423</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23735</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111380</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE LOYALL AND Generous minded for his Prince and Countries service, the hopefull Mr. EDMOND ELLISON, the Master and Commander in the ship and fight hereafter related.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brave memorable and dangerous sea-fight, foughten neere the road of Tittawan in Barbary : where the George and Elizabeth (a ship of London) under the command of Mr. Edmond Ellison, having but 19. peeces of ordnance, was encompass'd and encountred by nine great Turkish pyrat ships, or men of war, they being in number of men at the least 60. to one; and their ordnance more than ten to one against the English, yet (by Gods assistance) they were encouraged to a resolute fight, and obtained a glorious victory over their miscreant enemies, and a happy returne with men, ship, and goods to London</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 20, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE LOYALL AND Generous minded for his Prince and Countries service, the hopefull M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> EDMOND ELLISON, the Master and Commander in the ship and fight hereafter related.</head>
   <p>SIR, as Childhood brings us to manhood, manhood to old age, and old age to death, so (by consequence) a good life begets fame, which though Time doe seeme to devoure, yet when time is ended, an honest fame shall be invested with Eternitie. For as all the valiant men cannot boast of high birth and great houses, so all dejected and cowardly spirited mungrils are not borne in meane Tenements and poore Cottages: for my part (being a meere stranger unto you) I dare not to delineate your pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, having no skill in honourable <hi>Heraldry;</hi> yet hearing of the worthy forwardnesse, and fortunate endevours of yours, I could not refraine to set my pen to paper to the publishing of your late imminent dangers and most happy deliverance; which
<pb facs="4"/>
by the Almighties blessings, and your valorous fight, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and the worthy and remarkable courage of your few men, for the glory of God and the honour of our Country, you have accomplished. Sir, I did not write this onely for your sake, but for the example of others, that they in the reading of it may in the first place magnifie his great name, who is the giver of all victorie; and secondly to be truly constant in all extremities, by your worthy imitation: for as charitie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to forget mens faults, so it is shame and pittie that vertue and extraordinarie good Actions should be buried in the gulph of oblivion.</p>
   <p>I have made bold to make relation of what you know to be true in action; you doe know best if I have erred, which I hope I have not: I know that you are the sonne of a most worthy, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and serviceable Sea-man, whose old and good improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you doe most filially follow. To close up my dedication, I doe recommend my selfe and my labours to your love, you to your fathers, and both of you to the Almightie, craving par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for my boldnesse, and remaining yours.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>In any service befitting your worth to be commanded,</salute>
      <signed>JOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>