<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS BELOUED FATHER IOHN Valans, W. U. wisheth the grace of God with health and prosperitie.</title>
           <author>Vallans, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111492_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14275</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24590</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111492</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS BELOUED FATHER IOHN Valans, W. U. wisheth the grace of God with health and prosperitie.</title>
                 <author>Vallans, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tale of tvvo swannes : VVherein is comprehended the original and increase of the riuer Lee commonly called Ware-riuer: together, with the antiquitie of sundrie places and townes seated vpon the same. Pleasant to be read, and not altogether vnprofitable to bee vnderstood By W.V</title>
                 <author>Vallans, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Sheldrake, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>TO HIS BELOUED FATHER IOHN Valans, W. U. wisheth the grace of God with health and prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He dutie (deare Father) I owe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, the regard of my promise, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the remēbrance of your reasonable request, doo not a litle mooue me to write a few words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matter whereof, at my being with you last, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>th cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of our friendes talked, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> am well assured that you re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what a styr <hi>N. B.</hi> kept, when I said that shippe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> had bene at <hi>Ware,</hi> affyrming, how it was vnpossible that that riuer which but of late was scarce able to beare a smal whyrrie, shold in times past beare: big and mighty ships. Truly his wordes were many &amp; great, but his reasons were smal. And since that, at that time I promised to send you in a letter a plaine and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent prooffe of those words which there I vttered, I doubt not but in these few lines fully to satisfie, not only your request, but also your mind, and confirme you in that opinion which fewe men (vnlesse such as be altogether ignorant of the matter, and of the place) wil denie. And for so much as the cause for which the ships went thether, and what they did there, then will I plainly prooue both by auchoritie and examples, that it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y that they were ther. Lastly, I wil (as my promise was) shew you about what time and by whome <hi>Ware</hi> was builded.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>That Shippes haue bene at Ware</head>
      <p>THe Danes (who as <hi>Polidor Virgill</hi> saith) dwelled in olde time beyond <hi>Ister,</hi> but now be they inhabitants of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ocean or <hi>Denmark,</hi> perceiuing how that their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was ouermuch pressed with the great multitude of people y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in habited y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, determined to subdue the land, to driue out y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
         <pb facs="11"/>
Englishmen, and to plant themselues and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ir posterity for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> the same: for perfourming and accomplishing. whereof, they armed great store of chosen souldiers: who about the yeare 832. in 34. shippes entered the riuer of <hi>Thames,</hi> landed by great force, spoiled, fired, &amp; wasted the country so far, that <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> who then was king of the more part of England, was fame with an hoast of men to succour and relieue h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>stressed subiectes. But such was the will of God for the punishment of sinne that then was rise, that the kinge ioining battaile with the Danes, was by them discomfited and put to flight. After this batt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ile, the Danes were so encouraged, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> out of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e countrie like f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>armes of Bees, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> one weeke there were fiue thousand of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, yet in the werke following ther would come eight thousand more to supply their roomes. They were oftentime discomfited, and the greater part of them driuen b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ke by diuers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>akant kinges and princes, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> yet by reason of their often arriuall, therr force was still in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased and maintained. One while they arriued in one place, &amp; then in another, spoiling, burning, &amp; killing all they could come by. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> were too long to tell, and verie grieuous it is to thinke how religion was decaied, learning forgotten, all partes &amp; quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Realme wasted and spoiled: howe cities, townes, churches, abbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s &amp; religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ouses were consumed with fire &amp; flame, how miserablie the Commons were afflicted, how piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully men, women and children, and all fortes of people went to wracke, how wonderfully the kinges themselues were amased, the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ing of their enemies being both suddaine and violent: how cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>elly fire and sword, famine and death raged thorow out the land heauen and earth intending as it were the fatall destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and vtter dcay of the realme. This miserie continued the space of 300 and ddde yeares, within which yeares, namely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare of our Lord 217 the 23 yeare of King▪ <hi>Alfreds</hi> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ns a great armie of Danes hauing re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>eiued an ouerthrow at a place ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ed <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>tington</hi> beside <hi>Seuethe,</hi> fled into east Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and there wintered, and prepared a great hoast againe out of Northumberland and other places, leauing there their wiues and children, together with their money, shippes and munition,
<pb facs="11"/>
in east England, and with great speed got to the Citie of <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> (which at that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e was de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>late, the inhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for feare of the Danes forsa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>en it) or euer king <hi>Alfred</hi> &amp; <hi>Ethered</hi> the vnder king with their armies could ouertake the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. And yet such was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> that king <hi>Alfred</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>this purs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, that or euer his enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>es had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>th h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s companie tooke a great deale of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>riage with all the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> and other thinges that they in their iourney by robbing and spoyling had obtained and driuen away. Hee also besieged the citie two or three daies, but perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>uing it woulde finally auaile, he was fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ne (a grieuous thing to heare) to burn vp the greatest pate of the corne that grewe there aboutes and bestow the rest amongst his horses, least his enemies shoulde haue the fruit and commoditie thereof. The Danes perceiuing that, and seeing there was nothing left whereof they might liue in those partes, departed from thence, and in great has<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e got them to north Wales, where they spoyled and hartied the countrie farre and neere, driuing away great booties of Cartel, and carrieng with them rich spoiles. From hence they departed And because for feare of the Mercians they durst not traueile that way, they coasted along the countrie till they came to Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland, and so through middle England, taking the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> shippes their w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ues &amp; children out of cast England with them, they arriued at a little Island sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>uate in the Sea, in the east part of Essex called <hi>Merseyge.</hi> From thence they departed and came into the riuer of <hi>Thames,</hi> and seeing that Winter was now at hand, they drew or rowed their shippes vp the riuer <hi>Lygean.</hi> And twentie miles from <hi>London</hi> they began to buylde a Fort, which being finished, they taried there all that wynter, spoyling, robbing and burning those quarters without mercy. When Winter was past, a great part of the Citizens of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, with those that inhabited neere thereaboutes traueiled thether, and by force minded to breake downe the Fort or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition which they had there buylded. But the Danes stoutlye resisted them, and not far from the place gaue them a sharpe battaile, where the Christians were put to flight, and foure of King <hi>Alfreds</hi> men were slaine.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="12"/>
Thus the pagane or heathen Danes remained Lordes or maisters of those quarters, compelling the husbandmen to eare and till the ground, meaning themselues to reape the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of it. But the good King <hi>Alfred,</hi> who alwaies was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the welfare of his subiectes, gathered an armie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haruest time pitched his tents neer to the place of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode. By whose comming, the enemies were so affraid, that they durst not once peepe out of their hold to fetch either cattell or corne out of the fields by force. In this space, it happened on a time, as the King rode alongst by the riuer side, he viewed the water, and perceiued how that in some places of it, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell might easily bee stopped, and the streame made lesse. Whereupon he (as <hi>Huntington</hi> writeth) caused it to bee cut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three seuerall braunches or armes: but howsoeuer it was, hee so weakened the streame, that the Danes could not bring back their ships the same way they came. Which thing the Danes perceiuing, and knowing well it was in vaine for them to abide any longer there, they left their Shippes, and fled by land as fast as they could to <hi>Quatbridge,</hi> sending their wiues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren againe into east England. After this the king departed, and the Londoners and Countrimen seeing the Danes were gone, burst downe their Holde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, and got some of their ships backe againe to <hi>London,</hi> and the rest they burned and brake all to peeces.</p>
      <p>But here peraduenture you will aske me, howe I shoulde come by the knowledge of these thinges, beeing done so many hundred yeares agoe. To this I answere, that in things that were done long before any man that is now liuing can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, wee must credit that our Fathers haue committed to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting concerning the same. And in my opinion, the neerer the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter liueth to those times in which the thinges he speaketh or writeth of were done, the more credite is to bee geuen to him.</p>
      <p>And as concerning this matter, it is confirmed by the reporte of a verie auncient, reuerent and and learned Wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, namely <hi>Asserus Meneuensis,</hi> Bishop of Saint <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies,</hi> that liued in the verie selfe same time when these thinges
<pb facs="12"/>
were done, and <hi>Maryanus Scotus</hi> who liued and wrote a chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle at least 500. yeares ago, as <hi>Florentinus</hi> a Monk of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester, who continued it, doth witnesse and declare. Besides di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others of great antiquitie and credite as <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington, Mathew</hi> of <hi>Westminster,</hi> and manie moe, who d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e all confirme that which is before declared. Besides there remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet the ruines of an old Castle or Fort betweene <hi>Hartford</hi> Castle and the Mill, which I doe vndoubtedly beleeue was the verie selfe same Fort that the <hi>Danes</hi> builded.</p>
      <p>Moreouer, <hi>O. Crosse</hi> did credibly en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rine me that at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Stansted</hi> bridge, there were found within the riuer, pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of broken ships or Craets, nayles and other thinges which seemed to belong to some great shippes or vessels. All which thinges considered, together with the parting of the streame before remembred, me thinkes should be sufficient to confirme your minde, and cause you to beleeue that there haue bene ships at <hi>Ware</hi> and <hi>Hartford.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Hereunto may bee added that it was a common vse of the <hi>Danes</hi> to row or drawe vp their ships into some smaller creeke or riuer where that they might ride all winter with least dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And time worketh some alteration both by water and by land, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> where great riuers did somtimes run, nowe it is vtterlie drie, and in stead of maine waters we haue goodly &amp; florishing Meades. And in like sort, where goodly cities and castels some times did stand, there now groweth corne. For examples of this we need not seeke farre, since y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in <hi>London</hi> not aboue 277. yeeres ago namely in the yeere of our Lord 1300. when <hi>Henry Waleys</hi> was Mayor of the citie there ran a riuer through Walbrook w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> two bridges ouer it, whereof <hi>William Iordan</hi> and <hi>Iohn de Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> were maisters and gouernours. What is become of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Wer.</hi> that ran by S. <hi>Albons</hi> of which the great city that in old time stood there, took the name and was called <hi>Werlamche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> whereof <hi>Leland</hi> in his cōmentaries maketh mention, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning cities the diligent reader of chronicles shal meet with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> names of many, of which ther is at this day no rubbish nor ruin to be seen, as <hi>Andres Chester▪</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> stood in Sussex on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> edge of the great wood called <hi>Andreds weale</hi> of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>hancester,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> stood in the
<pb facs="13"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Panta</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Essex;</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e, of which as I sayd, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> is left n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ken, but as the Poet saith <hi>Est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> vb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> Thus haue you heard (deare father) both the doings of the <hi>Danes</hi> not only in <hi>Engl▪</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>lso what they made in those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>d wherof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e talked, and where you dwel. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> now to write <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ou as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, how k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Ware</hi> was built, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd in what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ges d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ies the same was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e, of which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to say no more then that which hath bene alreadie written by such as haue in their histories and chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>les made me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> as were builded by king <hi>Edward</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> aboute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>I cannot but much mislik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>that affirme that the towne of <hi>Hartford</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> by king <hi>Edward</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rst before the conquesh: Seem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> by the very wordes of <hi>Huntington</hi> it appeareth that it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ut the Castell that he builded, for we read in <hi>Beda</hi> his histo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> a counsel of Bishops that was b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> at <hi>Hartford</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>g bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Edwardes</hi> time, this castle I meane of <hi>Hartford</hi> was builded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> the yeare of our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>12, by <hi>Edward</hi> the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e of king <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>,</hi> and two yeares after hee builded a tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>n the North <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of <hi>Lee</hi> which is the same th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t I doe take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> be <hi>Ware</hi> and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s in hand when <hi>Witham</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> was also beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>res since. Thus much (father) for this time. I thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>vnto you concerning this matter; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>thing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> herereafter when all thinges be finished that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of the Lord Treasurer, maister <hi>Fanshaw</hi> and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in hard for the amendement and sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> riuer, you and I both shall see, though not shippes, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>g boates and vessels passe too and fro betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>xt <hi>London</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Ware</hi> to the commoditie and profite of the whole countrey, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h God graunt.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Your obedient sonne W. Vallans,</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="13"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>