<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Goodman, Godfrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111002_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12545</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Goodman, Godfrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sir Thomas Smithes voiage and entertainment in Rushia : With the tragicall ends of two emperors, and one empresse, within one moneth during his being there: and the miraculous preseruation of the now raigning emperor, esteemed dead for 18. yeares</title>
                 <author>Smith, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Trundle, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, the discourses of this voyage (at the comming home of the Gentleman that was chiefe in it and his company into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) affoorded such pleasure to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, by reason the accidents were strange and Nouell, that many way-laid the Nevves, and vvere gladde to make any booty of it to delight themselues, by vvhich meanes, that which of it selfe being knit together was beautifull, could not chuse but shevv vilde, beeing so torne in peeces. So that the itching fingers of gain laid hold vpon it, and had like to haue sent it into the world lame, and dismembred. Some that picke vp the crums of such feasts, had scrapt togither many percels of this Rushian commoditie, so that their heads being gotten vvith child of a Bastard, there was no remedy but they must be deliuered in <hi>Paules Church-yard.</hi> But I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the truth from the mouths of diuers gentlemen that vvent in the Iourney, and hauing som good notes bestovved vpon me in vvriting, vvrought them into this body, because neither thou shouldst be abused with false reports, nor the Voyage receiue slaunder. I have done this vvithout consent either of Sir Tho. himselfe, or of those gentlemen my friends that deliuered it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me: So that if I offend, it is Error <hi>Amoris</hi> to my Countrey, not <hi>Amor erroris</hi> to do any man wronge. Read and like, for much is in it vvorthy obseruation. Farevvell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>