<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND most generous Lords in England, especially those of his Maiesties Priuy Councell, and Councell of Warre.</title>
           <author>Smith, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111000_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12469</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22794</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111000</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND most generous Lords in England, especially those of his Maiesties Priuy Councell, and Councell of Warre.</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sea grammar : vvith the plaine exposition of Smiths Accidence for young sea-men, enlarged. Diuided into fifteene chapters: what they are you may partly conceiue by the contents. Written by Captaine Iohn Smith, sometimes gouernour of Virginia, and admirall of Nevv-England</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72, 83-86 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND most generous Lords in <hi>England,</hi> especially those of his Maiesties Priuy Councell, and Councell of Warre.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Great LORDS,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vlius Caesar</hi> wrote his owne Commentaries, holding it no lesse honour to write, than fight; much hath bin writ concerning the art of war by land, yet nothing concerning the same at Sea. Many others might better than my selfe haue done this, but since I found none endeuourd it, I haue aduentured, encouraged by the good ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tainment of
<pb facs="3"/>
my late printed Accidence. This I suppose will be much bettered by men in these things better experienced, others ignorance may fault it: I haue beene a miserable Practitioner in this Schoole of Warre by Sea and Land more than thirty yeeres, howeuer chance or occasion haue kept me from your Lordships knowledge or imployment. Yet I humbly entreat your Lordships to accept and patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize this little Pamphlet, as the best testimony I can present your Honours, of my true duty to my King and Country. Thus humbly crauing your Honours pardons, and fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable construction of my good intent, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all duty to be commanded, <hi>IOHN SMITH.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>