<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>W., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111643_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14878</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111643</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>W., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasant and delightfvl historie of Curan, a prince of Danske, and the fayre Princesse Argentile, daughter and heyre to Adelbright, sometime King of Northumberland : Shewing his first loue vnto her, his succeslesse suite, and the low deiections he vnderwent for her sake. His second loue to the same lady vnknowne, taking her for a poore countrie damsell. She (by reason of the vnkindnesse of King Edell her vnckle and gardian) hauing forsooke the court, and vndertooke the profession of a neatheardes mayde. His constant loue (after her long continued vnkindnes) rewarded with her wished consent, their happie nuptials, and mutuall reioycings, his valour and victorious warre with King Edell: and lastly, his peacefull installment in the kingly throne. Enterlacte with many pritty and pithie prayses of beauty, and other amorous discourses, pleasing, smooth and delightfull. By William Webster</title>
                 <author>Webster, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Higgenbotham, Richard 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>READER, Let not thy gentle eye disdaine</l>
      <l>To walke along my lines so smooth so plaine;</l>
      <l>Delightfull walkes they happily may proue,</l>
      <l>So they may catch thy liking, I thy loue;</l>
      <l>This volume, (though not large) at large discouers</l>
      <l>The fortunes of a payre of princely Louers,</l>
      <l>Prince <hi>Curan</hi> and the Princesse <hi>Argentile.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>He stranger, she a natiue of our Isle.</l>
      <l>He one for lineaments, and gifts of mind:</l>
      <l>Such as the like to him was hard to find:</l>
      <l>And sure, if to be amorous be no blot</l>
      <l>To vertue, then his vertues had no spot,</l>
      <l>And shee, a dame whose beauty so excell'd,</l>
      <l>That in those dayes shee was not paralell'd,</l>
      <l>And, if she were not coy more then shee should,</l>
      <l>No imputation could on her take hold,</l>
      <l>How loue, from Lordlinesse doth him debace,</l>
      <l>And makes him to supply a peasants place:</l>
      <l>And how his loue to shunne, th'assaults of loue,</l>
      <l>From Court to Cottage doth her selfe remoue.</l>
      <l>These things are here discourst, and here is showne</l>
      <l>How he the second time loues her vnknowne,</l>
      <l>How long he wooes her, how at last he sped,</l>
      <l>Though not till then, when all his hopes were dead,</l>
      <l>Then how he conquered him in bloudie fight</l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <l>That wrongfully vsurpt his Ladyes right,</l>
      <l>(Then which) his former taske was farre more hard,</l>
      <l>This last was easie with the first compar'd,</l>
      <l>T'was more to him his Ladyes loue to gaine</l>
      <l>Then to giue end vnto a tyrants raigne:</l>
      <l>To conquer her affections was a thing</l>
      <l>More hard to him then to vncrowne a King,</l>
      <l>Nay, all the weapons in these wars imployde,</l>
      <l>Against the Prince, not him so much annoy'd,</l>
      <l>As did his Ladies angry frownes, for those</l>
      <l>Could daunt him more then all his armed foes:</l>
      <l>How he was rays'd vnto a Kingly throne,</l>
      <l>That low deiections long had vndergone,</l>
      <l>Concludes this booke, which read vnto the end,</l>
      <l>Perhaps to thee, it may it selfe commend:</l>
      <l>Thus (of thy wishes) wishing thee possest,</l>
      <l>(For kind acceptance onely.) Thine I rest.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>