<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS VERY Louinge and especiall friende, olde Oliuer Fyndfault, of Englande, in the countye of Europe Gent. William Woulwell, in most friendlye manner sendeth most hartye greetinges.</title>
           <author>Wouldwell, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111413_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13666</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23952.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS VERY Louinge and especiall friende, olde Oliuer Fyndfault, of Englande, in the countye of Europe Gent. William Woulwell, in most friendlye manner sendeth most hartye greetinges.</title>
                 <author>Wouldwell, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short inuentory of certayne idle inuentions : the fruites of a close and secret garden of great ease, and litle pleasure. By C.T</title>
                 <author>Thimelthorpe, C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 68, 2 leaves, illustrations (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO HIS VERY</hi> Louinge and especiall <hi>friende, olde Oliuer Fyndfault, of <hi>Englande, in the countye of Europe</hi>
      </hi> Gent. William Woulwell, in most friendlye manner <hi>sendeth most hartye greetinges.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I shoulde so lightlye lett this passe, as hereby to geue fre scope to you my friend and to euerye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>cleheaded penmā, (flowing by dayly practice and experience, in all cunninge, and curious conceiptes, perusing this small pamphlet, which claymeth no other tytle then a toy,) to condemne y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> inuentor hereof I should great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iniury him, and not vnworthely of greate folly might condemne my self, in that I haue so rashly thrust him so nakedlye into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of so manye, wheras perhaps if I had
<pb facs="10"/> geuen him warninge thereof he might more strongly and better haue furnished himselfe, but as naked as I founde him, so nakedlye strayght wayes did I prefer him. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the truth is, a very friend of myne beyng driuen from all the benefytes and pleasures of this world, and inforced contrarye to the ordinances and rules of nature to hyde and harbor himself (though as a gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ltles guest) in a most solitary and dumpish desert, beyng therwith drawen from all ioy and felicity, in in any worldly necessary practise, and rather indeuoring himselfe to recreate, refresh, and delight his mind with some toy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh conceipts, then otherwise (being so incōbred) to charge it with any matters of importance or weight for his owne solace and pleasure, bestowed some part of that his ydle tyme in certayne playne and light toyes of inuentiō, not much vnlike therein vnto a certayne ydle kinge in <hi>Persia,</hi> who in his progresses, did nothig els but continuallye cutt, and whittle stickes, to dryue awaye the tyme. And by reason of my dayly recourse vnto him, beyng priuye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, I craued and obtayned the coppye of this now extant, the which I diuers times and ofte perusynge ouer, toke occasion as a toy, to lyke so well, as I procurde it to the presse, with this title as you see, and thought it as a tokē worthy to send vnto you, to read
<pb facs="10"/> whether beyng led there unto, by the greate &amp; good affection I bare to the maker, or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sart of the matter, I know not: but wel wee both know, it is the naturall incliation of friendes, one alwayes to thinke the best of an other. Therefore as I know the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentor hereof ment nothing lesse, then to put this forth to the publicke construction of the world, to hasarde or aduenture the allowing or disalowing therof: I wil not take vponme to geue out any showe of commendatiō ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at all. Fyrst because I knowe it was not made to that intente, and besydes, least if it should happen to be cōdempned of others as a vayne and tryfling toy, I should therewith also be condempned to haue made a partiall and vnworthye prayse. But syr (if you can rightly consider it) as by the least byrde that flyes in the ayre, by the least fish that swims in the Sea, and by the smallest worme that creepes vpon the earth. The omnipotent &amp; mighty power of God doth as fully &amp; playne appeare, as by the hougest and greatest mō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters that beares life in this worlde: euen so by the smalest booke that can be written, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most babling ballet that can be made, and by the least word that can be spoken, his strāge and wonderful workes in mā, with his most liberall and incomparable guiftes vnto thē
<pb facs="11"/> do as perfectly set forth and shew themselues as by the greatest volume y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euer was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, by the wayghtyest or wysest concept that euer was made, or by the most eloquente or learned oration that euer was vttered. The honest wyse and ciuil man doth as little des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyse the worst and meanest begger that goeth by the waye, as he geeatly honoureth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest &amp; greatest prince that ruleth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world, euen so here the indifferent and wel disposed myndes, wil as litle trippe, or spu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne at thys stumped, lame, and haui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nge toy, as they would greatly fawne vppon, or runne after a more fyne or pleasaunt inuention. But ther is an old prouerb <hi>Figulus Figulo inuidit,</hi> one Potter hateth an other, the which to auoyd, these may be sufficiently to assure you, in that I know you are a craftes man in that arte, that as for this vnskilful potter, this small trifle and toy is the first that euer hee made, who wil not iustify it to be lawful nor good, in that he was neuer prentice thereunto, and for any he intendes, I dare bouldly say shall be the last, vnlesse it be a little cup or cruese for his owne mouth▪ yet syr if your friendly actions hadde at anye tyme bene▪ agreable vnto your continual colourable showes, you would haue inabled him long before this by your friendly instructions, worthye of your felowship and company.</p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>But vnderstanding he had, though to verye small and litle purpose, some smacke in this your art, as only to take your vessels in hand and to reade them ouer, you alwayes shooke hym of, demaunding a double fee for the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of your skill, much like to amusition, who vsed to take of hysschollare, which had learned before they came vnto him, double soulare, deuble that he toke of others, which neuer learned before, sayinge that hee tooke double paynes with them, as fyrst to make them forget that they had learned before, and then to teach them perfectlye agayne: who if now he were alyue shoulde surelye fynde as small resorte of schollers, as I thinke you do in that you are so curyous in your art. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to imagine this short, and vnpleasaunte sounde, here at this tyme presented vnto your audable and pleasaunt eares, to be but as a preludium, vnto other conceytes, &amp; that he wil stryue to marre your markets, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such lyke rough hewen, or mishapen ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels, it shal be in vayn, for be intendes nothig lesse. And as for this small conceipt, here at this tyme, being cast in a very litle mould, &amp; wherin great want of an artifitial workman must needes appeare: I hope you will not stryue to condemne, but rather excuse, though it hath neyther heade to begynne, handle to houlde by, nor foote to stand vpon &amp; though
<pb facs="12"/> perhaps neare aboute the end you shall find it very imperfect, and so ful of secrete chinks and litle crantse, as it wil hardly hold liquor without leaking: but if your graue head shal esteeme it as an ydle toy, imagine it (as it is) the fruictes of an ydle place. For phisicke sake I know you haue swallowed many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasant and bitter pylles, for friendship sake you may as wel at this time digest this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling and ydle toy. But if you shal answeare mee, that your such Phisical rescerpts haue alwaies inforced you to vse the pap of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or els to roule them in suger, otherwise they might haue stucke in your throate: then for answeare agayne, I can but aduise you, for the more easy digesting of this my friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceipt, sent onely as a token vnto you &amp; to the rest of my friendes, to roule it in styd of an apple, in the sott asd slyppery pappe of your gentle pattence, or otherwyse (in stead of a suger lofe) in some sweete and sugred spice of your most frienly interpretation: and in this (for the old acquayntaunce of longe tyme continued betweene vs) I hope I shal not fayle but misse of your willing &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conformity: and therfore now, since I haue sufficiently declared vnto you, the cause of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> publishing herof, with the dispositiō and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the deuisor, and least I shoulde make this my foretrottīg shew or preamble (which
<pb facs="12"/> rightly should be but a breefe declaration of what is to come) longer then this his whole rase which is very short, and consideryng my old lesson (worthy in euery act to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and obserued) <hi>quod satis est sufficit,</hi> I commend me vnto you, you vnto God, and these few lines following vnto your friendly construction.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your assured friend VVilliam VVouldwell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>