<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NO∣BLE, AND WORTHIE ADVANCERS OF THE STANDART of CHRIST, among the GENTILES, the Aduenturers for the Plantation of VIRGINIA, W. S. prayeth that Nations may blesse them, and be blessed by them.</title>
           <author>Symonds, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111329_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13290</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NO∣BLE, AND WORTHIE ADVANCERS OF THE STANDART of CHRIST, among the GENTILES, the Aduenturers for the Plantation of VIRGINIA, W. S. prayeth that Nations may blesse them, and be blessed by them.</title>
                 <author>Symonds, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Virginia. A sermon preached at VVhite-Chappel, in the presence of many, honourable and worshipfull, the aduenturers and planters for Virginia. 25. April. 1609 : Published for the benefit and vse of the colony, planted, and to bee planted there, and for the aduancement of their Christian purpose. By William Symonds, preahcer at Saint Sauiors in Southwarke</title>
                 <author>Symonds, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <distributor>Edgar, Eleazar</distributor>
                            <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 54, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND WORTHIE ADVANCERS OF THE STANDART of CHRIST, among the GENTILES, the Aduenturers for the Plantation of VIRGINIA, <hi>W. S.</hi> prayeth that Nations may blesse them, and be blessed by them.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Noble and worthy,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCH as doe prayse the worthies, do cloth them with the robes of others that haue gone before them in vertues of like nature. A thing which I cannot doe of your Plantation, seeing neither Testament (that I can find) dooth afford vs a Parallell in men of like quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. That great, and golden SEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENCE, <hi>The seede of the woman, shall</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gene. 3. 15▪</note>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>breake the Serpents head,</hi> (the onely subiect of all ages) with a part of the wisedome that is folded therin, hitherto hath beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified the world with admirable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant varieties; more rich and delightfull then all the ornaments of Princes palaces, or the Curtaines of <hi>Salomon.</hi> Here may we see the Flood, the burning of Sodom; the drown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng of <hi>Pharoh:</hi> the subduing of the Cananites by <hi>Dauid</hi> and his sonnes; the breaking of Monarchies into chaffe: the<note place="margin">Dan. 2. 35.</note> surprising &amp; conquering of great Nations,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6. 17.</note> by Fisher-men, <hi>with the sword of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> the stamping of the Dragon (the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Empire) into pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es by <hi>Constantine;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Euseb. de vita Constantini.</note> the desolation, and nakednesse of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, now readie to be cast into the fire. Manifest demonstrations of the Serpents bruised head. But here is not all. These things were done in a corner, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of that which is in hand, and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be accomplished at the last iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Long since the Gospell <hi>of Christ did ride forth conquering that hee might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reue. 6. &amp;. 19.</note> And NOW, <hi>the hostes that are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="3"/> doe follow him on white horses. Now the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai. 52. 10.</note>
      <hi>Lord hath made bare his holy arme, in the sight</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reuel. 19. 12.</note>
      <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ll the Gentiles; and all the ends of the earth shall see the saluatiō of our God.</hi> NOW many Mighty Kings haue set their Crownes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of Christ. The valiant soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier saith, <hi>The shields of the world belong to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 47. 9.</note>
      <hi>God.</hi> The true Nobilitie, haue vpon their horse bridles, <hi>Holinesse to the Lord.</hi> And<note place="margin">Zach. 14. 20.</note> now the wise and industrious Merchant, doth hold the riches of the Gentiles too base a fraight for his shippes. He tradeth<note place="margin">Isai. 60. 9.</note> for <hi>his</hi> wisedome, that said: <hi>Surely the Isles wait for me</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>and the shippes of the Ocean most especially:</hi> namely to carry the Gospell abroad. The people in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, like stronge thundrings, doe say <hi>Hallelu-iah▪</hi> And who is wanting in this<note place="margin">Reuel. 19. 6.</note> blessed expedition? Surely, not any tribe, <hi>Prayse ye the Lord, — for the people that offered</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iudg. 5. 2.</note>
      <hi>themselues so willingly.</hi> For who can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himselfe from concurrence in so good an action: especially, when he shall but read, or heare, that one sentence which <hi>Deborah</hi> did sing: <hi>Curse ye</hi> Meroz, <hi>sayd the
<pb facs="4"/> Angell of the Lord curse the inhabitants therof:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iudg. 5. 23.</note>
      <hi>because they came not forth to helpe the Lord.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This land, was of old time, offered to our Kings. Our late Soueraigne Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> (whose storie hath no peere among Princes of her sexe) being a pure Virgin, found it, set foot in it, and called it <hi>Virginia.</hi> Our most sacred Soueraigne, in whom is the spirit of his great Ancestor, <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>onstantin t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e pacifier of the world, and planter of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi>
      <note place="margin">Euseb. de vita Constantin.</note>
      <hi>in places most remote,</hi> desireth to present this land a pure Virgine to Christ. Such as doe mannage the expedition, are carefull to carry thither no Traitors, nor Papists that depend on the Great <hi>VVhore. Lord fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish this good worke thou hast begun;</hi> and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this land, a pure Virgine to thy kingly sonne Christ Iesus; so shall thy name bee magnified: and we shall haue a Virgin or Maiden Britaine, a comfortable addition to our Great Britaine.</p>
   <p>And now Right Worthy, if any aske an account of my vocation, to write and Preach thus much; I answere: that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I could not satisfie their request
<pb facs="4"/> that would haue me goe; yet I could not omit to shewe my zeale to the glory of God. If they aske account of my Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I answere, your vertue hath exacted it. If any man list to be curious, or conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, wee haue no such custome, nor the Churches of God. Hold on your blessed course, and you shall receiue blessings of Christ. <hi>Blessed bee the Lord God; euen the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 72. 18. 19.</note>
      <hi>God of Israell, which onely worketh great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and hath put these blessed thoughts into your Christian hearts, <hi>And bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed be his glorious name for euer, and let all the earth be filled with his glory, Amen, Amen. </hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Fours most heartily affected in the cause of Virginia, WILLIAM SIMONDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>