<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111266_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12774</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23078</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111266</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Complaints : Containing sundrie small poemes of the worlds vanitie. VVhereof the next page maketh mention. By Ed. Sp</title>
                 <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Orwin, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>184 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE my late setting foorth of the <hi>Faerie Queene,</hi> finding that it hath found a fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble passage amongst you; I haue sithence endeuoured by all good meanes (for the better encrease and accomplishment of your delights,) to get into my handes such smale Poemes of the same Authors; as I heard were disperst abroad in sundrie hands, and not easie to bee come by, by himselfe; some of them hauing bene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerslie imbeziled and purloyned from him, since his departure ouer Sea. Of the which I haue by good meanes gathered togeather these fewe parcels present, which I haue caused to bee imprinted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather,
<pb facs="3"/>
for that they al seeme to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine like matter of argument in them: being all complaints and meditations of the worlds vanitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> verie graue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. To which effect I vnderstand that he besides wrote sundrie others, namelie <hi>Ecclesiastes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Canticum canticorum</hi> trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, <hi>A senights slumber, The hell of louers, his Purgatorie,</hi> being all dedicated to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; so as it may seeme he ment them all to one volume. Besides some other Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets looselie scattered abroad: as <hi>The dying Pellican, The howers of the Lord, The sacrifice of a sinner, The seuen Psalmes, &amp;c.</hi> which when I can either by himselfe, or otherwise attaine too, I meane likewise for your fauour sake to set foorth. In the meane time praying you gentlie to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of these, &amp; graciouslie to entertain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the new Poet. <hi>I take leaue.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>