<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111086_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20964</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7343</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The waters of Siloe : To qvench the fire of pvrgatory and to drowne the traditions, limboes, mans satisfactions and all popish indulgences, against the reasons and allegations of a Portugall frier of the order of St. Frances, supported by three treatises. The one written by the same Franciscan and entituled The fierie torrent, &amp;c. The other two by two doctors of Sorbon. The one intituled The burning furnasse. The other The fire of Helie. By Peter Du Moulin minister of Gods word. Faithfully translated out of French by I.B</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barnes, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 406 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>OONE after the meeting betwixt the Franciscan fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and my selfe, I sent him in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a discourse cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taining an exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie requesting him likewise in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to set downe his soundest reasons and strongest proofs. But either of my writing or request this good Doctor made no accompt, yet in my absence af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter my departure from Paris he sent to challenge me againe to a verball con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: &amp; before he particularized his departure, he repaired to the kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie and required reward for his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke
<pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
teaching,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Contrary to the rule of S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> nullo modo denarios vel pecuniam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e cipiant, per se vel per per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sonam inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positam.</note> as also for his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar conference with the Minister <hi>Du Moulin.</hi> Which nevertheles could not restraine me from publishing my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course intituled <hi>The waters of Siloe to quēch the fire of Purgatory.</hi> This writing wrought a greater effect then I could haue imagined: for attending the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscans answer, behold two Doctors of <hi>Sorbone Cayer</hi> and <hi>Du Val,</hi> tryed no doubt vpon the vollee among such a multitude as doe assault this treatise, as a forlorne hope are the first that enter the skirmish. Afterward stirred vp by their example, commeth this Portugal Monke into the field, as making vp the arrier guard of this Roman army: to whose worke the <hi>Iesuits</hi> of <hi>Tournon</hi> haue contributed, to the end that after the knocking together of so many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite pates, they may need no more to begin. In me it might be holdē great presumption to wrastle with so many men, and so loaden with titles, if the word of God stood in awe of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.
<pb facs="7"/>
For hee might bee holden for a mad man, who in a matter of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, in liew of waighing the reasons should fal to numbring of the persons. Truth is of more force in the mouth of one man onely, then vntruth in the mouthes of many, whose conspiracies against the truth of the Gospell resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the humming of a neast of wasps that in stinging doe lose their stinges. how ever it is, it seemeth that this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise hath stung some of them to the quicke: with so great strife doe they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault it. And indeed the gaule and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that herein they doe spue forth doth shew them to be vehemently mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. They tearme me a beast, a foole, a sot, a deceaver, an hereticke, an impious parson, a dolt, execrable, impudent, &amp;c. They send me quick into hell, yea they rather want words then stomack. They are sorrie that our language is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter stored with iniurious phrases: and God hee knoweth what people they are! But God grant that this their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb facs="8"/>
may be to them a purgation, that God may not iudge them with so great rigour, as they doe vs with rashnesse. This is all the revenge that I do desire: for what other interest haue we in this action then the glory of God and the salvation of such as hate vs? Whose stripes and blowes when they cannot penetrate into the truth doe reflect vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my person. But herein doe I boast that they be honorable bruises. These barkings I beare as of men starved, and as some portion of the reproches of my saviour Christ, who was in like manner outraged, and for our salvation bare more sorrows thē we cā suffer wrongs for his glory. Now albeit an impudent boldnesse be the only way to atchieue reputation of skill, yet am not I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to practise, that course: neither to requite these Doctors with such quoine. This attempt I despise &amp; laugh at such impetuositie: yea I even take cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion of it, as of a disease of the minde and a convulsion. Neither is it indeed
<pb facs="8"/>
my cause, it is the cause of Iesus Christ, whom we are not to defend but by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating of him; for how can we plead the cause of the Lambe of God with wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish hearts and poisoned stomackes? Yet is their wrath in some sort excuse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: for in quenching their Purgatory, what do you but put these our Masters to an hungry dispute, by stopping the currant of their trafficke, cutting their sinews, &amp; breaking the wheeles of this great frame of the Roman hierarchie? For as a beast deadly wounded, spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth with an extraordinarie force, even so these Doctors doe excessiuely storme, when you touch them in their best feeling: that is in the belly, in Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and in Idlenesse. Of all the rest this Portugal Monk is the most ridiculously violent: hee speaketh with a barbarous impetuositie: with such a pride as hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreeth with his habit: yet did I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare his honour and abstaine from all iniuries and bravadoes, albeit I had a large field open before me, and many
<pb facs="9"/>
proofes of his ignorance. But I seeke not to dishonor any man, only the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God do I aime at. To these books thus stuffed with civilitie haue these re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Doctors imposed Capriccious titles after the manner of those that hang out scurrilous tables over the forefronts of the houses where they act their enterludes: or as such as carue <hi>Cyclops</hi> and <hi>Satyres</hi> vpon the fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spice of their buildings.<note place="margin">CAYER.</note> Marke then the title of <hi>Cayers</hi> booke. <hi>The burning for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, or oven of reverberate &amp;c.</hi> And in his booke his speech runneth all vpon <hi>Limbecks</hi> firing, evaporating, recalci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c. All words of his art, and of all this he maketh an <hi>Amalgame</hi> cōtaining more moon then sunne. The other trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the same path and entituleth his booke <hi>The fire of Helie to drie vp the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Siloe.</hi>
      <note place="margin">VAL. Luke. 9.</note> You wot not by what spirit you be led.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The</hi> FRIER</note> The Frier was loath to bee behind his fellowes, or to vse a lesse ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous title then his writing is, so to procure an vniformity wherein he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb facs="9"/>
with great discreation and this is his title. <hi>The Torrent of fire proceeding from the face of God to drie vp the waters of Mara enclosed in the causey of the Mill of Ablon:</hi> O frock garnished with elegā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie! Who was able on this side the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinean mountaines to attaine to such gallant conceptions; and so well poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed? This Frier minor entendeth to haue all his pollutions and vncleannes that he spueth out throughout his whole booke to come forth from the face of God, that is to say, to bee expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of Gods presence. Which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse hee armeth with autoritie, entituling himselfe <hi>The Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iames, Observantin, Doctor, Preacher &amp;c.</hi> And in his preface braggeth that he writeth succinctly and strongly: yet had it beene good hee had expected o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens commendations: but he had more desire to ease them of that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
   <p>At the first blush therefore seeing so fierie bookes, such hot furnaces &amp; Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb facs="10"/>
of fire I feared to come neere thē: but plucking vp my spirits and being a little way entred into the reading of the same, I grew into farre greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, considering that these three friers were as farre discordant among themselues as fire and water: and that these Doctors did most fiercely bang each other, and yet were all signed and approved by the Doctors of <hi>Sorbone.</hi> Yea so hot was this contention among them, that one of them, namely <hi>Cayer,</hi> after hee had beene well displaid, and hardly entreated, was finally disclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in all their Pulpits, &amp; blasted with perpetuall infamie. All which they could never haue compassed, but they must likewise taxe those Doctors that subscribed and allowed his booke.</p>
   <p>Well did I knowe that the opinions of the Romish doctors doe agree but badly.<note place="margin">Herein is the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Basil contrary to the Coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> One saith that the pope cannot teach false doctrine, another that hee can. One that the Pope is aboue the Councell, another that the Councell is
<pb facs="10"/>
aboue the Pope.<note place="margin">Misteria Mislae. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi> Causa <hi>15.</hi> Cā. Alius &amp; Can. Nos sanctorū quaest. <hi>7</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travag. vnā sanctam de Maiorib. &amp; Oleo.</note> One that Invocation of Saints is necessarie, as Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the 3. and <hi>Cayer</hi> in his conference advowed &amp; subscribed by the Doctors of <hi>Sorbone.</hi> The others, as the Lord of <hi>Eureux,</hi> that it may wel enough be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne; and it is no matter of necessitie. The Iesuits and such as in their hearts are more soundly nailed to the Papall sea doe advow that the Pope may giue and take away kingdomes: &amp; that hee can absolue subiects from their oaths and fidelitie &amp; allegance to their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and this power haue the Popes of late assumed to themselues, &amp; doe now put in practise. Others that hold their iudgements somewhat more at liberty doe affirme all this to be meere vsurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The most strictest orders of Friers and such soules as they haue brought into captivitie doe beleeue that the Church of Rome cannot erre in any point of doctrine and doe defend even the most grosse absurdities: other more smooth tongued, but withall more
<pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
white livered doe say that there bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed grosse absurdities: That they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not any Purgatorie. That the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile is but a kind of Marchandize: That the fraternitie of the Corde is but su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition: That the hallowed graines are but prophane trumperies: That we might very well forbeare the portray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God: the taking of the cup in the Supper from the lay people: the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of bells: the singing of Masses for horses, corne, hogges, &amp;c. Yet for all this that wee must not separate our selues: and the reason that vnder hand they giue out is this: It is good for vs. All this passeth smoothly away so long as we speake not hardly of his holinesse and that the Church Profits be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minished. To be briefe, these people are like twinnes whose heads being devided the bellies are neverthelesse knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Surely this is the course whereby the vnitie of the Romish Church is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden. Nether were wee vtterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this discord, yet should I never
<pb facs="12"/>
haue imagined that they would haue published their contradictions, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced these Doctors to the stage, there to haue given them so rude a bastina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. But drinke yee together Doctors &amp; agree among your selues: for surely the same God that confounded the langua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of the builders of <hi>Babylon</hi> doth still suffer divisiō to molest those that build it againe. Now that which we speak of, concerneth not <hi>Cayer</hi> alone: for the Frier likewise gainesayeth his two cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, albeit he hath both seene their bookes &amp; out of them borrowed some part of his writings. So as that which in the sixteenth of Genesis was spoken of <hi>Ismael, His hand shall be against every mā, and every mans hand against him;</hi> doth very well agree with every of them: whereof in this Treatise I will shewe you sundry examples.</p>
   <p>These contradictions are somwhat hard of disgestiō, but much more their slanders wherein they impose vpon vs most horrible and wicked opiniōs, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb facs="13"/>
estranged from our beliefe. As thus: that we beleeue fiue mansions for the soules: that our drift is to deny the Immortalitie of the soule: that wee make al sinnes alike equal: that we hold that the soules doe sleep from the day of their decease to the day of iudgmēt: that wee would haue I wot not what Synode [that never was] to passe for an article of faith: that baptisme was not necessarie for any but the children of vnbeleevers: that out of our Kalenders we haue raised the Virgin Mary &amp; the Apostles, and in their places haue inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin:</hi> that our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters doe preach liberty of conscience without any apprehension of divine iudgemēt: that we hold that it sufficeth vs that Iesus Christ suffered for vs, and therefore that wee neede not doe any more: that at the Funerals of the late Queene of England they sung Masse, had their offertory and prayed for her soule: that <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> in liew of raising the dead to life did put the living
<pb facs="13"/>
to death, and that they are our Masters, Patriarkes and Apostles &amp;c. To bee briefe, they set downe even all the slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that hatred can devise, or malice can suggest, wherewith they seduce the people and abuse their simplicitie.</p>
   <p>What shall I speak of their vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in alleaging the Scriptures? All the passages that they produce are for the most part either falsified, or wrested to a contrary sense, or to no purpose. With a Magisteriall license they force a number of passages quoined vpon the anvill of Avarice, that are not to be found in the originals, either Greeke, or Hebrew: yea and sometimes contrary to the Roman translations. Of so much negligence or dulnesse of their reader do they presume, assuring themselues that the people shall never perceaue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, or can so much as cōsult with the Scriptures, which vnto them are as sealed letters and suspected bookes: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, in the meane time they are permit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to read the monstrous Legends: the
<pb facs="14"/>
Psalters of the Virgin Mary ful fraught with blasphemy: and the frivolous and and fabulous bookes of the life of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ. O yee soules that long for your salvation, will you still liue in such grievous bondage? What? shall we yet be so vaine as to passe the seas to looke vpon the relickes of some Saints, and will we not heare Iesus Christ when he offereth himselfe vnto vs in the holy Scriptures? Shall we stoop more to cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riositie thē to necessitie? To the cōtent of our eies then to the salvation of our soules? Shall we still be so rashly negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, as in a matter of such importance to credit the first commer? Contenting our selues with following in liew of knowing? Placing pietie in the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of nothing; thrusting our selues into the presse and shrowding vs amōg the multitude? Againe, when any man shall say vnto vs that Iesus Christ or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Apostles do in such a place, or in such a place teach vs Purgatory, or the Invocation of saints, &amp;c. Shall wee
<pb facs="14"/>
be so cruelly cowards to our selues, or so vnthankfull to God, as not to take so much paines as to look whether the same be truely alleaged? And indeed wherefore should these Doctors cite the places but that we might see them? For what an absurditie is this, to quote the places to the people and then to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>barre them from seeing of them: To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre them to the places and then to command them not to looke in the booke? The people of <hi>Beroe</hi> practised this examination of the things that <hi>S. Paul</hi> taught:<note place="margin">Acts. 17.10</note> for albeit he preached with farre more auctoritie and certitude thē any man in our age; yet did they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his preaching by the reading of the Prophets, farre more obscure then the new Testament. Enter therefore in to this examination I say, and yet I say vnto you [especially if you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to the originals] that you shall enter as it were into a shop where they sell vizards: yea where they doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sell them, but where they make thē,
<pb facs="15"/>
so excessiue is their licentious liberty▪ Of all this will wee in this Treatise pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce sundry proofes, according as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion shall serue. A Treatise whose principall drift is a defence of the only purging of our sinnes, which is the bloud of our Saviour Iesus Christ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the fire of Purgatorie. An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that carrieth with it the confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the doctrine of the <hi>Limboes,</hi> of Traditions, of Prayer for the dead, of mans satisfactions and of Popish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences. I plead the cause of Iesus Christ: I confute the reasons and passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of these Doctors and their burning writings: yet touch not their persons, neither their furnitures full of Invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues that concerne not the argument.</p>
   <p>Two things there are neverthelesse which I cannot overpasse: their folly in vanting, and their false dealing in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering me.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Fire of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic, p. 4.</note>First they paint forth many triumphs great conquests, and an extreame sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our Church: so many goodly
<pb facs="15"/>
soules, such a multitude of notable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages: namely forty at Diepe revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Romish Church, which now is in travel of them: If they come to life they shal come forth. These men doe packe them very grosly: for enquiring of any such breach in the Church of Diepe, I cannot learne of more long time revolted then two, the one a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den who allured by a carnall marriage hath violated her spirituall marriage with Christ: the other an English Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 5.22.</note> who vpon a fained conversion intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himselfe into our company and is now returned to his vomit. Howbeit let vs put the case that the reporte of these conversions were as true, as they be forged at pleasure: Is it any mervaile that some loue the world &amp; turn wing to that part that yeeldeth most quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and worldly promotion? Were it not rather a wonder if there were none such?<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.66.</note> Iesus Christ was forsaken of his disciples: how much more wee, who haue nothing but by his bounty? Men
<pb facs="16"/>
in these daies in matter of Religion do follow the course of the affaires, and do fit their beliefe to their worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. The belly hath no eares: And as vsually such are deafe as dwell neere the downefall of great waters, even so the word of God pierceth not into the eares that are deafned with the bruit of the world and stopped with the currāt of Covetize, of voluptuousnesse and of ambition: especially at Paris where mē are bought and sold, &amp; where rewardes are propounded. And God graunt that Idolatry possesse none but those whō she hath deerely paid for▪ herein are we to acknowledge the work of God: that notwithstanding so many allurements and discommodities, yet do the flocke of Iesus Christ grow and encrease, yea even since these men made their vaunts that our Church was so sore shakē. But we boast not so much, neither indeede are these victories ours but our Lorde Iesus Christs.</p>
   <p>In their triumphs they paint mee
<pb facs="16"/>
forth &amp; make me a party in the proofs of their sufficiencie. The auctor of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> fire saith that in the disputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the frier I was twise or thrice at a non plus and so made some of them merry: but hee sheweth neither when nor whervpon. It might peradventure be when the frier refused to enter into any orderly disputation, or to propoūd his reasons in forme, saying that he was not permitted so to do: either when he said that the theft was scourged,<note place="margin">Suetonius. Iulius in seg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento. <hi>73.</hi> Plautus in Aphitruone: aut satisfaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at mihi aut adiuret in super nol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le esse dicta quae in me in sontem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit.</note> but not the thiefe: That <hi>excogitatum Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum</hi> signified a Commentary: That the pardons of foure and fifty thousand yeares are good and receaueable: That <hi>satisfacere</hi> signifieth not to acknowledg his fault to the partie offended, or to testifie that he was sorry for it or when he saying vnto me that God should be vniust if there were no purgatorie, I an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swered that then God should be vniust to such as should liue in the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mēt: also to the Carmelites that dy vpō the friday, who [as themselues report]
<pb facs="17"/>
haue a priviledge that they shal remain in purgatory no longer but vntill the next saterday. But who would thinke that vntruth could so farre exceed? Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I am one of the least amonge the servants of God: yet would I be sorrie that my yeares or want of capacitie should any way preiudice the equity of my cause: but the word of God is migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty even in the mouthes of babes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides should I trouble my selfe with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering an vnlearned man vnseene in the Greeke and Hebrew, as appeared when we were to haue recourse to the Originals in both those lāguages, wher vpon the Iesuits of Turnon tooke vpō them to stuffe his booke with passages collected out of prophane auctors and the Rabbins, into whō hee never thrust his snowt: which Iesuits neverthelesse were many times mistaken in diverse things,<note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering.</note> as in place convenient shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. But how should they make faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful report of things spoken, who make no cōscience to falsifie my writing? See
<pb facs="17"/>
therefore how they entreat me. They produce not my wordes: they reverse the order of my speeches:<note place="margin">The frier beginneth with the last page of my booke.</note> here &amp; there they mangle &amp; snatch at my discourse; one beginneth at one end, an other in the middest: If I speak any thing that bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, they can quietly passe it over with silence: They obiect the matter that I answer, but my answers they suppresse, He that seeketh the truth ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce the very wordes of his adversary: he should trace him step by step with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out counterfeiting, curtalling, or dissē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: but these men by a certaine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral disposition do skippe, as at their masse, over whole leaues: they conceale the most forcible: and the sooner to lead the reader that followeth vs out of our tracke, they shuffle the course of my reasons, and bring the head forth last. Then having thus sented my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, they proclaime before the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace their fiery, burning, magnificall, &amp; and ridiculous titles.</p>
   <p>Some coulor they might haue had
<pb facs="18"/>
for their flight, had my first booke been either tedious or ful of wordes: The chardges of the Impression with the readers impatiencie might haue serued them in steede of figge leaues to cover their shame: but my writing contained few pages &amp; the Arguments lay close: for I studied to lay the bones bare that the sinewes might bee the better seene. Their vnfaithfull dealing doth proceed yet farther: for they forge other obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions then mine: and of mine do they take away the edge by propounding them in other manner then I did: Thus do they skirmish and sport them in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering of themselues: much like vnto the Bulles in the amphitheater to whō they cast men made of straw, vpō whō, being provoked, they dischardged their rage. As if they should say vnto me: you are too rough: The Church of Rome must be more gently entreated: Take away your forcible argumēts for these reasons lie to hard vpon vs, so wil we commune with you. Thus and thus
<pb facs="18"/>
must you obiect that so wee may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere with some coulor: but they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat to giue this warning before.</p>
   <p>I doe therefore protest that these writings of these Doctors doe not cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne me, for that I never spake manie things that they impute to me: &amp; they haue either fearefully dissembled, or malitiously corrupted my best obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Neither can I thinke my selfe suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently satisfied vntill I see my own wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting perfect in the writings of my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries, and their answer set down ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle to article: reason to reason, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cutting of or altering my wordes, or disordering the order of my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</p>
   <p>Reverend Doctors, I beseech you in curtesie,<note place="margin">None of these Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors haue yet answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctory yet resteth with the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uctor.</note> yea I adiure you by the relicks of your cōsciences to entreat me with more equirie: take this booke which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I offer vnto you encreased, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified and corroborated with reasons and some passages of Scriptures: and answer it in such wise as that my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb facs="19"/>
may not be mangled, nor thrust out of order: but that all men may see your answers at the foot of my obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. If your desire to bring the truth to light faileth you not, no more then your leasures, meanes, books, and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port [albeit all these faile vs] wee shall soone perceaue which of vs hath the word of God to warrant: and from the encounter of our reasons truly and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly reported wil proceed the sparks of the truth. The Lord God vouchsafe to direct our pennes, and dispose our hearts to propound such matters as may bee profitable to the salvation of his people, proper to the glory of God and comfortable to the truth of his word.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>