<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull the Maister, Maister-wardens, assistance, and other the brethren of the most worshipfull societie of the Drapers in London: E. W. wisheth all happi∣nesse and aeternall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Cary, Elizabeth, Lady</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111741_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15366</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25643</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111741</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull the Maister, Maister-wardens, assistance, and other the brethren of the most worshipfull societie of the Drapers in London: E. W. wisheth all happi∣nesse and aeternall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Cary, Elizabeth, Lady</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Isahacs [sic] inheritance : dew to our high and mightie Prince, Iames the Sixt of Scotland, of England, France and Ireland the First. By E.W</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Edw (Edward)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison, John 4.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Read, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull the Maister, Maister-wardens, <hi>assistance, and other the brethren of</hi> the most worshipfull societie of the Drapers <hi>in London:</hi> E. W. <hi>wisheth all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> and aeternall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, though my vnskilfull Muse, praesuming in her infancie to soare aboue her reach, feared at first the vulgar view of her vnpollish'd lines, least her wings scortched like those of <hi>Icarus,</hi> her downe-fall should be as great as <hi>Phaetons;</hi> knowing that snarling <hi>Zoylous</hi> will sooner bite with his blacke tooth of enuie, then any well-willer can read and iudge with fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble censure: yet soone resoluing to make choise of your worships for her <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> the aduancers of the vertuous, the maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the learned, friends to the Muses, and helpers to all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proceedings, thus farre she is bold to peepe foorth her head: assured neuerthelesse that some <hi>Agesilaus</hi> will tell her, he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer prooue <hi>sutorem expertum, qui paruo pedi magnos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duat calceos,</hi> and that she is no way to be commended, who tunes
<pb facs="3"/>so high notes with so slender an Oaten Pipe: But such she will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer that her will was better then her worke, and as the Painters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sometimes handles his Pensill, when he should but grinde his colours, so he that will prooue his craftes-maister, must ayme at the famest: but those which shall be such cynicall censorers of her first simtes, let them take the like taske, mend hers, and she will yeeld vp the Bucklers. Thus not doubting of your worships fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>able acceptance, crauing no more: friendly censure, hoping no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> kinde countenance the chiefe of her wish: all which shall arme her against each foule-mouthd <hi>Momus,</hi> or carping <hi>Diogenes,</hi> she commits the tuition of this her poore Orphan to your most worthie protection. Resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships most</hi> humbly deuoted <hi>Edw: Wilkinson.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>