<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen READERS.</title>
           <author>C., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111171_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5738</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen READERS.</title>
                 <author>C., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Wits fittes and fancies : Fronted and entermedled with presidentes of honour and wisdome. Also: Loves Ovvl. An idle conceited dialogue betwene loue, and an olde man. Recta securus. A. C</title>
                 <author>Copley, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>236 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen READERS.</head>
   <p>GEntlemen: these <hi>Wittes, Fittes and Fancies</hi> are of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to admit no eloquence wherewith to delight yee, as also manie of them to seem barren at the first sight, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles to the second eie may minister content and merriment: Vnderstand yee therefore, that I direct them not to the sullen and moodie person, who happily in his austeritie will befoole a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them before euer hee read them, as matter either differing from his soure disposition, or perhaps aboue his wit. Neither doe I professe them as regular Methodes or deepe grounded Axiomes of Logicke certaintie, but as certaine free Offals and presidents of <hi>Wits</hi> wandering variety. <hi>Momus</hi> (Gentlemen) I confesse, were able to make a foule wracke among them, were he as precise as he is malicious; Wherefore, my desire is they come not vnder his Rauin, nor yet vnder <hi>Minos</hi> heauie censure: But vvhosoeuer is Gentle merrie-wittie, he take all. Neither must anie person of what vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation soeuer, take offence at any thing herein cōtained: Considering that mirth, not malice, meanes it all. As for my <hi>Loues Owle,</hi> I am content that <hi>Momus</hi> turn it to a tennis-ball if he can, &amp; bandy it quite away: namelie, I desire M. <hi>Daniel,</hi> M. <hi>Spencer,</hi> &amp; other the Prime Poets of our time, to pardon it with as easie a frowne as they please, for that I giue them to vnderstand, that an Vniuersiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Muse neuer pend it, though humbly deuoted thereunto.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in desire to please you. A. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>