<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Another by A. B.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111843_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07753</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18133</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111843</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Another by A. B.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and easie introduction to practicall musicke : set downe in forme of a dialogue: deuided into three partes, the first teacheth to sing with all things necessary for the knowledge of pricktsong. The second treateth of descante and to sing two parts in one vpon a plainsong or ground, with other things necessary for a descanter. The third and last part entreateth of composition of three, foure, fiue or more parts with many profitable rules to that effect. With new songs of, 2. 3. 4. and .5 [sic] parts. By Thomas Morley, Batcheler of musick, &amp; one of the gent. of hir Maiesties Royall Chappell</title>
                 <author>Morley, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Hoskins, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 183, 35 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>Another by A. B.</head>
   <l>VVHat former tymes through selfe respecting good</l>
   <l>Of deepe-hid Musicke closly kept vnknowne,</l>
   <l>That in our tongue of all to b'understoode,</l>
   <l>Fully and plainly hath our <hi>Morley</hi> showne.</l>
   <l>Whose worthy labors on so sweete a ground,</l>
   <l>Great to himselfe to make thy good the better:</l>
   <l>If that thy selfe do not thy selfe confound,</l>
   <l>Will win him praise and make thee still his detter.</l>
   <l>Buy, reade, regard, marke with indifferent eye,</l>
   <l>More good for Musicke elsewhere doth not lie.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>