<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOVR TO THE Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111840_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68475</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18042</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111840</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOVR TO THE Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essayes : vvritten in French by Michael Lord of Montaigne, Knight of the Order of S. Michael, gentleman of the French Kings chamber: done into English, according to the last French edition, by Iohn Florio reader of the Italian tongue vnto the Soueraigne Maiestie of Anna, Queene of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, &amp;c. And one of the gentlemen of hir royall priuie chamber</title>
                 <author>Montaigne, Michel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 630, 2 pages, portraits (metal cut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOVR TO THE <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, loe-heere a well-meaning Booke. It doth at the first entrance fore-warne thee, that in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the same, I have proposed vnto my selfe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a familiar and private end▪ I have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect or consideration at all, either to thy service, or to my glory: my forces are not capable of any such desseigne. I have vowed the same to the particular commodity of my kinsfolks and friends: to the end, that losing me (which they are likely to do ere long) they may therein finde some lineaments of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and humours, and by that meanes reserve more whole, and more lively foster the knowledge and acquaintance they have had of me. Had my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on been to forestall and purchase the worlds opinion and favour, I would surely have adorned my selfe more quaintly, or kept a more grave and solemne march. I desire therein to be delineated in mine owne genuine, simple and ordinarie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, without contention, arte or studie, for it is my selfe I pourtray. My im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections shall therein be read to the life, and my naturall forme discerned, so farre-forth as publike reverence hath permitted me. For if my fortune had been to have lived among those nations, which yet are sayd to live vnder the sweet libertie of Natures first and vncorrupted lawes, I assure thee, I would most willingly have pourtrayed my selfe fully and naked. Thus gentle Reader my selfe am the ground-worke of my booke: It is then no reason thou shouldest employ thy time about so frivolous and vaine a subject. Therefore farewell. From <hi>Montaigne,</hi> the first of March. 1580.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>