<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111047_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12689</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23009</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111047</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true relation of that vvhich lately hapned to the great Spanish fleet, and galeons of Terra Firma in America : With many strange deliueries of captaines, and souldiers in the tempest, and other remarkable accidents, worthy the obseruation. Also, a catalogue of those persons of account, which eyther perished in this tempest, or were miraculously preserued. Faithfully translated out of the Spanish originall, as it is printed and published in Madrid, Sevil, Lishbone, and other places</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                            <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Spanish Originall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to my hands most op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely, tooke the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of my liking it, and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den apprehension, that it would please the Reader, whosoeuer: not so much because thereby is proposed a kinde of variety of Newes, as in that the glory of God is made apparant in his workes, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence, that can preserue men out of raging seas, and afford his mercy when wee thinke that it is quite denied vs: And although I may incurre an imputation by leaning more to the true sense, then to the words, as they lye in order: yet I will be bold to say, that the sentences here extended, shall neither receiue exoticke interpretation, nor bee carryed with any wanton hand from the true meaning:
<pb facs="3"/>
Be therefore thus fauourable I pray, to reade it without a strict comparison of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. and accept of an honest intent, that ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as much at the satisfaction of worthy deseruers, as any profit can arise out of so meane a worke.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>