<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111043_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12224</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22534</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111043</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie for poetrie. VVritten by the right noble, vertuous, and learned, Sir Phillip Sidney, Knight</title>
                 <author>Sidney, Philip, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Olney, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THE stormie Winter (deere Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Muses, which hath so long held backe the glorious Sun-shine of diuine Poesie, is heere by the sacred pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breathing words of diuine Sir <hi>Phillip Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> not onely chased from our fame-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiting Clyme, but vtterly for euer banisht eternitie: then graciously regreet the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall spring of euer-growing inuention, and like kinde Babes, either enabled by wit or power, help to support me poore Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, whose daring aduenture, hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red frō Obliuions wombe, this euer-to-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admired wits miracle. Those great ones, who in thēselues haue interr'd this blessed innocent, wil with <hi>Aesculapius</hi> cōdemne me as a detractor frō their Deities: those who Prophet-like haue but heard presage of his cōming, wil (if they wil doe wel) not onely defend, but praise mee, as the first publique bewrayer of Poesies <hi>Musaeus.</hi> Those who neither haue seene, thereby to interre, nor
<pb facs="4"/>
heard, by which they might be inflamed with desire to see, let them (of duty) plead to be my Champions, sith both theyr sight and hearing, by mine incurring blame is seasoned. Excellent Poesie, (so created by this Apologie,) be thou my Defendresse; and if any wound mee, let thy beautie (my soules Adamant) recure mee: if anie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend mine endeuored hardiment, to them commend thy most diuinest fury as a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged incouragement; so shalt thou haue deuoted to thee, and to them obliged</p>
   <p>Henry Olney.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>