<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE AVCTOR OF the counterfaicte conferēce &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111899_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19224</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5638.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE AVCTOR OF the counterfaicte conferēce &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discoverye of a counterfecte conference helde at a counterfecte place, by counterfecte travellers, for thadvancement of a counterfecte tytle, and invented, printed, and published by one (person) that dare not avovve his name</title>
                 <author>Constable, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_author">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE AVCTOR OF the counterfaicte conferēce &amp;c.</head>
   <p>ITvvere as easy for meyf Ivvould to discouer your name vvith as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured proofes as to detect the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises and dristes of your conterfeat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference made at Amsterdam, but since as it seameth youe are ashamed to iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the same vvith your name, I am not he that vvill publishe it, because it might be thought by somme that are redye to enterpret thinges to the vvorst that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred might induce me therunto, that vvhich I desire chefely to be effected by this discourse next to the inconuenience that might generally haue grovven by your fraude and desceit vndesciphred is that you vvould looke vpon your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or malice or perhaps bothe, vvhich is manifest by seakinge to maKe diuision betvvene Christian Princes that are in charitye and frendship one vvith an other, by defacing the Monarchical
<pb n="3" facs="2"/>
state, vvhich so longe tyme hath ben vsed and approued, and by disposinge of the Croune of Englande not vveighin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vvheare the right lieth, but vvhear your fācye best liketh; if in this later poit your vvould excuse your selfe by sayng you determine no mans title, the course of your vvhole booKe and diuerses pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises de facto shevue the contrarye.</p>
   <p>These thinges be not os small vveight or importance, for that they concerne kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and kingdomes, and require the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise vvisedome and experiēce of other maner of heddes then yours is, yea and that in nombre to the assēbly of a Court Parlement. Tharfore your maye see vvhat cause of discontentement you geue to all vvise and indifftrent men, and vvhat disgrace you haue braught to your selfe and bretherne, for thar if any happē to be kinge of England besides those tvuo youe vvould seme most to aduance, it is likelye, according to the rules of policye and state that your selfe vvilbe in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
for meddlinge in these matters abo uè your reache and capacitye, and your bretherne vvilbe blamed and banished out of the Country for approuinge, or at the least for not chastisinge your levvde and yvell demenor, methinketh the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting of these incomodities should ma ke youe cōsider of somme remedyes, and the remorse of your conscience shoulde breede repentaunce vvhich cominge from the botome of youe harte vvill force youe in as ample and publicke maner to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame and disauovve your sayd confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as euer passion and partialitye did inuite you to set forthe the same. This is the best and casiest vvaye to satisfie the Princes discontented the people scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized, and your selfe endaungered, and this is that I suppose your vvisest frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vvill aduise you vnto: for my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, I do praye for you, and vvishe no vvaye reuenge to your person, but re formation in your maners, as God I call vvitnes, vvho direct youe to that</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>