<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           <author>Farmer, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111790_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00563</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10698</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111790</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 <author>Farmer, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diuers &amp; sundry waies of two parts in one, to the number of fortie, vppon one playnsong</title>
                 <author>Farmer, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Byrd, William, Assignee of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Farmer, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48+ pages, music, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>Philomusicis.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aruaile not gentlemen, who
soeuer shal see this little book,
that Musicke shewes hir selfe
in this vnusuall vayne. For if
in other arts it be a common
practise (and yet not so ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
as commendable) euerie
way to deuise to further the
studie of each perticuler, why
should Musicke be denied that, which is graunted
the rest? Certes how men do thinke of hir, I do not
know (I doubt but bassely) how they should I am
out of doubt, that is most honourablie. No man can
denie, but that God is authour, as of all other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
qualities, so of this (for so euen the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
who had not right knowledge of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
maiestie, by instinct of nature did see and confesse)
and as of the 7. liberall sciences, which therefore haue
that name, because they are befitting men of most
free birth, she is one in number, so peraduenture,
nay, without peraduenture not the last, if not the
first, in dignitie: for delight wonderfull, for depth
infinite, for commoditie it may happilie be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
whether any more necessarie. Were it not so, it
had not beene to write, which <hi>Tullie</hi> writes true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
of the countrie of <hi>Graecia,</hi> where being the
fountaine of all learning, and the verie seate of wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<hi>sic Musici floruerunt,</hi> as he saith, <hi>vt omnes id
discerent, nec, qui nesciebat, satis excultus doctrina puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur.</hi>
In the same countrie <hi>Themistocles</hi> a Prince of
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Athens,</hi> for that at a feast he refused to play on the
Harpe, an instrument at that time of highest credit,
although in other respects in a maner peerelesse, onely
for this defect, was thought somewhat rude. The
ende of my speech and purpose is this, that the sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
being so excellent, and yet so couldlie followed,
euerie one that knowes any thing of her, should eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
waie be doing for her aduauncement, and such
as are not, are greatly in her debt, such as are, are
fauorably to be accepted, howsoeuer it be not each
mans fate to performe what is singuler. I professe (if
any lesse wise, then I could wish them, misconstrue
my meaning) to doe nothing of ostentacion (for alas
what is this, nay what haue I in me, whereof iustlie
to bost?) I was in hope that students in this art, such
as may learne, as my selfe may, and haue not yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
so farre as I haue, might finde somthing heere
not vnworthie their labor. If it so fall out, I shall be
glad, if otherwise, it was the error of myne opinion,
which I desire may be pardoned to my good will, so
shall I endeuour my selfe to continue my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
without repentance for this I haue done. Fare
yee well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Farmer.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>