<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY GOOD COUSEN Mr IOHN VICARS.</title>
           <author>Vicars, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111557_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14487</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24809</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111557</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY GOOD COUSEN Mr IOHN VICARS.</title>
                 <author>Vicars, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The XII Aeneids of Virgil, the most renowned laureat-prince of Latine-poets; translated into English deca-syllables, by Iohn Vicars. 1632</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 418, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>TO MY GOOD COUSEN M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>IOHN VICARS.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood cousen, as farre forth as my other serious studies would give leave, I have read your <hi>Virgils Aeneïds</hi> translated into english de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casyllables. Wherein (that I may be just, and give you your due) I know not whether you have performed better the part of a good poët or of a good interpreter. In my judgement, I will speak it without feare or flatterie (<hi>quorum causas procùl habeo</hi>) your great pains in transplanting this worthiest of latine poets, into a mellow &amp; neat english soile (a thing not done before) deserveth great applause and good acceptance of all scholars, both such as are under the <hi>ferula</hi> in Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar schools, and such as have their brows bedect with laurell in the Universities. If I were of a perfect wit, or a poët but of an inferiour alloy, I would have sent you some verses as an encomiastick: but I must not mount above my sphere, nor step beyond my last.</p>
   <l>Invida me spatiis natura coercuit arctis,</l>
   <l>Ingenii vires exiguásque dedit.</l>
   <l>Nature, a shallow wit in narrow brains</l>
   <l>That pent, forbids me all poëtick strains.</l>
   <p>And therefore in plain prose I bid you heartily well to fare, and shall ever rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your assured loving cousen <hi>Thomas Vicars.</hi> B.D. Ox.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>