<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111819_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26130</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111819</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doue: or Passages of cosmography : By Richard Zovche ciuillian, of New Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Zouch, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Norton, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thy Patience be not too much discouraged, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture on the little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale of my poore thoughts. I euer rather admired then profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Poetry, the necessitie of my Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to which a higher direction
<pb facs="33"/>
then mine owne choyse hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mee, forbidding the one, and that delight, which beyond ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent receiued in all sorts of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, hath beene presented to me in this, occasioning the other: yet haue I, as my leasure gaue me leaue, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my selfe in this idlenesse that reliefe, which in other varietie most doe thinke they may iustly vse. I know some whose credit hath chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged respect exceeding strong in preiudice against the composing and reading such trifles, yet the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of diuers in this kinde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb facs="33"/>
by others, whom I haue no warrant to distrust, makes my small experience thinke, that some Muses, like Silke-wormes, spinne a fine threed for necessary vse, as many like Spiders curious webs for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable admiration. His censure who affirmed the reading of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis du Gaule</hi> as dangerous to youth, as of <hi>Macciauel</hi> pernitious to old men, was, as the Author, truly gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; yet I presume it extends not to all which without proclaiming ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to wisdome and iudgement, seeme rais'd or fashioned by imagination.
<pb facs="34"/>
There is, who hath vndertaken to illustrate by places of the <hi>Arcadia,</hi> all the points of the Art of speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: I will adde (which is as much as <hi>Achilles</hi> his Father desired <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> should teach his Sonne) hee is rude that cannot discerne, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding austere that scornes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue therein, worthy behauiour and carriage both in priuate and common businesse: And one as vnderstanding in the Pollicie of Letters and Peace, as <hi>La Noue</hi> was experienced in the Discipline of Armes, and a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled State, by exquisite vnfolding of
<pb facs="34"/>
some fabulous Stories, makes it plaine, that the Cesternes of these times, deriue the fulnes of their wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by no other conueyance then such narrations, from the purer springs of all antiquitie. To whom he had yeelded his assent; who, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his faithfull labours in teaching to beleeue, I know had care he might not be disprou'd, and farther graceth Poetry, with the choise appellation of <hi>the Soules vvoing-Suite</hi>; in which diuers (their excellencie carrying them higher) haue shewed their thoughts not vnfit for solemne, yea
<pb facs="35"/>
Sabaoth deuotions. And truely, they who will be pleas'd to credit our owne tongue, and age, may finde our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and later Poets, capable of that commendation, which was giuen the antienst among the Greekes: That if their writings were preserued, no part of Learning should wholy pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish. <hi>Spencer,</hi> hauing as well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered Morall, and Heroicall matter for vse and action, as <hi>Du Bartas</hi> (now ours) Naturall and Diuine, for study and meditation. I would not diminish the worthy reputation of other Volumnes; for mine owne
<pb facs="35"/>
part, it being knowne to some, I haue spent time in them, I should be loth to be thought ignorant of that, which I am perswaded all that know doe well allow. But as the plaine way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth most, the neerest many, so I am sure there are some, who, had they beene shewed that which was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, would haue prooued successe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when they haue returned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding empty from Systems and Commentaries.</p>
   <p>What I haue attempted in this subiect, was long since excellently performed by <hi>Dionysius</hi> in Greeke,
<pb facs="36"/>
and diuers in Latin, whose example hath giuen me some incouragement, but no more direction then <hi>Magel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> to Syr <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> shewing the Straights might be past, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structing how. Some places may seem obscure, but I intend it to those who vnderstand, or desire to know some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this Argument: I haue not touched all, because I would be short, and haue vsed shortnes, as vnwilling to sweat, and make a labour of my sport, as any fastidious lookers on are quickly apt to distast satietie. As it is, <hi>Reader,</hi> I indifferently leaue it
<pb facs="36"/>
to thy discretion: what esteeme thou wilt be pleased to put on it, is in thy power, how I may valew thy esteeme remaines in mine.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>