<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my honoured Mistres, Mi∣stres Elizabeth Tanfelde, the sole Daugh∣ter and heire, of that famous and learned Lawyer, Lawrence T anfelde Esquire.</title>
           <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111950_Bo1_16</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20814</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7193</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111950</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my honoured Mistres, Mi∣stres Elizabeth Tanfelde, the sole Daugh∣ter and heire, of that famous and learned Lawyer, Lawrence T anfelde Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands heroicall epistles. By Michaell Drayton</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 77 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="48"/>
   <head>To my honoured Mistres, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stres <hi>Elizabeth Tanfelde,</hi> the sole Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and heire, of that famous and learned Lawyer, <hi>Lawrence T anfelde</hi> Esquire.</head>
   <p>FAire and vertuous Mistresse, since first it was my good fortune to be a witnes of the many rare perfections where-with nature and education haue adorned you: I haue been forced since that time to attribute more admiration to your sexe, then euer <hi>Petrarch</hi> could before perswade mee to by the prayses of his <hi>Laura.</hi> Sweete is the French tongue, more sweet the Italian, but most sweet are they both if spoken by your admired selfe. If Poesie were prayselesse, your vertues alone were a subiect sufficient to make it esteemed though amongst the barbarous Getes: by how much the more your tender yeres giue scarcely warrant for your more then womanlike wisedom, by so much is your iudgement, and reading, the more to be wondred at. The Graces shall haue one more Sister by your selfe, and England by your birth shall add one Muse more to the Muses: I rest the humbly deuoted seruant to my deere and modest Mistresse: to whom I wish, the happiest fortunes I can deuise.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Michaell Drayton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>