<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111197_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19533</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5963</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short summe of the whole catechisme : wherin the question is propounded and answered in fewe wordes, for the greater ease of the common people &amp; children. Gathered by M. Iohn Craig, minister of Gods word, to the Kinges Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Craig, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 49, that is 56, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>MEruell not (gentle Reader) that I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge no authoritie of the Scriptures, nor fathers, for the confirmation of this doctrine: seeing my purpose is not so much to instruct our prophane Atheistes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postates, as to put our brethren in memory of that doctrine, which they dayly here confirmed (in our ordinarie teaching) by the scriptures and consent of the godly Fathers.</p>
   <p>Alwayes if eyther the brethren, or other woulde haue further confirmation of this doctrine, let thē reade the <hi>Institution of M. Iohn Calum,</hi> and other godly men, who haue written aboundantly for the defence of this doctrine, according to the scriptures of God. I doubt not, but good men, and such as are perswaded of the trueth, will take this mine excuse in the best part, and giue thankes to God for my labour, taken for their comfort. But as for the godles band of Atheistes and Apostates whom God hath ordained to distruction, I care not what they shall iudge of this my simple writing, &amp; paines taken for the instruction of the ignorant. I woulde maruell greatly of the successe of our doctrine, which is now impugned and pursued by men, (to the sight of the world) of great estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and iudgement, if the same had not come to passe to the Prophets and Apostles in their age, whose doctrine and religion was most faisty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned, and cruelly persecuted by the Sonnes <pb facs="5"/> of perdition. Of this we are forwarned by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, that men, after the witnessing of the truth, shall depart to their vomit againe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Traitoures and persecutors of Gods trueth, which they professed afore with vs. When we see this fierie tryall and fearefull iudgement in the Church, let vs examine our selues be time, and call to God for constancie in the trueth, and praise his iustice in the blinding of those, that in so great a light, willingly and maliciously, delite in darkenesse and blaspheme the way of righteousenesse. Of this sort are sundrie of our nation, whose blasphemous writinges come dayly to our handes, to the tryall of our faith and constancie, to the farther blinding of the reprobate, and their greater condemnation in the day of the Lord Iesus Christ. To whome with the Father and the holy Spirit, be all honor and praise e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>