<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>This first booke of Table Philosophie sheweth the nature and qualitie of all manner meates, drinkes and sawces, that are vsed at meales.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111450_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24411</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111450</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>This first booke of Table Philosophie sheweth the nature and qualitie of all manner meates, drinkes and sawces, that are vsed at meales.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The schoolemaster, or teacher of table philosophie : A most pleasant and merie companion, wel worthy to be welcomed (for a dayly gheast) not onely to all mens boorde, to guyde them with moderate [and] holsome dyet: but also into euery mans companie at all tymes, to recreate their mindes, with honest mirth and delectable deuises: to sundrie pleasant purposes of pleasure and pastyme. Gathered out of diuers, the best approued auctours: and deuided into foure pithy and pleasant treatises, as it may appeare by the contentes</title>
                 <author>Twyne, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>This first booke of Table Philosophie sheweth the nature and qualitie of all manner meates, drinkes and sawces, that are vsed at meales.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the saying of <hi>Macrobius.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Macrobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> lib. 1. de Saturnalia.</note> It were a very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seemely thing that <hi>Philosophie</hi> which intreateth curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously in bookes, of dueties, &amp; behauiour at feastes, should be afearde to shew her self also at feastes: as who should say, shee would not auouch that in deedes, which shee professeth in words: Or that shee could keepe no meane or measure, who only prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the meane and measure her self vnto al humane affaires. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I now welcome her to my table to thintent shee should moderate herself, whose order of instruction is to teach all other, how to moderate and gouerne themselues. And shortly after in the same place he sayth, VVherfore, such a kinde of Philosophie, there is no goodman, no place, nor companie, that wyll exclude it, which so behaueth it self in euerie respect, that it seemeth to be necessarie in euerie place, as though it were vnlawfull it should be absent. Then forasmuch as <hi>moderate Philosophie</hi> ought to be present at the table and feastes of the wise, and learned: euerie goodman must vse the same, both for to profite &amp; delight others. For as the same <hi>Macrobius</hi> writeth, our talke ought to be merie at the table, more poudred with pleasure the sauced with seueritie. And our communication at the boorde, as it ought to be faier with honestie: so must it be pleasant with delight. VVherfore, it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally expedient, that all table talke be either concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; qualitie of the meates and drinkes wherof we feede, or of table questions wherwith we may be made merie and sturred vp to mirth at the boorde, or els touching them their condition, and manners with whom we meete at the table, or lastly of such meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and honest deuises wherwith we may be refreshed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted at our meate. And for this cause I haue determined to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title this worke, <hi>The Schoolemaster or teacher of Table Philosophie,</hi> and haue diuided the same into foure seuerall partes. The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherof, I haue thought good to set downe together before the whole worke, and afterwardes euerie Argument seuerally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eche booke whereto it belongeth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>