<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his Maiesties good Subiects.</title>
           <author>W., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111717_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15069</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25372</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111717</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his Maiesties good Subiects.</title>
                 <author>W., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discovrse and discovery of Nevv-found-land : with many reasons to prooue how worthy and beneficiall a plantation may there be made, after a far better manner than now it is. Together with the laying open of certaine enormities and abuses committed by some that trade to that countrey, and the meanes laide downe for reformation thereof. Written by Captaine Richard Whitbourne of Exmouth, in the county of Deuon, and published by authority</title>
                 <author>Whitbourne, Richard, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Barrett, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 69, 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To his Maiesties good Subiects.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing had my breeding for many yeeres together in the courses of Marchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and Nauigation, I haue, through the expence of my tyme in that calling, set this downe to my selfe, for my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therein, to obserue and collect, wherein my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours might become profitable to my Countrey; and the rather, because I could not be ignorant, how much the maintenance, and increase of Shipping and Mariners concernes vs, who may fitly be stiled, The nation of the Sea; which generall reasons were more and more commended to me, by more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular considerations offered me, in the notice I took of the disposition and affaires of other States, to which ours hath relation; some poynts whereof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now seasonably be mentioned; some others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to what I discourse of, will present themselues in their places, as I shall goe along in giuing account of my endeuours.</p>
   <p>Among my vndertakings &amp; imployments in Sea-faring, the most part haue been to an Iland, called <hi>New-found-land,</hi> in part heretofore outwardly disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, but neuer looked into by those discouerers as it deserued; from the beginning I found it promise
<pb facs="5"/>
well, in respect of the purpose, I had to gather some thing for the bettering of the Common wealth; and the more I made tryall of it, the more satisfaction it gaue me: Therefore I affected that course better then any other I fell vnto; insomuch as I did so fix my industrie vpon it, that for the qualifying of my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, I obtained Commission from the State to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in it, and am now come to propound to my Countreymen, the benefit they may make of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Plantation and Traffique there: the following Discourse will satisfie them, if they will forgiue the vnhansomenes of the forme it is put into, and looke into the matter it selfe only.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The description of new-found land, and the commodities thereof.</hi>
      </note>The Iland of <hi>New-found-land</hi> is large, temperate and fruitefull, the fruitfulnesse of it consisting not only in things of sustenance for those that shall inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite it, but in many sorts of Commodities likewise, of good vse and valew to be transported. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues in it are ingenuous, and apt by discreete and moderate gouernments to be brought to obedience. The seat is fit for Harbour and reliefe, vpon the way betweene vs and <hi>Virginia,</hi> and consequently of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to vs in any action that may engage vs, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by way of offence or attempt, in regard of those parts of the World. The Seas are so rich, as they are able to aduance a great Trade of Fishing; which, with Gods blessing, will become very seruiceable to the Nauie; and the increase of fishing there, cannot despaire of finding Portes enow to vent the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie at profitable rates.</p>
   <p>Now if you would vnderstand what motiues wee haue at home with vs to carry vs thither; doe but
<pb facs="5"/>
looke vpon the populousnesse of our Countrey, to what a surfet of multitude it is subiect; consider how charitable for those that goe, and how much ease it will be for those that stay, to put forth some of our numbers, to such an imployment of liuing. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the English nature with others; and finde whether wee haue not as much courage as they, both to vndertake and mainetaine; onely wee lose it, in hauing lesse industry. Turne then towards the Lowe Countries; behold how they haue wonne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, by taking aduantage of our sitting still; (and most remarkable in this point of fishing) which if their Audit were published, would be found (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue) one of the best Agents they haue, both for their strength and wealth.</p>
   <p>There is another motiue also, which amongst our Auncestors was wont to finde good respect, namely, the honour of the action, by the enlarging so Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; and that which will crowne the worke, will be the aduancement of the honour of God, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poore Infidels (the Natiues of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) to his Worship, and their owne saluation.</p>
   <p>I commend the designe to the entertainement of his Maiestie and his Kingdomes: because I esteeme it such a one as deserues, not only to be vndertaken, but to be gone thorow withall.</p>
   <p>And as it is a Proiect of no fantasie in mee, but a truth grounded vpon a well-weighed experience; so haue I not presumed to publish it, but vpon good approbation, as hath already appeared.</p>
   <p>If these considerations, with many others here omitted, but contained in the ensuing Discourse,
<pb facs="6"/>
may worke an impression in the affections of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Subiects, for the aduancement of Gods glory, their owne and their Countries prosperity, it shall be some content toward the great paines, losses of time, and expence of my meanes that I haue sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the prosecuting thereof, for which I trust you will at least returne your thankfull acceptance; and so I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing friend, <hi>R. W.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>