<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A famous fight at Sea in the Gulfe of Persia.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111388_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13447</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23753</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111388</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A famous fight at Sea in the Gulfe of Persia.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A famous fight at sea : VVhere foure English ships vnder the command of Captaine Iohn Weddell, and foure Dutch ships fought three dayes in the Gulfe of Persia neere Ormus, against 8. Portugall gallions, and 3. friggots. As also the memorable fight and losse of the good ship called the Lion, with the barbarous crueltie of the enemie truly declared. With a farewell and hearty well-wishing to our English sea and land forces</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A famous fight at Sea in the Gulfe of <hi>Persia.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THe Eternall prouidence hauing diuided mankinde into many Kingdomes, Climates, People, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet to the end there should be a vnitie or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall society amongst all men, hee hath permitted traffique and Commerce betwixt Nation and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Realme and Realme. Nauigation and Shipping being as it were the fleeting bridges, for the transportation and exportation of men &amp; Merchandise, from Countrey to Countrey, that though God hath not inriched any one Kingdome or Countrey with all things, (the one hauing what the other hath not:) yet to maintaine hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane society (but chiefly for his owne glorie in dispersing his gifts) Commerce and traffique hath been vsed at all times, and in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; for the which noble imployments our Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> hath not beene inferiour to any Nation for the ability and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Merchants, and I thinke not equalled by any for goodnesse and sufficiencie of skilfull Nauigators, and Marriners, and strength of shipping, and munition.</p>
   <p>So that neither the parching heat of <hi>Libia</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> or the benumming frigidity of <hi>Groen-land,</hi> or the <hi>Hiperborean</hi> Icle Regions, neither the farre remotenesse of <hi>China</hi> Eastwards, or the vttermost bounds of the new world <hi>America</hi> Westwards, the dangers Stormes, Gusts, Flawes, Tempests, Spowts, and
<pb facs="5"/>
Tornadoes, or Monsoones, the hazard of Shoales, Rockes, Leakes, Enemies, Pirates, barbirous and cruell Nations, vnwholsome and vntemperate Aires and Climates, Sea or Land Monsters, or what perills may be named or thought vpon, hath euer daunted or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred our Merchants and Mariners to prosecute and accomplish their continuall, laudable, and profitable vndertakings.</p>
   <p>Amongst whom our noble, worshipfull, and worthy East-India Merchants, and Aduenturers, may in these later times be held as superlatiue to those of former ages, their inestimable charge, their mighty force, their valuable returnes, and their aduenturous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards rightly considered. All which being no part of my purpose to treas of, I referre the Reader onely to the description of two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Sea-fights, performed betwixt the English and the Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals; which, though the newes of it could not be brought hither so soone as if it had beene done vpon the Coast of <hi>Zealand</hi> or <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>; yet, as soone as winde and weather could bring it, I had it, and with what time I could well spare I haue written it, assuring my selfe of what I dare assure my Reader, which is, that all is true. In which regard, I thought it vnfit to let it lie buried in obliuion, or the hatefull and ingratefull graue of forgetfulnesse. In it is valour described, and manifested in the liues and deaths of many of our English, and extreme cruelty and inhumanity in the Enemy. But to the matter.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>