<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the ryght worshyp¦ful Master Thomas Brooke Esquire, Rychard Shyrrey wysheth health euer∣lastynge∴</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111062_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12121</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22428</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the ryght worshyp¦ful Master Thomas Brooke Esquire, Rychard Shyrrey wysheth health euer∣lastynge∴</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of schemes [and] tropes : very profytable for the better vnderstanding of good authors, gathered out of the best grammarians [and] oratours by Rychard Sherry Londoner. Whervnto is added a declamacion, that chyldren euen strapt fro [m] their infancie should be wel and gently broughte vp in learnynge. Written fyrst in Latin by the most excellent and famous clearke, Erasmus of Roterodame</title>
                 <author>Sherry, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>232 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the ryght worshyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful Master Thomas Brooke Esquire, Rychard Shyrrey wysheth health euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastynge∴</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not but that the title of this treatise all straunge vnto our Englyshe eares, wil cause some men at the fyrst syghte to maruayle what the matter of it should meane:<note place="margin">The tytle of thys worcke straunge.</note> yea, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture if they be rashe of iudgement, to cal it some newe fangle, and so casting it hasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from thē, wil not once vouch safe to reade it: and if they do, yet perceiuynge nothing to be therin that pleaseth their phan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sy, wyl count it but a tryfle, &amp; a
<pb facs="2"/>
tale of Robynhoode. But of thys sorte as I doubte not to fynde manye, so perhaps there wyll be other, whiche moued with the noueltye thereof, wyll thynke it worthye to be looked vpon, and se what is contained therin.<note place="margin">Sheme and Trope.</note> These words, <hi>Scheme</hi> and <hi>Trope,</hi> are not vsed in our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishe tongue, neither bene they Englyshe wordes. No more be manye whiche nowe in oure tyme be made by continual vse,<note place="margin">Vse maketh straūge thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges familier.</note> very familier to most men, and come so often in speakyng, that aswel is knowen amongest vs the meanyng of them, as if they had bene of oure owne natiue broode. Who hath not in hys mouthe nowe thys worde Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphrasis, homelies, vsurped, abolyshed, wyth manye other
<pb facs="3"/>
lyke? And what maruail is it if these words haue not bene vsed here tofore, seynge there was no suche thynge in oure Englishe tōgue where vnto they shuld be applyed? Good cause haue we therefore to gyue thankes vnto certayne godlye and well lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, whych by their greate studye enrychynge our tongue both wyth matter and wordes, haue endeuoured to make it so copyous and plentyfull that therein it maye compare wyth anye other whiche so euer is the best. It is not vnknowen that oure language for the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rousnes and lacke of eloquence hathe bene complayned of,<note place="margin">Oure lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage falsely accused of barbarous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> and yet not trewely, for anye defaut in the toungue it selfe, but
<pb facs="3"/>
rather for slackenes of our coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimen, whiche haue alwayes set lyght by searchyng out the elegance and proper speaches that be ful many in it: as plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly doth appere not only by the most excellent monumentes of our aūciēt forewriters,<note place="margin">Gower. Chawcer. Lidgate.</note> Gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Chawcer and Lydgate, but also by the famous workes of many other later: inespeciall of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ryght worshipful knyght syr Thomas Eliot,<note place="margin">Syr Thomas Elyot.</note> which first in hys dictionarye as it were generallye searchinge oute the copye of oure language in all kynde of wordes and phrases, after that setting abrode good lye monumentes of hys wytte, lernynge and industrye, aswell in historycall knowledge, as of eyther the Philosophies,
<pb facs="4"/>
hathe herebi declared the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfulnes of our mother toūge, loue toward hys country, hys tyme not spent in vanitye and tryfles. What shuld I speake of that ornamente Syr Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wyat? which beside most excellente gyftes bothe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and bodye, so flouryshed in the eloquence of hys natiue tongue, that as he passed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in those wyth whome he lyued, so was he lykelye to haue bene equal wyth anye other before hym, had not enuious death to hastely beriued vs of thys iew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el: teachyng al men verely, no filicitie in thys worlde to be so suer and stable, but that quick lye it may be ouerthrowen and broughte to the grounde. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye other there be yet lyuynge
<pb facs="4"/>
whose excellente wrytynges do testifye wyth vs to be wordes apte and mete elogantly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare oure myndes in al kindes of Sciences: and that, what sentence soeuer we conceiue, the same to haue Englyshe oracion natural, and▪ holpē by art, wher by it may most eloquētly be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Of the whych thynge as I fortuned to talke wyth you,<note place="margin">The occasion of thys trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ise.</note> Master Brooke, among other matters this present argument of Schemes and Tropes came in place, and offered it selfe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be bothe profitable and pleasaunte if they were gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, and handsomelye set in a playne ordre, and wyth theire descriptions hansomely put into our Englishe tongue.
<pb facs="5"/>
And bicause longe ago, I was well acquaynted wyth them, when I red them to other in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Latin, and that they holpe me verye muche in the exposicion of good authoures, I was so muche the more ready to make them speak English: partli, to renew the pleasure of mine old studies, and partelye to satys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy your request.</p>
   <p>Beside this, I was moued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so wyth the authorytye of that famous clarke Rodul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Agricola,<note place="margin">Rodulphus Agricola.</note> whyche in a certeine Epistle wrytten vnto a frynde of hys, exhorteth mē what soeuer they reade in straunge to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gues▪ diligently to translate the same into their owne language: because that in it we sonar perceiue if there
<pb facs="5"/>
be any faute in our speaking, and howe euerye thynge ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rightly hangeth together or is darkelye, ruggishly, and superfluously wryttē. No ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nacion hath there bene but y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> learned in it haue written of schemes &amp; fygures, which thei wold not haue don, except thei had perceyued the valewe. Wherfore after theyr example obtaynyng a lytle lesure, I red ouer sundrye treatises, as wel of those which wrot long ago, as of others now in our daies: fyndynge amonge them some to haue wrytten ouer brieflye, some confuselye, and falselye some.<note place="margin">Mosellane</note> Mosellane hathe in hys tables shewed a fewe fygures of grammer, and so hathe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foūded them together, that his
<pb facs="6"/>
second order called of Loquu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion pertayneth rather to the rhetoricians then to hys pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.<note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> Quintilian briefly hathe wrytten bothe of the Grama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and rhetorical Shemes, but so that you may soone per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue he did it by the waye, as muche as serued hys purpose.<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> Cicero in hys boke of an ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour wyth hys incomperable eloquence hathe so hid the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, that scarselye they may be tryed oute by theyr names, or by theyr exāples. Erasmus in hys double copye of words and thynges,<note place="margin">Erasmus.</note> hath made as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tytle declareth but a comenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of them bothe, and as it wer a litle bil of remembraūce. Wherfore to make these thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges more playne to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> students
<pb facs="6"/>
that lyst to reade them in oure tongue, I haue taken a lytle payne, more thorowelye to try the definicions, to apply the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amples more aptly, &amp; to make things defused more plaine, as in dede it shal ryght wel apere to the dylygente. I haue not translated them orderly out of anye one author, but runninge as I sayde thorowe many, and vsyng myne owne iudgement, haue broughte them into this body as you se, and set them in so playne an order, that redelye maye be founde the figure, and the vse wherevnto it serueth. Thoughe vnto greate wittes occupyed wyth weightye mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, they do not greatelye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, yet to such as perchaūce shal not haue perfecte instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures,
<pb facs="7"/>
they may be commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to helpe them selues for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better vnderstandynge of such good authors as they reade. For thys darre I saye, no elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente wryter maye be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as he shulde be, wythoute the knowledge of them: for as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as al togethers they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe to Eloquucion, whyche is the thyrde and pryncipall parte of rhetorique. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon scholemasters be wont in readynge, to saye vnto their scholers: <hi>Hic est figura</hi>: and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme to axe them, <hi>Per quam figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi>? But what profit is herein if they go no further? In spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge and wrytynge nothyng is more folyshe than to affecte or fondly to laboure to speake darkelye for the nonce, sithe the
<pb facs="7"/>
proper vse of speach is to vtter the meaning of our mynd with as playne wordes as maye be. But syth it so chaunseth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> som<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme ether of necessitie, or to set out the matter more plaīly we be compelled to speake other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse then after common faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">A figure not to be vsed but for a cause.</note> onles we wil be ignorante in the sence or meaninge of the mater that excellente authors do wryghte of, we muste nedes runne to the helpe of schemes &amp; fygures: which verely come no sildomer in the writing and speaking of eloquente english men, then either of Grecians or Latins. Many thinges might I brynge in to proue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great profyt to be in them but that they are to be learned euen of necessitie, for as muche
<pb facs="8"/>
as not only prophane authors wythout them may not be wel vnderstand, but that also they greatelye profit vs in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of holye scripture, where if you be ignoraunte in the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue speches and Tropes, you are lyke in manye greate doubtes to make but a slender solucion: as ryght wyll do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stefy <hi>Castelio Vestimerus</hi> and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>,<note place="margin">Westimerus</note> no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble doctor saint Augustine.<note place="margin">Augustinus</note> I confesse I haue not made the matter here so perfecte as my wyll and desyer is it shoulde haue ben, and that I haue but brieflye touched, and as it were with my litle fynger poynted to these thinges, which require a lēger declaracion. For what can be hasted, and absolute to? But if God spare me lyfe, I
<pb facs="8"/>
truste hereafter to make it an introducciō, wherbi our youth not onlye shall saue that moste precious Iewell, Time, whyle they wander by them selues, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>adynge at all aduentures sun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry and varyous authors: but that also thei shalbe able better to vnderstande and iudge of the goodlye gyftes and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in mooste famous and eloquente oratoures. For as lyke plesure is not to him whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gooeth into a goodlye gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den garnyshed wyth dyuers kindes of herbes and flowers,<note place="margin">And apte si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> and that there doeth no more but beholde them, of whome it maye be sayde that he wente in for nothynge but that he wold come out, and to hym which be syde the corporall eie pleasure,
<pb facs="9"/>
knoeth of eueri one the name &amp; propertye: so verelye much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there in readynge good authors, and in sundrye sortes of menne that do it: and muche more pleasure, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit hathe he whiche vseth arte and iudgement, then the other, whiche wyth greate studye in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede turneth them ouer but for lacke of the knowledge of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes wanteth also the fruite and delectacyon that he more amplye myghte obtayne. The lyuynge God from whome all good giftes do procede, gyue vs grace so to order all oure words and speache, that it may be to his honour and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>¶ Geuen at London <date>the .xiii. day of Decembre. Anno. M.D.L.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>