<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONO∣RABLE AND VERTVOVS ELIZABETH VAVX, Mother to the Lord HAR∣RODOVVNE.</title>
           <author>F., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111535_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13694</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23988</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111535</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONO∣RABLE AND VERTVOVS ELIZABETH VAVX, Mother to the Lord HAR∣RODOVVNE.</title>
                 <author>F., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The follovving of Christ : Diuided into foure bookes. Written in Latin by the learned and deuout man, Thomas a Kempis, canon-regular of the order of S. Augustine. Whereunto also is added the golden Epistle of S. Bernard. And also certaine rules of a Christian life, made b Iohn Picus the elder, Earle of Mirandula. Translated into English by B.F</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 422, 30 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE AND VERTVOVS ELIZABETH VAVX, Mother to the Lord HAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RODOVVNE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable &amp; Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, the publike demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration which you haue lately giuen of your true desire to follow the footsteps of our Lord, vndergoing so heauy a Crosse for his sake, with so ready and resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a minde, hath moued mee to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate this little Booke of the IMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATION OF CHRIST vnto you: assuring my selfe that it will be no lesse gratefull to you to see it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in light, purged from many mistaken sentences which were in the former Translation, then the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and practise thereof wil be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to others; it being so diuine and excellent a worke, as in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb facs="3"/>
of such as can best judge of this matter, of all the Bookes which are written, that treate of Spirit &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Perfection, the holy Scripture excepted, it is inferiour to none, if it excelleth not all.</p>
   <p>No book hath bin more approued by generall consent, none more often printed &amp; translated into diuers lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, none more esteemed, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, yea commanded also by the chiefe Masters of Spirit of some reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Orders, to be often read by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one in priuate, and once a week publikely to al. So full of sweet sense is this diuine Flower, that the most spirituall Bees may daily draw from thence great plentie of celestiall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. It is a dish of so diuine meat, that it neuer satiates the deuout mind: but as the Wisdome of God doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to all such as sit at that heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly banquent; so shal they find in this spiritual food, <hi>The more they eat it, the more
<pb facs="3"/>
they shall hunger after it.</hi> Eccles. 4.</p>
   <p>And the reason hereof is, for that it containeth so great depth of spirit, and so great store and variety of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly documents, that it seemeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer new to the Reader, and like ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Manna, affordeth to euery one that delightfull taste which best a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the palate of his soule: and none can loath it, but they whose lustes doe carry them to Aegyptian slauery. A true Israelite may feed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it forty yeares together, and euer finde such pleasing taste and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing strength by vse therof, as wil su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine him in the desert of this world, and enable him to goe on without fainting, till he arriue at his promised inheritance of eternall rest.</p>
   <p>The practise of that which this booke doth teach, couereth the soule with the rich garment of grace, and adorneth it with the splendent pearls of Euangelical perfection, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="4"/>
vs more pleasing in the sight of God, then can the deckings of all earthly jewels make the fairest Lady in the Kingdome, where you are, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare beautifull to the eyes of men. It returneth abundant gaine for su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stained losses, and enlargeth the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which is now restrained. It rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth vp to cheerefull confidence the debased head, &amp; placeth in a Throne of endlesse honour those who in this world doe seeme imprisoned in the blacke cloud of disgrace.</p>
   <p>To you therefore who haue so willingly endured the losse of your earthly substance, I haue thought good to present this Euangelicall Pearle, and incomparable Treasure contained in a little roome. Here you shall find the most perfect manner of conforming our selues to Christ our heauenly paterne, &amp; see the vertues set forth in their colours, which did most shine in the life of our Lord
<pb facs="4"/>
himselfe; and reade in plaine and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar phrase those Lessons of high per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which are commended vnto vs by the highest Wisdome, &amp; which haue made as many Saints, as they haue had diligent and obseruant fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
   <p>Accept therefore, I beseech you, this little Present, presented by him who wisheth you much more tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall happines, then your present state affordeth; and that endlesse glory, whereof your present suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is no vncertaine pledge. This first of Nouember. 1612.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all dutie. <hi>B. F.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>