<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipful
and his good Vncle, Maister
HVGH BAMFILD Esquier, GEORGE
TVRBERVILE vvisheth Nestors
yeares, vvith all good fortune.</title>
           <author>Turberville, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111051_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12672</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22990</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111051</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipful
and his good Vncle, Maister
HVGH BAMFILD Esquier, GEORGE
TVRBERVILE vvisheth Nestors
yeares, vvith all good fortune.</title>
                 <author>Turberville, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eglogs of the poet B. Mantuan Carmelitan, turned into English verse, &amp; set forth with the argument to euery egloge by George Turbervile Gent. Anno. 1567</title>
                 <author>Baptista, mantuanus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 93, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Book industry, catalogues and inventories</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipful
and his good Vncle, Maister
HVGH BAMFILD Esquier, GEORGE
TVRBERVILE vvisheth Nestors
yeares, vvith all good fortune.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORSHIPFVL, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
not altogither to be
idle and vvaste the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
Time (the rarest of
all Ievvels) procurde me
to vndertake the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of this Poet: so
Nature, vvith your sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
curtesies bestovved
on me vvithout hope of
recompence at any time, enforced me (for vvant of
better vvay to shevve my good meaning) to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
to you this rude and slender Booke, translated
into our mother tongue. Hoping that as I haue not
vvronged the Poet in any poynt in my translation,
or impairde his credite vvith the Latins, in forcing
him to speake vvith an English mouth contrary to
his nature and kinde: so neyther that I haue mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred
you occasion to myslike vvith me for dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the same to you: a man vvhose benefites I
may and vvill endeuour to requite, but shall neuer
<pb facs="3"/>
be able to rid my score of his good turnes, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
the obligation of hys many and infinite curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies.
If a man be bound by all meanes that he may
to gratifie hys vvell deseruing friendes: then may
not I quiet my selfe and be at silence till I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised
the requital of some part of your friendships,
by some slender gift, such as my Fortune and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
chaunce vvill permit me to exhibite vnto you.
And none can I fynde, eyther more agreeing vnto
my state, or fitter for your vvorship, than this nevv
translated Poet. Whose title though at the first per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
shall seeme ouerrude and barbarous (for EG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOGS
are altogither of the Countrey affaires) yet
doubt I not but that both the matter shal be found
pleasant, and the style agreable to the Latin phrase.
I do not mystrust but MANTVANS Shephierds
vvill vse the matter vvith such dyscretion, and so set
their rusticke Pipes in tune, as you vvill rather cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
their melodie, than myslike their audacitie:
that being Countrymen dare vndertake to tel their
tales before you, and reason of so many and seueral
matters as in these Eglogs they do. They vvere not
in that age such siellie sottes as our Shephierdes are
novve a dayes, onely hauing Reason by Experience
to prate of their Pastures, and folde and vnfolde
their flockes: But these fellovves, vvhome the Poet
and I haue here brought in, vvere vvell able both to
moue the doubtful cause, and (if neede vvere) to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scide
the proponed case. They not only knevve the
Calfe from the Lambe, the Woulfe from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stife,
<pb facs="3"/>
but had reason to knovv the dyfference tvvixt
Tovvne and Countrey, the oddes betvvixt Vice and
Vertue, and other thinges needefull and appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to the life of man. Wherfore (Vncle) as I shal
craue you to accepte this my slender gift, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
the Patronage and Defence of the
same: So shall I request the Gods
to allovve you the aged
Nestors yeares,
vvith no mysseaduenture in al
your life.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Nephewe and daylie Orator
George Turbervile.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>