<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Praeface to the chri∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111546_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15779</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26043.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111546</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Praeface to the chri∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise, shewing the possibilitie, and conueniencie of the reall presence of our Sauiour in the blessed Sacrament : the former is declared by similitudes and examples: the latter by the causes of the same</title>
                 <author>Wright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Trognesius, Joachim</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 23, that is 121, 3 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Praeface to the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ROM the same fire the sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher match and the white taper draw two sundry flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: the one yeelding a sweet sauour, the other a stinking sent: the one in colour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling the brightnesse of heauen, the other in shew the darknes of hell: the one ascending with milde and calme motion, declaring the aeriall and vniforme substance, the other still frying &amp; bubling expresseth the terrestriall nature and violent mixture. From the same Scriptures Catholikes and Heretikes drawe diuers lights: the Catholike cleere, bright, worthy of God, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to man, agreeable with the Text, consent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Fathers, answerable to antiquitie. The Heretikes, darke expositions, forced interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, racked sences, stinking of pride, breathing sensualitie, dissenting from the Primitiue Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours, swaruing from ecclesiasticall traditions, repugning to Christs church the pillar of truth. This diuersitie proceedeth not from the word of God, which is most holy, and lieth alike open to them both, but from the Interpreters dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As in the aforesaide example, those vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="3"/> lights of the taper and match were not cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the fire, but by their owne qualities and temper. For the Catholike commeth with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, the Heretike with arrogancie: the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike with submission to the leaders of Christs flocke, the heretike with presumption of his own conceit: the Catholike armed with consent of Fathers, the heretike with his owne singularity: the Catholike trusting in God, and hoping in his grace, the Heretike relying wholly, eyther vpon the forces of his feeble wit, or beguiled with the illusions of Lucifer. The which difference, thogh in al controuersies of religion now called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, it appeereth manifestly (to all those who wil examine them to the botome, and wade into the depth: where they shal find no other grounds of heresie, than Chimericall interpretations, and selfe-willed expositions of the Scriptures) yet in none so much as about the blessed Sacrament. The Catholikes from these foure wordes,</hi> Hoc est corpus meum, <hi>deduce their dreadfull, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent, maiesticall, and deified sacrifice, the light of Paradice, the foode of Angells. The Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes their common-table Communion, their prophane supper, their schismaticall cup, their tipicall bread, their vnblessed breakefast. Yet as the taper receiueth often light from the stinking match, so the wisedom of God by his infinit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence
<pb facs="3"/> hath so permitted these hereticall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions in his church: that by occasion of them the verities of the Catholike religion shine nowe as cleare as the Sun at noonetide in the beuty of brightnes. For how many worthy Volumes haue bin penned thereupou most learnedly, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise should neuer haue sene light? what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion hath this antiperistasis or enuironing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsion wrought in the hearts of Catholikes? for by infallible recordes it may be prooued, that for a hundred that were accustomed to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate weekely in great citties, now there are well nie ten thousand. Againe, since the Eucharist hath beene so impiously blasphemed of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, how gloriously, how religiously, howe maiestically hath it beene consecrated vpon the altare, reserued in the tabernacle, caried in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession, in respect of former ages? what cōcourse haue we seene of Catholiques to the church to worship it? what feruour in praying to it? what learned Sermons in exalting it? what zeale to defend it? and not without cause: for so great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence the maiestie of God required, his loue deserued, our homage enforced, so many graces thereby receiued, exacted, so that heresie hath rubd off the rust of ignorance from many catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, it hath burned the chaffe of imperfections, and purified the corne of deuotion, it hath blown</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>off the ashes of remissenes, and reuiued the coles of seruour and charitie. Finally, it hath disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the cloudes of some irreuerence, and caused the blessed eucharist shine like a spirituall sunne in the Catholike church. If saint Gregory called the sin of Adam</hi> Foelix culpa, <hi>a happy offence, that deserued such a Redeemer, I may say hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py heresie that caused such reformation: nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cursed heresie, and blessed prouidence of God, in ordaining so inordinate a thing to so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate and noble an end. Wherefore since al ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, either by deuotion, or religious almes, or frequent communion, or dayly reuerence, or ardent affects, or learned bookes endeuoure to oppose themselues against the enimies of this sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, I thought good to cast my two Mites in</hi> Gazophylacium, <hi>that they with whome I</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luke 21.</note>
      <hi>am lincked in faith might knowe mine affection by worke, and he to whome my soule is due, may here receiue the of-spring of my soule. The title perhappes wil seeme somewhat stale, but I hope the maner of explicating to be new: or at least, that which lieth scattred abroad in Fathers &amp; Doctors, here they shall find vnited in one. And this argument the rather I haue handled first, because I prooued in my selfe and diuers other Catholikes, that it did not onely reuiue greatly our faith, but al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o moued vs to conceiue a more</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>maiesticall and diuine opinion of the wisedome and prouidence of God in instituting this sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For by vnderstanding how agreeable it was with all his attributes, how glorious for his church, how conuenient for man, how profitable to all members of his elected congregation, I could not but cry out with Dauid &amp; say,</hi> quam magnificata sunt opera tua Domine! Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia <note place="margin">Psal. 103.</note> in sapientia fecisti: impleta est terra possessione tua: <hi>How glorious are thy workes O Lord! thou hast made al things in wisedome: the earth is filled with thy riches. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I haue tried by experience, that whē faith and reason, grace and nature, consort together they make a sweet harmonie: that is, when rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son applieth the mysteries of our faith to the wit by shewing them credible, and worthy to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, then faith flourisheth exceedingly, and can hardly be remoued: as when an excellent eie meeteth with the cleare light of the sunne, howe farre, how sharply, and how distinctly will it dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne euen very aereall vapours, and almost in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisible moates. Of such a man spake the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet when he described the happy man, who did me ditate in the lawe of God night and day, that</hi> folium eius non defluet, <hi>his leafe shal not fal, because long meditation vppon the mysteries of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 1.</note>
      <hi>Faith keepeth the soule without withering, and
<pb facs="5"/> faith without perishing: not but that a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like may leese his faith, but with greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie and more excesse of malice: as it befell not long agoe to a person of no small account in England, whom I had knowne in time past a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, but then a protestant: by chaunce once falling in company with him, I demaunded how it fared with him in religion: if he had forsaken that faith vtterly which he sometime approued so feruently: forsaken quoth he, no faith, I am of opiinion, that he which once is thorowly groū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Catholique religion, can not possibly but with extreme malignitie alter his religion: wel he may change it in shew, wel he may maske it with protestancie, wel he may varie his affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but his iudgement, his conceit, his faith, hardly wil he change or neuer: and therefore by Gods grace, after I haue dispatched some af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; I wil renounce the externall profession, of that religion I knowe false and detest internally: but before his affaires were dispatched, death had dispatched him, that others may learn what it is to dally with GOD in matters of saluation. The third reason that mooued me was, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and clamorous voices of ignorant Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, who cease not to crie vpon Catholikes, &amp; vpbra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> them with absurdities, impossibilities, vnworthy opinions of God and man, dishonora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="5"/> to him, and horrible to vs. Therefore, that they may see their owne ignorance, I thought no better way to refute them, then by setting downe the theologicall causes of so diuine a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie: but yet I know it will befall manie that shal reade them, either not to conceiue them, or to contemne them, for so Dauid said long since:</hi> Quam magnificata sunt opera tua domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <note place="margin">Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lm. 91.</note> nimis profundae factae sunt cogitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes tuae, vir insipiens nō cognoscit, &amp; stul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus non intelliget haec: <hi>O Lord how glorious are thy works, thy thoughts are too profound: those an vnwise man doth not know, nor a foole vnderstand. For it seemeth to me that the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike reading these causes, and a Catholike rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the same, are like two men entring vnto a garden, but the one at midnight with a torch, the other in the morning: the heretike endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onelie with the light of reason, beholdeth them with torchlight, he can neither discerne the varietie of colours, nor grace of figures, not disposition of knots, nor borders enclosing, but onely a glimpse or darke shewe farre differing from that lustre and glory the beautie of the flowers and odoriferous hearbs represent. The Catholike comming in the morning when the sunne riseth, veweth and distinguisheth the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, lillies, marigolds, their formes, their sents,
<pb facs="6"/> their order, the gratefullaire and paradise of delight. The Catholike perusing this booke, will see what he beleeued, and note distinctly howe euerie thing standeth, with what faith all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes professe, because hauing had true faith before, by liuing in exercise of receiuing the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist in the Catholike Church, by reading bookes, hearing sermons and spirituall confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, all tending to the same effect: he (I say) wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> conceiue no small delight in contemplating all the garden, and euerie flower and hearbe in particular. And the heretike if he haue grace, may say with himselfe, if this the papists holde were true, certainely God were glorified won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully his loue were ineffable, the partakers of this sacrament were in a blessed state. Truly of God can do it, me thinks it standeth well with his prouidence, it argueth an abisse of loue and charitie, it were a thing to be desired of al men: and then afterwards let him consider who first abolished this point of faith out of many Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes hearts. Martine Luther an Apostate Munke, (Nunquid cognoscentur in tenebris mirabilia eius &amp; iustitia eius in terra obliui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis: Shall perhaps his wonders bee knowne in darkenesse? and his iustice in the lande of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion) for life a Libertine, a practiser with the Diuell, by whose suggestion hee confesseth
<pb facs="6"/> he first was induced to abrogate the masse, which for fifteene yeares (as himselfe saith) he celebrated: and last of all his bad life, had as beastly a death. After that he had suffred ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke in faith, and proclaimed wars against the Church of Christ while he liued, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after his death, the sectaries of his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies were diuided into factions, and principally about the blessed sacrament, who in interpreting foure simple and as plaine words as might bee spoken.</hi> Hoc est corpus meum, <hi>to auoyde the right interpretation of the Catholike Church, haue inuented no more then foure score false expositions. The which dissention while I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider they represent vnto me the blind Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, who wandering in the blacke night of their misbeleefe, sought out which was the last end of man, and almost as many diuers endes they set downe, as newe Philosophers tooke the question in hand. And no maruaile, for as the Mathematicians say, from point to point it is impossible to draw more right lines then one, but crooked and by lines ten thousand: therefore the Catholikes keeping perpetually one vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and right exposition, it is no wonder if he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes infinitely multiply their false and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious interpretations. To conclude, I would wis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> to preuaile so much with all Protestants, into</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>whose hands this present Treatise shal happen, as to mcditate with thēselues reason by reason, and confer the maiestie &amp; benefit of this myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with other supernaturall mysteries of our faith, as the incarnation of Christ, the renewing of our souls internally by baptisme and penance, the fauors and presence of the holy Ghost in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, and I doubt not but they shall find an admirable conformitie and proportion betwixt on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> another, and then let them remember what a treasure they want that the catholikes enioy: and how they are plagued into the deepest pit of ingratitude, by not acknowledging that benefit which (except the incarnation) surpasseth all others that euer God bestowed on man: and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally let them returne to the fold of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, where they shal find the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paradise watered with the flouds of Gods grace, and vpon the banks,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoe. 22.</note>
      <hi>the tree of life laden with the fruite of this sacrament.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>