<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my very especiall and sin∣uler good freinde, Mayster dmond Yonge, Gentilman: Student of the Law. Iohn Car, wisheth con∣tinuall health, and prosperitie, to the pleasure of God.</title>
           <author>Carr, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S111212_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18040</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4685</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S111212</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my very especiall and sin∣uler good freinde, Mayster dmond Yonge, Gentilman: Student of the Law. Iohn Car, wisheth con∣tinuall health, and prosperitie, to the pleasure of God.</title>
                 <author>Carr, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ruinous fal of prodigalitie : with the notable examples of the best aprooued aucthours which hath bin written of the same. Newly set foorth by Iohn Carr</title>
                 <author>Carr, John, citezein of London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Kirkham, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my very especiall and <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uler good freinde, Mayster</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dmond Yonge, Gentilman: Student <hi>of the Law.</hi> Iohn Car, <hi>wisheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall</hi> health, and prosperitie, <hi>to the pleasure of God.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDERYNG</hi> with my self, how greatelye wee are bounde, to render thanks vnto God, for the great benefits, which he hath bestowed vpon vs: whiche benefits are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit, and wee are not able to yeelde vnto him, prayse, honour and glory, so much as he deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, whiche thinge I did well perpend, therfore I thought it meete to practise my pen, in the exercise of the litle talēt which God hath lent vnto mee: to the
<pb facs="3"/>
augmenting of Vertue, and to abrogate vice, for I was moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to diuulgate, or set foorth this simple woorke, accordinge to my literature, as far as my capacitie was able to compasse. For I beyng wholy drowned, in the Lake of ignorance, had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more precious, to present vnto you, but this the paterne of my simplicitie, whiche God hath lent vnto mee. I was the much more imboldened, to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this simple worke vnto you, sith that I haue knowen your zelous affection, which yet you haue euer borne, to the encrease of learnyng, and that your stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hath euer bin prest, to serche
<pb facs="3"/>
and looke for the preseruation of the same. And moreouer because that I had a good hope and affection, that you woulde as well esteeme of this my sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple woorke, beyng the first fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of my labour, as though it were a greate deale more bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And according as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and vnderstand how that you doo take this simple woorke being presented vnto you, it wil animate and encourage me, to employ my studie, more then yet I haue doone hitherto. And although that I want the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of rethorike, to beutyfi and set forth this simple worke, yet I shall desyre ye, as I haue don
<pb facs="4"/>
before, to accept it: and if that any fault you finde there in, I shall desyer ye; to ostende your fauour so muche, that I may haue entelligence of it, for I wyll euer more submit my self, to the counsell of the learned: and further more, I shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syer ye, not thinke the worst of it, for I wil not, nor meane not to teache any man, how and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what sort, he shall behaue him selfe, in any respect. For I my self, haue as much neede of teaching, as he that hath most, but I will alway stande vnder the correction of the learned. Thus hopyng that you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this my trauayle and good
<pb facs="4"/>
wil, according to your accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med curtesie, and be a patrone, in the defence of this my worke and to gratifie your curtesie, I will shew my self frendable towards you, and now I am lothe to trouble ye, with any▪ more circumstance, but wishyng God to preserue you in health, wealth, and felicitie, to his blessed will and pleasure.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friende to his poore power Iohn Carr.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>