<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112196_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06984</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17403</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The description, of that euer to be famed knight, Sir Iohn Burgh, Colonell Generall of his Maiesties armie : vvith his last seruice at the Isle of Rees, and his vnfortunate death, then when the armie had most need of such a pilote. Written by Robert Markham, captaine of a foote company in the same regiment, and shot also in the same seruice</title>
                 <author>Markham, Robert, captain</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 22, 2 pages, plates, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>I</hi> Will not Dedicate these weeping lines</l>
      <l>Vnto a laughing Lord for Patronage,</l>
      <l>That without Mourning habit richlyshines</l>
      <l>In gold, nor will I send a Pilgrimage</l>
      <l>My sorrowes, brought a bed in this same Booke,</l>
      <l>To be protected by a Ladyes Looke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor will I inuocate a Iudge, because</l>
      <l>I write vpon an Honourable fate,</l>
      <l>Vntimely hastned; for within his lawes,</l>
      <l>Deathes immature are all degenerate,</l>
      <l>He that condemneth life, and goods, shall be</l>
      <l>No pittilesse protector (Booke) to thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No Sycophant shall see thee by my will,</l>
      <l>No, nor a golden Coward, for I vow,</l>
      <l>I hate his quaking qualitie as ill,</l>
      <l>As any the worst vice that raigneth now;</l>
      <l>A foole shall neuer thy sad lines behold,</l>
      <l>Because Brasse is as good to him as Gold.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But I will send thee like a Marshall Booke,</l>
      <l>Vnto all Souldiers, lac'd with noble skarres,</l>
      <l>That thinkes on <hi>BVRGH</hi> with a deiected looke,</l>
      <l>And that hath knowne him well in all his Warres,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>That can repeate all things that he hath done;</l>
      <l>Since the first minute that his sand did runne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And that perhaps the glory of his worth,</l>
      <l>His noble Birth, his seuerall Commands,</l>
      <l>Will in a larger volumne blason foorth,</l>
      <l>Then this that passeth through my feeble hands,</l>
      <l>For to set foorth his rise, and not his fall,</l>
      <l>Kirneld with life, and not with Funerall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I could my selfe Heroicke stories make,</l>
      <l>Of all the passages, of all his facts,</l>
      <l>But that a mightie volume it would take,</l>
      <l>And I should be so pleased with his Actes,</l>
      <l>I should not halfe be sad enough, to write</l>
      <l>His last fare well, my Heart would be too light.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And therefore I will vnto other braines,</l>
      <l>Leaue the whole progresse of his former dayes;</l>
      <l>Ile onely like an Eccho take the paines</l>
      <l>To sing his end, and crowne his end with Bayes,</l>
      <l>Which if I Miser-like too sparing doe,</l>
      <l>Let euery Soule ioyne in my sorrow too.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And then shall <hi>Robert Markham</hi> be,</l>
      <l>Most happie in his Ellegie.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>