<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHTLY HONORABLE, AND right Reuerend Father in God, IOHN, by diuine Prouidence, Lord Bishop of London.</title>
           <author>Price, Sampson</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112001_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10079</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20333</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112001</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHTLY HONORABLE, AND right Reuerend Father in God, IOHN, by diuine Prouidence, Lord Bishop of London.</title>
                 <author>Price, Sampson</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons warning by Laodicea's luke-warmnesse. Or A sermon preached at Paules-crosse, the 10. of October, 1613 : Being the first Sunday in tearme. By Sampson Price, Mr. of Arts, of Exeter-Colledge; and preacher to the cittie of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Price, Sampson</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 58, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHTLY <hi>HONORABLE,</hi> AND right <hi>Reuerend</hi> Father in God, IOHN, by diuine <hi>Prouidence,</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat your <hi>Honour</hi> commanded, I haue <hi>performed,</hi> as God <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled.</hi> This <hi>Sermon</hi> which by your <hi>powerfull</hi> Authoritie I preached, is now at the <hi>request</hi> of many <hi>religious</hi> friends prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and beggeth shelter and <hi>protection</hi> vnder your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships <hi>iudicious</hi> and reuerend <hi>approbation.</hi> It was <hi>harkened</hi> to attentiuely by the Honourable <hi>Lord MAYOR,</hi> and the publishing of it afterwards earnestly requested by <hi>him,</hi> whose <hi>true loue</hi> to learning, may challenge a greater <hi>duety</hi> from more worthy <hi>hands,</hi> then these rude <hi>first-fruits</hi> of my paines at the <hi>Crosse.</hi> Besides, my <hi>excuses</hi> may be, the <hi>raritie</hi> of Sermons in
<pb facs="3"/>this <hi>Argument</hi> which is so necessary, the <hi>manifesting</hi> of my desire of <hi>doing</hi> good to my vttermost poore pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Gods <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>testifying</hi> to the world that I desire to giue some <hi>testimony</hi> of my vnfained thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to your Honour, who <hi>countenanced</hi> mee in the Vniuersitie, where you were a zealous, religious, and worthy Gouernour. <hi>Sinne</hi> is more powerfull, now, in the <hi>dottage</hi> of the world, then it was in the <hi>nonage,</hi> so that there is neede of Pulpit and Presse, to <hi>represse</hi> it. I know your <hi>loue</hi> to the truth, which hath <hi>encouraged</hi> many, and now is so necessary to be <hi>manifested,</hi> the loue of many <hi>growing cold.</hi> My weekely labour, in that <hi>Pastorall charge,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth much <hi>paynes,</hi> constrained me to take vp those plaine notes, which I deliuered, and now haue retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>them,</hi> with an <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of the <hi>Authors</hi> names, which is the best reward that can be giuen to them in the iudgement of <hi>Patritius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Patrit.</hi> ep. l. de instit. resp. <hi>Bas.</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>Gr. Ier.</hi> apol. adu. <hi>Ruff. Gr.</hi> de <hi>Basil.</hi>
      </note> and the aduise of <hi>Basil</hi> to <hi>Gregory:</hi> Whose names concealed may brand a man with the note of <hi>theeuery,</hi> as <hi>Ierome</hi> speaketh. God hath made your Honour <hi>a Kingly Pallace</hi> of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and placed you, in the eye of this <hi>Land,</hi> ouer this <hi>Honourable Citty:</hi> goe on in <hi>defending</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; so the Lord shall continue his graces to your <hi>Honour</hi> in this life, and multiply them with greater <hi>glory</hi> in a better <hi>life;</hi> for which I shall pray while I <hi>liue,</hi> and <hi>rest</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your</hi> Honors <hi>in all dutie to be commanded, SAMPSON PRICE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>