<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT ILLV∣strious Prince, IAMES STEVVART: Duke of Lenox, Earle of March, Lord Darnley, Aubigney, Torbolton, and Methuen, Baron of Leighton, Bromswoulde, Knight of the most noble Order of the Gar∣ter, and one of his Majesties most Honorable Privie-Coun∣cell.</title>
           <author>Tyrwhit, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112798_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07610</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18003</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112798</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT ILLV∣strious Prince, IAMES STEVVART: Duke of Lenox, Earle of March, Lord Darnley, Aubigney, Torbolton, and Methuen, Baron of Leighton, Bromswoulde, Knight of the most noble Order of the Gar∣ter, and one of his Majesties most Honorable Privie-Coun∣cell.</title>
                 <author>Tyrwhit, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mirrour for Christian states: or, A table of politick vertues considerable amongst Christians : Divided, into three bookes. Reviewed, and augmented, by E. Molinier, of Tolose priest, and Doctor of Divinitie. And by him dedicated, ro [sic] the most illustrious lord, the Lord Cardinall of Valette, Archbishop of Tolose. Translated into English, by VVilliam Tyrvvhit, Sen. Esquire</title>
                 <author>Molinier, Étienne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parker, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 216, 219-361, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT ILLV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious <hi>Prince,</hi> IAMES STEVVART: Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> Earle of <hi>March,</hi> Lord <hi>Darnley, Aubigney, Torbolton,</hi> and <hi>Methuen,</hi> Baron of <hi>Leighton, Bromswoulde,</hi> Knight of the most noble Order of the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and one of his Majesties most Honorable <hi>Privie-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the wisest Counsell of the happiest Kingdome you sit E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, and judicious; that, by the advantage of your Princely extraction, this by the Industry of your owne endeavors. Hereby, your Grace hath confuted time; proving Experience is not alwayes wrinckled, nor Wisedome gray-hayr'd. This Greatnesse of
<pb facs="3"/>Your bloud, hath placed you neere to the most glorious Monarch, and the splendor of Your Vertue addeth yet a higher Title. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong these universall Acclamations, it were a Crime black as Malice, should I be silent, who to the Memory of the great and Good Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> Your Graces Vncle, owe a Religious Tribute. You are His heyre, and I by the Law of Gratitude Your Vassall. Receive (then) with a gracious Eye this first tender of a Service, than which none more humble, none more sincere. And by the Indulgency of Your Favor, give life to this Translation, which by Your Acceptation, shall tryumph over Envie. Though herein I may seeme presumptuous, yet shall I not (I hope) prove unserviceable, esteeming no mans happinesse above mine, being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Honor of Subscribing my selfe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most humble, and most Devoted Servant: <hi>WILLIAM TYRVVHIT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>