<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Harward, Simon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112568_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02793</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12924</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112568</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Harward, Simon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two godlie and learned sermons, preached at Manchester in Lancashire : before a great audience, both of honor and vvoorship. The first, containeth a reproofe of the subtill practises of dissembling neuters, and politique worldlings. The other, a charge and instruction, for all vnlearned, negligent, and dissolute ministers: and an exhortation to the common people, to seeke their amendment, by prayer, vnto God. By Simon Harward, preacher of the woord of God, and Maister of Arte, late of Newe Colledge in Oxfoord. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Harward, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>260 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧The Preface to the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a Christiā,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.7. Ephe. 6.11. 1. Thes. 5.8.</note> is in the holie Scriptures oftētimes compared vnto the life of a soldier, because we are as it were sworne in the Sacramēt of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, to fight manfullie vnder the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Iesus Christe, not onelie against the vaine and wicked entisementes of the fleshe, whereby we are drawne to the abhominable lustes and pleasures of voluptuous liuing and against the daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous assaultes of Satan the Prince of this world, which seeketh continuallie to deuoure vs, and to drowne vs in the pit of desperation &amp; confusion; but also against the subtill snares of the world, which either by ritches and the glorie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hereof, dooth prouoke vs vnto coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ousnesse, or else by slaunderings, reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nges, iniuries, and oppressions, dooth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rre vs vp to impatiencie, hatred, enuie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd malice: we are therefore to call to
<pb facs="3"/> remembraunce cōtinuallie, that notable propertie, and qualitie of a Christian Soldier, to arme our selues with patiēce against the daie of triall, that we may as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> sayth to <hi>Timothie; Suffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. 2.3.</note>
      <hi>as good Soldiers of Iesus Christe.</hi> And this dooth our Sauiour teach vs in the Gospell after the Euangelist Saint <hi>Luke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 14.31.</note> when he asketh the question. <hi>VVhat King going about to make warre against an other King, dooth not sit downe and take councel, whether he be able with ten thousand, to meet him which commeth against him with twentie thousande?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>VVhereby he dooth admonishe vs to ponder and weigh our strength and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie beforehand, and not rashlie and careleslie to enter into the battaile. And therefore, as that Captaine is greatlie to be condempned, which wil not prouide for any helpe and furniture, vntill the time doo come, that the onset must be giuen, and the stroakes begin to flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him. And as that Soldier sheweth him selfe verie carelesse and negligent,
<pb facs="3"/> vvhich will neuer thinke vpon his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and weapons, vntill the time doo come that he must enter into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Euen so that christian is ouermuch giuen to carnall securitie, vvhich being a Soldier in the Spirituall warfare of Christe, vvherin the victorie bringeth no earthlie triumph, but the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiple crowne of glorie: and the losse, is not the death of the body onelie, but the casting of bothe body &amp; soule into hell fire: vvill not yet once sit downe to take councell aforehand of his abilitie, nor once remember his weapon of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, nor once by praier make proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for it, vntill the houre doo come, that euen now the trumpet dooth crie alarum, and his enimies fal vpon him. Of which sort of Soldiers, I am afeard there are verie many in the Realme of Englād, vvhich because the Lord hath giuen vs many, happy, plentifull, and peaceable yeeres, vnder our gratious Princesse <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (the Lord lōg pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue her Maiestie, and giue vs grace so
<pb facs="4"/> to repent and amend our sinfull liues, that for our wickednesse and vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, her daies be not shortned:) do therefore lothe to heare the preaching of the armour of patience, and not once remēber to pray vnto God for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the same. But rather they seeke by their pollicies, to ioyne them selues in league with the enimies of Christe, that if trouble and affliction should come, they may auoide the daunger, not by patience in suffering for the name of Christe, but by a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous shrinking from their Lord and sauiour. And these may well be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the <hi>Ostridge,</hi> who when there was a battell, between the foure footed Beasts and the Birds to please the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, shewed foorth his hoofe, and to make the Birds beleeue that he was of their side, he put foorth his byll &amp; win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and so pretēding to take part with bothe, was in deede traytor to bothe.</p>
   <p>And therfore, wheras of late, beeing appointed by my very good Lord, the
<pb facs="4"/> Bishop of <hi>Chester,</hi> I preached a Sermon at <hi>Manchester</hi> in <hi>Lankashire,</hi> as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the bolde &amp; constant confessing of the Lord Iesus, and the patient suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of affliction for his names sake: I haue thought good to publishe the same in writing, to the view of those Christian Soldiers, into whose handes it shall please God to send it, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they maie learne bothe the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, which they owe vnto their grande captaine Iesus Christe, and the prouision which they ought to make in time for the armour of patience, and also be admonished, howe they shall sit downe and take councell, and make their accoumpts of the charges which are required to a Christian mans pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession. And this our sauiour dooth reach vs by an other similitude, taken of the wisedome which ought to be in a builder: <hi>VVhich of you</hi> (sayth he) <hi>bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing minded to builde a Tower,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 14.28.</note>
      <hi>dooth not first sit downe, and count the costes and charges, whether he haue sufficient to
<pb facs="5"/> performe it or no? least that after he hath laide the foundation, and is not able to finishe it: all that beholde it, beginne to mocke him,</hi> saying. <hi>This man beganne to builde, and was not able to make an ende.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Euen so all we which builde our sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vppon the foundation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apostles, Iesus Christe him selfe being the head corner stone, must first sit downe and cast our accoumpts, whether we be able to performe it or no. In what manner must we reckon our charges? First, whether we be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie resolued to shewe foorth the fruite of our profession, in our liues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersations. For otherwise, vnlesse with hearing, we ioyne dooing, &amp; with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing, expressing: Our sauiour shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs,<note place="margin">Math. 7.27.</note>
      <hi>That we build not vpon the rocke, but wee are like vnto the foolishe man, which buildeth vpon the sande, where the raine falling, and the floods running, and the windes blowing, doo beate downe the house, so that the fall thereof is great.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>And secondlie, we must count our charges, whether we be thorowlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by the grace and assistaunce of God (whome we call vpon continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for helpe, strength, &amp; succour) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantlie with the mouth to confesse the Lorde Iesus, and with patience to take vp our crosse and followe him, so that, <hi>Neither father nor mother, nor wife nor children, nor brother nor sister, nor farmes nor Oxen, nor lande nor liuing, nor golde nor siluer, nor worldlie promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor tribulation nor anguishe, nor persecution, nor famine, nor nakednesse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8.35.</note>
      <hi>nor perill, nor swoorde, nor life, nor death, nor Angelles, nor principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor powers, nor thinges present, nor thinges to come, nor height, nor deapth, nor anie other creature, shall be able to seperate vs from the looue of GOD, which is in Christe Iesus our Lord.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Argolandus,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Affrica,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ganne to laye a foundation, when
<pb facs="6"/> he came to <hi>Charles</hi> the great, the king of Fraunce, and was purposed to haue forsaken his Heathenish superstition, and to haue embraced the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Christe. But when he sawe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene poore folkes, simplie arrayed, to be set at meate before <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> he asked him what he meant to entertain such simple wretches in his presence?</p>
   <p>The king made aunswer: <hi>These be they whome I keepe alwaies before me, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of my maister &amp; his freends.</hi> And beeing demaunded, of what mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and of what freends? He sayde. <hi>Of my maister Christe and his twelue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, who liued in poore and base estate heere vpon earth. If the case be so</hi> (said <hi>Argolandus) that your maister vseth his freends no better, I care not greatlie for his freendship, neither doo I meane to be anie of his freends.</hi> And so the Heathen Prince refused to become a Christian, because he did not consider, that the Crosse was alwaies a companiō of the Gospel of Christ, and that the children
<pb facs="6"/> of God, were to be iudged and measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, not by outward prosperitie, but by inward graces, &amp; therefore with shame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he gaue ouer his building, so that it might iustly haue been said vnto him. <hi>This man beganne to builde, and was not able to make an ende.</hi> But we must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that the charges of a Christian building, is not to imagine, that we shall leade a softe, easie, quiet, ritch, delicate, and pleasaunt life: in honour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itches, daintie fare, pride, and pleasures of the world. But we must sit downe &amp; so make our accoūpts: <hi>That we must be content to forsake all we haue,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 14.33.</note>
      <hi>for the name of Christe: and patientlie to submit ourselues to all troubles whatsoeuer, for the bolde and open confessing of the Lord Iesus our sauiour.</hi> For so doth our mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er Christ foretell his Disciples: when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e sayth vnto them. <hi>Beware of men,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Iohn. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ey will deliuer you vp to the councelles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd scourge you in their Sinagogues. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hall excommunicate you, yea, the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>all come, that whosoeuer killeth you,
<pb facs="7"/> shall thinke he dooth God good seruice. If ye were of the world,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iohn. 15.19. &amp; 16.20.</note>
      <hi>the world would looue his owne, but because ye are not of the world, but I haue chosen you out of the world, therfore the world hateth you: Ye shall weepe and lament, but the world shall reioyce.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now therfore that we christian Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, may in time be carefull for suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient furniture against the day of trial, and thinke vppon our haruest before the hower doo come, that the stroakes shall light vpon vs, and learne afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande, what duetie we owe vnto our cheefe captaine Iesus Christe, and how we may in all thinges please him, for as <hi>Paule</hi> sayth. <hi>No man that warreth, will entangle himselfe in the affaires of this life,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim 2 4.5</note>
      <hi>because he woulde please him which hath chosen him to be a Soldier, and if anie man striue for a maisterie, he is not crowned, except he striue as he ought to doo.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That vve may therefore endeuour in time, to knowe howe we ought to
<pb facs="7"/> striue, and as vvise builders, sit downe and cast our accoumptes, before vve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ake that vvorke in hande, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours of the Gospell of Christe: I trust that this Treatise, vvill be some thing auayleable to prouoke vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, if the Reader thereof will not so much respect, and looke for any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urious and artificiall handeling of the same, as ponder and laye vppe in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eart, the proofes and reasons, vvhich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re simplie and plainlie therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed.</p>
   <p>I vvas purposed also to haue pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed the seconde parte of this Texte, vvhich I handeled in the same place, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e next morning following.</p>
   <p>But because I shall haue occasion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>treate more at large of that article <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f Iustification, in an other vvorke vvhich I am determined by Gods as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>taunce heereafter to publishe: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue thought good nowe to omit it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d in steede thereof to ioyne an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her Sermon which I made too, before
<pb facs="8"/> in the same place, the last time that Ministers were there ordained. That, as in the first Sermon generallie, all mē maie learne how to striue, and how to cast their accoumpts in their Christian profession: so in the second especially, Ministers may learne the same: which are as it were captaines and cheefe buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, vnder our Lord and sauiour Iesus Christ. It may peraduenture seeme vnto you a tedious thing, that so large a Treatise should at once be vttered vnto the people: but you may easilie consider, that the matter which we had then in hand, was not to be posted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with quick speede and celeritie, but that euen as in the Apostles time, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters were appointed with fasting &amp; prayer: so it was behoouefull that I should at that time with continuance in preaching and praier, keepe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple occupied longer then the wunted māner, and withdraw them from their accustomed diet. And againe, if nowe in penning the discourse, I haue in
<pb facs="8"/> some places enlarged it, I trust you wil not denie, but that the waightinesse of the matter, dooth greatlie require it.</p>
   <p>The Lorde giue grace, bothe to me which haue vttered this doctrine out of his holy woord, and also to you which shall reade the same, that beeing watered with the dewe of his holy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, it may so reforme vs, renew vs, and builde vs vp into the perfect building of Christe: that we may euerie one of vs, discharge our dueties in our seueral vocations, and let our light so shine before men, that they may see our good workes, and glorifie our Father in heauen. <hi>Amen.</hi> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in Christe Iesu: from <hi>VVarrington,</hi> the. 8. of <hi>Maie.</hi> Anno. 1582.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>Simon Harwarde.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>