<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE, Containing an Aduertise∣ment to the Readers, who call themselues CATHO∣LIKES.</title>
           <author>Carleton, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112818_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69071</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4632</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE, Containing an Aduertise∣ment to the Readers, who call themselues CATHO∣LIKES.</title>
                 <author>Carleton, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Directions to know the true church. Written by George Carleton, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Carleton, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 111, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A PREFACE, Containing an Aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Readers, who call themselues CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Readers, for your sake was this vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Your instruction is my desire and prayer. <hi>Moses</hi> did wish that all the people of<note place="margin">Num. 11. 21.</note> God might prophesie, and that God would giue them his Spirit: and so do wee wish. But there bee many false teachers, that keepe the people in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and are desirous that they may neither heare nor vnderstand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, but as they receiue from their lippes. Hence is it that so many Bookes are written, and secretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed into your hands, of purpose to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you. The care of your good hath mooued mee to take this paines, to lay downe these directions, that haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bene the directions of the Church,
<pb facs="8"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="10"/>
and must euer bee: that you may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderstand your owne estate, and the ostentation of them that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues <hi>Catholikes,</hi> but are not, that leade you with vaine shewes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of things that are not, as iugglers vse to doe. If any shall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse an answere to me, I will informe you before hand how you may easily iudge of the answere. For wee know what they can doe, we know their best and their worst: but for your satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which is all my care, I will heere warne you of the maner of their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; that your selues may bee able to iudge of the answere, if any shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. For whereas I haue proued, that the rule of faith is onely the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine written in the holy Scriptures; They happily may shew you out of the ancient writers, that there be some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things admitted in the Church, which are not written: So doeth Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bring ancient testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies for some things vnwritten. But these things wee confesse and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="10"/>
that some things vnwritten must bee admitted into the Church: but these are things in the discipline of the Church: And therefore wee holde things of discipline still vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written. But if you haue a care to saue your soules from these sleights, bid them prooue, that things vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten must bee receiued as doctrines of faith. For the controuersie betweene vs and them is not of vnwritten tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions in externall ceremonies, but of vnwritten Traditions in the rule of Faith. We say with <hi>Tertullian, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula<note place="margin">Lib. de vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. velan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis.</note> fidei vna omnino est, sola im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mobilis, &amp; irreformabilis: hac lege fidei manente, caetera iam discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae &amp; conuersationis admittunt nouitatem correctionis.</hi> That is, the rule of Faith is one altogether, onely vnchangeable, and vnreformable: this law of Faith remaining the same, other things pertaining to discipline and conuersation may be changed and corrected. Euer since this controuersie begun between vs and them of Rome,
<pb facs="11"/>
our writers haue confessed this that I say, and haue challenged their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries to produce some plaine testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that may clearely prooue, that an vnwritten doctrine may bee receiued into the rule of Faith: which thing to this day they haue not done; what they are like to doe heereafter, you may iudge by that which is done. Now suffer not your selues to bee blind-fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Take a courage vnto you, and a discerning spirit, to vnderstand the things that concerne you so neerely. And whereas I haue proued that the <hi>Pope</hi> was neuer admitted Iudge of Faith before the <hi>Trent Councill:</hi> it may be that some of these blinde sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers may tell you, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath beene a Iudge, and helde a Iudge in Christendome by some, long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: which in some sort is true, but not against me. For hee hath bene by diuers reputed a Iudge of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of right and wrong, in such things as come to bee pleaded by the Canon Law: But of matters of Faith he was
<pb facs="11"/>
neuer held to be a Iudge. Therefore the <hi>Popes</hi> Canons doe confesse, that<note place="margin">Dist. 2.</note> for exposition of Scriptures and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, the Expositors of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are to bee preferred before the <hi>Popes,</hi> as for their learning and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse farre excelling the <hi>Popes</hi> in the knowledge of the Scripture: but <hi>in causis definiendis,</hi> that is, in deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of causes, and ending of suits, which come to bee pleaded in the <hi>Popes</hi> Courts, the <hi>Popes</hi> are prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the height of their place. And this is all that their owne Cannons haue yeelded to them before the <hi>Trent Councill.</hi> I warne you of these things before hand, that your selues may bee the better able to iudge of any answer which may be returned against mee. And I thinke that this warning may suffice to instruct you against their idle answeres: so that I shall not need to trouble my selfe any further. I haue bene short in collecting these directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for these causes: First, because in this scribling age I would not trouble
<pb facs="12"/>
the Church with vnneedfull writings. Secondly, because I would inuite the moe Readers, who may bee content to reade a short Booke, whereas length doth often deter such as either haue not much leisure, or are coy of their pains. Lastly, because if any will answere it, they may see that I haue somewhat helped them in shortnesse. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may bee the better contented to set downe my words. Now where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as your seducers pretend that they loue the saluation of your soules, and glorie so much in the name of the Church, you must bee carefull to trie the spirit that speaketh in them: for it is as great a fault to beleeue eury thing without triall, as to beleeue nothing. It is Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> exhortation to you, <hi>Dearely</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4. 1</note>
      <hi>beloued, beleeue not euery spirit, but trie the spirits, whether they are of God, for many false prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> If S. <hi>Iohn</hi> had cause euen in the beginning of the Gospel to warne the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst seducers: what great cause
<pb facs="12"/>
haue we to warne you? For these false Prophets are now growen both in number and in cunning: But their multitude and cunning would vtterly faile them, if they did not presume vpon your ignorance. Wee labour to plant knowledge in all, and are desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that euery man might know the things needfull for his saluation: they labour to holde all in ignorance: their hope is not in the goodnesse of their cause: for they see the ruines of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon falling euery day: Only their care is to blinde you, and keepe you igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. They know well, that if you had knowledge to discerne their subtilties, it is not the pretence of the Church that could so much preuaile; whereas now the very bare name of the Church doeth trouble and entangle many of the simple, as a snare to catch the ignorant, a iust iudgment of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Wherein they deale with you, as the <hi>Arrians</hi> did deale with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of vnlearned Bishops and Priests in the Councill of <hi>Ariminum.</hi> For the
<pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>Arrians</hi> hauing procured the exile of the most worthie and best learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, perceiuing that the companie that was left, though they were not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry learned, yet would not be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded directly to disanull any thing that had beene concluded before in the Councill of <hi>Nice:</hi> did abuse their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in proposing the matter: For they demanded of them, whether they would worshippe <hi>Homoousion,</hi> or<note place="margin">Ruffin. lib. 10. histor. Eccles.</note> Christ? they not vnderstanding what the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> did signifie, reiected it with a kinde of execration, being as they thought opposed against Christ: Whereas if they had vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the matter aright, they would haue knowen that this word agreed most fitly with Christ, as best expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing his diuine nature. Euen thus your Priests and Iesuits deale with you: for when they haue told you somewhat of their Church, and that out of the Church there is no saluation, adding some trueths to some appearances, and framing your fancies after their owne
<pb facs="13"/>
deuised paterne. If then they aske you this question; Whether will you rather forsake the Church of God, or the allegeance to your Prince? Some ignorant men, (but moe women) that know not these subtilties, but thinke all to bee true that these men tell them in corners, must needs answere, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they would forsake Christ his Church, they will renounce the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of any earthly Prince. And thus is your zeale and ignorance abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by craftie companions. But if you might vnderstand, that you doe not forsake the Church, but are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed therein, by yeelding alleagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the King; then doubtlesse you would not bee vnwilling to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your owne errours, and the craft of your seducers. And here as I haue bene desirous to helpe you, so I hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreat you to helpe your selues, by louing and seeking the trueth. Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine not to take helpe of any. My la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour hath beene to bring endlesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to a short issue, for your satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction:
<pb facs="14"/>
onely I exhort you <hi>to trie the spirits, because many false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are gone out into the world:</hi> trust neither vs nor them, vntill you haue tried: for we are all contentious men, though some contend for the trueth and some against it. Trie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you trust; and remember that <hi>S. Chrysostome</hi> gaue this exhortation to his hearers, <hi>That they should be more carefull in trying the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctines which are deliuered to thē, then in telling of money, which is deliuered to them.</hi> Suffer no false and counterfeit stuffe to be thrust vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you at the motion of vaine men, who themselues know not the trueth, and haue no care to liue according to the trueth. And iudge your selues who are your best friends, and who are they that in reason may best be thought to hold the trueth: they who call you to the knowledge of Gods word; or they that would holde you in ignorance? they that desire you to examine their doctrines by the rule of Faith; or they
<pb facs="14"/>
that bid you take their doctrines vpon their bare word? they that make the Scriptures iudge of themselues, of their doctrines, of the <hi>Pope</hi> and all: or they that make the <hi>Pope</hi> Iudge of the Scriptures? they that call you to yeeld your allegeance to your Prince, or they that withdraw your hearts and allegeance from your soueraignes? they that were neuer found in rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, and conspiracies, or they that stirre vp rebellions against Kings? they that hold the same rule of faith, which the Church hath alwaies held before them; or they that haue chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the rule of Faith? Iudge whom you haue best reason to trust, and trie the spirits. All spirits are tried by the rule of Faith, &amp; the rule must be one to all. Iudge you whether they be not afraid to come to this triall, who haue changed the rule whereby they should be tried. Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced<note place="margin">Libr. de ver. Dei. cap. 2.</note> to say thus much, <hi>That the rule of Faith must be both certaine and well knowen: for if it bee not well</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>knowen, it is no rule to vs: if it bee not certaine, it is no rule at all.</hi> And he addeth thus much further: <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more certaine, nothing better knowen then the Scriptures contained in the Propheticall, and Apostolical writings.</hi> Take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of their Cardinall, and tell them that deceiue you, by suggesting ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rule, that there is but one rule: that whatsoeuer they bring besides this, it is both vncertaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to you▪ and therefore by their owne confession it cannot bee a rule to you.</p>
   <p>Consider therefore on both sides what is said. Against them wee say, They haue no Church: We prooue it, because they hold not Vnitie with the Catholike Church. I doe not wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, by producing sayings out of some of their writers, which they may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, that they are not warranted by their Church: but I deale with their Church it selfe, and their Trent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, and haue brought their long and
<pb facs="15"/>
tedious discourses to this short issue; Whether they haue not changed the rule of Faith in their <hi>Trent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill,</hi> which before that time was euer held the rule of Faith in the Church of God. This is the thing which I earnestly entreat you to search out. By this you may vnderstand where the trueth is, where the Church is. Then much haue wee against them: But what bring they against vs? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our Church they haue nothing to say: wee holde the rule of Faith, which the church of <hi>Rome</hi> euer held before the <hi>Trent Councill.</hi> We hold Ordination and Succession euen from the Apostles: albeit our succession be not from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor by that Church, yet we hold it sure, and that not without the testimony of that Church. In these things the learned make no doubt: onely there bee some ignorant men, and corrupted with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that haue deuised a strange tale to slander our Ordination: suggesting among the simple people, that we haue
<pb facs="16"/>
not a true Ministery: wherein, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorance, or malice haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, iudge you. I will relate the tale as they haue deuised it. Some of our owne seduced, and seducing countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue written, that <hi>Sandes, Scorie, Horne, Grindall, Iewel,</hi> and others in the beginning of the reigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> met at the Nagges head in Cheape side, where they looked for the Bishop of <hi>Landaffe,</hi> who should come to ordeine them there; But <hi>Bonner</hi> then being pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner in the Towre, vnderstanding this, sent his Chaplaine to the Bishop of <hi>Landaffe,</hi> denouncing and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him vpon paine of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to ordeine those that then and there expected him: The Bishop of <hi>Landaffe</hi> being terrified with that denunciation, refused to come and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine them; Whereupon they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that his Ordination was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, and so <hi>Scorie</hi> beeing but a Monke ordained the rest, and some of the other, being ordeined by <hi>Scorie,</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
laid handes vpon <hi>Scorie.</hi> This is the tale: a tale so odious would haue bene made somewhat probable. All that is brought to confirme it, is that <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Neall</hi> the Hebrewe Reader at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> should confesse this to his Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours, who tolde it to these men, and they tell it to you, and you beleeue it. By this you may perceiue how shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse they are that seduce you with such absurd tales: But all their hope is in your facilitie, and credulitie: for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to this tale, and all other of this kinde against our Ordination, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">•</seg> FRANCIS MASON</hi> hath dealt learnedly and faithfully, declaring the Consecration of all our Bishoppes that haue beene in the late Queenes time, and some yeeres before, out of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Records which are kept, that all men may see them that will. I will brieflly relate the summe of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, that the shame may returne vpon those shamelesse deuisers of such strange vntrueths. <hi>Iohn Scorie</hi> was consecrated Bishop of <hi>Hereford, anno</hi>
      <pb facs="17"/>
1551. in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust 30.</hi> by <hi>Thomas Canterburie, Nicholas Lond. Iohn Bedford,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Register of Archbishop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> fol. 334. The deuiser of this strange vntrueth, was but a sillie shifter, to set the Consecration of this man with them that were consecrated in the time of Queene <hi>ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH:</hi> hee hath made the lie impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and impossible. <hi>Edmund Grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall</hi> was consecrated Bishop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, anno 1559. Decemb. 21.</hi> by <hi>Matth. Canterburie, William Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester, Iohn Hereford, Iohn Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> out of the Register kept in Archbishop <hi>Parkers</hi> time, <hi>cap. 1. fol. 18. Edwine Sandes</hi> was consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>anno 1559. December 21.</hi> by <hi>Matth. Canter. William Cicester, Iohn Hereford, Iohn Bedford,</hi> out of the Register kept in Archbishop <hi>Parkers</hi> time, <hi>fol. 39.</hi> These were consecrated in the Chappell at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> the Sabboth day before noone, after morning prayer with imposition
<pb facs="17"/>
of handes, and with such forme of wordes and prayers as are vsed in the Church; where there was a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached by Master <hi>Nowell,</hi> then the Archbishop his Chaplaine, vpon this text: <hi>Take heed to your<note place="margin">Act. 20. 28.</note> selues, and to all the flocke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the holy Ghost hath made you ouerseers:</hi> And a Communion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently administred by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop. <hi>Iohn Iewel</hi> was consecrated Bishop of <hi>Salisbury, Anno 1559. Ianuary 21.</hi> by <hi>Matthew Canterb. Edmond London, Rich. Elie, Iohn Bedford,</hi> taken out of the Register in Archb. <hi>Parkers</hi> time, <hi>fol. 46.</hi> in the Chappell at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> vpon the Sabboth in the forenoone, with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers, and Communion, and a Sermon preached by <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Andrew Peirson</hi> the Archbish. his Chaplaine,<note place="margin">Matth. 5. 16.</note> vpon this Text: <hi>Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen. Robert Horne</hi> was consecrated,
<pb facs="18"/>
      <hi>anno 1560. February 16.</hi> by <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Canterbury, Thomas Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen. Edmond London, Thomas Couentrie</hi> and <hi>Lichfield: ex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistro Parker. chap. 1. fol. 88.</hi> in the Chappell at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> the Sabboth day the forenoone: the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner whereof in all respects was as the former.</p>
   <p>By this you may vnderstand what manner of men they are who seduce you: Is there any thing so shamelesse, which these men doe not venture vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on who dare venture to tell you such a tale, that by publike euidences may so easily so vnanswereably be conuinced? These are your guides and leaders: is it likely that these men should leade you into the way of trueth? Once free your selues from this pestiferous ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, who deuise still how to holde you in the bondage of their supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and consider what account they make of you, vpon whom they vent such stuffe; altogether presuming vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your simplicitie, hoping that you
<pb facs="18"/>
will take all without discussing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they deliuer. Men of common reason, will neuer put confidence in such men as are conuinced once for liars. If this bee true which they haue so confidently written, and by which they haue so notoriously abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed you, in slaundering of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of our worthie and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Bishops, then might you haue cause to be offended with our Church. But if this vpon triall bee found a manifest and absurd lye, then what cause haue you to trust them in any thing, whose whole studie is to abuse your simplicitie and credulitie; who hauing forsaken the trueth, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to drawe after them so many as they can into the societie of their Apostasie, respecting neither trueth nor conscience, so they deceiue by any meanes. And thus praying to him that keepeth the Keyes of Dauid, and openeth and no man shutteth, and shutteth, and no man openeth,
<pb facs="19"/>
that hee of his infinite mercie will open your eyes to see, your hearts to vnderstand his word and trueth, and therein your owne Saluation: I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the seruice of your Faith. GEORGE CARLETON:</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>