<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112455_Fr6_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112455</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The workes of Beniamin Ionson</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Meighen, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 1015, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb n="358" facs="193"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>AELius Seianus</hi>, sonne to <hi>Seius Strabo</hi>, a gentleman of <hi>Rome</hi>, and borne at <hi>Vulsinium</hi>, after his long seruice in court: first, vnder <hi>Augustus</hi>, afterward, <hi>Tiberius:</hi> grew into that fauour with the latter, and won him by those artes, as there wanted nothing, but the name, to make him a copartner of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. Which greatnesse of his, <hi>Drusus</hi>, the Emperors sonne not broo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, after many smother'd dislikes, it one day breaking out, the <hi>Prince</hi> strooke him publikely on the face. To reuenge which disgrace, <hi>Liuia</hi>, the wife of <hi>Drusus</hi> (being before corrupted by him to her dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, and the discouery of her husbands councells) <hi>Seianus</hi> practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth with, together with her Physitian, called <hi>Eudemus</hi>, and on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Lygdus</hi>, an Eunuch, to poyson <hi>Drusus.</hi> This their inhumane act hauing successefull, and vnsuspected passage, it emboldeneth <hi>Seianus</hi> to farther, &amp; more insolent proiects, euen the ambition of the Empire: where finding the lets, he must encounter, to be many, &amp; hard, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the issue of <hi>Germanicus</hi> (who were next in hope for the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession) he deuiseth to make <hi>Tiberius</hi> selfe, his meanes: &amp; instill's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his eares many doubts, and suspicions, both against the Princes, and their mother <hi>Agrippina</hi>: which <hi>Caesar</hi> iealously hearkning to, as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetously consenteth to their ruine, and their friends. In this time, the better to mature and strengthen his designe, he labours to marry <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia</hi>, and worketh (with all his ingine) to remoue <hi>Tiberius</hi> from the knowledge of publike businesse, with allurements of a quiet and retyred life: the latter of which, <hi>Tiberius</hi> (out of a pronenesse to lust, and a desire to hide those vnnaturall pleasures, which he could not so publikely practise) embraceth: the former inkindleth his feares, and there giues him first cause of doubt, or suspect toward <hi>Seianus.</hi> Against whom, he raiseth (in priuate) a new instrument, one <hi>Serto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Macro</hi>, and by him vnder-worketh, discouers the others coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells, his meanes, his ends, sounds the affections of the <hi>Senators</hi>, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides, distracts them: at last, when <hi>Seianus</hi> least looketh, and is most secure (with pretext of doing him an vn-wonted honour in the <hi>Senate</hi>) he traines him from his guardes, with one letter, and in one day, hath him suspected, accused, condemned, and torne in pieces, by the rage of the people,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>