<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRI∣OVS LADY, AND RIGHT Graceful Princesse, the eldest &amp; now only Daughter of our most gracious and Augustious Soueraigne, IAMES the CONCORDER, and of the most noble, excellent &amp; worthy Princesse, Queene ANNE his wife, Madame ELISABETH Infanta of Al∣bion, all happi∣nesse.</title>
           <author>Maxwell, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112547_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07317</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112547</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRI∣OVS LADY, AND RIGHT Graceful Princesse, the eldest &amp; now only Daughter of our most gracious and Augustious Soueraigne, IAMES the CONCORDER, and of the most noble, excellent &amp; worthy Princesse, Queene ANNE his wife, Madame ELISABETH Infanta of Al∣bion, all happi∣nesse.</title>
                 <author>Maxwell, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Queene Elizabeths looking-glasse of grace and glory : Wherein may be seen the fortune of the faithfull: that is to say, the wrastling, victory, and reward, or the combat, conquest and crowne of Gods children. All cleerely represented according to Scripture, &amp; illustrated by diuers notable examples of Gods seruants both men and vvomen: and likewise enterlaced with many memorable alligories &amp; morallties: both pleasant and profitable to be read. By I.M. Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Maxwell, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 215, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO</hi> THE MOST ILLVSTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS LADY, AND RIGHT Graceful Princesse, the eldest &amp; now only Daughter of our most gracious and Augustious Soueraigne, IAMES the CONCORDER, and of the most noble, excellent &amp; worthy Princesse, Queene ANNE his wife, Madame ELISABETH Infanta of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion, all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Make bolde to present vnto your grace a <hi>Looking-glasse,</hi> in the which (if it shall please your grace to make vse of it) ye shall see cleerly represented the <hi>fortune of the faithfull</hi> both heer &amp; hence; to wit, the <hi>Grace</hi> of Gods <hi>Seruants</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>on <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Glorie</hi> of his elect <hi>children</hi> in <hi>heauen.</hi> It will shewe your excellence how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a thing it is, for <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women</hi> to <hi>serue God</hi> by <hi>fighting</hi> against <hi>sinne, Sathan,</hi> the <hi>world</hi> and the <hi>flesh,</hi> and euen to be entred into his seruice in their <hi>tender yeeres.</hi> It likewise la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth open the greatnes of the <hi>rewarde</hi> that God hath layed vp for all his <hi>sincere</hi> and <hi>perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Seruants.</hi> For it pointeth out the right and streighte way that leadeth from the <hi>Garden</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> (wherin the flowers of all Christian vertues are to be found) vnto the <hi>Gallerie</hi> of <hi>Glorie:</hi> for into this there is none entrie, but by the other; euen as of olde, there was no passage into the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>honour</hi> but through the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>vertue,</hi> both builded by the most vertuous and honored Emperour <hi>Marcus Marcellus.</hi> In a word, it layeth open vnto the eye, such desirable things, as the very signification of your graces owne Christen name may serue to put you in minde of: for <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> signifieth asmuch as the <hi>fulnesse of God;</hi> And the <hi>fulnesse of God</hi> is none other thing ells, but <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glorie,</hi> wherof God is full aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, but <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women</hi> in a measure. To the same purpose may likewise serue the signification of the name of <hi>ANNA;</hi> which both importeth as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as <hi>grace</hi> or <hi>gratious</hi> and <hi>taking rest,</hi> and
<pb facs="6"/>is such a name, as I assure my selfe, your grace can neuer forget, as being the name of our most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Queene your graces owne deare <hi>mother</hi> by <hi>generation,</hi> &amp; likewise of a most vertuous Lady very neare and deare vnto your grace, I meane the Lady <hi>ANNE HARINGTON</hi> your graces most worthy <hi>Gouernesse,</hi> and euen your <hi>mother</hi> by <hi>Education.</hi> And because that this <hi>bookish loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glasse</hi> presenteth vnto the eye by reading, and vnto the eare by hearing, the most excellent obiects that either eye can see, or eare can heare or yet can enter into the heart of man, therefore, haue I made choise of two of the most excellent Princesses, that either eye hath seene, or eare hath heard tell of these many ages past; the one our most gratious <hi>Soueraignes</hi> most worthy <hi>mother,</hi> and euē your graces most noble Grandmother <hi>Queene MARIE</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the other the most renouned <hi>Godmother</hi> of both, <hi>Queene ELIZABETH</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> both of them once on <hi>Earth</hi> ful of <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> and now in <hi>heauen</hi> full of <hi>glorie:</hi> And as I haue in a manner Christened it by the name of the the one, euen of a <hi>much-lauded ELIZABETH,</hi> so haue I offered it as it were at the shrine of the other, I meane of a <hi>matchlesse MARIE.</hi> The which thing I haue done of set purpose to doe therby both their names some piece of honour, so much at
<pb facs="6"/>lest as lyeth within the small compasse of a meane Schollers ability to performe, as also therby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate and declare vnto all our Britaines, how much I doe dislike and detest the humorous and slanderous disposition of such passionate persones of whatsoeuer qualitie or condition, countrie or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as dare be so bold as by word or writte to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and diffame either of them. And vnto both of them I thought it my duty to performe this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian duty, but chiefly as being a Scottishman born (though likewise descended from the ancient En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish bloode) vnto my dreade Soueraignes most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mother, and your graces most gratious Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, as she who was not onely the Soueraigne Lady of our Scottish people, but also the most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy mistris of mine owne Good sire, who had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to serue her highnes in France from her lower yeers. Vnto the memory of whose most noble name, I haue not onely vowed this small part of mine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Essayes, but also a parte of my Latine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours written for the furthering of peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde amongs diuided Christianes: towards the which how great a good will I doe beare, may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by the 7. chapter of this Booke. To passe ouer a defence of her fame which some yeeres agoe being in France I began to be about against the wicked inuectiues of certaine leud libellers and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:
<pb facs="7"/>wishing with all mine heart that I may see with mine eyes, or rather help with mine hands one day to make a publike bonefire of all such fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand bookes, leaud libels &amp; spitefull pamphlets, as haue beene at any time hertofore published in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, latine or any other language, in poesie or in prose to the vnreasonable and treasonable reuiling &amp; reproching, blaming and diffaming, of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide most worthy Princesse the blessed mother of Britaines peace, whose noble name in the despite of all such detractors, shall be euer had of all honest hearted persones in a respectfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. That which resteth. <hi>most gracefull Lady,</hi> this <hi>bookish Looking-glasse,</hi> wherin ye shall see nothing but sound diuinity, and religious directions and enducements to primitiue deuotion and pietie, doth offer it selfe vnto your graces viewe, and beggeth your gratious acceptance both for the twofold most excellent matters sake therein hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, euen <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glorie,</hi> &amp; for the two most excellent Princesses sake, whose <hi>gracious</hi> &amp; <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> names in the forefront it doth beare. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde it therefore with your fauour able visage, &amp; garde it with your princely patronage, so shall it be secured vnder your highnes shadowe, and I encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to attempt yet more for the honour of your most gracefull Grandmothers name, and likewise
<pb facs="7"/>of your graces owne. And so wishing vnto your grace, the <hi>best things</hi> which can be had on <hi>earth,</hi> euen <hi>Grace</hi> with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> and after a long and happie life, the <hi>best things</hi> which can be had in <hi>heauen,</hi> euen <hi>Glorie</hi> with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your graces submisse seruant right deuoted to all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble duties, IAMES MAXWELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>