<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface, To the curteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Carr, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112763_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07605</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17997</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface, To the curteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Carr, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Mahumetane or Turkish historie : containing three bookes: 1 Of the originall and beginning of the Turkes, and of the foure empires which are issued and proceded out of the superstitious sect of Mahumet. 2 Of their conquests and the succession of the house of Ottoman, vntill the present reigning of Mahumet the third. 3 Of the warres and seege of Malta, which Solyman the great made to the great maister and brothers of that order. Heerevnto haue I annexed a briefe discourse of the warres of Cypres, at what time Selimus the second, tooke from the Venetians the possession of that iland, and by reason thereof I haue adioyned a small discourse conteining the causes of the greatnesse of the Turkish Empire. Translated from the French &amp; Italian tongues, by R. Carr, of the middle Temple in London, Gentleman. Dedicated to the three worthy brothers Robert Carr, William Carr and Edward Carr, in the county of Lincolne, Esquiers</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 122 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Preface,</hi> To the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no small wonder vnto me gentle <hi>Reader,</hi> though the worth of the argument contayned in these bookes were lesse, why the examples of other nations (as in other things) should not so much preuayle w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our countrey men, as to stirre vp some, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the presidents in many other languages (wherewith the world in large volumes is fraught,) to haue written somewhat of these <hi>Turkish</hi> affayres; For if wee regard the greatnesse of their attempts, their fortunatenesse in successe, their discipline, or what else may adde aught to militarie glorie: you shall finde them in my conceite not inferior but supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior farre in euery thing which hath giuen estimatiō to former ages, of which bookes we see euery hand and studie full, whilst these alone are hid from our people for want of some paine taking pen that might transfer so rich treasure from straungers vnto vs. If new things delight, (according to the naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted condicion of man,) these are new; If benefit be expected in bookes, (&amp; especially in histories,) for counsayle &amp; forewarning mischiefs in the examples and harmes of others, frō what former historie may we reap greater then this: stored with so many and notable presidents of all sorts, fresh bleeding as it
<pb facs="7"/>
were before our eyes, (and which should be a greater motiue) telling of ensewing danger, not much deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded frō our owne doores, when daylie we lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly see our neighbours houses not farre of flaming. New fashioned clothes deriued from straungers, are euery day much esteemed, new fashioned man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, new fashioned wittes are affected: then either for the worth or fashion, let these <hi>French</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> traductions receiue your fauorable censures: I dyd propound no greater gaine in my paines, and hope of your curtesies to obtaine no lesse, which graunted shall encourage me to shew you yet some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more worthie ere long in this argument, wherein I hauing first (for aught I know) broken the ice (sauing onely the Historie of <hi>Scanderbegg</hi> of the late <hi>Persian</hi> warres, &amp; that of <hi>Tamberlain</hi> though exceding well done yet but perticuler parts of this discourse) shall be glad to heare of any companion▪ for further paines, to whom this subiect will afford enough of sufficient and worthie matter; And so cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing you would friendly correct what faults in the Impression haue passed either by me or the Printer, I take my leaue, and rest the seruant of euery well willing reader.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. Carr.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>