<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Molina, Anthony de</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112795_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07608</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18000</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112795</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Molina, Anthony de</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of mental prayer· : In vvhich is briefly declared the manner how to exercise the inward actes of vertues by Fr. Ant. de Molina Carthusian. Whereunto is adioyned a very profitable treatise of exhortation to spirituall profit. VVritten by F. Francis Arias of the Society of Iesus. Togeather with a dialogue of contrition and attrition. All translated out of Spanish into English by a Father of the Society of Iesus</title>
                 <author>Molina, Antonio de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 365, 7 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY years be now past, that some Religious of this holy house, especially Lay-brothers whose exteriour occupations affoard them lesse tyme to bestow in reading bookes) requested m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to write for them some cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Treatise; to guide them in their spirituall deuotions. Charity and desire to serue, and help my Brethren, bound me
<pb facs="6"/>(though I knew well my owne insuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and experience in spiritual affaires) to do my best to satisfy their importunity. Being therfore to begin, I thought it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse to treate of Prayer, or of the Partes, Preparations, Conditions, and Directions that concerne the same, so many Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tises, some at large some more briefe, &amp; both very sufficient hauing beene written of this Argument. Notwithstanding I haue thought good to declare one point which I had a longe time wished I might see handled cleerly and distinctly: and the same, I knew to be the desire also of many persons that are deuoutly giuen to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall prayer; to wit, VVhat meditation is, how the Powers of the Soule are to be vsed, and the acts of the Vnderstanding, and the will directed to consider thinges with fruite, and to exercise affections &amp; internall acts of Vertue. The which is a most excellent kind of Prayer, and of very great profit, principally for beginners,
<pb facs="6"/>setting aside supernatural kind of Prayer wherof we are not to speake at this time.</p>
   <p>This point I intend to handle, and shall endeauour to do it with as much perspicuity, distinction, and breuity as I may, making v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of what I haue read of this matter, in Saints works, and Authors of auncient and moderne tymes, and of what our Lord hath specially giuen me to feel my selfe; yet with such plainnesse of stile, as the quality of the persons, for whome it was written, requireth. For I neuer imagined that the Treatise it selfe should get out of the gates of our Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery.</p>
   <p>As it was written with my owne hand, I imparted it to my Brethren: and seing them much comforted and content therwith, I cōmunicated the same to other deuout and spirituall persons. By this meanes the Treatise was deliuered from hand to hand, many co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies therof being spread abroad; and (as it commonly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="7"/>out) with the multitude of copies many errors and corruptions increased. For which reason; as also for that very many spirituall and intelligent persons iudged it might be profitable, because it declareth briefly and clearly the aforesaid argument, so necessary and important; I permitted the same to be printed, that such as would might make benefit therof, without the labour of copying it out.</p>
   <p>Neither haue I added or changed any thing, but let it passe as it was first di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulged in writing with so great content and profit of the Readers: nor do I pretend any other thing, but only to assist those who vse the exercise of Prayer; to the end that some part of their deuotions may be deriued to my selfe, and the whole directed to the greater honour and glory of God Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Fr. Ant. de Molina.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>