<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the freendlie and courteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112712_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23344</idno>
           <idno type="STC">978</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the freendlie and courteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dyall for dainty darlings, rockt in the cradle of securitie : A glasse for all disobedient sonnes to looke in. A myrrour for vertuous maydes. A booke right excellent, garnished with many woorthy examples, and learned aucthorities, most needefull for this tyme present. Compiled by VV. Auerell, Student in Diuinitie, and Schoolemaister in London</title>
                 <author>Averell, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the freendlie and courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle and freendlie</hi> Reader, if thou thinke him to be thy freend that besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vpon thee frankly, and with a lyberall heart, some costly iewell to delight thine eye, or some golden gyft to pleasure thy minde: then thinke me no lesse, that giue thee not a materyall thing alone to feede thy fancy, but a costly comfort for thy hearts delyght, which albeit it seeme small in shew, and beare a slender bulke, yet mayst thou, of what condition soeuet thou be of (if with iudgement thou reade it) picke out such wholsome lessons, as may pleasure thy minde, and profite thy life. Heere shalt thou learne in prosperitie, to beware of pride, and to auoyde security: if thou be a Father, how to bring vp thy chyldren with discretion: if a Sonne, how to reuerence thy Father with wisdome: if thou be single, how to choose thy wife, so that thy lyfe may be happy, and thy tyme spent in quietnesse: if married, how to gouerne thy selfe and thy mate in all seemelynes and vertue: heere may wiues learne wisedome, and maydens gather modesty. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the commodities are many, the examples plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt,
<pb facs="4"/>
and the practise thereof profitable, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to the ende that thou mightest be pertaker of that which may be thy future profite, I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyled this small Booke, not wearying thee with long discourses, least thy minde should (being quea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie) wexe lothsome, and so disdaine it before thou reade it: but in short and breefe Treatise, I haue pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together that which if thou can rightly vse it, shall be as gaine some as pleasaunt, wherfore, if thou bring with thee a thankfull heart, and a vertuous minde, thou wylt thankefully take that which I haue freendly written: but if thou haue an enuious eye, thou wylt soone carpe at that by enuie, which the Printer by ouersyght, and I by infirmity haue committed.</p>
   <p>Learned <hi>Homer</hi> sometime sleepeth, and the fastest foote somety me slyppeth, the wisest tongue maye catch a tryp, and the wariest penne committe a fault, errour is as naturall, as the correction thereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</p>
   <p>VVherefore that which remayneth is, I commit my selfe and my labour to thy good lyking, if thou lyke it, commend it and vse it, if thou dislyke it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, or refuse it, do not <hi>Nodum in scirpo querere,</hi> seeke a knotte in a ryshe: For many will finde fault, that cannot amend a worke, and some disday ne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers labours, that are themselues loytering ydle ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, that eyther cannot doo any thing woorthy commendation, or if they be able, consume theyr tyme in scoffing, or else in ydle liuing. But knowing
<pb facs="5"/>
I shall not be so fortunate as to escape some such al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, seeing that vnder euerie Stone lyeth a <hi>Scorpion,</hi> I commend me to the vertuous, despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the enuious, and so gentle Reader, wishing thy well fare, I ende, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thee to him, whome I beseech graunt thee to reade with profit.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>