<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Maister, Wardens, Assi∣stants, and whole Liuery, of the Honorable Company of Merchant-Tailors, being the worthy So∣ciety of S. Iohn Baptist, anciently deriued from S. Iohn of Hierusalem, and the famous Knightes of that religious Brother-hood. Also to the Wardens Substitutes, and the sixteene men of the same Compa∣ny, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112963_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07894</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18263</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112963</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Maister, Wardens, Assi∣stants, and whole Liuery, of the Honorable Company of Merchant-Tailors, being the worthy So∣ciety of S. Iohn Baptist, anciently deriued from S. Iohn of Hierusalem, and the famous Knightes of that religious Brother-hood. Also to the Wardens Substitutes, and the sixteene men of the same Compa∣ny, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe chronicle, of the successe of times, from the creation of the world, to this instant· : Containing, the originall &amp; liues of our ancient fore-fathers, before and after the Floude, as also, of all the monarchs, emperours, kinges, popes, kingdomes, common-weales, estates and gouernments, in most nations of this worlde: and how in alteration, or succession, they haue continued to this day</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 189, 192-613, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_guild">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Maister, Wardens, Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and whole Liuery, of the Honorable Company of Merchant-Tailors, being the worthy So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> anciently deriued from S. <hi>Iohn</hi> of Hierusalem, and the famous Knightes of that religious Brother-hood. Also to the Wardens Substitutes, and the sixteene men of the same Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene my hap (worthy and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful Gentlemen) among the variety of Collections, to build vp the body of this briefe Chronicle; to meete with an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and much esteemed Record, of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and brother-hood, styled by the name of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> of <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> and how many Great Maisters haue gouerned that Society, from Anno. 1099. to this present yeare, with some briefe obseruations of their liues and actions, as in Follio 187. more at large appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Concerning the originall, progression, &amp; seuerall Fortunes of this Military Brother-hood, beeing tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Knights <hi>Hospitallers,</hi> or Knights of the Hospitall of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist of Ierusalem</hi>; next, Knights of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and lastly, Knightes of <hi>Malta</hi>; I refer you there to be further satisfied: yet some thinges beeing there acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally omitted, may fauourably (and not vnnecessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily) here be remembred. These Brethren (by solemne profession) were bound to serue Pilgrims, and poore
<pb facs="5"/>
people in the Hospitall of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> at Ierusalem, and to secure (by their man-hood) their passages thither, they charitably buried the dead, were continually in praier, mortifyed themselues with Watchings and Fastinges, were courteous and kinde to the poore, whom they called their Maisters, and fed them with white Bread, when themselues did eate browne. They grew to be loued and liked of all sortes, and, through the liberal bounty of good Princes and priuate persons (admiring their piety and prowesse) they rose from this low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to so high an estate and great riches, that about An. 1240. they had within Christendome nineteene thousand Lordships or Mannors, as the Knights <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plers</hi> had nine thousand, the Reuennewes and Rentes wherof in England, fell afterward also to these knights <hi>Hospitallers</hi> of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist.</hi> And this estate of theirs (growne to so great an height) made way for them likewise to as great honors. So that their Prior in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (liuing then in the goodly Pallace of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> of <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> in the streete which receiued name of that house, and is called yet to this day, Saint <hi>Iohns-street</hi>) was reputed the Prime Baron of the land, and called the Lord of S. <hi>Iohns,</hi> beeing able, with ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and abundance of all things, to maintaine a very honorable Port.</p>
   <p>In successe of time, as this worthy Citty grew to encrease, not onely in large extendure and beautie of buildings, but also in election of Companies and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, for better supply of the Magistracy, and conueniency of all the aptest meanes thereto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; this Branch of your honorable Society of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> (deriued of that ancient and memorable Stem,
<pb facs="5"/>
of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Hierusalem</hi>) grewe to burgen and spread it selfe in goodliest manner. Beeing <hi>Tailors</hi> of the Linnen-Armory, and brethren of Saint <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist</hi> (as most Companies, in those times, had a Saintes appellation) they grew to be great in Kinges fauours, who thought it no indignity to themselues, to be stiled in the Brother-hood of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> and from theyr Guildes first Creation by King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, with authority to hold a feast yearely at Midsommer, and to make choyce of a Gouernor or Mayster (according to the order of a Great Maister, among the Knights <hi>Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallers,</hi> of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist of Hierusalem</hi>) and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, to assist and ayde him in that weighty charge: they proceeded on still (by the ensuing Kings) in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther additions of gracious regard, till King <hi>Henrie</hi> the seauenth confirmed their Charter, naming them <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors,</hi> of the Brother-hood of Saint <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist,</hi> to continue still the memorie of their Originall. Heere may I not also forget, that as the Knightes <hi>Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallers</hi> at <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> were alwaies respectiue in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to Pilgrims and Trauailers: euen so, as if such an humble condition did well merit not to be forgotten, in this Brotherhood (at the beginning) they did vse ech yeare to chuse a Pilgrime, who attended the seruice of the Maister of the Company, and trauailed in behalfe of the whole Society. One of the Pilgrimes names is recorded by <hi>Iohn Stow,</hi> to be <hi>Henrie de Ryall,</hi> and that name of Pilgrime continued vntill the eleauenth year of <hi>Richard</hi> the second, when the foure Wardens, were then called Purueyors of Almes, now called quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the fraternity.</p>
   <p>Seauen Kings haue borne Bretherens name of that
<pb facs="6"/>
Society (viz:) <hi>Edward</hi> the third; <hi>Richard</hi> the second; <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth; <hi>Henrie</hi> the fift; <hi>Henrie</hi> the sixt; <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth; and <hi>Henrie</hi> the seauenth, and (as is credibly affirmed) wearing the Liueryhood on their shoulders, they haue gone on the election day, from the Hall, to the Pallace of Saint <hi>Iohns,</hi> in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Streete, there to heare diuine seruice, and graciously permitted the Maister to goe on the vpper-hand, such (in those times) was the milde nature of Princes, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (by their owne example) how Magistrates, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their meaner Ministers, ought to be held in honor and respect.</p>
   <p>Passing ouer the Dukes, Earles, Lords, Byshoppes, Knightes, and Gentlemen, who haue likewise beene Bretheren of that honorable Society, and many other memorable persons, of whom this little limit allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no speech: I wil conclude this Epistle, with a briefe note of two or three worthy Bretheren, among infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite other, whose deserts doe iustly challenge perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall acknowledgement.</p>
   <p>Sir <hi>William Fitz William</hi> the elder, being a Merchant Taylor, and Seruaunt sometime to Cardinall <hi>Wolsey,</hi> was chosen Alderman of Bread-street-Ward in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, in Anno. 1506. And going afterward to dwell at <hi>Mylton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire</hi>; in the fal of the Cardinall his former Maister, he gaue him kinde entertainement there at his house in the Countrey. For which deede, being called before the King, and demaunded how he durst entertaine so great an enemy to the State: his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere was, that he had not contemptuously or wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done it, but onely because he had been his Maister, and partly the meanes of his greatest Fortunes. The
<pb facs="6"/>
King was so well pleased with his answer, that, saying, himselfe had too few such Seruaunts; immediatly hee knighted him, and afterward made him a priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler. This worthy Knight dying, gaue an hundered pounds to poore Maids marriages. His debs and deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ouer whose names he had written <hi>Amore Dei re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto,</hi> he freely forgaue. He gaue to the Vniuersities forty pound; to the poore thirty pound; to mend the high-waies betwixt <hi>Chigwell</hi> and <hi>Copersale</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> 50. pounds; to mend other high-waies about <hi>Thorney</hi> and <hi>Sawtrie</hi> Chappell, and the Bridge, fifty pounds more. And to the <hi>Merchant-Taylors</hi> his Bretheren, hee gaue his best standing Cuppe, as a friendly remembrance of him.</p>
   <p>Sir <hi>Thomas White,</hi> Lord Maior of this honourable Citty, and a worthy Brother likewise of that Society, beeing a louer of Learning, and an earnest furtherer thereof; first purchased the Hall in <hi>Oxenford,</hi> called <hi>Glocester-Hall,</hi> for Students and Schollers to receiue there the benefit of learning. But his priuate thoughts very often solliciting him, that he should (in time) meet with a place where two Elmes grewe, and that there his further forward purpose should take effect: At length he found out the place, where (at his owne cost and expences) hee founded the famous Colledge in <hi>Oxenford,</hi> called Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> Colledge, &amp; where those two Elmes (as I haue heard) are yet standing, endowing it with such liberall Guifts, Lands, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennewes, as would require too much time here to be remembred. Beside his prouision for Learning in this worthy place, he erected other Schooles, as at <hi>Bristow, Reading,</hi> and a Colledge at <hi>Higham Ferries.</hi> More, he
<pb facs="7"/>
gaue to the Citty of <hi>Bristow,</hi> the summe of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand poundes, to purchase Land, amounting to the yearely valew of an hundred and twenty pounds, the Maior and Cittizens paying therefore yearely an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds. Eight hundred pounds must bee lent to sixteene poore Clothiers, fifty poundes each man for ten years space, sufficient security being giuen by them for the same. Afterward, that eight hundred poundes was to passe to other sixteene Clothiers, according to discretion of them put in trust. Two hundred poundes beside was reserued, for prouision of Corne and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full occasions for the poore, in the order and care of the Maior, Aldermen, and Cittizens, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Then, according to his will, which remaineth yet to be seene, out of this bountifull guift to <hi>Bristow,</hi> these memorable braunches and beneuolences, were by himselfe deuised and ordered, beginning in the yeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>577. and thence forward they went on according to his owne direction. Then was brought to the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors</hi> Hall, an hundred and foure pounds, the hundred pound to be lent (for ten years space) to four poore men in the Citty of <hi>Yorke:</hi> And the foure pound ouer plus, to be imploied about the charges &amp; paines, that no man (vsed in the businesse) might receiue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment. Then in An. 1578. the like summe was to be deliuered thence to <hi>Canterburie,</hi> and so thence-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the same summes (yearely) to the Citties and Townes following orderly.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1579. Reading.</item>
      <item>1580. The Merchant-Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs themselues.</item>
      <item>1581. Glocester.</item>
      <item>1582. Worcester.</item>
      <item>1583. Excester.</item>
      <item>1584. Salisbury.</item>
      <item>1585. West-Chester.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="7"/>1586. Norwich.</item>
      <item>1587. Sothampton.</item>
      <item>1588. Lincolne.</item>
      <item>1589. Winchester.</item>
      <item>1590. Oxenford.</item>
      <item>1591. Hereford East.</item>
      <item>1592. Cambridge.</item>
      <item>1493. Shrewesbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie.</item>
      <item>1594. Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ne.</item>
      <item>1595. Bathe.</item>
      <item>1596. Derby.</item>
      <item>1597. Ipswitch.</item>
      <item>1598. Colchester.</item>
      <item>1599. New-Castle.</item>
   </list>
   <p>This summe of one hundred and foure pounds, pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing yearely to these fore-named places, from the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors Hall, and to the good intended vses of the giuer; that there might bee no breathing while for so iust a Stewards Talent, but to haue it kept on in continuall imployment for the poore: the same order was to take beginning againe (as before) at the Cittie of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and so successiuely (while the World stands) to the Townes before named, in selfe-same course as it had the originall, with great care and obseruaunce in them to whom it belongeth, that the dead may not be abused, nor poore mens right iniured.</p>
   <p>But did he thus shut vp his Pursse, and say to himselfe. I haue giuen sufficient? No, hee did cast his pittying eie next on the Citty of <hi>Couentry,</hi> distressed (at that time) in great and grieuous manner. What his instant beneuolence was, he tooke it to bee but as an houres Sun-shine, after a whole day of storme and tempest, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it might yeeld some comfort, were the season neuer so short. But to establish a certainty, that no dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may or doubt should euer after bee able to remooue, (euen as a worthy Piramide, erected to perpetuity) he gaue to the Citty of <hi>Couentry</hi> 1400. pound, therewith to purchase Lands, rising to the anuall value of 70. li.
<pb facs="8"/>
Twelue poore Inhabitants of that Citty, were to haue in free Almes twenty foure poundes, each man forty shillings yearely, on the eleauenth day of March. Four young men were also to haue fortie poundes yearely, ten pound each man, and for nine yeares space, vpon sufficient security giuen; And their turnes thus serued, then foure other young men to haue the like summe, and like limitation, and so from nine yeares, to nine yeares, for euer. Afterward it was ordred to two poore men of the same Citty, and lastly to one; in which nature (according to the seuerall limitations) it doth yet, and doubtlesse shall for euer continue. Also the same summe to one young man in <hi>Northampton</hi>; next, in the Citty of <hi>Leicester</hi>; Thirdlie, in <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>; Fourthly, in <hi>Warwick</hi>; Then returning to <hi>Couen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie</hi> again for one year, it repasseth to the said Townes againe, each after other yearely for euer. And least his worthy intent should faile in the continuance, hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged his first gift to <hi>Couentrie,</hi> of 1400. poundes, to 2000. and 60. pound, to bee imployed as hath beene remembred, fortie pound yearely being paid out of it to Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford:</hi> And allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances also by himselfe giuen in each place, that bonds should be made without any charge to the receiuer.</p>
   <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Row,</hi> Lord Maior of this famous Citty, and a worthy <hi>Merchant-Taylor,</hi> beside his charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cost and charges, in building the new Church-yard in <hi>Bedlem,</hi> for such Parishes as wanted benefit of buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: Gaue forty poundes yearely, to maintaine tenne poore men for euer, such as were not Bretheren of his owne Society, but chosen out of fiue seuerall Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies (viz.) <hi>Clothworkers, Armorers, Carpenters, Tylers,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
and <hi>Plaisterers:</hi> As considering, that by ouer-toyling labour, dangers, fals, bruizes, and such like inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, they were soonest like to become impotent, and vnable to helpe or maintaine themselues. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to each of these ten men, hee freely gaue the sum of foure pound quarterly, to be paid them at the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors Hall, during their liues; and then to succeede to other men in the same Companies, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to due consideration, of iust cause and most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity.</p>
   <p>Lastly, worthy Gentlemen, to hold yee no longer, in matter better knowne to your selues then mee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is in your owne eyes and eares (almost) dailie, the neuer dying memory, of a yet liuing (and long may he so be) Brother Merchant-Taylor, shall be my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion. This vertuous and Religious man, knowing Death to be an vnindifferent Executor, and Life much more worthy of trust and imployment; hath preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that gripple greedy Tyrant, and made such large Legacies to Life, that Death neuer deserued to be put in trust withall. If men of this World, such as GOD hath liberally bestowed his blessings on, would (with this good-minded man) consider, that, let their willes bee neuer so wisely made, yea, all Art and Dexterity therein (to the very vttermost) imployed: yet death, and his long wide gaping Children, haue many hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers on, many meanes &amp; deuises, but many more tricks and vnfaithfull performances; they would trust life the better, as this man hath done, and let death haue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reuersion, which is the easier to bee considered on. It is not for my pen to set downe his praises, leaues of Marble or Brasse are meeter for those Carracters,
<pb facs="9"/>
that the deuouring teeth of Time may neuer deface. Let this th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome addition to your honour, that you haue su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orthy Brother; mindful of the works of Mercy to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oore, among your selues, and many places else-where▪ carefull of offendours, whom law sentencing with Death, by the Watch-bell of Prayer are encited to compunction; and hopefull of al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to pursue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vertuous determinations euerie where. So that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is <hi>Dooue</hi> shall finde no resting place for his foote▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> reason of this Worldes tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous waues; hee may returne to the Arke of blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the happy home, that he, you, and all else that feare God, should daily long for.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer, <hi>A. MVNDY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>