<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Martin Iunior sonne vnto the re∣nowmed and worthy Martin Marprelate the Great, to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112312_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07040</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17457</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112312</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Martin Iunior sonne vnto the re∣nowmed and worthy Martin Marprelate the Great, to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Theses Martinianae : that is, certaine demonstratiue conclusions, sette downe and collected (as it should seeme) by that famous and renowmed clarke, the reuerend Martin Marprelate the great: seruing as a manifest and sufficient confutation of al that euer the Colledge of Catercaps with their whole band of clergie-priests, haue, or canbring [sic] for the defence of their ambitious and antichristian prelacie. Published and set foorth as an after-birth of the noble gentleman himselfe, by a prety stripling of his, Martin Iunior, and dedicated by him to his good neame and nuncka, Maister Iohn Kankerbury: hovv the yongman [sic] came by them, the reader shall vnderstande sufficiently in the epilogue. In the meane time, vvhosoeuer can bring mee acquainted vvith my father, Ile bee bounde hee shall not loose his labour</title>
                 <author>Marprelate, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Hodgkins (Hoskins), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marprelate, Martin, junior, Assignees of, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Martin Iunior sonne vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed and worthy <hi>Martin Marprelate</hi> the Great, to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THou shalt receiue (good Reader) before I set downe vnto thee anie thing of mine owne, certeyne of those thinges of my fathers dooings which I found among his vnperfect papers: I haue not changed any thing in them, detracted any thing from them, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto them aught of mine owne, but as I found them, so I haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them vnto thee. Mine owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thou shalt vnderstand at the latter ende in my Epilogue, to my nunckle Canturburie. This small thing that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth before his Theses, is also his owne. I haue set downe the speach as I founde it, though vnperfect. One thing I am sory for, that the speach pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth the old man to be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing discouraged in his courses.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>