<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian godly di∣sposed Reader, grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112697_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07288</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17683</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112697</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian godly di∣sposed Reader, grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Saint Peters chaine : consisting of eight golden linckes, most fit to adorne the neckes of the greatest states, nobles, and ladies in this land, as the chiefest iewell of true nobilitie: and not vnfit for the meaner sort. Digested into eight chapters, and published by R.M. minister. With a praier annexed to the end of euerie chapter</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 182 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian godly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposed Reader, grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (curteous Reader) how dangerous a thing it is accounted, to write &amp; publish books nowe in these plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dayes of learning and knowledge: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, how many great schollers and learned men of our land, are retained from doing that publike good (as I take it) to Church and commonweale, according to theyr seuerall abilities, because many men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that bookes want readers, more than readers want bookes: and because they feare the censure (oftentimes) of thē that are enemies both to God &amp; al godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: (for who, I praie you, are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon carpers of our time? Are they not
<pb facs="3"/>
for the most part either Papists or Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists?) yet am I of another, and I hope, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion, that these forenamed reasons or anie other of that kinde, that may bee named, ought not to affray or discourage anie from occupying of their talents in the feare of God, as well in writing, as in preaching, so that thereby the one be not hindered by the other.</p>
   <p>What though there be many bookes? yet al bookes are not godly bookes. True it is, that many haue iustly complained of the multitude of vain &amp; wanton bookes, but neuer did I reade or heare anie godly man complaine, that there are too manye bookes tending to vertue, and godlines<hi>:</hi> nay, let mee saie more, what though there be a multitude of good &amp; learned books? yet we know, the most part of people are not learned, and as necessarie it is, if it bee not more necessarie, that the ignoranter sort haue moebookes, composed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their capacities, as it is for the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to haue many learned books imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the increase of their knowledge. What though there be a great many that
<pb facs="3"/>
will carpe and finde faulte with our well dooing? Is it not sufficient that we haue God and a good conscience witnessing with vs, and comforting vs in our labors?</p>
   <p>Lastly, if euerie circumstance be duly weighed, some conuenient time spent in writing need not be a hindrance (as some pretend) but rather a furtheraunce vnto preaching: for can any write without stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying? and wil not that studying help thē in preaching? Hath onely S. Austen said, <hi>Proficiendo scribo, &amp; scribendo proficio?</hi> In profiting I write, and by writing I profit? Haue not as famous men as Europ hath bred these many yeres said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> like, that haue written much, &amp; yet preached almost eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day? Writing, we see, vnto thē was no let or hinderance vnto preaching<hi>:</hi> whose example therin might make many lerned men of our daies to cōsiderwhat their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings do require. Thus if we will duly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this matter, we shal see how these v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall obiections to hinder men from doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the most good they can in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, are but as thicke mistes, which the Sunne beames of trueth will easily scatter and disperse, or like vnto bugs, to afright
<pb facs="4"/>
little children withall, that are afraid with the shaddowe of anie thing. And now, (christian Reader) for mine owne parte, as I haue no cause to vse many wordes of perswasion vnto thee, for the acceptance of these my poore labours, seeing I haue (not long since) found more fauour that waie, than I my selfe did expect, or durst to desire, so I will not vse many speeches more in this preface, to hinder thee from reading the booke it selfe, wherin, if thou take the least comfort or profite, I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my selfe well recompensed for my paines.</p>
   <p>The whole booke it selfe is but little, and yet I haue digested it into seuerall Chapters, that thou maiest reade the same with the more delight. The title of this booke is somewhat glorious, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment surely godly, onely the handling of it is plaine and simple. The substance whereof this Chaine was made, is a met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall finer than the golde of Ophir, the workeman that by the spirite of God first riuited the links of this Chaine together, was such a one, to vse the wordes of Saint
<pb facs="4"/>
Paule, as did studie to shewe himselfe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of God, a workeman that need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to be ashamed. It was Saint Peters <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.15,</note> work, therefore called S. Peters Chaine. The title, you may see, is not forced: the matter I haue indeuoured to handle, according to this our Apostles owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod: amplifying and inlarging the same, agreeable with the tenor of the scripture. The onely marke that I leuell at is this, first, that as sathan by his subtiltie labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to linke many sinnes together in one soule, and to draw many soules with him in his chaine vnto hell, so the godly may be as carefull to linke many vertues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one, and so euen to tie themselues to vertue and godlynesse, as with a most strong Chaine, which all the deuils in hel may not be able to break. Againe, seeing we liue in these last &amp; loose daies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">Mat. 24.12</note> sinne doth abound, and iniquitie hath gotten the vpperhande, seeing the whole world, as Saint Iohn saith, is set on wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes, &amp; people drawe sinnes vnto them <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 9.19,</note> as it were with cart-ropes, insomuch that it seemeth the whole foundation of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb facs="5"/>
and godlines is shaken, that so in like manner y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godly may haue so many props as are possible, to staie them frō falling, &amp; being knit and lincked together with this holy Chaine, they may by little and little hale and tow forwarde, one helping and supporting another towardes the hauen of rest, where the tempestuous seas of sin and iniquitie leaue raging. Salomon, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <note place="margin">Eccle. 4.12.</note> speaketh of a threefolde corde, that is not easily broken: but heere is no cord, but a strong cable, not of three, but of eight twists, to draw thee forward vnto heauen. This cable must not bee diuided into partes, for then one twist will breake after another, thou must holde by all or none. Therfore is it rightly called a <hi>Chain,</hi> because one lincke must hold fast the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Faith must hold Vertue, Vertue must keep Knowledge, Knowledge must pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue Temperance, Temperance must staie Patience, Patience must retain God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, Godlines must vpholde Brotherly kindnes, Brotherly kindnesse must draw on loue or Charitie with it, &amp; Loue must haue recourse backe againe vnto Faith, &amp;
<pb facs="5"/>
so the Chain is perfected. So that in deed, he that hath one of these lincks, hath all, &amp; he that hath not all hath none. Here is no boasting of faith without workes: here is no reioycing in works without faith, here is no vertue without knowledge, no knowledge without temperance, no pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence without godlines, no godlines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out brotherly kindnes, no kindnes among brethren without godly loue or charitie. Begin with faith, &amp; end in loue, (for faith worketh by loue) so shalt thou be sure to haue the end of thy faith, euen the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of thy soul, which is the thing that I hartely wish vnto thee &amp; me. Thus do &amp; thou shalt liue, thus liue, &amp; thou shalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">Gal: 5.6.1. Pet. 1.9. Heb. 12.2.</note> die. <hi>Vale in authore salutis.</hi> Farewell in Christ, the author &amp; finisher of thy faith.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lorde, <hi>Radford Mauericke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>