<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112382_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07176</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17580</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112382</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of cattell : wherein is shewed the gouernment of oxen, kine, calues, and how to vse bulles and other cattell to the yoake, and fell. With diuers approued remedies, to helpe most diseases among cattell: most necessarie for all, especially for husband men, hauing the gouernment of any such cattell. Gathered and set forth by Leonard Mascall</title>
                 <author>Mascall, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 257, 5, 259-285, that is 301, 3 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>WHen I had gathered and collctted (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) certaine medicines how for to helpe cattel and to gouerne them. I considered what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and profit it might bee to my countrie and common wealth, specially vnto the husband men, and such as haue the gouernment of Oxen, Horses, Shéep, and such other cattell. For oft times for want of knowledge, many cattell being sicke, do perish and die: Where as sickenes and hurts are accident vnto man diuers waies, euen so it chaunceth vnto cattell. Whereupon I thought it good to take occasion for the loue of my countrie and common wealth, to write somewhat, partly of the gouernment for our most vsed cattell, as oxen, kine, calues, horses, shéepe, hogs, and such: with diuers approued remedies for them. Plainely and perfectly set forth, as well to bee vnderstood of the vnlearned husband man, as of the learned gentle man: shewing somewhat moreouer for the bones setting in a beast: Declaring likewise the order and nature of hogs, with the vse of dogs, and the cause of their madnes, with certaine helpes against the bitten cattell, and also to help mangie dogs, with diuers approued waies to take moules in any kind of ground. Which thing ye shall finde out in the tables of the same by alphabet and number, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into three bookes. Trusting (gentle Reader) thou wilt take all in good part, as is ment of the author here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>L. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>