<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the christian Reader, grace, mercie and peace.</title>
           <author>F., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112627_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13091</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23380</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112627</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the christian Reader, grace, mercie and peace.</title>
                 <author>F., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the anatomie of abuses : conteining the display of corruptions, with a perfect description of such imperfections, blemishes and abuses, as now reigning in euerie degree, require reformation for feare of Gods vengeance to be powred vpon the people and countrie, without speedie repentance, and conuersion vnto God: made dialogwise by Phillip Stubbes</title>
                 <author>Stubbes, Phillip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Ward, Roger.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>238 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the christian Reader, grace, mercie and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was neuer any age, or time (christian reader) since the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world how corrupt so euer, that was comparable to this our thrise vnhappie age in all kind of corruption, wickednes, and sin, with greefe of conscience I speake it, with weeping eies I behold it, and with sorrowfull hart I lament it. And therefore seeing wickednesse doth so abound, the Lord (least his children frosen in the dregs of their sinne should perish with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) raiseth vp in his mercie good men (as we see he hath done our good brother the author hereof) to plucke off the visors of sinne from their faces, and to lay them open to the view of the whole world, to the end that euerie one seeing the dung of his wicked waies, and the filthie dregs of sinne throwne in their faces, may blush at the same, be ashamed, repent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and turne to the Lord Iesus, and so eternally be saued To this end and purpose hath the author here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (for whose singular towardnes in his primar yeres the Lord Iesus be praised) taken in hand the compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this little treatise, conteining a summarie of certeine corruptions and abuses, as well in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraltie, as in the clergie. Wherefore good Reader read ouer the same mature, aduisedly, iudge of the
<pb facs="4"/>
same imparcially, and at no hand condemne not te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere, rashly, but compare euery thing with the truth of Gods word, and the state of time, and as it shall agree or disagree from the word of God. so to like or dislike of the same. For I am persuaded that there is nothing comprised in this whole booke, but what is agreeable to the word of God, sauing that in a few points the author bearing with the infirmitie of the time, hath somwhat qualified both his stile and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in hope of speedie reformation to insue, which God grant. Therefore gentle Reader, let me obtaine thus much at thy hands, as to accept his good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as well towards the truth, as towards the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors thereof, to rest thankfull to God for him, and to helpe him with thy praiers, that as hitherto euen from his youth he hath borne a zeale to the truth of Christs religion, so he may continue to the end, expressing (as he hath begun) in life and conuersation for euer through Christ Iesus our onlie Lord and Sauiour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy fellowe laborer. I. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>