<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The argument of the whole boke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1561</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112540_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14367</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24685</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112540</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The argument of the whole boke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ouer throw of the iustification of workes and of the vain doctrin of the merits of men : with the true assertion of the iustification of faith and of the good workes that procead or come of the same, and in what respect our good workes are crouned or rewarded of God settte foorth dialoge wise by John Veron. Newlye set foorthe and alowed accordynge to the order appoynted in the Quenes maiesties iniunctions. Ano. 1561</title>
                 <author>Véron, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tisdale (Tysdale), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1561</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 74, 6 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶The argument of the whole boke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrste and foremoste we haue declared, that we are freelye iustified, that is to say, deliuered from synne, eternall dampnation and euerlastinge death, and coumpted righteouse in the syghte of God, through fayth only in our sauiour Iesus Christ, without any merits or deseruynges, goynge before. Which thinge hathe bene mooste strongly proued both by manyfest and playne texts of the scriptures, and also by the autoryties of the aunciente fathers of the primitiue churche, contrarye to the sklaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous and most lyinge reportes of the enemyes of the truth, which do, most vngodlye blowe abroade, that we haue of late dayes sucked out thys doctrine of oure fyngers endes, not one af the olde writers saying once: <hi>Sola fides iustificat:</hi> faith
<pb facs="5"/> onely or fayeh alone doth iustifye. But how false this their report is, ye shal be iudges your selues, after ye haue reade the whole worke.</p>
   <p>We dyd, almooste in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynninge of this disputation, least anye impedimente or let should be lefte vnto the reader, concile Paul and Iames together, where, vnto the ignoraunt, they dyd seme to disagree, whiche (I truste) is so substantiallye done, that any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable man, wyll holde him self satisfyed. Secondlye it hath bene shewed, that as all the works, that we do afore oure iustification, I meane, afore we be graffed in Christ, and throughe fayth made members of his bodye, althoughe they seme neuer so glorious, so per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect and excellent, yet are but mere synne, and abhomination in the syght of God: so after we be once iustifyed, and made lyuely braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of that true vyne, we must not remain harein and vnfruteful
<pb facs="5"/> trees, but bringe foorth the frutes of our fayth, and abounde or flow in all kinde of good woorkes that God hath prepared for vs to walk in, remembring that we are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto created in Christ Iesus, who hath redemed vs, and clensed from our syns, to the end that we shuld be a peculiar people vnto him, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestlye geuen vnto good workes. Here haue we by the waye, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen wyll workes, that is such maner of works, as are set foorth by the mere inuētion of man, with out anye sure ground or foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Gods boke, or wythout any promysse conteyned in the same, prouinge, that all suche workes, for as muche, as they bee done withoute fayeth, canne in no wyse please god, but are an abominatiō vnto him, althoughe they be done, as they doe commonlye terme it, of a good intente and so, vppon occasion, we haue declared, and made manifest and playne, by the
<pb facs="6"/> historyes of Nadab and Abihu, of Saule, and of Dauid in bringinge the Arke in to Ierusalem, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than God had ordayned, how perilous a thinge it is, to attempte any thinge of good intente, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a sure warant of gods word, in the religion, worshipping, &amp; seruice of God. Thyrdlye we teach what be those workes that are to be takē for good works, euen such as God doeth expresselye comaunde vs in his worde. Which are moste liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set foorth vnto vs in manye pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the old and new Testament. How be it, this lesson is also ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that al they that do those good workes (althoughe they be neuer so good workes in them selues) do not by and by deserue, the comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and prayse of well doinge in the sight of God, eyther because that they do them, to the end that they may be glorified of menne, or for reward sake, the hope wherof beinge taken awaye they woulde
<pb facs="6"/> not as muche, as geue a cuppe of colde water, or for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishemente after this lyfe, and not for the loue onely, that they beare to God, and to theyr neighboure, or for to shew their obedience, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his wyl and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. But for the better instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ignoraunt, we haue set foorth at large, all the chiefe and pryncipall causes that oughte to moue vs, to do good woorkes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe we looked for no rewarde at all at Goddes hande, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandinge wyll not leaue our good workes vncrowned or vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, first because that we haue throughe sayeth, felowship with his sonne Iesus Christ, whose per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte obedience, he imputeth vnto vs for our owne, therbye most am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye and aboundantly supplying, what soeuer is wantinge and lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge in vs. Secondlye because, that he hathe made him selfe deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour vnto vs not by receauing any
<pb facs="7"/> thinge of vs, but by promissing all thinges, as saint Augustine doeth witnesse. Here also are the causes shewed, why oure good workes, althoughe in them selues, they be full of imperfection, do please God and are acceptable vnto him, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ought to be vnto vs a great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coragemente to lyue Godlye, and to excercise our selues in all maner of good workes, that God hathe cōmaunded vs in his word, beinge sure, that we canne not but please him in so doing. And as for merits it hath ben moste strongly proued, that althoughe we were able to do what soeuer God hath cōmaunded vs, yet we oughte to reckenne our selues vnprofitable seruauntes, &amp; that we haue done but our dutye. But for as muche as no man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doo the tenth parte of Gods cōmaundements, with such a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as God doth require, what do we merit or deserue (if our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be examined after the streight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="7"/> of Gods iudgement,) but the endelesse tormentes of hell fyer? Laste of all, concerninge the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of glorye after thys life, it hathe bene sufficientelye declared and shewed, that there can be no such diuersities or degrees of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, by reason of any merites, but that if therebe any, it commeth of the mere mercye and goodnesse of God, who doeth in vs moste libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally croune his owne giftes. The chefe scope or marke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we shote at in settinge foorth of this doctrine, is: that we hauing learned whence our saluation doeth come, shoulde geue the whole glorye thereof, to the onely mercye and goodnesse of God declared vnto vs in his sonne Iesus Christ, and most surely sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp by his bloude. To whome wyth the father, and the holye ghost be all prayse, glorye, and honoure, worldes wythoute ende. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>