<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVL my very kind Neighbour and Patron, THOMAS HARINGTON of Boothby-Paynell, in the County of LINCOLNE Esquire.</title>
           <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112209_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11458</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21709</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112209</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVL my very kind Neighbour and Patron, THOMAS HARINGTON of Boothby-Paynell, in the County of LINCOLNE Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two sermons preached at Paules-Crosse London : The one November 21. the other Aprill 15. 1627. By Robert Saunderson, Bachelour in Divinitie, and sometimes Fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sanderson, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL my very kind Neighbour and Patron, THOMAS HARINGTON of <hi>Boothby-Paynell,</hi> in the County of LINCOLNE Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR;</hi> although I neither haue, nor ought to haue any other <hi>prime inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the <hi>Publishing</hi> of these two Sermons, then I had in the <hi>Preaching</hi> of them, and then euery <hi>Minister</hi> that fore-casteth to make his last account with comfort ought to haue in the whole <hi>course</hi> and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
<pb facs="3"/>
of his Ministerie, <hi>viz.</hi> the building vp of the people of God in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Godlinesse:</hi> yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but desire withall, that as they passeth abroad in the world, they may stand vp euery where as a <hi>publique</hi> testimonie of my <hi>priuate</hi> obligations to you. Whereof (omitting those dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kinde offices of <hi>Friendship</hi> and <hi>Neighbourhood,</hi> which you are euer ready to doe me and mine vpon all occasions; as also your <hi>zeale</hi> vnto <hi>Iustice</hi> and the <hi>Common-good,</hi> aboundantly manifested in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the affaires of your <hi>Countrey</hi> with singular <hi>skill, Industry,</hi> and <hi>Faithfulnes:)</hi> I neede produce no other argument then this; that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing so long vnder my <hi>Charge,</hi> as I doe also vnder your <hi>Patronage,</hi> you neuer yet gaue me the least cause to
<pb facs="3"/>
thinke my selfe, either <hi>despised</hi> in the <hi>Worke,</hi> or <hi>defrauded</hi> in the <hi>Wages,</hi> of my Ministery. Which, as it is a gracious euidence of a <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>sincere</hi> heart in you; so it is a Circumstance, wherein I am <hi>happie</hi> beyond the condition of most of my <hi>Brethren</hi> in the same <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> God make me truly <hi>Thankfull</hi> to him for his good <hi>Prouidence</hi> ouer me therein, and for all other his <hi>Mercies</hi> towards me: and both <hi>continue</hi> and <hi>increase</hi> your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts</hi> amid all the Afflictions of this present euill World; and in the end make you <hi>partaker</hi> of the <hi>Ioyes</hi> of the world to come:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in the Lord,</hi> Robert Saunderson.</signed>
      <dateline>Boothby-Paynell, <hi>Linc:</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>1. Iuly. 1628.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>