<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Which, in the presentation before Queene E. was thus varyed, BY MACILENTE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112455_Ba2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112455</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Which, in the presentation before Queene E. was thus varyed, BY MACILENTE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The workes of Beniamin Ionson</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Meighen, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 1015, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb n="175" facs="99"/>
   <head>Which, in the presentation before Queene E. was thus varyed, BY MACILENTE.</head>
   <l>NEuer till now did obiect greet mine eyes</l>
   <l>With any light content: but in her graces,</l>
   <l>All my malicious powers haue lost their stings.</l>
   <l>Enuie is fled my soule, at sight of her,</l>
   <l>And shee hath chac'd all black thoughts from my bosome,</l>
   <l>Like as the sunne doth darkenesse from the world.</l>
   <l>My streame of humour is runne out of me.</l>
   <l>And as our cities torrent (bent t'infect</l>
   <l>The hallow'd bowels of the siluer <hi>Thames</hi>)</l>
   <l>Is checkt by strength, and clearnesse of the riuer,</l>
   <l>Till it hath spent it selfe e'ene at the shore;</l>
   <l>So, in the ample, and vnmeasur'd floud</l>
   <l>Of her perfections, are my passions drown'd:</l>
   <l>And I haue now a spirit as sweet, and cleere,</l>
   <l>As the most rarefi'd and subtile aire.</l>
   <l>With which, and with a heart as pure as fire,</l>
   <l>(Yet humble as the earth) doe I implore,</l>
   <l>O heauen, that shee (whose presence hath effected</l>
   <l>This change in me) may suffer most late change</l>
   <l>In her admir'd and happie gouernement:</l>
   <l>May still this <hi>Land</hi> be call'd <hi>fortunate</hi>,</l>
   <l>And rugged treason tremble at the sound</l>
   <l>When <hi>Fame</hi> shall speake it with an <hi>emphasis.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Let forraine politie be dull as lead,</l>
   <l>And pale inuasion come with halfe a heart,</l>
   <l>When he but lookes vpon her blessed soile.</l>
   <l>The throat of warre be stopt within her land,</l>
   <l>And turtle-footed peace dance <hi>fayrie</hi> rings</l>
   <l>About her court: where, neuer may there come</l>
   <l>Suspect, or danger, but all trust, and safetie:</l>
   <l>Let flatterie be dumbe, and enuie blind</l>
   <l>In her dread presence: death himselfe admire her:</l>
   <l>And may her vertues make him to forget</l>
   <l>The vse of his ineuitable hand.</l>
   <l>Flie from her age; Sleepe time before her throne,</l>
   <l>Our strongest wall falls downe, when shee is gone.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>