<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GREATEST HONOVR OF THE ME∣MORIE OF THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS LADY OF SAMOTHEA, MARJE.</title>
           <author>Maxwell, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112547_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07317</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112547</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GREATEST HONOVR OF THE ME∣MORIE OF THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS LADY OF SAMOTHEA, MARJE.</title>
                 <author>Maxwell, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Queene Elizabeths looking-glasse of grace and glory : Wherein may be seen the fortune of the faithfull: that is to say, the wrastling, victory, and reward, or the combat, conquest and crowne of Gods children. All cleerely represented according to Scripture, &amp; illustrated by diuers notable examples of Gods seruants both men and vvomen: and likewise enterlaced with many memorable alligories &amp; morallties: both pleasant and profitable to be read. By I.M. Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Maxwell, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 215, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO</hi> THE GREATEST HONOVR OF THE ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORIE OF THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS LADY OF SAMOTHEA, <hi>MARJE.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N her lifetime Queene-heire of Scotland, Queene-dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of France, and by naturall descent Princesse apparent of England, France, and Ireland;</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>A BRANCHE</head>
      <p>Sprung from the Imperiall and Royall stocke of CHARLES the great, once the
<pb facs="3"/>most Augustious Emperour of Romaines &amp; Germaines, and King of France most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>GREAT-GRAND-CHILDE</head>
      <p>Of the most prudent and puissant Prince HENRY the seuenth, King of England, France, and Ireland, by his eldest Daughter borne in the blessed Bed of the happy Vnion of the two Roses, the most illustrious Queene MARGARET wife to the most vertuous &amp; praise-worthy Prince IAMES the fourth King of Scots.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>DAVGHTER AND ONELY HEIRE</head>
      <p>Of the most noble, worthy &amp; mighty Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Prince IAMES the fift King of Scotland, and of the most excellent and prudent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse his wife. Queene MARIE de Lorrayne, Dutchesse of Longouille, and daughter of the right magnificent Prince, CLAVDE Duke of Guise.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <head>WIFE</head>
      <p>In first mariage, to the most Christian King of France, FRANCIS the second; and in second mariage by Gods especiall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, disappointing all the policies and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises of the Deuill, and euill men tending to the contrary, wife to the right generous and comely Prince her highnes nearest &amp; dearest coosin, as being descended likewise from the loynes of HENRY the seuenth by his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest Daughter MARGARET Queene of Scotland, by her Daughter in second mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, the right illustrious Princesse MARGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RET DOVGLAS Countesse of Angus, &amp; Lennox, mother to the said Prince HENRY Lord Darley, Earle of Rosse, Duke of Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Knight of the most renowned order of S. MICHAEL, and King of Scotland.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>MOTHER</head>
      <p>By the foresaid most generous Prince, her Maiesties right entierly beloued husband, of the most Augustious Prince, our most grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne IAMES the CONCORDER, supreme Lord of Samothea, and the first
<pb facs="4"/>Christian Monarch and Vniter of this Ile;</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>GRAND-MOTHER</head>
      <p>Of thee three graces of great Britaine; the most hopefull flower of Princes, HENRY the MAGNANIMOVS Prince of Cambria and of Cumbri, the most sweete tender Prince, CHARLES Duke of Yorke and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banie, and the most gracefull Princesse Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame ELIZABETH Infanta of Albion;</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>THE FLOWER</head>
      <p>Once of the whole women of her age, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with an admirable fortitude, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificent bountie of minde, adorned with an incomparable pulchritude and beauty of Body; decored with the most heroicall and princely properties, and honored most, of all the Ladies of the earth, with the many often profered mariages of the greatest Kings, and noblest Princes of Christendome.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>TO THE EVERLIVING MEMORIE</head>
      <p>(I say) of a matchlesse MARIE, once on
<pb facs="4"/>earth full of <hi>Grace,</hi> and now in heauen full of <hi>Glorie:</hi> and euen the <hi>peace-making mother</hi> of Albions greatest <hi>grace</hi> and vnited <hi>Glorie.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>The Sonnes sonne of her highnes faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full seruant,</hi> WILLIAM MAXWELL <hi>Sonne to the Lairde of kirkonnell, and in his life-time Man at Armes to the most Christian King, doth in most humble manner deuote &amp; dedicate the</hi> LOOKING-GLASSE OF GRACE &amp; GLORIE. IAMES MAXWELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>