<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Iudicious and vvell affected Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112046_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10898</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21169</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112046</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Iudicious and vvell affected Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the two sacraments of the Gospell: baptisme and the Supper of the Lord : Divided into two parts. The first treating of the doctrine and nature of the sacraments in generall, and of these two in speciall; together with the circumstances attending them. The second containing the manner of our due preparation to the receiving of the Supper of the Lord; as also, of our behaviour in and after the same. Whereunto is annexed an appendix, shewing; first, how a Christian may finde his preparation to the Supper sweete and easie: secondly, the causes why the sacrament is so unworthily received by the worst; and so fruitlesly by the better sort: with the remedies to avoyd them both. By D.R. B. of Divin. minister of the Gospell</title>
                 <author>D. R. (Daniel Rogers)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 199, 9, 244, that is 212, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Iudicious and vvell affected Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Reader, I have ever estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Lord Iesus, the newbirth and nourishment of his Church, to be (of all other Arguments and Treatises of Divinity) the most eminent and essentiall either for such as preach and write, to insist upon; or for those that heare and reade, to improove to themselves, by knowing and beleeving. And sithence our good God hath not contented himselfe to vouchsafe to his Church this great gift of Christ, onely by the word of promise: (which yet, being grounded upon such unshaken Foundations, as his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, the death of his Son, and the faithfulnesse of his dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, might well claime the obedience and consent of faith at our hands) But also hath added the Sacraments as seales of this his covenant, and as the utmost assurance of his good meaning; moreouer annexing the Spirit of promise and of seale, to them both, for the better applying to each soule in particular, his part in these good things which he hath betea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her: I have thought it fittest (having now leasure more than enough to chuse my argument) to light upon this, of Christ Sacramentall: as giving mee hope of doing the most
<pb facs="5"/> comprehen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e good, and becomming most advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>ch of God, both for the understanding and use of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>trine.</p>
   <p>Every man desires to have that which he buyeth or enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, when the commodity is at the best: When men would ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shew or buy wares or cattle in the Market, they desire to set them forth at the best; and when they are in best case to attract buyers: we love to behold the faces of them we love, when they are at the best, for health of body and spirit: and if we were as wise to improove every thing to the best, as we are willing to get it at the best; sure it is, we love to get no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at the worst, which may bee come by at the best. Now then the Sacraments exhibite Christ (as I may say) at his best: And as <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> daughter is invited to come &amp; behold <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> when he was clothed with all those costly ornaments and glory where with his mother made him glad on his crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninng day; so doe the Sacraments offer Christ a greater ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect than <hi>Salomon</hi> even in his best Grace, in the richest and royallest robe of his righteousnesse, in the best of his Peace, ioy, and contentation which God can bestow him in; Whose heart should not then esteeme him at this best of his, with best iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affection? Not by foolish or Popish comparison of one ordinance with another; But by considering that each ordinance with another is better than another alone, and so the Sacrament with a word, is above the word alone, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it containes the word and hath more besides in it, even Christ at his best, in the fulnesse, length, depth, and all trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of breeding and nourishing grace, not onely in himselfe, but made over to my soule by the Father, grace for grace to mee: my Wisedome, Righteousnesse, Sanctification, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
   <p>Alas! deere friends! What were the knowledge of this Lord Iesus, as he is only the second person in Trinity and the
<pb facs="5"/> eternall Word of the Father? If the depth of that mystery contained in <hi>Heb. 1:3.</hi> (To wit, that Christ is the brightnes of the Fathers glory, and the ingraven forme of his person) were fully understood by a man, (as who doubts but such knowledge were excellent?) yet alas! it falls short of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent knowledge which <hi>Paul</hi> speakes of <hi>Phil. 3:</hi> Of Christ Iesus my Lord, who hath given himselfe for me, loved me, by which the world is crucified to me, and I to it; this onely is that to which all other is dung and drosse. Nay further, put case I knew him, as the true Mediator, in all three offices, and namely the true onely Priest and satisfier for the sinnes of the world: Were this that excellent knowledge of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except he were crucified also in the eye and to the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gaine of my soule, as my Lord and God, and as my satisfaction, and the treader of the wine-presse of the fierce wrath of God, <hi>Esay 63.1,</hi> that the anger of God might be pacified to me? No verily. Nay lastly, put case this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Iesus Christ my satisfier, could possibly bee severed from the knowledge of him my Sanctifier also: and that Christ my birth, could bee divided from Christ my Nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; my support, health, growth, and fruitfulnesse; could this knowledge be counted the most excellent? Were it not a rending (rather) of one peece of Christs garment from another, yea a pulling of one especiall part of him from my soule, and breaking of so precious a Diamond in peices? What excellent things then must those be, which present the Lord Iesus in all these three, the beauty of his person, the benefit of his satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and the grace of his Sanctification; and that to mee, with seazin and delivery? That offer him (as I sayd) at his best? This doe the Sacraments, and therefore of how great esteeme should they be in the Church of Christ?</p>
   <p>I confesse if I presented Christ to thy view (good Reader) in those darke Sacraments of the Old Testament, or no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb facs="6"/> than <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptist could, I should bring thee a burgaine at the worst hand. For, although Christ were in them also, yet with such poore convincement, that I may safely say: The body of receivers, who beheld the covenant of the Law as a covenant of workes and Righteousnesse thereby; did receive the Sacraments as a curse rather than a blessing upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: and bred worse blood in themselves thereby, than before they had. For why? They renouncing the right co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of righteousnesse whereof they were seales, (as it is sayd, that <hi>Abraham</hi> received circumcision as a seale of it) and mistaking the law, as if it required a possible obedience from them, to merit life; what did they but curse themselves and say, Cursed be he who thinkes he can abide in all things written in the booke of the Law to doe them? And not being able to doe them, but deluding themselves, and taking the Sacrament upon it; what did they in effect, but seale up that curse to themselves and their seede? But lo, in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Ghospell, is offered thee a better ministrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the spirit of the Lord Iesus, in the seales of that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse which comes by faith: and therefore a curse is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a blessing. For as the covenant is, which thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest in, so is the seale which thou receivest, both are blessed, and thou comming in faith unto them, receivest from God blessing under seale: so that hee hath blessed thee, and thou shalt bee blessed. And is not this the Lord Iesus at his best?</p>
   <p>Moreover if I presented thee onely Iewish Sacraments, what great thing should I offer thee? Surely Christ in a darke corner, circumcision in a private family, the Passeover in an houshold by it selfe: But lo, I present Christ unto thee not with a veile before his face, which is obscure: but in a Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, with open face, transforming thee from glory to glory. I say a Christ Sacramentall, not offered by a Priest to God in a
<pb facs="6"/> Masse, and in a corner of the Church, with a boy to mumble an answere, but in the open view of his Church and assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of his Saints. Looke not heere for Popish, Anabaptisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Brownisticall or Scismaticall Sacraments huddled up by a false Church in their houses, barnes, or corners, (though I taxe not corners where the Church is present as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres were in woods: but in the midst of his people, where Christ the Lord of Sacraments is present with his owne, met in his name, even in the beauty of his holinesse. So that as he suffered not in a corner of heaven, or earth, but upon an hill before his Church, and refused not the world to bee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses; and was lift up as the Serpent in the wildernes, in the publike view of his people; so, that thou professest to bee a dove of his flocke, and one of the youth of his wombe, <hi>Psal. 110.</hi> Mayst fly to his loover and windowes, and come into his Temple with frequency as the dew falls upon the grasse, saying, How amiable are thy Tabernacles O Lord of hosts! My flesh longeth and my feete desire to see and stand in the courts of thine house. Even in the chambers of my Mother! and in the Garden of thy spices, even there give me thy love: There let thy Northwind of Prayer and blessing blow thy sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour into my nostrills, that after thine ointments powred out there, the Daughters my followthe! And is not this, Christ at the best?</p>
   <p>But to proceed a little in this argument (for I have locked my selfe out of the hall, &amp; therefore must stand a while in my porch rather than no where) what better proofe of the Lord Iesus at his best, than this, that he is offered to thee in no lesse mysticall union for the end of a more mysticall one? I meane as united to poore bread and wine, that he might also unite himselfe in the whole grace of his Sacrifice to thy soule and body? What better und easier conveiance couldst thou wish than this, for so feeble and weake a spirit as thine is? When
<pb facs="7"/> once that people which followed Christ sitting upon an Asse Colt, and riding as a King to Ierusalem, cryed Hosanna, and sayd, Blessed be he that commeth in the name of the Lord: Thinke we not that they saw Christ at the best? Why did they else, (except they had beheld his spiritual Kingdome) cut downe Palmes and strew them in the way, stripping them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of their garments to set him thereon? Surely they were not so offended at the meanenesse of his palfrey and basenesse of the outside, but they saw in this his riding, a cleere representation of his glorious grace, and the Maiesty of his person. So shouldst thou, in this union of Christ with base crummes of bread or drops of wine, behold a more spirituall presence of Christ, who careth not for such creatures, but for thy soule; and being farre from stumbling at the basenesse of the Asse, or Elements, raise up thy soule to a more heavenly sense, of the Lord Iesus comming into thy heart and spirit, bringing thee to God, and uniting thee to the fountaine of thy blessednesse in a farre closer manner than ever <hi>Adam</hi> was. And is not this union, the Lord Iesus at his best? yes verily.</p>
   <p>From this Sacramentall union, proceeds that exhibitive na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Sacraments, carrying the Lord Iesus into the soule of all the elect that communicate. For to what end is union Sacramentall, save that the Sacraments being thus pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of the Lord Iesus mystically in them, might exhibite to all, and effectually carry into the bosomes of the elect, the power of this Lord Iesus, and convey as Vessells, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelles and Pipes, that grace which they containe? I doe not meane that by vertue of the worke wrought, or by the force of Divine institution, there is any naturall holinesse put into them, or magicall power of inchantment, to take hold of the soule. No, in no wise: for how many thousands are there both young and old, who after the enjoying of
<pb facs="7"/> the Sacraments, doe put most woefull barres in their owne way, that the power of Sacramentall union might never come at them? So that when the Covenant comes to bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spenced unto them, they fare as persons utterly disabled to receive it. Nay, neither dare I thinke that by vertue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, its of absolute necessity that all Elect Infants must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive conversion of grace, just in the act of their Baptizing: for what were this but to ascribe more to the Seale than to the Covenant, yea to invert their order, and to ascribe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power to an ordinance, (under which they walke <hi>20, 30, 40.</hi> yeeres carelesly, without discovery of any grace at all) rather than to the lively power of the Covenant preached and working from that time forth, an apparant change? So that although in charity I am bound to thinke no other, save that all such as receive Sacraments duely, concurre with the grace of the Spirit for future improvement: Yet to tye the Lords hands behind him, and to make the Lord of Sacraments to become their underling, as if hee had put himselfe out of Authority and office, wholly to be subject to his Sacrament, what indignity were it for the ordainer? No not so: But so farre, so often, and where it shall seeme good to himselfe to make use of his Sacrament for the good of his Elect (for whose good they serve) there doubtlesse these Ordinances doe both present and conferre the grace which is put into them? Else to what end should they have it, except they might convey it? Now summe up all, and answere: Is not the exhibitive power of the Sacrament, the Lord Iesus at his best? Is not a reall tender, better than a bare signe, or a promise onely without performance? He that promiseth an hundred pounds to lend or give to his poore friend, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently tenders the money, that he might be before hand, doth he not lend or give at the best?</p>
   <p>Nay, more than this, not the Sacraments onely are thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitive of Christ to the soule: But by vertue of the union I
<pb facs="8"/> have spoken of, the Lord Iesus himselfe is there present (where his institution is duely observed) to be the Baptizer of his members, and to be the steward and nourisher of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: that is, to bestow himselfe upon the soule. Touching Baptisme first, true it is, That our Lord Iesus himselfe never baptised any outwardly: howbeit as then, so much more now being ascended, he it is who in the outward Baptisme of the Minister, doth give gifts unto men, and doth still baptise all his, with the holy Ghost and fire. A poore sinfull man doth what he can doe; but further he cannot goe: He dives the infant into, holdes it in, and receives it out againe from the water, baptising it in the name of the sacred Trinity. But this our great Baptist, he is all in all for the doing of the worke. It is he who casts in the salt of his divine healing power into corrupt and (of themselves) accursed creatures; and Element; and element; he removes the curse, death and barrennes of the waters, utterly unable to engender; he takes off their base uncomelinesse: he darts and plants in them the efficacy of his owne death and resurrection both for merit of pardon, and of holines: he sanctifies &amp; clenses them, that they may become hallowed and purging instruments; And as a planter takes the sien of the Apple-tree, and pitches it into a Crabtree stock: so the Lord Iesus takes the pretious sien of his owne Righteousnesse, the Power of his owne death and grave, the strength of his resurrection and exalting, and pitches both into water: so that water becomes Christ-water, Christs death and life, so that the soule is washt with the one as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with the other; The soule (by faith in the covenant) feele her descent into the water, to become a spirit of diving her into the laver, and blood, and grave of the Lord Iesus: her being under the water, to become the spirit brooding and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying the water, to become a seede of life abiding in the wombe of the soule, to regenerate it to the life of Christ; Her arising up from the water, to become a spirit of Resurrection
<pb facs="8"/> (as <hi>Peter</hi> excellently speakes <hi>1</hi> Epist. cap. <hi>3.</hi> verse <hi>21.</hi>) and a baptising of the soule with the activity and raising of her up with Christ, from her death, grave, basenesse and misery, unto immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and glory. Yea in all three the soule feeles the power of a new and omnipotent creation of her to God, ingrafting her in God, never to be pulled from him any more as at first. And as the spirit whereby the Lord offered up himselfe was, so is the power of the same spirit to the soule, begetting and renewing it; Eternall also: so that the never dying power of baptisme keepes the branch of the vine thus one put in, to abide for ever ingrafted and planted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the person of <hi>Emanuell:</hi> so that himselfe the stocke shall as soone wither, as the soule which by faith is in him shall perish. No more baptisings shall neede than one, because Christ ever liveth in the soule, and recovereth her by his unrestrained influence, from all her swouning, decayes and wanzings, to her former integrity: no more Barkes are required after shipwracke save this one. Now, if Christ himselfe in person (not the poore Minister with all his acts onely) be the true Baptist: can it be otherwise, but Baptisme must needes be the Lord Iesus at the best?</p>
   <p>Lastly, to adde one word also of the Supper: The sinfull tongue and hands (I say not of a wicked Masse Priest) but even the best consecrater of the Sacrament, that lives, cannot blesse sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: But the Lord Iesus our steward, he is the Administer of it completely; he is the true consecrater, yea the foode and feeder of the Soules of his owne, with his pretious body and blood unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. None whom the Father hath given him to be his living ones, can decay, pine, or wither under his hand while he lives to make them Provision. He told his Desciples, he would eate and drinke no more of the fruite of the Vine, till hee dranke it in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: meaning, till he spiritually without mouth or hands, did present himselfe with his Church Sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>amentally, there to feede them: But in that sence he promised to drinke it with them, to the worlds end He it is then who as the Master of the feast and the feast also, welcometh, provideth for, and encourageth his guests, to
<pb facs="9"/> eate good things, and to delight in fatnesse: He it is who not onely in the Ministers person still consecrateth, but by his might and strength, derives all his blood, spirit, marrow and nourishment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bones and veines of his poore members, by his union with the elements; whereby he saveth and sustayneth all his true borne ones that cry after his brest and succour; he cannot suffer them to lacke. And as himselfe in divers phrases expresseth, he feedes them in his Pastures, leades them to the waters, he cherisheth them as his spouse, nourisheth them as his branches, and by him as the doore, they goe in and out, finding pasture. For he hath made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe one with bread and wine, that man not living by bread onely, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God: may, in and by these Elements, draw a secret foyson and increase to the soule, and be therein susteined with faith and the fruits, as after in the Treatise (God willing) I shall more fully declare. He whose flesh once eaten is immortall, yet offers himselfe often for the releefe of daily defects. And is not this the Lord Iesus at his best in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament also?</p>
   <p>Endlesse it were to recite all which might convince thee of this excellency of Christ Sacramentall. Who would not confesse that friend to shew his love at the best, who should most draw neare to him in his greatest troubles? And is not Christ Sacramentall for the nonce? To what end then doth he offer thee his blood and bid th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e drinke it, save to conforme thee to a sweete meekenesse of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in suffering, and to a fellowship in all his Afflictions, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of overcomming in his strength? Againe, if a man should promise to doe thee a kindnesse, wouldst thou not interpret his kindnesse at the best, if it lay in such a kind, as should supply thy pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar want? What kindnesse is counted of, like that which is most se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sonable? That which releeves not some defect, may be thought superfluous. Even so is Christ Sacramentall: a releefe of each soules personall, peculiar diseases, wants, decayes, distempers. Like to the man of <hi>Baalshalisha, 2</hi> King. <hi>4.42.</hi> who brought loaves of Corne and presents to the Prophet, when there was a necessity of famine,
<pb facs="9"/> and a multitude to bee fed. But I end in a word: Wherein can it more cleerely appeare that the Lord Iesus is offered thee in the Sacrament at his best, than in his blessed fulnesse? If thou shouldest visite thy friends house, tell mee when shouldst thou most thinke thou camest at the best, than in the middest of a feast? So I say heere, The Sacrament is the Kings feast at the marriage of his Sonne: The feast of the hills, the feast of God, and heaven a full feast of all refined wines, fat and delicate things. If Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie be so good, is not his feast of Christ, Christ at his best? Wherein thy soule may fill it selfe for the present and for after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with choice Deinties, as the Aramites campe, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse thereof filled the leapers.</p>
   <p>But, now what is the upshot of all? Oh! sad mourning! That we are at our worst when Christ is best! Oh mourne that after <hi>70.</hi> yeeres liberty of the word and Sacraments in the Church: yet by the sinne of man, such mysteries as these should lye by, dise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed, because unacknowledged? True it is, as once it was a deepe conceit with the Iew, that his Messia must neede be some speciall person: But when the true Messia indeed came, they knew not what to make of him; he was a strange wonder unto them. So now, it deepely dwells in most men, that in the Sacrament some mysticall thing lyes hidden: but when they come to it, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they know not what: The cause is, their carnality, and sensualnesse, which is offended at the spiritualnesse of them: which makes them alleadge, oh they are darke matters, and for great Divines, not for such as they, to meddle withall. And thus in time, corrupt ease breeding error: that errour growes to proove religion: and as at first men thought them difficult, so at length its their best devotion, to rest in blind and superstitious reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a thing unknowne. As those Athenians, who set up an Altar, to the unknowable God blind devotion being the meere fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling short of faith. If this disease had infected popery onely, it had beene well: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this Popish leaven of carnall Sacraments which sowred the first reformation with a consubstantiate Christ: hath tainted us with as dangerous an error, even to rest in a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall devotion, and the <hi>opus operatum</hi> of a devout blinde recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, counting it the top of religion.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>Alas! poore soules. To what purpose doe we so crake and boast of our Sacraments of the Gospel, that they are above those of the old Testament in al respects (as indeede thy are) when as its cleare by good experience, that setting aside some places enlightned by the word, our Sacraments to the body of our people, are as dimme and dumbe representers of a Christ already crucified, as to the Iew, they were darke pretendings of the Messiah to come. Oh! How woefull a fruit of darkenesse is this, that people now in this midday of light, are so bafled, that it fares with them as if it were twylight? Is it not fearefull, that when there is so great odds in the season, there should be so little in the persons living in them! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause blindnes makes all seasons alike, both of darknes and light? How fearefull is it that our eye should be so evill to our selves when Gods is so good? &amp; that we should be such Almners of Gods bounty to our selves as if we still served an hard Master, what is this but to betray God to the blasphemy of Hypocrites, profane ones, and ignorants?</p>
   <p>This little understanding of these mysteries, among men in this age of ours (wherein mens frequency of receiving seemes to strive with their unfruitfulnesse) hath beene one occasion of my publishing this treatise. That (if possible) that excessive exalting of the Sacraments in Popery, above the word or any other peece of worship, through their Superstition: might bee equalled among us Protestants in the Church of God, with as truely honourable an esteeme thereof, and that from knowledge and experience of their worth. Considering partly the little care of teaching their doctrine in Congregations: and partly the cold preparation of such as receive; and partly the resting of men in their performances onely without power or fruit: I could not see wherein I should doe greater honour to God than to enhanse the knowledg of Christ Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall, &amp; to incite others to do it, whose learned and habituous abilities can farre better performe it? And surely it stands us all in hand, least signes of contradiction deface) to our uttermost to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the excellency of our Sacraments. That those rich legacies which the sin of man, or that man of sin, with his Complices have so long kept hid from the true heires and owners thereof, may be
<pb facs="10"/> cleared unto them, to be their just portion and claime. Beseeching the Lord, that as he shall vouchsafe us clearer light of knowledge, so (as our Church Liturgy commands us to pray) that ancient Discipline of Gods house might prevaile among us! I meane, That whereas the number of ignorant scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and unprepared ones, as much exceeds the number of prepared, peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and worthy Communicants, as the army of the Aramites exceeded the Israelites two flockes of Kiddes: by this meanes, it might please God, the number of the latter might as much exceede the former.</p>
   <p>For my owne part, (to returne to my matter) I blesse God, that while it was my lot to have a nayle in the Priests Sanctuary; next to the preaching of Christ in the promise, it was my poore care and course both by Catechis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and Sermons, to discover him in his Sacraments. Which labour (as weake as it was) I have so little cause to repent of: that now I am encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in my selfe to recollect and compile those scattered meditations into some method and view, for the benefit of others, that heard them not. A great motive whereto was also this, that as while they were preached, they found full as much approbation, as any part else of my labours: so, since; they have provoked the desires of many more than I can mention, that they might not with my selfe lye by, and be buried in forgetfulnesse. Adde heereto, that now in this vacancy of better service, I could not easily quit my selfe of that idle unfruitfulnesse which too soone (as rust) is ready to grow upon us without some service done in this kinde.</p>
   <p>To you then I addresse my speech, in the conclusion, deare friends who have beene taught by, and now are made partakers of my labours: Beseech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, and the Lord for you, that by the lively resemblance of these things which you have bin long moulded in, and shall be heere presented withall; you would give Testimony to this Truth, as the Truth is in Iesus. That is, that by your spirituall prospering in the grace of the Lord Iesus Sacramentall, yee would commend this Doctrine of the Sacraments, especially of the Supper. So shall I have cause to say, That you are my Epistle written in your hearts, knowne and read of all men, and manif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sted to be the Epistle of Christ, not written with Inke in paper, but with the Spirit of obedience and love, in the fleshy Tables of your heart! Oh how shall you then safeguard me not from the evill tongues of men (which I feare not) but the contradiction of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and the foule aspersion of an unprofitable Minister of Christ? In which happy wish I cease troubling you, and commend your reading hereof to the blessing of God. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>