<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prenter to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112574_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12968</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prenter to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The confutation of the Abbote of Crosraguels masse : set furth by Maister George Hay</title>
                 <author>Hay, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lekpreuik, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 49, 51-54, 56-96, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>The Prenter to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <pb facs="2"/>AS I haue at all tymes bene ready to employe and bestowe my laboures, to the auancement of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, and vtili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie of his Church, so the bruite rysing of this that I now present vnto thee good Reader Confutation of the Abbote of Crosragnels Masse, I wes moste diligent, and trauelled moste earnestly with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it, that it might come to light. Hard it wes vnto me, amongest many others, to obteane it of him, a man shamefast of his owen nature, yet by the inopportune and continuall sure of the Church, &amp; freindes being mollified and moued to yeald and remitte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omwhat of his will, in end oppenned vp his mynde, that he hath onely written this by maner of declamatiō, and so hath vsed some Greik wordes, as expressing the mater moste liuely and sensiblie, which wordes I had no Carracters to expres: this moued me somwhat at the beginning, yet finding them few in nomber, and so seruing to the mater, as I could not well suffer them to be taken away, yea, and no impediment to the vnlearned, the sentence being moste plaine, I coulde not those the learned to be frauded of so great a help, and so vndertuke the mater. Wherein I haue vsed the help of a moste excellēt young mā, wel exercised in the tongue, yit the trauel being wearisome in the hait of his occupatiōs the ordour and reule by him laide, I wes driuen, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to borrow the laboure of some Scollers, whome I iudged to be moste expect. Whom vnto it muste be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if ether fant shalbe in lacking of a letter, or otherway<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es in accent, and others such accidents. This I speak no but to the praise of the great good wil of the children, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> are ready and willing to gratifie the Church of God: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>dicat the name of the Author from all calumnie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> and wicked tougues. If I should haue su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Church, as I haue oftentymes implored, the shou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot the ingynes and labours of the learned in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> countrie be retarded by any such impediment, yea, and I will promes further, we should not be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to send here and there, abounding in all thinges necessarie within our selues. And so faire thou well in the Lorde Iesus. At our buith, the penult of Iuly. 1563.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>