<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vnto the faithefull Reader, greting, in our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112577_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02879</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13017</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112577</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vnto the faithefull Reader, greting, in our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chrystian exhortation verye profitable : gathered out of the holye scriptures, vnto the great comfort, and vtilitye, of euery faythfull soule, being in agony of death, vnto whom, it oughte to be rehersed, with lowd voyce, diuers and sundry times, if nede so require vnto the which is added, towarde the latter end a godly praier for the sick drawing to an ende of this life, with a catechisme, not onely to instruct the sicke, but also to refreshe his memorye, wyth the great mistery of our redemption. Translated out of Frenthe [sic] into Englyshe by Robart Heasse minister at Algate</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42 + pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Vnto the faithefull Reader, greting, in our Lord <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earelye beloued Reader, I pray the take in good parte this present exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taciō, that I haue here translated out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> French tounge, into thy vulgar tounge with greate thoughte and care vntill I of my part had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, I trust to the gret com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of euerye faithfull person, that feareth God, to vse &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, at the time of nede, when as it shall please god to call him out of this mortal and wretched worlde. But be aduertised that thou maiste vse it righte, that these thre letters. B.S.N. The first signifyeth brother, that is when thou speakest vnto a man The seconde signifyeth suster, a woman, and the thirde em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth,
<pb facs="4"/> that thou muste name the partye sicke, by his proper name, for he oughte not to be honoured, by names, either, of worldly, honours or worshipes, But rather to resist Satan the enemy of mannes soule, in and throughe the power of our lord and god, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sicke must be named, by his owne name, that he hath receiued, in the holy sacrament of Baptisme, and in so doinge thou shalt obey the Lord God, whom I beseche of his infinite goodnes and mercye, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to be Good and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, both vnto thee and me in the last iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>