<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull, his very louing Mother, ANNE ROGERS Widow, within the precinct of Christes Church CAN∣TERBVRY.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112048_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10903</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112048</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull, his very louing Mother, ANNE ROGERS Widow, within the precinct of Christes Church CAN∣TERBVRY.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon of loue : Instructing all men to vnite and ioyne themselues in hearty loue, and Christian charitie with one another. Preached at Folkestone, a maior towne in Kent. By Francis Rogers, Batchelor in Diuinity; and sometimes fellow of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 45, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull, his very louing <hi>Mother,</hi> ANNE ROGERS Widow, within the precinct of <hi>Christes Church</hi> CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERBVRY.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Husbandman doth not plant his Tree, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, Dongue it, Lop it, Prune it, to the end that when the time of bearing Fruit is come, it should be like the Fig-Tree, to bring foorth Leaues and no Fruit; but rather that it should be like vnto the Vine-tree which doth bring forth fruit in clusters, and in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance: euen so man, which is <hi>planta inuersa,</hi> a Tree, with his roote vpward, is not nourished in the wombe of his Mother for the space of fortie weekes together, and after he is borne into the world, hee is not suckled, fed, swadled, and tended by Mothers naturall care,
<pb facs="3"/>
and tender affection, to that end, that when hee is ripe in yeeres hee should proue like <hi>Absalon,</hi> a stubborne and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient childe, but rather to be like our Sauiour CHRIST, who was obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his Father and Mother in all things, that so he may be a ioy vnto his Father, and make glad the heart of his Mother.</p>
   <p>And howsoeuer <hi>Alexander</hi> the great propoundeth it as a great question, whether a man be more beholding to his Father which begetteth him, or to his Master which teacheth him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the one is occasion of his being, the other of his well-being: yet the Lawes of God and Nature tell vs that all reuerent respect, &amp; dutifull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is to be caried to our Father which begat vs, &amp; to our Mother which bare vs: almighty God hauing promised in the fift Commandement a special bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of long life vpon earth to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient childe. Wherefore as when the Grecians in a great solemnitie did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedon</hi> many goodly gifts; a poore Painter stepped in
<pb facs="3"/>
among the rest, and offred vp the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit of himselfe in a Table, besides which, were purtrayed out many Iewels, and Pearles, &amp; Rings, ouer each where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was inscribed, <hi>Vellem &amp; hoc:</hi> I would I were able to giue such gifts as these. Euen so my selfe, hauing at this time occasion, by importunitie of friends, to expose these my simple labours of that poore Talent wherewith God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued mee, to the worlds view (<hi>vtinam foeliciter,</hi> God giue it good successe) haue thought it my duetie to present vnto your selfe (most deare Mother) these my first, though vnworthy endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, vnfainedly protesting, that if there be any thing wherein I may shew my obedience, and bring comfort to your olde age, <hi>Vellem &amp; hoc,</hi> I desire of God that I may performe it. In the meane time let me entreate this fauour at your hands, that as <hi>Lewis</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth King of <hi>France,</hi> presented with a great roote by one of his poore subiects, perceiuing that it came from an hearty affection, tooke it in good part, and loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it vp in his Treasurie among his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chest
<pb facs="4"/>
Iewels: so let mee beseech you to accept this simple present, as an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward testimonie of my true hearty loue, and Filiall reuerence to you, my most louing and naturall Mother, and so I humbly take my leaue; earnestly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating Almighty God to giue you in this life peace of conscience, which is a continuall feast; and at the houre of your death to bring your gray haires with ioy vnto the graue; and after this miserable life is ended, to giue you peace of soule and body for euermore, in his blessed Kingdome of Heauen: which God the Father graunt for his Sonne Iesus Christ his sake. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your dutifull and obedient Sonne <hi>vnto his power,</hi> FRANCIS ROGERS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>