<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112717_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09920</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20180.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112717</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Prepositas his practise : a vvorke very necessary to be vsed for the better preseruation of the health of man. Wherein are not onely most excellent and approued medicines, receiptes, and ointmentes of great vertue, but also most pretious waters, against many infirmities of the body. The way how to make euery the said seuerall medicines, receiptes, and ointmentes. With a table for the ready finding out of euery the diseases, and the remedies for the same. Translated out of Latin into English by L.M</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 111, 17 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere hast thou (gentle reader) a booke for thy profit, such as in English I know not the like, for hearein maist thou readily finde medicines for sundry diseases, and how thy selfe maist make the same, or cause them to be made: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so thou maist here learne to know the vertue and operation, aswell of diuers hearbes with their seedes and fruites, as also of gummes, spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other Apothecaries stuffe, and how thou maist apply them for thy helpe, either outwardly or inwardely. But as nothing can be of euerie man well liked: for such a confused<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is there of opinions, that rightly it may be said: <hi>Quot homines, tot sententia:</hi> and men in viewing of other mens bookes doe for the most part iudge partially, or els enuiously. <hi>Homere</hi> found a cauelling
<hi>Zoilus, Cicero</hi> and <hi>Virgil</hi> wanted not such as found fault with their workes, though most excellent: much lesse may I looke to haue this booke spared of all busie bodies, and that it should passe without gainsay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Some peraduenture will obiect that it is preiudiciall vnto phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Apothecaries, and such other, that such manner bookes as this should be diuulged in the English tongue, and that the secretes of phisicke ought not to bee participated vnto the common sorte, but onely knowne of such as be professors of the arte. Hereto may be answered; that as to preferre the insatiable gaine of a few, before the commoditie of the whole publike weale, were a thing against na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture most iniurious and odious; so for to pleasure a few men, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue all other of such a benefit as concerne their health; yea, and their life also, for want of knowledge whereof many doe perish day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, were not onely great inhumanitie, but most opposite and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to that which God in his law hath enioyned vs vnder paine of damnation; that is, <hi>Loue thy neighbour as thy selfe:</hi> and in deede ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the heathen gaue to be obserued in generall, this, <hi>Doe vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as thou wouldest be done vnto.</hi> Neither can the learned phisitions (as I suppose) be hindred hereby: for as a man that hath attained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some insight and vse of learning, in what arte soeuer, is carried with more delight and willing cheare to seeke for to get some more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection therein, then he was when first he begun rudely, and hauing <pb facs="3"/>no perseuerance in the saide arte: so, no doubt, when men or women shall, hauing read this booke, see and vnderstand how that there are in hearbes, plants, gummes &amp;c. such seuerall vertues, and that of them diuers so wholesome conserues, confections, sirops and other like may be made, which they haue vtterly beene ignorant of vntill now, they will be the better perswaded to like and esteeme of phisicke then here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they haue done, and more readie to seeke helpe and counsell of the learned phisition, without whose aduise, if the vnlearned would in difficult matters take vpon them to deale as phisitions, they might in stead of helping the diseased, doe him much hurt. Hardly can the vnlearned in phisicke iudge rightly of his owne disease, much lesse of the diuers diseases of others: Onely for some diseases ordinarily knowne, for which some are not able, and some dare not to seeke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie at the phisition, no reason is that such yet should be vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred of that ordinarie helpe which God hath appointed. And if the learned in times past had beene so straitely bent to keepe hidden their knowledge from participating to others, or rather so enuious of other mens weale, as many now a dayes are iniurious, not in hiding their owne skill, but in seeking to bereaue men of the fruition of that good benefit of health, concerning which, sundry learned men haue giuen generally to be published; farre to seeke had all men now beene of that perfection that they are come vnto. But, for that I hope the wise and learned will gainesay nothing that is beneficiall to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale; nor esteeme such a benefit, vnto them a preiudise, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a pleasure: I not waighing the vnsauerie speeches and contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of carping cauellers, will leaue to commend those thinges which being tryed shall sufficiently praise them selues.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Vale.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>