<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112743_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17696</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4440</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112743</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons of Maister Iohn Caluin, on the historie of Melchisedech : Wherein is also handled, Abrahams courage in rescuing his nephew Lot: and his Godlines in paying tithes to Melchisedech. Also, Abrahams faith, in belieuing God: comprehending foure sermons. And, Abrahams obedience, in offering his sonne Isaack; in three sermons. Translated out of French, by Thomas Stocker, Gent</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 311, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou shalt receiue here (Christiā Reader) these fewe Sermons of Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Iohn Caluin, for thy benefit, if thou wilt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently read them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a preiudicate mind. Where, in the first three, thou shalt finde how A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram deliuered his nephew Lot from the hands of those which had taken him prisoner, and wherein also is handled who they are that ought to take warre in hand, and how farre they ought to proceed therein. In the next foure is handled the doctrine of iustification and saluation, by Faith onely: whereby such as are ledde away by a false opinion of their good workes and frree will, may greatly profit themselues, and lay fast hold vpon Iesus Christ alone, for their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes and sanctfication, knowing how greatly these two graces must bee distingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shed and not
<pb facs="4"/>confused, and that although they bee neuer so closely tied and linked togither, yet whosoeuer he is that will be said to be reputed to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and acceptable before God, by the benefit of his onely beloued sonne, and in the meane while haue no care nor conscience, ne yet will shew any signe and token of the amendment of his life, and liue in an holy conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rsation, that man I say must needs diuide them, and cut in sunder the inseperable bond of them, &amp; as much as in him lieth, striueth to dismember Iesus Christ, who by his righteousnes, hauing made vs good trees, doth also sanctifie vs, to cause vs beare &amp; bring forth good fruit. In the last three, there is hādled Abrahās obedience in the sacrificing of his son I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sahac, which was a wōderfull trial, so that in this thou maist see that Abraham who is by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God named the father of the faithfull, was all the course of his life maruellously tried. And therfore as many as will be indeed the children of faithful Abraham, must walke in his steppes and abide many hard trials all their life long, except it shall please the Lord in great mercy to forbeare them. Let vs therfore beseech the Lord of all mercy, in the name of this great mediator, by whom alone we haue accesse vnto the throne
<pb facs="4"/>of grace, daily to purge vs more and more, to the end, that by his holie spirit we may bring foorth more and better fruit, then we haue yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore dene, that it may all serue for his glory, and the edification of his whole Church.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>