<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❀To the Right Honorable Sir VValter Myldmay Knight one of the Queenes Maiesties moste honourable Priuie Counsaile.</title>
           <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112802_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18880</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112802</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❀To the Right Honorable Sir VValter Myldmay Knight one of the Queenes Maiesties moste honourable Priuie Counsaile.</title>
                 <author>Newton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of Marcus Tullius Cicero entituled Paradoxa Stoicorum : Contayninge a precise discourse of diuers poinctes and conclusions of vertue and phylosophie according the traditions and opinions of those philosophers, whiche were called Stoikes. Wherunto is also annexed a philosophicall treatyse of the same authoure called Scipio hys dreame. Anno. 1569</title>
                 <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❀To the Right Honorable Sir VValter Myldmay Knight one of the Queenes Maiesties moste honourable Priuie Counsaile.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Escenninus Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> (right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble being newly elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Empire of Rome, so litle cared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or prayse and gratulacion, that on a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ime, a certaine learned man, hauing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is prayse and commendacion penned a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olemne Oracion and offering himselfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ecite y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> same before him in a great As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ēblie: he halfe displeased with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>houre for employing his studie to such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vaine purpose, reproued him with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>retie and wise quippe saying: Good fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lowe, I would haue had better opinion in thee, if thou haddest writen the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="3"/>
actes either of <hi>Marius</hi> or of <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> or els of some other noble and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaunt Captaine that is dead, whose pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wesse and magnanymitie we might fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and set before our eyes as paternes to imitate. For so long as we be aliue, we had more neede to be taughte, howe to rule oure Dominions and to discharge our duties with iustice and equitie, that we may be thought worthy y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment vnto vs alotted, then with pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gloses of flattering termes to beex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolled aboue the condition of a humain creature, Doing vs thereby to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande that the vsuall fashion of praysinge Princes and Magistrates to their faces, may rather betaken for a plaine mockerie, then for any syncere affection sithence at their handes, hope of preferment is expected, feare of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure if they shoulde do otherwise,
<pb facs="3"/>
losse of life, proscription of goods with such like, debated and pondered in that heathen Breast, not swaruinge in that poinct from diuers textes of the sacred scripture, the infallible Touchstone of al truth and Christianitie: affirminge aswel the displeasure of the prince to be death, as also the festuringe Canker of feigned flaterie to be most contagious. Nothing is sopestiferous to Princes and maiestrats as to listen and geue eare to the fauning flatterie of Cosening clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backes, and the ranke rable of pieuish parasites, whose nature (hunting after lucre and Bellichere) is vnder the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefect visure of their sugred spech and diabolical dissimulacion to feede the hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mour of those, whō it hath pleased god and good fortune to decorat with world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dignitie and tēporal regiment, aboue the commune sort of other people. The
<pb facs="4"/>
hurt that therof ariseth, is by infinite examples more apparaunt then that it needeth here to be declared. This cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth me (Right Honorable) to leaue y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> large campe of deserued praise, iustlie due vnto your Honoure for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and singuler vertues of approued wisedome and exquisite learning, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughinge within the sanctuarie of your noble minde, to others that shall hereafter with more dexteritie blaze abroad and display the same to posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. Onely my humble sute and request is vnto your Honoure, that you would vouchsafe to accept the first fructes of this my simple trauaile into your patro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nage, the worke of a mā lōg since dead, vowed and due vnto none so fitte as to you, who haue bene a serious studient of <hi>Tullian</hi> eloquence, and a diligent peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser of all his works, and that vnder the
<pb facs="4"/>
safeconducte of your worthie name it may haue freer passage into the hands of manye. VVhich although it be not so exactly don, that it may seme to smel of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> or <hi>Cleanthes</hi> his Cādle, nor euerye iote and syllable to be preciselye waighed in Critolaus his Balaunce, yet I truste the sense of the Authoris in no place altered, nor my Translatiō in any point to swerue from the office of a faithful Interpretoure. Finallye that it may please you to waighe the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my goodwil, more then th, value of this my Scolasticall exercisee by the example of our sauiour Christ, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the two mytes, which a pore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man offered in the Temple in as good part as the great gifts and oblations of the wealthie: calling further to your re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membraunce that God at the buildings of his Tabernacle, accepted aswell such
<pb facs="5"/>
as to the erection and beautifiinge ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of brought stuffe of small importaunce and accompt as Brasse, yron, Goates heare, candlestickes, oyle and such like, as he did those that brought costlier &amp; more precious ware as Gold, siluer, pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, Scarlet, Bysse, pearles, precious sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and odoriferous perfumes. VVhich labour of mine if I may vnderstande to be not altogether misliked of you, I wil thinke not only my trauaile well bèsto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, but also much encouraged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede in workes of greater volume and paine, already begonne and in part per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fourmed byme, if my glassie health may be at any reasonable truce with his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerous maladies and continuall Atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies. Frō which and al other infirmities I beseech Allmighty God long to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue you, to the common vtility of this Realme, and after youre pilgrimage
<pb facs="5"/>
here ended, make you Coheire with his sonne Christ in his glorious Hierarchie </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Greenwich <date>the Kalendes of Iune. <hi>1569.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Youre honours most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to commaund Thomas Newton</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>