<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE ANCIENT, WOORTHY, AND RIGHT Worshipfull Company of the Gold-Smiths; the Maister, Wardens, Assistants, Liuery: and likewise to euery louing Bro∣ther, and member thereof.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112963_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07894</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18263</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112963</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE ANCIENT, WOORTHY, AND RIGHT Worshipfull Company of the Gold-Smiths; the Maister, Wardens, Assistants, Liuery: and likewise to euery louing Bro∣ther, and member thereof.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe chronicle, of the successe of times, from the creation of the world, to this instant· : Containing, the originall &amp; liues of our ancient fore-fathers, before and after the Floude, as also, of all the monarchs, emperours, kinges, popes, kingdomes, common-weales, estates and gouernments, in most nations of this worlde: and how in alteration, or succession, they haue continued to this day</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 189, 192-613, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_guild">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE ANCIENT, WOORTHY, AND RIGHT Worshipfull Company of the Gold-Smiths; the Maister, Wardens, Assistants, Liuery: and likewise to euery louing Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and member thereof.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et me not be thought (Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Society) more bolde then becomes me, that in search of Antiquitie, and Successe of Times, guided by good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation, and probable Authorities, I thus present you (in vnfaigned affection) what I haue gathered, concerning your worthy Brother-hood. If I had time heere to set downe (without preiudice to any other Misterie whatsoeuer) that which <hi>Holye Writ</hi> recordeth of you, and of men (then) most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in your profession; this poore Epistle would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease it selfe to a very large discourse, and exceede the limit wherto I haue tied my self in the whol labor. I passe ouer the captiuity of Gods chosen people in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and the Offices of those three especiall chosen
<pb facs="10"/>
men, <hi>Zerubbabell, Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi>: the first, being their Captaine to guide them home, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Temple was builded: the second, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming manners, and making a plantation of Religion: the third and last, to builde vp the wals, and make a new Citty of Ierusalem againe: Yet let me tell you, that among the multitude of Officers and Offices, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to this businesse, for building the walles, the Merchants and Goldsmithes do beare a remarkeable note, the very words in Scripture being these: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Chamber of the Corner vnto the Sheepe-gate, fortifyed the Gold smiths and the Merchants.</hi> Beside, that which is spoken of <hi>Malchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h</hi> the Goldsmithes sonne, fortifying to the house of the <hi>Nethinims;</hi> And then, of <hi>Bezaleell the Sonne of Vri, filled with the Spirit of God, in wisedome and vnderstanding, to worke in Gold, Siluer, &amp; Brasse;</hi> who had <hi>Aholiab</hi> ioyned with him, to make all curious workes (appointed by God himselfe) for the <hi>Tabernacle of the Congregation, the Arke of the Couenant, and the Mercy-seat, &amp;c.</hi> If these be not Testimonies of extraordinary honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, in the very names of <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Golde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths</hi> (but much more, in the matter of so high an employment) confirmed by an assurance so vnreproue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and equalling what can be saide (in like case) of venerable Antiquitie; I referre my selfe to be censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the very seuerest iudgement.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>Secondly, concerning the first workers in Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and other Mettalles, in any place of eminence or note in Europe (vnder controul neuerthelesse, of such as haue reade and obserued more then I haue done) I finde their Originall to be among the euer-curious &amp; ingenious <hi>Veni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ians,</hi> euen at the first plantation of Venice, which iustly may be tearmed <hi>Miracolo del Mondo.</hi> The foundation of Venice, holds paritie and proportion of Antiquity, with the prime estate of the <hi>Francs or French,</hi> as you may obserue where it is more at large expressed. Looking backe then to the first Note of Diuine obseruation, and remembering (after the worlds deuision among the sons of <hi>Noah</hi>) that <hi>Iaphets</hi> son <hi>Tubal</hi> had all Europe for his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with this last Collestion concerning Venice; and then, as all Arts and Sciences haue a place of Original, as Riuers from the Sea, and extend themselues after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the remotest places of the worlde: So may it likewise be gathered, that those respectiue times, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myring and honouring Art and Inuention, gaue such way to their present, and succeeding fame &amp; passage, that all Landes became Partners of their predecessors prerogatiues.</p>
   <p>Lastly, to speake but of our owne Kingdome, and therein (for breuities sake) but of this Noble Citty it self; I find, that when it had cast off the yoke of strange confusion, endured vnder the sufferance of so manie conquerings: After (I say) it came to haue command
<pb facs="11"/>
within it selfe, vnder the awe and gracious fauour of worthie Kinges and Potentates, who made choyse of Magistrates, to be their Deputies, and to present their God-like persons for general obedience: the very first man that attained to the place of eminence, and was styled Maire of this renowned Citty, was called <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fitz-Alwine, Fitz-Liefstane,</hi> Goldsmith, and held that supreame Office more then <hi>24.</hi> yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A memorable Note, in regard of Priority, and as since then, carefully remembred, so iustly challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging continuance to vtmost posterity.</p>
   <p>But because this slender volume speakes more, (though briefely) of you, then heere can wel be affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and commeth to you from a free hart, in kindnes, requiring but as free and courteous acceptance: this is al the charge by me imposed on it. To tel the whole Golden band of your worthy Brother-hood, that I haue done nothing heerein, either for flatterie or vaineglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or in expectation of mercinarie recompence; but according to truth, sincerity, and honesty which is the best defence for any that speakes of Antiquitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours to be commanded,</hi> A. Mundy.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>