<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OF THE POEMS of his Friend.</title>
           <author>H., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112789_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07542</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OF THE POEMS of his Friend.</title>
                 <author>H., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Poems occasioned by a melancholy vision or A melancholy vision vpon diuers theames enlarged : which by seuerall arguments ensuinge is showed ByH. Mill</title>
                 <author>Mill, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blaiklock (Blacklock), Lawrence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>272 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>OF THE POEMS of his Friend.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>I <hi>Read those lines, in them a worth I spi'd,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>I turn'd them back, and found this empty side?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To praise the worth, I had a minde unto it,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>'T will praise it selfe, what need I then to doe it?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>I tooke my pen, no longer did contest,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To try my skill, my love will prove the best:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The lines are usefull, sweet, and full of matter,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Composing words which men at randome slatter.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They are like darts to those that live in sinne,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They leave all speechlesse, that have shamelesse bin?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And sinne it selfe, is followed with such strength,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With all his power, he's overcome at length.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To all that loue truth, cordials, comforts sweet</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They doe convay, to all directions meet.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Plaine things are rais'd, the loftie levell made,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Things lasting priz'd, those slighted that doe fade,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>In pleasing tearmes, not strange, nor yet too low,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They beare a grace, yet such that all may know.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>
And if this be thy Musestuning strings,</l>
      <l>How sweet wil't be, when she both tunes and sings?</l>
      <l>Goe now with praise, feare not to finde successe,</l>
      <l>Whats here's thine own, thou hast not rob'd the press.</l>
      <l>Had I but hope, that I so well could doe,</l>
      <l>I'd wish, that I were melancholy too.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>P. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>