<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right woorship∣full maister Thomas Meade, one of the Queenes Maisties Iustices of her common Plees at Westminster, Ihon Hedlambe wisheth long life, with the increase of god∣linesse and felicitie.</title>
           <author>Lambe, John Hed</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112579_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02881</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13020</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112579</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right woorship∣full maister Thomas Meade, one of the Queenes Maisties Iustices of her common Plees at Westminster, Ihon Hedlambe wisheth long life, with the increase of god∣linesse and felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Lambe, John Hed</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the whole eight chapiter to the Romaines, expounded by Ihon Hedlambe, preacher and minister to the congregation at Braughin, and student of Diuinitie in Peterhouse at Cambridge, before Maister Doctour Squire, and the whole ministerie assembled at the laste synode, holden at Ware in Lent laste past 1579. Wherein is perfectly proued our iustification to bee by faithe onely, to the beatyng doune and ouerthrowyng of all erronious and false opinions to the contrarie. Seen and allowed</title>
                 <author>Hedlambe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walley (Waley), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right woorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> maister Thomas Meade, one of the Queenes Maisties Iustices of her common Plees at Westminster, Ihon Hedlambe <hi>wisheth long life, <hi>with the increase of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse and felicitie.</hi>
      </hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie order of that man of God: the right worship full &amp; our godlie Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon maister Doctor Squier, maie be knowē vnto your worshipp, for whō I with the reste of my brethren, and fellowe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Churche of God are to giue GOD moste hartie thankes, for that it pleased GOD to sende suche a faithfull distributer of his woorde to raigne ouer vs. Who bothe with godly zeale setteth forthe the truthe, and also with greate mildnesse encourageth vs to goe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the same: It was his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surs to appointe me, though moste vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie,
<pb facs="3"/>
at his laste Sinode at Ware, to open as GOD would blesse me, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte me at that tyme vnto my fellowe Ministers those notes, which according to my small capacitie, I had collected v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the viij. Chapiter to the Romaines, after whiche my rude discourse beeyng ended, he did so comfort me to go fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as was greatly to my ioye and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation in the Lorde: wherefore as du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie bindeth me, praiyng the Lorde long to cōtinue this our churche of England with hym, and many suche faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters to God his glorie, and their and, our greate comfortes, not beyng able to speake that he deserueth, neither to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that in hym, whiche my harte doeth conceiue, I referre it to your worship &amp; others, godlie and learned. Wherefore now returnyng my baise stile to write vnto your worship: as the diuine Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher <hi>Plato</hi> (right worshipful) did oftē tymes giue thankes to the Angell of his birthe for three thinges: first that he was a man, and not a beast: Secondly, that he
<pb facs="3"/>
was a Grecian, &amp; not a barbarian: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he was borne in the daies of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> whiche rhankfulnesse that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philosopher, euen to that God he knewe not, and that for worldly &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitorie thinges, hath pricked me forward (though not forgetfull, yet vnable to fulfill any part of my dueties) to be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely thankfull to the Father of mercie, &amp; God of all power, whom I truly knowe through Christe Iesus, for that he hath created me like vnto hymself, sinne one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted, &amp; hath not onely brought me to the pleasant spryng of the hie He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon, but also hath sent me suche a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas, who as he is able, so is he willyng to further those my studies and labours, wherunto God hath called me. And se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng (right worshipfull) that you are that fauorer of my labours in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, for whom I am not onely to pray to God, but also through his assistaunce in and by my self, to shewe some effectes and tokens, of my thankfull mynde and knowleging bothe with what loue you
<pb facs="4"/>
embrace the truthe of God his woorde: and what fauour you beare to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the same, as also what delight you take in reading of the same, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xyng the studies therof, with other your labours professed: I haue here sent vnto your worshippe a breef discourse of the whole viij. Chapiter to the Romaines, whiche although I haue neither so well pollished, drawen suche lineamētes, nor added such coulers as other both could and would haue dooen, if thei had been appointed to haue spoken in that place. Yet as GOD at that tyme did giue me grace and vtteraunce, and for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of that Spirite whiche he lent me, I did breefly bothe in deuidyng and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding, so labour, as the shortnesse of tyme wherein I had warnyng, and was to speake permitted me: whiche my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours if thei be accepted and approued by your worship, I trust I shall (God his grace assistyng me) take suche like or greater paines, in some other place of Scripture, to the building vp of the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="4"/>
of the decaied Hierusalem, and to the beatyng doune of the kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, bothe in other, and also in my self. Thus desiryng the God of mercie, who raised againe frō death, the great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of his flocke, euen Iesus Christe the righteous, alwaies to preserue and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere your worship and yours, bothe to his Churche, and also to this our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthe. Thus with due remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of my bounden dueties, I cease to trouble your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe: from Braughin this xxj. of Maie. 1579.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worshipps moste bounden in the Lorde, duryng life Ihon Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lambe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>