<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANS∣LATOR TO THE CHRISTIAN AND IN∣different reader, Grace, mer∣cie and peace.</title>
           <author>A., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112323_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15511</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112323</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANS∣LATOR TO THE CHRISTIAN AND IN∣different reader, Grace, mer∣cie and peace.</title>
                 <author>A., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutation of the Popish transubstantiation : Together with a narration, how that the masse was at sundrie times patched and peeced by sundrie Popes. Wherein is contained a briefe summe of the reasons and arguments which those render, that will not receiue the masse. Translated out of French into English by Peter Allibond minister of the word of God</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 21 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATOR TO THE CHRISTIAN AND IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different reader, Grace, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast in this little Treatise (gentle Reader) these two things deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto thee.</p>
   <p n="1">1 First, here is shewed that howsoeuer our aduersaries, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes, doo for the maintenance and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of their abhominable Masse, pretend antiquitie, &amp; long continuance of time: that yet the Masse was at sundry times collected, and patched vp by diuers Popes: some adding one thing, some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding another, as they thought good in their foolish imaginations. Wherein
<pb facs="3"/>they deale with vs as the Gibeonites did with <hi>Ioshua,</hi> who for to saue their liues, sayned themselues to be ambassadors,<note place="margin">Ios. 9.4.6.</note> &amp; that they came from farre, craftely brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with them old shooes, old sacks, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie bread, &amp;c. desiring <hi>Ioshua</hi> therfore to make a league with them. Into whose dealings if <hi>Ioshua</hi> had looked through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he should haue found them to haue bin but counterfets, and dissemblers. So not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that the Papists vaunt &amp; fay, that their doctrine, and their positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come from far, and are (as they say) of great standing and antiquitie: yet if we looke throughly into the matter, and examine all things by the touchstone of the word of God, which is the tryall of all trueth, we shall finde their Popish Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be vntrueths, new vpstarts, and counterfets.</p>
   <p>They further obiect vnto vs, that we depart from the Church, and haue (as they say) a new innouated doctrine. True
<pb facs="3"/>it is that wee are departed from them, as <hi>Moses</hi> departed from Egypt, because they are departed from God &amp; his truth. And for the newnesse of our doctrine (as it pleaseth them to terme it) it is euident that our doctrine and religion, both in the whole, and in the particulars therof, hath the warrant, and antiquitie of the holy Scriptures. <hi>Abrahams</hi> seruantes digged welles for their masters cattel: as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Philisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans stopped them:<note place="margin">Ge. 26.16.16</note> the seruants of <hi>Isaac</hi> did afterwards dig them anewe, so that the welles might in some sort be sayde to be new, because they were newly digged: So our religion, with some may be thoght to be new, not that it is so, but because that it was of long time stopped and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Popish Phylistians, and is now (the Lorde bee praysed for it) discouered and found out, by the holy and faithfull seruants of the Lord. For it is one thing to say that a thing is new, because it was
<pb facs="4"/>neuer in <hi>Esse</hi> before, and it is another thing to terme a thing new, because it is newly repaired. And thus (good Reader) thou seest how our aduersarie may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered in his obiection.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Nowe for the other parte of this Treatise, there is conteined in it a strong confutation of Transubstantiatiō: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Author (who both for his name &amp; person is vnknowen vnto me) vseth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry sufficient and forcible arguments, to confute their opinion, so that I need not to speake much of that, and yet somwhat I will be bold to ad: namely, that if their assertion for the reall presence bee true, then there will this absurditie ensue, to witte, that Christ at his laste supper had two bodies. For if (as our aduersaries say) that the bread was his body, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and playne, that he sitting with his Disciples, and performing the parts of a naturall man, by his speech, gesture, and eating, had a humane body: so that if
<pb facs="4"/>they affirme the former (which they can neuer proue) we dare auer &amp; iustifie the latter. This is one of our aduersaries shifts, that if any obiect vnto them, that it standes not with a humane body to be in diuers places at one and the selfsame time, they answere it and say; that this is done myraculously, by meanes of Christs glorification: but then what will they say vnto this obiection; for the bread in his last supper: for eyther they must confesse that the bread was not his body, or els that a body not glorified may bee in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places, at one and the selfsame time, for this was done before his glorification, resurrection, or death. There was euer betwixt Christ and vs this difference,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> to wit, that he euer was without sin. There is now further since his ascention, this dissimilitude, namely, hys glorification: and yet it is neither that that hee hath not, which we haue, namely sin: nor that that he hath, which we haue not (though
<pb facs="5"/>by fayth we be fully assured of it) namely, glorification, that doo take from him the true parts of a naturall body, and of hys humane nature. The women, namely, <hi>Marie Magdalen, Ioanna, Mary</hi> the mother of <hi>Iames,</hi> and others, comming vnto the sepulchre of our Sauiour, and to bestow their odors vpon him, &amp; to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balme him, it was sayd vnto them by the two men standing by thē in shining ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, <hi>Why seek yee him that liueth among the dead? he is not here, but is risen.</hi> And so much more may it bee sayd to our aduersaryes, why seeke ye him really in the bread?<note place="margin">Luk. 24.5, 6.</note> he is ascended, he is not there. S. <hi>Iames</hi> saith, <hi>Ye aske and receiue not,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.3.</note> because ye aske amisse:</hi> And so the poore papists seek &amp; find not, because they seek amisse: For it is plainly sayd that the heauens must conteyn hym vntil the time that al things be restored which is to be vnderstoode,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 8.27. Act. 3.21.</note> not of hys di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature (which the heauen of heauēs
<pb facs="5"/>cannot conteyn) but of his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And to conteyn in one place, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in heauen, and to be in many places in earth, are contraries: therfore that place in the 3. of the Acts, being vnderstood of Christs body, as it must needs be, wil not permit any reall presence.</p>
   <p>And thus much for the sum of the booke, which is very short and small, and therfore I must frame the boulk of mine Epistle, answerable vnto the quantity of the Treatise, lest the worke should be like vnto an Owle, more head than body: or for feare lest the porch should bee bygger than the Church. I haue bin the more bold and willing at this time, to take frō this Treatise the veyle of an vnknowen tongue, &amp; to publish it, both because at this time the Papists are very rife &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, with their seducing Seminaries and Iesuites, to delude and deceyue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with theyr Masses &amp; tromperyes:
<pb facs="6"/>and also to manyfeste vnto others the fondnesse of their opinions: that so men may looke vpon them, as vpon rockes, to auoyde them.</p>
   <p>And thus (Gentle Reader) I request thee to take in good part this my poor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, hartely wishing that God might be glorified, and that thou mightst receiue instruction and profit by it, which is the thing I aymed at, so I craue it for my labour, and paynes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord P. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>