<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader, if indifferent.</title>
           <author>N., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112729_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16273</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3191</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112729</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader, if indifferent.</title>
                 <author>N., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands Helicon : Casta placent superis, pura cum veste venite, et manibus puris sumite fontis aquam</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Flasket, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>200 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader, if indifferent.</head>
   <p>MAny honoured names haue heretofore (in their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer
interest,) patronized some part of these inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
many here be, that onely these Collections haue
brought to light, &amp; not inferiour (in the best opinions) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
before published. The trauaile that hath beene taken in
gathering them from so many handes, hath wearied some
howres, which seuered, might in part haue perished, dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
into this meane volume, may in the opinion of some not
be altogether vnworthy the labour. If any man hath beene
defrauded of any thing by him composed, by another mans
title put to the same, hee hath this benefit by this collection,
freely to challenge his owne in publique, where els he might
be robd of his proper due. No one thing beeing here placed
by the Collector of the same vnder any mans name, eyther at
large, or in letters, but as it was deliuered by some especiall
coppy comming to his handes. No one man, that shall take
offence that his name is published to any inuention of his,
but he shall within the reading of a leafe or two, meete with
another in reputation euery way equal with himselfe, whose
name hath beene before printed to his Poeme, which nowe
taken away were more then theft: which may satisfie him
that would faine seeme curious or be intreated for his fame.</p>
   <p>Nowe, if any Stationer shall finde faulte, that his Coppies
are robd by any thing in this Collection, let me aske him this
question, VVhy more in this, then in any Diuine or humaine
Authour: From whence a man (writing of that argument)
shal gather any saying, sentence, similie, or example, his name
put to it who is the Authour of the same. This is the simplest
<pb facs="4"/>
of many reasons that I could vrdge, though perhaps the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest
his capacitie, but that I would be loth to trouble my selfe,
to satisfie him. Further, if any man whatsoeuer, in prizing of
his owne birth or fortune, shall take in scorne, that a far mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
man in the eye of the world, shal be placed by him: I tell
him plainly whatsoeuer so excepting, that, that mans wit is
set by his, not that man by him. In which degree, the names
of Poets (all feare and dutie ascribed to her great and sacred
Name) haue beene placed with the names of the greatest
Princes of the world, by the most autentique and worthiest
iudgements, without disparagement to their soueraigne ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles:
which if any man taking exception thereat, in ignorance
know not, I hold him vnworthy to be placed by the meanest
that is but graced with the title of a Poet. Thus gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
I wish thee all happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>L. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>