<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112564_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02792</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12923</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112564</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The solace for the souldier and saylour : contayning a discourse and apologie out of the heauenly word of God, how we are to allow, and what we are to esteeme of the valiant attempts of those noblemen and gentlemen of England, which incurre so many daungers on the seas, t cut off or abridge the proude and haughtie power of Spayne. By Simon Harward</title>
                 <author>Harward, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wight, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The preface to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are three causes (good Christian Reader) which haue prouoked &amp; drawne mee to the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of this rude &amp; slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pamphlet. The first, for that I haue been thereunto requested, by certaine godly and valiant Captaines and Ship-masters, with whom being on the spanish seas, vnder the conduct of the most noble Earle of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> that they might with better confidence call vpon God, I laboured sundrie times, as well by priuate conference, as also in my publick Sermons so often and so farre forth as my text would giue mee occasion. The second, for that sithence my returne home I haue heard sometimes of the obloquies and reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="4"/>
speeches of many, which haue not stickt to affirme, that these my voyages vpon the seas haue beene some blot and discredite to the doctrine which is or shall by me bee deliuered vpon the land. And thirdly, for that England hath (I doubt) many sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous malcontents, which being wearie of their own welfare, doe repine against those meanes whereby our prosperitie is preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as may plainely appeare, as well by their vnnatural refusing to help their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, who had rather waste great summes in vngodlie suites of lawe, then to yeelde one mite towards the maintenance of the soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier and the publike affaires of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth; as also by their vnthankefull murmurings &amp; vnkinde grudgings, which cannot affoord a good word to them that willingly vndergoe so many deadly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers abroad, to procure thē peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnesse at home: for the satisfying of all which parties, I haue here taken in hand, by the infallible word of the eternall God, to discusse and examine that argument now so much in question, which howsoeuer at
<pb facs="4"/>
the first it will seeme strange, and as it were a paradox in diuinitie, yet being read with indifferent iudgement, I hope it shall in some part resolue and remoue the scruples and doubts in the hearts of the weake, if not stop the mouthes of the wilfull and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate. And thus least perhappes, percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing too large a preface to so compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a treatise, as the Cynick Philosopher sawe a wide and stately paire of gates to a poore and beggerlie Citie, thou shouldst begin to crie with him, <hi>viri Myndij claudite portas,</hi> I briefely end, referring thee to that which followeth, which as I haue penned for thy benefit, to encourage &amp; cheere vp those which must bee ready alwaies to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger themselues for thee and thine, so I wish thee to reade it with as friendly and welwilling affection. <hi>Jdib. Oct. Anno. 1592.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord</hi> Simon Harward.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>