<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MOST EXCELLENTEST of all Ladies, FRANCES, Countesse Dowager of Exceter.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112049_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06913</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17343</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112049</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MOST EXCELLENTEST of all Ladies, FRANCES, Countesse Dowager of Exceter.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Countrey contentments, or The English husvvife : Containing the inward and outward vertues which ought to be in a compleate woman. As her skill in physicke, surgerie, extraction of oyles, banqueting-stuffe, ordering of great feasts, preseruing of all sorts of wines, conceited secrets, distillations, perfumes, ordering of wooll, hempe, flax, making cloth, dying, the knowledge of dayries, office of malting, oats, their excellent vses in a family, brewing, baking, and all other things belonging to an houshold. A worke generally approued, and now much augmented, purged and made most profitable and necessarie for all men, and dedicated to the honour of the noble house of Exceter, and the generall good of this kingdome. By G.M</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80, 79-174, 173-133, that is 233, 3 pages, diagrams, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MOST EXCELLENTEST of all Ladies, FRANCES, Countesse Dowager of Exceter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owsoeuer (Right Honourable and most vertuous Ladie) this Booke may come to your Noble Goodnesse clothed in an old Name or Garment, yet doubtlesse (excellent Madam) it is full of many new vertues which will euer admire and serue you; and though it can adde nothing to your owne rare and vnparalleld knowledge, yet may it to those No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good ones (which will endeauour any small sparke of your imitation) bring such a light, as may make them shine with a great deale of charitie. I doe not assume to my selfe (though I am not altogether ignorant in abilitie to iudge of these things) the full inuention and scope of this whole worke: for it is true (great Lady) that much of it was a Manuscript which many yeeres agon belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to an Honourable Contesse, one of the greatest Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Kingdome, and were the opinions of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Physitions which then liued; which being now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued
<pb facs="3"/>
by one not inferiour to any of that Profession, I was the rather imboldned to send it to your blessed hand, knowing you to be a Mistresse so full of Honourable pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and goodnesse, that although this imperfit offer may come vnto you weake and disable, yet your Noble ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue will support it, and make it so strong in the world, that I doubt not but it shall doe seruice to all those which will serue you, whilest my selfe and my poore prayers shall to my last gaspe labour to attend you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The true admirer of your Noble Vertues,GERVASE MARKHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>