<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous and freend∣lie Reader.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112987_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07901</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18272</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112987</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous and freend∣lie Reader.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English Romayne lyfe : Discouering: the liues of the Englishmen at Roome: the orders of the English semiminarie [sic] : the dissention betweene the Englishmen and the VVelshmen: the banishing of the Englishmen out of Roome: the Popes sending for them againe: a reporte of many of the paltrie reliques in Roome: their vautes vnder the grounde: their holy pilgrimages: and a number other matters, worthy to be read and regarded of euery one. There vnto is added, the cruell tiranny, vsed on an English man at Roome, his Christian suffering, and notable martirdome, for the Gospell of Iesus Christe, in anno. 1581. VVritten by A.M. sometime the Popes scholler in the seminarie among them. Seene and allovved</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 75, 1 page, 1 folded leaf of plates, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the courteous and freend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thing long promised (gentle Reader) is now perfourmed at last, and that which my aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thought I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer set forth, to their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe and thy profit, I haue now publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. Thou shalt find a number of matters comprehended within this small volume: some, that will irritate the minde of anie good subiect, and therefore to be read with regard: others, importing the whole course of our Englishmens liues in <hi>Roome,</hi> with the od conceits, and craftie iuglings of the Pope, (whereto our Englishmen are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise conformable) they are in such true &amp; certaine order set downe, as if thou were there thy selfe to behold them. I will not vse manie words, now thou hast it, read ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisedlie, condemne not rashlie, and if thou thinkest mee woorthie anie thanks for my paines, then freendlie bestowe it on me.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in courtesie,</hi> Anthonie Munday.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>