<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ W. B. to the louyng Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1552</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112433_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00402</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10532</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112433</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ W. B. to the louyng Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Wonderfull newes of the death of Paule the. iii. last byshop of Rome : [and] of diuerse thynges that after his death haue happened, wherein is trulye set ... the abominable actes of his most mischeuous life. Written in Latin by. P. Esquillus, and Englyshed by W. B. Londoner</title>
                 <author>Flacius Illyricus, Matthias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Gaultier, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1552</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ W. B. to the louyng Reader.</head>
   <p>IT is wonderfull (good Reader) to see the sundry diuersities of wittes what meanes they inuente to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare &amp; publishe suche thynges as they thinke necessary to be knowē, some vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of fayned histories, some vnder the persons of specheles beastes, and some vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shadow of dreames and visions, of which thou haste here a notable and wurthy example. For some wittie man (as it appeareth by his wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng) priuie of the laste Popes secretes, (whiche are so abhominable as I haue hearde of fewe lyke,) willinge to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the worlde, howe men were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in him, whiche not onely called, but also beleued hym to be more than halfe a god, hath vnder the name of. P. Esquillus writtē an Epistle to his frēd forius. Wherin after that he hath tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="2"/>
declared the time of his death, he fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a poesie in manner of a vision, in which he seeth Paule Frenes. the Pope receyued into hell, and there meteth his sōne Petrus Aloysius, who in talking to his father, setteth forthe his wycked beliefe and doctrine. After that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth Arches and Pinnacles, wherin are graued the mischeuous dedes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pope, as the geuyng of his sister to be abused of one that was Pope before hym, the poysonyng of his mother, and of his sister, because she loued another better than hym, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abusyng of his owne daughter, and his persecuting of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> diuers other thinges. At last folowyng on still. S. Johns reuelaciō, he seeth him abuse princes, &amp; at last, cast with them into a lake of burnyng fyre. All this he fayneth properly, but lyeth not I am afrayed. And nowe somwhat to saye my fansy in the matter, me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the booke is very good and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,
<pb facs="3"/>
&amp; I wold wishe that al christē mē, especially princes, for whose cause prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally it semeth to be written, had red it, that they mighte learne here howe Popes and theyr ministers haue doen and doe abuse them. For I beleue that al whiche is here written of the Popes actes, and of others, be true, &amp; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I knowe no man would haue bē so shamcles so to make reporte, excepte he were assured of them. And to thentēt that all Englishe men myghte thanke God the more for his aboundāt mercy, in deliuering them through knowlege of his truth from the tiranny of so cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and stinking an heade, and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loue and obeye our soueraygne lord and kyng, theyr head by God appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I haue (good Reader) according to my poore cunnyng, Englished Esquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Epistle, that al they maye see there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Popes moste detestable, mische<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, and deuillishe doctrine, lyfe and
<pb facs="3"/>
deedes: that suche as yet for lacke of knowlege fauour hym, maye throughe credyting this, detest and abhorre hym, or at leste wyse his vices, whiche are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separably ioyned vnto the Popedome. Wherfore yf thou (good reader) shalt for this entente reade it, I shall thinke my paynes not onelye well bestowed, but also (as I wishe they maye be) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundātlye requited. Fare well.</p>
   <closer>¶ Loue and lyue.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>