<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christen Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112718_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4462</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christen Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo Godly and notable sermons preached by the excellent and famous clarke, master Iohn Caluyne, in the yere. 1555 : The one concernynge pacience in aduersitie: The other touchyng the most comfortable assurance of oure saluation in Chryste. Iesu. Translated out of Frenche into Englyshe</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christen Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde, sounde, and moste holsome les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, whiche are taughte vs in the heauenly schole of our Sauiour Iesus Chryst, there be none that the holy gost in more ernest wise requyreth vs to learne, or that more maketh for oure comforte here and in the worlde to come, then to haue quietnesse of mynde in aduersytie, and to be assured of eternal saluation in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>su. For<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> (though all trouble for the present tyme be greuous) yet lyke as when we pacyently run the race that is set before vs, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duryng suche correction and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisement as our heauenly father leyeth vpon vs, he then causeth
<pb facs="3"/> the same to turne so much to our profyte, and to bringe vs so qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ete fruite of ryghtuousenes, that we thereby obteyne more of hys holynesse, and become vesselles more apt to serue the glory of his name, and to edifye his churche: Euen so, of all consolations and comfortes, this is most incompa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 2. Tim. 1 Mat. 25</note> that throughe the mooste graciouse purpose of the eternall God, oure euerlastynge saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is so certayne and sure, that it was determyned and decreed by hym in Chryst Iesu his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall sonne, before the foundation of the worlde was leyed.</p>
   <p>Touchynge these two poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: namely, the quiet or pacient sufferynge of trouble in Christes cause. And the assuraunce of our eternall saluation in hym, thou
<pb facs="3"/> hast here (gentle reader) two no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table, godly and comfortable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, made by goddes faythful seruaunt, maister Iohn Caluine euen at such tyme as here in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, the sworde of tyrannye was full of bloudde, and the fyre burnynge hotte. By the whiche worthy sermons, we all be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon: partly to chose rather to suffre aduersitie with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> then to enioy the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of synne for a season: And partely in nothynge to reioyse so muche, as in that our names are wrytten in heauen.<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> As we be taughte by oure sayde soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lorde and master Chryst Iesus, bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for euer ∴ Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>