<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Proeme to the Search, with the occasion of it.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112683_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07541</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17921</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112683</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Proeme to the Search, with the occasion of it.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nights search· : Discovering the nature and condition of all sorts of night-walkers; with their associates. As also, the life and death of many of them. Together with divers fearfull and strange accidents, occasioned by such ill livers. Digested into a poeme by Humphry Mill</title>
                 <author>Mill, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bishop, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blaiklock (Blacklock), Lawrence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 88, 85-283, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <lg>
      <pb facs="26"/>
      <pb n="1" facs="26"/>
      <head>A Proeme to the Search, <hi>with the occasion of it.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>MVse, call thy <hi>Genius</hi> up, and let thy quill</l>
      <l>Prove thee a sharer in the forked hill:</l>
      <l>Trace flowry <hi>Peneus,</hi> taste the silver spring</l>
      <l>Of <hi>Helicon;</hi> scrue up thy treble string:</l>
      <l>Begin with cōcords, discords come apace,</l>
      <l>And then thou maist more freely strike the base.</l>
      <l>Let judgement guard thee, reasons counsell aske;</l>
      <l>Thou hast no common, but a painfull taske</l>
      <l>To undertake; not wanton idle bayes:</l>
      <l>Love-subjects are too thredbare now adayes.</l>
      <l>Nor lustfull Epigrams, nor jesting rime,</l>
      <l>Which might corrupt men, rob them of their time:</l>
      <l>Nor senselesse tales (such trash hath venom in't,</l>
      <l>No reason; but that sools would be in print)</l>
      <l>No, nor the brave exploits of worthy men:</l>
      <l>But worthlesse imps are destin'd for thy pen.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The bawdy rabble, which have bin protected</l>
      <l>By some too oft (and punishment neglected)</l>
      <l>Must be displaid by thee: their menstr'ous blaince</l>
      <l>Launc'd to the quick; their never dying staines</l>
      <l>Laid to the view of men; their private ends,</l>
      <l>And how th'are robd of reason, wit, wealth, friends;</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="2" facs="27"/>How vile they make the times, what things did fall</l>
      <l>Into the hands of fate, what hellish thrall</l>
      <l>Attends upon them; how their shamelesse breath</l>
      <l>At last is suckt into the whirlepoole death.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To those that will returne, and will endure</l>
      <l>Thy cor'sive, and thy lance, apply thy cure:</l>
      <l>Go boldly forth, the Constables will guard thee,</l>
      <l>And if thou dost good service, they'll reward thee.</l>
      <l>The watchmen, with the be adles, will attend thee;</l>
      <l>Aske light, or weapons of them, they will lend thee;</l>
      <l>The Iustices will grace thee in thy cause,</l>
      <l>And give thee warrants from the strongest lawes.</l>
      <l>Prepare thy selfe against tomorrow night,</l>
      <l>And be industrious; know, that candle-light</l>
      <l>May shew thee more than day: for why? the Sun</l>
      <l>Doth make those night-fowles into corners run.</l>
      <l>If any plead for hell, nere favour such;</l>
      <l>They have bin favout'd in the world too much.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Search other countreys too; for there are weeds</l>
      <l>Which harbour serpents, and as hatefull deeds</l>
      <l>As <hi>Brittaine</hi> ever did: lose not thy way,</l>
      <l>Thou mayst be here againe by break of day.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Mus.</hi> My charge is hard, time short for tedious things!</l>
      <l>Thou art a spirit, canst not use thy wings?</l>
      <l>I never was a subject to this sin;</l>
      <l>But now thy search being ready to begin,</l>
      <l>I'll help thee in't: and as a stander by</l>
      <l>May better judge (casting a serious eye)</l>
      <l>Than he that is an actor; so the fame</l>
      <l>Of sinfull crimes helps me to blaze the shame.</l>
      <l>Those that are pincht (perhaps) will fling and kick,</l>
      <l>(The gaull'd backt jade will snuffe) and seek to pick</l>
      <l>A quarrell with thee, and with envie swell;</l>
      <l>Though here they are, their venome came from hell:</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="3" facs="27"/>But answer them at last; none will oppose</l>
      <l>Thee in thy Search, unless't be some of those</l>
      <l>Which thou hast guilty found: and then they will</l>
      <l>Shew to the world that they are far more ill</l>
      <l>Than thou hast shew'd (although they have bin vaine)</l>
      <l>To peach themselves they'll be but fooles in graine.</l>
      <l>I name'em not; what is at randome showne,</l>
      <l>In frenzie fits they'll make it all their owne:</l>
      <l>Were they not guilty, they would be possest</l>
      <l>With gentlenesse, their mindes would be at rest.</l>
      <l>How ere they rage, yet enter thou their roofe,</l>
      <l>Though they resist, they are not vengeance proofe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Prevent the bawd, or she'll have her desire,</l>
      <l>Ere th'watchmen come, she'll draw away the fire,</l>
      <l>And let her harlots downe; such fobs are made</l>
      <l>As master-peeces, which do help their trade.</l>
      <l>Finde out their holes, take but the hearth away,</l>
      <l>There shalt thou finde a hell; the furies play</l>
      <l>There in the dark: being apprehended so,</l>
      <l>Let no man take a bribe to let them go.</l>
      <l>I make no doubt but honest mindes will take</l>
      <l>The sense at best, and good construction make</l>
      <l>Of what is spoke, and meant; and what is weak</l>
      <l>They'll silent passe, of what's of worth they'll speak.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Hearing the cries of husbands for their wives</l>
      <l>Being growne too light (who lov'd them as their lives.)</l>
      <l>Complaints of women, with their grieved moanes,</l>
      <l>Their bitter mourning, with their sighes and groanes</l>
      <l>For their lost husbands; who have bin undone</l>
      <l>With following whores: and how poore children run</l>
      <l>About for succour, how their brinish teares</l>
      <l>Have spoke the parents shame: how free from feares</l>
      <l>Vile strumpets walk abroad, how men like flaves</l>
      <l>Are chain'd, and brought untimely to their graves:</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="4" facs="28"/>How men have lost by trusting such an else,</l>
      <l>(I have bin gull'd by some of them my selfe.)</l>
      <l>They'll drive men off with words from day to day,</l>
      <l>Till they pimp, beg, or die, or run away.</l>
      <l>And finding many thus were over-throwne,</l>
      <l>I did resolve to make their courses knowne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Walking alone over the pleasant fields</l>
      <l>Which were enricht with treasure, all which yeelds</l>
      <l>Much matter for delight, 'twas cleerly seen</l>
      <l>That all the earth was newly clad in green:</l>
      <l>It did rejoyce that it had cast away.</l>
      <l>Its winter suite, which was a suite of gray.</l>
      <l>The ayrie Choristers did sweetly sing</l>
      <l>Their well-tun'd sonnets to the cheerfull spring.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Don Phoebus</hi> smil'd so lovely on the earth,</l>
      <l>That it beares twins, or hath a second birth.</l>
      <l>To make all yet more rich, the gentle showers</l>
      <l>With hony-drops resweets the various flowers,</l>
      <l>Which now are risen from their frozen beds</l>
      <l>To welcome in the Spring: they shew their heads</l>
      <l>To cheere mens hearts; the milder gales of winde</l>
      <l>Alaies the heat, refreshing every minde,</l>
      <l>It hardly chides the dust, being calme and faire,</l>
      <l>It breathes sweet gusts which do perfume the ayre.</l>
      <l>The beast that was imprison'd and did eat</l>
      <l>His bare allowance, now he carves his meat.</l>
      <l>The azure-colour heavens ioy'd to see</l>
      <l>Such concord on the earth: the harmonie</l>
      <l>Possest me with content; how did this day</l>
      <l>Resemble heaven! but, it pass'd away.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Charetter of heaven whipt his steeds</l>
      <l>That ran too fast before; he never heeds</l>
      <l>Our losse, nor care, nor did his fury rest</l>
      <l>'Till he had drove them headlong to the west.</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="5" facs="28"/>The day being slunk away, the season too</l>
      <l>Will part ere long (thought I) none can it woo</l>
      <l>To tarry here: to qualifie our feare,</l>
      <l>It promis'd us a visit every yeare.</l>
      <l>Black <hi>Morpheus</hi> did begin to chase the light,</l>
      <l>I could not call it day, nor was it night:</l>
      <l>But being refresht, the notions of my braine</l>
      <l>Somewhat reviv'd, homeward I came againe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I heard a cry, and as I pass'd along</l>
      <l>With listning found it was a womans tongue:</l>
      <l>A man replying (made the noise much more)</l>
      <l>With rayling words, Out of my sight you whore,</l>
      <l>Ile travell far enough; What, cannot I</l>
      <l>Accompany my friends, but presently</l>
      <l>Thou must controule me? go thou dirty hag.</l>
      <l>Ile bang thy sides, and make thee work, or beg.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The womans answer modest was, and milde;</l>
      <l>Alas, you know that I am big with childe;</l>
      <l>I've little ones beside, I am afraid</l>
      <l>If you mend not, they'll be through want destroid:</l>
      <l>You care not for us, nor provide us meat,</l>
      <l>We often sit and have no bread to eat:</l>
      <l>You spend what ere you get upon a whore,</l>
      <l>And now you will be gone to vex me more:</l>
      <l>What case am I now in? oh! if you leave me,</l>
      <l>I wish the grave more kinde, and to receive me.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then coming to'em, she exprest her griefe</l>
      <l>To me at large (I gave her some reliefe)</l>
      <l>But he with fury rayl'd, till at the last</l>
      <l>A Constable did make him cry as fast;</l>
      <l>Who coming, knew the case, where he did dwell;</l>
      <l>And to the Iustice neere to new Bridewell</l>
      <l>He had bin brought, but that I made request</l>
      <l>For him; he promist to forsake the nest</l>
      <l>
         <pb n="6" facs="29"/>Of bawdy strumpets, and to end the strife</l>
      <l>He did confesse his faults, and cleare his wife.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet afterwards this vassall was as bad</l>
      <l>As bad might be; which made his wife run mad,</l>
      <l>And so she still remaines: this gave more strength</l>
      <l>Vnto my purpose; then my Muse at length</l>
      <l>Possest with fury, prest with thoughts, grew bold</l>
      <l>To bend herselfe strange stories to unfold.</l>
      <l>Though she was angry, she was mov'd with pitty</l>
      <l>Towards ev'ry one, in Countrey, Court and City.</l>
      <l>It is the sin she strikes at, 'tis her end</l>
      <l>To shew examples, others may amend.</l>
      <l>These kinde of devils (though they range about)</l>
      <l>Where once they enter, seldome are cast out.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Her meaning is, in making sharp her pen,</l>
      <l>To drive ill spirits out, and save the men.</l>
      <l>She feares not envie, <hi>Ignoramus</hi> least;</l>
      <l>One's curst, but weak, and bayard's but a beast.</l>
      <l>If thou dost meet her, use her well (she's free)</l>
      <l>Or else she may unlookt for meet with thee.</l>
      <l>She smiles, yet grieves, to heare how some will roare,</l>
      <l>Although they purchase hell to get a whore.</l>
      <l>Thy night is come; go, quickly call the watch;</l>
      <l>Forth ou hast weighty businesse to dispatch:</l>
      <l>Grace honest Poets; as thou walk'st thy round</l>
      <l>The wanton Rimer will be quickly found:</l>
      <l>Search out the rest, judge as thou find'st their crimes:</l>
      <l>Then thou mayst be a register of times.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>