<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112480_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02637</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12763</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112480</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A detection of sundrie foule errours, lies, sclaunders, corruptions, and other false dealinges, touching doctrine, and other matters : vttered and practized by M.Iewel, in a booke lately by him set foorth entituled, a defence of the apologie. &amp;c. By Thomas Harding doctor of diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 417, 7 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the first comming of this Treatie to mens handes, what, saith one, so smal a Booke for answer to so great a Volume? Shal this Detection conteining litle aboue one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred streetes of Paper, matche the Defence, that is almost foure hundred sheetes? What meaneth D. Harding? Is he not hable to confute M. Iewel? Or is he loth to take paines? To this I answer. How hable I am to confute, what so euer M. Iewel hath written, not onely in his late pretensed Defence, but also in his Replie, or in the Apologie (whereof at leaste he is thought to haue benne the penneman) let it be iudged by the learned: this wil I boldly saie, if he haue no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meane to make his partie good, then hitherto he hath vsed, write he what him liste, it shal be no great praise to any man to haue confuted him. As it had benne smal glorie for valiant Achilles to haue beaten Thersites, whom Homere describeth ready of his tongue, and a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his handes: so among the skilful Diuines, he may not looke to winne great cōmendation of learning, who confuteth M. Iewelles writinges. For certainely good Reader, if thou haue but a meane insight in these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies nowe so much disputed of betwixte the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes and vs, and wilt bestowe some good labour about the exacte trial of the thinges he hath written: thou shalt easily espie the feeblenesse of his side. Thou shalt finde, that he perfourmeth more in shewe, then in acte: that commonly he maketh vp in Tale, where he lacketh of Weight: that with multitude of wordes,
<pb facs="3"/> he couer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
         <desc>•••••</desc>
      </gap> that with huge numbers of Doctours sainges, he setteth foorth the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennesse of substantial Prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ny do their thinne Hippes with stufte Hosen, and their solender Armes with bombast Sleeues.</p>
   <p>This being so, whereas the dewe discussion of these pointes in controuersie descendeth vnto the bottom of thinges, and swimmeth not aboue vpon the fome of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, euery man can soone conceiue, howe meane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning may suffice, to confute such a Writer. If therefore I make profession of sufficient habilitie in this case, there is no cause, why I should be reprehended, as one that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributeth more vnto him selfe, then male seeme to stand with modestie.</p>
   <p>This muche being said for proufe of habilitie, some perhappes would beare, what I haue to saie for my selfe, that I am not lothe to take paines. For he that is hable to doo a good and profitable worke, and refuseth the labour to doo it, seemeth to be gilty of sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wth. True it is, to refel al that M. Iewel hath written, or rather gathered together out of others (for in deed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> he doth nothing els in manner, but laie together he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mennes sayinges) against the Catholique Churche, and against the Catholique Religion, it were greate paine. By iudgement bothe of Cicero, and Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, the labour of writing is accompted very greate.</p>
   <p>And the Scripture saith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.</note>
      <hi>Faciendi plures libros nullus est finis, frequénsque meditatio carnis afflictio est.</hi> There is no ende of making moe Bookes, and the often breaking of a mannes braines about suche studie, is a greate pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
<pb facs="3"/> to the bodie. If any doubte hereof, let him set him selfe a worke earnestly about writing, in suche sorte as I speake of: and he shal saie as I doo, I doubte not. And therefore it behoueth them, that geue them selues to writing, to haue, not onely health, but also good strength of bodie.</p>
   <p>Al this M. Iewel knewe right wel. And for that very cause, when he sawe, that smal bookes would fone be answered, as it appeared by my Answer made to his Chalenge, and by my Confutation of the Apologie: he thought it better policie (or it was so put in his head by the aduise of his brethren) to goe an other waie to worke, that is to saie, to replie vpon me, and to make his Defence, with huge Volumes, that either a long time should passe, before an answere could be retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (hoping that in the meane while his Gospel should take too deepe a roote afterward to be pluckt vp out of the Readers ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s by any what so euer booke, that should come to their handes) or that I should be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and worne out with the labour of answering, and perhappes die before I came to the ende, or that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hugenesse of the bookes, should fraie me from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise of making a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>swer.</p>
   <p>In this case it seemed to mee best, neither by taking vpon me to answere the whole Bookes, and euery parcel of them, to geue our Aduersaries the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the time, not to shorten my life by immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate paines emploied to no great profite, nor by my silence, and by open geuing ouer the whole, as it were by fleeing out of the fielde, to leaue them vnto their Triumphe, but by answering the pointes of greatest
<pb facs="4"/> importance, to set forth a sufficient Defence of the truth for staying of the doubteful, to confirme them in the true doctrine, and thereby to geue out a cleere euidence, what truthe is to be looked for in the reste of his superfluous stuffe, sith he hath shewed him selfe so vntrue a dealer in the chiefe matters.</p>
   <p>Thus haue I do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne, not yeelding to slewth, but moued with good aduise, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as being loth to take paines, and to susteine a long trauaile, but as one, who, the state of the present time considered, and the vncertaintie of thinges to come mistrusted, thought it better, to doo some good out of hande, though it were of losse labour, then by long differring, whiles a larger Volume were intended, to suffer to the losse of many soules, so muche false do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to grow in credite.</p>
   <p>As touching the Replie, what hath benne donne, to those that reade our bookes, it is not vnknowen. What so euer he had to bring against the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nce, against the Sacrifice of the Bodie and bloude of Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, against the Masse, whereat the Priest receiueth the Communion without other companie receiuing sacramentally with him in the same place, against the Churche S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ice in a learned tongue, against the anci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of holy Images in Churches, and against the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>acie of his Successour, to whom louing Christ more then the reste of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohan.</hi> 21.</note> it was specially said, <hi>feede my sheep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> whiche are the weightiest, and chiefe among al the Articles of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge, and whereof al the rest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in manner doo depende: Al this is fully confuted by M. D. Sande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, by M. Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>man, by M. Stapleton, and by mee. As for his Sophistrie, and manifolde Arte, wherewith he enu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>igleth the vnlearned
<pb facs="4"/> muche like to that by which Mountebanckes gete their lyuing, and sundrie craftie, false and absurde practises, M. Rastel hath truly, diligently, and wittily detected them in three bookes written to that purpose, in whiche by the very Title of eche booke he geueth al menne warning to <hi>beware of M. Iewel.</hi> When I considered these chiefe and most special Articles of the Replie so wel and sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted, and the rest of that Volume to conteine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but needelesse heapes of diuers Writers say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, either true, and of vs confessed, or fowly falsified, and corrupted, and wrested to a sense quite contrarie to the authours meaning, or otherwise not perteining to the proufe of any thing by the Catholiques denied, or to the disproufe of any thing by them affirmed: I thought I might doo wel, to laie a side the Replie for a time, and to go in hande with some answer to the pretensed Defence of the Apologie.</p>
   <p>Here what should I doo? Many, as I vnderstand, haue wisshed, that I made a ful answer to the whole, and to euery parcel of it, and for the better perfourmance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they would allow me a yere, or two more. This desire requireth M. Iewels great Volume to be printed againe, that is to saie, the Apologie, my Confutation, and the texte of the Defence, and further so muche of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation to be added, as in printing his booke of set pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he hath caused to be cut of from the reste, and to be suppressed, to the intent a great parte of the best proufes brought against him should not be seene in his booke, which being added would amounte to one good parte, the whole Confutation being diuided into three.</p>
   <p>This ought to be done of necessitie, if an answer to the
<pb facs="5"/> whole were to be made. For where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> al my Treatie must rise vpon the wordes of the Apologie, and of my Confutation, and of the Defence: how should it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanded, how iustly I impugne the Apologie, and the Defence, and mainteine my Confutation, onlesse the places were laid forth before the Readers eies?</p>
   <p>The booke then of the Defence being alreadie so great,<note place="margin">The chiefe pointes of the Defēce being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvered, for vvhat causes a ful an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svver to the reste vvas thought not neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie.</note> as it is, by that time a iuste answer should be added vnto it, euery man that hath any iudgement in these thinges, maie soone conceiue, of what an huge quantitie my new printed Volume would be. In deed were euery idle point answered, and treated of at ful, it would seeme to matche, yea farre to ouermatche Foxes Huge Booke of his false Martyrs. Verely to saie, what reasonably I mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> saie, neither can I in three yeres doo the worke of seuen yeres, nor with a fewe Dallers defraie the charges of foure or fiue hundred poundes, nor can I finde in my Conscience to bring the weake into danger by setting out suche an heretical booke, bicause it is not possible, but that among so many heresies and erroneous pointes, some wil escape my penne vnrefelled, were I neuer so diligent. Nor thinke I it good and profitable, in that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful trauaile to spende so great a parte of my later yeres. Vnfruitful, I meane, bicause I shal be driuen for the most parte to bestow paines about light scoffes, Cauilles, wranglinges, and vaine trifles, worthy to be contemned, rather then to be answered. Briefly neither haue I liste, to set out so huge a Volume, which I beleeue, very fewe would bye.</p>
   <p>I haue therfore thought vpon an other waie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I hope to doo more good to others, sure I am, that to
<pb facs="5"/> my selfe I shal doo lesse hinderance, in respecte of time and health, and neuerthelesse perfourme that, whiche in this case is chiefly requisite.</p>
   <p>Whereas then M. Iewelles pretensed Defence maie be reduced vnto three principal Headdes, from whence,<note place="margin">The Summe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</note> as from their springes, the streames of the whole Booke doo runne, whiche are, 1 a desire to disgrace me, 2 an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest auouching of his new false doctrines in condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Catholique Faith, and of the whole state of Ancient Religion, 3 the reproufe of Priestes, Bishoppes, Cardinalles, and the Popes manners: in this Treatie I haue said somewhat in Defence of my selfe, as it was behooful I should: the most labour I haue emploied to defende the receiued doctrine of the Catholike Faith, which he hath laboured much to impugne. With the liues, and manners of the Clergie, I meddle litle. Menne be menne, and wherein they haue donne euil, I accoumpt them worthy of reproufe, no lesse then he. Howbeit, what so euer he bringeth, al is not the Gospel, that in this point pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth from his penne: and malice could neuer yet learne to saie wel.</p>
   <p>Touching bothe doctrine, and manners, if it shal please God, to geue our Countrie grace to imbrace that onely doctrine, whiche is true and Catholique, that is to saie, whiche we defende against the Nouelties, and Heresies of our time, so busily by M. Iewel, and by them of that side, with al diligence, force, and policie set forth, and commended to the people: concerning order of life and manners, their pleasant Gospel breedeth suche libertie, loosenesse and lewdnes among them that receiue it, that we doubte not, but it shal easily to al appeare, that when
<pb facs="6"/> the Catholiques (whom they cal Papistes) liued worst, the time brought forth moe felowes of Angelles, then their time (notwithstanding the great number they crake of) bringeth forth felowes of honest menne, when so euer they liue best, if it maie be truely said, that at any time they liue wel, who haue cut them selues from that bodie of Christe, into the members whereof onely, the grace of God is deriued.<note place="margin">The Summe and order of this Treatie.</note>
   </p>
   <p>If then thou be desirours Christian Reader to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the order and purporte of this Treatie, made for answer to the Defence for the present time, thus it is.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First, in defence of my selfe I haue shewed, how vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and sclaunderously M. Iewel hath burdened me with certaine hateful Crimes in his Epistle to the Queenes Maiestie. The Vntruthe of these pointes, I haue thought good plainely to laie before the Readers eies by confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the places in my Confutation, whence he tooke the occasions of his sclaunders, as he pretendeth by the quotations noted in the Margent.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Nexte, whereas he findeth him selfe muche agreeued with the sharpnesse of my vtterance, vsed in my Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and in my first Reioinder, and to make credite thereof, hath, as it were into a Table, cowched toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a large heape of sharpe wordes, pretended by his quotations to be in my said two Bookes, whiche are not there in deede altogether in that order, and meaning, as he vntruly hath alleged them: I proue his dealing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in partely to be agreable to his other false demeanour, and partely that good and iust causes there were, why I should, writing against him, vse suche order of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Furthermore, bicause he woulde the great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Vntruthes, with whiche I charged him, to seeme no Vntruthes at al, but that al is the Gospel, what so euer commeth from his Mouthe, and whereas for proufe thereof he hath set forth a View of his Vntruthes (the least of al that he could espie by me noted against him) and pretendeth to iustifie the same his least Vntruthes in the said View: I haue made an answere to that View of Vntruthes, and there doo shewe manifestly (specially in the chiefe pointes, where errour is most perilous) that he was truely, and iustly charged with those Vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and that for ought he hath yet said in Defence of them, he remaineth stil chargeable with the same, as before. This muche I haue perfourmed in the first Booke.</p>
   <p>After this in foure bookes folowing, I detecte his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Lies, Cauilles, shiftes, Sclaunders, and sundrie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true matters, founde in the firste, and seconde parte of his Defence. And in respecte thereof, I cal the Treatie, <hi>A Detection of sundrie foule errours, lies, sclaunders, &amp;c.</hi> At length hauing tried by very certaine experience, and exacte view of the whole Booke, that there was no ende of lying, what place so euer in reading my eie lighted vppon: I thought it most profitable, and most agreable with my profession, to let passe thinges of smal importance (the handeling of whiche serued him specially to scoffe, to vtter vile matter againste the Churche, and to fil vp his Booke in tended at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to be made greate) and to treate of the Articles of Doctrine, in defence of the Truthe, and to confute what he hath brought to the contrarie. Among whiche
<pb facs="7"/> Articles of doctrine, of some I haue treated briefly, as being alreadie treated of in my Confutation, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wheres, of some at good length, and with more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as of Succession, and of the vnlawful Marriages of Priestes, and al other Votaries, wherein he is very large, and copious of Doctours sayinges of al sortes, but vtterly destitute of any one saying, that maketh cleerely for his parte.</p>
   <p>In the ende I doo most euidently disproue and refel what he was hable to bring for Defence of two pointes, which he is not ashamed to affirme seming to me the one very false, the other very sclaunderous. The first is, as he auoucheth them, that matters of faith, and Ecclesiastical causes are to be iudged by the Ciuile Magistrate. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, that the Papistes haue taught, that simple Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is no sinne. How weake proufes he bringeth for the one, and for the other, and yet how shamelesly he goeth about to prooue them: by conference of bothe our Treaties it shal appeare. Withal, there I haue added a Comparison of Errours in mistaking names of menne, bookes, Chapters, &amp;c. with whiche M. Iewel chargeth me, and I him.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Matters let passe, vvith treating vvhereof the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is grovven to a Huge Volume.</note>Thus haue I, declared in fewe the Summe, as it were, and Order of this Treatie. As for sundrie other matters, as of forged Scriptures, of the doctrine of Deuilles (so he calleth the forbidding of Priestes, Monkes, Friers, and Nunnes to marrie) of the fruites of single life, whereof he laith out great stoare of filthy sayinges, of S. Iames Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, whether it be Canonical Scripture, of sundrie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Traditions now growen out of vse, of the Fourmes, and Accidentes, whereat he scoffeth like a Vice plaier,
<pb facs="7"/> of the number of the Sacraments of the Churche, which we defende to be seuen, he affirmeth to be but two, or els so many, as the thinges be, vnto which the name of Sacrament is by any Writer applied, which are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: of the Faith of Infantes: of their new found Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Faith, or rather phantastical Imaginatiō, that eateth the bodie, and drinketh the bloud of Christ, of the Popes Dispensations, of dissensions among the Fathers, of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minales, and Reales, of Thomistes, and Scotistes, of diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of religious persons Apparel, wherein he saith they put great holinesse: of the variance betwen the Lutherās, and the Zuinglians, of the fable of Dame Iohane the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Pope, of the Marble Image, lying in the high way at Rome, of the stoole of easement of Porphyrie stoane at Lateran, of Athenes and Rome, whether they were Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersities in the time, this Dame Iohane is feyned to haue liued in, of the vicious life of <hi>Petrus Aloisius</hi> Duke of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma and Placentia, of Iohn Diazius death, of the slaughter of the Boures of Germanie, that tooke weapons against the nobilitie there, prouoked by the preaching of Luther and his scholers, of Constantines Donation, of Poison ministred in the Sacrament, as he reporteth feined fables for stories of great soothe, of the abomination of desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the state of the Church of Rome, of Antichrist, of the mistaking of Cardinal Hosius, of their pretensed burning of the Scriptures, of S. Augustine the Apostle of the English Nation, that he was a wicked man, of Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes keeping of Concubines, of Images, of Latine Praiers, and Churche Seruice, of Comparison of learning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Catholiques and the Protestantes, of Rome, whether it be Babylon, of summoning of Councelles, of
<pb facs="8"/> the Stewes in Rome, whereof gladly he vttereth muche talke, of kissing the Popes foote, of the Popes hurling of <hi>Franciscus Daldulus</hi> fast tied in chaines vnder his table, there to gnaw boanes with his Dogges, of the Popes Bridle, and Stirop to be holden by Princes, of Pope Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrandes surmised wicked deedes, as they fable, of the Popes treadding on the Emperours necke, of the Pope whether he be euer holy, of the Popes Exactions, of the Cheast in the Popes bosom, whether the Pope be God, of the Popes power feined to be ouer Angels, whether the Pope can commit Simonie, whether the Pope be King of Kinges, whether the Pope be aboue general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, whether the Pope maie erre, or no, whether the Pope be a Kinge: Of these, and of a great many moe suche matters, whereof some be lothesom, some be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous, vaine, and friuolous, some be false, sclaunderous and spiteful, some blasphemous, some alreadie suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently treated of, briefly al tending vnto the contempt of the Catholique Religion, as M. Iewel handleth them, in which matters he hath vttered the stoare of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Of these I saie, I haue said nothing, much disaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taging my selfe thereby and the common cause which I defend, for so much as in the making vp of his great Booke with heaping together these ministerly matters, he hath vttered, as he doth euery where els, good stoare of most euident and grosse Lies, of which his owne fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and best fauourers, in case thei were detected, would be ashamed.</p>
   <p>These forenamed be the thinges, which I haue brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, and these other, and certaine mo the like, be those, which I haue let passe, as being partely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessarie,
<pb facs="8"/> and vnprofitable, partely vnmeete good houres to be bestowed about them. By the handeling of these the weightier pointes, it wil sufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to al menne, with what stuffe he filleth his great Bookes, what smal credite he deserueth, how litle pith there is to be found in his multitude of wordes, how litle there is that serueth aptly to the purpose among the great heapes of testimonies, that he laieth together. Surely his Defence being wel examined by any man that hath skil, and can iudge of these points, it must needes be thought, that when he saw he had not the plaine truth of his side, yet with multitude of allegations he would make a shew of learning to the ignorant, and trouble the answerer with confusion. Euen so many Barbarous Princes (as we reade in stories) when they lacked a conuenient number of good and tried Souldiers, haue gonne about to fraie their enemies with multitude of people, who haue learned by their great ouerthrowes, that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times victorie is not obteined by multitude of menne.</p>
   <p>In deede the Truth needeth not so many sayinges pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of Schoolemenne, of Summistes, of Gloses vpon Gratian, and other partes of the Canon Lawe, and out of so many Canonistes of al sortes. For trial of a mater to be prooued true, in questions touching our beleefe, one saying of the Scripture is sufficient: if the expresse Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture faile vs, twoo, or three Testimonies of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers not being contrarie to the reste, maie suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. But suche a confuse, and vnorderly number of sayinges, specially of suche as be not of great estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as this man commonly allegeth, of the same not one making cleerely for this purpose, in moste matters,
<pb facs="9"/> what doth it els, but breede a suspicion among the wise, that the matter is not true, for proufe whereof they be alleged?</p>
   <p>But by this meane he thought to winne credit at least with the people. For the people that can not iudge of these matters, thinketh him best learned, that hath most woordes. It is knowen, that when they beholde two reasoning together of any thing, whereof they haue no skil, commonly they commend the mainteiner of the worse cause, in case he be fuller of wordes, be they neuer so litle to the purpose, and say in his praise, that he answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the other partie to euery <hi>Quare.</hi> M. Iewel vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, and making his most accompte of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of them that be vnlearned, to whom he leaneth, and by multitude of whom he, and they of his side mind to stand (for touching the learned, they see they can winne none) bestoweth great paines, and charges to set out great bookes, that at least in the opinion of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, and of them that haue not leisure to examine the points how substantially they are treated, he maie seeme to haue done iolily, and to haue acquited him selfe like a great Clerke. In very deede if a man haue care howe muche he maie saie, rather then how truly, and feare not to vtter vntruthes: he hath this aduantage ouer his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie defending the truth with a conscience not to swarue from the censure of the Church, that he may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies finde abundance of matter to vtter. For (as it hath of olde ben said) <hi>Mendacium est multiplex, veritas sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex,</hi> Lying is manifolde, Truth is simple. Lying hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny plaites and foldinges, Truth is without plaite or wrinckle. Therefore it is no marueile, if the Treaties of
<pb facs="9"/> the one be narrowe and shorte; of the other wide and long.</p>
   <p>As for me, if I prooue M. Iewel an vntrue man in so many pointes, as I haue treated of, I haue donne that, whereby his credite must be broken. His credite being broken, what remaineth, but that in this kinde of trade he go for a Banckroute? If he be a Banckrout, worthily is he to be begiled, that trusteth him. Some wil say perhaps, it is not likely, I should with so smal a booke discredit him, that hath written so much. But it maie please this man to remember, that, to saie the truth, it is not M. Iewel, that hath written muche. He hath taken muche out of other mens bookes: of his owne he hath in māner nothing, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely very litle. So that, peruse his Booke who wil, he shal finde, that he is but a seely Translatour of other mens wordes, a heaper together of al Writers sayings, and that most commonly to more ostentation of tale, then to the making vp of good weight. So that if thinges be brought to an exact trial, he shalbe found no disputer, no reasoner, no discourser, no Writer, but only a gatherer together of other mennes Sentences. How be it, it is not the huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of a booke, that argueth the sufficiencie of proufes. Truth is content to be set foorth with few wordes. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet doo I reproue him, for that he allegeth what he findeth in other Writers. For therby we bring credite to doubteful matters. But for that alleging so much, he alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth so litle to the purpose, yea in manner nothing, and (boldly wil I auouche it) vtterly nothing, for due proufe of any his new and strange doctrines, being contrarie to that of ancient time hath benne beleeued in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Churche. This shal seeme more probable, if it be
<pb facs="10"/> confirmed by some plaine, and true examples.</p>
   <p>Lette vs then examine M. Iewelles common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour in an example or twoo. To discusse many, the breuitie of a Preface wil not permitte. O that he were in place to choose the example him selfe, out of his whole Booke to his best aduantage, that so it might eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare, with what weake tooles he fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the truth.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Exāples, vvhereby it is shew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, hovve vvith void and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nēt stuffe, M. Ievvel filleth his great Booke. Defence. <hi>Pag.</hi> 163. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Confut. 73, b. Marke hovv M. Ievv. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies keepeth him selfe from cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the point in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie.</note>Whereas in the Apologie much is said in the commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Matrimonie, which no Catholique man euer discommended, as that it is <hi>Holy and honorable in al sortes, and states of personnes, in the Apostles, in the Ministers of the Church, and in Bisshops, and that it is an honest and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing (as S. Chrysostom saith) for a man liuing in Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie to take vpon him therewith the dignitie of a Bisshop:</hi> to this I saie in my Confutation, that albeit Matrimonie be <hi>holy and honorable in al, and an vndefiled. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> as S. Paule saith: yet that it is not lawful for such personnes to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, who haue deliberately vowed Chastitie, or haue taken holy Orders. This there I prooue by good and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient authoritie, as it maie be seene in my said Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
   <p>Now what is M. Iewels part here to proue for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenāce of his doctrine, but that a man notwithstāding his Vow, or receiuing of holy Orders, maie lawfully marrie? This is the very point of the controuersie, and thereto onely should he haue directed his talke. If he go about any thing els, it is beside the purpose. But consider Reader, how he keepeth him selfe a luffe of from the point, with what stuffe he filleth certaine leaues of his
<pb facs="10"/> Booke, how he starreth from Doctour, to Doctour, how he confoundeth him selfe and the Reader, and though he bring neuer so much out of other Writers, yet commeth not at al to the point directly.</p>
   <p>First,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 165.</note> he laboureth to discredite the holy Ancient Fathers, as menne, <hi>that haue not dealte indifferently herein, but haue gonne to farre, either in the auancing of Virginitie, or in the disgracing of lawful Matrimonie.</hi> Before he entreth his Allegations, whereof that whole Treatie standeth, he putteth foorth twoo sayinges, the one of Origen, the other of S. Hierome, in reproufe of them that condemned Matrimonie. And yet euen there immediatly after he allegeth them both for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demners of Matrimonie. Then he laith foorth the stoare of his Allegations, whereby he would haue it appeare,<note place="margin">Tertulliā alleged by M. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Churche, in that for vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he is condēned of the Churche:</note> that certaine Ancient Writers had an euil opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Matrimonie. There he allegeth two sayinges of Tertullian <hi>in exhortatione ad castitatem</hi> (whiche Booke he wrote against the Churche, as S. Hierome saith, and therefore it is condemned of the Churche, for whiche cause he should not haue alleged him) then twoo say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges out of the Authour of the imperfite worke vppon S. Matthew vnder the name of S. Chrysostome, which also is a worke ful of heresies. <hi>Item</hi> certaine sayinges out of S. Hierome writing against Iouinian, and Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidius. Againe sayinges out of Athenagoras, S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Gregorie Nazianzen, and Origen, by whiche he beareth the Reader in hande, they haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the seconde Marriages of Widowers, and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes.</p>
   <p>After this he reckeneth vp so manie Priestes,<note place="margin">Pag. 166.</note> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops,
<pb facs="11"/> as he hath read of to haue benne married menne, who in deede were married before they receiued holy Orders, and not otherwise. There <hi>Palea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Palea.</note> that is to say, the Chaffe, that is set out in Gratian, concerning Priestes and Bishops that were many Popes Fathers, a very fonde fabulous tale, is admitted to the place of a great Doctor, yet by him much falsified,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 167.</note> and altered from that he found in Gratians booke. There also beside the report of <hi>Aeneas Syluius,</hi> whiche him selfe recanted, and of Polydore Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil, a man of our time, and in these matters of smal cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, he sticketh not to praie helpe of one Fabian, a late seely Chronicler of London, and with his woorshipful testimonie forsooth would faine prooue his mater, that is to saie, with a maine Lie, that Bishoppes and Priestes lyued a thousand yeres together with their Wiues, no lawe being to the contrarie.</p>
   <p>Nowe were al these thinges true, according to the purporte of M. Iewelles doctrine (as for the more parte they are very false, and the Doctours by him corrupted, and very vntruly reported) what should they make for his purpose, I meane, for the point it selfe of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, which is, that it is lawful to marrie after the Vowe of Chastitie, or after holy Orders receiued? For I trow M. Iewel wil not vse this simple kind of Logique, <hi>Certaine ancient Writers condemned Matrimonie</hi> (which is vtterly false in respecte of al others by M Iewel here named excepte Tertullian, that condemned the seconde Marriages, whom the Churche for the same reiecteth) <hi>Item, certaine learned and holy menne in the Primitiue Churche were made Priestes, and Bisshoppes, after they had benne married: Ergo, it is lawful to marrie after the
<pb facs="11"/> Vowe of Chastitie, and after holy Orders taken.</hi> As this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is fonde, and litle worth, so al the sayinges of Writers whiche he hath heaped together hitherto, serue him to no purpose, but to increase the bulke of his Booke.</p>
   <p>After al this feeling him selfe pressed with the force of the Vowe, which being aduisedly made is of necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be performed, as I prooued in my Confutation: to keepe him selfe stil a luffe of from the point of the Question, he taketh a newe waie, saying, that <hi>the Priestes in England were neuer Votaries.</hi> Touching this matter, whether the Priestes of England were Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or no,<note place="margin">
         <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 290.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> I referre the Reader vnto the first Chapter of the fifth booke of this Treatie. Howsoeuer it be, by this answer M. Iewel fleeth from the point, as farre as he fled before. For the Question is, whether Priestes in general that haue made a Vowe of Chastitie maie mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and he answereth that Priestes of England be not Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries. Which answer serueth as aptly in this case, as if a question being demaūded of him, whether Heretikes are to be burned, he would answer, <hi>we the Superintendentes of England, and our Ministers be no heretiques.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>From this he conueigheth him selfe to certaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places, and bringeth in a Huge number of Doctours sayinges tending to this meaning in effect, that Chastitie is hard to keepe, that it is the gifte of God, that God ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it not to al, that it is to be counselled, but not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that a man consider wel of what strength he is, and if he see him selfe not hable to perfourme the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of Virginitie, that rather then he fal into the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of deadly sinne, he take a wife, and vse the remedie ordeined against incontinencie. Al which sayinges (we
<pb facs="12"/> graunt) be true, and are to be vnderstanded of them, whiche be free, and haue not bounde them selues by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Vowe to conteine.</p>
   <p>To be shorte, it were a very tedious thing here to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herse, how he ronneth from Doctour to Doctour, how he craueth stuffing of the Canonistes, and Schoolemen, whom God wote he litle esteemeth, how he writeth out their sentences, and therewith filleth vp his Booke. As for the ancient Doctours sayinges, that folow after al this, they are spoken, some against the perfourmance of wicked Vowes, some serue for admonition, that certaine maie be suffred to marrie, who hauing made onely a sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Vowe, either can not, or wil not conteine, and that the Marriages of suche personnes ought to stand for good, and not to be dissolued, some importe rebuke of filthy life, and exhortation to Chastitie, some be written against them, that either vtterly condemned the state of Matrimonie, or willed Priestes, and Deacons in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Churche to be compelled to forsake the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of their lawful Wiues, whiche they had married be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they receiued holy Orders.</p>
   <p>Thus he writeth out other mennes sayinges without order, or discretiō, skippeth from one matter to an other, and emptieth, as it were, the stoare of his Notebookes into this Defence, and when he hath shuffled in al, he proueth nothing directly, but onely bringeth the Reader to a Confusion, and commeth not at al to the discussion of the point, that we staie vpon, whiche in this matter of Priestes Marriages is, that to marrie it is not lawful after deliberate Vowe of chastitie made, nor after holy Orders receiued. What colourable argumentes, or
<pb facs="12"/> testimonies he bringeth to proue the affirmatiue,<note place="margin">Infrà lib. <hi>5</hi> Cap. <hi>2</hi>
      </note> in this Treatie Reader thou shalt see them cleerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</p>
   <p>Likewise (to shew thee an other example) hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon him to proue,<note place="margin">Defence. Pag. 157.</note> that the Canonistes haue taught the people, that Fornication betwen single folke is no sinne, it is a worlde to see what a doo he maketh, what a number of Allegations he hudleth together, and when he hath vttered al his stoare, he is as farre from proufe of that he tooke in hand to proue, as he was before he beganne. So that in effecte nothing thereby is done, but onely malice shewed, and incke and paper spent.</p>
   <p>First, to make a great shewe,<note place="margin">Defence. 360.</note> and to increase his Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume (for to what other purpose I see not) he telleth vs of certaine beastly sayinges of <hi>Aetius</hi> the olde Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and of <hi>Prodicus</hi> the heathen philosopher, as though the Canonistes were to be blamed for the faultes of the Heretiques, and Infidelles of olde time. Nexte, he bringeth in Laurentius Valla the Grammarian, whose saying, though it be not needeful here to reherse for the reuerence of chaste eares, yet it maie with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient interpretation be honestly defended. Then <hi>Richardus de Sancto Victore</hi> a late Schooleman, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates the Historiographer are haled in to geue their verdite, and though they tel vs of the corrupte iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of certaine, that made litle accompte in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of Fornication and whooredome: yet that the Popes Canonistes taught the people, that simple For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication is no sinne, thereof they speake not one word. Which bicause M. Iewel him selfe perceiued right wel, he preuēted that he feared would be obiected, and after
<pb facs="13"/> that number of impertinent allegations,<note place="margin">M. Ievv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elles But.</note> commeth in, as his manner is, with his But, saying, <hi>But ye wil saie, al this hitherto perteineth nothing vnto the Canonistes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To whom answere maie be returned, that so it is in deed: and whereas he knew it him selfe, what meant he neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse to put it in, but to increase the heape of his Volume?</p>
   <p>After this he pretendeth to come to the very point, and to hit the naile on the head, as they saie. And there he taketh aduantage of a Decree of the first Toletane Councel falsly reported in Gratian by the ouersight of the printer in an olde Copie, many other Copies being true, whiche aduantage neuerthelesse eftsones there he forgoeth, confessing the Copie to be false. Yet al must in, to fil vp the great booke. Then he goeth to the true Copie, and either by ignorance he mistaketh the place, or by malice falsifieth the sense, dissembling, that the worde <hi>Concubina</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cōcubina.</note> is oftentimes taken in good parte, to witte, for a woman vsed in al respectes like a Wife, and with the intent, and affection of wedlocke, before the Marriage be openly solemnized. This shal be better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by reading that I haue said hereof <hi>Lib. 5. cap. 15.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>From that Councel (whiche was holden long before any of the Canonistes, whom so fowly he sclaundereth, wrote letter) he goeth to peake in his Gloses, the Gloses I meane vpon <hi>Otho</hi> (whom like an vnskilful lawier, he maketh one with <hi>Otho bonus</hi>) and vpon the Decrees of Gratian. The one Gloselie falsifieth by leauing out a worde of chiefe importance, the other of purpose he misconstrueth, the rest that he allegeth out of an other Glose, and out of one Petrus Rauennas a Canoniste, is
<pb facs="13"/> true, and perteineth nothing to the wicked doctrine, whereof he accuseth the Canonistes.</p>
   <p>From the Gloses he starteth to S. Augustine <hi>in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridio ad Laurentium.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Defence 361.</note> And out of him he taketh a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, vtterly to no purpose, but to fil vp the paper. From S. Augustine to the Councel of Basile, then to Erasmus <hi>in Enchiridio militis Christiani,</hi> belying them bothe. From Erasmus he crepeth to <hi>Iacobus de Valentia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iacob. de Valentia in Psal. <hi>118</hi>
      </note> saying of Iewes, Saracenes, and certaine il Christian menne, that <hi>to excuse their detestable life, they affirme sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Fornication to be lawful.</hi> But what is this to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonistes? From this <hi>Iacobus</hi> the Spaniard of <hi>Valentia,</hi> he conueieth him selfe to <hi>Alexander</hi> of Hales the English man, and from him to <hi>Antonius</hi> of Florence the Italian. But at their handes he findeth no more reliefe, then he founde at the others. By <hi>Antonius</hi> it is roported onely, that <hi>their errour is confuted, who saie, that simple Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is no sinne.</hi> In <hi>Alexander</hi> there is nothing founde, but onely a saying pretended to be S. Ambroses, whiche maketh nothing to the purpose, neither is it at al being vttered in suche wordes, to be found in S. Ambrose.</p>
   <p>At length he endeth this matter with a falsified saying of S. Augustine, making that holy Father (as vntruly he reporteth his tale) to saie, <hi>that he can not tel, whether that kinde of Fornication, whiche single menne committe with single womenne, be forbidden, or no.</hi> Whiche, were it true that S. Augustine so said, as in deede he saith it not, but speaketh otherwise, as here the reader shal finde by me declared, yet by that, the sclaunder vttered against the Canonistes, is not iustified.</p>
   <p>This muche haue I here noted for examples sake, to
<pb facs="14"/> the intent thou maist vnderstand Reader, what order he keepeth commonly in his writing, and whereof it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that his bookes rise to suche a huge quantitie.</p>
   <p>And as he hath donne in these two matters, so hath he donne in the reste, very fewe excepted. The same would I here by sundrie other mo euident examples shewe, were it not ouer long.</p>
   <p>Certainely this is not to answer a Booke, it is not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly to replie, it is not directly to confute a Booke. It is onely an ostentation of much reading, it is a copying out of common places laid vp in Notebookes, it is to render wordes for reasons, and heapes of impertinent sentences of what so euer Writers, for apte testimonies of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers. Briefly, it is not an orderly disproufe of the doctrine that the Church hath hitherto holden. For who so wil consider of it with right iudgement, shal finde our proufes to stande vnshaken, and my former Booke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a sufficient Confutatiō, not only of the Apologie, but also of the pretensed Defence it selfe. That it maie truly be said, there was a Confutation of the Defence made, before the Defence it selfe was printed. For if the pointes of my former Booke be wel weighed and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of, they wil to the learned seeme a sufficient an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to what so euer he bringeth.</p>
   <p>For trial hereof I referre me to the answere, whiche here I haue made vnto his View of Vntruthes.<note place="margin">The View of M. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvels Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes.</note> Among whiche Vntruthes thou shalt finde few noted out of the Apologie so by him discharged, but that in respect of my Confutation, notwithstanding his Defence, he maie seeme stil to stand chargeable no lesse then before. If he can no better discharge him selfe of suche Vntruthes,
<pb facs="14"/> which he him selfe hath chosen out of the whole heape, as the least, and easiest for him to defende, and in iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of which he had greatest cōfidence: it maie soone be iudged, how vnlike it is, that he shalbe hable to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him selfe of those others, whiche he thought best to conceele and dissemble.</p>
   <p>One thing good Reader it behoueth thee much to be warned of, in case thou desire to stande an vpright vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere betwen M. Iewel and me. Vpon what places so euer thou shalt happen to light, in which he shal seeme to haue any good aduantage against me, or against the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Catholique Churche, passe not them ouer lightly, weigh wel both our groundes, examine both our allegations, truste not to ought, that is laid forth by either of vs presently, but resort to the Bookes, whence euery thing is taken. Doing so, thou shalt most certainely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, whether of vs both vseth more truth. Doubtlesse in such places thou shalt seldō (it were much so saie neuer) find him to allege the wordes, whereby he pretēdeth any colour of aduantage, without some false sleight, or other.</p>
   <p>If thou desire to vnderstand this by some examples, consider I praie thee, what great a doo he maketh about the name of <hi>Vniuersal Bishop.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vniuersal Bishop.</note> As he handleth that matter, if a man wil beleeue him, al thinges seeme to be plaine on his side.<note place="margin">Defence. 120.</note>
      <hi>The Coūcel of Carthage</hi> (saith he) <hi>decreed by expresse wordes, that the Bishop of Rome should not be called the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersal Bishop.</hi> And behold Reader the confidēce that he hath in this cause, which he sheweth with these wordes speaking vnto me. <hi>This you saie, is forged, and falsified, and is no part of that Conucel. For indifferēt trial both of the truth, ād of the falshed herein, I besech you, behold the very wordes
<pb facs="15"/> of the Councel, euen as they are alleged by your owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour Gratian. These they are Prima Sedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Episcopus, &amp;c. Let not the Bishoppe of any of the first Sees be called the Prince of Priestes,<note place="margin">Dist. 99. Primae.</note> or the highest Priest, or by any like name: but onely the Bishoppe of the first See. But let not the Bishoppe of Rome him selfe be called the Vniuersal Bishoppe. &amp;c. Now M. Harding, compare our wordes, and the Councelles wordes together. We saie none otherwise, but as the Councel saith, The Bishop of Rome him selfe ought not to be called the vniuersal Bishop. Herein we doo neither adde, nor minis he, but reporte the wordes plainely, as we finde them. If you had lookte better on your booke, and would haue tried this matter, as you saie, by your learning, ye might wel haue reserued these vnciuile reproches of falshed to your selfe, and haue spared your crying of shame vpō this Defender.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Here is muche a doo, as thou feest Reader, and al standeth vpon falshed, as I said at the first in my Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We striue not for the name of Vniuersal Bishop: neither hath the Pope Challenged that title. Yet these menne haue neuer donne with Vniuersal Bishop. The whole matter is soone answered. These wordes <hi>vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salis autem nec etiam Romanus Pontifex appelletur:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Concil. Carthag. <hi>3</hi> Cap. <hi>26.</hi>
      </note> The Bishop of Rome ought not to be called the vniuersal Bishop, (these wordes I saie) be not the wordes of the thirde Councel of Carthage, nor in the Greeke, nor in the Latine, but the wordes of Gratian and they stande for the Summe of that parte of the distinction, whiche there foloweth. And thereof M. Iewel was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, as it appeareth by his owne wordes in the same place. Howbeit, were it true, that Gratian had igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly added them to the Councel as wordes of the Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,
<pb facs="15"/> what learned man trusteth Gratian, a man not greatly trusted in respect of sundrie his allegations, when it is easy to see the Original? For this I referre the Reader to the 39. Chapter of the third Booke of this Treatie, fol. 184. b.</p>
   <p>Perusing that I haue answered to this point there thou shalt fully vnderstand, how falsly M. Iewel hath dealte therein, and how litle cause he had so to triumphe. For neither hath the Councel any suche woordes at al, nor speaketh it there so much as one worde of the Bishop of Rome, nor hath Gratian put those wordes, as a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the Councel, but as the Summe of that parte of the 99. Distinction, which immediatly foloweth. As wel might M. Iewel haue said, that those other wordes there placed, <hi>vnde Pelagius secundus omnibus Episcopis,</hi> had ben the wordes of that Councel. He that knoweth Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians manner of writing, can not but either laugh at M. Iewelles ignorance, or maruaile at his impudencie.</p>
   <p>To proue that it is lawful for a man to marrie a wife being in holy Orders,<note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Eupsy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius.</note> he allegeth the example of one <hi>Eupsychius,</hi> who was a Laie Gentleman of <hi>Caesaria</hi> the chiefe Citie in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> and in a time of persecution suffred Martyrdom soone after that he had benne mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. Now most falsly he corrupteth the reporter of the Storie, and maketh this <hi>Eupsychius</hi> a Bishop, that it might appeare to the ignorant, that one had married a wife af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had benne made a Bishop, which would haue ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our married Superintendentes purpose gaily. For yet after so many yeres searche, they can not bring vs forth so much as one cleare example of the ancient Churche, that euer there was any Bishop, or Priest married after that degree, and holy Order taken. With such vncleane
<pb facs="16"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="16"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="17"/> conueiance their vncleane treacherie is defended.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Defence 176. <hi>Cassio. li.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note>His wordes be these, <hi>Cassiodorus writeth thus, In illo tempore ferunt Martyrio vitam finisse Eupsychium Caesa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riensem (Episcopum) ducta nuper vxore: dum adhuc quasi sponsus esse videretur:</hi> At that time they saie <hi>Eupsychius</hi> the Bishoppe of <hi>Caesaria</hi> died in Martyrdome, hauing married a wife a litle before, being yet in manner a newe married man.</p>
   <p>Beholde Reader the falshod of this man. First, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to his custome elswhere, he leaueth the Greeke fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine, where this Storie was First written, and goeth to the riuer of the olde translation in many places not most exactly answering the Greeke. And why did he so? For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth bicause if he had alleged <hi>Sozomenus</hi> the Greeke writer, his falshod had benne fowly bewraied. For he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this <hi>Eupsychius</hi> expressely,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eupsychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> a laie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, by M. Iewels forgerie made a Bishop, to proue the Mariages of Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as much to saie, <hi>Eupsychius one of the Lordes</hi> (or one of the Nobilitie) <hi>of the Citie of Caesaria in Cappadocia.</hi> Then, bicause the Tripartite Storie of <hi>Cassiodorus</hi> setting foorth hath not so expressely, that he was a nobleman of <hi>Caesaria,</hi> M. Iewel was so bolde, as to falsifie the place, and to putte in of his owne this woorde, <hi>Episcopum,</hi> to helpe his matter, and so corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting his authour, maketh him to cal him <hi>Eupsychium Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sariensem Episcopum, Eupsychius</hi> the Bishoppe of <hi>Caesa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> Thus he taketh vpon him to make him a Bishoppe, who was a Laie man, as wel a Bishoppe as he him selfe is, that it might appeare to the vnlearned, that a Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppe married a wife after he was Bisshoppe.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Fol.</hi> 302. <hi>&amp;</hi> 318.</note> See what I haue said hereto in this Treatie, where I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb facs="17"/> his false stuffe touching Priestes marriages. <hi>Lib. 5. Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Fol. 302.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Speaking against the number of the seuen Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the Churche,<note place="margin">Defence. 213. <hi>Apocal.</hi> 5.8.7.1.</note> to bring the Catholique Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in contempte, thus he saith. <hi>As for the reasons, that they of M. Hardinges side haue brought vs for proufe hereof, they are too childish to be remembred. For thus they saie, The Booke in the Apocalyps hath seuen seales: The seuen Angels there haue seuen Trumpettes: Christ hath in his right hande seuen starres: Christe walketh in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of seuen golden Candlestickes:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Zacha.</hi> 3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 37.</note>
      <hi>Zacharie saw seuen eies vpon a stone: There were seuen Candelstickes in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle: Ergo, saie they, there must needes be iuste seuen Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes in the Churche of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If this were true,<note place="margin">In Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendio Theologiae.</note> wee might be somewhat ashamed of our Doctours, I graunte. Neither can this Reason seeme but weake and feeble. But what if al this be false? Then are our Doctours not touched, then maie their reasons be thought substantial, and M. Iewel a vaine Iangler, that thus stuffeth his greate Booke with Lies. Peruse the place Reader,<note place="margin">In Cōpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
      </note> that by his quotation he directeth thee vnto, and thou shalt finde him like him selfe as he is euery where, a false Minister. For <hi>Compendium Theologiae,</hi> whiche he allegeth, hath farre otherwise. It saith not, there muste needes be iuste seuen Sacramentes in the Churche, bicause seuen Seales, seuen Trumpettes, seuen Starres, seuen Candlestickes, seuen Eies be thus spoken of in the Scripture: but it saith expressely, <hi>Sacramenta figurata sunt in septem Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnaculis,</hi> The Sacramentes were figured (or foresig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified) in the seuen Seales, in the seuen Starres, &amp;c.
<pb facs="18"/> That the number of those thinges is made a reason, or cause of the number of the Sacramentes, it is M. Iewels Lie, it is not the saying of him that wrote <hi>Compendium.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Defence 361. 8, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied by M. Ievvel.</note>Hauing taken vpon him to proue, that the Doctours of the Canon Lawe haue taught the people, that Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation betwen Singlefolke is no sinne, among a huge heape of sayinges taken out of writers of sundrie sortes, (whereof not so much as one affirmeth it) he bringeth in this saying, pretending it to be S. Augustine, <hi>in Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion. in Exod. quaest. 20. Illa Fornicatio, quam faciunt qui vxores non habent, cum foeminis, quae viros non habent, an prohibita inueniri possit, ignoro. That kinde of Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which Single menne commit with single womenne, whether it be forbidden, or no, I can not tel.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>By this sentence, as it is here set forth, S. Augustine is set to schoole, and made to confesse (whiche he would neuer haue confessed whiles he liued) that he could not tel, whether Fornication that is committed betwene single folcke, were forbidden, or no: whereby he should seeme to geue great libertie to single personnes to folow the filthy lustes of their flesh. And here, which is to be noted, whereas the reste of the sentence is printed in the smal letter, in which the Doctours testimonies be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly set out, these wordes in Latine, <hi>Fornicatio, an prohibita inueniri possit, ignoro,</hi> and these English wordes, <hi>Fornication, whether it be forbidden, or no, I can not tel,</hi> are printed in a farre greater letter, that they should rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily appeare to the eie, and be readde of al menne, as if he were desirous, as the Deuil him selfe is, that al were persuaded, that Fornication among single persons were no sinne. Which doctrine there, and in certaine other
<pb facs="18"/> places of that Booke, by sundrie colourable sayinges of Writers he seemeth to labour to persuade.</p>
   <p>But the true saying of S. Augustine, and the meaning of the same, is farre otherwise. For thus he saith, not in <hi>Quaest. in Exod. quaest.</hi> 20. as the place by M. Iewel is falsly quoted: but in <hi>Quaestionum super Exodum lib. 2. quaest. 71. Sed si non omnis Fornicatio etiam Moechia dici potest, vbi sit in Decalogo prohibita illa fornicatio, quam faciunt viri qui vxores non habent, cum foeminis, quae maritos non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, vtrum inueniri possit, ignoro.</hi> As muche to saie, But if it be so, that al Fornication maie not be called also <hi>(Moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia)</hi> Aduouterie, where that Fornication, which menne commit that haue no wiues, with womenne that haue no husbandes, is forbidden in the Table of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, whether it maie be founde, or no, I can not tel.</p>
   <p>S. Augustine saith not simply, he knew not whether simple Fornication were forbidden, or no: he knewe wel, it was forbidden: But if it were once denied, that al Fornication were signified by the woorde and name of <hi>Moechia,</hi> (whiche properly is Aduouterie, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is expressed in the ten Commaundementes) the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie whereof he prooueth in that place very learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: in this case, and not otherwise, he acknowlegeth him selfe not to knowe, where the Fornication, that is committed betwen single personnes, maie be found for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden (where? not generally, but) <hi>in Decalogo,</hi> in the ten Commaundementes. And this is the only point, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in S. Augustine confesseth his ignorance. Howbeit in the same place he sheweth, that vnder the name of <hi>Moechia,</hi> al manner Fornication is comprised, and that therefore
<pb facs="19"/> in the tenne Commaundementes it is forbidden, no lesse then Aduout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, as I haue at large declared in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lib. 5. Cap. 15. where M. Iewels falsehood is further detected.</p>
   <p>But what meane I to laie foorth places by M. Iewel falsified, and corrupted? If I woulde make profession thereof, I ought to laie foorth his whole booke new prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For of such stuffe the whole consisteth. One place, bicause therein he thought to touche mine honestie, I can not let passe. Thus it is.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Consider Reader hovv far suche a false for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is to be trusted</note>Hauing in my Confutation reprooued the Lady A.B. for turning these wordes out of <hi>Fulgentius, formam serui,</hi> and <hi>formam Dei</hi> (asmuch to say, the fourme of a feruaunt, and the fourme of God) into <hi>Manhed,</hi> and <hi>Godhed,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a false meaning is conueighed in against the true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of Christes bodie in the most blessed Sacrament of the Aulter: least I should haue seemed ouer sharpe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking a woman (whereas in deede for a Doctor of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie to confute a woman, I thought it no great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest) after certaine other wordes of reprouse,<note place="margin">Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Fol. 41.2</note> thus I say: Whether I maie without breache of courtesie charge her with so heinous a crime, or no, I doubte. Perhappes as shee passeth the bondes of womanlie state, in presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to medle <hi>so farre in these perillouse matters, &amp;c:</hi> so maie I seeme to forgete courtesie, <hi>thus roughly to blame so softe a creature.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Defence. fol. 89.</note>Nowe commeth me in this Master of Defence, and for the loue of his good Ladie, laieth busily about him, driueth very fiercely at me (though his strokes light not on me) and like a kinde harted Louer, saieth very much in her praise, and not a litle to my dispraise: that shee
<pb facs="19"/> forsooth is a Ladie of great learning, vertue, and graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that al that I haue sent ouer, are but toyes, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles (by like bicause I printe not my Bookes in Folio, as he dooth) that shee is ful of wisedome, and I ful of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
   <p>There he promiseth in great sooth, that he wil not tel me how lewdly I haue demeaned my selfe towardes her. And what is that? Nay, he wil not tel it me (ye may beleue him, bicause it wil sound to my great shame. Yet out it must, the man is taken with suche a lust. And bicause he was lothe it should come to the knowlege of many, thus forthwith he telleth it me in a printed booke. <hi>I beseeche you</hi> (saith he ful courteouslie) <hi>cal your wordes againe to minde, if you can without blusshing:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Handle,</hi> foisted in by M Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvel for <hi>Blame.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>So roughlie to handle so softe a Creature</hi> (where he hath changed my honest worde <hi>Blame,</hi> into his owne worde <hi>Handle,</hi> of filthie imagination) <hi>This Phrase of speache your very frends haue muche misliked, and as it is in dede, so in plaine wordes they cal it Ruffianrie, &amp;c.</hi> The whole matter thus he concludeth, with like truth as he beganne. <hi>But this fault, as I haue said, I wil dissemble.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To al this, what shal I saie good Reader? God be thanked, that M. Iewel, who is so desirous to tel that of me, whereof I should be ashamed, hath nothing to tel, but a Lie forged by his owne filthie imagination, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he must needes be ashamed, if he haue any sparke of honest nature in him. <hi>So roughlie to handle so softe a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> be not my woordes.</p>
   <p>If it be Ruffianrie so to speake (as he saieth, that in deede it is) then is this Superintendent of Sarisburie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Ruffian. For he speaketh so, I spake it not.
<pb facs="20"/>
      <hi>Thus roughly to blame so soft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> a creature,</hi> whether it might not in that place be honestly spoken, I reporte me to al that be honest. Bicause he knew him selfe, he had made this apparent aduantage against me by his false forgerie, foisting in the worde <hi>Handle,</hi> in place of the word <hi>Blame,</hi> of purpose, that his impudent falshed might not be espied, he least out of his Booke, xxvij. lines of my Confutation, where the wordes be with which I reproue the Lady for her false Translation, if it were hers, and not an others, set forth in her name.</p>
   <p>But my very frendes haue muche misliked this Phrase of speache, saith M. Iewel. I maruell how they could mislike it, before it was euer written. In deede bothe my frendes, and his frendes too, mislike this Phrase, as he hath forged it, very much, I doubte not. And as for his frendes, I dare saie, they are ashamed of him, and wish, he had not discredited his ministerly Diuinitie, with suche Ruffianly humanitie, or rather inhumani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For a ful answer hereto see in this Treatie, <hi>Lib. 3. cap. 2. Fol. 120.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for the Lady that translated the Apologie into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, in whose quarrel this vnhonest and vncleane lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse hath by this Champion ben practized, I wish her no woorse, but that shee tel M. Iewel, when shee meeteth with him nexte, that though shee were desirours bothe of Praise, and also of reuenge, yet shee had rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnpraised, and vnrevenged, then of suche a false handler to be praised, and with such open lying to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged.</p>
   <p>Thus Reader by Viewe of these fewe places noted out of the whole heape, thou maist conceiue, with
<pb facs="20"/> what manner stuffe M. Iewel hath filled vp that huge Booke. Suche as these are, after the same rate the more parte of the reste is. Wherefore al menne maie see, how good cause they haue to hier their Promotours, and Waiters, to lie in waite for our Bookes at the Portes, and Creekes, and with great extremitie to pounish al menne, who are founde to haue them. For by that meane they hope to winne a long time, before their guile and fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode be made open to al the worlde.</p>
   <p>Seeing then among al that huge heape so litle can be founde, whereby he maie seeme to go directly to the pointes that be in Controuersie, and presently treated of, seeing where he geueth out certaine shadowes, as it were of proufes, if the same be duely examined, they be tried corrupted, and falsified by one vntrue meane or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and seeing the confutation of al that is to be confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, must be made by repeating and laying forth againe the testimonies truly, whiche he allegeth falsly, by she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, where he clippeth of the Doctours wordes, where he addeth wordes of his owne, where he leaueth out the beginning, or the ende of Sentences, where he vseth false translation, where he conceeleth and dissembleth the Circumstance of the places, and foloweth the bare sounde of wordes without farther view of the Writers intent, where he maketh false exchange of wordes, as he is now taken in the manner, changing <hi>Blame,</hi> a worde of chaste meaning, into <hi>Handle</hi> a worde of vnchaste ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination: seing I saie, this is the meane and waie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Confutation of the pretensed Defence must be wrought: I leaue vnto the iudgement of those who can iudge of these thinges, what a long and tedious worke
<pb facs="21"/> it would be, and how litle profite would redounde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if I should refute his whole Booke.</p>
   <p>This being wel considered, specially whereas also a long time is required to the finishing of suche a worke, great charges are to be emploied in printing, and menne at these daies soone waxe wearie, and feele lothsomnes in reading long Treaties: I thought I should doo more cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently, if I confuted the chiefe pointes of Doctrine, then if I bestowed my labour about the confutation of the whole, whiche for the most parte consisteth of light and vaine trifles not worth the reading. And to saie the truthe, what credite is he worthy to beare in the reste, that in the chiefe pointes is proued to haue dealte so vntruly?</p>
   <p>If I truly charge M. Iewel with thertie, fortie, fiftie, yea with a hundred great and notorious Lies, and sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confute the same, shal I not seeme to haue proued him a Lier, and a false dealer in these causes, excepted I confute him in a thousand, eleuen, or twelue hundred mo? If the case be so, then is the aduantage in the multitude of Lies, and he is farthest from being confuted, who maketh most Lies, and specially he that maketh so many, as the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the truth shal not haue leisure to trie them Lies. It is wel knowen, how muche easier it is to write Lies, then to confute Lies. A Lie is vttered in a worde or two: the poison of an hainous Heresie is spet forth in a line or two: Nor this, nor that perhappes can wel and sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be confuted, so as it be made plaine vnto the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in foure or fiue leaues.</p>
   <p>Least I should seeme to saie nothing in his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb facs="21"/> and not to acknowlege his worthiest qualities, I graunt, he is furnished with Rhetorie, with humaine let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with Eloquence, with a mearie wit, and that he hath a readie grace in skoffing, yea that he is hable to greeue the harte not onely of his Aduersarie, but also of any other godly man, with scorneful flowtes in thinges of greatest holinesse. But Christian Reader, we striue not for the Garland of that game: we go not about to trie maisteries of suche witte, or of humaine learning. Our strife is about the Truthe. The waie to shewe it, and proue it, (whiche he him selfe by open Chalenge hath offred his Doctrine to be tried by) is by laying forth the plaine Scriptures, the examples of the Primitiue Church, the testimonies of the General Councelles, and ancient Fathers.</p>
   <p>Of these who hath so great stoare, saith a frende of his, as M. Iewel? Who euer sawe the margent of any Booke so beset with cotations, as his Bookes are? This were a great euidence of the Truthe on his side, if the matter were alwaies tried by what so euer multitude of writers sayinges. But what if the number of his testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies be quite beside the purpose? Seemeth he not then ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry shamelesse? Is he not then farre to blame so to abuse the plaine and wel meaning Readers? It shalbe said per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes in his excuse: He seeth the negligence of menne, he cōsidered, that fewe, or none examine our writinges. And therefore he thinketh, he shal seeme to saie muche, though in deede nothing be said, that perteineth to the pointes presently handled. And where a thing is to be done and the same for want of habilitie can not be done: there it seemeth good policie to geue the assaie, and
<pb facs="22"/> to make shewe, as if it could be donne, or were donne. It is knowen, how flatterers make resemblance of frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, how Hypocrites geue forthe tokens of holinesse, the intended Bankroute of good truste and credite, the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Coward of stoute courage, Beggers oftentimes of welth, Queanes of womanly honestie, and chast demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Right so M. Iewel feeling him selfe destitute of the Truthe, and impugning the Truthe, and professing to deliuer vnto the worlde a new Truthe, that is to saie, a heape of olde Vntruthes busily set forth of late yeres by Luther, Zuinglius, Caluine, Beza, and the reste, and by Wiklefe, Hus, Waldenses, and others, their predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours in former times, laboureth with al his witte, and cunning, to iustifie it, calling it by the name of Goddes pure worde, the Gospel, and the sincere Truthe: that whereas he is not hable to perfourme his intent in deed, yet he might seeme to make it good with wordes.</p>
   <p>Touching the life of the Clergie, wel maie I confesse, that M. Iewel hath somewhat to saie, out of certaine writers, how true, I knowe not: whereto I shal hardly be hable to make answer in ful defence of certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonnes. But as touching the Doctrine, that the Catholike Churche holdeth at this daie, and hath alwaies holden, I auouche boldly, as by sundrie our bookes it hath now ben clearely proued, and they vnderstand so much that doo thoroughly examine the reasons, authorities, and proufes of both partes: that he is not hable to bring so muche as one sentence out of any allowed writer, that may not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily be refelled.</p>
   <p>And bicause he knoweth, that in pointes of Doctrine the force of Truth is clearely on our side, he would faine
<pb facs="22"/> traine me from matters of Doctrine, wherein he hath smal hope of victorie, or of acquitting him selfe with euen hande, vnto matters of life, and other bye thinges, whereof what so euer be beleeued, therein is no great danger touching our Saluation. As for example, what cracke is there made in the Doctrine of the Catholique Churche, if the <hi>Nominales,</hi> and the <hi>Reales,</hi> if the <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mistes,</hi> and <hi>Scotistes</hi> dissent about pointes Logical, or Metaphysical, or perhappes also about the paringes of some Scholastical pointes of Diuinitie? What if some light beleeuing writers haue sadly and in ernest made mention of one Ioane a woman Pope, deceiued by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Polonus<note place="margin">Martinus Polonus.</note> a man of smal credite, who moued with olde wiues tales first committed that fable to writing? What if some later writers haue vttered their phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, whiche they dreamed thereof, vpon occasion of an olde Marble Stone hauing in it a woman with a ladde standing by her engraued? What if a fewe menne that helde with certaine euil Emperours, whiche could not abide to be reuoked from their vnlawful lustes by the Pope for the time being, haue written and reported il of a fewe Popes? What if Iohannes Casa wrote some vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaste Italian Sonettes and Rymes in his yewth, though for filthinesse not comparable to suche as be extant of Bezaes making the Apostle of the Frenche Hugueno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? What if Petrus Aloisius, whom Paulus Tertius the Pope loued so tenderly, were a vicious man? What if Iohn Diazius the Spaniard were vnnaturally murdered by Alphonsus Diazius his brother that liued at Rome?</p>
   <p>What if Luther, wrote against the furious vproares of the Boures in Germanie, when he sawe they were
<pb facs="23"/> sure to be ouerthrowen by the Nobilitie there (whom notwithstanding he had before by Thomas Muncer his scholer stirred to take weapons against their Lordes) that he might laie some good colour vpon that he had il be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne? What if some haue written, though not without contradiction of others, that Poison was ministred in the blessed Sacrament? What if a Pope shewed him selfe cruel, and without pitie, in suffering Frances Dandulus the Venetians Ambassadour to lie vnder his table like a dogge, whiles he was at diner.</p>
   <p>What if Popes haue suffered great Princes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narkes to kisse their feete, to holde their Stiroppes, to leade their horses by the Bridle? W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>at if Gregorie the seuenth, otherwise called Hildebrande, whom many graue Writers reporte to haue benne a man of great vertue, and an excellent good gouernour of the Church, be of some Writers of that age, who flattered the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour then being that Popes mortal enemie, accompted an il man? What if Pope Alexander vsed Frederike the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour more proudly, then became a man of his calling? What if Constantines Donation can not be most suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proued by record of antiquitie? What if certaine Emperours and other Princes, for great causes haue ben remoued frō their estates by the Popes authoritie? What if the Gloser vpon Gratian, and certaine other Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes haue immoderately magnified the Pope, and to extol his power haue vsed some termes vndiscretely, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse by fauorable interpretation maie be iustified?</p>
   <p>What if the Popes at certaine times either for negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence cared not, or for the wrechednesse of mannes il inclination could not, or for great considerations would
<pb facs="23"/> not vtterly purge the Citie of Rome of Courtesanes, and Brodel houses? What if the life of many Priestes, Bishoppes, Cardinals, yea of some Popes also hath iustly deserued to be reproued? Once to conclude, what if al sortes of olde Bookes being raked out of dusty corners, Schoolemen, Summistes, Glosers, vaine Chroniclers, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendes, writers of Dreames and Visions, and suche Riffe raffe, and menne for the purpose being set a worke to peruse them, in the same be founde a fewe fonde pointes of Doctrine, certaine loose Conclusions, many seely Tales not worth the telling, and some lewd faultes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious personnes, and others of the Clergie detected?</p>
   <p>What if I saie, al these, and many other suche thinges were graunted, of whiche we are persuaded, that some are true, the more parte is false, muche is so written, as it maie be defended, no lesse then impugned? What great inconuenience, what preiudice to our Faith can ensue of al this? Must the Catholike and ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Churche for these pointes be founde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true? Must this now needes be made a good Argument, Some of their liues were sinneful, Ergo, their Doctrine was false?</p>
   <p>Truely these be the matters, with the enlarging where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of his Defence hath risen to so huge a quantitie. About whiche I haue not thought it needeful to bestow muche labour, partly bicause in most of those pointes my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the Apologie yet standeth vnrefelled, partly also bicause it liked me not to emploie good houres in so friuolous and vnfruitful a trauaile, but chiefly bicause what so euer be said by M. Iewel touching these thinges, either on the one side, or on the other, it importeth
<pb facs="24"/> no disprouse of the Catholique doctrine in any Article, whiche specially I haue taken in hande to mainteine.</p>
   <p>Howbeit, the thinges he bringeth in to deface the Churche, must needes with wise menne in this case beare smal credite, being considered vpon whose au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, and reportes they be auouched.</p>
   <p>The Catholikes can not be greatly moued with suche thinges, as are written in preiudice of the Churche, either by them, whose Bookes be of suspected faith, and therefore condemned by the Church, as Auentinus, and Beno <hi>de vita Hildebrandi,</hi> or haue ben corrupted of late yeres by the Lutheranes of Germanie, as Vrspergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,<note place="margin">In Indice librorum prohibito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note>
      <hi>Antonius de Rosellis, Polydorus Vergilius de Inuentori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus rerum, Paschasius,</hi> and others, or who haue benne muche inclined to innouations in Religion, and fauoured the Procedinges of Luther, and his disciples, as Erasmus, Cornelius Agrippa, Carion, Lorichius, Cassander and suche others, or who be knowen to be manifest Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, and professed enemies of the Churche, as Gaspar Hedio the Author of <hi>Paralipomena</hi> added to <hi>Vrspergensis, Anselmus</hi> Rid, Vergerius, Sleidan, Illyricus, Fabritius Montanus, Iacobus Andreae, and many suche others, al whiche M. Iewel allegeth against the Churche, the Popes, and the Clergie boldely, as if they were Doctours of sufficient authoritie, and sound credite, against whom, specially in these matters no exception might be taken.</p>
   <p>As there is no cause why we shoulde greatly esteeme any thing spoken by these, either against the manners of the Clergie, or against the Ceremonies, and customes of the Churche, or against any parte of the Catholique Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, bicause in iudgement the bare worde of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser,
<pb facs="24"/> or of him that otherwise is an il willer, beareth smal credite against any man: So touching the doctrine of Faith, we feare not what so euer M. Iewel allegeth against vs out of the Schoolemenne, Canonistes of al sortes, Summistes, and Glosers, out of the Cardinalles, and those other learned and graue menne appointed by Paulus Tertius to geue information of thinges in the state of the Churche to be refourmed, and out of the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppes speaking their mindes freely in the late Councel of Trent. For we are wel assured, how so euer M. Iewel telleth their tales for them, they helde, and mainteined the doctrine which we professe, in euery condition.</p>
   <p>What so euer therefore he bringeth out of them, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any sound of wordes against the Catholike Faith, as very litle it is, that to that effecte he can bring, though with heapes of their sayinges he hath filled his great Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume: the same is either by heate of Disputation, or by waie of Obiection against the Truthe after the Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical manner, for the better opening of the Truthe, or by vehemencie of zele, or perhappes by humaine ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight vttered, otherwise then by them is determined in their Conclusions, whereof the taking of aduantage is vndue and ouer captious, or by some sleight of M. Iewel falsified and corrupted, or, to saie the least, by vntrue cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction wrested to a sense by the Authour neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
   <p>How so euer it be, they shew them selues either very blinde of iudgement, or very contentious wranglers, or very vaine Ianglers, that allege the wordes of any Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter against the Catholique doctrine, whose whole course of life shewed him to be Catholique. Which is tolde vs
<pb facs="25"/> by S. Augustine, as a moste certaine rule, whereby to vnderstand mennes wordes in matter of Religion. And therefore thus he crieth out vpon the blindenesse of such men, among whom M. Iewel maie take him selfe annum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that wil not vnderstād mens wordes by their dedes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Epist. Parme. li. 3. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Incredibilis est coecitas hominum, &amp; omnino nescio quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum credi posset esse in hominibus tāta peruersitas, nisi experimento verborum suorū factorū{que} patesceret, vsqueadeo se clausos habere cordis oculos, vt cōmemorent sancta Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae testimonia, nec intueantur in factis Prophetarū, quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum intelligenda sint verba Prophetarū.</hi> The blindnesse of men is inoredible, and certainely I wote not how I might make one beleeue, that there were such froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in men, onlesse by the proufe of their wordes and deedes it appeared openly, that the eyes of their harte were so faste shut vp, that they allege the testimonies of the holy Scripture, and doo not behold in the doinges of the Prophetes, how the wordes of the Prophetes are to be vnderstanded.</p>
   <p>Wherefore seing the farre greater parte of M. Iewels Defence consisteth of their sayinges heaped together, of whom some were either them selues, or their workes being vntruly set forth after their death of suspect faith, some found to fauour heretikes, some professed heretikes, some contrariwise knowen by publike profession of their life to be perfite Catholikes: making litle accompt, what they of the one side saie, as being of no credite, specially in matter of Faith, and not doubting but these of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, meant wel and godly, how so euer their wordes by M. Iewel be abused, corrupted, and misconstrued, in consideratiō thereof good Reader, I iudged a short Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="25"/> might suffice in this case: shorte I meane in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of that Huge Volume fraught with so much voide, impertinent, and superfluous stuffe. Otherwise, it is lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I am wel assured, then he shal euer be hable aptly, truly, and directly to confute.</p>
   <p>I saie not, but he maie do eftsones, as he hath twise al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready donne, that is to saie, gather together a huge num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of sayinges out of al sortes of Writers, and printing this Treatie withal, sende vs forth an other great booke, conteining much stuffe to litle purpose, and not once tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the very precise pointes, wherein he is charged with foule errours, and falshed. But to come directly to the pointes by me thoroughly refelled, and with good proufes to iustifie the same, keeping him selfe in from idle ranging abroad in matters not denied, or otherwise im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent: this is that I affirme, he shal neuer be hable to perfourme, though he write againe as muche as Foxe hath raked together into that Donghil of his stincking Martyrs.</p>
   <p>So then I trust good Reader, this my shorter, but more fruiteful trauaile, shal wel content thee. In which I haue defended, and iustified, the chiefe matters of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique doctrine by M. Iewel impugned, and therewith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen his weake Defence.</p>
   <p>In sundrie other pointes also, whiche depende of Doctrine, I haue detected his great and manifolde Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes. Neither haue I ioined issue with him in any point, wherein I haue not sufficiently proued him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiued, or a deceiuer. Wherein as Ignorance maie stande him in some excuse for the one, so muste he beare the gilte of malice for the other. Eche pointe
<pb facs="26"/> here is not handled with like diligence, and like exacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, I graunt, for the matter hath not so required.</p>
   <p>Yet where I haue benne least disposed to take paines, and founde my selfe most weary in answering his friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Obiections, thou shalt finde the truthe sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mainteined, and M. Iewel fully refuted. If any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where thou espie defecte, or insufficiencie, impute the blame to me. If in any parte I shal seeme to haue donne wel, take thou the profite, geue God the praise.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Harding.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>