<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The prologue of the authour / for the declaracyon of this pre∣sent treatyse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1523</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112253_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00895</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11005</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112253</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The prologue of the authour / for the declaracyon of this pre∣sent treatyse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here begynneth a ryght frutefull mater: and hath to name the boke of surueyinge and improume [n] tes</title>
                 <author>Fitzherbert, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pynson (Pinson), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1523</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, lvi, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_prologue">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶The prologue of the authour / for the declaracyon of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent treatyse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Alomon sapientie Primo. Omnis sapientia virtus / honor / di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gnitas / et que{que} scientia a dn̄o deo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sunt. That is to say: all wysdome vertue / honoure / dignyte / and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng / are of our lorde god. Than sithe almighty god our redemer &amp; creatour / by high wysdome / goodnesse / lyberalite / and prouydence / in this transitorie worlde and myserable lyfe: Hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned dyuers estates and degrees in his people &amp; creatures / and some of them: aswell hath endowed with goostly and heuēly wisdome and distynke gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / as with great honour / possessyons / and rychesse with great gyftes &amp; graces / aswell spirytuall as tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall. His highe cōmaundement / chargeth euery {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that is {per}taker of the sayd gyftes or graces / char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably and discretely / the same to distrybute and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde among his poore creatures / That euery poore persone that is wyllynge to laboure duely for his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng / may haue therby conuenyent helpe and sustey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce. And in as moche as the great estates / rulers and gouernours of this realme / whom our sauyour hath so largely and bountuously rewarded / with all suche gyftes / possessyons / and rychesse: haue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to his pleasure and cōmaundement / demysed / 
<pb facs="6"/>
distrybute / and graūted to the creatures of god. and to their fermours and tenauntes / their seuerall pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessyons and inherytaunces / reseruynge to them for the same certayne rentes / customes / and seruyces / to sustayne and vpholde their honours and estates / as to them apertayneth / acordyng to their highe gyftes and graces / wherwith they be so largety endowed. And for the great zele / loue / and confort that I beare to the sayd fermours and tenauntes / and to all other goddes creatures: that they may more surely / easely and profitably encrease and sustayne their pore hous<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde / wyues / and chyldren: and also truely to paye their rentes customes / and seruyces vnto their lord{is} and the honoures of their fermes and tenauntryce. Of late by experyence / I contryued / compyled / and made a treatise for the same poore fermers and tenā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and called it the boke of Husbandrie: the whiche me semed was very necessary for husbande men that vse tyllage / &amp; for many other of dyuers degrees and occupacyons. And where as in the prologue of the sayd boke I demaunded and asked a questyon / and that was this. Whervnto is euery man ordayned as playnely it dothe appere in the prologue of the same In lyke maner in the prologue of this treatise / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I entende by the suffraūce and helpe of our lorde Iesu / to contryue / compyle / and make to the profyte of all noble men and women bothe spyrituall &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall / I demaunde another questyon / and that is this. Howe &amp; by what maner / do all these great esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and noblemen and women lyue and maynteyne
<pb facs="6"/>
their honour and degre? and in myne opinyon / their honour and degre is vpholden and maynteyned / by reason of their rentes / issues / reuenewes / and profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that come of their maners / lordshippes / landes &amp; tenementes to them belongyng. Than it is necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to be knowen / howe all these maners / lordships / landes / &amp; tenement{is} shulde be extēded / surueyed / but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / boūded / and valued in euery parte: that the said estates shulde nat be disceyued / defrauded / nor dishe ryted of their possessyons / rentes / customes / and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyces / the whiche they haue to thē reserued / for mayn teynaunce of their estates and degrees. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there be no parcell therof lost nor imbeselde / and than may the lorde of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd maners / lordshippes / landes / and tenementes / haue parfyte knowledge where the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delyeth. What euery parcell is worthe / and who is his freholders / copyeholders / customarye tenaunte / or tenaunt at his wyll. And what rentes / customes / and seruice he ought to haue of them / with many mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>artycles / as here after shalbe declared. Wherefore it is necessary that euery great estate / bothe men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of worship / that haue great possessyons of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and tenementes / shulde haue a Surueyour that can extende / but / and bounde / and value them. And therof to make a boke in parchement / bearyng a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne date / after the maner &amp; forme as I shall make an intytulynge / and to amende it where he semethe conuenyent. Quia facilius est addere quam de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo facere. That is for to saye / It is lighter to adde / refourme / or correcte / thanne for to make newe and
<pb facs="7"/>
perfyte. And the Surueyour to leaue the sayd boke made by hym with his lorde in maner of a regyster / whervnto the same Surueyour or another offycer / maye alway haue resort / whan nede shall requyre to loke vpon. And that boke so truely made / maye be a regyster and sure euydence: that the lorde / his frehol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders / copye holders / nor tenauntes / shall neuer lose landes nor rentes / customes / nor seruyces: but euery man that redeth the boke / shall {per}fitely knowe where the lādes lye / whose it was at the day of the makyng of the sayd boke / and whose it is. Than if the owner make a true pee / degre / or cōueyaunce / by discente or by purchace vnto the said landes or lordshippes. and specially if the names of the lordes and tenaūtes that occupy / might be renewed ones ī fourtie or threscore yeres. for than it wolde be as a perpetuall and sure euydēce for euer / to put away all strife and varyaūce bytwene lorde and lorde / lorde and tenaunt / tenaunt and tenaunt / in good quyetnesse &amp; peace. But of one thyng I pronounce and declare / and take god to my recorde: that I make this boke all onely / to thentent that the lordes / the freholders nor their heyres <abbr>shuld</abbr>
nat be disheryt / nor haue their landes lost nor imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selde nor encroched by one from another / and to non other entent. And for that I aduertyse and exorte on goddes behalfe / all maner of persons as well lordes as other. That whan the lord{is} or freholders / knowe where their landes lye and what euery pasture or {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell is worthe by the yere. That the lordes nor the ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners therof do nat heyghten their rentes of their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes
<pb facs="7"/>
/ or to cause them to pay more rent or a gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fyne / than they haue ben acustomed to do in tyme past. For as me semeth / a gretter charyte nor almes dede a man may nat well do / than vpon his owne te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nauntes. And also to the contrarie / a gretter bribery nor extorcyon a man can nat do / than vpon his owne tenaūtes / for they dare nat say nay nor yet cōplayne / and therfore on their soules go it that so do and nat on myne. Parauēture the lorde wyll say it is nat his dede it was his Surueyours / but that can nat be so for saynt Augustyne saythe. Qui {per} alium facit per seipsum facere videtur. That is to say: he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maūdeth another man to do a thyng he dothe it hym selfe. And there be two princypals in one acte doyng and also he saythe. Consenscientes et agētes pari pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na puniantur. That is to say / the consentours and the doers shall be lyke punysshed. at grammer scole I lerned a vers and that is this. Dum poteris quid vis possis cognoscere quid sis. That is to say / whan thou mayst do what thou wylte / thou mayst knowe what thou arte. that is to wytte / good or yuell. But for a grounde of this treatyse the whiche I do note / and calle it the boke of Surueyng and of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouementes / I do take an olde statute named Extenta manerii / as a principall groūde therof: as herafter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sueth.</p>
   <trailer>¶Explicit.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>