<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112086_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11059</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21325</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of questions and answers vpon Genesis : Containing those questions that are most eminent and pertinent, vpon the sixe first chapters of the same booke: collected out of ancient and recent writers; both briefly and subtilly propounded and expounded, by Alexander Rosse, of Aberdine, preacher at Saint Maries neere Southampton, and one of his Maiesites chaplaines</title>
                 <author>Ross, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Constable, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 116 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>Q. <hi>VVHo wrote these bookes of</hi> Moses?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Himselfe: proofe; hee was the first that writ in the world. Secondly, The holy Ghost testifieth the same, <hi>Exo. 24.4. Deu. 31.9.</hi> and Christ, <hi>Iohn 1.45.</hi> and <hi>5.46.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Q. <hi>When wrote he this first Booke?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Before the Israelites went from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> Reas. <hi>1.</hi> Because then, feeding his Father-in-lawes sheepe <hi>40.</hi> yeeres, in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> he was most at leysure to write. Rea. <hi>2.</hi> To comfort the Hebrewes, beeing oppressed with Egyptian seruitude; for in this Booke they read the life and death of their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours; their courage; patience; vertue in affliction; Gods promises to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
that after.<hi>400</hi> yeares seruitude in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they should be deliuered, and inioy the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Q. <hi>How came</hi> Moses <hi>to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of these things contained in this Booke?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Either by reuelation from God, or by tradition of his Ancestors: for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of these things <hi>Moses</hi> had from <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephs</hi> children; they of <hi>Ioseph;</hi> he of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob; Iacob</hi> of <hi>Isaac;</hi> he of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and he of <hi>Shem; Shem</hi> of <hi>Noe;</hi> he of <hi>Methusalem;</hi> and he of <hi>Adam,</hi> with whom he liued <hi>243.</hi> yeeres.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>