<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my worthy Friend, Mr. PHILIP MASSINGER, vpon his Tragae-Co∣moedie, call'd The Emperour of the East.</title>
           <author>Cokaine, Aston</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112418_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07238</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112418</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my worthy Friend, Mr. PHILIP MASSINGER, vpon his Tragae-Co∣moedie, call'd The Emperour of the East.</title>
                 <author>Cokaine, Aston</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Emperour of the East· : A tragæ-comœdie. The scæne Constantinople. As it hath bene diuers times acted, at the Black-friers, and Globe play-houses, by the Kings Maiesties Seruants. Written by Philip Massinger</title>
                 <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomia">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <lg>
      <head>To my worthy Friend, Mr. PHILIP MASSINGER, vpon his Tragae-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moedie, call'd <hi>The Emperour of the East.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>SVffer, my friend, these lines to haue the grace,</l>
      <l>That they may bee a mole on <hi>Venus</hi> face.</l>
      <l>There is no fault about thy Booke, but this,</l>
      <l>And it will shew how faire thy Emperour is.</l>
      <l>Thou more then Poet, our <hi>Mercurie</hi> (that art</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Apollo's</hi> Messenger, and do'st impart</l>
      <l>His best expressions to our eares) liue long</l>
      <l>To purifie the slighted English tongue,</l>
      <l>That both the <hi>Nymphes</hi> of <hi>Tagus,</hi> and of <hi>Poe,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>May not henceforth despise our language so.</l>
      <l>Nor could they doe it, if they ere had seene</l>
      <l>The matchlesse features of the faerie Queene;</l>
      <l>Read <hi>Iohnson, Shakespeare, Beaumont, Fletcher,</hi> or</l>
      <l>Thy neat-limnd peeces, skilfull <hi>Massinger.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Thou knowne, all the <hi>Castillians</hi> must confesse</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Vega de Carpio</hi> thy foile, and blesse</l>
      <l>His language can translate thee, and the fine</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Italian</hi> witts, yeeld to this worke of thine.</l>
      <l>Were old <hi>Pythagoras</hi> aliue againe,</l>
      <l>In thee hee might finde reason to maintaine</l>
      <l>His Paradox; that soules by transmigration</l>
      <l>In diuers bodies make their habitation,</l>
      <l>And more; that all Poetik soules yet knowne</l>
      <l>Are met in thee, vnited, and made one.</l>
      <l>This is a truth, not an applause. I am</l>
      <l>One that at farthest distance view thy flame,</l>
      <l>Yet may pronounce, that were <hi>Apollo</hi> dead,</l>
      <l>In thee his Poesie might all bee read.</l>
      <l>Forbeare thy modestie. Thy Emper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urs veine</l>
      <l>Shall liue admir'd, when Poets shall complaine.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>It is a patterne of too high a reach</l>
      <l>And what great <hi>Phoebus</hi> might the Muses teach.</l>
      <l>Let it liue therefore, and I dare bee bold</l>
      <l>To say, it with the world shall not grow old.</l>
      <signed>Aston Cokaine.</signed>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>A friend to the Author, and well-wisher to the Reader.</head>
      <l>WHO with a liberall hand, freely bestowes</l>
      <l>His bounty, on all commers, and yet knowes</l>
      <l>No ebbe, nor formall limits, but proceeds</l>
      <l>Continuing his hospitable deeds,</l>
      <l>With dayly welcome, shall aduance his name</l>
      <l>Beyond the art of flatterie: with such, fame</l>
      <l>May yours (deare friend) compare. Your muse hath bene</l>
      <l>Most bountifull, and I haue often seene</l>
      <l>The willing seates receaue such as haue fedd,</l>
      <l>And risen thankefull; yet were some mis-led</l>
      <l>By <hi>Nicetie,</hi> when this faire Banquet came</l>
      <l>(So I allude) their stomacks were to blame,</l>
      <l>Because that excellent sharpe, and poinant sauce</l>
      <l>Was wanting, they arose without due grace,</l>
      <l>Loe thus a second time hee doth inuite you:</l>
      <l>Bee your owne Caruers, and it may delight you.</l>
      <signed>Iohn Clauell.</signed>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>To my true friend, and Kinsman: PHILIP MASSINGER.</head>
      <l>I Take not vp on trust; nor am I lead</l>
      <l>By an implicit Faith: what I haue read</l>
      <l>With an impartiall censure I dare crowne</l>
      <l>With a deseru'd applause, how ere cri'd downe</l>
      <l>By such whose malice will not let 'em bee</l>
      <l>Equall to any peece limnd forth by thee.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Contemne their poore detraction, and still write</l>
      <l>Poems like this, that can indure the light,</l>
      <l>And search of abler iudgements. This will raise</l>
      <l>Thy Name, the others Scandall is thy praise.</l>
      <l>This oft perus'd by graue witts, shall liue long,</l>
      <l>Not dye as soone, as pass'd the Actors tongue,</l>
      <l>(The fate of slighter toyes) And I must say</l>
      <l>Tis not enough to make a passing play,</l>
      <l>In a true Poet. Workes that should indure</l>
      <l>Must haue a Genius in 'em strong, as pure.</l>
      <l>And such is thine friend; nor shall time deuoure</l>
      <l>The well form'd features of thy Emperour.</l>
      <signed>William Singleton.</signed>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>