<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Fore-speech of Master I. S. to the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112681_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07529</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17913</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112681</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Fore-speech of Master I. S. to the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Papisto-mastix, or The protestants religion defended : Shewing briefely when the great compound heresie of poperie first sprange; how it grew peece by peece till Antichrist was disclosed; how it hath been consumed by the breath of Gods mouth: and when it shall be cut downe and withered. By William Middleton Bachelor of Diuinitie, and minister of Hardwicke in Cambridge-shire</title>
                 <author>Middleton, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 203, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="master_to_author">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Fore-speech of Master <hi>I. S.</hi> to the Author.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my chaunce (good Master M.) not long since to bee encountred by a learned Gentleman in the controuersie between the Papists and vs, whose ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments I could not answere, to my great griefe, and offence of diuers there present; I then wished your presence, and still desired your helpe for my deliuerie out of that Labirinth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into he brought me. I know that <hi>Quaedam falsa maiorem habent speciem probabilitatis, quàm quaedam vera,</hi> (as the Philosopher saith,) and therfore I write not this as wauering in my faith: for who so shall stagger for euerie argument whereunto he cannot make a learned solution, must either be a profound Clerke, or of no faith at all; but for my better satisfaction, and preparation vnto the like encounter, let me entreat <hi>vt mihi lumen de tuo lumine accendas.</hi> For accomplishing whereof, I will referre you to the discourse following, wherein for auoiding of the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious repetition of <hi>inquam,</hi> and <hi>inquit,</hi> I haue set downe his oppositions vnder the name of <hi>Pa.</hi> And my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweres thereunto vnder the name of <hi>Pro.</hi>
   </p>
   <div type="authors_answer">
      <head>The Authors Answere.</head>
      <p>SIr, I see no cause yet, why I should thinke other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of you, than I haue done euer since I first knew you. We were brought vp both together in the same Vniuersitie the same Colledge, the same Chamber, and vnder the same Tutor, and it hath
<pb facs="4"/>
pleased you euer since to acknowledge mee as one of your poore friends, and so haue I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged you as my christian brother; and therefore my full trust in the mercie of God is, that now in our age, after so long triall one of another, Poperie shall not be able to part vs. The Gentleman that encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with you, hath shewed little learning, and lesse wit in this encounter, but if euerie finger and toe that he hath, could write bookes, and euerie haire of his head, speake parables: yet <hi>Rome</hi> will fall doe what he can, and the ruines of it shall neuer be reedified. It is your modestie that makes you vnfit, but not vnable to answere such popish garrulitie, &amp; that cannot greeue you, if you be wise, nor offend other, vnlesse they be fooles, <hi>turbantur quia non illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minantur,</hi> saith <hi>Austine,</hi> and therefore they that finde themselues troubled with such blinde argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts, as this Gentleman of yours doth afford vs, may well be thought to haue little light in them: doe but look ouer my answere, &amp; confer my <hi>inquam,</hi> with his <hi>inquit,</hi> without partialitie, and then a Gods name feed in that pasture you finde best fenced. God the Father of our Lord Iesus Christ so guide and streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then you and your family against <hi>Iezabel</hi> and her Prophets, that when your day of reckoning shall come, you may answere cheerefully with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Esay, Loe, heere am I, and the children which God hath giuen mee.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>