<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
Honourable the Lord
Viscont Cranborn.</title>
           <author>Grimeston, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112465_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07266</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17661</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112465</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
Honourable the Lord
Viscont Cranborn.</title>
                 <author>Grimeston, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The heroyk life and deplorable death of the most Christian King Henry the fourth : Addressed to his immortall memory; by P: Mathieu, counceller and historiographer of France. Translated by Ed: Grimeston, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Matthieu, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 135, 134-189, 183-190, 1, 170, 30 pages, portraits (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
Honourable the Lord
Viscont Cranborn.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good Lord: I haue presumed
to offer this discourse vnto your
view, not for that you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
it not in the Originall, or
to instruct your knowledge, the
French tongue beeing familiar
vnto you, and the subiect, with all the Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
as well knowne as to any; but to make you
Censor of the worke, and of the Authors integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
hauing remained in that Court, and receiued
fauours from that great King, liuing in the height
of worldly felicity, and with all beene an eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of that sad and mournfull spectacle, and of
the generall consternation of the French, lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
the Tragicall and sodaine death of their King,
to their ir-reparable losse.</p>
   <p>This worke may happily seeme to some vnseaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
when as his death is in a manner forgotten,
there hauing also beene so many Pamphlets, and
petty discourses published of that subiect. But as
my Authors excuse is, That time can prescribe no
bounds to their sorrow, nor reason moderate their
griefe, which renues with time, and therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
vnseasonable to lament so great a losse. So I
finding it written by an eloquent Pen, and by his
owne Historiographer, who attended on him dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
to record both his words and Actions, and who
<pb facs="3"/>
both could and hath written many particularities
vpon this Accident, which were vnknowne to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
haue thought it as worthy the knowledge of
our Nation as any of the rest, and I hope will giue
the Reader more content.</p>
   <p>I haue presumed to make your Lordship Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron
of my labour, both for that you can Iudge if
there bee any thing defectiue, and in respect of my
owne priuate obligation, hauing receiued many
fauours from your Lordship during my aboade
in France, with that hopefull Gentleman Maister
<hi>Henry Howard:</hi> Vouchsafe it my good Lord your
countenance, and accept it as a poore testimonie
of his thankfulnesse, who is and will be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Alwayes ready to
do you seruice:
Ed: Grimeston.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>