<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112286_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07071</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17479</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112286</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The malcontent : By Iohn Marston. 1604</title>
                 <author>Marston, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am an ill Oratour; and in truth, vse to indite more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly then eloquently, for t'is my custome to speake as I think, and write as I speake.</p>
   <p>In plainenesse therefore vnderstand, that in some things I have willingly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as in supposing a Duke of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and in taking names different from that Citties families: for which some may wittily accuse me, but my defence shall bee as honest, as many reproofes vnto mee have been most malicious. Since (I heartily protest) t'was my care to write so farre from reasonable offence, that even strangers, in whose State I layd my Scene, should not from thence draw any disgrace to any, dead or living. Yet in despight of my indevors, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, some have bin most vnadvisedly over-cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in mis-interpreting me, &amp; with subtilty (as deep as hell) have maliciously spread ill rumors, which springing from themselves, might to themselves have heavily returned. Surely I desire to satisfie eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firme spirit, who in all his actions, proposeth to himselfe no more ends then God and vertue doe, whose intentions are alwayes simple: to such I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test,
<pb facs="3"/>
that with my free vnderstanding, I have not glanced at disgrace of any, but of those, whose vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet studies labor innovation, contempt of holy policie, reverent comely superiority, and establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed vnity: for the rest of my supposed tartnesse, I feare not, but vnto every worthy mind t'wil be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved so generall and honest, as may modestly passe with the freedome of a Satyre. I would faine leave the paper; onely one thing afflicts mee, to thinke that Scenes invented, meerely to be spoken, should be inforcively published to be read, &amp; that the least hurt I can receive, is to do my selfe the wrong. But since others otherwise would doe me more, the least inconvenience is to be accepted. I have my selfe therefore set forth this Comedy; but so, that my inforced absence must much relye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Printers discretion: but I shal intreat, slight errors in orthography may bee as slightly or'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed; and that the vnhandsome shape which this trifle in reading presents, may bee pardoned, for the pleasure it once afforded you, when it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented with the soule of lively action.</p>
   <closer>Me mea sequentur fata.
<signed>I. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>