<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOV∣RABLE LORD AND highly renowned Peere of this Kingdome, EDWARD Earle of Dorset, &amp;c. Knight of the most Noble order of the garter, Lord High Chamberlaine unto her most Soveraigne Majesty, QVEENE of great Brittane, &amp;c. And one of the Lords of his Majesties most honourable privy Councell. Edward May wisheth all health and glory.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112479_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07320</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17709</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112479</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOV∣RABLE LORD AND highly renowned Peere of this Kingdome, EDWARD Earle of Dorset, &amp;c. Knight of the most Noble order of the garter, Lord High Chamberlaine unto her most Soveraigne Majesty, QVEENE of great Brittane, &amp;c. And one of the Lords of his Majesties most honourable privy Councell. Edward May wisheth all health and glory.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most certaine and true relation of a strange monster or serpent found in the left ventricle of the heart of Iohn Pennant, Gentleman, of the age of 21. yeares. By Edward May Doctor of Philosophy and Physick, and professor elect of them, in the colledge of the academy of noble-men, called the Musæum Minervæ: physitian also extraordinary unto her most Sacred Majesty, Queene of great Brittany, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>May, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, folded plates, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE LORD AND highly renowned Peere of this Kingdome, EDWARD Earle of Dorset, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Knight of the most Noble order of the garter, Lord High Chamberlaine unto her most Soveraigne Majesty, QVEENE of <hi>great Brittane,</hi> &amp;c. And one of the Lords of his Majesties most honourable privy Councell. <hi>Edward May</hi> wisheth all health and glory.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR this Treatise I seeke no patronage, for if the Relation and the Author cannot defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, let them both suffer. A Swallow flies better then a Swanne, though his wing be lesse: And one little Diamond will buy 17. of <pb facs="3"/>those stones that were drawne to <hi>S. Paules Church</hi> of 17. Tunnes: yet whether this Description of mine be good, or great, worthy or otherwise, it is not dedicated to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as a matter presuming towards your worth, or presence, but as a publike obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the face of the world, of my future and more solid gratitude: You have honoured me before the Noble Peeres, and highest Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors of the Kingdome: You have otherwise done me reall favours, what am I, or what is in me that you have not conquered? and not by these benefits to me only, but these many yeares my observations of your most Noble nature, your more then humane partes, your vast and incredible comprehension of all things, both essentiall and accidentall to your place and dignity. Your innumerable merits and that universall acclamation of all men whatsoever, have made me, more your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble servant then you know, and when after a short space God shall giue me to sit a little qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, tending mine own affaires, your Lordship shall see, not by my writings but by my doings, that I am more your Lordships then any French or thrice devoted servant.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>