<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Mason, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112409_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07215</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17615</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112409</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Mason, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of sorcerie : VVherein the wicked impietie of charmers, inchanters, and such like, is discouered and confuted. By Iames Mason, Master of Artes</title>
                 <author>Mason, James, m.a</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 103, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou maiest maruaile (gentle reader)
what hath moooued mee (after so many
zealous and learned Diuines) to take in
hand this treatise against sorcery. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I haue thought it good to certifie
thee (in some measure) of my meaning
herein. It was my chance to fall into communication with
a notable supporter of those wicked vanities, which are
spoken against in this booke: who not contented to practise
the same himselfe, went about to perswade others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto:
and to that end had framed reasons and arguments
to vphold his assertion. Which when I heard, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood,
considering that he was a man of place, and some
learning, and therefore might preuaile the more in this
mischieuous deuise: I determined to search out what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
had written concerning that matter. But finding
them all that I could hit vpon to be more occupied in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
inuectiues against sorcerie in generall; then in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
setting downe what it was, or wherein it consisted:
thereby leauing a dare open to these vaine and wicked
men to creepe out at: by reason the chiefe grounds were
not taken away, whereon they stand. Therefore I resolued
to make some treatise of mine own. And because I thought
I should haue thereby fit occasion, both to answer his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and also to speake of other matters very meete and
necessarie in this case: I made choice of this text in the
<pb facs="3"/>
Actes of the Apostles: and so much the rather, for that it
was a place alleadged by the aforesaid partie himselfe:
that so I might (as it were,) <hi>vna fidelia duos parietes
dealbare.</hi> That is (as we say) stoppe two gappes with one
bush; both answering to the aduersaries reasons, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
opening the meaning of the said place, to all such sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
and true meaning Christians, as should heare or reade
the same. Howbeit at the first I had no such purpose, as to
make it common to all; but onely to such of my friends and
acquaintance, to whom I meant to commit it, and my selfe
should thinke good. Notwithstanding, afterward at my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid
friends request, who did beare me in hand, that it
would be profitable to the Church of God (if it should come
abroad into the open view of the world,) at the last▪ I yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
as thou seest. God graunt that it may worke that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
which I wish for: the which if I shall perceiue, it shall
encourage me to imploy my studies hereafter, for thy fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
benefit. In the meane while I commit thee to the tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of him, who is able to doe more then we can wish, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire.
And so I bid thee heartily farewell.</p>
   <signed>Iames Mason.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>