<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his witty and ingenious friend Master Iohn Melton:</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112560_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07418</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17804</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112560</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his witty and ingenious friend Master Iohn Melton:</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Astrologaster, or, The figvre-caster : Rather the arraignment of artlesse astrologers, and fortune-tellers, that cheat many ignorant people vnder the pretence of foretelling things to come, of telling things that are past, finding out things that are lost, expounding dreames, calculating deaths and natiuities, once againe brought to the barre. By Iohn Melton</title>
                 <author>Melton, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 4</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80 pages, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To his witty and ingenious friend Master <hi>Iohn Melton:</hi>
   </head>
   <l>I cannot chuse but laugh to thinke how all</l>
   <l>The broode of Figure-casting-knaues will braule</l>
   <l>When they by chance or rather mischance looke</l>
   <l>Vpon the title of thy well writ booke:</l>
   <l>Which in a True-borne-straine of wit displayes.</l>
   <l>Their grose abuses and how many wayes,</l>
   <l>They cheat old women, men, and maids, and such</l>
   <l>That build vpon their Art and do not gruch</l>
   <l>To giue them mony to be cheated when,</l>
   <l>They lose things that no Art can finde agen.</l>
   <l>But now I hope they will be wiser since</l>
   <l>Thy Pen hath truly blazd their Impudence,</l>
   <l>And when they lose gold, rather then bestow</l>
   <l>More on a Knaue; to let the first gold goe.</l>
   <l>For it is meere improuidence to care,</l>
   <l>For things drownd in the Ocean of despaire.</l>
   <l>Therefore if all beleeuing fooles could finde</l>
   <l>Like thee, their pollitike tricks wherewith they blinde,</l>
   <l>Their easie Natures; they, would then proclame,</l>
   <l>All Figure-sellers, Knaues and sharpely blame</l>
   <l>Themselues for being guld, and neuer more</l>
   <l>Whatere they lose, frequent them as before.</l>
   <l>Then would all Artlesse Empericks forsake.</l>
   <l>Cheating and study lying Almanacks.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Maslin, <hi>Master of Art and sometime Student of</hi> Trinity <hi>Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>