<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the vnderstanding Reader.</title>
           <author>Machin, Lewes</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112116_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06975</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17398</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the vnderstanding Reader.</title>
                 <author>Machin, Lewes</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dumbe knight : A historicall comedy, acted sundry times by the children of his Maiesties Reuels</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bache, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>74 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the vnderstanding Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>VMOR that <hi>Hydra</hi> headed Monster, with more tongues then eyes, by help of his intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencer enuy hath made strange miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions on this dumbe Knight, which then could not answere for himselfe: but now this publication doth vnty his tongue, to answer the obiections of all sharp critticall censures which heretofore haue vndeseruedly past vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. And for my part (I protest) the wrongs I haue receiued by some (whose worths I will not traduce) with a milde neglect I haue laught at their follies; for I thinke my selfe happy, because I haue beene enuyde, since the best now in grace haue beene sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to some slanderous tongues that want worth themselues, and thinke it great praise to them to detract praise from other that deserue it; yet hauing a partner in the wrong, whose worth hath beene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten approued, I count the wrong but halfe a wrong, because hee knowes best how to answer for himselfe: But I now in his absence, make this Apologie, both for him and me. Thus leauing you and the booke together, I euer rest yours.</p>
   <signed>Lewes Machin.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>