<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112211_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15654</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21797</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112211</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pithie exposition vpon the. 51. Psalme intituled, Miserere mei deus, &amp;c : Also a godly meditation, vpon the. 31. Psalme, intituled, In te Domine speraui. Written by Hierome of Ferrarie; and now newly augmented and amended, by Abraham Fleming</title>
                 <author>Savonarola, Girolamo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>256 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THou hast here (Christian Reader) a comfortable dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, wherein to exercise thy selfe, at suche time as thou shalt feele in thy selfe a disposition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion. It is but litle, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing pithie: and worthie to be read, marked, &amp; learned: for ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are manifestly set downe, the passions of a penitent sinner, his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of conscience, his sorowe for his transgression, his confession of his offence, his inuocation vppon God for remission, his confidence to be comforted, his hope to obteine
<pb facs="8"/> mercie: &amp; what good motion soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it pleaseth the spirit of God to worke in such, as he vouchsafeth, of his vnspeakable bountie &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, to stirre vp in the heartes of all Christian Conuerts. And sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the benefite of this booke, in consideration of the substance and matter therin comprised, is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; singular: so it ought with hotter zeale to be embraced, &amp; as a Iewell of ioy, among precious pearles and costlie treasure, to be reposed. For, whereas they, seruing only the delight of the eye, &amp; the satisfying of the fansie, are estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (and not without desert) as
<pb facs="8"/> things passing precious: this booke, in somuch as it hath an office of more excellencie, &amp; cōforteth the soule with spirituall consolation, is to be takē (as it is) for a thing much more valuable. Hath the sting of sinne hurt thee? Come hither, and learne a remedie. Hath the horror &amp; haynousnesse of thine offences dismayed thee? Come hither, here is a recept to increase thy courage. Haue wicked men entised thee to wallowe with them in the filthie puddles of vncleane life? Come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, here thou shalt know at what well to fetch water, that thou maist be cleansed. Hast thou not the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="9"/> to withstand the assaultes of the tempter, I meane old Sathan the malicious enimie of mankinde? Come hither, this booke will send thee to the storehouse of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where thou shalt finde furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to fortifie &amp; make thee strōg. Finally, art thou infected with any carnall venome? Hast thee hither, here thou shalt soone learne what Apothecarie hath the best &amp; most souereigne Mithridatū, euē Christ Iesus our Sauiour. Wherfore, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not the vse of this booke: for as the benefite thereof is singular: so dutie requireth that it be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly regarded. Farewell. Thine to vse:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>