<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Honourable Knight, Sir George Riuers of Chafford, in the County of KENT.</title>
           <author>I., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112106_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06937</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17363</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112106</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Honourable Knight, Sir George Riuers of Chafford, in the County of KENT.</title>
                 <author>I., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The inrichment of the Weald of Kent: or, A direction to the husbandman, for the true ordering, manuring, and inriching of all the grounds within the wealds of Kent and Sussex, and may generally serue for all the grounds in England, of that nature : as, 1. Shewing the nature of all wealdish grounds, comparing it with the soyle of the shires at large. 2. Declaring what the marle is, and the seuerall sorts thereof, and where it is vsually found. 3. The profitable vse of marle, and other rich manurings, as well in each sort of arable land, as also for the encrease of corne and pasture through the kingdome. Painfully gathered for the good of this iland, by a man of great eminence and worth</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 23, 1 page, 1 folded leaf of plates, 1 map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Honourable Knight, Sir <hi>George Riuers</hi> of <hi>Chafford, in the</hi> County of KENT.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad I no scale (more then this bare and plaine moulded Epistle) by which to come to your Worships eares, yet in respect of the honest Liuery which it carries (being necessary and husbandly collections, especially gathered for the Country and Soile wherein you liue) I know, it cannot chuse but finde both fauour and mercy in your acceptation; but when I call vp into my consideration, the great worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of your experience in this and all other the like affaires, which tend to the generall benefit of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, and weigh the excellency of your wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, iudgement, bounty, and affection vnto hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (which giue both strength and aduancement to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this nature) I could not but take vnto my selfe a double encouragement, and boldly say vnto this worke which I offer to your goodnesse; Goe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb facs="3"/>
with all thy sweetnesse before him, he that so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knowes all which thou canst or wouldst discouer; he that is able both to correct and amend any thing that is imperfect in thee, hee, for vertues sake, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forsake thee. Beleeue mee (worthy Sir) should this subiect wish it selfe a Patron, I doe not thinke, it could wish beyond you; for you are a volumne full of all that of which it intreateth: witnesse your yeeres, your place, your supportation of the poore, and your continuall imployments; with any of which, there is not (of your Ranke) a second liuing in your Country, to walke hand in hand with you; Being then (deare Sir) the oldest and best friend to your Country; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake neither her, nor this which comes to serue it; and though in this Glasse some lineaments may appeare im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, yet by the helpe of your fauour (though little be exact or most excellent) nothing shall bee grosse or vnworthy the suruay of your worthier patience. And so I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to be commanded, <hi>R. I.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>