<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Maister Hardinge.</title>
           <author>Sarisburie, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112182_Bo1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04468</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14600.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112182</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Maister Hardinge.</title>
                 <author>Sarisburie, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Apologie of the Churche of Englande : conteininge an answeare to a certaine booke lately set foorthe by M. Hardinge, and entituled, A confutation of &amp;c. By Iohn Iewel Bishop of Sarisburie</title>
                 <author>Jewel, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 742, 18 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_author">
   <pb facs="387"/>
   <head>To Maister Hardinge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T appeareth, M. Hardinge, by that yee
haue lately sente vs ouer, and specially by the vnpleasante
verdure of your speache, that my late Replie hath somme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
disordered your quiete minde. VVhiche thinge
notwithstandinge I mighte easily haue gheassed, was not
vnlikely to comme to passe, specially beinge before not vtterly vnskilful of
your affections, Yet, as I neuer sought to write any thinge, that of pourpose,
and iustely mighte offende you (the righte of the cause, and the Defence of
the Truthe euermore foreprised) euen so am I nowe righte soary, to see you
so vnhable to maister your passions, and so vnaduisedly to make them open
vnto so many. If it greeue you in respecte of your credite, for that I haue
thus discouered your errours, that was your faulte: it was not mine. If yee
had not made your errours knowen, they shoulde neuer, of my parte, haue
benne discouered. If you knewe, how soary I am in your behalfe, yee would
not so impatientely be offended.</p>
   <p>It misliketh you, that I haue alleged so many Doctours, and Councelles,
and, as you saie, haue so ambitiously painted my Margine with so many
Authorities, bothe Greeke, and Latine. Yet you, for your parte, haue not
spared, ouer and bisides these twoo tongues, to painte your Margine, for a
surcharge, with woordes in Hebrewe: bisides other sutche rankes of your
Englishe Scholies, so many, so thicke, and so close togeather, that it were a
harde mater, to force in one woorde of Truthe to stande emongest them. It
is no courteous dealinge, M. Hardinge, to reproue that in others, that you so
commonly doo your selfe.</p>
   <p>If the Number of Doctours haue offended you, I doo not marueile: A
cowardely Chalenger woulde alwaies wisshe the Defendente to comme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed
vnto the fighte. If I had alleged, either no Doctours at al, or nothinge
to pourpose, as your woonte commonly is to doo, yee would haue borne it a
greate deale better. How be it, my Authorities of Doctours, and Councelles,
be they neuer so many, yet, as you haue vsed them, are fewe yenough. For of
the whole number, by your good skil, more then three partes are leafte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched.
And in deede this was the wiseste waie. Children, where they
cannot reade, thinke it beste, to skippe ouer.</p>
   <p>VVhereas I examine, and laie abroade al the partes, and branches of
your Argumentes, and shewe, how directly yee growe to your Conclusions,
that your Reader maie see, by what weapons yee seeke to maister him, this
you saie is a kinde of scoffinge. Yee telle me, I racke, and alter, and abuse your
<pb facs="388"/>
Argumentes, and plaie with shadowes of mine owne. But, M. Hardinge, if
yee wil haue your Argumentes to passe smoothely without controlment, then
learne hencefoorthe to make them better. Yee are ouer tender, if yee looke to
speake, what yee liste, and yet to heare nothinge, but to your likinge: and, to
sende abroade sutche simple wares, to serue the people, and yet maie suffer
noman to telle you of it. Verily, where yee saie, I haue of pourpose Changed
your Argumentes, if yee make them otherwise, then I haue made them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge
alwaies an eie vnto your Conclusion, yee shalbe forced to make them
woorse. Touchinge the Scoffes, wherewith yee finde your selfe so mutche
agreeued, doubtelesse, who so had that grace, that is in you, as maie wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
throughout al your Bookes, might soone deserue to be called a scoffer.</p>
   <p>VVhere yee saie, you, and your Felowes haue espied a thousande fowle
greate Lies in my writinges: had not one of you benne a greate Father of
Lies, ye coulde neuer haue hitte so readily vpon the number. Sutche an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditoure,
I trowe,<note place="margin">Laurent. Surius Carthusian. In praefatione in Nauclerum.</note> was he, that founde vs oute eleuen thousande Lies in Slei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans
storie. The very multitude hereof, and the hugenesse of the heape, as
it be wraieth wel your stomake, so in any indifferent iudgemente, it decaieth
the credite of your reckeninge. A man maie reasonably thinke, it is as pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible,
to finde twoo hundred, and fiftie Vntruthes in your Booke, as in mine
to finde a thousande. Verily, as I neuer minded to defende any thinge, what
so euer, that in any my writinges, shalbe founde amisse, so I see, by the viewe
of your accomptes, it were no harde mater, with your eies, to finde Vntruthes
in the Gospel. For what so euer I saie, be it neuer so true, yet, if it like not
your taste, it is a Lie: VVhatsoeuer I allege, or translate, it is corrupted. So
euil is my lucke: I can touche nothinge, but it is either too mutche, or too litle:
or too shorte, or too longe: or too blacke, or too white: or one waie, or other it
standeth awry.<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hardinge, Reioinder: Fol. 203. b.</note> If I translate, <hi>Nonnulli Sacerdotes, Sundrie Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes,</hi>
yee crie oute, A corrupter, a falsarie. I shoulde haue saide, <hi>Certaine
Priestes,</hi> or, <hi>Somme Priestes:</hi> but I shoulde not in any wise haue saide,
<hi>Sundrie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If I translate, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Vnà nutritos, Fedde togeather,</hi> yee telle
the worlde, It is Falsehedde, it is fowle corruption. Thus, yee saie, I shoulde
haue translated it,<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hardinge, Reioinder: Fol. 115. b.</note>
      <hi>Eodem cibo alitos, Fedde vvith one kinde of
meate:</hi> as if <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> in Greeke, were not <hi>Vnà</hi> in Latine, or had not Relation to
the Place. Deale herein with your frendes, M. Hardinge, as you maie: The
Greeke Reader wil allow you no sutch Translations. If I happen to saie, <hi>M.
Hard, saithe, The thing, that vvee receiue in the Sacramente, is no
Breade,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioind. fol. 163. b.</note> Yee crie, Alarma: <hi>Looke,</hi> yee saie, <hi>in my Booke, Reader: M.
<pb facs="388"/>
Ievvel is an vntrue man: Here he is taken vvith a lie: Marke vvel:
I saie, It is not Breade: I saie not, It is No Breade. Not Breade,</hi>
yee saie. <hi>No Breade,</hi> yee saie not: As if there were so many miles distance
bitweene <hi>No</hi> and <hi>Nor.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These, and sutche like, be the shameful Vntruthes, and horrible Lies,
that you, and your Felowes with greate seekinge, and diligence haue espied.
And thus, if a man happen to vse <hi>Ensis,</hi> for <hi>Gladius,</hi> or <hi>Nam,</hi> for <hi>Enim,</hi>
or <hi>Que,</hi> for <hi>Et,</hi> yee thinke it cause sufficiente to make a Tragedie. How
be it I doubte not, but in my Replie, beinge so longe, and so ful of necessarie
allegations, yee maie happen to finde somme ouer sightes of greatter impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
And in acknowledginge, and refourminge of the same, yee shal finde
me as sharpe, and eger, as your selfe. But these fewe examples I haue touched
by the waie, that it mighte appeare, howe inquisitiue, and fierce yee are, to
seeke occasions: and that your Reader maie see, yee hunte wantonly, and
renne riote, and open oftetimes without a cause. Yet notwithstandinge,
if yee can telle vs sadly, as your manner is; that M. Iewel bringeth triflinge
obiections, and trasshe, and pelfe, and nothinge to pourpose, without lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge,
without reason, without witte: that he racketh, that he stretcheth,
that he wringeth, that he wreasteth, that he nippeth, and clippeth the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours,
and Councelles: (for these be the woordes, whereby yee thought, yee
mighte beste vtter your preaty fansies): If yee can crie oute, <hi>False partes,
False reportes, False dealinges, False Marchantes, False Ballance,
False Dise, and al is False:</hi> If yee can saie, <hi>Loe,</hi> Sir <hi>Defender, yee
vvrangle, yee trifle, yee are taken tardee, yee haue proued no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge,
yee haue nothinge to ansvveare:</hi> If yee can thus saie, and saie
it boldely, it shalbe sufficiente: al is safe: your frendes wil thinke, yee haue
saide sommewhat, and that yee woulde neuer haue framed sutche a counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
to saie nothinge.</p>
   <p>Yee telle vs ful often, wee are no Bishoppes: I trowe, for that wee haue not
sworne our obedience to the <hi>Pope.</hi> And therefore yee geeue the worlde to
vnderstande, wee can consecrate no Ministers, wee can holde no Synodes, we
canne doo nothinge. Euen so certaine your Forefathers in Olde times tolde
<hi>S. Paule,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Corinth. 9.</note> He was no <hi>Apostle:</hi> and others afterwarde by like authoritie
tolde <hi>S. Basile,</hi> and <hi>S. Hilarie,</hi> they were no Bishoppes. But, M. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge,
they were <hi>False Apostles,</hi> they were <hi>Arian Heretiques,</hi> that so
tolde them. It booteth not, to trie our titles before you. VVee wil onely saie
with <hi>S. Paule:</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Corinth 15.</note>
      <hi>By the Grace of God vvee are, that vvee are.</hi> And,
wee truste, wee haue not his Grace in vaine.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="389"/>
But specially, and aboue al other thinges, and that throughout al your
three Bookes, yee saie, that <hi>Sir Defender</hi> is vnlearned: that his beste skil
is in a fewe Figures of Rhetorique: that he hath neither Greeke, nor Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gique,
nor Philosophie, nor Diuinitie: that he hath readde no kinde of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours,
nor Newe, nor Olde, nor of his owne, nor of others: that al the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture
of his Booke was broughte to his hande, somme by Greeke Readers,
somme by Scholemaisters,<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. 21<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. a Et 259. a. and commonly in other places.</note> somme by Ciuilians, somme by Canonistes, somme
by Summistes, somme by Glosers, somme by others: that he hath nothinge
els but patched Notebookes, huddled togeather by snappes, and peeces. Some
parte hereof, or rather the whole al togeather, without exception, to doo you
pleasure, I would easily haue graunted you, M. Hardinge, vpon smal suite,
with more fauoure, and lesse adoo. Take from mee, what learninge yee liste:
distreine it, and pounde it at your pleasure: I wil neuer trouble you with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleuin.
How be it, if yee vtter al this of your indifferente iudgemente, and
certaine knowledge, yet is it impertinente: for wee pleaded of Faithe, and
not of Learninge: if otherwise yee speake it of heate of minde, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of Cholere, and therevpon thus proclaime it vnto the world, it is great
folie. Truely yee neuer sawe <hi>Sir Defenders</hi> Bookes, nor neuer sette your
foote within his studie. A wise Iudge wil seldome pronounce, before he
knowe. If it shal please you, for trial hereof, to sende your frende, he maie
happily see, that Sir Defender hath al these <hi>Summistes,</hi> and <hi>Canonistes,
and Greekereaders, and Scholemaisters,</hi> of his owne.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, it maie becomme vs bothe to saie, as a Heathen wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
sommetime saide,<note place="margin">Socrates.</note>
      <hi>This onely thinge vvee knovve, that vvee
knovve nothinge.</hi> Goddes Truthe dependeth not of our knowledge. Our
Tongues shal cease, and our knowledge shal faile: But the <hi>Glorie of
God</hi> shal stande for euer. For my parte, I wil saie to you with <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine,
Quaere doctiores: sed caue praesumptores: Seeke others of
more Learninge: but bevvare of them, that praesume of Learning.</hi>
If any praise falle out in this respecte, bestowe it freely vpon your <hi>Greeke-readers,</hi>
and <hi>Scholemaisters,</hi> who, in your iudgemente, haue beste deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
it. It shalbe sufficiente for mee, to haue saide the <hi>Truthe:</hi> whiche,
though it appeare neuer so simple, is hable to remoue a Mountaine of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge.
But happy are your <hi>Brethren of Louaine,</hi> that are so speedily
growen Learned vpon the suddaine, not by greate studie, I trowe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by destinee. As soone as they had once sauoured the soile of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
they lookte onely vpon twoo poore <hi>Titles</hi> of the <hi>Lavve,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Extra. Li. 5.</note>
      <hi>De Maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi>
and <hi>De Clerico promoto per saltum:</hi> and suddainely they were
<pb facs="389"/>
transfourmed, and nowe goe for <hi>Doctours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for your Learninge, M. Hardinge, wee neuer reproued it. How be
it, greately to feare it, wee haue no cause. God geeue you Grace, yee maie
wholy turne it to his glorie: leste in the daie of the Lorde it be laide againste
you. He is ouer wel learned, that bendeth his Learninge againste <hi>God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But, if wee be so vtterly voide of al manner of Learninge, paintinge, as
you saie, our Bookes, and Margines with the Names, and Authorities of so
many <hi>Doctours,</hi> what maie your frendes then thinke of you, that stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
so longe in the Defence of your Priuate Masse, are not yet hable to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege
one <hi>Doctoure,</hi> nor <hi>Greeke,</hi> nor <hi>Latine,</hi> nor one, nor other? It see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
greate marueile, yee shoulde haue sutche abundance of <hi>Doctours,</hi>
and shewe so fewe, specially where it standeth you so mutche vpon, to open
your stoare. Consider, I beseeche you, your late <hi>Reioinder:</hi> wherein, as
it is thought, nothinge of your parte is leafte vntouched. Of the Seuen and
twentie Articles conteined in my <hi>Replie,</hi> yee haue taken vpon you onely
to answeare One. And yet of the same One, yee haue scarcely touched the
tenthe parte. Your pourpose should haue benne therein, by euidente <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,</hi>
and good <hi>Authorities,</hi> substantially to haue proued your <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
Masse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now consider the order, and plainenesse of your dealinge. Yee bestowe
welneare the thirde parte of your <hi>Booke</hi> aboute the <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> as though
there were no <hi>Sacrifice</hi> without <hi>Priuate Masse.</hi> Al the reste yee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume
in idle discourses, and needelesse talkes, of <hi>Consecration,</hi> of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
of the Prieste,</hi> of <hi>Minglinge the vvater vvith the vvine,</hi>
of the <hi>Name of the Masse,</hi> of <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> of <hi>Real Presence,</hi>
of <hi>Churche Feastes,</hi> (whiche in olde time were called <hi>Agapae</hi>), of <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare
Communion,</hi> of <hi>Communion of Faithe,</hi> of our <hi>Vnion</hi> with
<hi>Christe,</hi> of sendinge abroade the <hi>Sacramente,</hi> of <hi>Priestes vviues,</hi> of
<hi>Vovves,</hi> of <hi>Bigamie,</hi> of <hi>Good vvoorkes,</hi> of <hi>Onely Faithe,</hi> of <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique
Praier</hi> in a tongue vnknowen, of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> of <hi>Fourmes,</hi> of
<hi>Accidentes,</hi> of the <hi>Epistles Decretal,</hi> of <hi>Clemens, Cletus, Anacle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,
Abdias, Leontius, &amp;c.</hi> Hereof yee haue tolde vs sutche thinges, as
perhaps wee knewe before, and were not harde to be knowen, and perteined
ful litle to the pourpose. Yee should rather haue proued, that within the firste
sixe hundred yeeres after Christe, somme one, or other of the Holy <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Catholique Fathers Ministred the Holy Communion open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in the Churche, and receiued the Sacramente Alone not diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge
the same to any other, the vvhole multitude of the people
<pb facs="390"/>
sittinge, or standinge by, and lookinge on him.</hi> This was the mater,
that laie bitweene vs: Hereunto yee should haue laide your force: This was
it, yee should haue proued. For proufe of sutche thinges, as needed no proufe,
yee haue brought foorthe greate shewes of Learninge. But as touchinge
your <hi>Priuate Masse,</hi> whiche onely yee had taken in hande to proue, yee
haue hitherto proued nothinge. Your <hi>Reader,</hi> M. Hardinge, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
be, neither so simple, nor so partial, but he muste needes haue an eie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
your issue, and remember, what yee had in hande. If emongest so many,
and so Learned woordes, he finde not one woorde of that he sought for, maie
he not thinke, he hath loste his laboure, and that there is somme folie in your
fardle? Maie he not saie within him selfe, <hi>Quò nunc se proripit iste?</hi>
VVhat shal I make of these vagaries? what meaneth this man, to shoote so
faire biside the marke? He muste needes perceiue by your silence, that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandinge
your so many faire, and liberal promisses, yet the thinge, he
sought for, cannot be founde. Naie, you your selfe, for excuse hereof, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
woordes haue tolde vs plainely,<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioind. fol. 281. a. Et fol. 88. a.</note>
      <hi>It mighte be, that none receiued
the Sacramente vvith the Prieste:</hi> And againe, <hi>VVhether the
Prieste had alvvaies a companie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. in his Reioinder, in the Preface to the Reader. &amp;. In the same Preface. &amp; ij. <hi>M.</hi> Hardinge, Reioinder: Fol. 210. a.</note>
      <hi>to receiue vvith him, or somme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
receiued alone, that is a circumstance of a facte: the proufe
vvhereof by manifeste Testimonies, cannot vvith reason be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</hi>
Againe, <hi>It is contentious, to put vs to proufe of the
Circumstance.</hi> Againe, <hi>It forceth not, vvhether vvee bringe
foorthe Testimonies of the sixe hundred yeeres, or no.</hi> Againe,
<hi>VVhether I can shevve, that a Masse vvas saide vvithout com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie
presente to receiue vvith the Prieste, that saide it, or no,
vvhat skilleth it?</hi> Againe, <hi>I must telle you, that I seeke not for
Priuate Masse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reioinder. 219. a.</note>
      <hi>vvhiche to finde, your scoffinge pretendeth me to
be desirous. I seeke not for that, vvhiche I acknovvledge not.</hi>
And againe, <hi>It forceth not greately, vvhether it maie be proued,
or no:</hi> VVhiche is as mutche, as if yee had tolde vs in plainer wise, that
for the space of sixe hundred yeeres after Christe, yee can heare no tidinges
in any <hi>Doctoure,</hi> or <hi>Councel,</hi> of your <hi>Priuate Masse.</hi> VVhiche thinge,
thus of your parte confessed, to our pourpose is sufficiente.</p>
   <p>Now, touchinge the Authoritie of your Amphilochius, not long sithence,
yee thought his force had benne inuincible. And therefore yee stoode vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofte,<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hardinge in his Answeare, Fol. 29. a.</note>
and braied alowde, <hi>Novve M Ievvel, and his Consacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
doo stagger, I doubte not.</hi> And for that cause, as if it had benne
somme greate woorthy <hi>Authoure,</hi> yee alleged him seuen times, with spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
<pb facs="390"/>
reuerence, in one Booke.<note place="margin">Roioinder. fol. 267. b.</note> And yet nowe at the laste, yee are contente, for
shame, to turne him ouer, and to let him goe. Perhaps yee thought, for the
while, a weake threede was sufficient to leade the people: and that, as folkes
vse sommetimes to please children, yee might quenche their thirste with an
emptie cuppe. Thus mutche hitherto, touchinge somme partes of your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioinder.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Concerninge your <hi>Former Booke,</hi> whiche yee haue intitled, a <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi>
I neede to saie nothinge. By the iudgemente of the wise, it saithe suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
of it selfe. But what meante you, M. Hardinge, therein to make so
large discourse, I wil not saie, in the <hi>Defence,</hi> (for that woorde your frendes
maie not beare) but at the leaste in the fauoure of <hi>Open Stevves:</hi> and to
calle the same,<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Confu. fol. 162. b.</note>
      <hi>Malum necessarium,</hi> that is to saie, although an il thinge,
yet sutche a thinge, as no good Common weale maie be without it? VVhat
meante you, to that purpose, to shewe vs the name, and Authoritie <hi>of S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine:</hi>
and thus to vpbraide vs in the ende,<note place="margin">Confu. fol. 162. a</note>
      <hi>In good soothe, Maisters,
ye are too yonge, to cōtrolle the Cittie of Rome in her doinges?</hi>
VVhat needed you to bestowe so fine eloquence in so fowle a cause?<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Confu. fol. 163. a.</note> Is vice
growen so colde in <hi>Louaine,</hi> that it muste be enflamed, and authorized by
open VVritinge? VVhat meante you to allege the <hi>Prophete Dauid,</hi>
the <hi>Euangeliste</hi> S. <hi>Mathevve,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Confut. 251. a. &amp; deinceps.</note> and S. <hi>Paule the Apostle</hi> for proufe of
your <hi>Pardonnes?</hi> VVil yee telle vs, that <hi>Dauid, Matthevve,</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi>
were <hi>Pardoners?</hi> Or, if yee dare to telle vs so, must wee beleeue it? If yee so
manifestly mocke vs with open folies, howe maie wee truste you in higher
Mysteries?<note place="margin">2. Corin. 4.</note> S. Paule saithe, Though our outwarde man be corrupted,
yet our inwarde man is renewed daie by daie. Here yee telle vs, in greate
soothe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Confut. fol. 117. a. Luke. 22. <hi>M.</hi> Hard Confut. fol. 192. b.</note> that these woordes vndoubtedly serue to proue <hi>Purgatorie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Christe <hi>saithe vnto</hi> Peter, I haue praied for thee &amp;c. Therefore,
<hi>yee saie,</hi> Christe novve requireth vs, not to be obediente to Peter,
or Paule, but to the Pope, that sitteth in theire Chaire. Christe
<hi>saithe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>M.</hi> Hard. Confu. Fol. 99. a.</note> The Sonne of Man came, not to destroie, but to saue:
Ergo, <hi>saie you,</hi> The Breade, and VVine in the Sacramente lose no
parte of their former vertues: but remaine in Fourmes, and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes,
euen as they vvere before: <hi>as if the</hi> Sonne of God <hi>had come
downe from Heauen to saue</hi> Accidentes.</p>
   <p>Thus yee nippe of the sense, and meaninge of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi>
and feede vs onely with emptie woordes: as if yee woulde pike awaie the
corne, and geeue vs the chaffe: or conueigh awaie the iewels, and throwe vs
the bagge. O M. Hardinge, be not wilful: let your owne conscience leade
<pb facs="391"/>
you. VVas this the meaninge of S. <hi>Paule?</hi> was this the comminge of
<hi>Christe</hi> into the worlde? was this the sense of the <hi>Holy Ghoste?</hi> I wil not
saie, what <hi>Olde Doctour,</hi> or <hi>Anciente Father,</hi> but, what <hi>Summiste,</hi>
what <hi>Canoniste,</hi> what <hi>Childe,</hi> what <hi>Heretique,</hi> euer either so vndis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely,
or so vnreuerently vsed the <hi>VVoorde of God?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I leaue the misconstrueinge, and falsifieinge of so many <hi>Fathers:</hi> the
allowinge, and soothinge of manifest Forgeries: the vpholdinge of Abuses,
and open Erroures: your weake Proufes: your seely Coniectures: your sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
Gheasses: your greate Ouersightes: your bolde Affirmations: your heapes
of Vntruthes: your disdeigneful Scornes: your immoderate Scoffes: your
vngentile, and vnciuile woordes, as for example, <hi>Villanes, Theeues,
Fooles, Disardes, Lourdaines &amp;c.</hi> I leaue other your vnmannerly,
and vncleanely speaches:<note place="margin">Confuta. 318. b.</note>
      <hi>Hungry Dogges eate dirty puddinges:
As common as life vvith beggers:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Confuta. 250. b.</note>
      <hi>They serue the belly, and the
thinges beneath the belly.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>VVas this a presente, M. Hardinge, meete either for the Modestie of a
<hi>Virgine,</hi> or for the <hi>Maiestie</hi> of a <hi>Prince:</hi> specially sutche a <hi>Virgine,</hi> and
sutche a <hi>Prince,</hi> so Chaste, so Graue, so Learned, so VVise, so Vertuous, so
Godly, as Christendome seldome hath seene the like? VVhat? thought you,
that either her wisedome coulde not espie your fraudes, and mockeries: or,
that her chaste eares coulde quietly beare your lothesome talke? Or, thought
you by the weight of sutche reasons, to mooue Mountaines, and to woorke
woonders, and to force her <hi>Maiestie</hi> to leaue <hi>christe</hi> and his <hi>Gospel,</hi> and
comme to <hi>Louaine</hi> to folowe you?</p>
   <p>Yee threape her <hi>Maiestie</hi> fondely with kindenesse, and, as yee woulde
haue the worlde imagine, with good likinge, and fauouringe of your side: as
if her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> hauing benne brought vp from her cradle in the knowledge
and feare of <hi>God,</hi> and through Goddes greate Mercie, and accordinge to
his knowen VVil, by the good aduise, and counsel of the states of her
<hi>Realme,</hi> hauinge refourmed the <hi>House of God</hi> from the filthe, and soile
of your diuises, shee stoode nowe in a mammeringe, and were not hable to
discerne, either <hi>Falsehedde</hi> from <hi>Truthe,</hi> or <hi>Darkenesse</hi> from <hi>Light:</hi>
or, as if your Errours were not so grosse, that a blinde man maie groape them
with his Fingers.</p>
   <p>Yee telle her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> shee hath neither <hi>Parlamente,</hi> nor <hi>Lavve,</hi> nor
<hi>Churche,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Confut. fol. 42. a. and so through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Booke.</note> nor <hi>Cleregie:</hi> The Churche of Englande yee commonly calle
the <hi>Tovver of Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Synagog of Antichriste,</hi> and the
<hi>Schoole of Sathan:</hi> ye charge her Maiestie with disordered proceedinges,
<pb facs="391"/>
with mainteinance of Infidelitie,<note place="margin">Confut. fol. 5. a. 15. a. 38. a. 49. a. and so through the whole.</note> of Sacrilege, of Schisme, of Heresie: For
your possible power, ye dishonour her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> bothe abroade, and at home:
where yee maie geate credite to your folies, yee sclaunder the gouernmente:
yee disquiete her <hi>Maiesties</hi> louinge Subiectes: yee breede Seditions:
yee procure Rebellions: yee hazarde her estate. And yet dare yee to pouder
al this poison with a fewe dissembled, and sugred woordes, and to offer the
same vnto her <hi>Maiestie</hi> for a presente? VVel, M. Hardinge, if yee had
foreseene the thankes, that her <hi>Maiestie</hi> moste iustely yeelded you for your
trauailes, yee woulde not haue benne so bolde, so rudely to presse into her
presence. It behooued you, to be aduised, not onely, what yee wrote, but
also what Personage shoulde viewe your writinges.</p>
   <p>If yee shal happen to write hereafter, sende vs fewer woordes, and more
Learninge. If yee shal diuise to talke any more of your <hi>Priuate Masse,</hi>
leaue your vagaries, and goe directly to the pourpose. Telle vs no moe sutche
longe tales, either of the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> or of other maters so farre from the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion.
It is no good <hi>Logique,</hi> to shifte of the thinge, yee haue in hande, and
to mocke your poore <hi>Reader</hi> with an other. Treade not so nicely, and so
gingerly, M. Hardinge. Saie not, your <hi>Masse</hi> is a <hi>Circumstance,</hi> and a
mater of Facte,<note place="margin">Reioinder. 232. b 233. a.</note> and standeth onely vpon supposalles, and gheasses, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
needeth no further proufe. VVhy soulde yee so trifle with the simple?
This is the Issue, that falleth out bitweene vs: <hi>VVhether any one of
al the Anciente Learned Fathers &amp;c. euer saide your Priuate
Masse &amp;c.</hi> This is it, that is denied. If yee proue not this, what so euer ye
proue, yee proue nothinge. Bringe out somme <hi>Learned Father:</hi> shewe
somme <hi>Catholique Doctoure:</hi> keepe them no lenger foorthe comminge.
The worlde looketh yee shoulde deale plainely.</p>
   <p>Denie nomore the manifeste Truthe: auouche nomore the open False<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedde:
Let there be somme probabilitie, and likelihoode in your saieinges.
Leaue your immoderate, and vncourteous talkes. They are tokens of sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make,
and not of Learninge. Therein yee haue deserued the honoure aboue
al others. In sutche kinde of Eloquence noman can matche you, but your
selfe. A good cause mighte haue benne pleaded with better woordes. The
more vntemperate, and firy yee shewe your selfe without cause, the more
in the ende wil appeare your folie. If yee haue hitherto taken any pleasure
in speakinge il, at my hande, by hearinge il, yee shal not lose it. If yee bringe
vs moe Fables of your <hi>Pardonnes,</hi> and <hi>Purgatories:</hi> If yee feede vs, as
yee haue donne, with <hi>Vntruthes:</hi> If yee depraue the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> If yee
falsifie the <hi>Doctoures:</hi> If yee Conclude without <hi>Premisses:</hi> If yee place
<pb facs="392"/>
your <hi>Antecedente</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and your <hi>Consequente</hi> at <hi>Louaine:</hi> If
yee stuffe so mutche paper, and blotte so many leaues, and shewe vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge:
briefely, if yee write none otherwise, then yee haue donne hitherto,
no wise man wilgreately feare your force.</p>
   <p>Deceiue not the simple. They are bought with price: They are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of <hi>God,</hi> for whome <hi>Christe</hi> hath sheadde his <hi>Bloude.</hi> Your shiftes
be miserable. Yee trouble your selfe, as a birde the lime. The more yee sturre,
the faster yee cleaue: the longer yee striue, the weaker yee are. Yee cannot
bridle the flowinge Seas: yee cannot blinde the Sonnebeames Kicke not
stil againste the spurre: Geeue place vnto the Glorie of <hi>God.</hi> VVil yee,
nil yee, the <hi>Truthe</hi> wil conquere. God geeue vs bothe humble hartes,
and the people eies to see: that al fleashe maie be obediente to his wil. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London. <date>27. Octobris. 1567.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Iohn Sarisburie.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>