<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112582_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00639</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10772</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112582</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the reasons of the counter-poyson, for maintenance of the eldership : against an aunsvvere made to them by Doctor Copequot, in a publike sermon at Pawles Crosse, vpon Psal. 84. 1584. VVherein also according to his demaunde is proued syllogisticallie for the learned, and plainlie for all men, the perpetuitie of the elders office in the church</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Must (gentle &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader) declare two things for iustify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this treatise fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Firste, why it came not out before, then why it commeth out nowe. Before, the trueth is, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Counterpoyson</hi> neuer coulde gette the answeres in writing as nowe I haue got them. He sawe notes of them taken by a Doctor of the ciuill Lawe, which (as he then saide) made him ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke howe to contemne them, then to answere them. So this was the cause the author let it alone. Since that time I my selfe haue fallen vppon the whole Sermon in writing: so that it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it goeth from hande to hande a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst those who delight in it. It may be some perceyue not the weakenes of
<pb facs="3"/>
the answeares. It may be, some beleeue the slaunders and lies made in it, both against the cause and the persons. Wherefore to shewe the trueth of the cause and her strengthe against all her enimies newe or olde, continued or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapsed, to cleare the trueth from olde &amp; newe slaunderers, I haue made the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence following. The Author of the <hi>Coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter-poyson</hi> I am sure will take it in good part. This Defence the Author of the Aunswere may confute if he can. Thou mayest iudge of both, as Euidence of Reason shall leade thee. The Lord graūt vs first to vnderstande his wil, then to practise it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>