<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTERS TO
the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112268_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10844</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112268</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTERS TO
the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the lavvfulnes of hearing of the ministers in the church of England: penned by that late learned and reverent deuine, Mr. Iohn Robinsz. late pastor to the new English church of God in Leyden. Printed according to the copie that was found in his studie after hi decase [sic] : and now published for the common good. Together with a letter written by the same authore: and approued by his church: vvhich followeth after this treatise</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 77 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTERS TO
the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>CHristian Reader. How euer the
verie naming of the Author
of this following Treatise,
vvere sufficient reason for vs to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish
this same vnto the vvorld, in
regard of those large abilities aboue
many others, vvhich the Lord had
bestowed vpon him, and in regard he
being now at rest, with the Lord, and
so hauing finished long since his course
in this his pilgrimage, vve cannot
expect to haue any more vse of his
helpe this waye, and although it were
great pittie that such a vvorke as this
should be concealed for so long time,
considering the worke vvas perfected,
and vvritted by his owne hand, and
so found after his death (which is nine
yeares since) in his studie, yet haue we
thought it good all this while to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale
it, in respect of that desire vve
had to the peace of that church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="3"/>
the Author of this Treatise vvas
for so many yeares a Pastor. In regard
vve did perceiue that some though not
manie vvere contrari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> minded to the
Authors judgement expressed in this
Trtatise: And this vve judge to be
a sufficient reason of our so long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying
of publishing this Treatise to
the world: Yet to our griefe vve haue
now just cause to put this same on foote;
For as vvhen a citie is in danger of
enemies to be surprized, it is then
high time to take vp all those vvarr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Munitions vvhich happily before
that time vvere cast aside and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded,
that so they may the better
maintaine their citie, and the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
of it against their enemies: so
vve judge it as necessarie if not more
vvhen vve see the enemies of Gods
church to incroach vpon the priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of the same especiallie vvhen they
ayme at the vtter ruinating of it,
that then it is high time for vs to
<pb facs="3"/>
defende the cause of Christ, and it
vvas the vvisdome of Iehojada the
High Priest perceiuing the malice of
Athalia, seeking to destroy the
vvhole seed of Iehosaphat, to hide
Ioash the right heyre of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
and vvhen he sawe a fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie
then to reueale him, and
make him knowne, so vve vvho
haue obserued Athalias spirit in part
to be in some, vvho haue laboured
to assume the power to themselues,
vvhich is proper to the church, and
so Diotrephes like vvould cast out
vvhom they please, and retayne
vvhom they thought good, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then they vvill be hindred in
this their attempt, they vvill la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
to rent that church in pieces in
vvhich they haue liued for manie
yeares together, and that vve may
not seeme to accuse them of any thing
vvithout just reason, vve desire the
Christian Reader, and themselues to
consider this that followes▪.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
First, their schisme or as they call it
their leauing of the church, doth arise
vpon this occasion, to wit, that 2. which
vvere members of the same church
with them hauing vpon some occasion
heard some of the Ministers in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland
preach, and it coming to the
knowledge of some of these vvho haue
now made this rent the church, they
vvould presently haue these persons
dealt vvithall as for sinne, and if they
did not repent after dealing, they
vvould haue the church to proceed
to excomunicate them <hi>ipso facto,</hi>
vvhich the church not willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
vnto, these men could not be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
but they vvould haue their owne
vvilles done or els they vvould rent
from the church, vvhich proceeding of
theirs, if it vvere approued of and
followed no church could long continue
together in peace, for vvhat these
foure or fiue men haue done, that may
any other man doe, so that if any man
do conceiue any of his brethren to
<pb facs="4"/>
vvalke in any such sinne, vvhich he
judges doth deserue excomunication,
if the church will not thereto consent,
he may rent himselfe from the same;
Although the Author of this Treatise
haue taught them otherwise, to vvit,
that if the church, see not that to be
sinne, vvhich I see to be a sinne, I
hauing informed the church there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
according to my place, I haue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scharged
my dutie, and the sinnes
lyes vpon the church (if it be a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,
and not vpon me; but it seemes
these men do looke for that in the
church on earth vvhich is onely to be
found in heauen, for themselues haue
affirmed, and that before diuers wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses
that there is no sinne small or
great that is to borne vvithall, and
that the verie speaking of a vvord
through fraylty about worldly busines<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
vpon the Sabbaoth day, should
haue as seuere a sentence, as he that
shall openly &amp; prophanely transgresse
against the 4. Commandement, the
<pb facs="5"/>
verie naming of with their opinion, is
sufficient to discouer their weaknes, &amp;
that we may yet further discouer these
mens folly to the world more fully, we
will shew you how contrary they are to
themselues in this their iudgment, for
as they say, and do affirme that there
is no sinne vvhich is to be borne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
in the church, yet themselues, or at
least the chief of them do practise the
contrarie, as for example, one in
stead of manie may serue the turne:
The chiefe of Author of this trouble
doth hold, and so hath for manie
yeares together, to vvit, that it is
vnlawfull for the members of one
church to haue communion with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
church, and yet not vvithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
this his judgement, he can beare
vvith one, vvho hath contrary to this
his judgement practised, and so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth
still to do vpon occasion, and
yet not vvithstanding his so practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,
and so professing, he is receiued
among them, and is their chiefe if not
<pb facs="5"/>
their onely Teacher which they haue:
So that vve may here easily perceiue,
that though this man doth vse Iehu's
peace against the sinnes of others,
with whom he desires to be alienated,
yet he can beare vvith as great sinnes
in others, in his judgement vvith
vvhom he desires to vvalke, we could
shew manie more reasons to proue his
partialitie, but then vve should ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
the bonds of an Epistle onely vve
desire to giue the Reader to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of those two things: First, that
this practize of hearing the Ministers
of the church of England, is not against
any Article of faith, vvhich is by
this church professed, vvhereof the
Author of this Treatise vvas a Pastor,
it being no Act of Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
for if hearing simplie vvere
an Act of Communion, then euerie
h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>tique, or Atheist, or whatsoeuer he
were that should come into the church
of God, should haue Communion
vvith them, vvhich if it vvere true,
<pb facs="6"/>
as this following Treatise proues the
contrarie, then it vvere good for
euery church that will auoid commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
with profane men, to meete in
priuate, and then to shut their dore
when their own compagnie is meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:
else I cannot see how they can
auoid hauing communion with wicked
men: to wit if beare hearing be an
acte of communion: Secondly, as this
hearing is not against any Article of
their faith, so likewise it was not in
the iudgement of the church esteemed
as a thing that might not be borne
withall,<note place="margin">The letter you shall find after the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note> &amp; this may appeare by a copy
of a letter which we haue heer fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
published where the church in
the counsell which they giue to the
church of London do sufficiently make
it appeare, that their iudgement did
manifestlie differ from those which
now haue made this breach, and which
is well to be marked by the reader how
that the church when this letter was
write: enioyed the Pastor, and their
<pb facs="6"/>
company was fiue tymes greater then
it was when this breach was made: &amp;
because these men in his their error
are vvilling to retraine it, and not
being able to make any sufficient reply
to the answere made in this Treatise to
their obiections, though the manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script
therof hath bene in their hands
for many yeares, yet because they will
find somthing to say, more then others
haue done heretofore, though of lesse
force, therefore they haue ioyned some
new obiections which both the seducer
and the seduced do thinke are vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable,
therfore it will not be amisse
for vs to propound them, and to giue
some answere to them that so if their
stomachs serue they may reply to all at
once: First, they obiect and say that
we hold the church of England to be a
false church, and the Ministers thereof
to be Antichristian, and yet we go
thither to worship the true God.</p>
   <p>Before we answere directly to this
objection, we shall intreate the Reader
<pb facs="7"/>
and themselues to consider of this that
followes.</p>
   <p>First, A church may be said to be
false in diuers respects, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to those respects, vve are to
haue diuers Considerations thereof,
as first, a church may be said to be
false in respect of outward order, to
vvit, vvhen a church is gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
not according to the rule of
Christ neither, in their outward go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement,
do they conforme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto,
now this church cannot be said
to be the church of Christ being thus
erected, and gouerned contrary to the
rule of Christ, but is false and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian,
and yet notwithstanding
the faith professed by this church, and
the doctrines, taught in this church
may be sound, and according to God.</p>
   <p>Secondly, a church may be false
not onely in respect of outward order,
but likewise in respect of faith and
doctrine.</p>
   <p>Now to this latter, vve counsell no
<pb facs="7"/>
man to go, because from thence no
good can be expected, and that is the
esteeme vve haue of the church of
Rome.</p>
   <p>But now as in a true church in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
of outward order, there may be
manie false doctrines taught, so in
a church, that is false in respect of
outward order, there may be manie
sound, and seasonable truths taught,
and this esteeme vve haue of the
preaching in England: Namelie,
that the doctrine there taught ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Articles of their faith
is sound, and the effects of it hath
appeared, in the vvorking of
faith in the hearts of manie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands.</p>
   <p>For the outward order, or mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
there as a church, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
themselues, and those that
are in vnion, vvith that church
estate, but not all that heare them.</p>
   <p>Now that worshipping of God which
consists in hearing his word is warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="8"/>
for vs to doe in England, we proue
it by this argument.</p>
   <p>That preaching which ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
begets men to the faith of
Christ may lawfully be heard.</p>
   <p>But the preaching of many
Ministers in the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland
hath, and doth ordinarily
beget men to the faith of Christ.</p>
   <p>Therefore the preaching of
many Ministers in England may
lawfully be heard.</p>
   <p>The first part of this sillogisme is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
out of Rom 10. where the Apostle
telling what is the ordinary vvay God
vses to beget men to the faith of Christ
telles vs, it comes by hearing of the
vvord of God preached, if faith comes
by hearing the vvord of God preached
(to vvit, if that be the outward mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes)
then there is no question but that
a man may heare such preaching, and
any man may blush for shame, that
<pb facs="8"/>
shall deny this: so that the major part
of the argument is cleare:</p>
   <p>And for the Minor parte they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
deny it, no more then a man at
noon day can deny the sunne to shine:
for if any man make question whether
faith comes ordinarily by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
and hearing in England, it is a
great question vvether they euer had
faith or no: yet because some are so
grosse as to deny this, we will therefore:
proue the contrarie by this Argument.</p>
   <p>That preaching and hearing
which makes them which were
altogether carnall, and so not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of a church-estate, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
saints &amp; so fit for a church-estate:
That preaching must
needs beget men to the faith:</p>
   <p>But the preaching and hearing
in England, made them that were
vnfit &amp; carnall to become saints,
and so fit members to the true
church, which were not so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
Therfore the preaching in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland
and hearing the same doth
beget men to the faith: That the
preaching, and hearing in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland
hath done this: Witnesse
the church of Leyden, and of
Amstelredam.</p>
   <p>Let them tell vs where they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
their faith: if they say they had it
not till they ioyned in these bodies,
how could they then be true to their
owne grounds, that none but visible
Christians are fit matter for the church
vvhereas none can be so esteemed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
in the iudgement of charitie, we
iudge them to haue true faith.</p>
   <p>But some of these that haue made
this diuision haue not denyed, but
faith is wrought by the preaching and
hearing in England: and yet which is
wonderfull contradiction: they say it
is not the vvord of God as it is there
preached: so that it seemes there is
something besides the vvord of God
which is an ordinary meanes to beget
<pb facs="9"/>
men to the faith, and there is another
vvord besides Gods vvord that vvill
do it; the like absurditie hath sildome
bene heard from any that professe them
selues to be Christians, and that they
may, not seeme to say this vvithout
some reason, marke the reason that
they bring to proue it, say they we do
deny that to be the vvord of God, as it
is there preached: by a false Ministry,
though the vvord it selfe be of God yet
as it is by them preached, it is none of
Gods vvord so Gods vvord here stands
at fast, and loose, it is Gods vvord, and
it is not Gods vvord, as if they should
say, it is Gods word if M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Canne shall
preach it: but if another, that is a
Minister in England preach the same
it is none of Gods vvord: so that mens
outward callings true, or false, makes
the vvord to be the vvord of God,
or not to be the vvord of God, an asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
rather to be pitied then refuted,
being litle better then blasphemy, that
which they bring to make this assertion
<pb facs="10"/>
good, to vvit, that any man hauing
an outward calling vvhich is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
makes the vvord of God, vvhich
he preacheth, not to be the vvord of
God, and this, say they to proue it,
it vvas true incense vvhich Nadab
and Abihu tooke,<note place="margin">Lev. 10. 1.</note> to offer vp to the
Lord, but because they tooke strang
fire, and not the fire, vvhich vvas
from the Altar as the Lord had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,
therefore the Lord sent a
fire to destroy them: so say they, it is
the true vvord of God, which is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
in England, but because they
preach the same by an vnlawfull office,
therefore the Lord abhorres it: A
stranger collection I thinke can hardly
by heard, for here strang fire is opposed
to an vnlawfull outward calling,
vvhich nothing can be more absurd,
for Nadab and Abihu had a true out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard
calling to offer, they vvere the
sonnes of Aaron (saith the text) ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
if any thing hence might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,
in iust proportion, it must be
<pb facs="10"/>
to the doctrine taught, and not in
the least to the calling: so that vve
may from thence gather thus much,
that if a Minister in regard of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard
calling true: shall teach any
thing, that is not from the Lord, they
are to expect Gods iudgement for the
same, and more cannot hence be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected,
further, let it be shewed, that
euer any prophet in the old or new
Testament vvas euer termed a false
prophet in respect of his outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
but allwaies in respect of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;
vve can find that such as had
true outvvard calling in the true
church, yet vvere false prophets in
regard of their doctrine in many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulers
as Christ teaches concerning
the Scribes and Pharises for their false
expounding of the Law, let them shew
the like for outvvard callings: Thus
haue vve thought good, hauing bene
eare vvitnesses of these things here
propounded to set downe our censure
of them, desyring the Lord to make
<pb facs="11"/>
this vvhole vvorke (for the generall
good now set forth) take effect in those
that loue the Trueth.</p>
   <closer>Fare you wel.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>