<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MVCH ESTEEMED FOR HER HIGH BIRTH, BVT MORE ADMI∣red for her vertue, the Lady KATHE∣RINE STANHOPE, wife to PHILIP Lord STANHOP, Baron of Shelford.</title>
           <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112414_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07237</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17634</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112414</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MVCH ESTEEMED FOR HER HIGH BIRTH, BVT MORE ADMI∣red for her vertue, the Lady KATHE∣RINE STANHOPE, wife to PHILIP Lord STANHOP, Baron of Shelford.</title>
                 <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Duke of Millaine : A tragædie. As it hath beene often acted by his Maiesties seruants, at the blacke Friers. Written by Philip Massinger Gent</title>
                 <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MVCH ESTEEMED FOR HER HIGH BIRTH, BVT MORE ADMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for her vertue, the Lady KATHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RINE STANHOPE, wife to PHILIP Lord STANHOP, Baron of <hi>Shelford.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>MADAM:</hi> If I were not most assured that workes of this nature, hath found both pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, and protection, amongst the greatest Princesses of <hi>Italie,</hi> and are at this day che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished by persons most eminent in our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, I should not presume to offer this my weake, and imperfect labours, at the altar of your fauour, let the example of others more knowing, and more experienced in this kind (if my boldnesse offend) pleade my pardon, and the rather since there is no other meanes left mee (my misfortunes hauing cast me on this course, to publish to the world, if it hold the least good opinion of mee) that I am euer your Ladyships creature vouchsafe therefore with the neuer sayling clemency, of Your Noble disposition, not to contemne the tender of his duty, who while hee is, will euer bee.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>An humble seruant to your
Ladyship, and yours.</salute>
      <signed>PHILIP MESSENGER:</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>