<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Caesar Frederick to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112444_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00611</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10746</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Caesar Frederick to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The voyage and trauaile : of M. Cæsar Frederick, merchant of Venice, into the East India, the Indies, and beyond the Indies. Wherein are contained very pleasant and rare matters, with the customes and rites of those countries. Also, heerein are discovered the merchandises and commodities of those countreyes, aswell the aboundaunce of goulde and siluer, as spices, drugges, pearles, and other iewelles. Written at sea in the Hercvles of London: comming from Turkie, the 25. of March 1588. For the profitable instruction of merchants and all other trauellers, for their better direction and knowledge of those countreyes. Out of Italian, by T H</title>
                 <author>Federici, Cesare</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 41 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Caesar Frederick to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hauing (Gentle Reader) for the space of eighteene yeeres continually coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted &amp; trauailed as it were, all the East <hi>Indies,</hi> and many other countreyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the Indies, wherein I haue had both good and yll successe, in my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells: I haue seen &amp; vnderstood many things worthy the noting, and to bee knowne to all the world: the which were neuer as yet writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of any, I thought it good (seeing the almightie had giuen mee grace, after so long perilles in passing such a long voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,) to returne into my owne Country, the noble Citie of <hi>Ʋenice,</hi> I say, I thought it good, as breefely as I could, to write and set foorth this voiage made by mee, with the meruellous things I haue seene in my trauels in the Indies. The mightie Princes that gouern those Cuntreys, Their Religion, and faith that they haue, the rytes and customes which they vse, and liue by, of the diuers successe that hapned vnto me, and howe many of these conntreys are a bounding with spices, drugs, and Iewels, giuing also profitable aduertisement, to all those that haue a desire to make such a voyage. And because that the whole world may more commodiously reioice at this my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: I haue caused it to bee printed in this order, and nowe I present it vnto you (Gentle and Jouing Readers). to whome for the varieties of thinges herein conteined, I hope that it shall bee with great delight receiued, and thus God of his goodnesse keepe you.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>