<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112188_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68450</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17444a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112188</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A morall poem, intituled the Legend of Cupid and Psyche. Or Cupid and his mistris : As it was lately presented to the Prince Elector. Written by Shackerley Marmion, Gent</title>
                 <author>Marmion, Shackerley</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Shepherd (Sheppard), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>90 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were inhabitant in a certaine Cittie, a King and Queene,
who had three Daughters; the elder two of a moderate, and meane beauty; but the
yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest was of so curious, so pleasing a feature, and exact symmetry
of body, that men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem'd her generally a Goddesse, and the
<hi>Venus</hi> of the earth. Her sisters being happily married to their
desires and dignities, shee only out of a super-excellency of perfection,
became rather the subject of adoration, then <hi>Love. Venus</hi> conceiving
an offence, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious of her good parts, incites <hi>Cupid</hi> to a
revenge, and severe vindication of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers honour. <hi>Cupid</hi> like a
fine Archer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to execute his mothers designe, fals in love with the
<hi>maide,</hi> and wounds himselfe. <hi>Apollo,</hi> by <hi>Cupids</hi>
subornation, adjudges her in <pb facs="7"/>marriage to a <hi>Serpent.</hi> Vpon
which, like <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromeda,</hi> she is left chain'd to a Rocke, her marriage
being celebrated, rather with fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obsequies, than Hymenaeall
solemnities. In this miserable affright she is borne farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the
west Wind, to a goodly faire house, whose wealth and statelinesse
no praise can determine. Her husband in the deadnesse, and solitude of
night, did oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times enioy her, and as he entred in obscuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, so he
departed in silence, without once making himselfe knowne unto her: thus
she continued for a long season, being onely waited upon by the
ministery of the winds, and voyces; Her sisters came every day to feeke,
and bewaile her; and though her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band did with many threats prohibit her the
sight of them; yet naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prevailed above coniugall duty; for
she never ceased with teares to solicite him, till he had permitted their
accesse. They no no sooner arived, but instantly corrupt her, and with
wicked counsell deprave her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, infusing a beliefe, that
she had <pb facs="7"/>married, and did nightly embrace a true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; nor are
they yet contented to turne the heaven of her security into the hell of
suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, but with many importunities proceed, exhorting her to kill him,
which she also assents unto: Thus credulity proves the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of
deceite, and curiosity the Step-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of safety: Having thus prepar'd for
his destruction, the Sceane is altered, and shee acts the Tragedy of her
owne happy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; for comming with an intent to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe him, so
soone as the light had disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered what he was, shee fals into an
extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of love and passion, being altogether ravisht with his beauty
and habiliments; and while she kisses him, with as little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty as
care; the burning Lampe drops upon his shoulder, whereupon her husband
furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously awakes, and having with many expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulations abandoned her
falsehood, scornes and forsakes her: the maide after a tedious pilgrimage
to regaine his love and society: <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> having both
repulsed her, freely at the last offers up her selfe to <hi>Venus,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>where through her iniunctions and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious commands: she is
coursely intreated, and set to many hard and grievous taskes: as first
the seperation of severall graines; with the fetching of the
<hi>Stygian</hi> water, and the golden fleece, and the boxe of beauty from
<hi>Proserpine;</hi> all which by divine assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance being performed,
shee is reconcil'd, and in the presence of all the gods mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to her
husband: the wedding is solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd in heaven.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>