<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An admonicion for the vnlearned touching the vse of the figure of the beades here after portrued.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112699_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17125</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4000</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112699</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An admonicion for the vnlearned touching the vse of the figure of the beades here after portrued.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Instructions for the vse of the beades : conteining many matters of meditacion or mentall prayer, vvith diuerse good aduises of ghostly counsayle. VVere vnto is added a figure or forme of the beades portrued in a table. Compiled by Iohn Bucke for the benefit of vnlearned. And dedicated to the honorable good lady, Anne Lady Hungarforde, sister to the duchesse of Ferria</title>
                 <author>Bucke, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Maes (Masius), Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 87, 2 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>An admonicion for the vnlearned touching the vse of the figure of the beades here after portrued.</head>
   <p>THou hast here (gentle reder) a figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re or forme of the beades; vvith cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein matters of meditacion to be vsed vvhen thou art disposed to recite the crovvne of our ladie vpon the beades vvhiche matters haue not bene before this tyme put into englishe meter, for the beter memorie and delectatiō of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout persons. Therfore if thou hast bene here to fore delited vvith vain ballads and sonets, thou may novv vpon better aduise please thy selfe vvith songes and ditties more profitable. And of vvhat good trade, occupacion or qualiue so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you are, vvhiles you goe about your necessarie businesse in your vocation, or vvhiles you are traualing by the vvaye: or in tillinge or plovvinge the grovvnd that hit may bring great increase, you may not vvithstanding, some tyme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong,
<pb n="85" facs="43"/>call vpon our Sauiour or vpon the blessed virgin mary, eyther in vvorde or in thought, and vvith great comfort, yea and profit also both spirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, repeat or thinke vpon the Pater noster and Aue Mary, or some part ther of, and of the verses, or of some of them set dovvne in the table folovvinge. And ther vpon may you take occasion to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se and thinke lesse or more of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conteyned in the verses or any of them. VVher vpon you by Gods grace shall be induced in to a svvete cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion vvhat speciall graces God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stovved vpon you; from vvhat euells he hath preserued you; to vvhat good ende he hath created you: vvhat good reward he hath prouided for you, yf you come to that end: and to come vnto it you are assured if you be so vvilling as you ought to be. Thus shall you also take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to kepe your self vvell occupied, auoyde idle thoughts, the snares of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and so kepe your self in the vvay tovvardes heauen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>