<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Heigham, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112122_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03296</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1341</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112122</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Heigham, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An instruction how to pray and meditate well : Distinguished into thirtie six chapters. Composed at the request of certaine louers of pietie, desirous to aduance themselues in perfection. By the Reuerend Father, Ignatius Balsamo Priest of the Societie of Iesus. And translated out of French into English, by Iohn Heigham</title>
                 <author>Balsamo, Ignazio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>331, 5 pages, 24°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="154"/>
   <pb n="303" facs="154"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is vpon Iesus-Christ, your best beloued Spouse (deuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> &amp; deare affected soule) on whome your hart ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to muse &amp; meditate. in all your thoughtes, wordes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> deedes wills, desires, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirations, yea euen in all the houres, and moments of your life; It is he, I say, Who ought to be imbraced and lodged therin, both night and day, the Idea of your soule, the desire of your hart, and the onlie obiect of all your motions.</p>
   <p>To the end therfore, neuer so diuide or sequester your
<pb n="304" facs="155"/> selfe from his blessed compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, behould here certaine amourous discourses where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to entertaine you, and where vpon to employ your spirit in euerie moment, in manner of Petitions or briefe Meditations, so sweete, so fruitfull, so spirituall, yea s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> deuout and aggreable to your dearlie beloued Sauiour Iesus Christ, as that the same is a true and assured meanes, and most perfect methode, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue you perpetuallie in his holie grace, and to dwell with him, and in him, and he likewise with you, and within you in all occasions. Performe then, I beseeche you, that which is here perscribed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, not for the loue of me (allbeie I instantlie require
<pb n="305" facs="155"/> you) but for the most tender loue which you beare to his diuine maiestie.</p>
   <p>You shall begin this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall office at fiue a clock in the Euening, to meditate the first Aspiration &amp; sweete discourse, and so from houre to houre you shall continue, vntill the four and twentith houre, which will bring you to finish this exercise, at four a clocke, the next day after in the Euening; And then you shall begin againe att your first, and so shall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue euerie day (Gods grace assistinge you) vntill the day and houre, that he shall determine to place you with him selfe in perpetuall repose.</p>
   <p>Now, as touching the
<pb n="306" facs="156"/> houres ordained for rest, you shall obserue this easie rule. Before you fall a sleepe, be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ethor in your bed, or he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ort you goe to take your rest, you shall meditat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> four of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid Meditations. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> if it happen also that you awake in the night time, you shall meditate one or two more. If you awaken not all the night, in the morning you shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōplish althose houres which you haue omitted: and in this sort you shall alwaies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
   <p>This holie Exercise, you haue meanes to performe in working, talking, walking and in all manner of affaires which you shall doe, for it is nether the bodie, nor yet the tongue which is burthened by
<pb n="307" facs="156"/> this Exercise, but it is the spirit &amp; the hare which spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and testifieth to Iesus-Christ, the fidelitie and care which it hath to please him. This also may be done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hindringe you any thinge at all from your other pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ether Mentall, or Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, yea or so much as to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould you from attendinge, to any other godlie worke, or laudable Exercise whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer; Practise then, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuere.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your seruant in Christ Iesus. Iohn Heigham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>