<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The peroracyon or conclusyon of / the worke to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1535</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112620_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07430</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17817</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The peroracyon or conclusyon of / the worke to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of peace: lately translated out of laten in to englysshe. with the kynges moste gracyous priuilege</title>
                 <author>Marsilius, of Padua</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marshall, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1535</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 21, 23-1340, that is 140, 2 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="conclusion_to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1340" facs="143"/>
   <head>¶ The peroracyon or conclusyon of / the worke to the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haste here most gentyll reader, A worke, whiche albeit that it is not perauenture set forth with paynted wordes, and eloquent speache / yet is there wysdome in it not to be dyspysed. This say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de worke, it hathe lyked and pleased the auctor therof: to entytle Defensor pacis / that is to saye in Englysshe: the defender or maynteyner of Peace / because in it he hathe dylygentlye and faythfullye gathered togyther, and also hathe in goodlye ordre sette forthe, all the wayes and meanes: by whiche most cheyflye, empyers, realmes, or any other cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyle socyetes, or felowshyppes of men, amonge them selues are or maye be beste holden, or kepte, and consydered, or ioyned togyther, by a certayne contynuall fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoure and loue of the offycers or rulers and of the multytude or cōmunes eache to other establesshed, and made fyrme and sure, without feare or dreade of any sedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, dyscorde debate or stryfe, bothe partes keapynge themselues within theyr owne ryghte, as it were within a certayne lymytes or boundes: and neyther of them chalengynge or vsurpynge any thynges vnto themselues, saue onely that, whiche the lawes wyll gyue them leaue. Whiche consent, and concorde, or agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwene the orders, degrees or estates, because it hath not ben so dylygently regarded and seen vnto, as was mete and accordynge that it shuld haue ben: and whyles the one sorte, to boldlye, agaynst ryght and lawe, dothe hurte the other howe great hurtes, and troublouse stormes, it hathe alwayes styrred and raysed vp, not onely in temporall maters, but also in sprytualte maters: bothe the tymes of our elders and forefathers partely, but specyally and cheyfly these presente tymes, vexed with so many incōmodytes, and myscheuouse euylles and troubles by reason hereof, doth euydent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declare and proue. Agaynst whiche euylles, wolde god that some conuenyent helpe &amp; remedy were founde, afore it come to that passe that they be vtterlye paste remedye: by tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se persones, whiche worthelye both ought and also myght remedye them. But I exorte and desyre the, most good &amp; gentyll rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: dylygentlye to tourne ouer and to laboure this worke, called the defender of peace. Thou shalte fynde in it the Image of these our tymes most perfytly and clerlye expressed and set out. And also, that euen afore these dayes, euery one of the beste Emperours hath ben con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynually sore vexed &amp; troubled with the same tyrannye of Romanystes: wherwith nowe all good men be accombred, greaued, and noyed, not without the cruell and deadelye iniurye of the cōmune weale.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>