<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112010_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10497</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20773</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fovre svmmons of the Shvlamite : A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse vpon Rogation Sunday, the 5. of May. 1605. By John Rawlinson, Bachelor of Diuinitie, and fellow of Saint Iohns Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London ; Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 82 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my purpose <hi>(Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader)</hi> that these my sory labours should ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue slept in silēce, and ben buried in the <hi>Church-yard</hi> where first they were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht, then by a second publicatiō (more publike) haue stoode to the mercie of many mercilesse <hi>Censors.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Sure J am, it had ben my safer and surer way, to haue practised the policie of <hi>Antony</hi> in <hi>Tully,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cicer. orat. pro Cluen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> who woulde never make his pen <hi>publike-Notarie</hi> to his tongue, that if ought had at any time fallen from him superfluous or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, hee might safely denie that to haue ben spoken, which written hee could not so soundly warrant:</p>
   <p>Especially, considering the conditiō of these times: wherein <hi>VVriters,</hi> and
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Readers</hi> are both too-blame. For as there is more than Gods plenty of <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> such as are at <hi>Davids Dico ego ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra mea Regi:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 45.1.</note> before they can saie with <hi>David, Eructavit cor meum verbum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> More carefull to provide a vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Patron for their worke, than a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worke worthy the Patronage: and so combring the Presse with froathy &amp; worthles Pamphlets, that had it voice, it would hideously roare and cry, like a man now almost presst to death: <hi>More weight; for the loue of god, more weight: more weight in your matter, but lesse of your paper.</hi> So is there a marveilous pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of <hi>Readers,</hi> (such as are wel &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably affected;) insomuch that fevve there are of the more ingenuous sorte, <hi>Qui malint eloquendo culpam deprecari,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Macrob. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. l. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>quàm tacendo culpâ vacare:</hi> who had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by divulging their endevors craue a curteous pardon; than by suppressing them be out of gunshot of cavill &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; the very quintessence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens learning being nothing but a
<pb facs="3"/>carping at other mens labors; and yet some of those many such, as I know had rather preach 20. Sermons, than print one, least their filching and purloining should be tracked and detected.</p>
   <p>But the Reasons that haue vvrought me, thus to venture vpon the sharpe of this ages censure, are chiefly two;</p>
   <p>One, The incessant <hi>importunity</hi> of friends, to whom J may say as <hi>Paulinus</hi> doth to his vpon like occasion:<note place="margin">Paul. epist. <hi>9</hi> ad Sulpit. Sever.</note>
      <hi>Sibi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putet famem, qui pauperis amici forem pulsat, &amp; promptuariū inane scrutatur.</hi> Let him thanke himselfe, if hee be sent away hungry, who knocks as the dore of his poore friend, and rifles his empty cupbord for victuals.</p>
   <p>Another, The instant <hi>necessitie</hi> of these daies (these last, &amp; evill daies) the sores wherof run and cease not, because the sinnes thereof cry, &amp; stent not; that by a deepe and diligent consideration of the many saving lessons herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the men of this generation may vnfeignedly and effectually turne from
<pb facs="4"/>their wicked waies, and so turne awaie from them, and from this whole Land the angry viols of Gods dreadfull ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, the dregs wherof else they are likely to sucke vp.</p>
   <p>These (with other the like) reasons, haue somuch the rather prevailed with me, because I am for surety givē to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstād, that there passe abroad for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, some maimed and dismēbred co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, (such as were cursorily taken frō my mouth) which J knowe not how far forth they may turne to my preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: And haue caused me to republish this Sermon,<note place="margin">Ioan. 11.44</note> like a <hi>Lazarus rediuinus,</hi> newly risen out of the <hi>graue</hi> of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, bound about not with <hi>napkins,</hi> but with <hi>paper-sheets;</hi> to preach not <hi>Viuâ v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ce,</hi> with any liuelyhood of voice as before (which yet is the chiefe grace &amp; vernish of a Sermō) but with a dead &amp; black letter: A killing letter to those that will not turne, but a quickening letter to the penitent <hi>Conuert;</hi> That what then was sounded forth in the
<pb facs="4"/>eares of a Great and Honorable assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (the very confluence of the whole Land) may now subiect it selfe likewise to the eies, aswell of the then absent, as of those that were present:<note place="margin">Aug. tract. de Epicur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Stoic. ca. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Vt nesci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes instruantur, scientes cōmoneātur: illi cognoscant, illi recognoscāt:</hi> that the ignorant may be instructed, the learned admonished, that the one may learne what his duty is, the other recognize what he hath learned:</p>
   <p>That what then was confined with in the space of two houres, may now be <hi>Omnium horarum:</hi> A sermon for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very houre:</p>
   <p>Lastly, That what thē, (by the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God) was thought fruitfull to many, may now (by the same blessing) become profitable to all. It shal then be thy part <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> (such as it is) to take it in good part, naked, and (J think) <hi>Verbatìm</hi> as it was vttered: as imparted vnto thee to no worse end, than to make thee partaker of that bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed aspect, which is promised (&amp; should
<pb facs="5"/>also haue ben hādled) in the second ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral part of my <hi>Text,</hi> had not the time intercepted my discourse.</p>
   <p>Now if any shal aske (as in such a world of <hi>Busybodies,</hi> many of liklyhood will) what the reason might be, that albeit I serue a Right-worthily Great &amp; eminent Father of the Church, the Lorde Bishop of London, (sole prop and pillar of my hopes and fortunes) to whome as (in parte) J owe to the very prime beginnings of that smal preferment which J haue (which since he hath also seconded by many grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous encouragments:) so J wholy vow <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, the very vtmost mite of my poore seruice: Yet J send forth this Sermon into the world, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior did his disciples,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.10.</note>
      <hi>sine baculo et perâ:</hi> without either <hi>the staffe</hi> of protection, or <hi>the scrip</hi> of dedication wherwith to beg patronage; My answere is ready, that as <hi>Minimum maximi maius est maximo minimi.</hi> The least of that which is greatest is more than the greatest of
<pb facs="5"/>the least: so the least of his fauours is more then the greatest of my desarts: and to present his Greatnes with so small a <hi>present,</hi> were but <hi>assem Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanto dare:</hi> as J may say,<note place="margin">Macrob. Sat. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> to giue a <hi>dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin to a Monarch.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue therfore chosen rather to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it as a poore patronlesse <hi>Orphan,</hi> that so it may happily meet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Patrons.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vide. Pag. <hi>56.</hi>
      </note> J am sure one part of it hath already met with some.</p>
   <p>Or if it proue so infortunate, to haue none to patronize it, yet my trust is that God <hi>(the father of Orphans)</hi> will accept it,<note place="margin">Psal. 68.5.</note> To whose blessed protection J commit both it and thee: as my selfe &amp; al my studies to thy godly and dayly prayers: reciprocally prayeng vnto God, for thee, and thy souls good.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> JOHN RAWLINSON.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From</hi> S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Iohns Coll. in Oxon.</hi>
         <date>Ian. 10.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>