<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112048_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10903</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112048</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon of loue : Instructing all men to vnite and ioyne themselues in hearty loue, and Christian charitie with one another. Preached at Folkestone, a maior towne in Kent. By Francis Rogers, Batchelor in Diuinity; and sometimes fellow of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 45, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Hierom</hi> saith very well, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet nescio quid latentis energiae viua vox, &amp; in aures discipuli de authoris ore transfusa fortius so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat:</hi> the liuely voyce of man, speaking hath some especiall secret operation in the minde, and doth send a more strong sound into the eares of the hearer In which respect, I perswade my selfe this Sermon will prooue like vnto Tapestry wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> which seemeth faire farre off, but when yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> neere vnto it, you may discerne the coursenesse of the threed; for as Philosophy tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, the eare is a farre more dull iudge then the eye; and reason teacheth vs, that we cannot so truely discerne of things which suddenly passe away, as of obiects which are still permanent.</p>
   <p>Therefore as alwayes, so now especially, I did desire to imitate <hi>Plato</hi> the Diuine Philosopher, of whom it is said, <hi>Maluit aliena verecunde discere, quam sua impudenter ingerere:</hi> Hee had rather learne of others with modestie, then impudently make shew of his owne knowledge. Yet the importunitie of my fellow-brethren and Ministers, then present, was such, as my case did resemble the seruants of King <hi>Eglon,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iudg. 3.25.</note> they tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at the doore till they were ashamed: so I denied them so long as I was ashamed to deny them any more. Wherefore now I present this Sermon vnto thee (gentle Reader) accept it
<pb facs="5"/>
kindely, read it patiently, censure it charitably, and practise it diligently. If thou reapest any good thereby, giue the glory to him who is the Author and giuer of euery good gift: onely thus much I aduertise thee: <hi>Aristotle</hi> the great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher in his bookes doth often refell the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Master <hi>Plato,</hi> and he neuer doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse his so doing, but onely in his Ethickes; the reason whereof is giuen, that hee being in those bookes to giue precepts of good manners vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, would not himselfe seeme so much to transgresse the bounds of modestie &amp; good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as once publikely to write against his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster which taught him, and his Tutor which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed him, without good reason and lawfull excuse. Euen so remember (good Reader) that when thou doest reade this Sermon, thou doest read a Treatise of <hi>LOVE,</hi> then do not while thou art reading of loue, so farre degenerate from the nature of loue, and bond of Christian Charitie, as once to giue it an harsh censure, and vncharitable construction: <hi>humanum est er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare,</hi> to erre, and be deceiued, is proper to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailtie: <hi>ergo pietatis est ignoscere, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitatis non agnoscere;</hi> therefore pietie teacheth thee to forgiue the faults, &amp; humanitie biddeth thee not to acknowledge the faults: And thus I commit thee to the protection of the most high God. From <hi>Alkham</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Kent,</hi> this <hi>10.</hi> of <hi>February. 1613.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, <hi>FRANCIS ROGERS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>