<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Exhortation to the Planter and Graffer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112379_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07168</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17574</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112379</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Exhortation to the Planter and Graffer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke of the arte and maner, howe to plant and graffe all sortes of trees : howe to set stones, and sowe pepines to make wylde trees to graffe on, as also remedies and mediicnes [sic] . VVith diuers other newe practise, by one of the Abbey of Saint Vincent in Fraunce, practised with his owne handes, deuided into seauen chapters, as hereafter more plainely shall appeare, with an addition in the ende of this booke, of certaine Dutch practises, set forth and Englished, by Leonard Mascall</title>
                 <author>Mascall, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wight (Wyght, Wayght, Whyte?), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 90, 10 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_planters">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>An Exhortation to the Planter and Graffer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lwayes before ye do intend to plant or graffe, it shal be meete to haue good experience in thinges meete for thys Arte, as in knowing the Natures of all trees and fruites, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Clymates, which be contrarie in euery land: also to vnderstand the East and West win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, with aspectes and Starres, to the ende yee maye beginne nothinge that the winde or rayne may oppresse, that your labour be not lost, and to marke also and consider the disposition of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that present yeare, for all yeares be not of lyke operation, nor yet after one sorte, the Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and Winter doe not beare one face on the earth, nor the spring time alwayes rayny, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne alwaies moyst: of this none haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, without a good and liuely marking spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, fewe or none (without learning) may discerne of the varieties &amp; qualities of the earth, &amp; what he doth aske or refuse. Therefore it shall be good to haue vnderstanding of the ground where ye do plant, either Orchard or gardē with fruite, first it behooueth to make a sure defēce, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> end, that not only rude persons and children may be kept out, but all kinde of hurtfull cattell indomaging your plantes or trees, as Oxen, kyne, Calues, Horse, Hogges &amp; shepe, as the rubbing of Sheepe doth greatly burne the sappe, and often doth kyll yong
<pb facs="11"/>
trees and plantes, and where they are broken or brused with cattel, it is doubtful to grow after. It shal be good also, to set, plant or graffe trees all of lyke nature and strength togither, that the great and hye trees, may not ouercome the lowe and weake, for when they be not lyke of heyght, they growe, nor rype not your fruit so wel at one time but the one before the other: that earth whiche is good for Vynes, is good also for other fruite. Ye must digge your holes a yeare before ye plant that the earth may be better seasoned, mortifyed and waxe tender, both by rayne in Winter, and heate in Sommer, that therby your plants may take roote the sooner, if ye will make your holes, and plant both in a yeare, at the least, ye ought to make your holes two monethes before ye plant, and as soone as they be made, then it shal be good to burne of strawe or such lyke therin, to make your grounde warme: the further ye make them asunder, the better your trees shall beare: make your holes lyke vnto a fornayce, that is, more straight in the mouth than beneath, whereby the rootes may haue the more roome, and by straight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the mouth, the lesse raine or colde shal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by in Winter, and also lesse heate to the roote in Sōmer. Loke also that the earth ye put to the rootes, be neyther wet, nor layde in water: they doe commonly leaue a good space betwixt euery tree, for the hanging bowes, for being nyghe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther, yee cannot set rootes, nor sowe nothing so well vnder your trees, nor they wyll not beare
<pb facs="11"/>
fruite so wel: some loweth fourtie foote, some thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betweene euery tree: your plantes ought to be greater than the handle of a shouell, and the lesser the better: see they be straight, without knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or knobbes, hauing a long straight graine or barke, which shall the sooner be apt to take graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, and when ye set braunches or boughes of old trees, choose the yongest and straytest braunche therof, and those trees which haue borne yearely good fruite before, take of those which be on the sunny side, soner than those that grow in the court or shadowe, and when ye take vppe or alter your plantes, ye shal note to what winds your plant is subiect, and so let them be sette agayne, but those which haue growne in dry groundes, let them be set in moyst ground: your plantes ought to be cut of three foote long. If ye will sette two or three plantes togither in a hole, ye must take heede the roote of one touche not one another, for then the one will perishe and rot the other, or dye by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or other varmen, and when ye haue placed your plantes in the earth, it shall be good to strike downe to the bottō of euery hole two short stakes as great as your arme, on either side your hole one, &amp; let thē appeare but a little aboue the earth that ye may (therby in Sommer) giue water vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rootes if neede be. Your yong plantes, and rooted trees are commonly set in Autumme, from the first vnto the .xv. of October, yet some opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, better after Alhollowtide vnto Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masse, than in the spring, bycause the earth wyll
<pb facs="12"/>
dry to soone after, and also to set plantes wythout roote after Michaelmasse, that they may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mollifie and gather roote against the spring, wherof ye shall finde hereafter more at large. Thus much haue I thought meete to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto the Planter<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, whereby they may the better auoyde the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and daungers of planting and graffing, which may come oftentymes through ignoraunce.</p>
   <p>1572.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>