<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>VPON THIS WORKE OF HIS beloued friend the AVTHOR.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112414_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07237</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17634</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112414</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>VPON THIS WORKE OF HIS beloued friend the AVTHOR.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Duke of Millaine : A tragædie. As it hath beene often acted by his Maiesties seruants, at the blacke Friers. Written by Philip Massinger Gent</title>
                 <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_author">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>VPON THIS WORKE OF HIS <hi>beloued friend the</hi> AVTHOR.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>I <hi>Am snap't already, and may goe my way;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The Poet-Critick's <hi>come; I heare him say,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>This YOVTH'S mistooke, The Authors WORKE'S a PLAY.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>He could not misse it; he will strait appeare</l>
      <l>At such a baite; Twas laid on purpose there</l>
      <l>To take the <hi>vermine,</hi> and I haue him here.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Sirra, you wilbe nibling; a small bitt,</l>
      <l>(a sillable) when yo' are i' the hungry fitt,</l>
      <l>Will scrue to stay the stomacke of your witt.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Foole; Knaue;</hi> what's worse? for worse cannot depraue</l>
      <l>And were the <hi>diuell</hi> now instantly to haue thee, (thee</l>
      <l>Thou canst not instance such a <hi>worke</hi> to saue thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Mongst all the <hi>ballets</hi> which thou dost compose,</l>
      <l>And what thou stil'st thy <hi>Poems,</hi> ill as those,</l>
      <l>And void of rime, and reason, thy worse <hi>Prose.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet like a rude <hi>Iack-sauce</hi> in <hi>Poesie,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>With thoughts vnblest, and hand vnmanerly,</l>
      <l>Rauishing branches from <hi>Apoll'os</hi> tree.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thoumak'st a garland (for thy touch vnfit)</l>
      <l>And boldly deck'st thy pig-brain'd sconce with it,</l>
      <l>As if it were the <hi>Supreme Head</hi> of <hi>wit.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <l>The blameles <hi>Muses</hi> blush; who not allow</l>
      <l>That reuerend <hi>Order,</hi> to each vulgar brow,</l>
      <l>Whose sinfull touch prophanes the holy <hi>Bough.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Hence (shallow <hi>Prophet</hi>) and admire the straine</l>
      <l>Of thine owne <hi>Pen,</hi> or thy poore <hi>Copesmat's</hi> vaine.</l>
      <l>This <hi>PIECE</hi> too cartous is, for thy course <hi>braine.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Here <hi>witt</hi> (more fortunate) is ioyn'd with <hi>Art,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And that most sacred <hi>Frenzie</hi> beares a part</l>
      <l>Infus'd by <hi>Nature</hi> in the <hi>Poe'ts</hi> heart.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Here, may the <hi>Puny-wits</hi> themselues direct,</l>
      <l>Here, may the <hi>Wisest</hi> find what to affect;</l>
      <l>And <hi>Kings</hi> may learne their proper <hi>Dialect.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>On then, deare friend, Thy <hi>Pen</hi> thy <hi>Name</hi> shall spread;</l>
      <l>And should'st thou write, while thou shalt not be read,</l>
      <l>Thy <hi>Muse</hi> must labour, when thy <hi>Hand</hi> is dead.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>