<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112182_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04468</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14600.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112182</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Apologie of the Churche of Englande : conteininge an answeare to a certaine booke lately set foorthe by M. Hardinge, and entituled, A confutation of &amp;c. By Iohn Iewel Bishop of Sarisburie</title>
                 <author>Jewel, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 742, 18 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pitieth mee in thy behalfe, good Christian
Reader, to sée they conscience thus assaulted this daie
with so contrarie Doctrines of Religion: and special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
if thou haue a zele to folowe, and séeste not, what:
and wouldeste faine please Eod, and knoweste not,
howe: nor findeste thée selfe sufficiently armed with
Goddes Holy Sprite: nor hable either to discerue thy
meate from poison, or to vnwinde thée selfe out of
the snares.<note place="margin">2 Corin. 11.</note>
      <hi>For Satan transfourmeth him selfe into an
Angel of Light:</hi> The wicked is more watcheful, and
vehemente, then the Godly: and Falsehed is oftentimes painted, and vewtified,
and shineth more glorious then the Truthe.</p>
   <p>These be the thinges,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. Matthae. 24. 2. Tim. 2. Iohan. 10. Roman. 8.</note> that, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> saithe, <hi>woorke the subuersion of the
Hearers:</hi> and by meane whereof, as <hi>Christe</hi> saithe, <hi>if it were possible, the very
Bsecte of God shoulde be deceiued.</hi> Howe be it, <hi>God knoweth his owne: and no
Power can pusse them out of his hande.</hi> God is hable to woorke comforte out of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
and to force his light to shine out of darkenesse. <hi>Al thinges woorke vnto good
vnto them, that be in Christe Iesu.</hi> Be Falsehed neuer so freashely coloured, yet in
the ende the Truthe wil conquere.</p>
   <p>Notwithstandinge, <hi>God</hi> in these daies hath so amazed the Aduersaries of his
<hi>Gospel,</hi> and hath caused them so openly, and so grossely to laie abroade their folies,
to the sight, and face of al the world, that noman nowe, be he neuer so ignorante,
can thinke, he maie iustely be excused. They deale not nowe so suttelly, as other
Heretiques in old times were woont to doo: thei hide not the lothsomenesse of their
errours: they cloke not them selues in Shéepeskinnes: they dissemble nothinge:
they excuse nothing: but, without either shame of man, or feare of God, they rake
vp those thinges, that before were buried, that themselues had forsaken, the wise
had abhorred, the worlde had lothed. It had benne more policie for them, to haue
yeelded in sommewhat, and to haue staied in the reste. So there might haue appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
somme plainenesie in theire dealinges.</p>
   <p>But this is <hi>Goddes</hi> iuste iudgemente, that they, that wilfully withstande the
Truthe,<note place="margin">Esai. 30.</note> shoulde be geeuen ouer to mainteine Lies, as beeinge the <hi>Children of Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthe,
Children, that wil not heare the Lawe of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For trial whereof, I beseeche thée, good Reader, aduisedly to peruse these fewe
notes, truely taken out of <hi>M. Hardinges late Confutation.</hi> Iudge thereof, as
thou shalt sée cause. Let no affection, or fantasie cause thinges to séeme otherwise,
then they be.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The twoo principal Groūdes of this whole Booke are these:</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. Harding. fol. 334. b.</note>
      <hi>First,</hi> That the Pope,
although he maie erre by personal errour, in his owne Priuate Iudgement, as a man, and as a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulare
Doctour in his owne opinion: yet as he is Pope, as he is the Successour of Peter, as he is
y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Vicare of Christe in Earthe, and as he is the Shepheard of the Vniuersal Churche, in Publique
Judgement, in deliberation, and Definitiue Sentence, he neuer erreth, nor neuer erred, nor neuer
can erre: <hi>As if he woulde saie, The Pope walkinge in his Galerie is one man: and
fittinge in Consistorie, or in Iudgemente, is an other: Whiche thinge to holde,
<hi>Alphonsus de Castro</hi> saithe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Alphons. lib. 1. Cap. 4.</note>
      <hi>it is mere folie. Yet is this M. Hardinges chiefest,
or rather, as I might in manner saie, his onely grounde.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Seconde is this,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Confu. Fol. 16. b. Fol. 261. b.</note> The Churche of Rome is the whole, and onely Catholique
Churche of God: and, who so euer is not obediente vnto the same, muste be iudged an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>lere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.
<hi>These twoo groundes beinge once wel, and surely laied, he maie builde at
pleasure, what him listeth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for the <hi>Pope,</hi> the better to countenance his estate, he saithe, that <hi>Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="11"/>
thee, I beséeche thee to consider, with what indifferente Iudgement M. Harding
woulde haue thée to passe bitwéene vs.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Firste he saithe,</hi> What should wee seeke for Truthe?<note place="margin">Reioind. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Preface to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Reader. * iij * iiij a. * iiij b. ** ij. a.</note> Let vs onely beholde the custome
of the Churche. <hi>Againe,</hi> What Argumentes, what Assegations, what shewe of disproufe
so euer he bringe againste these thinges, wee ought to make smal accoumpte thereof. <hi>Againe,</hi>
I would blesse mee selfe from him, as from the Minister of Satan, and as from the Disciple of
Antichriste, and as from Goddes open, and professed enimie. <hi>Againe,</hi> M. Iewelles Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie,
and other like Hereticol Bookes, are vnlawful to be readde, by order of the Churche,
without special licence: and are vtterly forebidden to be readde, or keapte, vnder paine of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.
<hi>And againe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reioind. In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Preface to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Iewel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> As for the Replie, none other waie wil serue, but to throwe al
into the fire.</p>
   <p>Of the other side, touching the <hi>VVoorde of God,</hi> with most terrible woordes
he fraieth thée from it, and biddeth thee to consider of other thinges, and to behold,
I knowe not,<note place="margin">Confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 212 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Reioind. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Preface to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Reader.</note> what. <hi>Yee prostitute the Scriptures,</hi> he saith, <hi>as Baudes doo their Harlottes,
to the Vngodly, Vnlearned, Rascal people:</hi> Againe, <hi>Prentises, Light Personnes, and
the rifferaffe of the people:</hi> And againe, <hi>The Vnlearned people were keapte from the
Reading of the Scriptures by the special prouidence of God, that pretious stoanes should not be
throwen before Swine.</hi>
      <note place="margin">M Har. in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare, Artic. 15. Diui. 7.</note> In sutche regarde these menne haue, as wel the <hi>Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi>
as also the <hi>People of God.</hi> The <hi>scriptures</hi> they resemble to common
Harlottes, and the vileste creatures of the stewes: The people of God they calle,
<hi>Vngodly, Rascalles, Rifferaffe,</hi> and <hi>Filthy Svvine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus he suffereth thée not to reade, either <hi>my poore Booke,</hi> whereof thou
shouldest Iudge: or the <hi>Holy VVoorde of God,</hi> whereby thou mightest he hable
to Iudge: but onely biddeth thée to folowe him, and to saie, as he saithe: and al is
safe. Thus, firste he blindeth thine eies, and then willeth thee to looke aboute, and
to condemne the thinge,<note place="margin">Hierony. in Esa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iam, lib. 9. ca. 30.</note> thou neuer kneweste. So saithe S. <hi>Hierome, Isti tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam
sibi assumunt Authoritatem, vt siue dextra doceant, siue sinistra, id est, siue
bona, siue mala, nolint Discipulos ratione discutere, sed se praecessores sequi:
<hi>These menne take so mutche vpon them selues, that, whether they teache with the Right
hande, or with the Lefte, that is to saie, whether they teache good thinges, or badde, they
wil not haue theire Hearers, or Learners, to enquire causes, wherefore they shoulde doo this,
or that: but onely to folowe them, beeing theire Leaders.</hi>
      </hi>
   </p>
   <p>But beware, I beséeche, thée, good Christian Reader. A simple eie is soone begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.
It is very course Woolle, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> wil take no coloure. It is a desperate cause, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> with
woordes, and eloquence maie not be smoothed. Be not deceiued. Remember, of
what maters, and with what Aduersaries thou haste to deale. With feace, and
reuerence be careful of thine owne Saluation. Laie downe al affection, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure
of parties. Iudge iustely of that shalbe alleged. Onlesse thou knowe, thou
canste not Iudge: Onlesse thou heare bothe sides, thou canste not knowe. If thou
like ought, knowe, why thou likeste it. A wise man in eche thinge wil searche the
cause. He, that cannot iudge golde by sounde, or insight, yet maie trie it by the
poise. If thou canste not weigh these maters, for want of Learninge, yet, so
sensible, and so grosse they are, thou maiste féele them with thy fingers. Thou
maiste soone finde a difference bitwéene Golde, and Brasse: bitweene Iacob, and
Esau: bitwéene a Face, and a Visarde: bitweene a fuile Body, and an emptie Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Saie not, Thou arte settled in thy Beliefe, before thou know it.</hi> Vaine Faith,
is no Faithe.<note place="margin">August De Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore. Sermon 145. August. in quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ion. Veter. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stamen quaest. 43.</note>
      <hi>S.</hi> Augustines <hi>counsel is good: <hi>Beleeu: nomore of Christe, then
Christ hath willed thee to beleeue:</hi>
      </hi> Nemo de Christo credat, nisi, quod de se credi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit
Christus. <hi>Likewise he saithe,</hi> Fides stulta non prodest, sed obest: <hi>Fonde
Faith is hurtful, and dooth no good. <hi>S.</hi>
      </hi> Hilarie <hi>saithe,</hi> Non minus est, Deum fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,
<pb facs="12"/>
quàm negare:<note place="margin">Hilar. in Psal. 1.</note>
      <hi>To diuise fansies of God, it is as horrible, as to saie, There is no God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Anciente Father <hi>Tertullian,</hi> speakinge of the Enimies of the Crosse of
Christe, that disdeigned to submitte theire willes to the wil of God, saithe thus:
<hi>Amant ignorare,</hi>
      </hi>
      <note place="margin">Tertull. in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logetico.</note>
      <hi>cùm alij gaudeant cognouisse. Malunt nescire, quod iam ode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.
Adeo' quod nesciunt, praeiudicant id esse, quod, si scirent, odisse non pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent:</hi>
They desire to be ignorante, whereas other folkes desire to knowe. They woulde not
knowe the Truthe, bicause they hate it. (<hi>What so euer it be</hi>) they imagine it to be the same
thinge, that they hate. But if they knewe it in deede, thei coulde not hate it. <hi>Let Reason
leade thee: let Authoritie moue thée: let Truthe enforce thée. The <hi>VViseman</hi>
saithe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 2.</note> Who so feareth the Lorde, wil not be wilful againste his Woorde. <hi>God of his
mercie confounde al Errours: géeue the Victorie to his <hi>Truthe:</hi> and Glorie to his
Holy name, Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London. <date>27. Octobris, 1567.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>