<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To all true louers of the
pure Gospell and holy doctrine of
Iesus Christ, and to all those that
desire the preseruation of the Realme
of France, Peter Erondelle wi∣sheth
health in the Lord.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112258_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00397</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10512</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112258</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To all true louers of the
pure Gospell and holy doctrine of
Iesus Christ, and to all those that
desire the preseruation of the Realme
of France, Peter Erondelle wi∣sheth
health in the Lord.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration and catholick exhortation to all Christian princes to succour the Church of God and realme of France. Written by Peter Erondelle, natife of Normandie. Faithfully translated out of the French</title>
                 <author>Erondelle, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aggas, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To all true louers of the
pure Gospell and holy doctrine of
Iesus Christ, and to all those that
desire the preseruation of the Realme
of France, Peter Erondelle wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth
health in the Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Doubt not but doe sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly
perceiue, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
shall consider of my
calling wil disdain to looke
vpon this briefe Treatise,
as proceeding frō a person
vnworthie such a worke,
yea and will maruaile from whence J should
gather such boldnesse, sith I am not adorned or
furnished with any humaine wisedome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
to beautifie or rather paint out the same.
But what aunswer shall J make them? For it
is not I that haue wrought this woorke, but
euen GOD himselfe through the vertue and
power of the holy Ghost working in mee, who
word by word hath shewed and enstructed me
in all that is herein set downe, as vsing mee a
poore and miserable sinner to indure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade
or rather commaund all those that haue
the feare of God and doctrine of Iesus Christ
before their eyes, to succour his afflicted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
who are on euery side oppressed, but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
in our France by some tyrants, vnto whō
J present not this briefe discourse, for I am suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
perswaded that this kinde of people do
but seeke occasion to subuert &amp; set at va<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3+ letters">
         <desc>•••…</desc>
      </gap>nce
such a Commonwealth as before remayned in
peace and vnitie: But vnto you my brethren,
doe J direct the same, desiring you not to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine
the sight therof, but in equitie and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
al passion (other thē reason) to reade it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
therein you finde some fault:
Neither would I herein seeke to flatter or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale
the aucthors of these present troubles:
namely the house of Guyze, who are the chiefe
Captaines and conductors thereof, as also I
should get nothing by concealing them, as being
a matter which euery man knoweth better
then J can tell them how it standeth. Besides I
will not delay the time in beautifying this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
with any painted speech to adorne it
withall, as some doe when they seeke and goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
to perswade lyes in stead of trueth vnder
the colour of a pleasant phrase and painted
speech which is sufficient to leade the Readers
thereunto, and lulling them on sleepe procureth
them, as afore is sayde, to admit lyes in liew of
truth, euen as the Mermaide who by her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
song ouercommeth the Saylers, and when
they be at rest deuoureth them all. J would not
<pb n="6" facs="3"/>
therefore imitate them, but onely speake plainly
according to all the wordes that haue fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
my mouth whereby God hath holpen me to
bring the same to passe. To him therfore are we
to yeeld thankes, and withal to pray him to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
al our workes to the glory of his name and
excellencie of his iustice, as also that through
the blood of his welbeloued sonne Iesus Christ,
he will vouchsafe vs remission of all our sinnes.
<hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <div type="prayer">
      <head>A Prayer.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God almightie who
knowest the hearts and thoughtes
of al men, so as we doe not so son<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
imagine what to say but thou kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>west
better then our selues what
our tongue should pronounce, &amp;
that there is nothing vpon the earth or vnder the same
how secrete soeuer, but is manifest vnto thee. Wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
thee O Lorde in the name of thy welbeloued
sonne Iesus Christ, that it may please thee to open and
reueale whatsoeuer the wicked purposes of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse,
whereby they may haue no meanes left to perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
thy faithful. Neuerthelesse if it please thee O Lord
yet to continue the afflictions of thy Church, like as
we know thee to be a iust and true Iudge, we do not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
beseech thee not to punish vs in thy
wrath or according to our deserts, who deserue onely
euerlasting damnation, but thy will be done, for so it is
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
most expedient. We confesse that we haue grieuously
prouoked thee against vs and are greatly endaungered
to thy most iust iudgement, howbeit we beseech thee
O Lorde, enter not thereinto with vs, for our sinnes in
thy sight are innumerable euen as the sand of the Sea
or droppes of water of the same, it may please thee
therefore O Lord, not to call thē to thy remembrance,
but through the death and passion of thy welbeloued
sonne Iesus Christ to wipe thē away. We beseech thee
also that it may please thee to preserue those Kings &amp;
Princes that are endued with the knowledge of thy
Gospell, and doe dayly fight for the same, thereby vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the shadow of their wings preseruing many faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
poore persons: vouchsafe them the encrease of thy
grace. Touch also the mindes of such Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
as doe vexe thy poore seruants, and suffer not their
hearts to be hardened like as was the heart of Pharao
King of Egipt against thy people of Israell, and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
O Lord vouchsafe to bring them into the bosome
of thy Church, so to enioye the cleare light thereof,
which is, to see and knowe the trueth. And this do we
most humbly beseech thee in the name and fauour of
thy dearely beloued sonne our Lorde Iesus Christ as
himselfe hath taught vs saying. Our Father which art
in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
      <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>