<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the VVorshipfull his very good Cosen William Carr of Stafford in the county of Lincolne Esquire, and one in hir Maiesties Commission of peace there.</title>
           <author>Carr, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112763_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07605</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17997</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the VVorshipfull his very good Cosen William Carr of Stafford in the county of Lincolne Esquire, and one in hir Maiesties Commission of peace there.</title>
                 <author>Carr, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Mahumetane or Turkish historie : containing three bookes: 1 Of the originall and beginning of the Turkes, and of the foure empires which are issued and proceded out of the superstitious sect of Mahumet. 2 Of their conquests and the succession of the house of Ottoman, vntill the present reigning of Mahumet the third. 3 Of the warres and seege of Malta, which Solyman the great made to the great maister and brothers of that order. Heerevnto haue I annexed a briefe discourse of the warres of Cypres, at what time Selimus the second, tooke from the Venetians the possession of that iland, and by reason thereof I haue adioyned a small discourse conteining the causes of the greatnesse of the Turkish Empire. Translated from the French &amp; Italian tongues, by R. Carr, of the middle Temple in London, Gentleman. Dedicated to the three worthy brothers Robert Carr, William Carr and Edward Carr, in the county of Lincolne, Esquiers</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 122 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <head>To the VVorshipfull his very good Cosen William Carr of Stafford in the county <hi>of Lincolne Esquire, and one in hir Maiesties</hi> Commission of peace there.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR, to you who are the second possessor of my heere expressed rich will, though weake power: I commend this second booke of my French and Italian traduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, concerning the succession of the great house of Ottoman, and those their fortunate armes whether in offence, or defence taken; The rather for that your selfe beeing resident in court where this argument (by reason of the present Hungarian wars and the often assemblies of the Germaine Princes to prouide some remedy for their feared harmes) is much spoken of▪ you may with others see the manner and growing of this continuing and admired felicitie, (heere by me deciphered) though the meanes how, by very few is seene, saue such onely as are true spectators and obseruers of high reaching pollicie; what my paines hath effected in this point, I freely giue as you may boldly chalenge it for your due; who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire nothing more then euer to be found the generall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler seruant of your selfe and your most worthy brothers true iointenants by vndeuided moieties (as our lawiers terme it) of mee and what I may, whereof the suruiuor whilst I sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue may dispose of the whole: And so with all duety done which may be demanded of a most affectionate kinsman and seruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble friend: I take my leaue, from the middle Temple in London this</hi> 20▪ <hi>of March</hi> 1600.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships of all others most at command
R. Carr.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>