<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE COLENE, EARLE OF SEAFORT, Lord Mackenzee and Kintaill, one of his MAIESTIES most Honorable Privie Councell in the Kingdome of Scotland.</title>
           <author>Weemes, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112662_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73378</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25207.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE COLENE, EARLE OF SEAFORT, Lord Mackenzee and Kintaill, one of his MAIESTIES most Honorable Privie Councell in the Kingdome of Scotland.</title>
                 <author>Weemes, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the lawes of Moses : Viz. Morall. Ceremoniall. Iudiciall. The second volume. Containing an explanation of diverse questions and positions for the right understanding thereof. Wherein also are opened divers ancient rites &amp; customes of the Iewes, and also o the Gentiles, as they haue relation to the Iewish. Together with an explication of sundry difficult texts of Scripture, which depend upon, or belong unto every one of the Commandements, as also upon the ceremoniall and iudiciall lawes. Which texts are set downe in the tables before each particular booke. All which are cleered out of the originall languages, the Hebrew and Greeke, and out of the distinctions of the schoolemen and cases of the casuists. By Iohn Weemse, of Lathocker in Scotland, preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Weemes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 261, 33, 221, 3 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="152"/>
   <pb facs="152"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE COLENE, EARLE OF <hi>SEAFORT,</hi> Lord <hi>Mackenzee</hi> and <hi>Kintaill,</hi> one of his MAIESTIES most Honorable Privie Councell in the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honorable and my very good Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD who is the God of order and not of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, from whom all good things descend, hath placed here below sundry sorts of people;<note place="margin">Prov. 30.25.26.27.28</note> the <hi>Ants</hi> are a people not strong, yet they prepare their meat in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer;
<pb facs="153"/> the <hi>Conies</hi> are but a feeble folke, yet make they their houses in the Rocks; the <hi>Locusts</hi> haue no King, yet goe they forth all of them by bands; the <hi>Spider</hi> taketh hold with her hands, and is in Kings palaces; this sort of people dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer very much, for some of them are <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, which provide onely for the present day, but lay up nothing against the morrow; the <hi>Gras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper</hi> provideth not against the winter as the <hi>Ant</hi> doth; there are others of them who liue by rapine, as the <hi>Caterpillers</hi> who devour all and then flie away;<note place="margin">Nahum 3.16.</note> and <hi>Nahum</hi> compareth the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>Ninive</hi> to these, that carry all the wealth away with them; and there are some of those people which are insatiable, as the <hi>Horsleach,</hi> that hath two daughters who cry continually,<note place="margin">Prov. 30.15.</note>
      <hi>Giue, giue;</hi> This sort of people are governed by instinct onely; the <hi>Locusts</hi> haue no King, yet they goe out in bands; the <hi>Ant</hi> hath no guide,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.7.</note> overseer, or ruler, yet <hi>shee provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her meat in the Summer, and gathereth her foode in the harvest,</hi> although they haue no King or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to command them, and oversee them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a guide to direct them, yet they are ruled by instinct.</p>
   <p>There are a second sort of people that God hath placed here below, and they are men; and there is a greater difference amongst this
<pb facs="153"/> people, than amongst the former, for looke upon some of them, and yee shall hardly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne whether they be men or not, and as the <hi>Philosophers</hi> say, there are some sorts of creatures that we cannot tell whether they liue the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitiue or the vegetatiue life onely, there is so little life in them, as in the Shel-fish; so it is hard to discerne whether those liue the reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable life, or the brutish onely, they haue no lawes, they lodge in the caues of the earth, goe naked, eat raw flesh, and although they haue the shape of men, yet they haue but the heart of beasts in them, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had. There are other men who are ruled by reason, and politicke government, for their God hath taught them, he may be called <hi>their God</hi> in this respect,<note place="margin">Esay 28.26.</note> as the Prophet <hi>Esay</hi> calleth him the <hi>husband-mans God,</hi> because he teacheth him how to manure the ground, and so God commeth neerer to them; they are a people here, but yet they are not Gods people, and it is better to be a dorekeeper in the house of God,<note place="margin">Psal. 84.10.</note> than in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est advancement amongst such.</p>
   <p>There is a third sort who liue in his Church, and this is the highest societie in this life, and here we shall see policie, justice, frugalitie, and all vertues, because Gods worship is here, and as the inferior faculties of the soule are
<pb facs="154"/>
      <hi>eminenter</hi> by way of excellencie contained in the superior, so are all those comprehended in Religion; and as the shadow followeth the bodie, so doth policie and order follow Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; if a man would learne frugalitie, let him looke to <hi>Ioseph,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 104.22.</note> who taught the Senatours of <hi>Egypt;</hi> if he would learne policie, let him looke to the government of <hi>Salomons</hi> Court and his house;<note place="margin">2 King. 4.</note> if he would learne to be a good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, let him see what order the Lord hath placed in the Campe of the <hi>Iewes;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Numb. 80.10.</note> and if he would learne justice, he shall see it exactly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in the Law of God.</p>
   <p>My Honourable Lord, I haue made choise of your L<seg rend="sup">P</seg>: to recōmend this Treatise to your Patrocinie, because yee know what it is to be amongst Gods people; many great men if they get their portion in this life amongst the people of this world,<note place="margin">Psal. 17.</note> they care not to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisons in the societie of Gods people, and they content themselues with the portion of this world, and say, <hi>Benum est hic esse;</hi> but this is a freedome which is bought at a higher rate, it cost the chiefe Captaine a great summe of money to be made a freeman in <hi>Rome;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 22 28.</note> but to be made a freeman in the Church of GOD, it cost the price of Christs bloud. Great men desire to be out of this first societie, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
<pb facs="154"/> not to liue like beasts; but if they come to the second societie, to liue like civill men, that doth content them; they giue GOD thankes (perhaps) for this, that they are men and not beasts, and that they haue beene bred civilly, but few giue God thankes for this, that they liue under the Gospell, where they may learne Christ, <hi>not many Noble are called.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.</note> Sometimes they may tremble and feare,<note place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> as <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> did,<note place="margin">Act 26.28.</note> and put off their conversion to another time, and some of them are like <hi>Agrippa,</hi> who almost are perswaded to be Christians; but few like <hi>Sergius Paulus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 13.7.</note> who was converted at <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching.</p>
   <p>My Lord, you haue had still the practise of Religion in your house, and one of the best helpes to further you, your worthy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Lady, whose name smelleth now like the wine of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> when shee is gone,<note place="margin">Hosea 14.7.</note> and now she enjoyeth the fruit of that, when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her Nobilitie, birth, or worldly honour profited nothing; and this I write unto your L<seg rend="sup">P</seg>: beseeching you to goe on in that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian course, that both by your place and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, you may draw others unto the truth. The Lord promised that he would giue the <hi>uttermost parts of the earth for a possession to his Sonne;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 2.8.</note> this is the Motto of this Iland, and the farther
<pb facs="155"/> North, it is the nearer to the ends of the earth, studie therefore my good Lord, that Iesus Christ may haue his possession enlarged in the North, and this shall be your crowne in the latter day, when all your possessions shall faile you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours in all dutifull submission,</hi> IOHN VVEEMSE:</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>