<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112574_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12968</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The confutation of the Abbote of Crosraguels masse : set furth by Maister George Hay</title>
                 <author>Hay, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lekpreuik, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 49, 51-54, 56-96, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the approued, laudable, and receaued vse of writers, that do trauell in any argument of consequence, I haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it verie necessarie, to admonishe thee good reader, of the fyle, ordor, and maner that I haue followed and obserued,<note place="margin">For thre reasones it may seme strā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, why this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor suld vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this charge.</note> in this my answer and confutation of the Abbote of Crosraguels masse. For it may appeare strange at the first face, that for a smal tractie and volome, not exceading the boundes of threttie small leaues, direct forth and sent by him, he shal receaue hard by fourtie sheites of paper, in greatest and fullest measure.</p>
   <p>Secondly, it may be asked pereuenture, that in suche aboundance of flourishing ingiues, in suche welth of solide iudgementes, in suche plentie of eloquent men and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of letters, tongues and erudition, as I may treuly affirme, ether wes neuer at least these thousand yeares wes not, that this charge should be laide to me, or by me vndertaken. For in that one, may appeare temeritie and rashnes, in that other arrogancie and lack of iudgement. Somthing thridly may be inquired of our long silence in consideration, that this our Abbote hath continually bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked from the beginning of this mercyful visitation of our God, and reformation in Scotland, yea, and set forthe some thinges that be plainely red,<note place="margin">Ane an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the firste reasone, wherein is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red why this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor may seme pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lixt, and the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot breif &amp; short.</note> and euerie where to be found, that the rest of his workes which be no les perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous be neglected, and this onely hath bene iudged wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of answer.</p>
   <p>To satisfie thee good Reader, in the first head, thou shal vnderstand my studie and trauel to haue bene, to make all thinges plaine and sensible, aswel of Scripture, as of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie: for in this, no dout, lyeth the cause of his short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and of my prolixetie, not that I haue bene any wayes long in this argument, which vndoutedly requireth an ample tractation: but in respect I speak of his compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes and obscuritie.</p>
   <p>In the maters of Scripture it can not be denyed, but he hath bene (as I note) in some places, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther sleuthfull, negligent, and obliuius, or els so addicted to his owne iudgement (wherein he confidis not lytle) that whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="6"/>
he hath iudged of any place, the same should the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der immediatlie approue, and without any stay or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, esteme it for a verie vndouted treuth, To prike forward to this, the imprudent and vnskilfull Reader. We obserue his craft to be, to alledge and cote in the margen the authorities of Scriptures, Fathers and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, as should appeare to the Lector, that all, that is alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by him, is spoken out of the mouth of suche Authors as he there notes. In this part I am driuen to produce euerie place,<note place="margin">Why the authour must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.</note> oppen vp the mynde, sense and vnderstandīg of it, and satisfie to euerie thing can be obiected, because the danger is so great that if I should pas by any thing with silence, that incōtinentlie should be iudged to make for his partie.</p>
   <p>In the Fathers and councils I foresaw somwhat more, that they hauing almoste continually in mouth, solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Masses, Sacrifices, Hostes, Oblations, worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinges, Myrackles, and suchlyke, I feared that these thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges should be interpreted, and vnderstand after the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious vse that we haue sene, rather then according to the mynde of the Author, and the practise and custome of that tyme. Here am I constrained by conferrence of places, to shaw the mynde of the writer, and by the consuetude then vsed, to declare the naturall intelligence of euerie thing, which part as it hath bene to me painefull and tedious, so I dout not, but it shall not onely be to the vnlearned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, where they are assured of the antiquitie, but also to the learned, they being releaued of the werisome wadīg through the Doctors, and to bothe shall this my lauboure serue for a Mirror to behold the great puritie, the godly lyfe, the care ouer the poore, and the liberalitie of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, and the old Fathers which being confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the exemples of those that vanteth and brageth of the tytles of successors, may be knowen, how far they be not onely fallen from the puritie of the doctrine, but lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise horrible declined and degenered in all good vertuus and maners. This shortly for answer to the first head.</p>
   <p>In the Second head I shal not be verie long,<note place="margin">Ane an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the secōd head.</note> the ordor of reformed persones we know, to be subiect to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Church, without all shift, tergiuersatiō, or repugnancie. What is the iudgement, and opinion of men of letters of me, I haue not to inquire: the occasions,
<pb n="2" facs="6"/>
mouing the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to laye this charge to me (moste vnable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges many hundreth) ar vnknawen. But alwayes God be preased, my duetie I know, which is all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare respectes and considerations layed asyde, to giue and dedicat my self holye to the seruice &amp; proffect of the Churh of God, Iudgeing it rather my part and office in obeying there honest charge, to euenture my fame and estimation then in disobeying and schif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing, to be estemed contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and fearfull.</p>
   <p>The argument I knowe to be vnplausible &amp; odious till a great noumbre, and they not of the lawest sorte. But vnder protestation, I speake of the particulare offence of any: that simplie I prosecute my mater and declares my iudgemēt frelie, wherin I dout not but euery man wil tak in good part, that I gentlie and with a liberale hert doth offre euer submitting my self to iudgement &amp; correction.</p>
   <p>In deid the raling and babling forthe, without all modestie vpon the ministers of God, hes moued me to be somewhat scharper then my nature beares or yet the Law of amitie requires, with the Abbote. But in that let euery man be assured, that nether haue I bene so hoite as he moste iustlie haeth deserued nether yet do I meane any thing but of the qualitie of his mynde, without any further respect. Which vnfeynedlie I protest euery where, doeth displease me with all the learned and Godlie.</p>
   <p>As to the speaking somtymes in the singulare som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes in the plurale nombre that my lorde knowes well yneugh, to be the maner of speaking in all tounges and of all writters in suche cace.</p>
   <p>In the thrid poynt, ī verie deid I may say that before this boke wes deliuered to me,<note place="margin">Answer to the 3. head.</note> I neuer had sene none of his workes, yea, and I beleue that the most part of his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings be ether vnsene to the rest of my brethren, or at least, they that they haue sene, they haue iudged vnworthy of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny āswer. The causes of their silence may be easelie gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of Lipriane, against Demetrian{us}, whome he along tyme barking and continually inueying against God, did contemne, iudgeing it better to winke at his ignorāce, thē by answer to stirre ād prouoke him to a greater phrenesie. We know wel yneugh the nature of such men, that rather by answer they be kindled &amp; inflamed to burste forth, thē to receaue any instruction, or be moued to conteane them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="7"/>
within the boundes of modestie and shame fastnes.</p>
   <p>Cypriane adduceth sindry places out of the Scriptures, as.<note place="margin">Prou. 23.9.</note> Thou shal say nothing in the eares of the vnwise, least when he shal here, he mock at thy witty speaking: and in an other place. Thou shal not answer to the foolish, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his foly,<note place="margin">Prou. 26.4.</note> that thou be not lyke vnto him. We be warned by our Master, not to cast holy thinges before Swyne.<note place="margin">Math. 7.6.</note> Many other causes may be adduced of their si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which should moue any man to beare with these mē for a certane tyme, in esperence of some amendimēt. But where the euil is incurable and danger appearing to the simple,<note place="margin">Why cheiflie the Abbo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes boke is answe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red.</note> then the brydle is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o be loused to the tongue, and the pen sharped to the battell, not for the satisfaction of suche mē that giuen to cōtention, be indured ād wrapped vp in all blindnes and obstinacie, but in consideration of the good and vnlearned Rearder, who may here be sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and caried out of the way by a blinde guide.</p>
   <p>I haue trauelled here to comprehend his whole boke in this my answer, I haue broght forth his argumētes, word by word, wherein if any faut shalbe found, let it not be imputed to me, but ether to the author him self, or els to his scribe. To the argumentes I haue answered formally in my iudgement, his wordes be noted in the margine, with this marck "so that the Reader may easylie discerne betuix his text and my answer. Somethings in the latter part of his boke as nothing apertenīg to the mater, by his own cōfessiō, I haue only touched, &amp; not fully recited. The mater is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fortable, seing as it were two aduersaries, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hād to hand in a feild, &amp; contending for the victorie.</p>
   <p>These were the principall thinges I had to forwarne thee good Reader, praying thee, to tak in good part, this my trauel. Thus I commit thee to be guyded by the Spirite of the Lorde Iesus, in expectation of better, when God shal giue it vnto me, and when the occasion and opportunitie shal serue. At Edinburgh, the 15. of Iulie. 1562.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>