<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the right Ho∣nourable,
Syr William Cicill, of the
Noble order of the Garter, Knight,
Barron of Burgley, Lord high Treasurer of
England, and one of her Maiestyes most
honourable prie Counsell, health,
honour and prosperitie.</title>
           <author>Golding, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112496_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07401</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17785</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112496</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the right Ho∣nourable,
Syr William Cicill, of the
Noble order of the Garter, Knight,
Barron of Burgley, Lord high Treasurer of
England, and one of her Maiestyes most
honourable prie Counsell, health,
honour and prosperitie.</title>
                 <author>Golding, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorke of Pomponius Mela. the cosmographer, concerninge the situation of the world : wherin euery parte, is deuided by it selfe in most perfect manner, as appeareth in the table at the ende of the booke. A booke right plesant and profitable for all sortes of men: but speciallie for gentlemen, marchants, mariners, and trauellers, translated out of Latine by Arthur Golding Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Mela, Pomponius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 93, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧To the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,
Syr William Cicill, of the
Noble order of the Garter, Knight,
Barron of Burgley, Lord high Treasurer of
England, and one of her Maiestyes most
honourable pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e Counsell, health,
honour and prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntending long since
(my very good Lord) for the
benefit and delight of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen,
to haue set foorth a
description of the whole world
in our owne Language, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the consent of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
and late VVriters, I
thought this mine Author <hi>Pomponius Mela,</hi> for hys
breefenesse, order, and perspicuitie, to bee a very fitte
ground to begin with, for those three partes which were
knowen in former ages: purposing, therewithall to haue
added some breefe collection of the late wryters, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the description of the other partes, which beeing ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
vtterly vnknowen, or very lyghtly and darckly glaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced
at by the men of auncient tyme, haue since beene
better discouered and brought to light, by the continuall
Nauigationes of the trauellers of these our latter yeeres.
And as my meaning and hope was then, to haue made
this first enterpryse of myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e as a frame of a buyldinge, to
haue beene set vp and finy shed by mee more exactly, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="3"/>
at further leysure, accordinge to the small ability of
my poore skyll; or as a roughe hewen Image, to haue beene
perfected and polyshed by the industry of some other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of greater readyng, better skyll, and longer experience,
and finally to haue beene beautifyed and furnished wyth
more particular and large discourses, bothe of the places
and of the notablest thinges whych eyther the places
themselues doo naturally yeelde, or haue beene doon or
made in them by the famousest personages, whome the
wrytinges of our auncestors haue made renowmed vnto
vs: So least this worke of myne (which hath slept now many
yeeres) might passe away as it were in a Lethargy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
I of the performaunce, and my Conntry of the enioying
of any fruite of my duety in this behalfe, myght be vtterly
bereft, and so consequently my sayd purpose and the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
taken to the setting forward thereof, should bee of
none effect at all: I haue caused the Printer to put to hys
helping hand to the preuenting of that perrill, whych
thinge wyl easely be doon, if it may please your good Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe
(according to your accustomed good wyll towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
such as any way indeuour, eyther to further others or
to profit themselues, in the knowledge of lyberall Artes)
to permitte thys my trauell to shroude it selfe vnder
the shadowe of your protectyon, that beeing by your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
after a sort quickned and cheered vp againe, it may
if not growe in tyme to full rypenesse, yet at least<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse
yeeld the pleasure of the infancy, the delight wherof,
may chaunce to bee such as shall prouoke some person, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to traine it vp to full grouth, or to vndertake the doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of some better worke of the same kynde. And for the
more inlarging hereof with substaūce and variety of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="3"/>
both delectable and profitable, as farre as tyme would
permytte: I haue delyuered vnto the Printer hereof the
Polyhistor of <hi>Iulius Solinus,</hi> and certayne trauelles of
one <hi>Andrew Theuet,</hi> lykewyse translated long a goe to
bee added as appendauntes to thys worke of <hi>Pomponius
Mela,</hi> that as they treate though diue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sly, yet cheefely of
one ground, so they may ioyne in one volume to remayne
together to the behofe of posterity, vnder the security of
your Lordshyps fauour, vnto the whych I most humbly
commend my selfe, and these my simple dooinges,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>wrytten <date>thys sixt of <hi>February.</hi> 1584.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your good Lordships, most humble alwayes to commaund. <hi>Arthur Goldinge.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>