<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVELY NOBLE, and his Worthie Kinseman in all re∣spects, Sir RALPH DVTTON</title>
           <author>Marmion, Shackerley</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112201_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07024</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17442</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112201</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVELY NOBLE, and his Worthie Kinseman in all re∣spects, Sir RALPH DVTTON</title>
                 <author>Marmion, Shackerley</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fine companion : Acted before the King and Queene at White-hall, and sundrie times with great applause at the private house in Salisbury Court, by the Prince his Servants. Written by Shakerley Marmyon</title>
                 <author>Marmion, Shackerley</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meighen, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVELY NOBLE, and his Worthie Kinseman in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, Sir RALPH DVTTON</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee haue great cause to triumph over the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the times, that in all ages there wants not a succession of some candid Dispositions, who (in spight of malice &amp; ignorance) dare countenance Poetry, and the Professors. How such an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and divine part of Humanitie should fall vnder the least contempt, or arme the petulancy of Writers to declaime against her, I know not: but I guesse the reason, that having their soules darkned, and rejoycing in their errors, are offended at the lustre of those Arts that would enlighten them. But the Fates haue not so ill befriended our studies, as to expose them to contempt, without the protection of such, whose abilitie of judgement can both wipe off all aspersions, and dignifie desert. Amongst the worthy Patrons of Learning, that can best vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate her worth, you are not the least; And because custome and respect to noble friends, giues a priviledge to dedicate our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours where they may find admittance, I haue made bold to present this piece vnto you. It hath often pleas'd, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermission. If you shall second that applause by your kind favour, it shall not aspire to be more honour'd.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By him that is yours in all observance, SHACK; MARMYON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>