<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THESES MARTINIANAE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112312_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07040</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17457</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112312</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THESES MARTINIANAE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Theses Martinianae : that is, certaine demonstratiue conclusions, sette downe and collected (as it should seeme) by that famous and renowmed clarke, the reuerend Martin Marprelate the great: seruing as a manifest and sufficient confutation of al that euer the Colledge of Catercaps with their whole band of clergie-priests, haue, or canbring [sic] for the defence of their ambitious and antichristian prelacie. Published and set foorth as an after-birth of the noble gentleman himselfe, by a prety stripling of his, Martin Iunior, and dedicated by him to his good neame and nuncka, Maister Iohn Kankerbury: hovv the yongman [sic] came by them, the reader shall vnderstande sufficiently in the epilogue. In the meane time, vvhosoeuer can bring mee acquainted vvith my father, Ile bee bounde hee shall not loose his labour</title>
                 <author>Marprelate, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Hodgkins (Hoskins), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marprelate, Martin, junior, Assignees of, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THESES MARTINIANAE.</head>
   <p>I See my doings and my course misliked of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both the good and the bad, though also I haue fauourers of both sortes. The Bishops, and their traine, though they stumble at the cause, yet especially, mislike my maner of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Those whom foolishly men call Puritanes, like of the matter I haue handled, but the forme they cannot brooke. So that herein I haue them both for mine aduersaries. But nowe what if I should take the course <gap reason="blank" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
      </gap> in certeine Theses or conclusions, without inueighing against either person or cause? might I not then hope my doings woulde be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether approoued of the one, and not so greatly scorned at by the other? Surely, otherwise they should doe me great iniurie, and shewe, that they are those who delight neither in heate nor colde, and so make me as weary in seeking howe to fitte them as the Bishops are in labouring how to find me. The Bishops I feare are past my cure, and it may be I was vnwise, in taking that charge vpon me: if that which I haue already done can do them any good, or any wise further the cause which I loue, I shall be glad, if not, what hope is there of amending them this way? The best is I know how to mend my selfe. For good leaue haue I to giue ouer my desparate cure, and with this my farewell vnto them, I wish them a better Surgeon. Yet ere I leaue them, I do heere offer vnto the view of the world, some part of their monstrous corruptions; in defence whereof, for their liues dare not they in any learned meeting or assembly dispute with with me, or attempt to ouerthrowe mine asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by modest writings handled any thing scholer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<pb facs="3"/>that is, by good and sounde syllogismes, which haue both their Maior and Minor, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the worde. I woulde once see them enter into either of these courses, for as yet they haue beene farre from both. Fire, and fagot, bands, and blowes, railing, and reuiling, are, and haue bene hitherto their common weapons, as for slandering &amp; lying, it is the greatest piece of their holy profession. And these with their bare asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ōs, &amp; their wretched cleuing to popish absurdities, are in a maner the onely proofes and tried max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes they offer vnto the Church in this age. And so if a man woulde be confuted, I must needes say, my Lord of Winchester hath long agoe sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and dexterely performed it. <hi>I am not of opinion,</hi> (saith he) that, <hi>vna semper debet esse oeconomia Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae,</hi> That the gouernement of the Church shoulde alwayes, and in all places, bee one and the same, especially by a company of Elders. Lo sir, what say you to this? here is inough, I trowe, for any mans satisfaction, that bishop Couper <hi>is not of opinion.</hi> Yea but our Sauior Christ his Apostles &amp; holy Martirs are of opinion, that the gouernment of the church should alwayes, and in all places, be one, especially by a company of Elders. As for my Lord of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesters
<hi>opinion,</hi> wee haue little or nothing to doe with that: nor no great matter which side it leane to, whether with or against the trueth. For if his bishopricke and vnruly iurisdiction were no more noysome and hurtfull to the Church of God, then his learning and opinion is hurtfull to the cause of Discipline, he might sitte long enough vndistem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in his chaire for vs: the good olde manne might cough his fill, and be quiet, hauing his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<pb facs="3"/>promise and booke-oth (as we haue also Iohn a Bridges and Bancrofts) that by arguments hee will neuer hurt vs. For they must thinke, that it is not such drie blowes as this, <hi>I am not of opinion, &amp;c.</hi> that will satisfie the learned, and answeare the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrations that are brought on the contrarie side. If then they haue indeede any purpose at all, to quiet the contentions of our Church, let them bring vnto vs, not these bables of their owne, <hi>VVe are not of opinion, &amp;c.</hi> but some sound warrant from the word, that Christ and his Apostles <hi>vvere not of opinion</hi> with vs in the pointes wherein wee truelie charge them to haue erred, otherwise their 812. their 1401.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>