<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A breefe description of the Iland of Cyprus: by the which not onely the Venetians title why they haue so long enioyed it, but also the Turkes, whereby now he claimeth it, may plainly appeare.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112366_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07119</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17520</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A breefe description of the Iland of Cyprus: by the which not onely the Venetians title why they haue so long enioyed it, but also the Turkes, whereby now he claimeth it, may plainly appeare.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true report of all the successe of Famagosta, of the antique writers called Tamassus, a citie in Cyprus : In the which the whole order of all the skirmishes, batteries, mines, and assaultes geuen to the sayd fortresse, may plainly appeare. Moreouer the names of the captaines, and number of the people slaine, as well of the Christians as of the Turkes: likewise of them who were taken prisoners: from the beginning of the sayd seege vntill the end of the same. Englished out of Italian by William Malim. With certaine notes of his and expositions of all the Turkishe wordes herein necessary to be knowen, placed in the margent, with a short description also of his of the same iland</title>
                 <author>Martinengo, Nestore, conte</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 16, 1 leave, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="description_of_Cyprus">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ A breefe description of the Iland of Cyprus: by the which not onely the Venetians title why they haue so long enioyed it, but also the Turkes, whereby now he claimeth it, may plainly appeare.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Iland of Cyprus is inuironed with diuers seas. For Westward it is washed with the sea called Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philium: Southward, with the Sea Ægyptium: on the East part, with the Sea Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium: and Northward, with the Sea called Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licium. The which Iland in time past had diuers names: called once Acamantis, as Sabellicus witnesseth: Philonides maketh mention, that it was called sometime Cerasis, Xenagoras wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that it was named Aspelia, Amathusa, and Macaria. There were in time paste 15. Cities or famous Townes in it, but now very fewe, amongst the which Famagosta is the chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, and strongest, situated by the Sea side. There is also Nicosia, which was wont, by the trafficke of Marchauntes, to be very wealthy: besides the Citie of Baffo, Arnica, Saline, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misso, Milopotomo, and Episcopia. Timosthenes affirmeth, that this Iland in cōpasse is 400. and 29. miles, and Arthemidorus writeth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> length of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same to be 162. miles, measuring of it frō the
<pb facs="6"/>
East to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> West betwixt two promontories named Dimareta &amp; Acamanta. This Iland is thought to be very riche, abundant of Wine, Oyle, Grain, Pitch, Rosin, Allum, Salt, &amp; of diuers precious stones pleasant, profitable, &amp; necessary for mans vse, &amp; much frequēted of Marchantes of Syria, vnto the which it lieth very neare. It hath bene as Plinie writeth, ioyned sometime with Syria, as Sicilia hath bene also with Italy. It was a long time subiecte vnto the Romaines, after, to the Persians, and to the Souldan of Ægypt. And last of all the Ʋenetians haue enioyed it of late a long time, in this order following. In the yeare of our Lord. 1470. Iohn King of the sayd Ilād sonne to Ianus of Lusignian had by Hellen his wife, which was of the Emperiall house of Paleologus one daughter onely called Charlotta, &amp; a bastard called Iames: the which Iames was afterward consecrated Bishop of Nicosia. This Charlotta was maried first to the King of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall, of whom he had no issue, so that he being dead, Lewes Duke of Sauoy (to whom she was the second time maried) sonne to Lewes the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of that name (vnto whom the sayd Iland by the right of this his wife Charlotta did apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) had the possession of the same. Iames the bastard as soone as his father was dead, of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop
<pb facs="7"/>
became a Soldier, and with an army wanne the Jland, making it his owne by force. This Duke of Sauoy hearing these newes, with a nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of well appointed soldiers, arriued shortly after in Cyprus, &amp; recouering againe the Iland, compelled y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Bastard to flye forthwith ouer to the Souldan of Ægypt. Who making him selfe his subiecte, in time so wrought and tempered the matter, that the Souldan in person at his request passed ouer into Cyprus, beseeged Duke Lewes in the Castell of Nicosia, &amp; at length compelled him to depart, leauing his kingdome. So that this Bishop became againe King of this Iland: who shortly after cleauing to the Ʋenetians ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made a league of frendship with them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by their consent one Catherina the daughter of Marco Cornaro, which Catherine the Senate of Venice adopted vnto them soone after as their daughter. This Bishop not long after sickned, &amp; died, leauing this his wife with child, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not long after his fathers death. By y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which meanes the Ʋenetians making them selues the next heires to Catherina by the lawe of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tooke vnto them the possession of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and haue kept, and enioyed the same al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most this 100. yeares. Now this great Turke called Sultan Selim in the right of the Souldan
<pb facs="7"/>
of Ægypt, whom his grandfather (called also Sultan Selim) conquered, pretendeth a right ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vnto it, and now as you may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand by reading of this short treatise hath by conquest obtained the same. Whom, I pray the euerliuing God, if it be his holy will, shortly to roote out from thence.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>