<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Henrie Bullinger, Mini∣er of the Church of Zurich, to the gentle Reader, wisheth grace and peace from the Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112817_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17191</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112817</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Henrie Bullinger, Mini∣er of the Church of Zurich, to the gentle Reader, wisheth grace and peace from the Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most godly and learned discourse of the woorthynesse, authoritie, and sufficiencie of the holy scripture : also of the cleerenesse, and plainnesse of the same, and of the true vse thereof. Wherin is discussed this famous question: whether the canonical scriptures haue authoritie from the church, or rather the church receiue authoritie from the Scriptures. By occasion wherof are touched the dignities and duties of the church, touching traditions, with aunswere to all obiections. Translated out of Latine into English, by Iohn Tomkys: and dedicated to the right honorable Sir Richarde Pipe, knight, lorde maior of the citie of London</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 119 leaves, 1 leaf of plates, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Henrie Bullinger, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>er</hi> of the Church of Zurich, to the gentle Reader, wisheth grace and peace from the Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Booke was brought me, gentle Reader, from a farre distant &amp; famous Citie, certaine weekes past, without the senders and authours name. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s his onely request, that if this Booke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ight be thought worthie to be set foorth, might bee deliuered to the diligent man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. Christopher Froschouerus to be printed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him. The title of the booke was this: <hi>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>scourse, whether the holie Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aue authoritie from the Church: or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ther the Church receiue authoritie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>om the holie Scripture?</hi> collected by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uer of godlinesse, for the instruction of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nlearned and simple. Being much delited <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith this holy, profitable, and necessarie ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
<pb facs="7"/> I began foorthwith to read the Booke with great affection, and easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that the authour being indued with singular humanitie and modestie, did (of purpose conceale his name, not regarding to make it knowen. For hee woulde not seeke to gette any praise of the worlde, which manie foolishly doe by setting foorth Bookes: but was rather willing to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, extolle and sette foorth the glorie of GOD onely, and of his woorde. I sawe also in the man a feruent desire to bringe the syncerenesse of pure Religion to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to further the manifest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the louers of godlinesse. To bee briefe, I acknowledged the giftes of God to appeare in this man, I meane his dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie and happinesse in handeling this famous argument, hauing beene long in controuersie among the learned, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly expounded. For whatsoeuer may be spoken thereof necessarily and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, hee hath wholy conteined it in this booke, yea and that briefely, euidently, plainly, and in verie good order. For hee hath distinguished the whole matter, being otherwise copious, into Chapters: then hath
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee placed before euery Chapter the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, so that euen by these briefe Chapters thou mayest easily perceiue the scope and ende of the whole Booke, the summe, and maner of the handeling of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ame. Wherevpon I haue prefixed before this woorke, the Title of the Booke, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed of the matter handeled therein, that thou mayest euen with one viewe, and foorthwith in the beginning, beholde all thinges in a verie briefe summe, whiche are conteined in this Booke. He setteth foorth plainely, and confirmeth all his matters, especially, as it is meete, by the holie Scriptures, then also by fitte testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the blessed auncient Fathers. Neither hath this his profitable trauaile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iked mee onelie, but also certaine other godlye and learned men, vnto whome thou mayest worthilie ascribe more than vnto mee. I haue therefore placed this mine Epistle before this Booke, least the woorke beeing sette foorth without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Authours name, shoulde eyther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee little regarded or suspected of thee. Neither shall this Booke bee namelesse,
<pb facs="8"/> if it meete with anie stoute aduersarie, which can assaile it and oppugne it. Those thinges which I haue hitherto spoken in praise of this booke, thou shalt by experiēce, and with admiration witnesse to be true, so that thou reade it diligently, and with a sincere minde, and also weigh it duely. Farewell gentle Reader. From Zurich, the moneth of August. 1571.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>