<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112749_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07603</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17995</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mohammedis imposturæ: that is, A discouery of the manifold forgeries, falshoods, and horrible impieties of the blasphemous seducer Mohammed : with a demonstration of the insufficiencie of his law, contained in the cursed Alkoran; deliuered in a conference had betweene two Mohametans, in their returne from Mecha. Written long since in Arabicke, and now done into English by William Bedwell. Whereunto is annexed the Arabian trudgman, interpreting certaine Arabicke termes vsed by historians: together with an index of the chapters of the Alkoran, for the vnderstanding o the confutations of that booke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Linguistics and philology</term>
                    <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>THat which here I offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy view, courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is, as the title doth shew, the translation of a booke imprinted certaine yeares since, and published in the Arabicke tongue: Yet when, or where, or by whom, is not, as vsually the manner is, in the same any where expressed or declared. It was first written, as the Author himselfe seemeth to intimate, about 600 years since. Who he was, and what, I dare not for certaine affirme; Many of the obiections, demands, answers, arguments, and speeches are too good to be thought to come from the breast of an Heathen, Turke, or Saracen: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though of them many scarce good enough to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered vpon a well grounded Christian. That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration first mooued me to iudge it framed by some Christian, in disgrace and confutation of
<pb facs="3"/>
that fond and foolish religion. Yet when I called to mind, that I had heard many Merchants, and especially M. W. G. a worshipfull Gentleman, who did spend the better part of his youth continually resident amongst them, That it was a common thing to heare from themselues such like obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and doubts made against their law. Againe whē I considered, that whatsoeuer is here alledged and layd downe, though neuer so good and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianlike; Or contrariwise absurd and monstrous; is notwithstanding found and read in that their law: And lastly, seeing that my selfe can testifie that from their owne mouthes I haue heard; and can shew in their bookes and tractates the like morall sayings, and zealous exhortations vnto vertue, and holinesse of life; I then altered that mine opinion, and did verily beleeue it to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by some Saracen or Mohametane, who did in truth make these doubts and demands, as being desirous of better satisfaction. If any man shall obiect and say, as the consistorie of Rome did by the Talmud, That it were better that such foolish fables and blasphemies were concealed and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suppressed, then made publike and common to all: I answer, I haue done no more, nay not so
<pb facs="3"/>
much, as the ancient Fathers, <hi>Tertullian, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus, Epiphanius, Augustine,</hi> and others, who haue taken vpon them to confute the errors and opinions of Heretiks, haue done. <hi>Nullum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim est dogma, insigniter impium &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersum in Alcorano, quod non extet in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris eorum quos antea indicaui, Irenaei, Tertulliani, scriptorum Ecclesiasticae histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae, Epiphanij, Philastrij, Augustini; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum libri saepius foetant propè quàm cuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi: Et Typograghi quaestum inde non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iguum tolerant, &amp; rem studiosis bonae lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raturae inprimis gratam faciunt. Quaedam etiam absurdiora in veterum haeresium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptionibus reperiuntur, quà Alcoran protulerit, &amp;c.</hi> For in the Alkoran, saith a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diuine, there is no one opinion so impious &amp; wicked, which may not be found in the bookes of those writers which I haue before spoken of; to wit, <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian,</hi> the Ecclesiasticall hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians, <hi>Epiphanius, Philastrius,</hi> and <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi>; whose bookes do breed wellnere as oft as conies: And the printers do thereby reape no small gaines, and withall do deserue very well of all good students. Some things also, in the discoueries
<pb facs="4"/>
of old heresies, are met withall, more absurd and grosse, then the Alkoran doth afford any. But the examples following, being of the same nature, &amp; practised by graue iudicious Diuines, are more proper to our purpose. Peter, Abbot of Cluniak, a man highly commended in his time, for learning, religion, and Christian charitie, did well nere 500 yeares since, cause Robert of Reading our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman, to translate the Alkoran or lawes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamed into the Latine tongue; Which translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was by the said Peter dedicated vnto S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, that famous Abbot of Clareuall. At the end of which his translation you shall find this which followeth; <hi>Illustri glorioso{que} viro Petro Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacensi Abbate praecipiente, suus Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena, Robertus Retinensis, librum istum transtulit, anno Domini</hi> M.C.XLIII, <hi>anno Alexandri,</hi> M.CCCC.III, <hi>anno Alhigere</hi> D.XXXVII, <hi>anno Persarum quingentesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo vndecimo.</hi> About this time did Euthymius a learned Grecian translate, if not all, yet diuerse and sundrie peeces of the same. The Councell of Vienna, celebrated by Pope Clement the 5, in the yeare of our Lord 1311, hath an act enioyning certaine Vniuersities to maintaine Professours of
<pb facs="4"/>
the Arabicke tongue, for the translating of books out of that language into Latine. Now, as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man truly gathereth, those holy Fathers had no care of Physicke and Astronomie, but of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie onely: and therefore they meant of the Alko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran and such others concerning religion. Not long after this, Iohn Bishop of Segouia, offered vnto the Councell of Constance, the Alkoran by him translated and confuted. In the yeare of our Lord 1543, Theodorus Bibliander, (animated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto and commended by Philip Melanthon) did publish and imprint the aforesaid version of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinensis</hi> the English-man. Within foure or fiue years after this edition, Andreas Arriuabene tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Alkoran, as he saith, out of Arabicke into Italian: The title by himselfe praefixed to that his edition is thus; <hi>L'Alcorano di Macometto, nel qual si contiene la Dottrina, la Vita, i Costumi, &amp; le Legge sue, tradotto noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente dall'Arabo, in lingua Italiana; Con Gratie, e Priuilegij,</hi> M.D.XLV II. The Alko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran of Machomet, in which is contained his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Life, Customes &amp; Lawes, translated new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of Arabicke into the Italian tongue. When as in deed that translation of his is nothing but
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Retinensis</hi> Italionated; neither do I thinke that he vnderstood much Arabicke. Thus you see what presidents I haue, for that which is done: Such as I doubt not, but will fully satisfie the learned and indifferent: the peeuish and froward, I weigh not: this paines was not taken for them. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I know may please them that is not of their owne breeding. Neither do I see what benefite the vnlearned may reape by it. Now concerning the thing it selfe, I do giue the Reader to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, (the louers of these studies, and such as haue seene the booke can testifie that I speake the truth) That the copie that I haue followed, was so badly imprinted, that in verie many places I was constrained to diuine and guesse. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if in any place I haue failed, it is not much to be maruelled. Notwithstanding, although I will not say, that I haue failed in any particular: yet I dare boldly affirme, that I haue hit the generall scope and purpose of the Author, which for the thing it selfe might haue bene sufficient. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side this generalitie, for the benefite of students, which I especially aimed at, I haue so set it foorth that they might be bettered by it: And therefore I haue tied my selfe, as neare as the English
<pb facs="5"/>
phrase would suffer me, vnto the words of the Arabicke. Wherefore for their sakes, which are desirous to vnderstand that language, and for that purpose do please to vse this our labour, we haue, in the margent of this our booke, set downe the numbers answering to the pages of the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicke copie. Truth it is, that in that booke you shall find no such numbers expressed: but that want any man with his pen may easily supply. If I haue added any thing to helpe the English, that we haue caused to be imprinted in an Italica letter.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>