<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣rend
Father in GOD, the Lord
Arch-bishop of Canterburie his Grace,
Primate of all ENGLAND, and
Metropolitane.</title>
           <author>Mason, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112437_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07210</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17610</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112437</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣rend
Father in GOD, the Lord
Arch-bishop of Canterburie his Grace,
Primate of all ENGLAND, and
Metropolitane.</title>
                 <author>Mason, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nevv art of lying : couered by Iesuites vnder the vaile of equiuocation, discouered and disproued by Henry Mason</title>
                 <author>Mason, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 106, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
Father in GOD, the Lord
Arch-bishop of Canterburie his Grace,
Primate of all ENGLAND, and
Metropolitane.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Reuerend Father,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He first newes that I heard of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocating
Arte,</hi>
      <note place="margin">a Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>efa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> praefixâ Sex Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. cap. 1. &amp; cap. 1. de Mendac. num. 12, 13, 14.</note> was that which
I learned out of your Graces wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.
And well might this be to mee
the first newes. For, if I mistake
not, you were the first Writer, that published those
trickes in print to the World: though (as begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
vse to be) that discouery of this Art was but
briefe in comparison, either because that occasion
did not admit of any long or full discourse, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause,
but little of this mystery could then at the
first be discouered; the professors of that Trade, as
your selfe also signifie, labouring to hide their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets
from the knowledge of other men. And indeed
it may be obserued, that in managing of the Papacy,
they haue certaine <hi>mysteries</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> which the
<pb facs="3"/>
more they vse, the more they coceale. One of which,
is their power to murder Kings, and blow vp Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,
&amp; kill all that stand in their way, like the
<hi>Assassini,</hi> who held it a point of great merit to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
all that were their aduersaries in Religion: but
yet they are not willing that the world should know
that this is any part of their <hi>Creede.</hi> Another such
policy may be that of their <hi>Indices Expurgatorij,</hi>
by which they haue circucised the lips of such Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
as spoke any word against the Roman Church:
but this they kept as a great <hi>mystery</hi> among some
few of themselues, till misfortune brought it to
light, full sore against their wils. And for a third
such-like policy, I may reckon also this Art of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocation,
which the Masters thereof did keepe se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
as long, and as much as they could. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it was no maruell, if your first discouery of
this <hi>mystery</hi> were but briefe in comparison. But
afterward<note n="a" place="margin">D. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton B. of Lichfield and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentry, Confutat, of Equiuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> another Reuerend &amp; learned Prelate,
lighting vpon a more compleate Treatise then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
had appeared, penned by a Popish Priest in
defence of this Arte, and approued by the Arch-Priest,
and the Prouinciall of the Iesuits: he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued
the point more fully according as that Treatise
gaue him iust occasion. The crye of which pursuit
did vnkennell the olde equiuocating<note n="b" place="margin">Persons, who by occasion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopps booke wrote a large Treatise in defence of Equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on.</note> Foxe, and
<pb facs="3"/>
hunted him into the open field, there to display
himselfe, and to shew what trickes he could vse, for
sauing his new Art from the infamy of lying. And
here I finding him well chafed, did by the sent fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
after him vnto his Den, to espie if I might, what
he and his Cubs were deuising in the darke. And I
found them very busie in hammering <hi>Reseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
and <hi>mentall</hi> frauds, vpon euery occasion and
in all kindes of dealing, thereby to catch vs at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares,
who being plain and simple men our selues,
could not suspect such frauds and impostures in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
And in case these things should come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,
as in part themselues had discouered them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
their wils: yet so confident and resolute did
I finde them, to maintaine all for good and honest
dealing, as that Father<note n="a" place="margin">Mitigat. cap. 9. nu. 81. p. 403.</note>
      <hi>Persons</hi> maketh a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of it, and thinketh that God should deale worse
with men then hee had done with beasts, if hee
should not grant them <hi>equiuocating</hi> trickes, and
<hi>reserued</hi> wiles, as he hath granted to <hi>the Hare
and the Foxe, their leapes and turnings, and
windings, and going backe againe in the same
trace they come, to deceiue the Dogges</hi> that
pursue them. And yet all this confidence I take to
be but a copie of their countenance. For euen in
their printed Apologies of this Arte, they seeke to
<pb facs="4"/>
cast mists before the Readers eyes, that hee may
not be able to see the depth of their meaning. These
things when I had found, as I thought, (though I
know I am much short of finding all) I was willing,
according to my abilitie, to impart them vnto well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning
Christians, that they seeing the deepe
frauds of these men, may learne to shun their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
and acquaintance.</p>
   <p>In which indeuour of mine, what seruice I may
haue done for the publique good, I cannot tell: but
sure I am, if there be any good in it, I should in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
returne it thither, where I first found it. The
consideration whereof, hath made mee to presume
so far vpon your Graces clemency, as to lay downe
at your feete thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> poore Treatise, the grounds
whereof I first learned from your owne pen: desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
(if therein I be not ouer-bold) that it may, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
your name and protection, be sent forth into
the world. Which being all, that at this time I haue
to say, I humbly take my leaue, desiring the God of
<hi>peace</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> to preserue you from euery <hi>euill
word and worke,</hi> that you may maintaine his
<hi>truth</hi> in this world, and enioy his <hi>peace</hi> both in this
world, and the World to come.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces deuoted in all seruice,
HENRIE MASON</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>