<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Hickock, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112444_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00611</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10746</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hickock, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The voyage and trauaile : of M. Cæsar Frederick, merchant of Venice, into the East India, the Indies, and beyond the Indies. Wherein are contained very pleasant and rare matters, with the customes and rites of those countries. Also, heerein are discovered the merchandises and commodities of those countreyes, aswell the aboundaunce of goulde and siluer, as spices, drugges, pearles, and other iewelles. Written at sea in the Hercvles of London: comming from Turkie, the 25. of March 1588. For the profitable instruction of merchants and all other trauellers, for their better direction and knowledge of those countreyes. Out of Italian, by T H</title>
                 <author>Federici, Cesare</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 41 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ To the courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing at Sea (Gentle and friendly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> in this my last voyage to <hi>Tripoly,</hi> in Anno. 1587. This little Booke of M. <hi>Caesar Fredericks</hi> (Merchant of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi>) comming into my handes: which when I had read it ouer, I was desirous to translate the same out of Italian into our vulgar tongue. In which Booke (Gentle Reader) thou must not looke for a garden of sweete English Roses, (meaning pleasant English termes,) but thou shalt finde bancks full of <hi>Sauory,</hi> for I haue not beene a Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler (brought vp to write fine Schoole-termes,) but haue simplie fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Authors sence in that phraze of speech that we common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vse: In which Booke, (if thou readest it through), thou shalt find good sauour to thy selfe, and profite to thy Countrie. And as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was in traualing these Countries eighteene yeres, and got great benefite in them with a small stocke: so mayest thou if thou wilt trauell those Countries, and get great gaine as he did. For why? the way is layde open before thee, and as thou readest, consider with thy selfe, that he which looketh on a Iewell, perceiueth not at once all the faultes in it: but when many eyes haue the same, some findeth one fault, and some another, so that the blemishes cannot be hid. So (Gentle Reader) thou mayest see that in this worke which I coulde not see: wherein, if thou finde a blemish in this my simple worke, I pray thee hartily couer the same with the shadowe of Patience, or else friendly correct the same: and not rashly to iudge or contemne the paines of a willing minde, so shall I be encouraged to take the like paines in annother. Thus I refer to the Epistle of the author, wherein thou shalt vnderstande the effect of this booke, and all the trauails that he tooke in those Countries: read (I say) &amp; then iudge of the matter, according to thy good discretion. Thus I leaue thee to the tuition of the almighty: who euer keepe thee in health, and giue thee in the Lorde thy owne hearts desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. Hickock.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>