<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, answering that of the Gagger's to his Catholike Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112831_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07646</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18038</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112831</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, answering that of the Gagger's to his Catholike Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A gagg for the new Gospell? No: a nevv gagg for an old goose : VVho would needes vndertake to stop all Protestants mouths for euer, with 276. places out of their owne English Bibles. Or an ansvvere to a late abridger of controuersies, and belyar of the Protestants doctrine. By Richard Mountagu. Published by avthoritie</title>
                 <author>Montagu, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 23, 28-44, 41-172, 177-328 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, answering that of the <hi>Gagger's</hi> to his Catholike Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Am not, nor would you haue</hi>
      <note place="margin">Curteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, before I presse thee to peruse this treatise, haue, I pray thee, so much patience, as to permit me, to giue thee my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning some cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nts very necessary for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me thy selfe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>of with fruit and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ofit.</note>
      <hi>me, it seemeth by your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription Sir</hi> Gagger, <hi>much interessed in this your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. For you will not, I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, admit me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> for one of your Curteous Readers: and I professe, I am none of your Catholike Readers: that is, as you intend it, according to the Romancutt. Your inscription, is onely to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Reader: your addresse alone vnto the Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>eous Reader. And sure I am, you neede both the one and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Catholike and Curteous, or none at all, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view your pure Naturalls. Indeed, because Catholike, beleeuing any thing: therefore so curteous, admitting,
<pb facs="10"/>
admiring any thing. You are sure of a Curteous one, without more adoe, if he be a Catholike one that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it. Such Readers you leade in a string by the nose: you neede not pray them their patience: spare that paines and engagement, you are sure enough of so much patience, as heart can wish, though, otherwise af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, or but indifferent Readers, would count it a pressure, to peruse such idle treatises, as you permit your selues leaue to send amongst them. But Sir, what incongruity is this, which your Gagger-ship presenteth vs with, at the first Gaping? It was intended by you, and accordingly fitted, to choke vp the new Gospell, and Gospellers for euer. The very title doth challenge that opinion, and threaten that performance, and yet see your vnaduisednesse, you would not haue it put into their mouths at all. Catholikes alone, are addressed and inuited to it: that is, Biddengape to begagged. They onely are to reade it, and to receiue aduice in what sort to vse it: that is,</hi> to serue themselues thereof with fruit and profit. <hi>Whereas in all Eristicall discourses, those</hi> ad oppositum <hi>are to be Readers, if not onely, yet principally: as men to be conuerted or confounded, of that which is written against them. For my part, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire not, nor would I willingly maske vnder a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cloake at all, yet as some Protestants sometime, out of a desire, to be Eye-witnesses of your Antique trickes there, doe couertly repaire vnto your Masses: so for once I care not if I take vpon me the stile of a Curteous and Catholike Reader, to heare your aduice concerning those same points which are so very necessary for your Catholikes in perusing this treatise, the better to serue
<pb facs="10"/>
themselues thereof with fruit and profit; in all, and in</hi>
      <note place="margin">The first point is, that in the inscription thereof, it doth not tell thee out of which English Bible, the alleadged p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stages are extracted. For as much, as this were mecrely in vaine: sith that England hath brought forth within these few years past, to the number of 20. seueral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orts of Bibles, farre different one from another, so that the Protestants haue not all one sort of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing know this for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, that they are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taken forth of the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>le in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Barker, Anno,</hi> 1615.</note>
      <hi>the seuerall points, no doubt, of great and much behooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obseruance.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The first point is, an excuse of some negligence, or at least ouersight in the very title of the Pamphlet. For whereas the refutation of the errors of the Protestants, so vaunted of, was vndertaken to be out of expresse texts of their owne Bibles: this indetermined generality may amuse and puzle the Reader, who will be to seeke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all question, out of which English Bible, the alleaged passages are extracted. Well thought vpon, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</hi> Bonum factum, <hi>had hee beene so punctuall and precise in his Texts of Fathers,</hi> to bee seene <hi>for</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>God knoweth what oftentimes: in none of which, the editions are specified; being many, diuers, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. In many of which, no place designed: or but at rouers and randon, or els falsly, and not to purpose. Some</hi> aduice <hi>would haue beene thought vpon here: Bibles are of more speciall care, I grant. Therefore as this was necessarily done: so in discretion that should not haue beene left vndone.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And yet, what such necesssity; to tell the Reader, out of which English Bible they were alleadged? Great doubtlesse: For</hi> Qui bené distinguit bene docet. <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land hath brought forth within these few yeares past, to the number of twenty seuerall Bibles. I grant that, perchance to the number of twenty, and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, in many seuerall impressions, and editions, in folio: in quarto: in octauo: as many hath Rome, and Lions, and Antwerpe, and Paris, and other places, nay farre moe, brought forth seuerall sorts of the vulgar
<pb facs="11"/>
Latine, and sent them abroad into the world. It was very vnaduisedly therefore done of</hi> Bellarmine, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Vasquez, <hi>and the rest of our Controuersors, not to giue vs a speciall direction vnto that precise Edition which they followed, as you haue done for yours, of 1615.</hi> in quarto, by Robert Barker: <hi>that we might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse our selues, in perusing Controuersies, vnto the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition by them followed, the time, place, and quantity thereof. Surely a materiall and most remarkeable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, Catholikes could neuer haue</hi> perused this treatise with profit; <hi>without this.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Oh but the Protestants sorts of Bibles, are sarre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent one from another. Meane you in forme? So are yours: but then you enlarge beyond art and skill. There are but fiue seuerall forms of Bibles at the most. You mean in matter: For the translations differing one from an other. Then in plaine English,</hi> you lye. <hi>Name me ten of this twenty if you can. Some different Translations there haue beene of late, but authorized I know but two: The Bishops as they call it, and this last which hath perchance beene printed in seuerall formes, twenty and twenty times, but without diuersity in the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that you might as well haue directed your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Reader to 1614. 1616, or any other yeare, as well as 1619. by</hi> Robert Barker.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>But admit there had beene amongst vt twenty seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Translations, (as you belye vs:) so long as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority gaue not countenance vnto them, what can we be taxed for more then the Church of Rome may? not so much as the ancient Catholike Church might. For beside eight or nine seuerall translations into the Greeke</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>tongue;</hi> Saint Augustine <hi>is punctuall, Lib. 2. cap. 11. de doct. Christ. that the seuerall Latine Translations in his time,</hi> could not be numbred: <hi>and</hi> Hierome <hi>in his preface vpon Iosua saith, there were</hi> Tot exemplaria quod codices: <hi>as many Translations as Copies. Which variety he misliked, but</hi> S. Augustine <hi>doth well like. And in the Church of Rome at this day, are moe seuerall Translations extant of the Scriptures into Latine, then are in England into English: beside the corrections of the Lovanists, of</hi> Sixtus 5. <hi>and</hi> Clemens Octavus, <hi>contrary, repugnant to one the other. Besides the infinite variety of the vulgar Edition, not one copy almost like vnto another. It cannot be obiected with such good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son vnto vs, what edition doe you follow? as it may be vnto you with reproofe enough. Doe you follow</hi> Sixtus <hi>or</hi> Clemens <hi>in your quotations? For we affix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility vnto any Translator, as you doe to their Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that haue thwarted and crossed shins with one the other. And if you tye your men in publique passages vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your authorized Edition: so doe we our men in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Liturgies, in like sort.</hi> Iam sumus, ergo pares. <hi>And you may turne your finger home vpon your selfe, before you point it out to vs;</hi> so that wee Papists haue not all one sort of Bible.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>One, or many: if it had beene so materiall, or so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for the</hi> Curteous Catholike Reader <hi>to know, which Edition it was you followed, but that you are meerely a vaine man, the inscription might haue told vs which you followed: without any great adoe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbring of the Page, thus; After,</hi> English Bibles, <hi>you might haue added,</hi> in quarto, by Robert Barker, 1615.
<pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>and not made so much adoe about plaine nothing: but then you could not haue had this fling at so necessary a Point, the</hi> great variety <hi>of our translations: and such an opportunity was not to bee slipped, for giuing the Protestants a wipe with a meere lye, of the multiplicity</hi> of Bibles differing one from another.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Seconded with another of like nature: For know for certaine; Reader, whatsoeuer thou art, there is no such</hi>
      <note place="margin">If any one shall shew vnto thee some other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wherein they are not so written, word for word, as here they are, yet rest assured, and out of doubt, that thou shalt finde thē written as they are here alleadged, at the least in this of <hi>Robert Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>faithfulnesse in these citations as this man pretendeth. For neither are all citations word for word expressed in the Gagger, according to our Bibles of any Translation, but sometime the sense onely: sometime not that: and sometime expresse consequence and no more. Contrary to promise and vndertaking: euen so, when the sense is not differing from the supposall: For by promise he was bound vnto</hi> expresse <hi>and direct</hi> words. <hi>And yet par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him this false asseueration, that they are not so written, as he pretended, not in that Edition of</hi> Robert Barker. <hi>As for instance,</hi> Luc. 24. 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 13. Math. 9. 3. 3. 8. <hi>and 3. 5. 6. and</hi> 19. 12. Act. 15. 14, 15. 1 Cor. 14. 32. 2 Cor. 11. 2. <hi>and</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 10. Philip. 2. 30. Esay 49. 21. <hi>And haply other places beside these. This is the first point, Reader, to serue thee for thy profit and togather fruit thereout.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A second is, touching the splendour of Truth: which</hi>
      <note place="margin">The second point is, that thou admire the splendour of Truth, and accordingly to stand as stoutly and as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueably in the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereof.</note>
      <hi>indeed is admirable and attractiue. Falshood, and fraud are corner-creepers, but</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Truth is euer with a cheerefull countenance: and as the verticall sunne at noone: which hauing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled both the darknesse of the night, and fogges of the day, shineth forth in brightest glory. But there are sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
<pb facs="12"/>
as well as substances:</hi> et notâ maior imago, <hi>most an end in course of kind, the shadow is of greater aspect then the substance. Truth is,</hi> appearing, <hi>as well as</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>The diuell will seeme an Angell of light. Not the veriest Theese that euer tooke purse, but will say of his fellow, and sweare for himself, we are honest men, Change but the tearmes, the case is yours Sir Gagger. The truth is your owne, is it not? Oh take it as granted: though nothing more questioned or so questionable, yet the Truth is onyour side; there is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ay. You may speake it boldly, and stand to it stoutly, to your</hi> Catholike Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>For if you want Knights of the post, themselues will supply the place, and sweare it.</hi> That notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Protestant Ministers haue endeauoured to obserue <hi>(you would say obscure)</hi> the same by so many varieties of translations, and by such an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of corruptions and falsifications, yet neuerthelesse their condemnation is so expresly set downe, in their own Bible, and is so cleare to al the world, that nothing more needs hereto, but only that thou know to reade, and to haue thine eyes in thy head, at the opening of this their booke. <hi>Euen as you put the words into their mouths, as a witnesse at large, in case of Tithes once did sweare in my owne hearing, he knew the place, Tithable, for 300. yeares, and yet was aged but 99. yeares. This man spake with a good will to the cause; So will your Catholikes if you aske them; touching Protestant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, their Translations, Corruptions, and Falsificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beleeue you, forestall you, protest and sweare for you, accordingly. Can you desire greater</hi> Curtesie <hi>then so? Some variety of Translation betwixt ours and yours
<pb facs="13"/>
your selfe haue taken the paines to obserue: in these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions: 7. 14. 15. twice. 25. 29. 38. 46. and happily some others. Are these Corruptions or Falsifications of the text? you charge them not so: you cannot: you dare not doe. Variety of Translations, for all your enlarging, there are not many. As many or moe in the Church of Rome. If so: not authorised, you will say. Why no more are ours. The Councel of Trent hath authorised yours: and the Church of England representatiue, ours. Neither one nor other, this or that, for Authenticall variety of Translation, there may be some, if this make Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Falsifications, your Authenticall Latine is in a poore case: or rather a shop of Corruptions, to depraue and obscure the</hi> splendour of Truth, which is such and so passing bright notwithstanding <hi>that it shineth forth aboue, and against them all. For if a man</hi> can but reade and haue his eyes in his head: <hi>at the very ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the booke, he shall finde your Bibles infinitely full of such varieties: which no man will deny, per ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture not your selfe, who yet may claime to weare</hi>
      <note place="margin">Yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation is so expresly set downe, in their owne Bibles, and is so cleare to all the world, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more needs hereto, but onely that thou know to reade and haue thy eyes in thy head at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of this their booke.</note>
      <hi>a Liuery, as one of</hi> Belzebubs <hi>attendants in this kind. And for Corruptions and Falsifications, if they be so infinite and so cleere, it had beene honesty to haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med halfe a score, halfe a dozen, one at least, to haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted your toung of Lying and slandering: as it is,</hi> Calumnia est, non accusatio. <hi>There are quoted by you in your Abridgement, 276 seuerall places of Scripture, or thereabout. It seemeth strange vnto me that not one of these should fall foule vpon that infinite number of corruptions and falsifications which you talke so freely and loudly of vnto your Catholike Reader. Had there
<pb facs="13"/>
beene any such thing to be discouered, your charity wee know is no way so Transcendent, as to conceale it: wee should haue heard thereof on both eares to a purpose. He can doe little that can not belye his aduersary in grosse, though put him to proofe, and he prooueth recreant. Do this, I challenge your Gagship if you can or dare; or prooue your selfe a Gagler and a Goose for euer. For va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of reading, deprauation, corruption, falsification, here I offer to charge and prooue, your most Sacrosanct Authenticall edition of Trent, in the best and most cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected copy you can choose, is as guilty of at and euery one of these particulars, as you or your betters can proue our Bibles to be. When you will, or when you dare, vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it shall be.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">This in my mind cannot choose but be an exceeding comfort vnto a Catholike. Yea, rather a great signe of security and assurance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the truth and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnesse of his cause in shewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe content to be tried by their owne Bibles. The translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whereof doth in a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of places, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in those that are now in controuersie, swarue and differ notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously from the Authenticall Latin and that to the incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, darkning and obscuring of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like verity.</note>
      <hi>this in my mind is but a cold comfort vnto a Catholike, who opineth, poore deceiued soule, that hee may be secure, and build his saluation vpon the facing impudency of euery light-skirt mountebanck, and shaued emposter. You do well to seale vp the truth and vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this forlorne cause of yours, with security, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance, that is, to captiuate their vnderstanding with</hi> implicite faith. <hi>For you know, and I can make it good, that let the</hi> Truth <hi>you talke of, come to scanning,</hi> Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>true History will be as warrantable. It is true, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not, our translations all, and singular, and so your owne, done by your owne men, differ both amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, as also from the Authenticall Latin, as you call it, notoriously: your Authenticall Latin, differeth from it selfe: Is this to the disparagement, darkning, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scuring of the Catholike verity? Looke you to that. I can rid my hands of it well enough, and cleere both our
<pb facs="14"/>
Church a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d Bibles, of all such imputation, or impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Catholike verity any way. If it bring such dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement, the reason is, in my conceit, you swarued euen from the Councell of Trent, which neuer intended such a royal prerogatiue vnto your Latin edition, as the Iesuits and Iesuited faction giue vnto it. I speake not this to disparage it. I professe, I respect it, as much as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Translation extant, and to quite your kindnesse, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> content to be tryed by our Bibles, <hi>I will be tryed in any point the Church of England maintaineth this day against the Church of Rome, by no other but your owne Authenticall Latin. Eate your words Goodman Gag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Neuer did, nor neuer dare our aduersaries of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themselues to giue the like aduantage to vs, as to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our own translations.</note>
      <hi>I am your aduersary I professe my selfe: I will and dare offer my selfe to giue what aduantage you can make thereof,</hi> to be tryed by your owne Translation: <hi>and to deserue your loue the more, may happily ere long Gagge your mouth in this very kind of putting you to it with your</hi> owne translation. <hi>In the</hi> interim, <hi>put mee to it when you please, I will not waue your so Authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Latin, in maintaining the assertions of our Church. And so much for your second point of aduice vnto your Reader.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly, you aduise him somewhat farther off, for generall affronting the Protestant in any point whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The third is, that when thou shalt vrge, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, any passage in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of thine owne faith, if any one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the change, be it either in recrimination<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and blaming of the Roman Church; or be it in alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure text, and ill vnderstood to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point thine. Shew, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>as I can conceiue it in briefe thus. The manner of the Protestant is in conference of controuerted points, when he is vrged with text of Scripture, plaine and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, to beate backe the argument, or as you phrase the thing, to</hi> Counterpoint <hi>it, with some other text of Scripture. For instance, when you bring those euident</hi> few words, This is my body, <hi>they vse to rebutt it with</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>
Iohn 6. 63. The flesh profiteth nothing, the words that I speake vnto you, they are spirit, and they are life: and by this allegation, suppose they haue put by the point of your weapon, or giuen you a great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw; <hi>as you speake. In such a case, your aduice is, to shew the party amiably; that this is not to proceede by order, and that he dealeth not with thee as he ought, nor sincerely, in opposing a passage darke and obscure, to confound a passage that is most cleere. A man may take good counsell of his enemy, though against his will: and so haue no cause to thanke him for it. Sir Gagger, of your selfe and your owne gagle, this aduice we meane to make vse of, and put it home to your selues, as we haue occasion, frequent enough. I know no men guilty of this blameable carriage, at least, so guilty, as your selues be: I haue rubbed your memory with it sometime, as it fell out. But here, hauing so iust cause, you can not blame me if I gagge you with your owne gagge. Misticall pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages are not argumentatiue. What so mysticall as the Reuelation? In which are,</hi> tot Sacramenta, <hi>as many darke passages as there by words. And yet we want not proofes of plainer particulars, from mysticall</hi> signing in the forehead. The number of the beast. Power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Saints ouer nations. <hi>What more absurd then to prooue ordinary oeconomy in Gods disposition, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary dispensation? This you haue done, out of</hi> Math. 17. 3. Math. 27. 52. <hi>or points of faith, as you would haue them, out of a dreame.</hi> 2 Mac. 15. 12. <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto Saints, is defined in your Creed. Your proofes for that against euident scripture,</hi> Psal. 51. 15. <hi>are</hi> Luk. 16. 24. Iob 5. 1. <hi>Without Purgatory, Popery cannot stand.
<pb facs="15"/>
The</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>two pillars of Purgatory, are those two places of</hi> S. Paul. 1 Cor. 3. 13. 1 Cor. 5. 29. <hi>then which there are not two more obscure places in all the scripture. Adde to them a third, though of a baser alloy, that intricate and depraued place of</hi> 2. Mach. 12. 44. <hi>I could goe further, and gagge you Doper, out of your owne practise: Who if you had not so much honesty, as to forbeare belying of your opposites, should haue had so much discretion, as not to obiect that vnto another, which, had you that good signe of a bad cause in you,</hi> Blushing, <hi>might ashame you, being by recrimination re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted vpon your selfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I say</hi> belye: <hi>for it is not better, nor worse, but euen so. For Transubstantiation, that monster of monsters, you haue neuer done with,</hi> This is my body. <hi>Which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not, either in words or sense. The very body of Christ really receiued in the Sacrament of the Altar, is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by those formall words of Institution,</hi> This is my body: <hi>but not</hi> per modum Con, <hi>or</hi> Trans, <hi>or any other like. It is not said, This is my body corporally; eaten o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; there carnally; conceiued of grossely. This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, say the Protestants: and for proofe thereof, that the thing being granted, the manner cannot be so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, proceedeth thus: That which one Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth cannot bee contraried by another: But this carnall sense of those words,</hi> This is my body, <hi>is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traried by another: an instance. In</hi> Iohn 6. 63. The flesh profiteth nothing: <hi>as plaine a text against carnall eating of Christs flesh as can be. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had formerly discoursed of eating his flesh, and
<pb facs="15"/>
drinking his blood. His very Disciples, supposing as you doe, that he meant they should eate his Flesh, as they did the Fishes, or vsed to eate the Paschall Lambe, were here it offended. Our Sauiour vnderstanding this their scandall, replyeth in these words, according to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Authenticall edition,</hi> Hoe vos scandalisat? spiritus est, qui viuificat, caro non prodest quicquam: verba, quae ego locotus sum vobis, spiritus, &amp; vitasunt. <hi>You remember an allegation you brought out of</hi> S. Paul? If these things be hidden, they are hidden vnto those that perish. <hi>I put it to you, if this be obscure, it is obscure to him that will not see, or to him who iustly God hath abandoned and giuen ouer. Nothing can be more direct and plaine, then that our Sauiour telleth them, his speech of eating his flesh, was Sacramentall: not carnally but spiritually to be vnderstood. This is it, saith</hi> Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, <hi>which he meaneth:</hi> You must conceiue of me spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually: <hi>For he that taketh this carnally, is not benefit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereby, nor getteth any good therewith. It was a carnall thought to make a doubt, in what sort he came downe from heauen: And to suppose him the sonne of</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph: <hi>And to dispute, how can he giue vs his flesh to eate? All these were carnall thoughts: which must be mystically and spiritually vnderstood.</hi> The words that I speake vnto you, are spirit and life; <hi>that is, are diuine and spirituall, hauing nothing carnall, not any infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or consequence naturall: But are freed from all such necessity as this, surpassing legal tyes and conditions below; conteining another sense, and meaning, then is literally set downe. If this be not an important pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, goe gagge</hi> Saint Chrysostome, <hi>and other ancient
<pb facs="16"/>
Fathers that put this saying into the Protestants mouths: as plaine a text of Scripture as, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God made heauen and earth. Plaine or obscure, yet to no purpose. For, it</hi> affirmeth nothing lesse then that which they pretend to prooue thereby. <hi>And what is that? are you aware of it? That the flesh of Christ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing. It is plaine the flesh profiteth nothing. It is plaine, the passage is of Christs flesh: Therefore the flesh of Christ profiteth nothing. This you say is</hi> absurd. <hi>And so say I: nay I adde, this is impious. For,</hi> his Flesh is life; <hi>and</hi> giueth life, <hi>and therefore nothing</hi> profiteth <hi>so much as that. If the passage be not of Christs flesh, of what is it, can you tell? I beleeue you cannot. But your instructors can tell you, they would haue it taken, that</hi> Carnalis intelligentia non prodest. <hi>Good: And so say I. But</hi> Intelligentia cuius? <hi>of a certaine</hi> indiuiduum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, abstrahendo <hi>from all subiect, or obiect whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? Idle, and absurd. But</hi> Carnalis intelligentia <hi>of that which must bee taken spiritually. And so of this place: and principally, and primarily of this place, as giuing occasion vnto this Axiome of our Sauiour: The flesh profiteth not. This is not vrged by</hi> Peter Martyr, <hi>or any Protestant, against</hi> Hoc est corpus meum, This is my body: <hi>but against</hi> This is my body by this means; <hi>This way, that is, by Transubstantiation. Which is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to take that, which was spoken and intended spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually onely.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>It is easily granted you by the Protestant, and you might haue made your friends of this aduice that way.</hi> That it is doubtlesse better to explicate an obscure pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage by one that is cleere, then one that is cleere by a
<pb facs="16"/>
passage obscure. <hi>For reason it selfe, and commonsense will dictate this, that the proofe must be more euident then the thing prooued. The epexegesis, more manifest then that which is explaned. The Protestants obserue this course they say. You in this so small a Pamphlet, as I haue let you see, are culpable that way more then once. It is much more cleere and euident what our Sauiour mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by Flesh and Spirit: Then how; This can be my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> Sic etiamsi carnem ait nihil prodesse ex materia, dicti dirigendus est sensus. Nam quia durum &amp; intolerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem existimauerunt sermonem eius, quasi verè carnem suam, illis edendam determinasset, vt in spiritu dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neret statum salutis, praemisit, spiritus est, qui viuificat. Atque ita subiunxit, caro nihil prodest ad viuificandum scilicet. Tertul. de Resur. cap. 37. <hi>Intanglements and obscurities in this place, if there be any, proceede from your glosses, not the places, nor yet the Resolutions of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity. Were your rule</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, That one text shold giue place to many, rather then many vnto one or few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>yet apply that rule you may, where it will or neede be fitted, here no neede of any such aduise at all, where,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius sic alter poscit opem locus, &amp; conspirat amicé.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The fourth will hardly come vnder the title of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The fourthis, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect some one of the passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which thou produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it to be Apocrypha, though it be not true.</note>
      <hi>it is rather a vaunt, at most and best an Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what is obserued in the</hi> Gagge, <hi>concerning texts out of Scriptures Apocryphall, to make good the assertions against the Protestants. The man supposed exception would sometime be put in against some of his witnesses (though for my part, I haue passed them all, without putting backe any, as</hi> homines legales, <hi>to say what they could) for he knew well enough they were exceptiue, and
<pb facs="17"/>
not passeable in strict tearmes and iust exception. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to preuent what he feared, their credit is salued as</hi>
      <note place="margin">That to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent this obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, no such scriptures as they call Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall are there produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but still there goe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers also that are Canonical.</note>
      <hi>much as may be, that is, they are brought in as</hi> o <hi>in cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, to enhaunce the number onely, so as they with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may make vp a tallie. Others beside them passe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and with weight. They without others carry no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Know, saith he, that to preuent this obiection</hi> (viz. <hi>that the testimonies are authenticall) no such scriptures as they call (and haue prooued, and will maintaine to be Apocrypha) are here produced, but still they goe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with others that are Canonicall, by their owne confession. Which I grant is obserued, for the most part at least. Nor will we refuse a testimony of</hi> Aristotle, <hi>or</hi> Demosthenes, <hi>that agreeth with, and commeth in with subordinate dependance vpon Scripture. Where Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is apparant, and consent incident, and manifest. But</hi> non feremus, <hi>as in the point of Purgatory is obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a plainer and more obuious place of</hi> Toby <hi>to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope betwixt two Canonicall Texts, the hardest two in</hi> Saint Paul, <hi>and all agree in one as well as harpe and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: nor any correspondency in the</hi> vinculo communi, <hi>as is pretended, to make</hi> vtraque vnum: <hi>and all speake for that which is farre enough from all, or any state of Purgatory after death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The second branch of your fourth point I mislike not at all for the matter of it. Scripture is not in the words, but in the sense and meaning of the words, that is, in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
      <note place="margin">But if they shall contend with thee not about the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both cleere and Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but about the sense, or meaning of thē know this that for such places as may bee subiect to such ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thou hast here the warrant and authority of the holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood these places, in the selfe-same sense that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes doe. A thing which they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer do in their defence.</note>
      <hi>and intents of the Spirit of the highest, intimated vnder the couert of words. There are moe things then words to expresse those things by. Hence doubts and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguities doe arise about the meaning of things expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="17"/>
by those words. There is none at all, or little contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the words of Scripture. All is about the sense &amp; meaning of the Scripture: &amp; how we may grow vnto resolution, where doubts and ambiguities do intervene. I will not goe with you about the bush. I come home, vp to your own desire;</hi> The warrant &amp; authority of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers, <hi>that is, the practise and tradition of the Church, shall regulate, I promise you, my resolution, and settle my iudgement in things that are</hi> huius contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersi. <hi>I will not put in</hi> exceptionem fori. <hi>For I am assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I need not, I appeale vnto antiquity and will follow you where you dare aduenture to call me. I know your performance that way: I laugh at your vanity in brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Fathers that haue vnderstood these places, in the selfe same sense that Catholikes doe. What Fathers haue said for you in Gagging our mouths I haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>euery one. Their answers to the questions proposed to them: their resolution for the points remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, he that will know may finde, and as he findeth, so pronounce. What we can doe in our defence may appeare when we come to be defendants. This I will promise, out of my ownepoore reading I will droppe Fathers with a better read man then you are in them</hi> point per point, <note place="margin">And what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son were it then to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Cobler before S. <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> of a Baker be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>S. Basil?</hi> of a Tinker before <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an?</hi> and so of others.</note>
      <hi>and if I say not more for my cause, that is for iustifying the Church of England, then you haue done for calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niating of it: or can say for iustifying your Popish faith, I will be reconciled to Pope</hi> Vrbans <hi>faction: For vnto the Church I neede none. We vse not Sir scurility to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult with Coblers, or Bakers, or Tinkers, they and their Trulls may meet at their stawling kenns with such clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdogeons as your selfe. Little better are those Patrons
<pb facs="18"/>
of your forlorne cause,</hi> Abdias, Amphilochius, Martialis, <hi>and others: and those Tararagmales, the Decretall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles of the Popes scullen-boyes making: or the outcasts of some groomes of his stable.</hi> Tertullian, Basill, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome, <hi>and the rest of the worthies of their times, we neither</hi> geld, <hi>nor</hi> delumbate <hi>for speaking too plaine nor vse them like you; as merchants doe their counters, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a</hi> que, <hi>sometime for a</hi> thousand pound. <hi>Euer in their place we heare them speake, rise vp with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, at their asseuerations yeeld vnto their dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call conclusions. Take not this as an enlargement, or braggadochianisme. I that say it will performe it: Put me to it as you can or dare, if I flye from antiquity, hisse at me for euer. I could haue played the foole in allitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hunted the letter as you haue done. But I speake plaine English, without a Cobler for</hi> Chrysost. <hi>a Tinker for</hi> Tertullian, <hi>a Baker for</hi> Basill. <hi>Then</hi> Tertullian, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sill, Chrysostome, <hi>and the rest of their compeeres I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire no better dayesman, or Diribitores betwixt you and me. Therefore set your heart at rest, set out when you will, I will walke along with you to the Fathers houses; and stand to their award whatsoeuer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But the fift and last is any thing rather then aduice: indeed,</hi> vox, <hi>and</hi> praeterea nihil, <hi>pure Popish Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisme, that is, insolent triumphing before victory, nay before stroke striken in the field, diuiding of the spoiles of poore Protestants, men of no action or performance at all; men that will looke before they leape, and goe warily and wisely to worke, neuer sell the skinne before the beare is slaine. It may be some one, nay any one Protestant, that hath but beene at Rama, and saluted the schoole of the
<pb facs="18"/>
Prophets, can discerne</hi> Saul <hi>amongst them, a fellow that as idly taketh God to witnesse, as</hi> Saul <hi>bound</hi> Israell <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishly with an oath, which in conclusion might haue cost him deare. The man was afraid he should hardly finde</hi>
      <note place="margin">I here protest in the presence of God, whom I call vpon in this behalfe.</note>
      <hi>credit vpon his word (being happely knowne for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his people, that will speake when he cannot doe, or meaneth not to make performance) therefore he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forward with an oath, and protesteth in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God more then he is able (beleeue me Reader) to make good;</hi> That it is not in the power of all the Protestants in England to finde in their owne Bibles, one onely expresse text; <hi>what to doe?</hi> by which they can possibly prooue one onely point of the false do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. <hi>I might say he doth aequiuocate in</hi> false doctrine, <hi>and intendeth a refuge, when he is shamed,</hi> viz. That false doctrine is not prooued by our Bibles. <hi>But I cauill not at words, I take his meaning. He suppeseth all our doctrine is false, and not to be iustified out of Scripture. Which if it be not, I will grant it false, and am ready to disclaime and to abiure it.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>It is our doctrine, he saith,</hi> No man can forgiue sinnes but God. <hi>If it be, there is</hi> expresse text <hi>for it, and that also exclusiue,</hi> Luc. 5. 21. Who can forgiue sinnes but God onely? <hi>An interrogation, in your owne learning, is equivalent to a Negatiue.</hi> None but God can forgiue sinnes. <hi>Here is, neither adding, nor diminishing, nor changing ought. Your owne Authenticke Latin hath it so,</hi> Quis potest dimittere peccata, nisi solus Deus? <hi>It is our doctrine, he saith.</hi> No man hath seene God at any time. <hi>If it be so, it is</hi> expresse words <hi>of our, and your Bibles.</hi> No man hath seene God at any time. Deum
<pb facs="19"/>
nemo vidit vnquam. Iohan. 1. 18. <hi>Here are two texts, that is more then</hi> one onely; <hi>in their Bibles also, not onely in our</hi> owne, expresse <hi>as may be, without</hi> adding, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing, <hi>or</hi> changing, <hi>to prooue two points of our doctrine imputed vnto vs by himselfe, collected out of his obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and yet the brasen face, and leaden heart, is not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to bragge it so Catholikely, and call God to record of an apparent lye. It is our doctrine that</hi> some things are hard <hi>in diuine Scripture.</hi> Saint Peter 2. 3. 16. <hi>saith as much. It is our doctrine, some things are easie.</hi> Heb. 2. 2. Write the vision and make it plaine vpon tables, that he who runneth may reade it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 11. This commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I cōmand thee this day is not hid frō thee: neither is it farre off. <hi>It were easie to passe through all points of controuerted opinions and shew the vanity of this vaunt: the confident impudency of this</hi> Ignaro. <hi>But</hi> extra oleus: <hi>this is no place for that purpose. I may happely finde him more worke this way then he can handsomely cleere his hands of in hast: without</hi> adding <hi>art,</hi> diminishing, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, <hi>or such like practises of</hi> litting Law, <hi>the Archite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctonicall science of our Popish Catholickes.</hi> Ex animi tui sententia Gagger. <hi>Who are more likely to play such trickes of legerdemaine, those that neuer vsed to pare, prune, shaue, gold, or correct Authours, but plainely send them foorth</hi> in puris naturalibus, <hi>as they finde them: or those that make a trade and profession of it, and blush not to publish vnto the world, that all Writers, old or new, sacred and prophane, must speake as our Masters will haue them speake, or hold their peace for euer. This you nor can, nor do deny. To this day you put it in practise. For according to such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections from higher powers. The</hi> Bibliotheca Saint Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,
<pb facs="19"/>
      <hi>was last yeare printed at</hi> Cullen. <hi>Shamelesse Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebancks that obiect that to others, whereof themselues are notoriously guilty. But it seemeth this man did, as the tale is; a wench once gaue her mother counsell to doe. A brace of neighbours, women by sex, scolds by profession, falling out, after they had passed some ordinary language, saith a daughter of one of them to her mother; Oh Mother, call her where first, least she call you so, and prooue it. Haue you heard of this good counsell? I am sure ye follow it to an heire. It is your profession, to adde, diminish, alter, change, to aequiuocate your selues, and teach your Authours so to doe notoriously. For feare wee should iustly lay it to your charge, you preuent vs, and cast it in our teeth. But play the honest man once in your dayes: name</hi> where, when, how, <hi>by</hi> whom <hi>this hath beene done.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I name your selfe guilty of this cousening trick; and name for false and ridiculous interpretation, the 1. of</hi> Saint Luk. 8. 9. <hi>and</hi> Leuit. 16. 17. <hi>in the sixt Proposition. For</hi> adding <hi>to</hi> Math. 9 8 <hi>in the eleuenth Proposition. For</hi> diminishing Phil. 2. 30. <hi>in the fourteene Proposition.</hi> Tria <hi>are not</hi> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia: <hi>but enough to shame you if you be not past grace and shame. In briefe your whole booke is compacted by this art. For 39. of these Propositions, are no doctrines of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>those that are, are vnfaithfully hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. By ambiguity, by adding to, taking from, peruerting of sense and meaning, this little Pamphlet is meerely made. Detract these particulars, not so much will remaine, as with a whole impression to stop one mustard pot. I shall not need</hi> actum agere <hi>here, I haue discouered your false play in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars hereafter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>This is to imploy I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rowe, mans wilinesse if not wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="20"/>
to serue the diuell: both are bad, but yet better it were</hi>
      <note place="margin">Which yet should be to alter the text, and to imploy mans wisdome in stead of the word.</note>
      <hi>to employ mans wisedome in stead of the word. For true wisedome is of God wheresoeuer or howsoeuer, Lying is, you haue heard from whom: the father of lyes, that graund Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogue in the Iesuite schooles brought you vp a good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in this faculty: you may sing a song of degrees there</hi> in medio chori: <hi>according to your progresse from our twenty seuerall Bibles, and their manifold varieties, to their more</hi> Corruptions <hi>and</hi> Falsifications, <hi>to darken and</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure the truth: <hi>and yet those also handled sophistically, and contrary to the mind of all antiquity: nor only so, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer produced without some tricke of adding, diminishing, or</hi>
      <note place="margin">A thing by their owne confession forbidden them they protesting, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>changing by interpretation: that the old saying may take hold vpon the Gagger,</hi> Qui semel verecundiae fines est trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressus, eum grauiter oportet esse impudentem. <hi>Sir know this. Our profession is not such as yours is: our practise answerable to our profession. We protest you say, and we doe so indeed, that,</hi> The word of God containeth all that is necessary to saluation. <hi>Your sarcasticall irony shal not beate vs from it. And therein we say no more then</hi> Saint Paul <hi>in that well knowne place of</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 16. 17. The whole Scripture is giuen by inspiration of God, and is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to teach, to improoue, to correct, and to instruct in righteousnesse, that the man of God may bee abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute being made perfect vnto all good workes. <hi>For to know God in Christ is life eternall.</hi> Ioh. 17. 3. <hi>That is the way vnto, and meanes whereby to attaine eternall life. The absolute direction for that way is</hi> Ioh. 20. 31. These things are written that you might beleeue that Iesus is Christ, the Sonne of God, and that in beleeuing yee might haue life through his name. <hi>These are moe texts
<pb facs="20"/>
then one, and without</hi> adding, diminishing <hi>or</hi> changing <hi>ought by interpretation, as expresse as words can make them: that all things necessary vnto saluation, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the Scripture. Yet farther to be inforced by this reason. Saluation is the end of reueiled knowledge from God: If that knowledge be not sufficient, God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue in proportioning the meanes vnto the end inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: which auouch, if you can, without blasphemy. If man adde any thing to it as defectiue: or detract from it in the materialls, or alter and change it against minde and meaning, we may well enquire,</hi> quo warranto <hi>he doth it, and condemne his presumption as enormious. An Embassadour hath commission and instructions from his penne, according to them he must proceede. Differ hee must not vpon life: nor change the state and tearmes of his direction so farre, as to come short of, to exceede vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be thwart vnto, and against the maine of the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes negotiated. Explane he may, adde, detract in words: alter phrases, or occurrences according as occasions are, so he hold the maine, and keepe close to the meaning, and direct vnto the end of his negotiating still; Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces sometime may alter much, this point discretion must regulate as it may: but substances altered, make a maine change, indeed</hi> aliud, <hi>and</hi> aliud, <hi>not</hi> aliter <hi>If we say</hi> it is not lawfull for men nor Angels, to adde, diminish, or alter ought thereof, <hi>we meane for the maine and substance of the Gospell, we intend not such a precise ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruance, as not to say,</hi> Rites, <hi>for</hi> ceremonies: statutes <hi>for</hi> ordinances: Church <hi>for</hi> congregation, <hi>and such like, or</hi> vice versâ. <hi>And therein we say no more then</hi> Saint Paul <hi>himselfe hath said in so many words (an other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
<pb facs="21"/>
text, for another point of our false doctrine)</hi> Gal. 1. 8. Though we, or an Angell from heauen, preach vnto you otherwise, then that which we haue preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, let him be accursed. <hi>Otherwise, so as</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>thereby to corrupt and abolish the Gospell. Now this is not onely when they preach contrary, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molish the whole.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>if they alter and change some small obuious thing, saith</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome: <hi>and his reason is, The Scriptures were commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to vs by God, the Lord of all: Men and Angells are but seruants, whose commendation is, to doe his will.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>This precise obedience hath that warrant yet further: It is better to obey God then man. If men stand</hi> ad op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positum <hi>to God. But we are not thus perswaded of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: We nor vse them so: nor speake so of them.</hi> We command not our followers vtterly to renounce all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, customes, multitude, humane wisedome, iudgements, decrees, edicts, <hi>or</hi> councells. <hi>The Councels of</hi> Trent, <hi>of</hi> Florence, <hi>of</hi> Laterane, <hi>are not all Councels. We refuse them as factious, as bastards, as partiaries, as hauing nothing but the names of Councels. You refuse moe Councels then we doe: in the foure first so highly commended by your owne</hi> Gregory, <hi>you presume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe, you reiect, and retaine what you please. We accept them absolutely sans exception. We may as well presse you with the Sinods of</hi> Gapp <hi>and</hi> Dort, <hi>as you vs with</hi> Trent, <hi>and diuers others.</hi> Edicts, <hi>and</hi> Decrees, <hi>and</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginents, <hi>what meane you by them? of whom? where? when? vpon what grounds? why? a rambling logo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diarrhe without wit or reason.</hi> Edicta Principum. Decreta Synodorum. <hi>And</hi> iudicia pro tribunali, <hi>are
<pb facs="21"/>
of large extent, of different alotment: For, against God, Equity, Truth and Honesty: what an idle discourse is it thus to shoote your bolts as boyes doe stones, to make Duckes and Drakes vpon the surface of the water, to glide smoothly for two or three grasings, and then sinke to the bottome without any more adoe. Adde quantity to iudgements, Decrees, Edicts, wee shall know what you would say, and so answere. As for humane wisedome, that helpe on our right hand; haue you such cause to boast, we haue no sense nor reason? I thinke you doe not find vs such arrant fooles, as vtterly destitute of humane indowments: If you doe, the better for you: You may ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the cause against vs without more adoe. Customes we haue many, of the better sort: not all your anticke fits, and gesticulations. You haue not all antiquity had, you haue many they neuer saw. Silly man, know you not most cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes doe and may vary? keepe your owne if you please: we are not so wedded to them, nor to all ours, but vpon reason, we haue, will, and may change by better warrant then you can auoide. As for multitude, we dare drip Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with you, old and late: but these are meere flashes of your Catholike vanity, I haue said it often, I repeate it in the close, that you may remember it the better, at least, you shall find, that is my selfe, that will ioyne issue with you when you dare, to maintaine the doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and oppose the doctrine of the Romish Church by all of these or any of these,</hi> Antiquitie, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, Multitude, humane wisedome, Iudgements, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, Edicts, and Councels. <hi>If I haue not for me in all or euery one as good and better share and interest, for my confession, thē you for yours, I wil yeeld. As for</hi> Miracles,
<pb facs="22"/>
Visions, <hi>and such hobgoblin-stuffe, I am contented you appropriate to your owne. So did the Gentiles brag of the like as</hi> Chrysostome <hi>obserueth,</hi> Orat. 1. in Iudai santes pag. 34. Edit. Heshe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>So did the</hi> Donatists <hi>as S.</hi> Augustine <hi>reporteth,</hi> de notis Ecclesiae, ca. 19. <hi>Their miracles were then, as yours now,</hi> Figmenta mendacium hominum, aut portenta fallacium spirituum. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: <hi>is a prouerbiall speech in</hi> Athenaeus. <hi>Fooles may be frighted with Hagges, and Fairies, men of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding know it is but knauery: At</hi> Lauretto, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem, Annuntiada, <hi>or wheresoeuer we haue the like pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet playes amongst our Catholike neighbours:</hi> Cachin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantibus daemonijs, <hi>at such iugling tricks for their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. And yet take me not so, as if I cast off all mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: I admit, I admire them, that were true, for a true end, the ratificatiou of Truth, vnto the soule,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>That such as would not yeeld vnto the word preached, might yet be conuicted by that miraculous power, saith</hi> Clemens <hi>in his Constituions. This was that the world might beleeue, but yet since and euer</hi> Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome <hi>said true.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>? One faith and beleefe is to be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, not by miracles, but by the Scripture, <hi>which</hi> on good foundation, <hi>we defend containes all that is Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary</hi>
      <note place="margin">Farewell my deare Reader, seeing I haue now said all that vnto thee which I desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>
      <hi>for our saluation. You haue done with your Reader, and I with you, till we meet againe at the next turne: till then farewell.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>