<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>R., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112956_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10289</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20571</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112956</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two fruitfull exercises : the one: A Christian discourse vpon the 16. and 17. verses of the 16. chapter of the booke of Iudges, wherin are handled these three principal heads: The portreature of Dalila. The bridle of lust. The seale of secrets. The other: A godly meditation vpon the 41. and 42. verses of the 10. chapter of Saint Luke, containing especially The profit of reproofe, togither with the necessitie and excellencie of Gods word. Also a brief discourse intituled A buckler against a Spanish brag: Written vpon the first rumor of the intended inuasion, and now not altogither vnmeete to be published. By E.R</title>
                 <author>E. R.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="137" facs="75"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>GOod Reader, this short discourse follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was penned when the rumor of the Spanish inuasiō was first dispersed; which I did then forbear to publish for som particular causes. But now being mooued for dutifull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations to present the two former to that good Ladie: I thought it not amisse; hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered some thing in the first copie, to ioine this also vnto them, and to offer the same to thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous acceptation. It is verie true that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of season in respect of the action: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles considering that the enimie carieth still the same mind towards vs, and that he is not so repulsed with dishonor; so departed with disgrace; so ouerwhelmed in the sea; &amp; disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by Gods mightie power with intollerable losse and dammage; but his inueterate malice, and our sinnes may cause fresh supplies to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: as likewise that such meditations are profitable not only against those Spanish threts and attempts; but also against the practises of all other aduersaries of his nature, qualitie and disposition, wherof there are manie, which looke askew, and with an enuious eie vpon the pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous &amp; florishing estate of our sacred Prince,
<pb n="138" facs="76"/> Countrie, and Religion: I haue presumed to offer vnto thee this <hi>BVCKLER</hi> against all his, and their future brags and malicious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises. I know the zealous minister hath and doth deliuer vnto thee daily bucklers of perfect proofe: vse theirs, and neglect not this in thy like occasions: Theirs are of better proof, bicause they are of better skill: yet maist thou find somwhat heerein wherewith to defend thy selfe. If thou shalt accept thereof, it will encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me to endeuor to prepare some better and stronger weapon, when any iust cause shall be presented. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>