<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GREAT EXAMPLE OF HONOR AND VERTVE, THE MOST NOBLE WILLIAM, EARLE OF PEMBROKE, L. CHAMBERLAYNE, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112455_Fr11_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112455</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GREAT EXAMPLE OF HONOR AND VERTVE, THE MOST NOBLE WILLIAM, EARLE OF PEMBROKE, L. CHAMBERLAYNE, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The workes of Beniamin Ionson</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Meighen, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 1015, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="409"/>
   <pb n="767" facs="409"/>
   <head>TO THE GREAT EXAMPLE OF HONOR AND VERTVE, THE MOST NOBLE WILLIAM, EARLE OF PEMBROKE, L. CHAMBERLAYNE, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y LORD.</hi> While you cannot change your merit, I dare not change your title: It was that made it, and not I. Vnder which name, I here offer to your Lo: the ripest of my studies, my <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grammes;</hi> which, though they carry danger in the sound, doe not therefore seeke your shelter: For, when I made them, I had nothing in my conscience, to expressing of which I did need a cypher. But, if I be falne into those times, wherein, for the likenesse of vice, and facts, euery one thinks anothers ill deeds obiected to him; and that in their ignorant and guiltie mouthes, the common voyce is (for their securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) <hi>Beware the Poet</hi>, confessing, therein, so much loue to their diseases, as they would rather make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for them, then be either rid, or told of them: I must expect, at your Lo: hand, the protection of truth, and
<pb n="768" facs="410"/>
libertie, while you are constant to your owne goodnesse. In thankes whereof, I returne you the honor of leading forth so many good, and great names (as my verses mention on the better part) to their remembrance with posteritie. Amongst whom, if I haue praysed, vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately, any one, that doth not deserue; or, if all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere not, in all numbers, the pictures I haue made of them: I hope it will be forgiuen me, that they are no ill pieces, though they be not like the persons. But I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see a neerer fate to my booke, then this: that the vices therein will be own'd before the vertues (though, there, I haue auoyded all particulars, as I haue done names) and that some will be so readie to discredit me, as they will haue the impudence to belye themselues. For, if I meant them not, it is so. Nor, can I hope otherwise. For, why should they remit any thing of their riot, their pride, their selfe-loue, and other inherent graces, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider truth or vertue; but, with the trade of the world, lend their long eares against men they loue not: and hold their deare <hi>Mountebanke</hi>, or <hi>Iester</hi>, in farre better condition, then all the studie, or studiers of <hi>humanitie</hi>? For such, I would rather know them by their visards, still, then they should publish their faces, at their perill, in my <hi>Theater</hi>, where <hi>CATO</hi>, if he liu'd, might enter without scandall.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lo: most faithfull honorer, BEN. IONSON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>