<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A few volu ntary verses to the general readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112587_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18740</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5237</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112587</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A few volu ntary verses to the general readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A handefvl of gladsome verses, giuen to the Queenes Maiesty at Woodstocke this prograce. 1592. By Thomas Chvrchyarde</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A few volu ntary verses to the general readers.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF aged daies, had dryed vp my Muse</l>
      <l>As summer drouth, hath partcht both hearb and grasse</l>
      <l>Yet now compeld, my pen againe to vse</l>
      <l>That world shall see, my minde is as it was</l>
      <l>Looke for no gold, when I can giue but glasse</l>
      <l>My morning dew, sun beames hath taken hence</l>
      <l>And troubled springs, yeelds puddle water sence.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Take edge away, the knife can cut no more</l>
      <l>Hard stony ground, can beare but little corne</l>
      <l>Old appels sone, are rotten at the kore</l>
      <l>Ne Figs nor Grapes, can come from pricking thorne</l>
      <l>The glasse soone goes, from silke that long is worne</l>
      <l>Hope for no fruit, when leaues forsakes the tree</l>
      <l>So falleth out, betweene my verse and me.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>When youth was fresh, and florisht as a flowre</l>
      <l>The wits were quicke, and ready to conceiue</l>
      <l>When age did frowne, and browes began to lowre</l>
      <l>My skill grue scant, the muses did me leaue</l>
      <l>Then tract of time, in head did cobwebs weaue</l>
      <l>So rusty grew, the reason of the braine</l>
      <l>And euer since, I lost my Poets vaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>What though ripe wit, be now but bare and blunt</l>
      <l>And fine deuice, of head is farre to seeke</l>
      <l>And age can not, doe that which youth was wont</l>
      <l>And pen scarce makes, a verse in halfe a weeke</l>
      <l>And all my workes, not worth a little leeke</l>
      <l>Yet what I doe, but bad or worthy praise</l>
      <l>I neuer robd, no writer in my daies.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>It is mine owne, I bring to Printers Presse</l>
      <l>I haue by happe, a Hatchet in my hand</l>
      <l>To hew the wood, (let it be more or lesse)</l>
      <l>In what strange forme, I list to let it stand</l>
      <l>though some be chips, let all bee iustly scand</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Ne chips ne choice, nor nothing els I knew</l>
      <l>But was well ment, and may abide the vew.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A Booke in Presse, that I my challenge name</l>
      <l>Shall tell you more, of workes that I haue done</l>
      <l>But blame me not, (since each man striues for fame)</l>
      <l>To holde on right, the course wherein I runne</l>
      <l>I ought to weare, the cloth my fingers spunne</l>
      <l>I will so Iowd, for bookes and verses crie</l>
      <l>That sure no bird, shall with my feathers flie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Some Peakocks then, will spread their tailes no more</l>
      <l>Small boast is best, let touchstone trie out golde</l>
      <l>I haue as yet, some tragedies in store</l>
      <l>That like Shores wife, in verses shalbe tolde</l>
      <l>Condemne no man, though he be waxen olde</l>
      <l>A rough barkt tree, whose bowes but crooked grow</l>
      <l>When season serues, some mellowd fruit may show.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A great olde Oake, long time will akornes beare</l>
      <l>And small young graffes, are long in sprouting out</l>
      <l>Some saie old wine, is liked euerie where</l>
      <l>And all men knowes, new ale is full of grout</l>
      <l>Old horse goes well, young tits are much to doubt</l>
      <l>But sure old golde, is more esteemd then new</l>
      <l>No Hawke compares, with Hagard in the mew.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Old men know much, though young men cal them fooles</l>
      <l>Old bookes are best, for there great learning is</l>
      <l>Old authours too, are daily read in Schooles</l>
      <l>New sectes are nought, olde knowledge can not misse</l>
      <l>Old guyes was good, and nothing like to this</l>
      <l>Where fraude and craft, and finenesse all would haue</l>
      <l>And playnest men, can neither pole nor shaue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Olde fathers built, faire Colledges good store,</l>
      <l>And gaue great goods, and landes to bring vp youth</l>
      <l>Young men thinke skorne, to make of little more</l>
      <l>And spends away, their thrift to tell the truth</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Olde mindes were full, of mercie grace and ruth</l>
      <l>And pitty tooke, of those that seemd to lacke</l>
      <l>Young gallants gay, from poore doe turne their backe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Olde customes good, at length becam good lawes</l>
      <l>Olde lawes are likte, and honourd of the wise</l>
      <l>Good men obey, the euils olde order drawes</l>
      <l>Newe fond delights, olde fathers did despise</l>
      <l>In olde graue heads, great skill and wisedome lies</l>
      <l>Sounde councell comes, from age in time of neede</l>
      <l>Olde mens aduice, is that which doth the deede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Olde beaten waies, are readie still to hit</l>
      <l>These new by-paths, leades men on many stiles</l>
      <l>An olde prouerbe, hath no more wordes then wit</l>
      <l>Newe fangled heades, at each light fancie smiles</l>
      <l>Olde wisedome farre, surmounts young fondlings wiles</l>
      <l>Experience is, the doctor eury daie</l>
      <l>That carries close, all knowledge cleane away.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Young houndes are fleete, the olde hunts slowe and true</l>
      <l>Olde dogges bite sore, if all his teeth be sound</l>
      <l>Olde auncient friends, are better then the newe</l>
      <l>In younglings loue, there is small suretie found</l>
      <l>For like a toppe, fine fancie turneth round</l>
      <l>Olde colth or silke, made in our elder daies</l>
      <l>Weares long and firme, when new things soone decaies.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No further nowe, of age but to my taske</l>
      <l>I tooke in hand, to shewe my duety throw</l>
      <l>Yet licker sweete, comes none from emptie kaske</l>
      <l>With vargis sowre, is fild olde barrell now</l>
      <l>But reason must, inuent the meane and howe</l>
      <l>I doe discharge, my duety as I ought</l>
      <l>To make a booke, shall answere writers thought.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nowe must my Muse, goe borrowe if I may,</l>
      <l>My betters workes, to fill my matter full</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>Tush world growes hard, each man will say me nay</l>
      <l>Some cannot spare, a little locke of wooll</l>
      <l>So greedely, for pealfe they plucke and pull</l>
      <l>But namely some, so watch and pry for fame</l>
      <l>That they with wordes, will hinder mens good name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Spite is a sparke, of fire that flies in thaire</l>
      <l>And makes a cracke, like pouder in a dagge</l>
      <l>Spite hides foule thoughts, in lookes and speeches faire</l>
      <l>Whose wordes rests not, as long as tongue may wagge</l>
      <l>Spite of himselfe, will boldly boast and bragge</l>
      <l>To hurt by hate, the hart that harmeles is</l>
      <l>For spite like snake, in euery hedge can his.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who flings a stone, at euery dogge that barkes</l>
      <l>A wearie arme, is surelie like to haue</l>
      <l>Though enuy shootes, his bolts at many markes</l>
      <l>Pride wins not all, the glory he doth craue</l>
      <l>Some will not giue, the dead good words in graue</l>
      <l>Howe should the quicke, then get bad worlds goodwill</l>
      <l>When hollowe harts, but harbours hatred still.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>March on plaine booke, although thou passe the pikes</l>
      <l>Some marshall man, will saue a souldiers life</l>
      <l>Holde in thy head, from those that thee mislikes</l>
      <l>In skornefull daies, I knowe disdaine is riefe</l>
      <l>Thy gladsome verse, stirs vp more mirth then strife</l>
      <l>So Prince thou please, thine owne desire thou hast</l>
      <l>Come cleare from court, care not for enuies blast.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus Readers all, I bid you heere farewell</l>
      <l>And to the Prince, a simple tale I tell.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>