<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, GEORGE MARQVIS OF BVCKINGHAM, Viscount Villiers, Baron of Whaddon, Master of his Maiesties Horse, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of his Maiesties Bed∣chamber, and of his most honorable priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Cestren, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112905_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07801</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18179</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, GEORGE MARQVIS OF BVCKINGHAM, Viscount Villiers, Baron of Whaddon, Master of his Maiesties Horse, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of his Maiesties Bed∣chamber, and of his most honorable priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Cestren, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the innocencie of the three ceremonies of the Chvrch of England : viz. the surplice, crosse after baptisme, and kneeling at the receiuing of the blessed Sacrament. Diuided into two parts: in the former whereof the generall arguments vrged by the non-conformists; and, in the second part, their particular accusations, against these III. ceremonies seuerally, are answered, and refuted. Published by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 308 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, <hi>GEORGE</hi> MARQVIS OF BVCKINGHAM, Viscount <hi>Villiers,</hi> Baron of <hi>Whaddon,</hi> Master of his Maiesties <hi>Horse, Knight</hi> of the most noble Order of the <hi>Garter, Gentleman</hi> of his Maiesties <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber,</hi> and of his most honorable priuie Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY LO.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bene your happinesse, to haue had that highest <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> that can befall vnto the sons of men; I speake not now of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sci,</hi> but of <hi>Renasci,</hi> through <hi>Baptisme,</hi> in this our most Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe, and flourishing <hi>Church:</hi> which alas! now (by the same obligation, arising from the due respect of a <hi>child</hi> vnto the <hi>Mother)</hi> may seeme to require your Lordships aide and assistance, especially against two sorts of <hi>Aduersaries,</hi> by whom she is (although in a different degree) vnworthily and vniustly impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the one whereof are the <hi>Papists,</hi> and the other the <hi>Non-conformists.</hi> The <hi>Papists</hi> persecute her
<pb facs="3"/>
with all their engines of hate, as if she were an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Apostate: notwithstanding they themselues, (to instance but in two points) first, worship with diuine honor, as the person of the Son of <hi>God,</hi> that, which, in their opinion, may; but, in the iudgement of all other <hi>Churches,</hi> doth remaine still (according as Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, <hi>1200</hi> yeares since, in expresse words determined) <hi>in forme, figure, &amp; substāce,</hi> Bread. which necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inferreth an high degree, not only of a possible, but euē of an infallible <hi>Idolatry.</hi> And secōdly haue they, of late, added <hi>twelue</hi> new <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Beliefe</hi> vnto our Christian <hi>Creed,</hi> with an opinion of <hi>equal necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> which kind of <hi>addition</hi> vnto the Christian <hi>Faith</hi> doth proue them notoriously heretical, and liable vnto the <hi>Apostles</hi> curse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal. 1.8.</hi>
      </note> who pronounceth an <hi>Anathema</hi> vpon either man or <hi>Angell,</hi> that shall coine any new doctrine of that kind. Concern̄ing the <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formist.</hi> He, although he doth owe his spirituall birth vnto the <hi>Church,</hi> as wel as his natural vnto his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents;</hi> yet neuerthelesse doth he defame his <hi>Mothers</hi> religious worship; infringe her wholsome libertie; and contemne her iust authoritie: thereby occasioning that horrid <hi>Schisme,</hi> which is made by <hi>Separatists,</hi> the dissected Sects, and verie <hi>Acephalists</hi> of this present age. Against the <hi>Papists</hi> I haue had many conflicts. Now, in this Treatise, my purpose is
<pb facs="3"/>
principally to cōtend against the <hi>Non-conformists</hi>; which being finished, I thought my selfe bound to deuote the same vnto your Honour, in testimonie of my due acknowledgment, for your Lordshi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, sing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fauour, and respect towards me: and so much the rather haue I thus aduentured, because the Treatise it selfe was first occasioned by your Lordship. If therefore (Right Honorable) in that eminence of <hi>Fauour,</hi> which you haue in the eyes of our most gracious <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> you shall imitate his Maiesties admirable wisedome and zeale, in the aduancing of This, the true daughter of that <hi>primitiue</hi> Mother-<hi>Church,</hi> against whatsoeuer kind of Aduersaries; <hi>She</hi> shall make you twice-honorable, both in the eies of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> by blessing you with her prayers, wishing vnto you <hi>Good lucke with your Honor;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 45.5.</hi>
      </note> and happie <hi>prosperitie</hi> for preseruing of her <hi>Peace:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 12 2.6.</hi>
      </note> whereunto, according to my especiall dutie, I resound an answerable <hi>Eccho;</hi> beseeching God to <hi>prosper</hi> your Lordship, and to accomplish you, especially, with all his spirituall <hi>blessings, in heauenly things</hi>; and to preserue you to the glorie of his sauing <hi>Grace.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours, in all humble acknowledgement,</hi> Tho. Cestren.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>