<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right vvorship∣full, and his singuler good freend, Maister William Wrathe, Warden of the Worshipfull Company of the Mercers, W. Auerel wisheth health of body, happinesse of soule, and continuall prosperitie, both in this life, and in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Averell, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112712_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23344</idno>
           <idno type="STC">978</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right vvorship∣full, and his singuler good freend, Maister William Wrathe, Warden of the Worshipfull Company of the Mercers, W. Auerel wisheth health of body, happinesse of soule, and continuall prosperitie, both in this life, and in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Averell, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dyall for dainty darlings, rockt in the cradle of securitie : A glasse for all disobedient sonnes to looke in. A myrrour for vertuous maydes. A booke right excellent, garnished with many woorthy examples, and learned aucthorities, most needefull for this tyme present. Compiled by VV. Auerell, Student in Diuinitie, and Schoolemaister in London</title>
                 <author>Averell, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right vvorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and his singuler good freend, <hi>Maister</hi> William Wrathe, <hi>Warden</hi> of the Worshipfull Company of the Mercers, W. Auerel <hi>wisheth health of body, happinesse of</hi> soule, and continuall prosperitie, both in <hi>this life, and in the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing long tyme</hi> studied (well beloued Syr) which way I might shew the fr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ies of my good will, by gratifying your worship, with some signe of my affectionate heart, and hauing by opportunitie this booke ready finished, I could not tell on whome I might better bestowe it then on your worshippe, whose affabilitie, gentlenesse, courtesie, vertue, and other commendable giftes, I haue not onely heard with mine eares, but iudged by mine eyes, as hauing had experience thereof from the beginning of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, whome therefore I haue made the sole supporter of my labour, in bestowing this handfull of paper vppon you, knowing that you will courteously take it, thankfully accept it, and freendly defend it, being a matter vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, against all the scoffes, and girdes of the vicious, whose enuie and ignoraunce, so dimmeth the seate of theyr affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="3"/>
that being blinded with follie, they lothe wisedom, and euerie vertuous exercise, for which cause I studie not to please them, nor care not to content them, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that to please the wicked, is to displease the godlie.</p>
   <p>I haue rather selected you out as a patrone of my paynes, then any other, for that I hope you wyll more gratiouslie take them, then accustomablie the greater sort doo in these dayes, whose ingratitude is growne so great, that the studdies and toyles of menne, which in tymes paste were in great fauour regarded, and with lyberallytie rewarded, are nowe so coldly esteemed, and so vnthankefullie receyued, that the learned are nowe a dayes, rather bent to studdy for theyr owne gaine, then by writing, to procure the publique profyte of others.</p>
   <p>By meanes whereof, learning groweth in contempt, and men wexe colde in the studdie thereof, seeing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue lacketh her reward, and learning looseth a freendly countenaunce.</p>
   <p>Yet I knowe there are that fauour good letters with cheerefulnesse, take the giftes of the good Studentes, that both receyue theyr labours., and reward theyr ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and such are truelie vertuous, and duelie noble, how inferiour a calling soeuer they possesse, for vertue is true Gentillitie, and the onelie badge of renowmed Nobillitie, which dooth more nobillitate the name of a Gentleman, then treasure, and more aduaunce his fame, then ritches.</p>
   <p>Among whome I account your vvorshippe, hoping
<pb facs="3"/>
that you wyll with a good countenaunce accept my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes, and with freendlinesse esteeme my labours, which if you doo, then am I as fullie satisfied, as if I had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a greater benefite, accounting your good wyll my suffycient recompence, and your fauourable acceptation, a freendlie requitall: And thus committing you and yours to the gouernement of the Almighty, I ende, desiring God to blesse you in this lyfe with all happinesse, and in the lyfe to come, sende you perfect felicitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your poore freend and well willer. <hi>VV. A.</hi> Schoolemaister.</signed>
   </closer>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>