<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Testimonial]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112452_Fr1_3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17668</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112452</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Testimonial]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Remarkeable considerations upon the life, and services of Mounsieur Villeroy. Together with certaine politicall observations upon the fall of Seianus. Translated out of the originals by Sr. T.H</title>
                 <author>Matthieu, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Emerson (Emondson, Edmonds), Godfrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 79, 1, 2, 48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="testimonial">
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E who affords not honour to Mounsieur Villeroy,</hi> denyeth it to vertue: I was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the last was done him at Lyons in the Church of the Minims, and there heard his learned discourse, whom <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Great</hi> so much had lov'd and esteemed, who had beene for aboue foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen yeares the Chrysostome of the Court, and of whom Fraunce may more truly say, then Greece of Pericles, that the Temple of Perswasion was seated on his lips.</p>
   <p>And although hee forgat nothing, which appertained to the merit, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this occasion, yet cannot I thinke
<pb facs="4"/>though he well acquitted himselfe, that I stand disobliged from what I owe to the memory of this man.</p>
   <p>He reaped all that was exquisite, and excellent in this subject, I but gleane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, yet it is sufficient I let it appeare, that as to model the pourtrait of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury at Athens, they tooke the picture of Alcibiades, so perfectly to delineate a states-man, we must make use of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>