<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE FIRST OF THOSE   SEVEN BOOKES, WHICH WERE</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112613_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04680</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14809</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112613</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE FIRST OF THOSE   SEVEN BOOKES, WHICH WERE</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famovs and memorable vvorkes of Iosephvs, a man of mvch honour and learning among the Iewes. Faithfully translated out of the Latin, and French, by Tho. Lodge Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Josephus, Flavius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 554, 4, 555-812, 28 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="286"/>
   <pb n="555" facs="286"/>
   <head>THE FIRST OF THOSE <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> SEVEN BOOKES, WHICH WERE</head>
   <byline>WRITTEN BY FLAVIVS IOSEPHVS THE SONNE OF MATTHIAS, AS TOVCHING THE WARRE, AND DESTRVCTION OF THE IEWES.</byline>
   <div type="preface">
      <head>THE PRAEFACE, In which the Author taxeth diuers Historiographers of vntruth: and declareth his intent, and specifieth the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> points of this Historie.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as the warre which was enterprised betwixt the Iewes and Romans, hath (amongst all other) beene the greatest that either hath beene attempted in our age, or heard of in any other; either between citie or citie; or nation against nation: there haue beene some, who (rather building their discourse on the vaine and <note place="margin">The duty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher; and how things that are past should be written.</note> improbable report of others; then their owne iudgements) haue (according to the manner of orators) made a historie of their hearsay, and haue filled their discourses not only with vanitie, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> also with cōtradiction. Others there were (who for that they were eie witnesses or actors of the same) haue according to their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies preferred many lies; either to flatter the Romanes, or exercise their hatred against the Iewes: forging somewhiles accusations, otherwhiles breaking out into praises without any obseruation of <note place="margin">Ioseph himself had a hand in the warres of the Iewes.</note> historicall veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e. For this cause, I <hi>Ioseph</hi> the sonne of <hi>Matthias,</hi> by birth an Hebrew, and a citizen and priest of Ierusalem: who in the beginning of these wars bare armes against the Romanes, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (being therunto forced by necessitie) was present at all those things, which were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted and prosecuted in those warres; haue thought good to discourse in the Greeke tongue (in fauour of all those who acknowledge the soueraigntie of the Romane Empire) all that, which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my owne language I haue imparted to those Barbarians that inhabit the East. For at such <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> time (as I haue alreadie spoken) as these most bitter and busie warres tooke their beginning; the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans were at ciuill warres among themselues: and as touching the Iewes (who were in yeeres valiant, and in wits turbulent) they being both strong in power, and rich in money, did so insolent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuse the time, that being animated by the greatnes of those seditions and troubles; haue some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles swamme in hope, sometimes sweltered in feare of possessing or losing certaine soueraignties in the East. For the Iewes hope was, that all those of their nation (euen they who inhabited the parts beyond Euphrates) would haue both followed them in their rebellion, and seconded their follies with their forces. Moreouer at that time the Frenchmen (who bordered vpon the Romans) suffered them not to liue in peace: and the Germanes also began to take armes. Finally, after the death of <hi>Nero,</hi>
         <note place="margin">After Neros time all things full of trouble.</note> seditions raigned euery where: so that by reason of the oportunitie of these times many men went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to make themselues kings, and the souldiers whetted on with the couetous desire of gaine, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> nothing more then trouble and alteration. For which cause, I thinke it a matter both worthy reproofe, and ill beseeming my reputation, if in so waightie affaires, I should suffer the truth to be smothered in incertainties, and should permit the Parthians, Babylonians, and the furthest distant <note place="margin">Ioseph had written this history in the Hebrew toung before.</note> Arabians, and those of our nation inhabiting beyond Euphrates, togither with the Adiabenites, to obtain the true knowledge of those euents by mine industrie; whilest the Grecians, &amp; diuers of those, who haue not born armes with the Romans, being distracted with factions, &amp; deceiued by adulation,
<pb n="556" facs="287"/>
should be ignorant hereof. Yet some of these there be, who (notwithstanding their false informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> stick not to write histories, not only void of all truth, but also no waies answerable to their sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect which they vndertake. For whilest they labour to dignifie and extoll the Romans, they altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther suppresse the fame and fortunes of the Iewes: yet cannot I coniecture by what meanes they maie be held great, who triumph in the conquest of men so obscure and abiect. Nay whilest they thus extol <note place="margin">The glory of the Romans is diminished if you dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>rom their labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>s at the siege of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem.</note> the Romans valour in conquering the Iewes, they nothing at all respect the continuance of the wars, nor the multitude of the Roman souldiers, nor the honour of their captaines, whose titles are much embased if they (hauing laboured so much to conquer Ierusalem) should haue any thing derogated from the honour and prosperitie of their attempts. For mine owne part I am not resolued to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict those who shall enhance the glorie and noble actions of the Romans, neiher to extol and dignifie the deserts of mine owne nation, but my resolution is in all truth and sinceritie to set downe each oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current, without respect or partialitie towards either part. In performance whereof I will fashion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> my discourse according to the matter. I entreat of, and as my griefe and sorrow shall inuite me to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the miseries of my countrey: For the ciuill dissension that dismembred the same, was the cause that brought it to confusion, and those tyrants that raigned amongst vs, were such, who forcibly drew the Romans with sword and sire to seeke the desolation of our holy temple. The truth whereof <hi>Titus Caesar</hi> himselfe can iustifie, who destroied the same, and who during all those warres still pitied the <note place="margin">Titus his piety towards the Iewes.</note> people, for that they (as he well perceiued) were kept in awe by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>he seditious: And who oftentimes of his owne accord deferred the surprisall of the Citie, purposely protracting the siege, to the intent that in the meane time the authors of the sedition and bloudie wars might haue leasure to repent and submit themselues. Now if any man thinke that I write this, as one that exclaimeth against the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and their the eueries, or that in bewailing the miseries of my lost countrey, I accuse their villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <note place="margin">All calamities that hapned sithence the beginning of the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared with those the Iewes suffered are of no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and thereby transgresse the limits of a historie, let it be imputed to my griefe and so pardoned. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> For amongst all the Cities that were euer gouerned by the Romans, our Citie onely attained to the top of felicitie, which now alas is brought into extreame miserie, captiuitie, and desolation. Nay if all the misfortunes &amp; calamities which the world from the beginning hath seene, be compared with the infelicitie and fall of the Iewes, they are slight and of no moment.</p>
      <p>And to increase our sorrow, no forrainers but our owne familiar friends and countrimen haue been the actors of our tragedie. This considered, if any man of too seuere and stoicall iudgement shall reprehend this my lamentation, let such a one attribute the deeds I recount, to the historie which I write; and reserue the lamentations and sorrowes therof to me, who am the historiographer: although in my mind I may iustly challenge the smoothe tounged Grecians, for that (notwithstanding these our so miserable, and so memorable warres hapned in their daies, in respect wherof all other former trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <note place="margin">The Grecian Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe the wars of the Iewes with silence.</note>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> were obscure and of no reckoning) they haue restrained their tongues &amp; pens; and vndertaken an ouercurious silence, to the end they might carpe at those with greater libertie, who vndertake the publishing thereof: whom though in learning and eloquence they both exceede and outstrip, yet are they inferiour vnto them in the matter and subiect they intreat of. For they forsooth discipher and set downe the valiant acts of the Assyrians and Medes, as who should say the ancient writers had but coldly and scarce conceitfully handled the same: and yet God knoweth they come so far behinde those auncient authors in their writings, as they neither second them in sense, nor equall them in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. For such as in times past published any worthy historie, endeuoured to write that which they themselues had seene: and for that each of them were eie witnesses of those affaires they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to writing, they more effectually performed all that which they promised; the rather for that they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> accounted it to be an act of dishonestie, to report and publish lies in steed of a historie. And truely in my opinion that man is both worthy commendation and praise, who striueth by his studious inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, to register not onely the occurrences of times past, but also those memorable euents that haue hapned in his daies: and he only and truely is to be accounted industrious, not that altereth and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at his pleasure an other mans works, but he that of himselfe compileth a historie; wherof no man hath before time written. For mine owne part (the rather for that I am a stranger) I haue beene inforced to my no small labour and expence, to refresh the memorie and truth of these euents in the <note place="margin">Who may rightly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher.</note> eares of the Greeks and Romans. For as touching their owne learned men, their mouthes are alwaies open to gaines and controuersies, and to this purpose their tongues still run on pattens: marie if they come to a historie wherein they should both tell truth, and with great labour enquire of those things that are past, here are they mum, the trauell is too tedious, the bit is in their teeth, so that they leaue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> the matter to their performance, who are incapable and vnapt both in stile and studie, to register the noble actions of royall princes.</p>
      <p>Since therefore the Grecians make no account of the truth of historie, it behooueth vs both to esteeme and honour it. Now to discouer vnto you the originall of the Iewes, what their estate hath been in times past, and after what manner they departed out of Aegypt, to shew what countries the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and what colonies they planted, were in my iudgment both impertinent and to little purpose; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering
<pb n="557" facs="287"/>
that diuers of mine own nation haue before my time made and written an exact historie of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> noble attempts of our auncestors: yea many Greeks also haue translated these mens writings into their owne tongue; and haue as truly, as rhetorically exemplified the same. I will therfore begin my historie in that time where these writers and our owne prophets ceased, and set downe at large all those warres that hapned in my time: and as for those things that exceede my knowledge and remembrance, I will onely touch them bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ly, and in a word or two; First how <hi>Antiochus</hi> surnamed <hi>Epiphanes,</hi> tooke the Citie of Ierusalem, and possessed the same for the space of three yeeres, and six moneths: and finally how <note place="margin">Antiochus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanes the first author &amp; fountaine of the warres of the Iewes.</note> he was dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>en out of that countrey by the Asmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>eans. After this I will set downe the dissensions that hapned amongst <hi>Antiochus</hi> successors for the kingdome; and how by this meanes they drew <hi>Pompey</hi> and the Romans into the managing and medling with their affaires. How <hi>Herod</hi> likewise the sonne of <hi>Antipater,</hi> being assisted by <hi>Sosius,</hi> vtterly ouerthrew and canceld their felicitie &amp; authoritie: and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> how in <hi>Augustus Caesars</hi> time and after the death of <hi>Herod,</hi> and during the gouernment of <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Varo,</hi> a sedition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s raised among the people: and how in the tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> yeere of <hi>Neros</hi> raigne the warre began to take head and continuance. That likewise which happened in <hi>Cestius</hi> time, and what <note place="margin">The Epirom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> of the warre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> of the Iewes.</note> warlike executions the Iewes performed in their first attempts and reuolts, how they strengthened the Cities and forts about them, and how <hi>Nero</hi> (hearing of the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>er throw which his army receiued vnder <hi>Cestius</hi> their Generall, and fearing least he should lose all) made <hi>Titus Vespasian</hi> the Generall of his army: who being attended by his eldest sonne, came into Iudaea accompanied with as great a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Romans as he could possibly gather: what number of their allies inuaded &amp; spoiled Galilee, what Cities they surprised in that place, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r by forcible assault, or by any other composition. Besides all these things, I will expresse what order and discipline the Romans obserue in their wars, and wherein they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> are accustomed to exercise their souldiers. I will note downe also the places and nature of the countrey of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ee, and the description of Iudaea, togither with the mountaines, lakes and fountains thereof, with all the properties of the same; not forgetting those miseries which the captiue Cities suffered: neither how they were surprised. All which (togither with all those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ils and miseries which during those troubles befell me) will I discouer, and discourse with all truth and diligence; the rather in that I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish them in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r eares, who are no waies ignorant of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>m. After this I will set downe how (vpon the decli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>g and downfall of the Iewes). <hi>Nero</hi> died; and how (at such time as <hi>Vespasian</hi> had vndertaken the expedition to Ierusalem) he was withheld from the action, to receiue and enioy the imperial digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: How at that instant when he retired himselfe into Aegypt to establish that estate, the Iewes began to mutinie among themselues: how many tyrants arose amongst them, who hatched much ciuil discord and <note place="margin">The signes and changes after Neroes death.</note> debate in their gouernment. Againe, how <hi>Titus</hi> departing out of Aegypt, came the second time into <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Iudaea, and ranged ouer the countrey, and how and where he leuied and encamped his armies. How and how oftentimes the city hath been vexed by sedition, especially at such time as he himselfe was present. What onsets he gaue, &amp; how many mounts he raised in begirting the city with a treble walithe strength <note place="margin">Titus besie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Ierusalem</note> and prouision of the Citie, the scituation and platforme of the Temple, and the altars therein: the rites and ceremonies which were vsed vpon festiuall daies: the 7. purifications and offices of the priests: the garments also of the high priest; and the holy sanctuary of the temple. All which I wil recount with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any dissimulation, or swaruing from the truth of historie. After this I will relate what cruelty the <note place="margin">The manners and sacrifices of the Iewes.</note> tyrants vsed against their own countrimen, &amp; what humanitie the Romans shewed towards strangers, and how oftentimes <hi>Titus</hi> (who desired the safetie both of the Citie and Temple) prouoked and inuited the seditious to mutual amitie. Furthermore I wil report how the people of the Iewes (after these many <note place="margin">The humanity of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> Romans towards the Iewes.</note>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> and grieuous wounds which they both suffered and suncke vnder, sometimes by warre, otherwhiles by sedition, and many times by hunger) were at length ouerthrowne to their vtter confusion. Neither wil I omit the slaughter of such as reuolted, neither the punishment inflicted on those that were captiue: but I will set downe how the temple was burned against <hi>Caesars</hi> will, and what an infinit masse of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred treasure was deuoured by the fire. But to shut vp the historie, I will annex the surprisall of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <note place="margin">The burning of the temple, and the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the citie. The Romans triumph ouer the Iewes. The cause why he wrote this historie.</note> and what signes and wonders hapned before the same: the captiuitie also of the tyrants themsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>es, and the number of those that were led away into captiuitie: and what miserie euerie one of them end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how the Romans continuing their wars vtterly raced the fortresses of their captiues: finally, how <hi>Titus</hi> in trauailing thorow the whole countrey, established a for me of gouernment therein; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward returning into Italy, triumphed with much honour. All these things haue I comprehended in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> bookes: indeuouring as much as in me lieth; to flie and auoide all occasion of reproofe and reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from those men; who knew these affaires and were actors in the warres. All which I haue done for their sakes, who rather affect truth, then follow their pleasure: and according to that order and for me I haue proposed, I will begin and prosecute my stile and Historie.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>