<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable, CHARLES, Lord Ho∣ward, Baron of Effingham, Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, Lorde high Admirall of England, and one of her Ma∣iesties most Honourable priuie Counsaile: Thomas Hickock, wisheth long life in good health, with much en∣crease of Honour, and all happy successe.</title>
           <author>Hickock, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112444_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00611</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10746</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable, CHARLES, Lord Ho∣ward, Baron of Effingham, Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, Lorde high Admirall of England, and one of her Ma∣iesties most Honourable priuie Counsaile: Thomas Hickock, wisheth long life in good health, with much en∣crease of Honour, and all happy successe.</title>
                 <author>Hickock, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The voyage and trauaile : of M. Cæsar Frederick, merchant of Venice, into the East India, the Indies, and beyond the Indies. Wherein are contained very pleasant and rare matters, with the customes and rites of those countries. Also, heerein are discovered the merchandises and commodities of those countreyes, aswell the aboundaunce of goulde and siluer, as spices, drugges, pearles, and other iewelles. Written at sea in the Hercvles of London: comming from Turkie, the 25. of March 1588. For the profitable instruction of merchants and all other trauellers, for their better direction and knowledge of those countreyes. Out of Italian, by T H</title>
                 <author>Federici, Cesare</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 41 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, CHARLES, Lord</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Baron of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight <hi>of the most Noble order of the Garter,</hi> Lorde high Admirall of England, and one of her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most Honourable priuie Counsaile:</hi> Thomas Hickock, wisheth long life in good health, with much <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of Honour, and all happy</hi> successe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing (Right Honourable) long time purposed, to put somewhat in practize that I might present to your honourable viewe, the weaknesse of my abilitie hath hitherto holden mee in doubt, whither I were best, by writing to shew my good wil, or by stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my penne to conceale the same. But being at Sea in March last in the Hercules of London, I resolued to take in hand the translating of this little worke out of Italian into Englishe, aswell in regarde of the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse therof, being neuer printed before that time: as also for the rarenesse of the subiect and matter it trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth off, and the commoditie thar Merchants and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Cuntrimen may reape by it. And hauing fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the same, presuming more vpon your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble curtesie, then vpon the worthinesse of so small a woorke, and hoping of your honourable fauour for
<pb facs="3"/>
the defence therof, I am bolde in all humble and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sort to present the same to your honourable viewe and protection, not as a thing worthy the patronage of so honorable a personage as your honour is, but as a token of my dutifull affection and bounden duty to your Lordship: beseechiug you therfore to vouchsafe of the same with so good a will as I present it vnto you. And so most humbly I take my leaue, beseeching the almightie to blesse and prosper you in all your honourable enterprises, to the good liking of her Maiesty, and profite of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most humble and ready at commaund, Thomas Hickock.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>