<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface conteyning the occasions of the Conference.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112583_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24726.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112583</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface conteyning the occasions of the Conference.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Actes of conference in religion, holden at Paris, betweene two papist doctours of Sorbone, and two godlie ministers of the Church. Dravven out of French into English, by Geffraie Fenton</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 <distributor>Norton, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 120 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A Preface conteyning the occasions of the Conference.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Icause many desire to bée directly satisfied touching a common brute spredde of the conference appoynted at the Duke of <hi>Montpensiers,</hi> betwéene two Doctors of <hi>Sorbone,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sorbonae a College of Papists in Paris.</note> and two Ministers of the Church: whereof some settle and yéelde to ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reportes, and some beléeue and iudge according to their proper fansies, I haue thought good (as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to satisfie the one, as to take from the others all occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of hastie incredulitie,) to draw into writing the whole discourse, as it passed, togither with the cause and first moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the disputation.</p>
   <p>The Duke of <hi>Montpensier,</hi> who (as the world knoweth) is zelouse in his Religion, and of great loue to his children, seeing the Duchesse of <hi>Buyllon</hi> his daughter happely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen from the Romish opinion, to bée henceforwarde a blessed member of Iesus Christe, and that with suche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie and confirmation in the knowledge and feare of God, zeale, holynesse, with all other holesome vertues, that neither by priuate persuasions, nor other publike meanes, he coulde stoppe the course of Gods grace working in hir, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined at laste to apply a laste remedie, as thinking to allure hir with the learning and eloquence of doctor <hi>Vigor,</hi> a man of deare reckening with him: wherein for the better satisfaction of the Lady, after he had imparted his intente with the Duke hir husbande, it was agreed that the persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions should be ministred to hir in the presence of certayne Ministers, as <hi>Spina,</hi> with other suche as he woulde call vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: with libertie to alleage what they coulde against the doctrine of <hi>Vigor,</hi> vnder this condition, that if after the Conference they were not consuted and wholly vanquished by him, his daughter shoulde remayne quiet in hir opinion, without further attempts to draw hir from it. Herevnto the Duke of <hi>Buyllon</hi> did not vnwillingly condiscende, and for a better proofe of his readinesse in the cause, he imparted the
<pb facs="4"/>
whole businesse with the Admirall, by whose aduise with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (assisting the procéeding) <hi>Spina</hi> was immediatly sente for, who at his comming tolde the Lordes that (the qualitie and humor of his aduersarie considred) he hoped for no great frute in this conference, as beeing far more parciall for the Pope and his traditions, than of any zeale at all to the word and truth of Iesus Chryst: which albeit was affirmed by all the assistants, yet it was agréed that he should vndertake the conference, &amp; that for two considerations, the one to instruct and strengthen the good duchesse agaynst the sophistries &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillations of <hi>Vigor:</hi> the other to take from him al occasions to brag (as he is wont to doo) that the Ministers durst not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him. Here the order &amp; methode to procede in this businesse, was agreed vpon, with licence to <hi>Spyna</hi> to require the authoritie and sufferance of the King, that (to auoyde confusion) it might passe in a small presence: that a certayne Theame and subiecte might be proponed to conferre vpon: And lastely, that there might be established two Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for all the Actes, and two others deputed to gather faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully all the Reasons and arguments of either parte.</p>
   <p>All whiche orders béeing orderly communicated to the Duke of <hi>Buyllon,</hi> by the L. Admirall and <hi>Spina,</hi> he iudged them of suche reason as not to be denied, warning <hi>Spina</hi> to prepare him selfe agaynst the firste of Iuly, when the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence should begin in the after noone. <hi>Spina</hi> intreated <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Barbasta,</hi> minister to the quéene of <hi>Nauar</hi> to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him in this disputation, who at the day and houre afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, conducted by thrée Gentlemen appoynted by the duke of <hi>Buyllon,</hi> went to the L. of <hi>Montpensiers</hi> house, where the duke of <hi>Buyllon</hi> (aduertised belike of their comming) mette thē in the hal: and there (induced as it séemed by the doctors who were in the chamber frō whence he came) asked <hi>Spina</hi> if (afore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning of the conference) he were determined to make his prayers, according to the custom of the reformed churches: He answered yea, and that neither he nor his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, either might, or ought to set vpon a matter of suche importance, as to treate vpon the mysteries of Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb facs="5"/>
afore they prepared them selues thervnto by inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the name of God. With which answere he returned eftsones into the Chamber of the Doctors, who after some priuate counsell amongest them selues, appoynted Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> to tell them, that for their parts they would not assiste their prayers, and that there was no more reason for them to be present when they prayed, than for the ministers to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare their Masse. The ministers answered, that in good conscience they could not beginne to dispute, afore they had prayed to God, and for the Doctors they had libertie, either to assiste or be absent from their prayers at their pleasure: but touching them selues, they were content to make their prayers in the place where the assembly and conference shoulde bee, onely they sayde there was greate difference betweene their prayers (which haue conformitie with the pure worde of God, as they them selues confesse,) and the matter of their Masse, which conteynes many things quite contrary, as is easely seene and iudged by suche as will exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it by the rule of the Scripture, and therfore (by reason of the impietie and idolatrie in their Masse) as they can not any way communicate therewith without offence to God, and bring them selues guyltie afore him: so yet, neither he nor the other Doctors his companions, stoode barde from the societie of their prayers by that difficultie, bicause there was neither poynt nor article, which (by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession) was not holly and consonant to God. Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> replied, that they rested vpon a small matter: but they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered him, that as the principall exercise of Christian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion stoode vppon prayer, so it was also the moste necessarie meane to obtayne Gods grace, without the which mortall men coulde not attayne to any successe in their doings, and therefore very dangerous to omitte it: they tolde him also, that they marueled on his behalfe, that professing the name of a Doctor and a Deuine, he made such a negligent estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of prayer, which is the true practise, fruite, and vse of all the knowledge touching God and his worde, like as by this the worlde might discerne, what was the nature of their
<pb facs="5"/>
iudgementes, who measured diuinitie by idle and vayne spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations. He answered that the Duke of <hi>Montpensier</hi> would neuer suffer such a brauerie in his house, and muche lesse that it should be sayde, that it was a place for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters to make their prayers in. The ministers protested to be farre from their profession to braue it, and that muche lesse they would vse any brauerie towards Princes (whom they honored with all feare and obedience) but that they would condemne themselues if they vsed it to any man, of what meane condition soeuer he were: wherwith they assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, that aswell he as others, which layde such slaunders vpon them afore Princes, to kindle &amp; enflame them against them, shoulde one day giue reason of their doings afore the maiestie of God. Here Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> asked them why they stoode so resolutely vpon this poynt of prayer: they answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the purpose of the Conference, was to reueale the true sense of the Scripture, and deliuer it to the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Bearers, which coulde not be done without the spirite of God, who cleareth the vnderstanding of men to comprehende it, and openeth their mouthes to pronounce it, in which respecte they are to implore and obteyne Gods grace by prayers: besides, God hath commaunded all suche as haue neede of wisedome, to demaunde it of him, to searche what they would finde, &amp; to knocke at the gate if they would haue it opened to them: all which beeing not otherwise to be obteyned than by prayers, they concluded, that for that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion their inuocation was necessarie. They alleaged more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that all things ought to be referred to the glory of god, and therefore prayer to be requisite in the beginning, and thankesgiuing in the ende, and consummation of all our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors, euen as when wee begin and ende the ordinary refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our bodies, wee blesse and glorifie the name of God.</p>
   <p>Here Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> tolde them that they should not haue any let to pray, so that they prayed in their hartes: but they answered, that that suffised not, but that they muste aswell exercise their mouth, as <hi>S. Paule</hi> commaundes. Then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw you apart (sayth he) and make your prayers al alone:
<pb facs="6"/>
they tolde him that was also inconuenient in suche a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, as béeing commaunded by God to make their lighte shine afore men, to the ende, that seeing their good works, they might haue meane to glorifie God, and be edified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: besides, by this they might procure cause of slaunder to their neighbours, as to confirme the lewde opinion raysed by their aduersaries touching their doctrine and exercises, which is, that in respecte of the errours and blasphemies, they dursie not publish it: and therefore the better to purge this reproche, they thought it moste conuenient, that as they were to speake publikely, so also their prayers might not be kepte from the hearers. Lastly they sayde, in reason and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie they ought not to be denied there the authoritie which the king had agreed vnto them in the conference at <hi>Poyssy,</hi> where in all the seuerall assemblies it was lawefull for them to make publike prayer to God, afore they entered any spéeche of disputation. They added for their laste reason, that it was néedefull to comprehende within their prayers, bothe they &amp; al such as should assiste the conference, to the ende that by the helpe of Gods grace, aswel they as others might be made cleane from all passions, as béeing hindered with nothing to iudge rightly of suche matters as shall fall in question of the one and other side, leauing by that meanes a facilitie to the hearers the better to make their profite. I am ashamed to recite in this place a worde which escaped from doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> in this talke, who in a disdayne to God and his seruice, sayde, that if the ministers wold go pray, he wold go pisse the while: the same seeming so impudente to the ministers, that they cried, what resolution, what counsell, yea what one good worde to bee hoped for in a heart filled with suche apparant, disdayne of God?</p>
   <p>The Duke of <hi>Buyllon,</hi> and the sayde Doctor <hi>Ruze,</hi> sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the constancie of the Ministers not to enter Conference, onlesse they prayed publikely in the presence of the assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, after they had imparted the same with the lord of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensier,</hi> and the other doctors that were with him, they deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to sende them away, as not meaning to dispute with-them
<pb facs="6"/>
vnder suche condition.</p>
   <p>Whereupon the Ministers departed, &amp; being called backe againe before they were at our Ladies bridge, they returned with expectation of cōsent to their request, wherin notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they were deceiued. For Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> meeting them at the gate, tolde them for a finall Resolution, that if they wold pray, they shoulde haue a house appoynted for that purpose: only the Lord of <hi>Montpensier</hi> wold not suffer them to make his house their place of Prayer, nor that any of his houshold partake with their Prayers: whereunto the Ministers An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, that in this, their request was rather restrained than satisfied, and therefore they coulde Answere them no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes than afore.</p>
   <p>Héere Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> ministred particular spéeche to <hi>Spyna,</hi> to whom in scoffing manner, he told, that he saw two causes why he was of so hard a desire to be drawn into disputation, and that héeretofore he had bene of their secte and companie, but now he was cut of. <hi>Spyna</hi> Answered, that if he had ment to eschue the conference, he wold not haue taken the trauaile of .viij. leagues in so great distemper of heat, and muche lesse left his Churche, more deare to him than any other thing, to come to them in their owne houses. Touching his departing from their societie, he estéemed it one of the greatest benefits that euer happened to him, for the which he had cause to yeld continual thankes to God. And bicause neither he nor his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship should dout indirectly of his readinesse to dispute, he laide afore him a meane by which bothe parties might be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, as to trauerse the disputation by writing, the same be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moste conuenient, to intercepte all contentions: that the Arguments and Answers may be the better handled and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand: that the people shuld be the better edified: And last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that in this manner there was no daunger of alterations, either by additions or detractions: <hi>Ruze</hi> Answered that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be wrytten, which hath not earst bene wrytten: euen so sayth <hi>Spyna</hi> we can pronounce nothing, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore hath not bene spoken.</p>
   <p>This was the Resolute end of all their spéeches, by which
<pb facs="7"/>
may be gathered the will and disposition of the doctors to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the conference with the Ministers: to whome euen in the beginning, to preuent their further procéeding, they offered a condition which they knewe would not be accepted, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a publike conference of the scripture, and yet barde to pray publikely in the place and assistance where they shuld dispute. Besides, their intente is easily iudged by the order they established touching the conference: For in place to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide conueniently for the ease and quiette of the Ministers, come with no smal paines to them, they had procured at least a hundred persons of all qualities to enuiron the saide Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and so to amaze them, either with inreuerente scoffes, violent iniuries, or inciuile threates, that had not the three Gentlemen of the Duke of <hi>Buyllon,</hi> kept a precise care ouer them, they had bene in daunger of violent hurt. By their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings also may be discerned their regarde of duetie to God and holy Prayer, seeing they could not admit Prayer in their presence. And lastly, what vnderstanding can they haue of the scripture, with what Faith can they handle Gods Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yea with what integritie and facultie can they preach and pronounce, seeing they disdaine in their presence Prayer to God to obtaine all things, as though theyr sufficiencie were in aide of them selues, and not to proceede from God the Author of all lighte?</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>