<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112749_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07603</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17995</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mohammedis imposturæ: that is, A discouery of the manifold forgeries, falshoods, and horrible impieties of the blasphemous seducer Mohammed : with a demonstration of the insufficiencie of his law, contained in the cursed Alkoran; deliuered in a conference had betweene two Mohametans, in their returne from Mecha. Written long since in Arabicke, and now done into English by William Bedwell. Whereunto is annexed the Arabian trudgman, interpreting certaine Arabicke termes vsed by historians: together with an index of the chapters of the Alkoran, for the vnderstanding o the confutations of that booke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Linguistics and philology</term>
                    <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="40"/>
   <pb facs="40"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>IN the reading of the Orientall histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries I finde two things oft times to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble euen those that would seeme to bee great schollers; to wit, the Names of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, dignity, office, &amp;c. and the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles or inscriptions of the Chapters of the Alkoran. For these both being for the most part called and cited as they are termed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Turks and Arabians, are not easily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of any, but such as are skilfull of that language. How oft, I pray you, in the histories and writers of their affairs, &amp; in what page almost shal you not meet with some exoticke and strange terme or other, as Mussleman, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kade, Hakkim, Alfaqui, Azoara, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hers like? And what one amongst many hundreds is there that doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what is meant by them? For the better vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therefore not onely of this present Treatise of ours, but generally of all histories of the Saracens, Persians, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Turks, &amp; Africans: as also of all bookes and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises written of their superstition and ceremonies, I haue, for thy good, gentle Reader, in the midst of my many and great troubles, procured by the fraudulent practises of the wicked, according to my best ability, and small helpe that I haue, out of those kinde of writings gathered and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed these two Treatises ensuing; The one containing a
<pb facs="41"/>
Catalogue of all such Arabicke termes and words vsed by historians: The other an Index of the Chapters of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koran. But some man may say, That in those histories there are many other strange words found that here I haue not mentioned; I answer, it is true. But those being for the most part Turkish or Persian, that is, barbarous and out of the compasse of my skill, I leaue them to be handled by others. Againe, if any man shall finde that we haue omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diuerse, euen of this nature here by vs nominated, let him know, that we could not seriously reade ouer all books of that argument; onely wee did for this purpose but lightly cast our eye ouer some of the principallest, and such as we could haue the vse of at this time. Our studies at this time are imployed otherwise. If any thing be wanting I doubt not but ere long we shall supply it abundantly, and I hope, to the satisfacton of all. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>