<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The translatour to the reader, Good and gentle reader,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1535</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112620_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07430</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17817</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The translatour to the reader, Good and gentle reader,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of peace: lately translated out of laten in to englysshe. with the kynges moste gracyous priuilege</title>
                 <author>Marsilius, of Padua</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marshall, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1535</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 21, 23-1340, that is 140, 2 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The translatour to the reader, Good and gentle reader,</head>
   <p>There hast thou the boke intytled in latyne, Defensori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pacis, in englysshe the defence tuicyon or maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of peace, vndoubtedly full worthy so to be called, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge selfe in the vse therof shall full well and manyfestly declare and shewe. Aboue two hondred yeres passed, there was a varyaunce, stry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, and controuersy, betwyxte the proude bysshoppes of Rome, that <note place="margin">Ihon̄ y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>. xxii. Benedicte the xii. Clement the. vi.</note> then were, &amp; the most gentle prynce &amp; Emperour Lewes of Bauary. The bysshoppes of Rome (as auncyent hystoryes do make mēcyon) were cōmenly, &amp; for the more parte, before that tyme, yea &amp; euer syns haue ben, stoute &amp; stubbourne, proude &amp; presumptuous vsurpers, &amp; murtherers, traytours &amp; rebellyons, (cōtrary to theyr allegyaunces) not onely agaynst theyr owne naturall soueraygnes lordes, prync{is}, kyng{is}, &amp; Emperours, but also agaynst all other prynces, &amp; peraduen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture not without the aydes, consent{is}, mocyons, &amp; coūsaylles, of other foreyn &amp; straunge bysshoppes. Nowe because this good Emperour Lewes moued no lesse with pyte towardes his louyng subiect{is}, then with a true loue &amp; zele towardes the worde of god, &amp; his moste godly honour, wolde not permyt &amp; suffre the sayd bysshops of Rome to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sume, wast, &amp; deuoure (after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> accustomed maner of theyr wycked &amp; vngracyous predecessours) therfore (I saye) arose betwyxte the sayd Emperoure and the sayd bysshops a greuous &amp; an intollerable tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy. For in the defence of the moste iuste cause of whose imperyall maiesty, it lyked the noble and vertuous clerke Marsilius of Pad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, to compyle and endyte this same defence of peace. Nowe as touchynge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> translacyon of Marsilius out of laten, &amp; in teachynge hym to speake englysshe, beynge an Italyan, whether it be done so well as it myght or shulde haue ben / I woll not saye, but I hertely pray the gentle reader, to take it in good parte, and to correcte and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende it where nede is. To dysprayse the doyng of it, I iugde it no hygh poynt of learnynge. And to translate it but meanely, I thynke it some learnynge. This dare I be bolde to say, that from the iniust and lyenge carpours, and pryuy detractours, there cōmeth nothyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in to lyght, neyther by preachyng, ne yet by wrytyng, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sauoureth or hath any taste of vertue or learnynge, I wolde gladly that suche whysperers and blowers in mēnes eares, wolde preache, wryte and sette forth sermons, and bokes of vertue and good learnynge and in the same (aswell without makynge of fayned and vntrue escuses) as
<pb facs="3"/>
without theyr olde accustomed crafty iugglynges truly declare and publysshe the worde of god &amp; shewe themselues, to be suche in theyr hertes (as of ryght, and duety, by the worde of god) they shulde euer haue ben, &amp; as with theyr mouthes, by theyr wrytinges, and by theyr Seales, they haue professed, and sworne / &amp; not (as the olde prouerbe is) to goldsmythes of theyr owne occupacyons, iniustly, falsely, and secretly, in corners to slaunder and bely men. Nowe good gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I do aduyse and counceyll the, to do, as I woll my self, that is to say, in nothynge to beleue theym, what soeuer they say, before suche tyme &amp; vntyll they haue done as aboue is sayd, &amp; also vntyl they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue openly and suffycyently improued and confuted vs. But to make fewe wordes, I woll promyse and assure the of one thyng (good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) and admonysshe and warne the of another, and so fare well. In this boke I dare saye, thou shalte fynde wherwith to make iuste and inuynsyble answeres, yea &amp; wherwith vtterly to confute all and euery the obieccyons, fantastycall argumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, reasons, &amp; perswasyons, that by the papysty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call sorte can be made, for the settynge forthe, and extollynge of the vsurped power &amp; auctoryte of the bysshop of Rome, ben they neuer so false, crafty, &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyle. And of this I do warne the, that in the translacyon of this boke dyuerse thynges ben omyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and lefte out, as maters, not so moche profytable, as longe and tedyous, as in the laten boke at lar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge more pleynly apperyth / the resydue I cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte to thyne owne dylygence, whiche in readyng this boke may in nowyse lacke. And thus farewell, &amp; pray for the lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge lyue &amp; prosperous preseruacyon of our most gracyous souerayg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne lorde kynge Henry y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eyght, of his most vertuous Lady quene Anne, and of the Lady prynces Elyzabeth doughter and heyre to theym bothe.</p>
   <trailer>¶ Thus endyth the preface of the translator to the reader.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>