<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, THOMAS, LORD ELLES∣MERE, LORD CHAVNCELOVR OF ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>Rollenson, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112081_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10994</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21264</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, THOMAS, LORD ELLES∣MERE, LORD CHAVNCELOVR OF ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>Rollenson, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons preached before his Maiestie : 1. The bridegromes banquet. 2. The triumph of constancie. 3. The banishment of dogges. By Francis Rollenson, Batcheler of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Rollenson, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 79, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, THOMAS, LORD ELLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERE, LORD CHAVNCELOVR OF ENGLAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Printing</hi> of Sermons, if both be done for the glory of God, and the good of his Church, are like the <hi>Two siluer Trumpets</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> excellent <hi>instruments</hi> to call men to <hi>Christ,</hi> but if in <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Preaching, Diuines</hi> seeke their owne glory, and thirst after popular applause, then they be but <hi>Trumpets</hi> of <hi>Rams-hornes,</hi> whose sound leuels not the walles of <hi>Iericho,</hi> but <hi>Hierusalem</hi> with the ground: I dare not auowe that these my <hi>labours, Preached</hi> and <hi>Printed,</hi> be <hi>Trumpets</hi> of <hi>Siluer,</hi> for then should I paralele the <hi>proud Pharasie</hi> in iustifying my selfe; neither will I acknowledge them to be of <hi>horne,</hi> for so should I wilfully brand mine owne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with <hi>shame,</hi> and carie <hi>Caines marke</hi> euer vpon me; let the <hi>censure</hi> be referred to him, who is the searcher of the reines, and whose <hi>all-seeing</hi> eie hath ouer-lookt the ayme and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my heart, vpon which this <hi>Nil vltrà</hi> is grauen; <hi>Deo &amp; Ecclesiae; For God and his Church; This God</hi> by <hi>One starre</hi> conducted the <hi>wise men</hi> from the <hi>East,</hi> when they came to worship the <hi>starre</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and offer their <hi>Gold, Incense,</hi> and <hi>Myrrhe</hi> to our <hi>King, Priest,</hi> and <hi>Prophet Christ:</hi> but he hath directed me to your <hi>Lordships</hi> presence by <hi>Two starres fixt</hi> by his gracious goodnesse in the <hi>firmament</hi> of your noble <hi>heart, Vertue</hi> and <hi>Honour;</hi> there to make an oblation, not of <hi>Myrrhe, Incense,</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> but of <hi>one slender talent,</hi> and <hi>Two poore Mites, Three worthlesse Sermons,</hi> preached as
<pb facs="3"/>
once our <hi>Sauiour</hi> did in a <hi>Ship royall,</hi> but written out for the presse, as <hi>Ionah</hi> praied in the <hi>Whales belly;</hi> I know that the <hi>Magi</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> doe daily cast out of their aboundance, <hi>Rich</hi> offerings into your <hi>Treasurie,</hi> to whose writings I may iustly apply that of the Poet, and call them
<q>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</q>
The <hi>Garden</hi> and <hi>Table</hi> of <hi>Alcinous,</hi> so well fraught and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht they be with <hi>Knowledge, Iudgement, Wit,</hi> and <hi>Elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie;</hi> but the poore <hi>Widow</hi> must do as she may, not as she would: They that cannot bring <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Pearles</hi> to the building of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> must present a <hi>Rams-skin</hi> and <hi>Goates-haire; All</hi> the <hi>Patriarches</hi> wore not <hi>Party-coloured Coates;</hi> and all the <hi>Seruants</hi> had not <hi>fiue Talents;</hi> They then that haue but one <hi>Talent</hi> in their <hi>Purse,</hi> and one <hi>Coate</hi> to their backe, must measure their actions by their ability, euen as <hi>God himselfe</hi> by <hi>ballance</hi> doth distribute his <hi>Graces; Yet many things in themselues of no moment, are highly priced, because of their dedication to the Temples</hi> (saith <hi>Plinie.</hi>) The <hi>two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles being</hi> but of <hi>stone,</hi> were reuerently regarded, because in them the <hi>finger</hi> of God writ the <hi>Law;</hi> nay, the very <hi>Besomes</hi> and <hi>Ash-pannes</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> were much esteemed, because they were instruments in the Lords house; so I hope these my <hi>Endeuours</hi> shall purchase the better <hi>Respect</hi> in the opinion of the <hi>Readers,</hi> for that they were, and are <hi>dedicated</hi> to the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout eare</hi> of his <hi>Sacred Maiestie, the inuincible defender of the faith,</hi> and to the <hi>Iudicious eie</hi> of your <hi>honourable selfe,</hi> being a bountifull <hi>Nurcing-father</hi> of our <hi>Church;</hi> which if it shall please you out of your <hi>True worth</hi> fauourably to <hi>Accept, Patronise and Protect,</hi> I will boldly promise to second them with a better <hi>Present.</hi> And thus as most bounden in duty, readie in seruice, and daily in <hi>Praier,</hi> vnto Almighty God, to be your <hi>Honours guide</hi> and <hi>fortresse</hi> both in this life and the life to come, I rest most humble at your <hi>Honors</hi> commaund,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>FRANCIS ROLLENSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>