<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112379_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07168</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17574</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112379</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke of the arte and maner, howe to plant and graffe all sortes of trees : howe to set stones, and sowe pepines to make wylde trees to graffe on, as also remedies and mediicnes [sic] . VVith diuers other newe practise, by one of the Abbey of Saint Vincent in Fraunce, practised with his owne handes, deuided into seauen chapters, as hereafter more plainely shall appeare, with an addition in the ende of this booke, of certaine Dutch practises, set forth and Englished, by Leonard Mascall</title>
                 <author>Mascall, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wight (Wyght, Wayght, Whyte?), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 90, 10 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle reader thou shalt vnderstande, I haue taken out of diuerse Authors this simple worke, into our Englishe tongue, praying thee for to accept it in good part: in so doyng thou shalt bolden me to trauail further therin: &amp; thus shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my good will in declaring of diuers wayes of planting and graffing, &amp; how in the meetest times of the yeare, with shewing of diuers commodities and secretes herein, howe to set or plant with the roote, and without the roote. Howe to sow or set Pepines or curnelles, with the ordering thereof. Also howe to clense your graffes and cions, howe to helpe barren and sicke trees, howe to kill wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and vermin, and to preserue and keepe fruit: how to plant and proyne your Vines, and to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and presse your grape: how to clense &amp; mosse your trees, how to make your Syder and Perry, howe to set, choose, order and kepe Hoppes, with many other secrete practises, which shall appeere in the table following, that euery person may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily perceyue in these our dayes more largely of the art of planting and graffing than heretofore hath bene shewed. Which thing is not an exercise only to the minde, but likewise a great profit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes, with maintenaunce of health vnto the bodie. Therefore spare not the bodie to shewe so great goodnesse therevnto, &amp; also to the common wealth. In these dayes (among the rest) ye may see many, whiche be of the base and abiect sort of
<pb facs="5"/>
the common wealth, as those which wil not stick to say. Fie on thee slaue, what thing is now coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more filthy in these days (amōg faire persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) than labooring of the earth which we must al liue by. Wel, these be dainty persons: yet thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, what thing is more beautifull to the eye, more profitable to the purse, or more healthful vnto the body? &amp; herein to put away all nourishing of vice and idlenesse, it is easie to recite infinite &amp; many worthy Lordes and Gentlemen, which haue had a greate care to followe the example of others. Wherefore gentle Reader, let vs nowe leaue of from al wanton games and idle pastimes, and be no more as children whiche seeke but their owne gaine and pleasure, let vs therfore seeke one of vs for another in all good woorkes for the common wealth, whereby those that doe come after vs may so enioye our workes and trauell herein, as we haue done of our predecessours, that therein God may be glorified, praysed and honored in all our workes of planting and graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing: and we therefore maye be thankefull, from age to age, during this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lyfe. </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>