<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FATHER OF ARTS AND ARMES CHARLES LORD HOVVRD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, EARLE of Nottingham, High Constable of the Castle and Forrest of Windsore, Lord chiefe Iustice in Eyre of England, Gouernour and Captaine generall of all her Maiesties maritime Forts and Castles, High Admirall of Eng∣land and Ireland, Lieutenant of Sussex and Surrey, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maie∣sties most honourable priuie councell.</title>
           <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112613_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04680</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14809</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112613</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FATHER OF ARTS AND ARMES CHARLES LORD HOVVRD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, EARLE of Nottingham, High Constable of the Castle and Forrest of Windsore, Lord chiefe Iustice in Eyre of England, Gouernour and Captaine generall of all her Maiesties maritime Forts and Castles, High Admirall of Eng∣land and Ireland, Lieutenant of Sussex and Surrey, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maie∣sties most honourable priuie councell.</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famovs and memorable vvorkes of Iosephvs, a man of mvch honour and learning among the Iewes. Faithfully translated out of the Latin, and French, by Tho. Lodge Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Josephus, Flavius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 554, 4, 555-812, 28 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FATHER OF ARTS AND ARMES CHARLES LORD HOVV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>RD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, EARLE of Nottingham, High Constable of the Castle and Forrest of Windsore, <hi>Lord chiefe Iustice in Eyre of England, Gouernour and Captaine generall</hi> of all her Maiesties maritime Forts and Castles, High Admirall of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland, Lieutenant of Sussex and Surrey, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties most honourable priuie councell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, there is a saying in <hi>Zenophon</hi> most worthie the citing and insight, that matters of worth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence are both to be committed and commended to their trust and protection, who know the waight and value thereof, and both can and will defend the same by authoritie and reason: For this cause and vpon this ground, I haue chosen your Honour out for a most noble patron of this most famous and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished Historie of the Iewes, which (for dignitie and antiquitie of the subiect, the elegancie and puritie of the stile, the choice proprietie and copie of words, the grauitie and varietie of sentences, the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and memorable euents; and lastly for the birth and dignitie of the Author) requireth a spirit of no lesse wisedome, courage, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie then your selfe, who haue power to defend, and knowledge to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the worth thereof. Uouchsafe therefore to leuell the eie of your esteeme vpon the Center of this happy Historie: and as <hi>Themistocles</hi> was animated to noble actions by beholding <hi>Miltiades</hi> Trophies, and <hi>Alexander</hi> in seeing <hi>Achilles</hi> tombe, did grieuously sigh with an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable emulation: so let the zeale, magnanimitie, and admirable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie which euerie where affronteth you in this booke (and rauisheth the best mindes from the boundlesse troubles of this world, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them into the contemplation of true perfection) so settle your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loue and affection to emulate the same, that as for glorie in armes;
<pb facs="3"/>
so for preseruing and protecting artes, you may outstrip your competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and amaisse to curious expectation. And in mine opinion the time challengeth no lesse at your hands: for as your transcendent dignitie and courage hath returned vs a happy haruest in our expected and long pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed peace, as by your second care and diligence next vnder her sacred Maiestie we all reape the fruit and felicitie of blessea abundance; so by your example in reading and respecting both learning and the learned, you shall pull downe that <hi>Babel,</hi> which confused ignorance hath raised to ouerreach industrie; yea you shall strengthen the weakned abilitie of learning which (alas the while) is now adaies like acommoditie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out request scarce saileable by the hands of a cunning broker, nothing is more worth money, and lesse in request: onely the worlds blinde crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (as S. <hi>Ierom</hi> tearmeth them) the vnlettered take delight in their errors, whose writings (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> speaketh of <hi>Aristophanes</hi> poems) are written for no moderate mans pleasure. Let therefore your vpright estimation of this worke (most noble Earle) awaken the dead deuotion of such as contemne Artes, and let no such corrupt drones (as make sale of sinfull thoughts for good merchandise) buz about the hiue of true science: But as Emperors, Kings, and Princes haue euer in their Greeke, Italian, and French with a respectiue acceptance, and bountifull hand entertained this Historie; so let this translation of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus</hi> which courteth you now in English, be accepted at your hands, and countenanced by your honour, for whose vnconfined felicitie both I and other of my name haue euer praied, and will neuer cease to study.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors vnfainedly deuoted, THOMAS LODGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>