<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112107_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06946</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17372</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112107</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Markhams farwell to husbandry or, The inriching of all sorts of barren and sterill grounds in our kingdome, to be as fruitfull in all manner of graine, pulse, and grasse as the best grounds whatsoeuer : together with the anoyances, and preseruation of all graine and seede, from one yeare to many yeares. As also a husbandly computation of men and cattels dayly labours, their expences, charges, and vttermost profits. Attained by trauell and experience, being a worke neuer before handled by any author: and published for the good of the whole kingdome</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 160 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Id not the beginning of the worke it selfe sufficiently pleade an excuse for euery part of the Worke; I should (Gentle Reeder) trouble thee with a tedious tale of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, matter, and cause of this Building; and therein begge that cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>itable Almes, which the hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie of thine owne Nature will giue me without any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome acclamation: Let it suffice, I haue written no more then I haue seene, nor added a benefit which I haue not knowne liberally bestowed vpon the industrious; of which, if you will be a pertaker, follow their Imitation, and to good labours adde a good life, and there is no feare of a Blessing: if any man be costiue or hard of beliefe. I know not how to purge him, except it be with the bitter ayres of those barren places where these Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill Grounds are; on which, if he liue and haue no foode but his owne labour, doubtlesse he will not only belee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, but loue and admire what is written for a generall profit; and to that I leaue those: The rest that are of more equall indifferencie, to the Blessings and Increase which shall come by worthy knowledge and experience. <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>G. M.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>