<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENTLE READER</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112653_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07463</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17849</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112653</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENTLE READER</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The foreste or Collection of histories : no lesse profitable, then pleasant and necessarie, dooen out of Frenche into Englishe, by Thomas Fortescue</title>
                 <author>Mexía, Pedro</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 187, 5 leaves, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE GENTLE <hi>READER</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Euer was I ignorante (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader (to howe many daungers he willyngly expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth hymself, that for thy sake taketh paine to publish any thyng in writyng, so daintie, and so diuers are the iudgementes of menne, so prone to depraue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the sweate of others. How be it, to dooe thee pleasure, I would not leaue to hassarde my credite, moste assured that I shall not please all, and glad not withstandyng, if I might content some. The learned I truste, will take all in better parte, coueryng, and excusyng whatsoeuer thei finde lesse absolute, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte, knowing that there neuer yet wrote any so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisedly, who had not, or at least neded not, the file a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of some one other. And as touchyng the others, I no more dread their harde, and sinister iudgement, then I hunte, or thirste in any thyng, their praise, or commendation. To profite neuerthelesse generally, was my desire, but chiefly the lesse learned, with this present Foreste, whiche for good cause me thought, I so might name, or title, for that beyng a collection of diuers, and sundrie matters, is as a Foreste, well
<pb facs="5"/>
furnished with many trees, birdes, and beastes, of different, and contrary natures. And if ought herein maie please thee, or profite thee in any thyng, accepte it thanckfully, other price thou paiest none, and giue by thy good example, occasion to the studious, and learned in good letters, to take in hande, or attempte with like good will some other thyng, to thyne onely profite, furtheraunce, and commoditie. Assuryng thy self, that none in any sorte, do better deserue of their countrie, that none in any exploite dooe toyle, or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile longer, that none swincke, or sweate with like paine, and anguishe, that none in like sorte hassarde, or aduenture their credite; that none desire lesse sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende, or salarie for their trauaile, that none in fine, are worse in this age recompensed. Shewe thy self therefore gratefull, bee thankefull to the aucthour, enter into his Foreste, disportyng thee therein, some laune, some range, perchaunce maie please thy indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent mynde, some walke, or some thyng els, maie lende thee contentation, nothyng I trust shall greue, or annoye thee hedgde therein. And as for me, this onely in recompence I craue, that thou fauourablie wilte accepte, and iudge of these my paines, whiche if I maie perceiue, I will not leaue to greue me, to doe thee greater pleasure. Fare thou well, and suche lette
<pb facs="6"/>
bee thy censure, as is towardes thee my meanyng.</p>
   <p>Suche faultes as haue paste in Printyng, as thei in deede bee many, and euery where aboundante, so of thy courtesie excuse vs, whether thei bee but let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whole woordes, or otherwise, and as the sense shall leade thee, so amende what so thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deste, or lackyng, or superfluous, assuryng thy self, that it somtymes paste vs, in more perfecte wise, then thou in these recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest them.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Giudica de gli altri come vorreste di te sigiudicasse.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>