<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An addition concerning the great profit of Homilies set forth by the Church.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112012_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10559</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20830</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An addition concerning the great profit of Homilies set forth by the Church.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The communion booke catechisme expounded, according to Gods holy Word, and the established doctrine of the Church : Written for the furtherance of youth and ignorant persons, in the understanding of the grounds and principles of the true Christian religion, set forth by publique authority. Wherein also are explaned sundry of the highest points in divinity, and matter greatly considerable in these present times. In speciall there is demonstrated, that his most excellent Majesties declaration to his subjects, concerning lawfull sports to be used, doth tend unto a very great encrease of true godlinesse thronghout [sic] the whole kingdome</title>
                 <author>Reeve, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 216 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>An addition concerning the great profit of Homilies set forth by the Church.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In the table of the degrees wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by Law men are prohibited to marry, appointed to be set up in Churches, there is signified,</hi> That the Homilies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready set forth are to be read for the instruction of the people, and such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forme of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as shall bee hereafter by author<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity published.</note>WHeras is the end first tome of the Homilies the Church signified, <hi>that more Homilies should be set forth, as against couetousnesse, envy, wrath, and malice, with many other matters, aswell fruitful as necessary to the edifying of Christian people, and the increase of godly living;</hi> and as yet peculiar Homilies against the said grievous fins have not bin composed: And whereas in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke immediately following the Nicene creed it is said, <hi>After the Creed, if there be no Sermon, shal follow are of the Homilies already set forth, or hereafter to be set forth by common authority,</hi> we are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to understand, that they are fruitfull and necessary to the<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>In the 35. of the Articles of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, wherunto every one admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, doth sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe, it is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> most memorably said concerning the Hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>lies,</hi> viz. The second booke of Homilies, the save<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall titles whereof we haue joyned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this article d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th containe a godly and wholsome doctrine, and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary for these times, as doth the former booke of Homilies, which were set forth in the time of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the sixt: and therefore we judge them to be read in Churches by the Ministers diligently and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly that they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the people.</note> edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Christian people, and the increase of godly living; and that from time to time (according as the divine wisdome of the Church seeth it requisite) more and more may be set forth by the publike authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Also seeing that they are concerning the fundamentall matters of the Christian Religion, they are not to be accounted onely usefull for times past, but to be profitable perpetually; because in them in all plaine manner is delivered, how the<note n="*" place="margin">All people ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore should en deavour to know the whole do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, that thereby they may judge of doctrines delivered by private Ministers, whether they agree with the fundamentall doctrine of the Church, yea or no. Also in no wise to account, that the homilies serve onely for the use of Minist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs which cannot preach, seeing that they are set forth for all peoples learning and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing in mind and conversation.</note> Church doth teach such and such points of faith and life. They are in no wise now needlesse (as many suppose) for that there is such a plenty of those which can by memory speake forth of the pulpit; but they are greatly necessary, both for peoples information in the truth, and also for their enable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereby the better to understand and judge of Sermons made unto them. Yea they are very greatly profitable for Pastors and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to instruct congregations withall, and to be as a rule of doctrin, from which themselves may not swarve in the Sermons which they make. People also for the most part have not the spirit of discerning betweene doctrine perfect and unperfect, but doe account whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver foundeth eloquently unto their eares, to be wholesome and very good: and few take into serious consideration and examination, what are the effects in mind and conversation, which such doctrine cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, that is contrary unto the doctrine of the homilies. And whereas the booke of homilies is the Theologie or divinity set forth by the supreame divine wisdome of the Apostolicall Church of England, ought not all Priests and people to be conversant therein, that in faith and life they may become conformed thereunto? Also, even as we in our hearts assenting unto the prayers read out of the Communion booke, doe thereby with our minds speake unto God: so with all due reverence attending unto the Sacred Homilies publikely read, we doe heare Christ Iesus speaking unto us, who hath said and ever doth say unto his Ministers concerning their publishing of his truth: He that heareth you, heareth me, and he that despiseth you, despiseth me, and him that sent me. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>