<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM EARLE OF Salisburie, Vicount Cranborne, Baron CECILL of Essendon, Knight of the Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</title>
           <author>Hawkins, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112489_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07270</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17666</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112489</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM EARLE OF Salisburie, Vicount Cranborne, Baron CECILL of Essendon, Knight of the Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Hawkins, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vnhappy prosperitie expressed in the histories of Ælius Seianus and Philippa the Catanian· : Written in French by P: Mathieu and translated into English by Sr. Th: Hawkins</title>
                 <author>Matthieu, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Emerson (Emondson, Edmonds), Godfrey.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 299, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div n="translator" type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM EARLE OF Salisburie, Vicount Cranborne, Baron CECILL of Essendon, Knight of the Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold <hi>Sejanus</hi> of Vulsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, and <hi>Philippa</hi> the Catanian: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Examples of Ambition in either Sex: Both which having with great applause beene already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented in France, by the elegant
<pb facs="3"/> and inimitable <hi>Mathieu,</hi> clad in the rich robes of his purer lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, appeare now in the poore habit of an English stile. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, encouraged by your Lordships particular affection to this choyce Peece in the Originall, and obliged for noble favours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on some neare unto mee; I adventurously presume on this present addresse to your Honour; who I doubt not will as freely pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize this slender endevour of a weake hand, as the more polished labours of a powerfull pen. The matters herein treated are impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, the Observations prudent, Maximes of State usefull, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences weightie, and had not our Author with Posteritie, suffered in the much deplored losse of some
<pb facs="3"/> part of <hi>Tacitus</hi> his Annals, there could not have been a worke more amply, and politely furnished out, to satisfie either the most judicious, or curious His defects from that maime are unavoydable▪ mine pregnant, and (I feare) inexcusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. It rests in your Lordships ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Nature, as with Iustice to apologize for the first, so with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour sweetly to dissemble the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of the latter, whilst I with due acknowledgement of much Obligation, shall to your Honour seriously devote the ever ready services of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Th. Hawkins.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>