<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader grace and peace.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S112319_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16720</idno>
           <idno type="STC">362</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S112319</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader grace and peace.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An alphabet of the holy proverbs of King Salomon specially from the beginning of the tenth chapter to the end of the booke : for the helpe of memorie and for a more ready finding out of any whole sentence, if onely the beginning be called to mind: with a short interpretation of the more hard prouerbs, wherein also diuers translations are compared and laied together for a further helpe to vnderstanding. Collected and set down in this order with a mind desirous to procure that these holy prouerbs might be made yet more familiar euen to children by the delight of so plaine and familiar a method</title>
                 <author>Allen, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 123, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader grace and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in the Lorde (Right christian &amp; prudent reader) may it please thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that I thy poore well willer, doe willingly accord, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouslie professe together with thy self, that the most holie scriptures of God are set downe and deliuered vnto vs, by his owne diuine dispensation, in all wise and holy perfection, not onlie for the matter therein contained, but also euen for the order and manner it selfe, whether for phrase of speach, or for coherence of sentence, yea euen in those parts which to vs maie seeme lesse coupled and knit together then the rest.</p>
   <p>Where as therfore this present di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesting of the holie prouerbes for the greater part (of the whole booke) in that forme which here thou seest is far differing from the originall dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of them; yea so as they may seeme
<pb facs="3"/>transposed as it were out of their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and kindly seat &amp; soyle: I thought it necessarie by way of intreatie (euen for the pittie thou bearest toward hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmitie) to seeke to obtaine that fauorable allowance at thy hands) wherin God hath vouchsafed the first permission and leaue) which cannot otherwise by anie other sufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son be extorted from thee.</p>
   <p>Now then may it please thee to bee intreated, yea rather by humble and heartie intreatie to be ouercome, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so farre to fauor this bold enterprise as it may be either discerned by light of thy fauorable iudgement or shall bee found by willing diligence in the vse of it, to be helpefull to anie, toward the more profitable reading and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of these diuine sentences, in that holie order wherein the holy pen-men of the Lord haue first set thē downe.</p>
   <p>If this request may seeme reasonable vnto thee vpon the premises and also according to al good hope which may be conceiued herein: then also may the
<pb facs="4"/>practise of the Lorde himselfe who hath succoured memorie by his owne disposing of diuers portions of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; blessed worde in the same order, (as is euident in the holie language both in sundrie <hi>Psalmes</hi> and in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of <hi>Ieremie:</hi> and euen in the last Chap. of this booke of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes) this I say may further induce thee to conceiue so much the better liking of this indeuoure, at the least vpon such wise caution as the matter requireth: that is to say, that the comparison bee in no wise equalled herein, but onlie tolerated as an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reuerend &amp; begged imitation for a helpe to our weak and frayle memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as hath bene saide.</p>
   <p>Besides through the grace of God, it may bee thou shalt finde something performed in this poore labour which of thy selfe thou wilt iudge, not a toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthie some peece of thy gentle acceptaunce. Namely in that the translation of diuerse sentences is somewhat neerer fitted to the authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb facs="4"/>text: and also because the diuers interpretations of manie sentences are presented before thee in one short view, for the exercising of thine owne modest iudgement and wittes in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the best choise, as in some fewe places (not doubting of thy good leaue) I haue not feared to doe.</p>
   <p>But that I bee not tedious; I will rest in this perswasion that thou wilte yeeld to bee of this minde (in such sort as hath beene intreated) that what good and helpfull way soeuer (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus by the order of the letter, or by laying together all sentences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one &amp; the same matter which indeede often falleth out in this alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, but must be left to an other labour as touching the exact performance of it) I will rest I say perswaded, that thou wilt account euery commodious way, seruing to make this excellent portion of the worde of God more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarlie knowne, and to drawe it forth to a more plentifull and holie vse, to be accepted as a grace giuen from him
<pb facs="5"/>who is the only author of euery good gift and grace.</p>
   <p>Hitherto for the manner of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent disposing of these holy sentences: I beseech thee (gentle reader) to heare me in a few words concerning the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences themselues, as touching the most excellent wisedome comprised therein.</p>
   <p>Many make great reckoning of the sentences of <hi>Tullie</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other fine witted heathen mē. And verily they are not to bee contemned especially of wise Christians, the least whereof can more holilie vnderstande and also make better vse of their owne sentences (such as poynt towards any good matter) then they could them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. And also by such sentences sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and dispersed in their writings we may as by certaine ruines perceiue what was the excellent frame &amp; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of mans first creation.</p>
   <p>But what are those their sentences, and the rather if they bee interpreted according to their heathnish &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="5"/>minde, seing they had not the true knowledge of God, nor of them selues, nor of anie thing pertaining to true religion and godlinesse: seeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so their guide was but corrupt and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scured light of weake and vnperfecte reason: what (I say) are all those their sentences, in comparison of the most holy and perfectly wise prouerbes of King <hi>Salomon?</hi> Yea in comparison of such of them, wherein, for som appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of wordes, they might seeme to aime at the same thing with him? For all the sentences of this our heauenly teacher (a verie true maister of senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces indeede) they are holie and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, proceeding from the holy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God in the work of his regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and new birth, through a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall enlightning &amp; sanctifying of the heart, tongue and penne of his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes, whose faithful labours are met in the publishing of them for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon instructiō of the Church of God: but the sentences of heathen men are in themselues vnholy, earthly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="6"/>The sentences of King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> are all grounded vpon the true knowledge of God, in the faith of Christ Iesus our redeemer &amp; sauiour, who is the only true light of men, and the verie life, soule &amp; spirit of all sonud doctrine and perfect instruction: they haue also their scope and drift, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God cheefely, and then the faith and repentance of Gods people vnder the assured hope of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of sinnes, and of the inheritance of eternall life in the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: but the sentences of the heathen are nothing so, but wanting all sure ground they teach rather a shadow of vertue, then vertue indeede, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without a better teaching all the fruite vanisheth awaie in an idle and fruitlesse speculation.</p>
   <p>Moreouer as the sentences of King <hi>Sulomon</hi> guide vs certainly to the right end of faith, euen the glorie of God &amp; saluation of our soules, so do they laie out and perfectly describe vnto vs the onely right waie of holie obedience
<pb facs="6"/>and dutie both to God and man: but all the goodlie direction of humaine and philosophical vertues dieth in the seruing of mens owne turnes, eyther for the gayning of worldly prayse or worldly honour, or for some other like end, in so much as it is truely said that (the matter truely scanned) all their vertues are but shining and glittering sinnes.</p>
   <p>Wherefore nowe vppon such vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall comparison let euerie of vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke our harts to haue these most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie sentences among the rest of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred scriptures in more high and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious estimation in finitely aboue all sentences of heathen men. And to this purpose I beseech thee to cōsider with mee that whatsoeuer may haue speciall force to moue the minde to desire a thing absent, to ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it being present, and to hope for after fruite by it, they all doe meete in the gratious sentences of King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō</hi> (considered together) as in one sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. For what moueth the minde to
<pb facs="7"/>desire any thing, but fame, sweetenes, pleasure, riches, bewtie and such like? What delighteth but the same things, &amp; therewithall in the matter of speach and instruction, these three thinges plainnes, breuitie, and varietie? And what afterfruite is more comfortable then ioy after sorrow, saftie after dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, glorie after reproch, and if there be any other like vnto these.</p>
   <p>Behold then what fame (the fame of our Sauiour only excepted) was euer so greate as the fame of <hi>Salomons</hi> wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? How sweete are his wordes as ointment &amp; sweet perfume to reioyce the heart by all kinde of sweete coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell? How pleasant and bewtiful like apples of golde with pictures of siluer? How rich, euen like the chaine about the necke, yea like the diadem and glorious crowne vpon the heade? Againe doe not K. <hi>Salomons</hi> prouerbes most briefely containe most ample &amp; large matter? doe they not leade vs as it were by the hand into verie high turrets whence by a quick vew we may
<pb facs="7"/>easilie behould manie thinges a far off which would aske greater paines &amp; longer time to bee lesse discerned of the wisest among vs, walking through the low vallie of our owne thoughts? Touching varietie, what a large gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is here vnlocked vnto vs, full of all sorts of sweet fruit &amp; pleasant flowers: what a store-house for al plentie of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall foode and vittaile? what a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drope with robes fit to decke the mindes of all that resorte to it like princes children? what a iewell-house of all kinde of pretious iewels to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the soule withall? what a libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of all flowers and elegancies of the best learning as in one litle enchiridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or shedule to replenish thy minde with holie vnderstanding &amp; wisdome? And touching the fruite therefore of these so excellent sentences wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; digested in the mind and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie practised in the ordering of the life, who can reckon them vp in order? On<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly this shall now be saide in generall that blessed are they of God who will
<pb facs="8"/>dayly exercise themselues in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, remembrance, vse &amp; practise of them as of any other the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God. Blessed are those Parents which wil wisely &amp; carefully acquaint their children with them, as the verie manner of setting them downe in the name of a father most louingly and carefully teaching his childe doth declare that it is the will of God they should do so: and blessed for euer are those children who hearkning to their wise and godly Parents wil learne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and wisdome from them.</p>
   <p>Now finally this booke is dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more particularlie to the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble children aboue mentioned, to this end (beside the reason expressed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) that by one duetie tendered to them, many by occasion therof, might be made partakers of a common bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. And thus good reader, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende thee to the Lorde, beseeching him most humblie for our Lord Iesus Christes sake to deliuer vs more and
<pb facs="8"/>more from all vanitie of minde, and to preserue our harts with daily increase of all heauenly grace both for wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and godlinesse, vnto his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting kingdome of glorie Amen.</p>
   <p>Thine in the Lord both cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy faithfull prayer and also praying withal his heart for thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>