<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Ghosts of HANNIBAL and SCIPIO.</title>
           <author>Nabbes, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113063_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18341</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113063</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Ghosts of HANNIBAL and SCIPIO.</title>
                 <author>Nabbes, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hannibal and Scipio : An historicall tragedy. Acted in the yeare 1635. by the Queenes Majesties Servants, at their private house in Drury Lane. The author Thomas Nabbes</title>
                 <author>Nabbes, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Greene, Charles</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Ghosts of</hi> HANNIBAL <hi>and</hi> SCIPIO.</head>
   <l>WHere e're your thin remaines, and shaddows dwell;</l>
   <l>In the Elysian blisse, or paines of Hell;</l>
   <l>I, that with writing of your story new</l>
   <l>Am almost worne into a ghost like you,</l>
   <l>Present you with your selves: such as you were</l>
   <l>When you breath'd ayre, and had your beings here.</l>
   <l>Let not hells Judges damne it to the fire;</l>
   <l>It past mens sentence: there's besides some hire</l>
   <l>Yet undischarg'd; and where the debt was due</l>
   <l>Being deny'd, I have sent the bill to you,</l>
   <l>Say not for money, how shall we come by it?</l>
   <l>Borrow of <hi>Pluto:</hi> he will not deny it</l>
   <l>Vpon your bond. Stay: here's a great mistaking;</l>
   <l>His state and riches were of Poets making:</l>
   <l>And they I feare so apt are to belye him,</l>
   <l>I cannot think he hath one penny by him.</l>
   <l>How e're your patronage shall doe me right,</l>
   <l>'Bove the prefixt name of a Lord or Knight:</l>
   <l>Or other outside men: such as inherit</l>
   <l>Of honour but the title, not the merit.</l>
   <l>Who think that if the least state action rest</l>
   <l>On their dispatch; or to a Christmas feast</l>
   <l>They yearly call the neighbour-hood; or be</l>
   <l>Put in commission, or the Shrivaltie</l>
   <l>(The Countreys highest grace) they may dispence</l>
   <l>With what belongs more to their difference,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Bounty unto desert. But you are free;</l>
   <l>And if you might would rather come to me,</l>
   <l>Then put me to a charge: the journey's great,</l>
   <l>And ere I could return, I might want meat:</l>
   <l>Vnlesse some kind poore cobler, (you know well</l>
   <l>Mending of soales is no rich trade in Hell.)</l>
   <l>Lend me a shilling. Loth I am 'tis true</l>
   <l>At any rate of hopes to come to you.</l>
   <closer>
      <salute>The honourer of your memories,</salute>
      <signed>THOMAS NABBIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>