<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Davison, Fra.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113564_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19943</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6373</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113564</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Davison, Fra.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A poetical rapsody : containing, diuerse sonnets, odes, elegies, madrigalls, and other poesies, both in rime, and measured verse. Neuer yet published. The bee and spider by a diuerse power, sucke hony' &amp; poyson from the selfe same flower</title>
                 <author>Davison, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bailey, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>236 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EING induced, by some priuate reasons, and by the instant intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of speciall friendes, to suffer some of my worthlesse Poems to be published, I desired to make some written by my deere friend <hi>Anomos,</hi> and my deerer <hi>Brother,</hi> to beare them company: Both without their consent, the latter being in the low Country Warres, and the former vtterly ignorant thereof. My friendes name I concealed, mine owne, and my brothers, I willed the Printer to suppresse, as well as I had concealed the other: which he hauing put in, without my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, we must both now vndergoe a sharper censure perhaps then our nameles works should haue done, &amp; I especially. For if their Poems be liked, the praise is due to their inuention, if disliked, the blame both by them, and all men will be deriued vppon me, for publishing that which they meant to suppresse.</p>
   <p>If thou thinke wee affect fame by these kindes of writings, though I thinke them no disparagement e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en to the best iudgements, yet I answere in all our behalfes, with the Princely Shepheard <hi>Dorus;</hi>
      <q>Our hearts doe seeke another estimation.</q>
   </p>
   <p>If thou condemne Poetry in generall, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that it doth intoxicate the braine, and make
<pb facs="3"/>
men vtterly vnfit, either for more serious studies, or for any actiue course of life, I only say, <hi>Iubeo te stultum esse libenter:</hi> Since experience proues by examples of many, both dead and liuing, that diuers delighted and excelling herein, being Princes or States-men, haue gouerned and counceled as wisely, being Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, haue commanded armies as fortunately, being Lawyers, haue pleaded as iudicially and eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being Diuines, haue written and taught as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly, and being of any other Profession, haue discharged it as sufficiently as any other men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer: If liking other kindes, thou mislike the Lyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, because the chiefest subiect thereof is Loue; I reply, that Loue being virtuously intended, &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily placed, is the Whetstone of witt, and Spurre to all generous actions: and that many excellent spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with great fame of witt, and no staine of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, haue written excellently in this kind, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the euer-praise worthy <hi>Sidney:</hi> So as if thou will needs make it a fault, for mine owne part,
<q>
         <l>Haud timeo, si iam nequeo defendere crimen</l>
         <l>Cum tanto commune viro.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>If any except against the mixing (both at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ende of this booke) of diuerse thinges written by great and learned Personages, with our meane and worthles Scriblings, I vtterly disclaime it, as being done by the Printer, either to grace the forefront with Sir <hi>Ph. Sidneys,</hi> and others names, or to make the booke grow to a competent volume.</p>
   <p>For these Poems in particular, I could aledge these excuses; that those vnder the Name of <hi>Anomos,</hi> were
<pb facs="4"/>
written (as appeareth by diuers things to Syr <hi>Philip Sidney</hi> liuing, and of him dead) almost twentie yeers since, when Poetry was farre from that perfection, to which it hath now attained; that my Brother is by profession a Souldier, and was not 18. yeeres olde when hee writt these Toyes: that mine owne were made most of them sixe or seuen yeeres since, at idle times as I iourneyed vp and downe during my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uails. But to leaue their workes to iustifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, or the Authors to iustifie their workes, and to speake of myne owne; thy mislikes I contemne, thy prayses (which I neither deserue, nor expect), I esteeme not, as hoping (God willing) ere long, to regaine thy good Opinion, if lost, or more deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly to continue it, if already obtained, by some grauer Worke. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>FRA: DAVISON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>