<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To THE RIGHT Worshipfull, religious, and courteous Knight, Sir William Wray, my approoued good friend and benefactor, salu∣tations in the Lord Jesus.</title>
           <author>Smyth, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113474_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12551</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22874</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113474</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To THE RIGHT Worshipfull, religious, and courteous Knight, Sir William Wray, my approoued good friend and benefactor, salu∣tations in the Lord Jesus.</title>
                 <author>Smyth, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bright morning starre: or, The resolution and exposition of the 22. Psalme : preached publikely in foure sermons at Lincolne. By John Smith preacher of the citie</title>
                 <author>Smyth, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 196 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To THE RIGHT Worshipfull, religious, and <hi>courteous Knight, Sir</hi> William Wray, my approoued good <hi>friend and benefactor,</hi> salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the Lord <hi>Jesus.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>SIr: it seemeth a thing very reasonable to me, that seeing euery bald tale, vaine enterlude, and pelting ballad, hath the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of the Presse, the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and readings of ministers may challenge the same: the worlde is full of <hi>Guy</hi> of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, <hi>William</hi> of Cloudeslee, <hi>Skoggins,</hi> and <hi>Wolners</hi> iests, and writings of like qualitie: and therein men take great delight to read, and so make themselues merrie with other mens sinnes, bestowing to this purpose much
<pb facs="3"/>vaine time and superfluous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences: and J thinke the Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners shop, and some mens shelues are better furnished with such trifles, which deceiue the minde and affection as the baite doeth the fish, then with wholesome writings of nature, arte, or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. In which respect in seemeth to haue beene lesse hurtfull to mankind, if Printing had neuer beene inuented, sauing that the vse of a thing is not to be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den because of the abuse: these things considered, haue imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to publish my meditations and readings to the worlds views and seeing that Printing is a trade wherby diuers good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians maintaine their charge, &amp; that for want of better imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they sometime are compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to prostitute their Presses to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>s and vanitie: seeing also the
<pb facs="3"/>trueth may better appeare by writings of diuers men, which perhaps one or two or more could not readily discouer: therefore I haue thought good in some part to preuent the danger of the one, and promote the benefit of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. J haue not varnished my writing with the superficiall learning of words, and figures, tongues, and testimonies of men (which not withstanding I do not disalow) but because I purposed to apply my style to the vnderstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the simple, I indeauour to vtter matter with all plainenesse of wordes and sentences. Nowe because I haue experienced your selfe to be vnder the Kings Maiestie a principall professor and protectour of religion in these quarters: (for what a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of faithfull ministers are debters to you in the flesh?) and
<pb facs="4"/>for that I among the rest haue rested vnder your shaddowe, your name came first to my mind in this writing: wherefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you vouchsafe to intitle it with your name, and I shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my selfe graced ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. The Lord increase in your selfe and your vertuous Lady and childrē all manner of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces &amp; blessings.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worsh. humbly in all manner of Christian affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Iohn Smith.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>