<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Mary Make-peace, of the Mannor of All∣well, in Northamptonshire, to all the Sisters of her Female Society, Health, Hearts-ease, and Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Make-Peace, Mary</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113015_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13439</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23747</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113015</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Mary Make-peace, of the Mannor of All∣well, in Northamptonshire, to all the Sisters of her Female Society, Health, Hearts-ease, and Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Make-Peace, Mary</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Divers crabtree lectures : Expressing the severall languages that shrews read to their husbands, either at morning, noone, or night. With a pleasant relation of a shrewes Munday, and shrewes Tuesday, and why they were so called. Also a lecture betweene a pedler and his wife in the canting language. With a new tricke to tame a shrew</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sweeting, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 228 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Mary Make-peace,</hi> of the Mannor of <hi>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire, to all the Sisters of her Female Society, Health, Hearts-ease, and Happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>Sweete Sisters,</opener>
   <p>ANd fellow Spinsters, (for the weakest of us is no worse, and the best no better) it is the Character under which all our Sexe is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; I lovingly salute you all hoping you are in as good health of body, and in quiet
<pb facs="3"/>
of minde, as I was at the writing hereof: These are further to let you understand, that it is come to my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; how by the course car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of some amongst our Sexe; others, whose mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties are no way guilty of the like misdemeanour, are not privately bated, but (even in Print) publickly branded: &amp; by such who consider not, that as there was a <hi>Maechael Helena,</hi> so there was a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron-like <hi>Hecuba</hi>; and as a loose <hi>Lais,</hi> so a loyall <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crese.</hi> Nor that we might as well retort upon them, that as there was an <hi>Hercules,</hi> so there was an <hi>Herostratus</hi>; and as a <hi>Salemon,</hi> so a <hi>Sinon.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But all this is to little or no purpose: you know my
<pb facs="3"/>
name is <hi>Mary Make-peace,</hi> and have alwaies studied to <hi>make peace</hi> betwixt both Sexes: Then, though they raile at us, let not us revile them: for patience must prove our best preservative: For as the Grammer rule learnedly instructeth us: <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineo generi tri<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>untur — propria quae maribus</hi>: which is, as I interpret it: <hi>Though the Feminine gender bee troublesome, let us seeke to please proper men, least they bring us downe upon our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribones:</hi> which done, we shal prevent all prejudice and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert all disasters.</p>
   <p>I confesse there is <hi>Tabitha Turbulent,</hi> of a terrible tongue; and <hi>Franke Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> who though shee bee
<pb facs="4"/>
given more to pouting than to prating, yet neither of them I hold to be necessary: <hi>Betrisse Bould-face</hi> doth all things without blushing: And <hi>Ellen Ever-heard</hi> makes too much noyse amongst her neighbours: And of the like quality and condition are <hi>Parnell Prate a pace,</hi> and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell Raile at him: Vrsula Vpsefreeze</hi> is condemned to for her uncivill carriage; as proov'd to be no better than a pot companion: As for <hi>Hannah Hit him home,</hi> and <hi>Ioaene Iowle him well,</hi> they are valued in the ranke of Vixens, and will be loud by no allowance: these hnmours I like not.</p>
   <p>Marry againe, (for thats our womens constant phrase,
<pb facs="4"/>
when we bury our husbands) There are on the contrary side, <hi>Grace grieve him not,</hi> a simple and good soule: <hi>Kate Kisse-well</hi> no cunning, but a conniving creature: <hi>Luce Lye-close</hi> no wanton, but a willing wench: <hi>Dorothy Doe-little</hi> not to be caveld at, because so cald: for you know the Proverbe, so said, so done, and little said soone amended: and for <hi>Sisly Sweet-lips</hi> my sister, and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery Quiet</hi> my Cousen-ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: if all the rest were of their simplicity, and modesty, men shonld not have such reason to cavell at us, nor wee such cause to complaine of them. Alas, why should not Ivory teeth bridle intemperate tongues?
<pb facs="5"/>
and soft lippes conceale ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len hearts? or why should a faire face bee the betrayer of hidden faults? of all these things, as a Sister of your society, I thought good to advise you.</p>
   <closer>
      <hi>Given at our Mannor of</hi> ALL-VVELL.
<signed>MARY MAKE-PEACE</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>