<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER GRACE AND PEACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113143_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05105</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15241</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113143</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER GRACE AND PEACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French academie : Fully discoursed and finished in foure bookes. 1. Institution of manners and callings of all estates. 2. Concerning the soule and body of man. 3. A notable description of the whole world, &amp;c. 4. Christian philosophie, instructing the true and onely meanes to eternall life. This fourth part neuer before published in English. All written by the first author, Peter de la Primaudaye, Esquire, Lord of Barre, Chauncellour, and Steward of the French Kings house</title>
                 <author>La Primaudaye, Pierre de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 330, 10, 331-634, 4, 635-643, 646-1031, 1034-1038, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="182"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER GRACE AND PEACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ENECA</hi> the Philosopher reporteth (gentle Reader) that the looking glasse was firct innented to this end, that man might vse it as a meane to know himselfe the better by. Now besides that in a glasse wee may attaine to some kinde of knowledge of our selues when wee take a view of our owne countenance, and of the liueaments and proportion of our bodies outwardly, <hi>Socrates</hi> applied the same to a further vse for the instruction of maners. For as <hi>Apuleius</hi> writeth of him, he earnestly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded his Auditors to looke often into a glasse, and to beholde themselues therein, to this intent, that hee which thought himselfe beautifull and faire, might take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion thereby to auoide al kinde of deformity in manners and conuersation, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that beauty of his would bee greatly blemished: and that whosoeuer perceiued by the glasse any defect of comelinesse in his countenance, might labour so much the more seriously by the helpe of vertue and inward graces of the minde to recompence the outward wants and imperfections of his body. In which respect this booke may most fitly be resembled to a glasse, as that which affordeth vnto vs both these vses in far more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner than can be performed by any looking glasse how rare and surpassing soeuer it be. For euen the best of that kinde doeth represent vnto our eyes only so much of the surface of our on we bodies as is directly before it, but as for the hinder parts we take no view of them by a glasse, much lesse is it able to giue vs a sight of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> members of our bodyes, whereby we may attaine to any profitable knowledge of them. But if wee take a diligent view of this booke, and with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> eies both of body and minde looke intentiuely vpon the same, it will in most euident manner represent vnto vs not onely the outward members of mans body both before and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde and on euery side, but euen the most hidden and inward parts thereof, which otherwise before life haue left the body cannnot possibly be seene of any man. Here may you behold all the bones as it were the frame and timberworke of mans body, yea the very foundation vpon which all the residue of the building is laide. Heere may you see the exquisite frame and composition of the head, as it were the vpper lodging of this house, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ventricles of the braine, as so many sundry chambers for the entertainement of the <hi>Animall spirits:</hi> the singuler workemanship of the eies, as of the lights and windowes, appertaining to this pallace of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: the matter and four me of the humors in the eies, as it were the christal glasse set in the windowes, together with the eye-lids, as casements to open &amp; shut, to receiue in or keepe out the light as neede requireth, besides the eyebrowes as penthouses to defend those windowes from the violence of stormy weather, What should I speake of the eares, as of high watch towers whereby warning is giuen to the internall senses so often as any aduersarie noyse giueth notice of enemies approching to anoy this good castle? The mouth is it not as the doore that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in all kinde of prouision meete fort he reparation and maintenance of this great building, as occasion ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth? It is a world to thinke what excellent workemanshippe appeareth in the voice and tongue of man, and singular vses it hath very requisite for the perfection of this piece of worke. Now if we shall descend and enter into the contemplation, as of the breast, as of the middle story of this building, and consider what with what goodly householde stuffe those roomes are adorned, who is able either with tongue to vtter, or with heart to conceiue, the rare deuises, the precious Iewells the singular art there to bee found? What an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faire roome is the dining chamber of the heart, the receptable of the will and affections, the shope wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the vitall spirites are wrought, and the forge from whence is deriued that fire and heate which warmeth the whole house? And least this fire should breake forth into such a flame as might bring perill of burning to this goodly building, the chamber of the heart is daily and continually refreshed with coole blasts procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="183"/>
from the lungs as from an outward roome that is built round about a great part thereof. Here also is to be seene the <hi>Artery</hi> which as a liuely co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>duite carieth forth continually most christall streames of vitall spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits into euery r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>me and office of the house. Betwixt this second story and the third is laide the Midriff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as a store that maketh a seperation betweene the instruments of the vitall parts being the implements of that midle roome, and the naturall instruments of the neather story which serue both for the vpholding and maintenance of the whole building, and also containeth in it matter for the erecting of a new frame, which is to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>and after the former is come to his full period. In this third story or partition is to bee seene the stomake, which being as it were the kitching of the body receiueth at the doore of the mouth all such meates and drinkes as are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site for the keeping of it in sufficient repar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tions and for the defence of it against two mighty enemies <hi>Hunger</hi> and <hi>Thirst,</hi> who by continuall vndermining of the same, labor, to lay it euen with the ground. And because no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be prepared in the kitchin without heate, and the maintenance thereof besides the naturall heat of the stomake it is compassed on the rightside with the liuer, on the left with the spleene, behinde with the muscles of the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> before with kal, abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e it hath the haert and midriffe, and within it are sundry vitall spirits, from all which as from so many seuerall fires, it receiueth heat for the better dressing and conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cting of that which is conueyed into it. Neither are the gutters and sinkes necessarily belonging to euery house, wanting to the perfection of this beautifull building of mans body: as may appeare by the guts and other parts of baser seruice, without which it is not possible that this frame should, long continue. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w besides the singular delight &amp; pleasure, which this naturall knowledge of our owne bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es yeeldeth vnto our minds, the profite and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that issueth here from is great and manifolde. For first in regard of our selues, if we were throughly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Anatomy</hi> of our bodies, with the substance and situation, with the forme and qualities, with the <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ou. 4. 6. 1. Cor. 12.</note> vses and offices of euery part and member of the same, it is out of all question, that by the knowledge thereof, we might both preuent many diseases and infirmities, which through want thereof would seaze vpon vs, and being ouertaken with any, might recouer our selues more speedily by a wise and skilfull cariage of our selues according to the same. Neither is it laide vpon euery one to haue so much skill as is requisite for him that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth profession of that art towards all men, but onely so far forth as may serue for the preseruation of his owne health eyther in imploying the talent of his priuate knowledge, or in yeelding himselfe more readily vnto the wise direction of the skilfull Physition. Secondly as <hi>Salomon</hi> sendeth vs to the industryous nature of the Pis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire to learne diligence and forecaste in our calling, so the Apostle taketh occasion by the variety of members in one body, to reprehend two sorts of people in the Church of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, both such as were caried away with e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y towards their superiours, themselues being indued with meaner gifts, and those also who being furnished with more excellent ornaments of Gods spirit, were puffed, vp with pride in themselues and with disdayne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others of fewer graces. And this being the second vse that ariseth from this naturall knowledge of our bodies, offreth it selfe in most plentifull man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er to be obserued by vs, in euery part and member of the same. What a notable lesson of good neighbourhood are we taught by the view and contemplation of mans face? For as many seuerall members of different vses are so artificially knit and linked together in one face, that not one of them is any impediment or hinderance, vnto another in the execution of his office: so wee are instructed thereby how to carry our selues towards our neighbours, euery one to containe himselfe within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of his seuerall calling, and not to incroch one vpon another as the manner of a great many is, that are not contented with their owne estate. Againe, in the second story of this frame when wee consider the lungs, which are the bellowes of the voice, are placed so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eere the heart that they compasse it round about, are not all men thereby admonished, that their speech is but the interpreter of the heart, and the messenger thereof? that the mouth must like a good seruant attend vppon the heart, and vtter nothing but that which it receiueth first from the same? that no man ought to imitate the example of <hi>Hyppolytus</hi> in <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>des,</hi> who being admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished of his Nurse to remember his Oath, made her this mishappen answer, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: The tongu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hath sworne, but the minde is v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sworne? As many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ollow harted subiects of late daies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued <note place="margin">Iob. 33. 3. Psal. 12. 2.</note> themselues towards her Maiesty, hauing receiued a dispensation so to do from Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the thirteenth, whose goodly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sie was set downe in certaine tokens sent to all such as were to bee reconciled vnto him, Fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mi da <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ihicor &amp; sufficet, <hi>My son, giue mee thy hart, and it sufficeth,</hi> which is all one as if he bad said sweare and for sweare thy selfe if thou wilt, say thou art a good subiect, go to the church, do whatsoeuer <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 27. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3.</note> is commanded thee, so thou let mee haue thy heart, it skilleth not who haue thy tongue, thy hands, and all the rest of thy body. <hi>Elihu</hi> being of another spirit, was better instructed in the knowledge of this neere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, which naturally ought to be betweene the heart and the tongue: and therefore speaking to his friend <hi>Iob</hi> he telleth him, <hi>that his words would bee in the vprightnesse of his heart:</hi> Whereas they that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not this course of nature, but violently draw their tongue to vtter that which is farre disagreeing from the meaning of the heart, are branded for the same by the kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> with this marke of infa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, that they are men of two hearts, or of a double heart, which is monstrous in nature. The like instruction to this we are taught in that the tongue is placed so neere vnder the braine, which is the seat of the minde and vnderstanding part of man, as it were at the feet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of her schoolemaster, to the intent is should not speake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduisedly
<pb facs="183"/>
&amp; hand ouer head, as we vse to say, but with great deliberation, both in regard of the matter it selfe to be deliuered by speech and also of the circumstances of time, place, and persons, which are not to be neglected. For looke how preposterous it is to set the cart before the horse, so is it for the tongue to run before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he wit, and to vtter it knoweth not well what, hauing receiued no direction from the same. And therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> putting the name of heart for the minde and vnderstanding part of man, saith, that <hi>a righteous mans heart meditateth or pondereth what it shall answer: and that the hart</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 28. and 16. 23.</note>
      <hi>of the wise guideth his mouth prudently.</hi> Neither is it slightly to be passed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uer, that euery one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing two eies that serue for seeing, two eares for hearing, two nostrils for smelling, two feete for going, hath yet but one soft and fleshy tongue for sundry vses, and that tyed fast with strings, and compassed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with gums, teeth, and lips, as with a double wall to teach men thereby, that the tongue being a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnruly member, had neede to be brideled and hemmed in on euery side, least it breake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orth into a world of wickednesse, and breede destrustion to the whole body. Now if we looke into the middle story of this building, there we shall see that although the heart be the fountaine of life, and the root of all the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall spirits that are dispersed into euery part and member of the body, yet it cannot want either the coole refreshing it hath from the lungs, or the veine-pipes proceeding from the liuer, or the moouing strings it hath from the sinewes, or the necessary defence of the ribbes and bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, which as strong bulwarks and rampires fence it in on euery side. Euen so fareth it with the great and mightie men of this world; who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in regarde of their power and authority ouer others, they seeme to haue their liues and liuelihoods at their becke and commandement, yet they are so farre from being able of themselues to maintaine their honours and high places without the necessary aide of the inferiour sort, as that without them they should want wherewith to vphold their owne liues. But this appeareth yet more euident in the lower story of this frame, where the guttes and intrailes of the body as it were the sink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of an house haue their a biding. For although in regard of their vse they may seeme to be the basest and most abiect parts of the body, yet if we consider the necessity of them, we shal see that a man may better spare a principall member of his body then the least gut that is in his belly. Euen so fareth it with the politike body of a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, in which the base <hi>Artisan</hi> will sooner be missed oftentimes, then he that carrieth a greater port, and is aduanced to a higher roome and office in the same. A third vse that may bee made of this booke as it were of a christall glasse worthy the looking into, is that singular delight and pleasure which may bee reaped, by the view and consideration of the harmony betweene this terrestriall frame, and the celestiall habitation of the heauens, when they are compared together. And as that famous sentence, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Know thy selfe,</hi> is reported of many to haue descended from the heauens, so surely it will be small fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to a man whereby he may attaine to a better knowledge of himselfe, if he seriously obserue what a great agreement there is betweene him and the heauens, whereunto the very situation of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance lift vp towards heauen, doeth as it were lead him by the hand. First therefore if wee consider the originall of them both, wee finde in holy Writ, that as God is said to haue made the heauens in the beginning, so also it is there related, that not long after hee made man after his owne image and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him the soueraigntie ouer the earth and ouer all liuing and moouing creatures vnder the cope of heauen. Neither can it bee truely saide that howsoeuer the Lord himselfe formed the first man, and breathed in his face the breath of life, yet since that first creation he hath not intermedled at all with the continuall propagation of mankinde, but hath surrendered all his working power into the hands of nature, by whose powerfull operation the matter of mens bodies is brought to this glorious perfection, <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 1. 26.</note> which we see it hath when it first appeareth in the world. For this is to speake after the manner of meere naturall men, that haue not as yet learned the language of Canaan, as is plaine if wee call to minde what the kingly Prophet saith vnto the Lord, that <hi>it was he that possessed his raignes, and that couered him in his mothers wombe.</hi> Which also is more manifestly taught by that holy mā <hi>Iob,</hi> who confident<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Psal. 139. 13. Iob. 10. 10. 11</note> affirmeth, that it was the <hi>Lord who had powred him out as milke, &amp; turned him to cruddes like cheese: that he had clothed him with skinne &amp; flesh, &amp; ioyned him together with bones and sinewes.</hi> Wherefore as it was the eternall God, who first turned the body of the heauens into that roundnes, gathered the light into the bodies of the celestial lamps, fixed the stars in the firmamēt, endued each planet with his seueral motion, &amp; clothed the inferiour world with this glorious circumferēce: s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the same God at the first planted <hi>Adam</hi> as the roote of mankinde, and euer since hath caused his whole race and euery seuerall person as so many branches to issue and grow out of his loynes. He turned the eyes into that roundnesse, he planted the eares as watch towers in the vpper part of the head, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e placed the tongue, fastened the teeth, stretched out the sinewes: hee watred the veines with blood, gaue massines to the bones and clothed the flesh with a fine skine as with a garment, he seuered the fingers and toes, caused the feet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to walke, and the hands to gripe. Hee, and none but he giueth sight to the eyes, hearing to the cares, taste, to the tongue, smelling to the nostrilles, and feeling to the fingers. Who but he hath endued the lungs with breathing, the heart with the spirits of life, the stomacke with concoction, the liuer with the making of blood, and womens breasts, with the making of milke? Who hath fashioned the instruments of hearing in
<pb facs="184"/>
the head like to a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er and an anuile, the hart in the body like a piramide, and made the spleene in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāce like a spunge? Who hath couered the heade with haire for comelines, &amp; boared the skine throgh with infinite pores for enacuation? In a word, who hath giuen beauty to the whole body, and to each member his seuerall operation? What father, what mother, what workeman hath wrought these things, but the only wise and imortall God? But to proceede, as the sunne, moone, &amp; celestial stars and planets haue a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble motion, the one common with the whole body of the heauens, the other proper and peculiar according to the nature of euery seueral star: so haue the parts of mans body two motions, wherof the one dependeth of the motion of the whole body, and is therefore vniuersall, and the other is particular according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set nature and disposition of each seuerall member. And to descond to a more speciall comparison of one particular thing with another, how doth the diuerse operations of the <hi>animall spirit</hi> (whose seate is in the braine) concur with the different workings of the sunne in the firmament vpon the inferiour bodies here below vpon the face of the earth? We see that through the selfe same reflexion of the sun beames, the the clay is hardned, and the waxe made soft: that the light of the sun is comfortable to some eyes, whereas other become worse through the brightnes of the same, that it worketh otherwise vpon a thicke body then vpon a thin, vpon a hard then vpon a soft, vpon a plant then vpon a stone, vpon the earth then vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. So the <hi>Animall spirit</hi> being distributed into sundry parts and members of the body worketh diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly in each of them according to the diuerse nature, composition and temperament of euery one. For being imparted to the eyes by the optike sinewes it giueth sight: to the eares by certaine passages, it worketh hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: to the tongues by small Nerues, it breedeth tasting: in a word, being dispersed into the muscles and skine by meanes of certaine sinowie threedes concurring in manner of a net, it infuseth feeling through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole body. And as it often falleth out that wee are dipriued of the heate and light of the Sunne, when either some thicke cloude, or the body of the Moone, or some such thing is interposed &amp; put between vs and the same: so wee quickely see and feele the want of the <hi>Animall spirit,</hi> when any thicke clammie humor, or winde, or melancholike fumes, or any such impediment stoppe the passages and hinder the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, as is to be seene in them that are taken with the palsie, apoplexie, madnesse, numnesse, and such like. It is no lesse delectable then strange to consider in how many things the Sunne as it were the heart of the heauens, agreeth with the heart of man, which may not vnfitely be called the sunne of the body. For as the Sunne being the chiefest of the Planets occupieth the middle place among those wandring starres, hauing the rest as his guarde both aboue and beneath him, to imploy as neede requireth both for their owne safetie and the good of the inferiour worlde: so the hearte beeing the chiefest member of the body, is seated in the middle story of the same, hauing the other parts both aboue and beneath it &amp; on euery side, employing them according to their seueral offices for the vpholding and preseruation of the whole frame. And as the Sunn is the store-house of that celestiall heate, which together with a diuine and quickning spirit working in the bowelles of the earth maketh it a fruitfull Mother, &amp; tender Nurse for the bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing foorth and preseruation of all things: so the heart is the barth from whence proceedeth all that inset and natiue heate, which being conueyed with the vital spirits into euery member of the body maketh them liuely and powerfull to performe those duties that are enioyned them. Concerning the motion of the heart, as it agreeth with the Sunne in this that they both haue a double motion, so in that the heart being the first that receiueth life and motion, is the Originall of all motion in the body it resembleth the whole heauens, of which dependeth all naturall motions of inferiour bodies whatsoeuer. Againe the two eyes in the heade represent the two chiefe lights in the firmament. And as there are both simple starrs in the heauens, namely the Sunne, Moone, Saturne, Iupiter, Mercurie with the rest, and also com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound as the Charles-waine, the Lion, both the beares and others: so in the bodie there are simple or simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar partes, as the sinewes, bones, arteries, vienes, &amp;c. and compound partes, as the heart, liuer, braine, sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, lungs &amp; such like. Moreoeuer, it is certaine, that the Planets, howsoeuer in regarde of their moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to and fro they are said to be wandring starrs, haue yet their certaine limites in the heauens, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the <hi>Zodiake,</hi> in which as in their dwelling houses they exercise those naturall powers wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they are endued, as the proper mansion of the sunne is in <hi>Leo,</hi> of the Moone in <hi>Cancer,</hi> of <hi>Saturne</hi> in <hi>Capricorne,</hi> of <hi>Iupiter</hi> in <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> and so of the rest. In like manner, although the body of man be so framed, as that there is no one part but it is seruiceable vnto all, yet there are certaine seuerall places ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as peculiar shops for each facultie to worke in especially, as the braine for the <hi>Animal spirit,</hi> the heart for the <hi>Vitall,</hi> and the liuer for the <hi>Naturall:</hi> the gall is the receptacle for choller, the spleene for Melancholy, the sucking veines serue to purge the blood from the serous substance of it, &amp; so of the other powers and parts of the body. To conclude this third vse (for a day would not suffice to vtter al that might bee spoken in this matter) as the Sunne by reason of his Annuall progresse through the twelue signes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a sensible diuision of the yeare into foure parts, which haue their different seasons &amp; qualities: if they fall out according to the course of nature, and so likewise the Moone by her race quartereth the moueth accordingly: euen so fareth it with the body of man in regarde of his whole age, which being considered frō the beginning vnto the ending, agreeth very fitly to those seuerall seasons both for number and praedomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb facs="184"/>
qualities, if the threede of life be not cut off in the midway by the rasor of death. For the body of man in his first age, which is his childhood, is moist &amp; hot, and so is the former part of the yeare called the spring, as also the first part of the moneth from the new moon to the ending of the <hi>1</hi> quarter. In the second part of mens age, which is his flourishing &amp; youthful time, the body of man is hot &amp; dry, such as are the qualities of the secōd part of the yeare or summer season, &amp; of the second part of the month, which is from the first quarter to the ful Moone. Thirdly, the body of man in the third part of his age, commonly called mans age, is cold &amp; moist, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the disposition of the third part of the yeare called <hi>Autumne,</hi> &amp; of that season of the moone which is from the full to the last quarter. To conclude, in the <hi>4</hi> and last quarter of mans age, called old age, his body is cold and dry, like to the winter season, and to the fourth part of the moneth, which is from the last quarter to the next new moone. Now as these three former vses of the Anatomy of mans mans body, serue for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and delight of man, so the fourth is the same that ought to be made, not only of the body of man, but as <hi>Salomon</hi> teacheth vs of all the creatures both in heauen &amp; earth, &amp; that is the glory of God. For the Lord hauing set in his visible creatures euident marks of himselfe and of his eternity, power, goodnesse, wisedom &amp; prouidence, as the Apostle teacheth, what remaineth but that man for whose sake &amp; seruice the Lord created all things, should thereby acknowledge his soueraigne Lord, and returne vnto him all glory, praise, and dutiful <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 20.</note> obedience for the same. That we ought to make this vse of the Anatomicall consideratiō of our bodies, the king ly prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth vs most diuinely by his owne example, when after a view taken of the admirable work of God in fashioning him in his mothers womb, be breaketh forth into this saying, <hi>I will praise thee, for I am fearfully and wonderfully made, maruellous are thy works: &amp; my soule knoweth it wel.</hi> And surely vnles we tread in the steps of this worthy king and propound this as the scope of all our trauels in <note place="margin">Psal. 139 24</note> searching out the seuerall parts of our bodies, that God our creator and gratious preseruer may be praysed, worshipped, &amp; feared therby, we shall neuer know our selues aright, &amp; as we ought to do, but rather ioyn with the most part of men who not vsing their skil in this behalfe as a ladder to climbe vp by vnto God, stick fast in the very matter and forme of their bodies, so that many of them become meere Naturalists and very Atheists One special cause wherof, as I take it, is because they lay not the ground and foundation of their skil in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, the fountain of all sound knowledge, which teach vs, that it is the Lord that made vs and that formed vs from the womb, but follow after some small streams of this knowledg, euen such as are polluted with <note place="margin">Isay 44. 2.</note> the inuention of mans braine, placing the course of nature in the procreation of mankind (which is but an effect of Gods almightie working power,) in the roome of God himself the supream cause of al. In which respect they may not vnfitly be resēmbled to Moles that are alwaies plodding in the earth, or to swine that finding acorns vpon the ground, neuer look vp to the tree from which they fal. They forget that mans eies are therfore set in the head, which is the vpper part of the body rather then in his breast, belly, or feet, because he should be admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nished therby to lift vp his mind vnto heauen &amp; heauenly things: &amp; therefore <hi>Plato</hi> saith that mens eyes were set in a body erected &amp; looking vpward, that they might be as guids to lead thē to the knowledge of God, vpon the sight of the celestiall light, &amp; notice taken of the heauenly motions. Otherwise, although a mans skill be neuer so great, although he knoweth the way of the stars, the wals of the world, the foundations of the earth the top of the heauens, yet if he be ignorant of the creator &amp; moderatour of them al, it shall profit him nothing. But as no man is to look for graps of thornes, or figs of thistles, so we must not thinke that Epicures &amp; Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists wil once either labor to know God or open their lips to praise him, when as yet they haue not learned to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> that he is, much lesse that he is a rewarder of them that seeke him. And surely of all Sathans delusions wrought by him in the harts of vnbeleeuers, this monstrous error of Atheisme is most ougly, as that which is destitute of all shew of reason, wherby it might insinuate it selfe into the hart of man. For howsoeuer in regard of mans natural corruptiō, hunger &amp; thirst is not more incident vnto him then is error in religion &amp; aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in manners, yet for any man not to see and acknowledge by the dim candle of nature, that God is, that his prouidence watcheth ouer all, that the soule of man is immortall, and that after this life there is a place of hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinesse for the good and of torments for the wicked, is as I may term it, a supernaturall error, or rather clean against reason, religion, and nature &amp; all. The truth wherof appeareth both by the common consent of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who haue generally approued those points, as inuiolable principles &amp; maximes in nature, and also by the iudgement of the sounder sort of Philosophers and Lawmakers amongst the heathen, who knowing that all mens consciences did naturally acknowledge not onely a being of a diuine power, but a subiection also therunto pretended that their Lawes and superstitions came from some one or other of their supposed gods and goddes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: as <hi>Minos</hi> King of the Cretensians made the people beleeue that hee had receiued his lawes of <hi>Iupiter, Lycurgus</hi> the Lacedemonian lawmaker of Apollos oracle, <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> a Romane king of <hi>Aegeria</hi> the Nimph, and so the rest of others. And in truth, they that deny the diuine essence, what doe they but deny themselues, and the being of all things in the world besides? For as <hi>Aratus</hi> the heathen poet teacheth, which <note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> is also conformed vnto vs by the Apostle <hi>Paul, In God we liue, mooue and haue our being:</hi> so that with out him it is impossible we should haue any being one moment of an houre. And it is strange to consider how these reasonable beasts (for men I dare not call them) standing so much vpon reason &amp; sense as they would seeme to do, cannot inreason conceiue that this great variety and exquisite order, which they behold and see
<pb facs="185"/>
in nature &amp; natural things, must of necessity haue some superior cause from which they receiued both their first being, &amp; their continuall perseruation in the same. When they look vpon any excellent picture, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently iudge, as the truth is, that is was wrought by some cunning painter, &amp; euery curious building leadeth all men to the consideration of some exquisite master builder that framed it. And shall not the view of the world, &amp; the knowledge of so many admirable things therin as are subiect to al our senses, constraine vs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a superior cause and creator of them all? Doth any ship sayle his right course without a Pilot? or is there any city well gouerned without a Magistrate? And shall any surmize, that the celestiall lights could obserue their right motion without the direction of him that made them? or that the terrestriall globe of the earth could continue so well ordered by the course of nature, were it not that all things are vpholden by him that framed them all? But such is the blockishnes of these Epicurian beasts that they will beleeue nothing but that which they may see with their eies, and take knowledge of by the light of their bodies. As though, if their eies were plucked out of their head there could be no sun in the heauens, nor light in the world because them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues were in darkenesse and could see nothing. How many things are there in nature which cannot be seen, &amp; yet no man maketh any question of their being, no not they themselues, who notwithstāding deny that there is any diuine nature, any immortallsoule, Angel or spirit, because they are not visible &amp; subiect to sight. Can any of them see the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ind, look vpon the voice of man, behold the sweet harmony of musick? Nay, can they take a view of the hearts in their bodies, or of the braines in their heads? Are they therfore without heart &amp; brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse? Surely it seemeth they are cleane voyd of braine, wit, and common sense, that nayle all their beliefe so fast to the sight of their bodily eyes. And yet were it so that they would not most wilfully cōtradict theeuidence of their owne hearts, they should there behold with the eies of their mind as it were in a christal glasse that <hi>which may be knowne of God.</hi> Nay the holy Ghost procedeth further, and telleth vs, that euen our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies may and doe after asort looke vpon the <hi>eternall power and Godhead, which are seene by the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 19</note>
      <hi>creation of the world, being viewed in the workes thereof.</hi> And because it may so fall out by the iust iudgement of God, that these beetle eied Atheists may aswell be depriued of their bodily eies, as they want the <note place="margin">Psal. 20.</note> sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t of their mindes, the creator and Lord of the whole world, hath set such marks of his Deitie in his works that such as haue onely the direction of nature may euen with their eies closed vp, touch &amp; handle him ifthey will but <hi>grope after him, in whom we al liue, moo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e and haue our being.</hi> What should I presse them with the certaine testimony of their owne harts and consciences, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch will they, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ill they, draw them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o a fear full acknowledgement of the mighty power of God, whensoeuer either by his terrible voice of thunder he sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Act. 17, 27</note> their hearts, or by some irrecouerable disease, as a messenger of death, he summo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth them to appeare be fore his tribunall seate and throne of iustice. But there needeth no other proofe to conuince thē then the words of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r own mouths. For doe not their horrible oathes wherby they blaspheme the maiesty of God, &amp; asmuch as lyeth in them teare him in pieces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare witnes against themselues that the Lord wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m they despite in that moustrous manner hath a being, howsoeuer otherwise they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ny the same? And if no reason wil sinke into their brains, yet me thinks the weight of Gods iudgements which haue from time to time seased extraordinarily v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> these Atheists that haue sprung vpin the world, should cause them more seriously to consider of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable estate.</p>
   <p>It is reported of <hi>Protagoras,</hi> who was one of the first of that stamp, that being banished from Athens, and his books publikely burnt, he was drowned in the sea as he sailed into S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cilia. <hi>Diagoras</hi> was violently stain by <note place="margin">Protagoras D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>agoras. Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urus. Lucianus.</note> certain men whom the Athenians had hired with mony for that purpose, <hi>Epicurus</hi> also, who placed his fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in corporall pleasures, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed miserably in a vessell of hot water, after that he had bin fourteene daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extremely tormented with the stone in the bladder. <hi>Lucianus,</hi> surnamed by his own coūtrymen the <hi>blas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemer,</hi> as he behaued himselfe most currishly in barking both against the gods of the heathen, and against Christ Iesus the Sauior of the world, so his end was thereafter by being torn in peces &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oured of dogs. <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> the elder denying the immortality of the soule of man and placing Nature acreature in steade of God the <note place="margin">Plinie Sen.</note> Creatour, whilest he was ouer curious inseaching out the cause of the burning of Etna, was choaked with the smoke that issued from it. A iust punishment for him to end his life by smoke, who esteemed his soule to bee no better then a little vapour. <hi>Cassius</hi> being aprofessed Scholler of <hi>Epicurus</hi> &amp; <hi>Brutus</hi> most brutishly railing vpon the prouidence of God because his enterprises against <hi>Caesar</hi> succeeded not to his desire, were both ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with the reuenging hand of God, the one of them causing his seruant to be his Butcher, &amp; the other em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bruing <note place="margin">Cassius. Brutus.</note> his hands in his own blood. The like befell <hi>Lucretius</hi> a most notorious Atheist, who being depri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed of the right vse of his senses, abused by him to the denying of God and of all religion, slew himselfe in the midst of <note place="margin">Lucretius. Pope Iohn 13.</note> his madnesse. Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>13.</hi> may worthily be enrolled in this band, as he that was not ashamed to put vp a supplication to the diuell to send him good luck at dice: and one day in the midst of his iollity he tooke a cup of wine and dranke to the diuell. But by the tust <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udgement of God he was stabbed in with a dagger by one who tooke him commiting adul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ery with his wife, so that he died thereof within eight daies after. <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth <note place="margin">Pope Leo. 10.</note> Pope of that name, who thought there was neither heauen nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ell after this life, and blasphemously said that that the Gospell of Christ was but a fable, was sodainely striken dead with an extreame laughter which hee fell into by reason of news brought him of the slaughter and ouerthrow of certaine French men in Italie by his
<pb facs="185"/>
meanes. The French histories make mention of one <hi>Frances Rabelais,</hi> who hauing sucked in this poison of A <note place="margin">F. Rabela is</note> theisme made a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cke at alreligion, as <hi>Lucretius</hi> his forerunner had done before him: but the selfe same author &amp; defender of true religion, that tooke from <hi>Lucretius</hi> al vse of reason, did so depriue this beast of of all sense, that as heled a brutish life, so he died like a swine in the midst of his drunkennes, deriding those that spake vnto him of God &amp; of his mercy. <hi>Iodellus</hi> likewise a French poet, &amp; a professed Atheist, as hee <note place="margin">Iodell us.</note> gaue himselfin his life time to write tragedies, so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he made a right tragicall end. For hauing through gluto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; riot wasted his patrimony and wealth, he fell into such extreme neede, that he was miserably famished for want of sustenance, It would aske a long time to set downe the iudgements of God that haue iustly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken sundry others of the abominable crew: only I wil rehearse one history worthy our knowledge concerning this matter, mentioned by <hi>Enguerran</hi> in the second volume of his histories. In the reigne of <hi>Lewes</hi> the <hi>11.</hi> and vpon the fift day of Iune 1464. there happened (saith hee) a wonderfull accident in the palace at Paris, whilest there was a controuersie in pleading between the Bishop of Angiers and a rich citizen of that towne whom the Bishop accused of notorious Atheisme, namely, that he had said in the hearing of many, that he be leeued not there was any God or diuell, either any heauen or hell. Now as the Bishops aduocat rehearsedthese <note place="margin">A citizen of Angiers.</note> words the place wherin they were pleading trēbledvery sore, in somuch that with the shaking a stone fel down frō the top to the bottom, but hurt no body, albeit they were taken with a greatfeare. Wherupon they went all pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sently out out of the place vntill the next day when the matter was to be heard againe. And then also the said roome began to shake againe, so that one of the sommers of the chamber sprang out of the mortesse, and bowed downward two feet, but fell not. Al that were present supposed they should haue died no other death, which caused them so violently to rush out, that for hast some left their hats, some their caps, some their slip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers behind them, neither durst a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y plead more there before it was throughly mended. Now albeit <hi>Enguer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>an</hi> speaketh nothing of the determination of that suite, yet forasmuch as nothing commeth to passe by hapha zard (as they vse to speak) but all things are guided by the good prouidence of God, it is out of question, that the Lord would teach vs hereby, how we should detest and abhor such execrable thoughts &amp; speeches, seeing the very dumb creatures, as the stones, the timber, and the earth it selfe (which of it owne nature is vnmoue able) were it so affected with the horror thereof, that they could not abide it so much as to heare it spoken of without shaking. But here some will say vnto me, that this labor might well haue binspared, considering that the sunshine of the Gospel which breaketh forth so cleerely in all quarters of the land will quickly discry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such ougly bird should once begin to pepe out of the shell within the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>est of this Iland. And if the Athenians being meere heathen men banished <hi>Protagoras</hi> out of the territories, and burnt the Books in a publik place because in the beginning of one of them he calledthe deity into question, we may not think but that in this land ouer spread with the knowledge of God, this monstrous brood shal be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ipped in the head so soone as euer it shal dare to shew it self. Indeed a man would thinke that Atheisme should not once bee dreamed of, or named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, considering that we liue in those times of which the Prophetforetold, <hi>That the earth should</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isaiah 11. 9. &amp; 54. 13. Ier 31. 34.</note>
      <hi>be ful of the knowledge of the Lord's the waters that couer the sea, that all the children of the Church should be taught of the Lord, so that one neighbor shal not teach another, saying, know the Lord, for they shal al know me from the least of them to the greatest, saieth the Lord.</hi> So a man would think that France, hauing bin for these these <hi>30.</hi> yeares &amp; vpward almost continually scourged with ciuil wars, &amp; that for the cause of religion, should be so far from being steinedwith the least spot of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme, as that it might now at the length truly say with the Prophet <hi>Dauid. It is good for mee that I was afflicted, for therby I haue learned tokeepe thy law.</hi> And yet both this our authour and some <note place="margin">Psal. 119. 71</note> other of that nation, knowing that this infection haue sezed vpon many of their country men, haue laboured by their writings to suppresse the same. And surely it is greatly to be feared, that as their disguised attire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the bodies of many of our people &amp; maketh them deformed, so this poison of Athe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sme hath praised i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eanrrow seas &amp; islanded in the harts of no small number, to their vtter d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>structiō both of body and soule, Neither is this the feare of some few with out any ground, but of a great many wise &amp; godly Christians, who seeing the generall propha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>esse of mens li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es almost euery where, both publikely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ry out against the present infection, &amp; plainly bewaile the future euils that necessarily follow the same. And albeit peraduenture there be noneamongst vs, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t are so far gone in Atheisme, as <hi>Ligneroles</hi> a French Courtier of late dayes was, who i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> said to haue made open profession thereof, yet if the tree may be iudged by the fruites, &amp; the outward ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of mens liues do shew shew the inward affections of their hearts, he that hath but halfe an eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay see, that there are a great many amongst vs of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se foolish men of whom Dauid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>peaketh. <hi>Who say in their</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 14. 1.</note>
      <hi>hearts that there is no God.</hi> In the forefront of which company, the students of <hi>Machi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uels</hi> principles &amp; practis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rs of his precepts may worthily bee raunged. This bad fellow whose works are no lesse accounted of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his followers, then were <hi>Apollos</hi> Oracles amongst the Heathen, nay then the sacred Scriptures are among sound Christians, blushed not to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch out these horrible blasp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>emies against purereligió, &amp; soagainst God the Author thereof, namely, <hi>That the religion of the heathen made them stout and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, wheras Christia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> religion maketh the professors therof base minded, timerous, and fit to</hi>
      <pb facs="186"/>
      <hi>become a prey to euery one: that since men fell from the religion of the Heathen, they became so corrupt that they would beleeue neither God nor the Diuel, that Moses so possessed the land of Iudea, as the Gothes did by strong hande vsurp part of the Romane Empire.</hi> These &amp; such like positions are sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed out by this hel hound sometime against true religion, other whiles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gianst the religion and Church of Rome, sometimes also taxing the religion of the heathen, of falsehoode ad consinage, so that in truth he would haue all religiō to be of like accompt with his disciples, except it be so far forth as the pretēce &amp; shew of religion may serue to set forward &amp; effect their wicked policies. And for this cause he setteth down this rule for euery Prince and Magistrate to frame his religion by, namely, that <hi>he should pretend to bee very religious and deuout, although it be but in hypocrisie.</hi> And to this hee addeth a second precept no lesse impious, that a <hi>Prince should with tooth and naile maietaine false miracles and vntruth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in religion, so long as his people may thereby be kept in greater obedience.</hi> Now what fruits we are to expect from the students of this profession, let all men iudge that haue any sparkes of pure religion glowing in their hearts. Vnto these may be added, such as tread in the steps of <hi>Lamech,</hi> who derided the iudgement of God vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n <hi>Caine:</hi> such as walke in the waies of <hi>Ismael,</hi> who mocked <hi>Isaack</hi> inregard of the promise: &amp; such as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> irreligious persons were of whom <hi>Peter</hi> speaketh, who in iesting wise asked what was become of the promise of Christ his comming to iudgement. That there are such amongst vs, euen in these times wherin we li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> the testimony which one of that crew g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue lately of himselfe when the heauie hand of God by sicknesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him to giue him an accompt of his desolate life. He being one day admōished of his friends to lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d course of life, which otherwise would bring him to vtter destruction, scoffing returned them this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere: <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h</hi> (quoth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e) <hi>what is he better that dyeth in his bed then he that endeth his life at Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn?</hi> And being f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rther vrged to doubt the losse of his soule in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l fire for eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> although he feared not death in this world, he replied, <hi>Hell? What talke you of Hell to me? I k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>owe if I once come there, I shall haue the cōpany of better then my selfe: I shal also meet with some knaues in that place, and so long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> I shall not sit there alone, my care is the lesse. But you are mad folks</hi> (quoth he) <hi>for if I fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the Iudges of the Bench no more then I dread the iudgmēts of God, I would before I slept diue into one karles bags or other, &amp; make merry with the shels I found in them so long as they would last.</hi> The voice of a meere Atheist, and so afterwards he pronounced of himselfe when he was checked in conscience by the mighty hand of GOD. And yet this fellow in his life time and in the midst of his greatest ruffe, had the Presse at commandement to publish his lasciuious Pamphlets, wherby he infected the hearts of many yong Gentlemen and others with his poisonful platforms of loue, &amp; diuelsshed discourses of fancies fits? so that their minds were no lesse possessed with the toyes of his irreligious braine, then their chamber's &amp; stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stred with his lewd and wanton books. And if the rest of his crew may be permitted so easily as he did without controlment to instil their venimous inuentions into the minds of our English youth by means of printing, what other thing can we looke for, but that the whole land should speedily be ouerflown with the dead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly waters of al i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pieties, when as the flood gates of Atheism are thus set wide open? Are they not grown alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to this boldnes, that they dare to gird at the greatest personages of all estates and callings vnder the fables of sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge beasts, not sparing the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ry dead that lie in their graues, that the holy Apostles, the blessed virgin M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ry the glorious kingdome of Heauen it selfe must be brought in as it were vpon a stage to play their seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts, according as the humour of euery irreligious head shal dispose them? And wheras godly learned men, and some that haue spoken of their owne experience, haue in their books that are allowed by authoritie, tearmed Stage plaiers and Theaters, <hi>The school of abuse, the schoole of baudery, the nest of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel &amp; sinke of al sin, the chaire of pestilāce, the pōpe of the diuel, the soueraign place of Satan,</hi> yet this commendation of them hath lately passed the Presse that they are rare exercises of vertue. It were too l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g to set down the Catalogue of those lewd &amp; lasciuious books, which haue mustred themselues of late yeers in Pauls Churchyard, as chosen souldiers ready to fight vnder the diuels banner: of which it may be truly said that they preuaile no lesse (if not more) to the vpholding of Atheisme in this light of the Gospell, then the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend of Lies, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on of Burdeaux, King Arthur,</hi> with the rest of that rabble, were of force to maintaine Popery in the daies of ignorance. Wherfore my humble sute is to all such as may by vertue of authority stay the violēt course of Atheisme daily spred abroad by these pernicious Pamphlets, that they would lay to their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand for the spedy redresse therof. And as for those that reape the gaine of iniquity by the sale of such in fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ious stuffe, oh what a sweet smelling sacrifice should they offer vnto the Lord, if they would gather al such h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tful Books together, &amp; cause them to passe through the fire in the midst of that yard, where now they are so commonly sold. Hereby it would come to passe, that the land being purged of so great contagion as droppeth out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of such godlesse braines, the Lord would withdraw his be any hand, which now many waies pres<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>seth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sore, the preaching of the Gospell would preuaile mightily, as it did in Ephesus after the like sacrifice, <note place="margin">Act. 19 19. 20.</note> and yong Gentlemen and others would employ good houres, vpon better studies: which the Lord grant for his mercies sake,</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>