<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST
Excellent, Illustrious, and vertuous
Prince, HENRIE, eldest Sonne to our Soueraigne
Lord the King, and Heire apparant to the King∣domes
of Great Britaine, &amp;c.
({inverted ⁂})</title>
           <author>Palmer, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113921_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08874</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19156</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113921</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST
Excellent, Illustrious, and vertuous
Prince, HENRIE, eldest Sonne to our Soueraigne
Lord the King, and Heire apparant to the King∣domes
of Great Britaine, &amp;c.
({inverted ⁂})</title>
                 <author>Palmer, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An essay of the meanes hovv to make our trauailes, into forraine countries, the more profitable and honourable</title>
                 <author>Palmer, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 131, 1 page, 4 folded tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST
Excellent, Illustrious, and vertuous
Prince, HENRIE, eldest Sonne to our Soueraigne
Lord the King, and Heire apparant to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
of Great Britaine, &amp;c.
({inverted ⁂})</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering with what libertie and
Applause, Princes, in times past,
vndertook voluntarie trauaile &amp;
aduentures into forraine parts:
and how of latter dayes those
Illustrious Stemmes of noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
(<hi>I</hi> know not now by what custome restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
of that recreation and renowne) haue not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
improued their pretious times at
home vnto no lesse rent of commoditie &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendablenes,
by suffering themselues to be tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
vp and delighted in the faculties and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of diuine and humane things: I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed
(most excellent and gratious Prince) hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
to prefer, vnto your rare protectiō and view,
<pb facs="5"/>
this Essay, of the means how to make the trauailes
of other men (who for the good of this kingdom
wherein they liue so happily, their better seruice
to his Maiestie, and making of themselues more
Compleat in all things, haue faire libertie &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
to aduenture trauaile) somewhat more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
and honorable, not only before trauaile, but
in the <hi>interim</hi> of trauaile, and after their returnes.
First, because your highnesse is (in all happie pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilitie)
to be a most noble Iudge of all mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts
in this point, rather then to make experience
your selfe therin, vnlesse in Martial causes: wherin
<hi>I</hi> know not whether <hi>I</hi> may account your royall
Auncestors (Princes of this State) to bee more
happie alwaies in their good successe, or in the
faithfulnesse of their voluntarie great traines. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
for that the people of great <hi>Britaine</hi> (of
all other famous and glorious Nations separated
from the maine Continent of the world) are by
so much the more interessed to become Trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,
by how much the necessitie of euerie seuerall
estate of men doth require that, for their better
aduancement. Lastly, in regard this subiect hath
not worne an English habite hertofore, (from the
custom dew to Princes in the Novelty of things)
<hi>I</hi> thought it my dutie (vnder the compasse of my
obligation and seruice vnto your Highnesse) to
make a present hereof (although but meanly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled
and suited) and in most humble wise to
<pb facs="5"/>
beseech the greatnesse of your Excellencie, to
fauour &amp; patronize the same. Which gratiousnes
<hi>I</hi> must euer acknowledge (sir) to proceede from
the cleare fountain of your generous, ingenuous,
and princely disposition vnto all bountie, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and vertue: and the world alreadie knowes,
that your singular towardlines, to euerie good &amp;
perfect thing, is such, that neither can it or is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to be paralleled of any in the world (so long as
your Highnesse continews in these religious ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
&amp; studious paths, which God graunt) nor
circumscribed within the Kings most Ample
kingdomes, and States, but is knowen, feared, or
admired in forrain parts. The which as it is a most
Soueraine and inexpressible blessing vnto all, of
these his Maiesties Dominions: So, vnto mee, it
shal be the onely studie &amp; care to make expressiō
of all dutifull alleageance: And in the meane
seafō to pray vnto God cōtinually for your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
to continue for euer in health, felicitie and
euerlasting glorie, And rest during life</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your <hi>HIGHNES</hi>
most humble and
deuoted Seruant,
THOMAS PALMER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>