<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A description of the Chariot or Pompees bridge, inuented
to giue an assault to the Halfe-Moone of the Spaniards
at Ostend, as it appears in the plot of the towne.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113561_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08577</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18895</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113561</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A description of the Chariot or Pompees bridge, inuented
to giue an assault to the Halfe-Moone of the Spaniards
at Ostend, as it appears in the plot of the towne.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true historie of the memorable siege of Ostend : and what passed on either side, from the beginning of the siege, vnto the yeelding vp of the towne. Conteining the assaults, alarums, defences, inuentions of warre, mines, counter-mines and retrenchments, combats of galleys, and sea-fights, with the portrait of the towne: and also what passed in the Ile of Cadsant, and at the siege of Sluice, after the comming of Count Maurice. Translated out of French into English, by Edward Grimeston</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 152, 145-224, 8 pages, 2 folded plates, maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="description_of_siege_tower">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A description of the Chariot or Pompees bridge, inuented
to giue an assault to the Halfe-Moone of the Spaniards
at Ostend, as it appears in the plot of the towne.</head>
   <list>
      <item>A. The Bridge being let downe.</item>
      <item>B. The Mast against the which the Bridge was raised, being 150.
foote high.</item>
      <item>C. The vpper part of the Bridge, made of great Roapes and Cables
of Musket proofe.</item>
      <item>D. The neather part of the Bridge made likewise of Roapes of
Musket proofe.</item>
      <item>E. A Poste like vnto the beame of a Wagon, to draw the Bridge vp,
and to let it downe.</item>
      <item>F. Foure-score horses to draw this Chariot.</item>
      <item>G. Wheeles eight foote broad, and 14. or 15. high, the which are
exceeding strong, and did cost 300. Ducats a peece.</item>
      <item>H. Heere Musketiers should be placed to shoote at them of the
Towne, and to keepe them from cutting of the Roape.</item>
   </list>
   <p>The Arch-duke after he had done what he could to take <hi>Ostend,</hi> or
to annoy the besieged, by the inuention of an <hi>Italian</hi> Ingeneur named
<hi>Pompee,</hi> he caused a Chariot to be made, or a Bridge called <hi>Helwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi>
or <hi>Loywagen,</hi> or <hi>Pompees Chariot,</hi> by the inuentors name, to
go vnto the assault at the Spanish Halfe-moone, the which was made
and held by them of the towne: the Bridge is 100. paces long &amp; 16.
broad: on the which ten may march in front, it hath foure Wheeles
euery one 8. foote broad, and 14. or 15. high: at the end of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot
there is a tree or mast 150. foote high, by meanes whereof the
bridge is drawne vp and let downe with poollies. Their desseigne was
to fasten Anchors on either side of the Halfe-moone, against the
which 80. horses should draw the bridge, as it is set downe in the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.
They of the Towne hauing intelligence thereof, made a high
Palyssadoe with trauerses of masts like vnto Gibets, to receiue the
vpper part of the bridge, being let downe: the besieged seeing this
bridge approach neere vnto the Halfe-moone, they brake one of the
Wheeles with a Canon-shot, so as it was of no effect, which made thē
of the towne call it the Cowards-bridge.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>