<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>B., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113208_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07453</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1784</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113208</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon exhorting to pitie the poore : Preached the. xv. of Nouember. Anno. 1571. at Christes Churche in London. By Henry Bedel uicar there, which treatise may well be called The mouth of the poore</title>
                 <author>Bedel, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Awdely (Sampson), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHere as some for the trial of their wyttes, and proofe of knowledge, are mooued to pen their studies &amp; trauels, which they do most exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitely, and others for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of their country, some tyme of their own labours set forth bookes, and some of other mens workes in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toung do open the meanyng, and all I trust to Gods glory, and the furtherance of knowledge: Euen so I, not of my selfe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by any worthynes I know in my selfe, neither to purchase prayse of men (for this my dede is nothing praise worthy to me, for if ought be fauty, that is to me due, and if any thing be to purpose, that was &amp; is Gods worke in me) haue laboured as farre as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie might teache, neither addyng nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minishing to or from the wordes I spake in the pulpet, to write and pen somwhat for rhe help of the poore. VVhich the rather I haue done, for that then I was requyred by my friend so to do. VVhich purpose or sum of matter, though of an other it might be more excellently done, then of me it is in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise done: yet thinking that all men wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
<pb facs="3"/>
my god hart and well meaning to the poore, it made me the more bolde to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise thys matter, to further their poore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state that want, and so to put in print those rude wordes that then by preaching I spake.</p>
   <p>And thus hopyng that al men wyll accept my sylly good wyll in this my labour, vnto which I may speake as Ouid did, Vade sed in cultus, I leaue the succes vnto God of this paynes I haue taken, as wel tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching my selfe, as also for the poore for whom I haue spoken.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>