<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right vvorshipfull, Brian Stapleton of Carleton, in the Coun∣tie of Yorke Esquire, the heauens graunt health, content, and after life, euerla∣sting happinesse.</title>
           <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113739_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11169</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113739</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right vvorshipfull, Brian Stapleton of Carleton, in the Coun∣tie of Yorke Esquire, the heauens graunt health, content, and after life, euerla∣sting happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasant historie of Ornatus and Artesia : Wherein is contained the vniust raigne of Thaeon King of Phrygia. Who with his sonne Lenon, (intending Ornatus death,) right heire to the crowne, was afterwardes slaine by his owne seruants, and Ornatus after many extreame miseries, crowned King</title>
                 <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right vvorshipfull, <hi>Brian Stapleton</hi> of <hi>Carleton,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Yorke</hi> Esquire, the heauens graunt health, content, and after life, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His vnpollisht Historie Right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, wanting the Ornament of Eloquence fit for rare inuention, presenteth it selfe in his naturall and selfe expressing forme, in well applied words, not in tedious borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed phrases: wherein neither the lewde can finde examples to sute their dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the vertuous no tearmes to discontent them, nor the well affected any cause of offence. Here shall you see lust Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing, auarice, guilty of murther, &amp; dignity, seeking his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with vsurpation, yet all subuerted by vertue. Which I am bold to present vnto you, not for the woorth, but to expresse my good will, which is not vnmindfull in some sort to gratifie the manifold curtesies I haue receiued of you. And although it be altogither not worth estimation, and to be accounted no requitall for so many good turnes, yet I desire you to accept the same in steed of a better, and the summe of that which my abilitie at this time can affoord: Which beeing but a fancie, vouchsafe to esteem, though not agreeing with your grauitie, yet (as many both Noble and wise in such like matters haue done) to be red for recreation. As the value of the gift expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth not the affection of the giuer, nor the outward show the inward meaning, so I trust you will esteeme my good wil, not
<pb facs="3"/>
by the worthinesse hereof, but the qualitie of my well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted intent, which is deuoted vnto you in the bands of perfect good will, and will be readie to shewe it selfe constant in any triall you shall make thereof. And for that I know your wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and curtesie to be such, as that you wil not misconceiue me, but esteeme well hereof, and my affection to you, to bee exprest in the dedicatiō, I haue aduētured to dedicate the same to your protection, though altogither vndeseruing the title of your patronage, which your further kindnesse shall binde me hereafter to requite the same, with some worthier worke col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by my labors. Thus being loth to be tedious and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome vnto you, I commit this silly present to your gentle acceptation, and your selfe, to the gratious protection of the Almightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships most readie at commaund,</hi> Emanuell Ford.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>