<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTV∣OVS YONG GENTLE∣MAN, AND HIS VVORTHILY RE∣spected friend, Mr. Thomas Edgworth, vnder Treasurer of Windsor, Health and Con∣tent in his owne Person, and in the happy fruition of his vertuous Wife.</title>
           <author>Niccholes, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113190_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08179</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18514</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113190</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTV∣OVS YONG GENTLE∣MAN, AND HIS VVORTHILY RE∣spected friend, Mr. Thomas Edgworth, vnder Treasurer of Windsor, Health and Con∣tent in his owne Person, and in the happy fruition of his vertuous Wife.</title>
                 <author>Niccholes, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse, of marriage and vviuing : and of the greatest mystery therein contained: how to choose a good wife from a bad. An argument of the dearest vse, but the deepest cunning that man may erre in: which is, to cut by a thrid betweene the greatest good or euill in the world. Pertinent to both sexes, and conditions, as well those already gone before, as shortly to enter this honest society. By Alex. Niccholes, Batchelour in the art he neuer yet put in practise</title>
                 <author>Niccholes, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Becket, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS YONG GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN, AND HIS VVORTHILY RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected friend, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Edgworth,</hi> vnder Treasurer of Windsor, Health and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in his owne Person, and in the happy fruition of his vertuous Wife.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, your felicity, the highest top of enioyment in this kind, is become the aime, that the practicke Art in this schoole of direction leuelleth at, you being already instated (with enuy and admiration) in that blisse, which others may thus toyle after in most beseeming circumstances (by many degrees) to come short of: VVhen I enter this course of life (as, for ought I know, I may one day marry) be it my highest ambition, with all my directions, to haue one to be a neere imitator of her so many Religious and Morall vertues, for whose happy continuance my best wishes shall be spent, that she may long continue yours, to make you a father of happy and vndoubted children;
<pb facs="3"/>
sonnes for the earth, and Saints for heauen, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying vpon your head all the comforts in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant: And for this Treatise, which, by your dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, comes forth to direct others to that modell of happinesse wherein you stand eminent, may it haue that successe with all, that it hath had approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with you, and as kinde entertainement with the world as those best creatures, the subiect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in their perfection deserue, which are the Seed and Seminary thereof, and which (by this meanes) haue maintained that lasting, and yet vn-ended, war against those two arch, and vnwearied aduersaries of Mankind <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> the wasters thereof, and consumers of all sublunary things, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan their siege against the first man that liued, and haue euer since held on without league, or impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, for the space of these 5500 yeares and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and which shall go on and continue the siedge to the end thereof, and consummation of all things: VVherein if it shall be so happy (beyond expectation) the paine thereof hath beene well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, and your encouragement fortunately se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded, which howsoeuer I leaue it to the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and you to your hearts best wishes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>By him that intirely is dedicated yours:</hi> ALEX. NICCHOLES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>