<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVL SIR RICHARD MARTEN KNIGHT, MASTER OF HER MAIESTIES MYNT, ALDERMAN, and twise Lord Maior of the Citie of London.</title>
           <author>Maxey, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113159_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07301</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17695</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVL SIR RICHARD MARTEN KNIGHT, MASTER OF HER MAIESTIES MYNT, ALDERMAN, and twise Lord Maior of the Citie of London.</title>
                 <author>Maxey, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nevv instuction [sic] of plowing and setting of corne, handled in manner of a dialogue betweene a ploughman and a scholler : Wherein is proued plainely that plowing and setting, is much more profitable and lesse chargeable, than plowing and sowing. By Edvvard Maxey. Gent</title>
                 <author>Maxey, Edward, gent</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL SIR RICHARD MARTEN KNIGHT, MASTER OF HER MAIESTIES MYNT, ALDERMAN, <hi>and twise Lord Maior of the Citie of London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well knowne (right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull) how great a benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and furtherer you haue been to many good workes and profitable to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: for by your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, the inhabitants of sundrie parts of England and Wales, haue gained for many yeeres, many thousand pounds yeerely. How much then those poore are bound to praise God for you, and such as further the like good works, all wise men acquainted with your great charge and trauell can testifie, which I thought worthy to be published, and left in memorie for other ages yet to come, to your great commendation and incouragement of others, to follow your good example. And now (right Worshipfull) calling to minde my former time spent in Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie;
<pb facs="3"/>the most sweete and comfortable kind of life to all vertuous minds (that <hi>Adams</hi> poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie can enioy) if it were not for the wickednes of seruants, who discourage many industrious minds; and seeing an vnskilfull Pamphlet (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>God speede the Plough</hi>) to be so long vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, set foorth by some Nouice in Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, as should appeare as well by his writing, as that he saith in the same, it is none of his profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; which hath and may doe much hurt by disswading men from so profitable an imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the setting of Corne; which when I considered, and remembring that I had spent the most part of thirtie yeeres in Husbandrie: I aduentured to publish this little Treatise, for the instruction of those that will be perswaded to practise this kind of excellent and profitable worke: which with my selfe I desire to be protected by your accustomed lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fauour towards me.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to be commaunded, <hi>EDVV. MAXEY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>