<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in GOD, RICHARD, Lord Arch bishop of Yorke his Grace, Primate of ENGLAND and Metropolitane; And one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Privie Councell.</title>
           <author>Odingsells, Charles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113411_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08457</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18782</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113411</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in GOD, RICHARD, Lord Arch bishop of Yorke his Grace, Primate of ENGLAND and Metropolitane; And one of his MAIESTIES most Honourable Privie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Odingsells, Charles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pearle of perfection sought after by Charles Odingsells, Doctour of Divinitie</title>
                 <author>Odingsells, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Williams, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in GOD, RICHARD, Lord Arch bishop of <hi>Yorke</hi> his Grace, Primate of ENGLAND and <hi>Metropolitane; And one of his</hi> MAIESTIES <hi>most Honourable Privie Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are not a few, who with NAAMAN the <hi>Syrian</hi> take greater delight in <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Tharpar,</hi> rivers of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mascus,</hi> than in <hi>Iordane,</hi> wherein our Saviour was baptized, than in the waters of <hi>Israel,</hi> the holy waters of <hi>Sailo,</hi> which run gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; than in the living waters of the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ezek. 47 9.</note> which given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> to them which
<pb facs="3"/>mooue therein. These are they who after the vulgar estimation, preposterously judge the fine meale of pure literature to be course bran, and their own course bran of humane knowledge and observation to be fine meale: who with <hi>Aesops</hi> Cocke refuse the pearle, and choose the barley corne. Such I desire not to please, but those who are <hi>meliore luto, of a better mould and temper,</hi> of sounder resolution and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The argument of perfection, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be intreated of, is handled by me, not as I would, much lesse as it requireth, but so as by reason of my bodily infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and other defects I could. I haue propounded this briefe indigest worke, as a short modell and briefe draught to be curiously polished and embellished by some others, to whom God hath beene pleased to giue a greater measure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, with more health and strength of bodie, and withall a richer Librarie, a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall helpe not in the last place requisite. For surely as in other Sciences and arts, so also in our transcendent Science of Theologie, the Philosophers rule is true,
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:<note place="margin">Arist. polit. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>12.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>He that shall excell in his worke, must haue excellent tooles to worke withall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the meane time, I am bold to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent unto your <hi>Grace</hi> this <hi>imperfect worke of perfection,</hi> in token of my dutifull and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble respect to your <hi>Lordship,</hi> our most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Metropolitane</hi> and <hi>Diocesan.</hi> To whom wee under your <hi>Graces</hi> jurisdiction doe by good right owe all canonicall obedience and observance: unto whom I in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular doe earnestly desire and wish all spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and corporall happinesse here on earth; and after, everlasting fruition of eternall glorie and felicitie in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces in all humble dutie to command, <hi>CHARLES ODINGSELLS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>