<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOVRE vpon the figure before going.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113605_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03768</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13888</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113605</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOVRE vpon the figure before going.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent treatise of the begynnyng of heresyes in oure tyme, compyled by the Reuerend Father in God Stanislaus Hosius Byshop of Wormes in Prussia. To the moste renomed Prynce Lorde Sigismund myghtie Kyng of Poole, greate Duke of Luten and Russia, Lorde and heyre of all Prussia, Masouia, Samogitia &amp;c. Translated out of Laten in to Englyshe by Richard Shacklock M. of Arte, and student of the ciuil lawes, and intituled by hym: The hatchet of heresies</title>
                 <author>Hozjusz, Stanisław</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Diest (Coppens van Diest), Aegidius (Gillis)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 95, 9 leaves, illustrations (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOVRE vpon the figure before going.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>Who planted this tree, which there is set oute?</l>
      <l>Sathan the sower of syn withoute doute.</l>
      <l>The rote is rayling: but can you tell why?</l>
      <l>Take away rayling and heretykes dy.</l>
      <l>
         <note place="margin">Sampson Humfrey Cole. with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>The body is rebellion: wherefore can you tell?</l>
      <l>For a cap they be redy their Prince to expell.</l>
      <l>The braunces is blodshed: knowe you the cause?</l>
      <l>Thei wold kyl (if thei could) al without lawes.</l>
      <l>But why with lyes arre so loden the leaues?</l>
      <l>Ah heresie with lyes all the worlde deceaues.</l>
      <l>The apples be atheisme: what doth that meane?</l>
      <l>Heresie remoueth religion cleane.</l>
      <l>wherefore dothe Sathan so sowrely loke?</l>
      <l>Oh he is angry at Hosius boke.</l>
      <l>what meaneth the crosse, which here you do carue?</l>
      <l>The badge of truth which neuer doth swarue.</l>
      <l>what meaneth the cock which here I do fynde?</l>
      <l>The badge of heretykes which waue with the wynde.</l>
      <l>But what doth the ape vnder the cock?</l>
      <l>Signifieth heretykes, which holy thinges mock▪</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>