<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113224_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08121</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18482</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113224</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The palme of Christian fortitude. Or The glorious combats of Christians in Iaponia. Taken out of letters of the Society of Iesus from thence. Anno 1624</title>
                 <author>Rodrigues, Jo~ao</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard (Buree), Jeanne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 170, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>HEre wrapt vp in a few sheetes of ordinary paper, the Trās<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latour offers thee, ò Englād, with a present of inestimable price, with a carkanet of the richest gēmes the Orient euer sent into Europe, <hi>Iewells of Iaponian pearle</hi> within the sea of persecution, bred of the dew of Diuine grace, infused into soules, that by exact puritie of life, and by magnanimous contempt of all earthly obiects, were euer open to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and ready to intromit his celestiall influences.</p>
   <p>This fortunate and thrice happy Church was primitiuely planted by
<pb facs="3"/>the great <hi>Indian Apostle S. Xauerius,</hi> brought thither by the course of his charity, which had no other bounds but the world; watered by the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding labours of the Fathers of the <hi>Society of Iesus,</hi> the sole worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in that holy haruest for many yeares, finally manured also by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Professours of Euangelicall Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, whom their vnquencheable zeale of soules vrged to passe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Europe,</hi> ouer many vast worlds of water.</p>
   <p>As Religious profession was the parent of these Christians, so by this narration (the theater of their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues) you may see they doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate but shew thēselues a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy extract of so noble a stock, a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine offpring of so sacred a plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiō,
<pb facs="3"/>a pourtraicture of diuine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection corresponding to the high sanctimony of the Patterne. In the course of their liues so enamoured of Pouerty, so inflamed with Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, so deuoted to voluntary afflictiō of the body, to disclplines, wearing of haire clothes, extraordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stings, retired praying, dedicating themselues to the teaching of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and helping of soules, shine liuely lineaments of more then se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular sanctity, and assured markes of a Religious spirit superiour to the world. In their deathes they blaze forth rare, diuine, miraculous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of heroicall fortitude, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the peerlesse lustre of primitiue Martyrdome is renewed in these dayes, to shew the neuer decaying
<pb facs="4"/>merit of the pretious Immaculate Blood, in whose shining candour all Martyrs, auncient and recent <hi>made white their Triumphall Robes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The light of the <hi>Christian Roman Religion,</hi> which from thee, ó Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke <hi>Europe, Iaponia</hi> receaued, is here returned back againe with interest, &amp; encrease, adorned with glorious victories, which by vertue thereof to the amazement of Infidels ouer Paganisme she hath obtained; by thy Religion, I say, professing and practising veneration of Relickes, Adoration of the Crosse prayer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Saints, deuotion vnto Pardons, hearing of holy Masse, diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the Venerable Eucharist, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Confession of sinnes, the saying of Angelicall salutations to
<pb facs="4"/>the B. Virgin in a set number on beades, finally (to pretermit other points) ioint inuocation of IESVS MARIA euen till the last moment of their sacred breath; This light of Religion to the splēdour of her shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning victories improued, she sends thee back, to driue away the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heresy, that ouershads some parte of thy dominions, to discouer the blasphemy of their conceit, who thinke thy Religiō Idolatrous, and to open their eyes, that by the light of new triūphes they may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne who be the heires of <hi>Ancient Truth,</hi> and not to doubt, but in that Church is found the light of <hi>Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Faith,</hi> where the vigour of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall Fortitude by the victory of torments and death to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe
<pb facs="5"/>of Idolatrie flameth.</p>
   <p>Such barbarous varietie of cruell torments they endured, such glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious varietie of excellent vertues in their sufferings shined, such a multitude of both sexes of all states and of all ages, from aboue Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie till vnder Seauen were by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome crowned, that this on Ilād within the space of one yeare, may seeme to haue renewed all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous examples of former Christian ages. Here is more then one <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> rosted in fires without groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or stirring, or somuch as shrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, with no other chaine then of charitie tied to the torment. Here is more then one troupe put into freezing waters starued to death in winter nights, not so much as one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting,
<pb facs="5"/>the feruour of Faith kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the frost of infidelitie frō their hart. Here is more then one <hi>Andrew</hi> adoring the crosse prepared to be his deathbed, and singing for ioy he was to die in the embracements therof. Here is more then one <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> fleade aliue, or minced into morcells, enduring as manie mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdomes, as he had members to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the cruell gluttonie of death, that would taste him by peece-meales. Here is more then one <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> fearing nothing more then that the persecutour would be mercifull, the torturer gentle, the instruments of his death dull and not eager enough of his blood. More then one <hi>Eleazarus,</hi> willing to die rather a thousand deathes, then to dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="6"/>once, or to permit the voice of another, though without his priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or consent, to belie the constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his faith; More then one <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auctus,</hi> who meeting with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of designed Martyrs, going to the place of their death, by spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous ioining encreased their nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, &amp; made the ioy of the heauēlie banquet the greater, whilest all har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie wellcome the deare vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted guest.</p>
   <p>And to speake also of the other sexe by nature inferiour, by faith equall, by the renowne of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in a sorte superiour vnto mē, the strength of diuine grace shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it self more admirablie in feeble bodies; behold more then one <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas</hi> with drie eies looking on the martyrdomes of her children, sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="6"/>them before her to heauen, as harbingers to prepare a place of blisse for their mother, that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentlie to followe. More then one couragious mother, that with her daughters entred into deepe gulfes, holding each other by the hand as in a dance, singing the praises of Christ on the waters, as it were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolles on the Christmas day of their happie natiuitie into eternall life. More thē one <hi>Catherine,</hi> by the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of their birth Princesses, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the infidelitie of the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime priests, being after the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of manie torments and fearce combats cōsummated by the sword. More then one <hi>Apollonia</hi> charged with yeares, but more stored with merits of vertuous life, readier to
<pb facs="7"/>burne for Christ, then the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to put her into the fire. More then one <hi>Agnes,</hi> that ouercame ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse of age by maturity of faith, lawfull witnesses of Christian truth, before they could be witnesses in any cause of the world, that recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on their tēder neckes the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering sword as ioifullie, as if they had put on chaines of gold, holding the daies of their martyrdomes as their marriadges feastes. In a word, here (as I said) within one Iland, and in one yeare, you shall finde in a manner all the memorable martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and glorious triumphes of the primitiue times reuiued, and by new glorious imitation expressed to the quicke.</p>
   <p>We the Catholickes of England,
<pb facs="7"/>who liue in the happie danger of being partakers of the like crownes, haue speciall cause to behold with ioie this <hi>Iaponian Palme-tree of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Fortitude</hi> translated, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on English soile. The victories of Martyrs recorded in writing be encouragemēts vnto martyrdomes, that the Christian souldier, as Saint Gregorie saith, <hi>eo minus in certamine trepidet, quo ante se positos tot virorum fortium triumphos videt,</hi> so much the lesse doubt of the glorious successe of this combat, in that he beholdes the manie conquests of triumphant Chāpiōs displaied to his sight. And although you doe not want other examples of great force; yet these may seem more potēt (besides other respects) because they are more
<pb facs="8"/>recent. Their sacred blood newlie issued out of the fornace of their ardent breast, doth yet still freshlie euaporate diuine loue, and by how much neerer they are to our daies, by so much the more efficaciouslie they applie to vs their flames. They were members of the same Church, professours of the same Religion, practisers of the same deuotions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording not only the substance, but also euerie circumstance, which yet be variable with the time; and we haue Preachers of all the same Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Orders, that were their guides &amp; leaders in those victorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats.</p>
   <p>The vexations we endure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with theirs, will seeme more tolerable; and if they should grow to greater excesses, we haue here
<pb facs="8"/>cōfortable pledges to make vs sure the Faith, we professe, is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the most superlatiue rage of the world. As from <hi>the vttermost coastes</hi> we receaue newes of rare crueltie; so likewise from thence is brought the rare <hi>prize of the valiant woman.</hi> Here we learne that <hi>many waters cannot extinguish her charity,</hi> nor any frosts benumme harts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed therewith. The fires of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, of disgrace, of torment, that rage without, be not of equall force with the burning of her faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Nor continuance of sharpe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions can be so extended by lēgth of time, as to outreach her longing to suffer for her crucified Lord.</p>
   <p>O fire of heauen! ô desire of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdome! possesse our harts, pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into our spirits, consume the
<pb facs="9"/>drosse of humane pretences, quench in vs the flame of other loues. O that to die for Religion, that to suffer for Christ, that the crowne and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of martyrdome were the summe of all our wishes, the marke of all our ambitions, our meditation in the day, our dreame in the night, that we were in all our prayers still seeking to obtaine it, in all our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions still ayming to deserue it, in all our cogitations still longing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy it! O let vs without partiality of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten view ourselues in this admired mirrour, thereby to take away all dissimilitude from them in life, whō we desire to paralell in the felicity of their death.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>