<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113556_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08590</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18902</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113556</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true Christian catholique or The maner how to liue Christianly : Gathered forth of the holie Scriptures, and ancient fathers, confirmed and explained by sundrie reasons, apte similitudes, and examples. By the Reuerend Father F. Phillip Doultreman, of the Societie of Iesus. And turnd out of Frenche into Englishe by Iohn Heigham</title>
                 <author>Outreman, Philippe d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>474, 6 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="11" facs="6"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Title of a <hi>True Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiā Catholique,</hi> is not of so base &amp; of so smale a reckning as perhaps (my friendly Reader) thou doost account it: for I finde, that the greatest and renowned of the world, haue glorified more therof, then of all their other titles of honor and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie. <hi>Non principis, non terrenae, &amp;c.</hi> We are not honored (saith Saint Chrisostome, <hi>Hom. 8. in Ioan. circa finem,</hi> with the name of Prince, or of some earthly power, not of Angell not of Archangell, but with the name of the Kinge of the whole worlde. That valerous martyred Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, called Sanctus (as Eusebius wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>l. 5. hist. Eccl. c.
1.</hi>) being asked<pb n="12" facs="7"/>of the tyrant vvhat his name vvas, ansvvered. <hi>I am a Christian.</hi> Of vvhat familie art thou? <hi>I am a Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stian,</hi> quoth he. Of vvhat quallitie, free, or a bondman? To all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes vvhich vvere made him, he returned no other ansvvere but, <hi>I am a Christian.</hi> The same author vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that S. Blandinas martyr, in her confession of faith, and in the midst of all her torments, as often ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes as she pronoūced these vvordes, <hi>I am a Christiā,</hi> so many times she felt her selfe strēghtned anevv, &amp; reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And vvhat shall I say of S. Greg. Nazianzen. Who speaking of him selfe and of S. Basil, saith (<hi>in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ortion of S. Basil.</hi>) <hi>Nobis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna res, &amp;c.</hi> that is to say. We esteemed it for a great thinge, and held it for a great and noble name, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be, and to be called Christians:
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>wherof we glorie more, then euer Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas did of the change of the stone of his ring (if notvvithstanding it were not fabulous) by the which he possest himselfe of al Lidia. Thou shalt further see in the first chapter of this booke, that which the great Kinge Lewis of France also iudged of this name.</p>
   <p>Consider then the excellencie of this booke, sith it beareth a name so loftie and so honorable; But yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould rather (ô Christian) the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name which thou doest beare, &amp; if the life ought to answere to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the name, hast thou not cause to make account of this booke, vvhich teacheth thee in a few leaues, how to liue Christiāly, that is to say, conforme to the life of Iesus Christ, whose name thou bearest? <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nismus est imitatio diuinae naturae &amp;c</hi> (<hi>saith S. Gre. Naz. tra. denomine</hi>
      <pb n="14" facs="8"/>
      <hi>professione Christiani.</hi> Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is the imitation of the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If then thou be a Christian, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Iesus Christ thy God. Beware thou beare not a name emptie and vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but complete. Employ then the measure of so great a name, vpon wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes worthie of the name. For this it is that thou art Christian (saith S. Iohn Chrisostome,
<hi>orat. 5. in Iud.</hi>) &amp; that thou hast receiued this name, to the end that thou imitate Iesus-Christ, and fulfill by worke his cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Briefly, <hi>Nemo Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus verè dicitur &amp;c.</hi> (saith S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian) No mā is rightly called a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, who endeuoureth not to become like vnto Iesus Christ by his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian workes. Now to imitate Iesus Christ, one must doe two thinges. The first is, to roote vp all the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vices that are in his soule.<pb n="15" facs="8"/>The second, to plant virtues in their places: for our Lord is not come into this worlde, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy sinne (1. Ioan. 3.) and to teache vs by examples, (1. Pet. 2. 21. Ioan. 13. 15. Heb. 10. 20.) and wordes, the exercise of virtues, and of good workes.</p>
   <p>Behould here the summe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of all Christian iustice, saith S. Prosper with S. Aug. <hi>(in sent. 98. ex Aug.) to fly from euill, and to doe good.</hi> And to this it is, that also Isay, Dauid, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle doth exhorte vs. (Isay 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. Psal. 33. 15. Rom. 12. 9. Colos. 3. 9. Ephes. 4.
22. 23.) This also is the vvhole subiect of these tvvo bookes, vvherin as in a most cleare miroir, thou shalt finde these tvvo pointers taught vnto thee, by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and holie Fathers, vvith<pb n="16" facs="9"/>sundry notable reasons, rare simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and examples. And note that I haue serued my selfe of examples, because I see that the Sonne of God him selfe serued him selfe thereof, as also the holy Fathers did, especial lie S. Aug. and S. Greg. vvho in one of his homilies saith (38. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang. vvherin he bringeth sundry examples) that it hapneth oftenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that the hartes of the hearers, are more conuerted and moued, by the examples of the faithfull, then by the vvordes of the preachers.
<hi>Nonnunquam mentes audentium, plus exempla fidelium, quam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centium verba conuertunt.</hi> Which sith it is so, I assure my selfe that this litle booke, vvill bringe vnto thee both profit and contentment, if vvith a serious and attentiue le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, thou ioynest together the<pb n="17" facs="9"/>practise and good vvorkes. God grant, that both thou and I, may so vvell practise these profitable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments, that after vve haue by the meanes hereof, led a life <hi>Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Christian and Catholique,</hi> vve may one day haue the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence promised to all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; life and glorie euerlasting, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>