<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the most mightie, verteous and excellent prince
Edward the sixt, by the grace of God, kyng of England, Fraunce and
Ireland, defendor of the Catholike faith, and vnder God supreme hed,
of the churches of England and Ireland. Your moste humble
subiect Edward Halle, wisheth health, honor and felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113110_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02595</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12722</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113110</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the most mightie, verteous and excellent prince
Edward the sixt, by the grace of God, kyng of England, Fraunce and
Ireland, defendor of the Catholike faith, and vnder God supreme hed,
of the churches of England and Ireland. Your moste humble
subiect Edward Halle, wisheth health, honor and felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vnion of the two noble and illustre famelies of Lancastre [and] Yorke, beeyng long in continual discension for the croune of this noble realme : with all the actes done in bothe the tymes of the princes, bothe of the one linage and of the other, beginnyng at the tyme of kyng Henry the fowerth, the first aucthor of this deuision, and so successiuely proceadyng to the reigne of the high and prudent prince kyng Henry the eight, the vndubitate flower and very heire of both the sayd linages</title>
                 <author>Hall, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, c lxxviij, c lxxxj-c xciij, c xcv-cc lx, that is 250, lix, 1, lxi, 1, cc lxiij, 1 leave, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶To the most mightie, verteous and excellent prince
Edward the sixt, by the grace of God, kyng of England, Fraunce and
Ireland, defendor of the Catholike faith, and vnder God supreme hed,
of the churches of England and Ireland. Your moste humble
subiect Edward Halle, wisheth health, honor and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Bliuion the cancard e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie
to Fame and renoune
the suckyng serpēt of auncient
memory, the dedly darte to the
glory of princes, and the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer
of all conquestes and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
actes, so muche bare rule
in the firste and seconde age of
the worlde, that nothyng was
set out to mennes knowledge
ether how the world was made
either howe man and beastes
wer created, or how the worlde
was destroyed by water til fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Moses had by deuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiraciō
in the third age, inuented letters, the treasure of memorie, and
set furth fine notable bokes, to the greate comfort of all people liuyng
at this daie. Likewise Mercurie in Egipte inuented letters and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng,
whiche Eadmus after brought in to Grece. So euery naciō was
desirous to enhaunce lady Fame, and to suppresse that dedly beast O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliuiō.
For what diuersitie is betwene a noble prince &amp; a poore begger,
ye a reasonable man and a brute beast, it after their death there be left
of theim no remembrance or token. So that euidently it appereth that
Fame is the triumphe of glory, and memory by litterature is the verie
dilator and setter furth of Fame. How muche therfore are princes, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernoures
and noble menne bounde to theim whiche haue so liuely set
furth the liues and actes of their parentes, that all though thei bee ded
by mortall death, yet thei by writyng and Fame liue and bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
present. If no man had written the goodnesse of noble Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus,
nor the pitie of mercifull Traian, how shoulde their successours
haue folowed ther steppes in vertue and princely qualities: on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie
parte, if the crueltie of Nero, the vngracious life of Caligula
had not beene put in remembrance, young Princes and fraile gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors
might likewise haue fallen in a like pit, but by redyng their vices
and seyng their mischeueous ende, thei bee compelled to leaue their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
waies, and embrace the good qualities of notable princes and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
gouernours: Thus, writyng is the keye to enduce vertue, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
vice, Thus memorie maketh menne ded many a thousande yer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
still to liue as though thei wer present: Thus Fame triumpheth vpon
death, and renoune vpon Obliuion, and all by reason of writyng and
historie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Alas my soueraigne Lorde, my herte lamenteh to knowe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre
what rule this tyrante Obliuion bare in this realme, in the
tyme of the Britons. For from the first habitacion of this land, no man
of the Britons ether set furthe historie of their begynnyng, or wrote the
hole liues of their princes &amp; kynges, excepte Gildas whiche inueighed
against the euill doynges of a fewe tyrantes and euill gouernours. In
so muche that Cesar writeth, that when he was in this realme, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
could not tel their linage, nor their begynnyng. But one Geffrey of
Monmothe a thousand yere and more after Iulius Cesar, translated
a certayn Britishe or Welshe boke, conteinyng the commyng of Brute
with the sequele of his linage, till the tyme of Cadwalader, whiche Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tishe
boke if it had slept a litle lenger, Brute with al his posteritie had
ben buried in the poke of Obliuion, for lacke of writyng.</p>
   <p>The strong Saxons, after thei had gayned this lande, set vp the
bāner of Fame, and had their liues notably writtē by diuerse and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery
famous clerkes, euen from their firste entery into this lande, till
the firste Monarchy, and so sucessyuely. In the Normans tyme, many
notable woorkes hath been set furthe, some of one prince perticulerly,
and some of mo: So that in fine, all the stories of kynges, from kyng
Willyam the firste, to kyng Edward the third, bee set <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urthe at length
by diuerse authours in the Latin toungue, as by Matthewe of Paris
sometyme religious in saincte Albons and other. After whome Ihon
Frossart wrote the liues of kyng Edward the third, and kyng Richard
the seconde, so compendeously and so largely, that if there were not so
many thynges spoken of in his long woorkes, I might beleue all writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
in his greate volumes to bee as trewe as the Gospell. But I haue
redde an olde Prouerbe, whiche saithe, that in many woordes, a lye or
twayne sone maie scape. Sithe the ende of Frossarte whiche endeth at
the begynnyng of kyng Henry the fourthe, no man in the Englishe
toungue, hath either set furth their honors accordyng to their desertes,
nor yet declared many notable actes worthy of memorie dooen in the
tyme of seuen Kynges, whiche after kyng Richarde succeded: Excepte
Robert Fabian and one with out name, whiche wrote the common En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish
Chronicle, men worthy to be praysed for their diligence, but farre
shotyng wide from the butte of an historie.</p>
   <p>Wherfore moste drad and benigne souereigne Lord, lest cancarde
Obliuion should deface the glory of these seuen Princes, to whom you
be of all sides lineall heire and very enheritour, I haue compiled and
gathered (and not made) out of diuerse writers, as well forayn as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe,
this simple treatise whiche I haue named the vnion of the noble
houses of Lancaster and Yorke, conioyned together by the godly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
of your moste noble graundfather, and your verteous grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
For as kyng henry the fourthe was the beginnyng and rote of the
great discord and deuision: so was the godly matrimony, the final ende
of all discencions, titles and debates.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Besechyng your highe Maiestie, to take this my simple and rube
woorke, accordyng to your accustomed goodnesse in good part, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardyng
the thyng, but my good will to my natiue countree, whose
fame for lacke of writyng may muche be darkened and defaced,
and thus I pray to the celestiall Lorde to send you vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie
ouer your enemies, Peace with your confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates,
loue of your subiectes: and
in conclusion, perpetuall ioye &amp;
❧ eternall felicitee ❧</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>