<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Eburne, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113959_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12557</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113959</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Eburne, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The two-folde tribute or two speciall duties commanded by our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ to be rendred: the first of subiects to their Cæsar, the second of Christians to their God: for the better furtherance of the one in his regall dignitie, and of the other in his Eulangelicall ministerie. Explaned in two sermons and now published. Anno. 1613. By Richard Eburne</title>
                 <author>Eburne, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 27, 11, 59, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Book industry, catalogues and inventories</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous and Christian Reader, I had a purpose to haue seconded my first labour, <hi>The Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Ministerie,</hi> in such sort as it might haue satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thine expectation, and that title at full: but partly discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by want of time and meanes fit for a worke of that waight; partly detained by hope that (as I had heard) some one farre more able and ancient, would ease me thereof, I do for the present, present thee againe with this sermon, which as a supply to my former treatise; may so much further thee, (if thou take some small paines in perusing and conferring both that by both thou maist haue as it were one sufficient volume of this Argument, and I the lesse neede heereafter to labour any farther therein. If thereby I preuaile with thee so much that thou acknowledge the same for truth, and conforme thee to the practise, I haue a great part of my desire: or if I may but occasion some or other more learned and able to performe what I haue but rudely informed, I shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my labour not wholly lost, I haue abounded in quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other mens obseruations for Ornament to the
<pb facs="19"/> worke, Authoritie with the learned, direction to the vnlearned, and protection for my selfe: which if thou vse well, will informe thee at full, that I am neither alone, nor from the ancient, nor with the worst.</p>
   <p>Touching the Argument or subiect of my labour in this my Sermon, if any shall thinke it not so fit for the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit as the pen, let him know, There can bee no more fault in me to preach thereof, then in <hi>Moses,</hi> in the Prophets, and in the Apostles, so oft, so much and so diuersly to speake and write thereof. They feared not (as <note n="*" place="margin">Rulling. Decad. lib. 5. Serm. 10.</note> one well notes of <hi>Moses)</hi> lest in handling that matter, they should be accused of greedy desire or couetousnes: neither need I. That imputation may with better right and reason, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted vpon them, which after all our preaching and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of doctrine so necessary, vrged so oft, by so many, in so sound and effectuall manner, as might make euen the stones of the street to heare, an heart of Adamant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and a brow of brasse to blush at this sinne: and for all our preaching and publishing of other doctrines most holy, most necessary, most sweet, and comfortable, for which they are not able to yeeld vs sufficient recompence with all <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> that they haue, (for what are their carnall things to our spirituall?) Doe yet suffer vs to liue in all needinesse and contempt; and making due prouision and supply for the wants of the meanest of themselues, passe by vs as not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the looking on.</p>
   <p>Touching the meanes by which our distresses &amp; wants may be releeued, it may happily seeme hard or strange to some, that I intimate the off-cutting of customes, prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, exemptions, &amp;c. But whoso shall well and thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consider of this businesse, shall well perceiue, that if euer there be a sincere intent and setled purpose to effect this
<pb facs="19"/> so holy, so necessary, so iust, and so great a worke, it must this way, and none other be effected. For whereas our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state cannot bee bettered, but either by restoring vs that which indeed, and properly is our owne, which once wee had, and which was vnaduisedly, and vniustly taken from vs; or else by allotting and bestowing vpon vs some things that we neuer had. To expect the latter, that is, that we should haue either sufficient stypends added in all places, where need is, vnto that which we already haue, or that our gentlemen, patrones or parochians should lay vs out so much of their fineable lands and temporall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, as might increase our gleeb in that measure, as might supply the want and roome of our tithes, by their customes, prescriptions, &amp;c: which held, is neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, possible nor reasonable. It resteth therefore, that by the meanes which I haue mentioned especially, this must, if euer, be effected. Thence is the maine cause of the disease and euill, and thence according to the old Maxime, <hi>Sublata causa, tollitur effectus,</hi> must come the cure and remedy: much helpe I grant may be had by <hi>Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but neither can they wholly be restored, nor is the hurt they doe, so great, so common and generall, as of the former.</p>
   <p>Doth it seeme improbable, that euer this great &amp; good worke should be effected, and as a case desperate, a matter past hope?</p>
   <p>This may doe so to some, but to me it doth not. For first, when I consider, that it is much easier to repaire some Churches, then to endow all, and yet doe perceiue that time hath beene, that all our Churches, the whole land thorough, haue beene indowed both with conuenient gleebe and <hi>their full tithes in kinde,</hi>
      <q>I perswade my
<pb facs="20"/> selfe, if we had that true zeale to the Church, and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue to religion, that the first Christians (which so endowed our Churches) had, that the ruines, rents and maymes of our Churches might with facility and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity enough be repaired and amended: the rather for that, as in ruines and rubble of old buildings, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in the place, matter conuenient and sufficient for performance thereof.</q>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. When as I doe finde, that for long agoe, in time of darkest popery, one man alone, one bishop of the land, I mean that famous Bishop <hi>Grosthead</hi> then Bishop of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne could and did obtaine of the Pope, being yet scant his friend, power and authority both to institute vicaridges in Churches impropriate▪ where none were, and where such were as seemed too slenderly prouided of sufficient allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to augment the same as <hi>to him should seeme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.</hi> The coppie of which letters papall I haue for the worthines thereof, as in <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> I find them recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note place="margin">Matth. Paris.</note> here inserted.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Innocentius Episcopus &amp;c. Cum sicut accepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in tua ciuitate et Diocaesi, nonnulli religiosi et alij collegiati ecclesias parochiales in proprios vsus obtineant, in quibus nimis exiles, aut nullae taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae sunt vicariae. Fraternitatituae per authoritatem summam mandamus, quod in ijsdem ecclesijs de ipsarum prouentibus vicarias instituas, et institutas exiles adaugeas vice nostra: prout iuxta consuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem patriae secundum Deum videris expedire, non obstantibus si praedicti exempti sint, aut aliâs muniti Apostolicis priuilegijs siue indulgentijs, per quae idimpediri vel differri possit. &amp;c.</hi> in English thus: <hi>Innocentius</hi> Bishop, &amp;c. Forsomuch as we are credibly
<pb facs="20"/> informed, that within your City and Diocesse many reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and other collegiate persons doe holde parochiall Churches vnto their owne proper vses, in the which vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caridges either too small and slender, or none at all are set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Vnto your Brother hood by our speciall and supreame authority we doe command, that in the saide Churches of the prouentions, and emoluments of the same, <note n="*" place="margin">These two things duely and well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, would very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the poore and wretched estate of our clergie.</note> vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridges you doe institute, and such as being already insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, * are slender, and not sufficiently endowed, you doe on our behalfe augment: according as after the custome of the country to the Honour of God, you shall see it to bee expedient: Notwithstanding that any the persons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said be exempt, or otherwise fensed with Apostolicall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges or indulgences, by which the same might be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or differred. And whosoeuer shall you contradict or withstand therein, that you doe by censures ecclesiasticall, by vertue of our power Apostolical to you committed, them punish and condignely represse. Dated at <hi>L.</hi> vij. Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lend. of <hi>Octob.</hi> in the yeere of our Popedome the viij. which was, saith our English history <hi>Anno. Dom.</hi> 1252. This memorable monument finding, which hee good man did execute <hi>Cum effectu,</hi> I do reason thus with my selfe. <q>If this one good Bishop in the daies of vtter darkenesse could obtaine of the Pope, though scant his friend, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to repaire the Churches of his Diocesse in this sort, for the better sustentation of blind Masse priests, why may it not be possible that the most reuerend Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops and other graue, wise and zealous in the land, might by some good meanes best known to their owne wisdomes, prouide and settle maintenance in their Churches for the learned, able, and worthy preachers of the Gospell.</q>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <pb facs="21"/> 3. The very state of the time present doth so necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly require some alteration to be made, some augmentation of our maintenance to be yeelded, that he that shall denye it, may iustly bee thought to speake against all reason and conscience. For why must our paies, our stipends, our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions alone stand now as they did for an hundred yeares agoe? And why are wee alone vnworthie that fauour which is affoorded (and iusty too) vnto labourers, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, artisans, and to whom not? will they tell vs, things done cannot be vndone? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> We answere, common sense and daily experience towards others in cases not vnlike, do tell vs and assure vs the contrary. <hi>Humanum est errare, in errore vero perseuerare, diabolicum.</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Will they say, we must be content? We confesse we must perforce, till reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can be had. But they will not I hope in the meane time forbid vs to complaine, and secke as men diseased, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned, or distressed, some redresse and ease. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Neither can they replie, That we complain without cause, and are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented without need, seeing it cannot be denyed, that vnto many of vs, that which is left was with the least, and but in a most sparing sort, when it was at first laid out, and allotted to the Church: and therefore can no way be found competent or sufficient now, were it in no other respect then of the time it selfe, which is so farre different in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of all things from that then it was.</p>
   <p n="4">4. Besides which (though the state of times were alike) there ought some other manner of consideration to be had of our clergie men that now are, then heeretofore there was or seemed to be needfull. For respecting learning and sufficiencie, our clergie are not (God be thanked) as heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, (euen our enemies being iudges) blind and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned bussards, idolatrous and massing priests, of whom
<pb facs="21"/> little more was expected, then to be able to turne their <hi>Portuise,</hi> or to reade plaine english, nor are they now like <hi>Ieroboams</hi> priests taken out from amongst the lowest and dregs of the people, for whom that they had, or that they got in the ministerie (their deserts considered) was enough, if not too much: But a great number of them now are (and long or this, if due prouision for them had been made, manie more there would haue beene) learned and worthie men: men whose education and time spent, whose friends expences &amp; great charge before they come into the ministerie: men whose present labours and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siduous paines in their ministerie, doe both deserue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire better regard. What comfort shall they finde for the time present, and what reward shall they reape for the time past if their best preferment bee so little: and their highest pitch so low? Can they continue and maintaine their studies with nothing? or is it intended so soon as they are placed, they shall, for lacke of meanes to maintain them and their studies scoller-like, giue ouer their studies, and betake themselues to idlenes or drudgerie?</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then respecting their manner of life, our ministerie at this day consisteth for the most part of married Men, whereas in former times, they were all vnmarried. If in those times they made prouision accordingly, and left (as in many places they did) no more to the Church then might then conueniently finde and suffice a single Man, must that suffice still? If any will say, that it is not their part to prouide for married men, and that if there be not sufficient to maintaine vs with our families, we must liue vnmarried too. I say that is <hi>Vox Daemonis, non ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> a speech not befitting the mouth of a Christian. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 3.</note> Neither will I stand to prooue that wee ought to haue
<pb facs="22"/> such maintenance prouided vs, as may suffice for vs and our families too, if we be disposed to enter that state of life, which is as free &amp; as fit for vs, as for anie other estate of men: but referre them that make a question thereof to the practise of the first and best times, in which (for our owne Church) they may see, if they will not be blinde, that the prouision they made for their Curch-men, was euerie where such, as was both able for, and befitting only a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried clergie: <q>and not feare to conclude, that vntill the like bee made for our Clergie, in some measure, which in many places by the one halfe at least is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, our people haue not done their duety in this behalfe, but doe shew themselues vnworthy of such worthy men as the Lord doth send vnto them, and vnworthy of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and gladtidings of saluation, which they preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Thus Christian Reader, hauing imparted vnto thee in part and in breefe, what hath induced me to the hope I haue, to see at length the cause I handle in my succeeding Sermon, better respected, whereof thou maist reade more what I haue written otherwhere, as one zelous for the house of God, whose stones it pittieth mee to see still lying <note place="margin">M. Minist. cap. 7. et. 10.</note> in the dust, praying God to put into the heart of our thrice noble, gratious and religious King (into whose hand hee hath put the sword of Soueraigne authoritie) not onely a good inclination and forward disposition this way, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so an irreuocable and vnresistable resolution to execute his supreame power for the reformation of this euill, and extirpation of this shame of our Church, and disgrace of our Nation. I pray thee <hi>for our Lord Iesus Christs sake, &amp; for the loue of the spirit, that thou wouldst</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.</note>
      <hi>striue with mee by prayers to God for mee, that I</hi>
      <pb facs="22"/>
      <hi>may bee deliuered from them which are disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and euill minded men, and that this my seruice and labour for the Church and house of God in our land, may bee accepted of the Saints.</hi> VVhich God for his Gospell sake vouchsafe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine euer in the Lord</hi> R. Eb.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>