<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the King.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113238_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16950</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3841</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113238</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the King.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true discourse, vpon the matter of Martha Brossier of Romorantin : pretended to be possessed by a deuill. Translated out of French into English, by Abraham Hartvvel</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the King.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>BY the commaundement of your Maiestie, wee haue
set downe in writing, briefly and truly, that which wee
haue found in our visiting of <hi>Martha Brossier,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
to bee a <hi>Daemóniake,</hi> together with the aduise,
which we haue giuen therein and thereupon, in our conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
We present the same vnto your Maiestie, without any
Art, without any painted shew, without any flourish, but with
a naked simplicitie, the faithfull companion of trueth, which
you haue desired from vs in this matter, and which in euery
other thing you haue alwaies loued and curiously sought.
This desire, Sir, is a most certaine proofe of the vprightnes,
which you carrie both in your mouth and in your soule, as a
witnesse of your iust and holy intentions: whereby you haue
gained, and for euer confirmed the hearts of your Subiects
withdrawne from your obedience: and the amitie of forren
Nations, as much as you haue done by the terror of your
Armes: both the one and the other being as greatly assured
in the certaintie of your word, as they haue feared and stood
in awe of your inuincible courage. Receiue therefore, Sir, if
it may please you, the trueth contained in this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise,
as a testimony of our most humble obedience: and vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe
to honour the same with the benignitie of your surueigh,
in fauour of the singular affection that you beare vnto
the trueth, which indeede doth make you so much the more
conformable to the <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> whereof you are a liuely I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,
and which is the very Trueth it selfe. Whom we doe
humbly beseech to redouble vpon you his holy graces and
blessings, and to giue vnto you as much prosperitie, good
fortune, and health as doe wish vnto your Maiestie,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>SIR, Your most humble, most affectionate
and most faithfull Subiects, the
Phisitians of Paris.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>