<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Readers health.</title>
           <author>Fouleweather, Adam</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113749_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01097</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11210</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Readers health.</title>
                 <author>Fouleweather, Adam</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vvonderfull, strange and miraculous astrologicall prognostication for this yeere 1591 : Discouering such wonders to happen this yeere, an neuer chaunced since Noes floud. Wherein if there be found one lye, the author will loose his credit for euer. Newly corrected. By Adam Fouleweather, student in astronomy</title>
                 <author>Foulweather, Adam</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26+ pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Readers health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Itting Gentlemen vpon Douer cliffes, to quaint my selfe with the art of Nauigation, and knowe the course of the Tides, as the Danske Crowes gather on the Sandes against a storme: so there appeared on the downs such a flock of knaues, that by Astrological coniectures I began to gather, that this yeere would proue intemperate by an extreme heat in Sōmer, insomuch that the stones in Cheap side should be so hot, that diuers persons should feare to goe from Poules to the Counter in the Poultrye: wherupon I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took me to my Ephimerides, and erecting a figure, haue found strange accidents to fall out this yeere, Mercurye being Lord and predominate in the house of Fortune, that many fooles shall haue full cofers, and wise men walke vp and downe with emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pursses: that if Iupiter were not ioyned with him in a fauourable aspect, the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="3"/>
of East-cheape should doo little or nothing all Lent but make prickes: seeing therefore the wonders that are like to fall out this present yeere, I haue for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of my Countrymen taken in hand to make this Prognostication, discoursing breefelye of the Eclipses both of Sunne and Moone, with their dangerous effectes like to followe, which if God preuent not: many poore men are like to fast on Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies for want of food, and such as haue no shooes to goe barefoot, if certaine deuout Coblers proue not the more curteous: but yet Astrologie is not so certaine, but it may fayle: and therfore diuers Hostesses shall chaulke more this yeere then their Guests wil wipe out: so that I conclude, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is saide by art. <hi>Sapiens dominalitur astris.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your freend and Student in Astrologie.
<hi>Adam Fouleweather.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>