<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113147_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18455.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Articles, of a treatie of truce. Made and concluded in the towne and citie of Antvverp, the 9. of April 1609. betweene the commissioners of the most excellent Princes, Arch-dukes Albert and Isabella Clara Eugenia, as well in the name of the Catholicke Kings Maiestie, as in their owne. Together with the commissioners and deputies of the renowmed Lords, the Estates Generall of the Vnited Prouinces of the Low-countryes : and that through the mediation and with the aduice of the Lords Ambassadors of the most Christian Kings, and of Great Britaine. At the Haghe by Hillebrant Iacobz, printer ordinarie to the Lords the States Generall of the Vnited Prouinces of the Low-countreyes</title>
                 <author>Netherlands, Sovereign (1598-1621 : Albert and Isabella)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Potter, George</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O it is, that the most excellent Princes, Archduke <hi>Albert</hi> and <hi>Isabella Clara Eugenia, &amp;c.</hi> hauing vpon the foure &amp; twentie of April, 1607. made a Truce and Cessation of Armes, for eight mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, with the most renowmed Lords the generall Estates of the vnited Prouinces of the Low-Countries in qualitie, and as holding them for free Estates, Prouinces and Countries; ouer the which, they pretend no authority: The which Truce ought to be ratified with like declaration, by the Catholike Kings Maiestie, for so much as might concerne him; and the said ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and declarations deliuered to the said Lords Estates, three moneths after the said Truce, as it is passed by Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the eighteenth of September the said yeare: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, giueth a speciall procuration to the said Lords Archdukes, of the tenth of Ianuarie <hi>1608.</hi> aswell in his name as in their owne, to doe all that they shall iudge to bee fitte and conuenient, to attaine to a good Peace or Truce for many yeares. By vertue of which procuration, the said Lordes Archdukes should also by their letters of Commission, of the <hi>27.</hi> of the same moneth name and depute Commissioners, for to conferre and entreat in the said names and qualities: and hereupon haue consented and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, that the said Truce should bee prolonged and continued at
<pb facs="4"/>
sundrie times: namely, the <hi>20.</hi> of May, vnto the end of the said yeare <hi>1608.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But after they had assembled themselues diuers times with the deputies of the said Lords Estates, who had also procuration &amp; Commission from them, dated the <hi>5.</hi> of February of the said yeare: they could not come to agree of the said Peace, for many great difficulties hapning among them: For which cause, the Lords Ambassadors of the most Christian Kings, and of great Britayne, of the Princes electors Palatine and Brandenburg, Marques of Ansbach, and Lantgraue of Hessen, sent thither on the behalfe of the said Lords, Kings and Princes, to the aide, and furtherance of so good a worke: seeing that they were readie to depart and to break off al Treaty; did propose a Truce for many yeares, on certaine conditions contained in a writing, by them deliuered to both parties, with entreaty and exhortation to agree thereunto. Vpon the which writing, many other difficulties likewise hapning.</p>
   <p>In the end, this ninth day of April, in the yeare <hi>1609.</hi> there assembled Seignior <hi>Ambrosio Spinola,</hi> Marques de <hi>Benafro,</hi> Knight of the order of the Golden Fleece, Counsellor of Estate, and of the Warres to his Catholike Maiestie, Master of the Camp, Generall of his Armies: and Seignior <hi>Iohn Richardot</hi> Knight, Lord of Barby, Counsellor of Estate, and chiefe Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of their Highnesses priuie Counsell: <hi>Iohn de Mancicidor,</hi> of the Counsell of warre, and Secretary to his said Catholike Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie. The reuerend father frier <hi>Iohn Neyen,</hi> Commissioner generall of the order of Saint <hi>Francis</hi> in the Low-Countries: and Seignior <hi>Loys Verreyken</hi> Knight, Master of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests and chiefe Secretary to their Highnesses, &amp;c. By vertue of the letters of procuration from the said Lords Archdukes, to treat as well in their names, as in the name of the Lord King
<pb facs="4"/>
Catholike; the tenor of which procuration is hereafter inserted: with the like also of the said Kings on the one part, and Seignior <hi>Loys</hi> Earle of Nassaw, <hi>Catzenellebogen, Vyanden Dietz &amp;c.</hi> Lord of Bilsteyn, Gouernour and Captaine gene-ral of Frize, the Citie of Groeningen and Ommelanden Drente, &amp;c. Seignior <hi>Walrauen</hi> Lord of Bredero, Vianen, Vicounte of Vtrecht, L. of Ameyden, Cloetengen, &amp;c. The L. <hi>Cornelius</hi> of <hi>Gendt,</hi> Lord of Loeuen and Meynerswick, Vicount &amp; Iudge of the Empire, and of the Citie of Nuninegen: Seig. <hi>Iehan</hi> of Oldenbarneuelt Knight, Lord of Cimpell, Rodenris, &amp;c. Aduocate and keeper of the great Seale, Charters and Registers of Holland and West-Frizeland: Seignior <hi>Iaques</hi> of Malderee Knight, Lord of Heyes, &amp;c. The chiefe, and representing the Nobility of the Estates and Counsell of the countie of Zealand; the Lords <hi>Girard de Renesse,</hi> Lord <hi>Vander Aa.</hi> of <hi>Streeffkirck</hi> Niew Lecker landt, &amp;c. <hi>Iellius Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi> Doctor of the lawes, Counsellor ordinary of the Counsell of Frize: <hi>Iohn Sloeten</hi> Lord of Sallicq, Drossart of the County of Vellenhoo, and Steward of the Seigneury of Claunder, &amp; <hi>Abel Coenders</hi> of Helpen, Lord <hi>In Faien</hi> and <hi>Cantes,</hi> in the name of the said Lordes Estates, as also by vertue of their Letters of procurations and Commission hereafter likewise inserted on the other part; who together with the mediation and aduise of Lord <hi>Iohn Charles</hi> Baron of Chagnie, and <hi>Monyeu</hi> Counsellor of Estate to the most christian King, and his Embassador extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, with the said lordes Estates.</p>
   <p>And the Lord <hi>Elias de la Place</hi> Knight, lord of Russy, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Marchault, Counsellor also in the said Counsell of Estate, Gentleman in ordinary of the said Lord, the kings chamber, Baylife and Captaine of Vitry le <hi>Francois</hi> and his ordinarie Ambassador, with the said lordes, the estates. Sir <hi>Richard Spencer</hi> knight, Gentleman in ordinarie, of the king of great
<pb facs="5"/>
Britaynes priuie chamber, and his Ambassador extraordinary, vnto the said Lordes the Estates, and Sir <hi>Raphe Winwood</hi> knight Ambassador ordinary, and Counsellor to the said king in his Counsell of estate, in the vnited Prouinces, haue accorded and agreed, in the manner and forme following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>