<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO AL THE GENTYL readers of this treatyse gre∣tyng in our Lorde Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113404_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19240</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5654</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113404</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO AL THE GENTYL readers of this treatyse gre∣tyng in our Lorde Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exortacion to charite : very needefull at this tyme for eche man and woman to inbrace, compyled by Wyllyam Conway</title>
                 <author>Conway, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Powell, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO AL THE GENTYL readers of this treatyse gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng in our Lorde Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch (good reader) as the moste thyng that we good Chrysten men shulde looke for nowe in this age, beynge fyxed fastened, and rooted in the faith of Iesus Christ this. xv. C. and .l. yeres is charitie, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bryngeth with hym in company all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues. And maketh a perfecte full and suffycyent faythe to the saluacyon of man. For as holy Writ saytk, and al holy Doctors, and as the Catholyke Churche teacheth, fayth without charytye auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no more the soule, then the sape of soure onions auayleth sore eyes. Yf fayth I say then be nothynge without charitie, for gods sake let eche man that hath fayth vse therwiih charitie. Now what chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is anone by gods grace, I wyll shewe you. And in the meane tyme (good reader) Let vs somewhat talke of fayth. And how many faythes as I perceyue and all men shall knowe, that wyl not be dombe when
<pb facs="5"/>
they shulde speake, death when they shuld heare, and blynd when they shuld se, there is nowe vsed fayth faynte, fayth fayned and faythe faythfull. Nowe howe these kyndes of fayth are vsed, hereafter shalbe declared. This I knowe wel and am assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and thou reader knowest so wel as I, that eche man in this realme hath faythe, or at the leaste wyse sobre fayth. And I thynke in lyke maner, that eche man sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posethe hym selfe to haue a ryght and a good fayth: yet in deede it is not so: For as saynt Iames sayth. Cap. ii. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll hath fayth. But nowe to ende this preface. Fyrst I shal desyre al men of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, yf by my schaunce any thyng shal es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape me the auctour hereof, for as it is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly sene, a straunger shal espye a faute in a mans house sooner then he hym selfe shall. And so I thynke a man shal quycly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er espye a faute in this worke, then I my selfe, wherefore yf there be any man that shall so do, moste hartelye I requyre hym for to mende it. Secondly I shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre the good reader not to be discontented with me for any thynge herein wrytten. Leaste thereby thou shake of cleane all the fruytes of my boke which tendeth chefely to charytie, perhappes I wyll saye some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that shall touche some men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>