<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian and in∣different Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113066_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19859</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6287</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113066</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian and in∣different Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triall of Maist. Dorrell, or A collection of defences against allegations not yet suffered to receiue convenient answere : Tending to cleare him from the imputation of teaching Sommers and others to counterfeit possession of divells. That the mist of pretended counterfetting being dispelled, the glory of Christ his royall power in casting out divels (at the prayer and fasting of his people) may evidently appeare</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>103, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="81" facs="41"/>
   <head>To the Christian and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Reader.</head>
   <p>THE <hi>Report</hi> before promised (for some causes not sent with this treatise to the presse) was omitted so long, as that (in meane while) the booke against M. Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell begottē (as for som reasons it may seeme) by one, to wit th'authour of <hi>Scottizing Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevating discipline,</hi> is come foorth in deede; but fathered (as a bastard) vpon another, viz. S. H. Whereof I thought good to take knowledge, and to referre some fewe things to thy Christian consideration.</p>
   <p>First concerning the Publishing thereof, Jt is to be observed, that as copies of Deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were denied before hearing, and M. Dorrell not suffred to answer (as he should) at hearing, So he is traduced in print after hearing, though he be yet in sure holde, and therefore without conuenient meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in such sort, as this case requireth. Is not this to binde a man, and then to fight with him? Hath not the publisher of M. Dorrels <hi>apologie</hi> some reason to call such courses <hi>exorbitant?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="82" facs="42"/>Secondly, concerning the Matter: It is to be considered, That howsoeuer the Discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of M. Dorrels practises in teaching sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry to counterfeit possession, be only preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; yet D. Barlowes opinion <hi>That in these dayes there is no possession</hi> must needes be heere and there maintayned, and yet not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly. J call it D. Barlowes opinion, Because in processe of disputatiō the last Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt in Cambridge, he defended the same; yea so, that he would haue no possessiō (but obses<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion) in Christes time. Notwithstanding that worthy Vniversity would not suffer him at first to professe so grosse an error, but (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serting this word Ordinary) compelled him to set vp his question to this effect, <hi>In these dayes there is no Ordinary possession, &amp;c.</hi> Now to what purpose is <hi>Possession</hi> so sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply denied? Marry, to cut Mai. Dorrels combe. For, if there be no <hi>Possession</hi> at all, then Sommers was not possessed, and then M. Dorrels supposed crowne of glory may proue but a withered garland. Nay verily. If this were so, yet they gaine nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, neither is M. Dorrels cause the worse. For what if there be <hi>Obsessiō</hi>? &amp; so if Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers were thus affected and tormented in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, as he appeared in shew, is M. Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell then to be condemned as an impostor?
<pb n="83" facs="42"/>
Yea further, admit Sommers to haue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaited: why should M. Dorrell deceiued by him, be punished? Was that good man, of reverend memorie (M. Fox) deceyued by <hi>Anne Brigges</hi> &amp; <hi>Rachel Pindar,</hi> called in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to question for the same? Hee was not.</p>
   <p>But how is this absolut deniall of posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion proved? First, forsooth, by an Induction not vrged as a reason, but insinuated like a fallacy, thus to be collected: <hi>Wil. Sommers, Tho. Darling, Kath. Wright, the seauen in Lancashire, &amp;c. Martha Brossier</hi> (whose matter is discoursed by <hi>Abraham Hartwell</hi> &amp; published in the very nick with <hi>S. H.</hi> his <hi>Discouery) were coūterfeits: Therfore</hi> (as it is concluded p. <hi>77.) a Magistrate saide to Mengus, Of 50. exorcistes 49. are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeits. To whom Mengus answered: If I were not present, you would so iudge of me.</hi> O worthy <hi>Induction</hi> from a most suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient enumeration of vndoubted particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. But marke (good Reader) how like a squint-eyed man S. H. in his parting blow lookes one way, and strikes another. For in the title he pretendeth to discouer Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Dorrells bad practising but with <hi>4:</hi> and yet, in sundry places of the discouery, hee laboureth to proue the <hi>7.</hi> in <hi>Lancashire</hi> to be also counterfeits, yea, though he confesse
<pb n="84" facs="43"/>
pa. <hi>4.</hi> that, touching thē <hi>examinations haue not bene taken.</hi> If the L.B. of London had tryed at first, how his Chaplaine could (by verie witt) without farther examinations haue made th' other <hi>4.</hi> Counterfeits in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniō of all that would beleeue him, his Lp. might haue saued great charges, and paines bestowed in hunting after their supposed counterfeiting. Here is yet another note vpō this <hi>Induction</hi> not to be forgottē, viz. That S.H. presuming (belike) to be borne out, doth call into question the sentences of death gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by her Maiecties Justices of <hi>Oier</hi> and <hi>Determiner</hi> vpon the Witches, that bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the <hi>7.</hi> in <hi>Lancashire,</hi> and the boy of <hi>Burton,</hi> to the publique and perpetuall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of those her Maiesties Courts of Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</p>
   <p>Secondly, Absolute deniall of possession is faced out by a ridiculous and slight (not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering, but) evading from arguments fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by S.H. him self from the word for pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, &amp;c. the refutation whereof I referre to some treatise that may be heereafter: also from the volūtary confessions of witches thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; who, at their death haue confessed, That they sent Divels into parties possessed. Indeed, if witches by deniall would excuse themselues, Such deniall for sundry reasons
<pb n="85" facs="43"/>
might bee thought insufficient. But seeing many witches, in sūdry Kingdomes &amp; ages, haue, by their voluntarie confessions, iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evidences and sentences giuen against them, and when? Euen at their death when they see no hope to saue them selues by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting in deniall, what reason is there, why they may not bee thought guilty of sending euill spirits into the possessed, whereof they were conuicted? S. H. auoucheth none, but suggesteth (pag. <hi>39.</hi>) that learned men haue sufficiently confuted this already. But S. H. are you ashamed of your learned men, or of their reasons, that you neither quote th'one nor set downe th'other? Must J helpe at a pinch? If memory faile me not (as it may be it did S. H.<note place="margin">In his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of witchcraft</note>) M. <hi>Scot</hi> imputeth such confessions to a stronge imagination arising from Melancholy the predominant humor of old women and such like. O superstitious Catholique Melācholy, that no lesse strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thē strongly deludeth so many young, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as old, men, aswell as women, and that at their executions! Tell me S. H. what you thinke <hi>bona fide:</hi> was it Melancholy that caused <hi>Hartley</hi> (who bewitched the <hi>7.</hi> in Lancashire) stifly to deny, both at the barre and gallowes, his divelish witchcraft: &amp; yet when he saw that breaking an halter would
<pb n="86" facs="44"/>
not deliuer him from hāging (as the Divell had promised) then penitently to confesse, that all wherewith M. <hi>Starky</hi> (in whose house the <hi>7.</hi> possessed were) had charged him, was very true? Yet admit the reason. But know withal, that your learned men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend theroby to dispoue not only possession, but all witchcraft whatsoever, otherwise then by poysoning. Are you S. H. of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion too? Why should I doubt it? For doe not you hold (pag. <hi>36.</hi>) That Witches can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not send Divels into men and women? and, Is it not as easie for witches to sent Divels Into, as Ʋnto men? Heere Doctors doubt. But D. <hi>Barlowes</hi> reason at <hi>Cambridge</hi> strikes all dead. For (saith he) one substāce cannot enter into another. Heere is a dead blowe indeede. For, Jf neither ayre (which is a substance) nor meate can enter into our bodyes, what will become of vs? Jf either en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, why cānot the Divel, sith he is a <hi>spirite</hi>? But admit that it is an harder matter to sende the Divell Into, then Ʋnto a man: I meane so Ʋnto, as to torment him, yet (me thinkes) S. H. doeth holde the deniall of one, aswell as of th' other. For, by th'autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the same authours, who deny witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft in sending Divells both Ʋnto &amp; Jnto men,<note place="margin">Lib. 1.6.</note> he likewise indefinitly concludeth that
<pb n="87" facs="44"/>
his discourse against the cōfessions of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Againe, Is it not likely, That <note n="*" place="margin">D. Barl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; Abrah. Hartwell belong to the L. B. of Can. S.H. to the L. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of Lond.</note> birdes of a fether will fly togeather? Further, D. Barlowes reason at Cambridge Why in these dayes there is no possession, was this: <hi>Christ came to dissolue the works of darknes,</hi> &amp; <hi>vpon the Crosse he triumphed ouer pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and principalities:</hi> Ergo, There is nowe no possession. He may conclude aswel, Ergo, There is now no witchcraft: yea no murder, no pride, no Jdolatry, &amp;c. Moreover, There is reason why it is expedient for S. H. inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly and implicatiuely to make witchraft doubtfull. For, If there be no witchcraft at all, then may he conclude, All M. Dorrels possessiōs (which ar said to be by witchcraft) must needes be counterfeitings. Who would loose such an argument? But consider (good Reader) whether such a conclusion tend not to the cōfirmation of Atheists. If so: may we not feare, that Witches &amp; Atheists may hope for more fauour with thē, then M. Dor. The rather, if we cōsider <hi>2.</hi> actions of S.H. his L. &amp; master on friday <hi>8.</hi> dayes at the Session in Lond. First, howe vnwilling hee was to finde <note n="“" place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Anne Ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ke, spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the end.</note>Witchcraft if his L. could haue overruled that court: for notwithstāding he heard suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiēt witnesses testifying grieuous things, &amp; saw a yōg girle falling into a most terrible fit
<pb n="88" facs="45"/>
yet he smiled (at no laughing matter, as som of the Bench tolde his L.) saying, <hi>That hee sawe nothing that might not be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited,</hi> and tolde, how many Counterfeits he had lately discouered. Wherevpon Iudge <hi>Anderson,</hi> and other of the Bench thought it necessarie for the satisfying of the Iurie to vrge the Scriptures for proofe that there is witchcrafte, and (of their owne knowledge) to tell of sundry bewitched, yea possessed out of whom Diuels spake: and of a childe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched to death whose eyes were fast clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, yet when the Witch came in presence they opened, and (as it were) stared vpon the Witch. Second: How earnest his L. was to free an Atheist then and there arraigned for blasphemie against God. For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing his L. acknowledged that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theist had bene before the high Commission for such blasphemie, yet he pleaded that the secular power had nothing to doe with him vntill the spiritual iurisdiction had pronoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him obstinate in his blasphemie. Ʋpon whose wordes the Atheist tooke holde and heart, openly and impudently to say, <hi>My Lord, if any heere can proove there is a God, I will beleeue it.</hi> Would the L. B. haue done such a part if Mai. Dorrell had bene then and there arraigned for teaching
<pb n="89" facs="45"/>
to coūterfeit possession? To drawe towards an ende. Whereas S. H. his <hi>Discoverie</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth partly of matter of Opinion, viz. a close fight against possession, at least in these dayes: and of matter of Fact, viz. a bearing downe of Mai. Dorrell with a tumultuous riot of wordes as a Teacher of sundry to counterfeit possession: This (I hope) I may presume to saye touching the former, that if S. H. will take in hande directly and syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistically to conclude his negatiue opinion from the Scriptures, sonne (no doubt) of M. Dorrels friendes (so oft by him provoked) wil returne (to vse his own wordes pag. <hi>324) matter sufficient to shewe his skill in.</hi> As for the matter of Fact, this I dare boldly say: That if M. Dorrell doe not refute all imputations &amp; arguments materiall, which are not sufficiently answerd in this Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (provided hee may haue libertie) all his friendes will abandon him: yea the Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Publisher of his apologie, and this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, if they be alive &amp; make cōscience of their wayes. I say, If they be aliue, because if they be all one (as some may suppose, and I haue heard presumptions giuen so to thinke) then they, in one, be departed this life.</p>
   <p>Jn meane while, I desire thee (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to consider one thing with me, that is,
<pb n="90" facs="46"/>
whether it may not be concluded, That a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Raking of riches doeth manifest the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfyed pouertie of a couetous minde; so the Raking of matter, euen from papistes, and that to no good purpose: The exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of M. Dorrell (at seuerall tymes) v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>8.</hi> or <hi>9.</hi> skore interrogatories; and the deposing of <hi>52.</hi> witnesses (as S. H. recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth pag. <hi>13.</hi>) doeth not manifest an vnsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied minde, and (by consequence) the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie of S.H. his cause. Which point, that is, of the Prelates their not beeing satisfied (in their secret perswasion) touching M. <hi>Dorrel</hi> his guiltines, may the rather be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved, For that, within these fewe dayes, notwithstanding Ma. <hi>Dorrell,</hi> and Ma. <hi>Moore</hi> were both deposed from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, and committed to close prison, there to remayne vntil order were taken for their further punishment, (as S. H. reporteth pa. <hi>9.</hi>) yet for all that, they haue offered (by M. <hi>Barker</hi> the Register, who went of purpose to M. <hi>Dorrell</hi> in the <hi>Gatehouse</hi>) libertie vpon these conditions, That they should not iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their cause, nor meddle any more with prayer, and fasting for parties possessed.</p>
   <p>Which good motion of graunting liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (J say not vpon such conditions) to Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, of whose Ministery the Church may
<pb n="91" facs="46"/>
haue good vse, in these tymes, when Priests and Papistes multiply and practise so fast, I could wish the Reverende Prelates would follow, and doe that of loue towards <hi>Christ</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Gospell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 16.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 39.23.18.</note> which the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of <hi>Philippi</hi> did for feare of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> to wit, They deliuered <hi>Paul</hi> out of prison with credit, whom they had punished more severely then casting out a Diuell had deserued. But how soever it shall please God to mooue the heartes of our Reuerend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Let me intreat thee (Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to suspende thy iudgement in M. <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels</hi> till M. <hi>Dorrell,</hi> or some of his friendes haue made further aunswere then heere is, or can bee made: and then to iudge as thou shalt see cause. And so I passe to the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>Report,</hi> accompanied with another of like argument.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>