<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WELL meaning Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113892_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11734</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3532</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113892</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WELL meaning Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vnreasonablenesse of the separation : Made apparant, by an examination of Mr. Iohnsons pretended reasons, published an. 1608. Wherby hee laboureth to iustifie his schisme from the church assemblies of England</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WELL meaning Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hink not euill, if thou meanest well, wee intend not to insult over him that is downe, or to pursue a man that is flying of himselfe: but to lend him a hand that knoweth not well which way to take. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Iohnson in deed, is rather to bee pitied, then much opposed: wee need but stand still as lookers on: hee falleth willingly on his owne sword but that his fall may bee a rising againe, not onely to himself, but to others also, both armour-bearers &amp; followers of his: it was iudged necessarie, to guide them a litle while their heads are dizzy, &amp; bring them fairly from of the bogge they haue stood on.</p>
   <p>It is not M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Johnson that is dealt with alone
<pb facs="3"/>for change the name onely, and put in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Ains<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, or any such: themselues will not say but the reasons are theirs, and the answer, to them, as well as to him. Jt may bee that they hauing lesse acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with logicall formes of dispute, will looke for large discourse, or heaped quotations out of scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. But reason will tell them, that many words doe rather hide them vntie the knot of a syllogisme: and much quoting may proue some-thing, but ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wereth not directly to any thing. Now the wrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters meaning was, not to gather proofes, but to poynt at the weaknesse of such as these men haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered. Read therfore with vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and learn a mean betwixt <hi>All</hi> and <hi>Nothing.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>