<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable Sir Francis VValsingham Knight, Principall Secretarie to her Maiestie, and of her Highnesse most Honourable Priuie Counsell: And to the godlie and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Vrsula his Wife: RICHARD SAINTBARB the vnworthie seruant and mi∣nister of Christ, wisheth great prosperitie in this life, with encrease of grace and peace from GOD the Father, and life euerlasting through Iesus Christ our life and Redeemer.</title>
           <author>Saintbarb, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113423_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11295</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21556</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113423</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable Sir Francis VValsingham Knight, Principall Secretarie to her Maiestie, and of her Highnesse most Honourable Priuie Counsell: And to the godlie and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Vrsula his Wife: RICHARD SAINTBARB the vnworthie seruant and mi∣nister of Christ, wisheth great prosperitie in this life, with encrease of grace and peace from GOD the Father, and life euerlasting through Iesus Christ our life and Redeemer.</title>
                 <author>Saintbarb, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine points of christian religion</title>
                 <author>Saintbarb, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <distributor>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Young (Yong), William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 58-90 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>To the right Honourable Sir <hi>Francis VValsingham</hi> Knight, Principall Secretarie to her Maiestie, and <hi>of her Highnesse most Honourable Priuie</hi> Counsell: And to the godlie and vertuous <hi>Ladie, the Ladie</hi> Vrsula <hi>his Wife:</hi> RICHARD SAINTBARB the vnworthie seruant and <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of Christ, wisheth great prosperitie in this</hi> life, with encrease of grace and peace from <hi>GOD the Father, and life euerlasting</hi> through Iesus Christ our life and Redeemer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ight I not <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> seeme ouer bold, or might my presumption therein be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: I should not only then hold my selfe freed from one of my chiefest cares, but also it woulde minister greate ioy vnto my distrustfull and fearefull mind. For now I rest doubtfull to make your Honours defenders of these my first fruites &amp; simple labours: but I cannot on the sudden comfort my timorous and weake spirit with possession of such your fauours (and that it were vnmeete that good thinges should be hindred &amp; buried for anie perticular respect,
<pb facs="2"/>
I wil reserue vnto my selfe the hope of your good and godlie likings: and so as one who as well by the report of Gods deere children, both of preachers and others, as in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure himselfe hath beene made acquainted with your holie &amp; religious dispositions not onely in sauouring good things and the truth of the Gospell which is the power of God to saluation. <hi>Rom. 1.16.</hi> but also in furthering by all good &amp; godly meanes the building vp of the beawtifull and precious house of God that the sanctified spouse of Christ <hi>Ephes. 5.</hi> might bee edified and furthered in all sound knowledge and holie faith. <hi>2. Pet. 1.5, 6, 7, 8.</hi> I wholly therefore depend vpon your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance of the cause I handle, which I doubt not, but throughlie assure my selfe it shall doe great good in the Church of God: and bring singuler profite vnto Gods deare Saintes: and thus being resolued, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thereof, your Honours will vouchsafe to beare with my ras<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nesse and weakenesse, and take to your defence this godlie treatise of the grounds and principall questions of christian Religion: my proceeding wherein I leaue to be censur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d by your wise and sound
<pb facs="2"/>
iudgments: little regarding the carping mate and curious reader either of proud papist, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Heriticke, dissembling hipocrite or blind Atheist who neuer with godlie reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence regard the truth of Christ, neither the deuiding of the worde of God aright. And thus praying that GOD of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies will blesse your Honours with all his good blessings, I humblie take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Kingswood in Wilt.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the 2. of September, 1589.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours most humblie to commaund in the Lord Jesus,</hi> Richard Saintbarb <hi>Preacher of Gods word.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>