<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE LOYALL Hearted Subiects of ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>R., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113759_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08083</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1845</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113759</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE LOYALL Hearted Subiects of ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>R., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tocsin, or watch-bell : sent to the king, queene regent, princes of blood, to all the parlaments, magistrates, officers, and loyall subiects of France. Against the booke of the popes temporall power, not long since set forth by Cardinall Bellarmine Iesuite. By Memnons Statue. With the permission of the best genie of Fraunce. And done into English by I.R</title>
                 <author>Le Jay, Nicolas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE LOYALL Hearted Subiects of ENGLAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Author of this small Treatise testifieth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be a true hearted subiect to the Crowne of France, by composing it; J will likewise (in emulation and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his fidelity) approue my selfe to be no lesse to the Crowne of England, by translating it. For sith this bloudy booke of Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (ambitiously ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating to himselfe the Title of the
<pb facs="3"/>Popes <hi>Temporall power</hi>) though par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly sent to France, is neuerthelesse meant, and doth concerne all other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Soueraignties and free States whatsoeuer; I thought in honour to God, in alleageance to my Prince, in loue to my Countrie, and in duetie to all, J was bound to dispoile out of his French habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, and to sute in our English attire this iudicious and compendious Treatise, which so worthily opposeth and impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it. Come, nay then run, if not flie hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you loyall hearted English men, and as the choise of the wisest, chiefest and loyallest hearted French haue already, so in religion, in zeale, in discretion and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice doe you now commit and sacrifice to the fire both <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke, and the thought, much more the practise of those irreligious, vsurping and sanguynat spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and positions therein contained, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="3"/>to the disgrace, preiudice, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction both of our Kings &amp; Countries; yea for euer (in your hearts and soules) not onely spit at, but defie the wrongfull, tyrannicall, Jesuiticall and Diabolicall pretence of this (Sophisticall traytor, and treacherous Sophister) <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who (as subtlely as inueterately) aimeth, not to reach at, but to take off the Crownes of Kings, and (iniustlie) to place them vpon the heads of Popes; yea to trample their Scepters and Regall Ornaments vnder their feet, and to bring their Dominions and subiects, both into a wofull desolation and a miserable subiection and slauerie.</p>
   <p>For alas, shall we permit to see, or liue to permit that our Roiall Kings of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (not inferior to anie, but equall with the greatest Kings of the world) should now (through our negligence) be made homagers, subiects, nay slaues vnto Popes
<pb facs="4"/>(Gods mortall enemies, and our deadly professed foes) as was our King <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Fredericke Barbarossa,</hi> the King of Nauarre, and Earle of Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louse, &amp;c.)</p>
   <p>No, no, illustrious and generous Nobilitie, iudicious and faithfull priuie Counsellors, learned and vpright Judges, reuerend and religious Prelates, valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and warlike Gentry, incorruptible and watchfull Magistrates, faithful and vigilant Officers, obedient and loyall Commons; ioine all in one, yea, let euery mothers sonne (if occasion require) with an vnanime consent, <hi>Viua Voce,</hi> cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and couragiously, with Drummes beating, Trumpets sounding, and Canons roaring, denounce Warre to that Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, nay to that Pope, nay to that diuell, which presumeth or durst presume to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue either our King of his soueraigntie,
<pb facs="4"/>or our Countrey of her independencie: yea next and immediatly to the zeale of the glory of God, let vs be zealous &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, watchful and couragious, couragious and resolute, for the securitie and preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of King <hi>IAMES</hi> our dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and his heires for euer; and for the conseruation and maintaining of the Soueraigntie, both of his Crowne and Kingdome of England, the Paradice of the world, and our sweet natiue Countrie.</p>
   <p>And the more to incite, and powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incourage you in the performance of this your religious and sworne duety; I haue translated, published, and here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent you this <hi>Tocsin,</hi> (or <hi>Watch-bell</hi>) that when you chaunce to sleepe in your beddes of securitie, it may arouse and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake you to stand vpon your guard, with Swordes drawne, Muskets charged, Match lighted, and hearts eagerlie sharpened and animated to destroy and
<pb facs="5"/>confound the Pope and his adhaerents, and to subuert and ouerthrow all other hostile enemies whatsoeuer, which shal ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incroach vpon our Temporalitie, or attempt to depriue vs of our Soueraignty; to the end that neither the fame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of our deceased triumphant and victorious warriours (which hath hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore spread it selfe to the farthest and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motest parts of the world, and is for euer characteris'd vpon the neuer-dying Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of immortality) may not deseruedly taunt &amp; taxe vs with the scandalous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of cowardise, nor our posteritie hereafter, reuile and curse vs for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them inheritors and heires, onely to Tyrannicall slauery, and Presbyteriall seruitude: from the which God of his mercy preserue &amp; defend both our selues and them. And hereunto let all the loyall hearted subiects of King <hi>Iames</hi> clappe hands, and say <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By I. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>