<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Le. A. to the Reder.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113407_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09706</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19970</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113407</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Le. A. to the Reder.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The goodli history of the moste noble and beautyfull Ladye Lucres of Scene in Tuskane, and of her louer Eurialus verye pleasaunt and delectablevnto ye reder</title>
                 <author>Pius, II, pope</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <head>¶ Le. A. to the Reder.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>I this litle boke y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> maist perceiue mi frend</l>
      <l>The end of loue not fained nor fortunable</l>
      <l>By which right plainly thou maist entend</l>
      <l>That loue is no plesur, but a paī {per}durable</l>
      <l>And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> end is deth which is most lamētable</l>
      <l>Therfore ere thou be chayned with suche care</l>
      <l>By others peryls, take hede and beware.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Fyrst by Eurialus, by whome perceyue thou mayst</l>
      <l>The best it is, to eschue shortlye</l>
      <l>To drynke of the cup, or of it to taste</l>
      <l>That sauoured more of gall than of hony</l>
      <l>Also I coulde shewe the hystoryes of many</l>
      <l>That if they by tyme had made resistence</l>
      <l>They myght haue eschued al such inconuenyence.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ There was also the noble Troylus</l>
      <l>Whych all hys lyfe, abode in mortall payne</l>
      <l>Delayed by Cresyde whose history is piteous</l>
      <l>Tyll at the last Achylles had hym slayne</l>
      <l>Yet other there be, whyche in thys carefull chayne</l>
      <l>Of loue haue contynued; all theyr lyfe dayes</l>
      <l>Deathe was theyr end, there was non other wayes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ We rede also of Piramis and Thisbe</l>
      <l>Whych slew them self by theyr seruent loue</l>
      <l>Of Hercules, and of the fayre Ioyle</l>
      <l>Wyth many other, whyche I coulde not attayne</l>
      <l>And of Dido, whiche wyth her selfe stroue</l>
      <l>For loue of Eneas, whan she coulde not attaine</l>
      <l>Tyll at the laste she had her self slayne</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <pb facs="34"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>