<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Angelus Politianus his Epigram on the banish∣ment and death of Ovid.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113811_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08674</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113811</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Angelus Politianus his Epigram on the banish∣ment and death of Ovid.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ouids Tristia : containinge fiue bookes of mournfull elegies which hee sweetly composed in the midst of his aduersitie, while hee liu'd in Tomos a cittie of Pontus where hee dyed after seauen yeares banishment from Rome. Translated into English by. W.S</title>
                 <author>Ovid</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Grove, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>130 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epigram">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> his Epigram on the banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and death of <hi>Ovid.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>THe <hi>Romane</hi> Poet lies in the <hi>Euxine</hi> shore,</l>
   <l>And barbarous earth the Poet covers o're:</l>
   <l>Him that did write of love that land doth hide,</l>
   <l>Through which the <hi>Isters</hi> colder streame doth glide.</l>
   <l>And wert not asham'd to be (O <hi>Rome</hi>)</l>
   <l>More cruell than the <hi>Getes</hi> to such a sonne?</l>
   <l>Oh Muses, while he sicke in <hi>Scythia</hi> lay,</l>
   <l>Who was there that his sicknesse could allay?</l>
   <l>Or keepe his cold limbes in the bed by force,</l>
   <l>Or passe away the day with some discourse?</l>
   <l>Or that could feele his pulse when it did beate,</l>
   <l>Or apply to him warme things to cherish heate?</l>
   <l>Or close his eyes even swimming round with death,</l>
   <l>And in his mouth receive his latest breath?</l>
   <l>There were none, for his ancient friends then were</l>
   <l>In thee O <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Pontus</hi> distant farre.</l>
   <l>His Wife and Nephewes were farre off, together</l>
   <l>His daughter went not with her banisht father.</l>
   <l>The <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssi</hi> and <hi>Coralli</hi> were in these partes,</l>
   <l>And the skin-wearing <hi>Getes</hi> wirh stony hearts.</l>
   <l>The <hi>Sarmatian</hi> riding on his horse was there,</l>
   <l>To comfort him with lookes that dreadfull were.</l>
   <l>Yet when he was dead, the <hi>Bessi</hi> wept, the <hi>Gete,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And stout <hi>Sarmatians</hi> did their faces beate.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>Woods, mountaines, beasts, a mourning day did keepe,</l>
   <l>And <hi>Isters</hi> pearly streame they say did weepe.</l>
   <l>Some say that frozen <hi>Pontus</hi> did begin</l>
   <l>To melt, with teares of Sea-nymphes shed for him.</l>
   <l>Light <hi>Cupids</hi> with their mother <hi>Venus</hi> ranne,</l>
   <l>And vvith torches set the funerall pile on flame:</l>
   <l>And while his body did consume and burne,</l>
   <l>They put his ashes in a closed Vrne:</l>
   <l>And on his Tombe-stone these words graven were,</l>
   <l>He that did teach the Art of love lyes here.</l>
   <l>Then <hi>Venus</hi> with her white hand did bedew</l>
   <l>His grave, while she sweet Nectar on him threw.</l>
   <l>The Muses brought their Poet many a verse,</l>
   <l>Which I am farre unworthy to rehearse.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>