<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL AND Religious Knight, Sir THOMAS POSTHVMVS HOBY, and to the honourable and vertuous Lady, the Lady MARGARET his wife, A. B. wisheth the increase of grace heere, and the fruition of glory hereafter.</title>
           <author>Bifield, Adoniram</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113882_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69028</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4233.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL AND Religious Knight, Sir THOMAS POSTHVMVS HOBY, and to the honourable and vertuous Lady, the Lady MARGARET his wife, A. B. wisheth the increase of grace heere, and the fruition of glory hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Bifield, Adoniram</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rule of faith: or, An exposition of the Apostles Creed : so handled as it affordeth both milke for babes, and strong meat for such as are at full age. By that worthy seruant of Gods Church, Master Nicholas Bifield, late minister of Gods Word at Islevvorth, and by him in his life time fully perfected and transcribed, so much as is now published for the benefit of Gods Church, by his sonne, Adoniram Bifield</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Miller, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rounthwait, Ralph</publisher>
                            <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 63, 84-100, 81-272, 301-563, 25 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL AND Religious Knight, Sir THOMAS POSTHVMVS HOBY, <hi>and to the honourable</hi> and vertuous Lady, the Lady MARGARET <hi>his wife,</hi> A. B. <hi>wisheth the increase of grace</hi> heere, and the fruition of glory <hi>hereafter.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are many waies to attaine to seeming honour heere vpon earth; there is no way to attaine to true honour, besides this of Piety and Vertue: Godlinesse brings the best gaine, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test honour vnto a Christian: others may be more rich, none are more honorable then they: others may bee more esteemed of by the men of the world, none haue more honour both with God and good men then they: as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>The wise shall inherit glory, but fooles, dishonor, though they</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 335.</note>
      <hi>be exalted:</hi> this is the inheritance of the godly, who is the onely <hi>Wise man:</hi> So that I may now say with
<pb facs="3"/>
our Sauiour, your Worships haue both chosen the better part, which shall neuer be taken from you: I hauing euer obserued it to haue been your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test ambitions, to be true Christians: which alone makes you <hi>more excellent then your neighbours:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue you made choise of Religion as many Hypocrites and Time-seruers doe, making it a stalking horse, a footstoole to the seat of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; making choice of Religion for nothing else but onely for the aduancing of themselues and compassing of their owne priuate ends: no, your end and aime hath euer beene in all your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices and imployments, both to aduance the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, as also to further the peace and welfare of this Church and Common-Wealth wherin we liue, and whereof God hath made your Worship a worthy member. This indouldens me humbly to present this ensuing Treatise vnto you both: which may be called the <hi>Rule of Faith, the Symbole or Badge,</hi> whereby a true Christian may be distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished, and knowne from all Iewes, Turkes, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists, Papists, Hereticks, counterfeting Tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, and false Professors: the Doctrine of the <hi>Creed,</hi> containing in it the substance of Christian Religion, Taught by the Apostles, Imbraced by the ancient Fathers, and Sealed by the bloud of the Martyrs: The exposition of which <hi>Creed,</hi> so far
<pb facs="3"/>
as it was perfected by the Author, I heere present vnto you both, desiring that it may shelter it selfe vnder your protection; many reasons infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing me thereto: first, that honour, and <hi>Singular Loue,</hi> which you both haue shewed vnto those that <hi>Labour in the Word and Doctrine:</hi> as you are pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of Piety, so are you Patrons of pious and godly men, and of their labours: secondly, that loue and respect which you were pleased in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to expresse vnto the Author of this Treatise (my deare Father, now with God) which since his death, you haue been pleased to continue both vnto the fruit of <hi>his Braine,</hi> as also to the fruit of <hi>his body,</hi> this imboldens me to commit this <hi>Posthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> to your protection: thirdly, that good esteeme which you haue euer had of this work, manifested, both, when you were pleased to bee diligent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of it when it was preached, so long as you were both resident in those parts, as also by your earnest desire of the publishing of it, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Gods Church: and I doubt not but that you will now fauorably receiue that which formerly you haue so highly esteemed, &amp; so much desired: lastly, that speciall duty which I my selfe owe vnto you both for your extraordinary Loue, and (by me vndeserued) fauours which you haue beene both pleased to shew vnto me, since it pleased God
<pb facs="4"/>
to depriue me of the benefit of such a Father; this my duty bindeth me, with all humility and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to acknowledge them, therefore doe I willingly take this oportunity, humbly to present this ensuing Treatise vnto you both, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but that you will receiue it into your Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: so that whilst you beleeue, and countenance and defend the Truth, <hi>The Truth shall make you free:</hi> These things do, and the God of Truth and Peace shall be with you: now the God of all grace make you perfect, confirme, strengthen, and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish you, and blesse you with all spiritual blessings in heauenly things through Christ, with temporal blessings here, and with eternal blessings in his Kingdome, <hi>Such shall be the dayly Prayers of</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships humbly deuoted,
ADONIRAM BIFIELD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>