<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfuls, Sir Frauncis Iobson Knight, Lieuetenaunt of the Toure, Sir Henrie Neuell Knight, and M. Pellam Lieuete∣naunt of the Ordinaunce, geue these.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113017_Fr1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13812</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24113</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfuls, Sir Frauncis Iobson Knight, Lieuetenaunt of the Toure, Sir Henrie Neuell Knight, and M. Pellam Lieuete∣naunt of the Ordinaunce, geue these.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to certein assertions of M. Fecknam, sometime abbot of Westminster : which he made of late against a godly sermon of M. Iohn Goughes, preached in the Tower the xv. of Ianuarie. 1570. Seen and allowed</title>
                 <author>Tomson, Laurence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                            <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>79 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="Fecknams_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfuls, Sir Frauncis Iobson Knight, Lieuetenaunt of the Toure, Sir Henrie Neuell Knight, and M. Pellam Lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of the Ordinaunce, geue these.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our worships re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest</hi> was vpon Sunday last, as I came from the Churche, to know my ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>M. Goughes</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Wherunto I answered: that I was very lothe to finde any faulte with the sayings or dooings of any man, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in trouble as you knowe. You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied and sayd: that I was not able to find fault, where no fault was. I had thē no leisure to make any further answer, you departing homewardes, and I to my prison. But now considering wyth my self, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I might séeme vnto you a greater offēder in holding my peace, than in spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my mind: when as saying nothing I might ingender an opinion in you, that I am obstinate, self willed, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="3"/>
to mislike but mine owne proper fansie. On the other side, to declare my minde, I might signifie vntoo you the iust causes, and true occasions, which I haue to finde fault withall: not so much for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending other men, as to shew the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary stayes of mine owne conscience: I thought good, vppon your lycence graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and obteyned, to expresse by wryting some faultie matter of his sermon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by your worships might perceiue in the rest, how much fault he is worthy of for speaking, and how litle I deserue for not lyking of so vngodly pointes of doctrine. Desiring you most humbly, fauorably to interprete these my notes of reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Sermon: that is, to proceede of a minde, not desirous of contention, but desirous of the truthe: more seeking to satisfie your request and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, than to minister a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occasion of further argument.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>