<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Friendly and Courteous Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113628_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08551</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113628</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Friendly and Courteous Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seuenth booke of the Myrrour of knighthood : Being the second of the third part. Englished out of the Spanish language</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>316 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ To the Friendly and Courteous Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T length, on the vncertaine surges of your gentlenes I doe aduenture, of all necessaries my vnfurnisht barke, hauing none other confidence but the generall acceptance of the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, safely to let me Anchor my desires on your contēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This onely did imboulden me to satisfie the requests of many, and not the will to publish my owne folly, and disgrace: whose harsh and vnpleasing Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode the sequell amply shewes. In which I haue in many places addrest my speech, &amp; directed the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as it were particulerly to one or to more Ladies or Gentlewomen; wherein I must aduertise you, It is ment by no especiall <hi>Mistres,</hi> saue onely an immitation of my Author, &amp; the rather because in loue discourses (and this story treating nothing else) they haue the sole preheminēce, as also hoping for their sakes (to whom euery Mothers Sonne that moues is adicted) to finde a more kinder intertainement: whose memorie I trust will impetrate it. My faults by the Printer omitted &amp; aggrauated gently amend, and though you do dislike, doe not (for my good will deserues it not) condemne me, so shall I neuer cease to crie <hi>(Amen)</hi> to your own wishes, and will ere long gratefie your fauours wyth another part, Meane while.</p>
   <q>Cum desint vires, nostr' est laudanda voluntas.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>