<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Master Bayne his Prayer before his Sermons.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113830_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05990</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1634</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113830</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Master Bayne his Prayer before his Sermons.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians garment : A sermon preached in London, by the late faithfull minister of Gods word, Master Paul Bayne</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rounthwait, Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 19, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Master <hi>Bayne</hi> his Prayer before his Sermons.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR gracious God and mercifull Father in Christ: We confesse, that as wee are vnworthy to appeare in thy sight, so wee are of our selues insufficient to euery good worke; and much more to those of speaking and hearing thy Word: for which, who are sufficient? Wee beseech thee therefore, in the entrance of these our duties, to help vs with thy good Spirit, that the thoughts of our hearts, and words of our mouthes may be acceptable before thee. Wee confesse to thy glory and our shame, that we are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable sinners: if we looke to our selues, as lying in the loynes of our first parents, we are a tainted seed, iustly disinherited of glory: if wee consider our selues, as comming into this light, we are all concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and brought forth in sinne, which like a Leprosy hath spred it selfe into all the powers of vs; that what we haue done of our owne strength, is abomination, and whatsoeuer is truely good, we haue altogether neglected it, there being not one that doth good, no not one. More particularly we acknowledge, euen we, to whom thou hast beene mercifull, to make vs taste how good thou art in Christ; that since the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall working of grace in vs, wee haue not ceased, through the relickes of our corruption, to multiply trespasses against all thy commandements, especially we haue prouoked the eyes of thy glory by taking thy Name in vaine, by comming to heare and speake
<pb facs="4"/>thy Word without renewing our faith, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and so haue deserued, that thou shouldest turne thy Ordinances to become a sauour of death vnto vs: Yea, if in none of these kinds we had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded heretofore, yet since we haue bowed our knees, making these our confessions, wee discerne such blindenesse of minde, and hardnesse of heart with vs in the same, for which thou mightest iustly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, wouldst thou deale in Iustice, and deny vs Mercy: Neuerthelesse, seeing it pleased thee by faith in Christ to make vs thy sonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wee do in this regard enter thy presence with boldnesse, as it becommeth thy children, beseeching thee to make vs able alwaies to challenge our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse before thee, that we may say with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, making requests in the death and resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Christ: It is Christ, that is dead, yea who is risen from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, and maketh intercession for vs. Who shall condemne vs, or lay any thing to the charge of vs thy chosen? To this end, send the holy Spirit of thy Sonne into our hearts, which may renew vs more and more to that heauenly Image from whence wee are fallen, which standeth in sauing knowledge, righteousnesse, and true holinesse. And because thou hast appointed thy Word preached, for a meanes of begetting and strengthening this faith, and perfecting thine owne Image in vs, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, blesse thy Ordinance at this time vnto vs; Thou, who hast made the Ministery of it, a Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Spirit, in which thy Spirit worketh our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations: And because we know, that when we should
<pb facs="5"/>receiue the greatest benefite from thee, that then Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than is most malicious against vs; we beseech thee to saue vs from the power of all spirituall wickednesse, and from the darkenesse, deadnesse, wandring and wearinesse of our owne hearts. O thou who hast promised, that if we resist Sathan, he shall flye from vs; grant, that we flying to thee in prayer of faith, may begin, proceed in, and conclude these, and all such duties to the glory of thy name, and the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our true happinesse. Blesse our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne the Kings Maiesty, blesse his Person and his Throne, sanctifie his heart, enlarge it euery day more and more for thy glory, his owne comfort, and the good of his people. Blesse the Queene, the Prince, with the Nobility and Clergie of this Land: giue them all, O Lord, from the highest to the lowest, such a measure of thy grace, that they may faithfully and conscionably, according to their seuerall Callings, discharge such duties both in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as thou in thy sacred Word hast comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Wee beseech thee to heare vs in these, and all things thou knowest needfull for vs: yea make vs to see that thou hearest vs (for such is our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion toward thee in CHRIST) that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer we aske agreeable to thy will in his Name, it is giuen vnto vs, but make vs finde it by good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that our faith may be strengthened, and that wee may teach all flesh to resort vnto thee, who art a God hearing prayer: To whom with thy Christ, and the Spirit, be giuen from our hearts all Honour, for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>