<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE SVMMARIE OF THIS WORKE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113483_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05335</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15488</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113483</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE SVMMARIE OF THIS WORKE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the interchangeable course, or variety of things in the whole world : and the concurrence of armes and learning, thorough the first and famousest nations: from the beginning of ciuility, and memory of man, to this present. Moreouer, whether it be true or no, that there can be nothing sayd, which hath not bin said heretofore: and that we ought by our owne inuentions to augment the doctrine of the auncients; not contenting our selues with translations, expositions, corrections, and abridgments of their writings. Written in French by Loys le Roy called Regius: and translated into English by R.A</title>
                 <author>Leroy, Louis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Yetsweirt, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 130 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE SVMMARIE OF THIS WORKE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ECAVSE the Discourse following is long, and somewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to comprehend, by reason of the diuersitie of matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein; I haue gathered, and set downe, first: The Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie of the whole worke; Then of euery Booke in order; to giue more light vnto the Readers, for the vnderstanding therof. In the whole worke therfore are represented, the successiue, or rather alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue changes of the whole world, aswell in the higher or superiour, as lower and inferiour part thereof; and how by the concurrence of Armes and Letters, thorough the most renowmed Nations of the world, all liberall Sciences, and Mechanical Arts, haue flourished together, fallen, and bin restored, diuers times in proces of Age: With a comparison of such Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as haue excelled, both in power and knowledge; of the great Empires, and renowmed Monarkes, vnder whom these notable mutations of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind haue hapned; and conferring of this our present, with the famousest former Ages, to know wherein it is either inferiour, superiour, or equall to any of them.</p>
   <div n="1" type="part">
      <head>THE FIRST BOOKE.</head>
      <p>THE Enterchangeable course, or Variety obserued in the motions of Heauen, and the Heauenly Spheares, (whereon are depending the Changes which happen in this inferiour World) are declared in the first Booke. The Vicissitude which the fower Elements haue one with an other, and euery one by himselfe. How all things in the World are tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and conserued by others, that are contrarie, and dislike. The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of Shadowes, Daies, and Seasons of the yeare; and the Diuersitie of habitations of the Earth: and other thinges, according to the difference of places. The Variety and Vicissitude of Men, of Nations, Cities, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weales, Kingdomes, and Empires.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="part">
      <head>THE II. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>THE Variety of Tongues vsed thorough out the world; both Learned, and Vulgar. The Beginning of them, Continuance, Perfection, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, Chaunge, and Losse of the old; Introduction of new; Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of one into an other; Imposition of Names to things; Inuention and profit of Letters; Diuersitie of Characters, and Writings, Instruments and Matters to write with. Of Printing, Orthographic, and Pronunciation.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="part">
      <head>THE III. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>THE Vicissitude, and Inuention of Arts: And how Men from their first simplicitie and rudenesse, haue attained to the Commoditie, Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and Excellencie of this time.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="part">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>THE IIII. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>THe Intercourse of Armes, and of Letters, concurring in the coniunction of Power and Wisdome, amongst the most renowmed Nations of the world: And who haue bin the first, and Auncientest of all, that haue excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in both. The Power, Knowledge, and other Excellencie of the Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Assyrians, and Persians. A Comparison of the great Monarchies, the Egiptian, Assyrian, Median, Persian, and Parthian, in their situations, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, largenes, reuenewes, riches, mightines; &amp; of such famous Monarchs as founded them; and vnder whom they perished. Of the Egiptian Priests or Prophets; of the Chaldees, Mages, Brachmanes, Druydes, and others of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Learning amongst the Auncients. Nobilitie amongst the Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Persians, Assyriansi, Indians, Scythians, Thracians, and other aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and modern Nations. The exquisite Artisans, and workmanship of the Auncients.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="part">
      <head>THE V. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>OF the Learning, Poesie, Eloquence, Power, and other Excellencie of the Greekes. A Comparison of them with the Egiptians, Assyrians, Persi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Indians. The Empire of Greece. A Comparison of Alexander the great, with Cyrus, Agesilaus, Themistocles, Pericles, Achilles, Vlysses, Diomedes, Bacchus, Hercules, and others. A Comparison of the Grecian Philosophers, with the Chaldees of Babylon, and the Priestes of Egipt. The Nobilitie of auncient Greece. The Artisans and workes of the Grecians.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="part">
      <head>THE VI. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>OF the Power, Warfare, Learning, Eloquence, Poesie, and other Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the Romaines. The fall of their Power, Learning, and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="part">
      <head>THE VII. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>A Comparison of the Romains with the Egiptians, Assyrians, Persians, Greeks, and Parthians; in Power, Warfare, Learning, Language, Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, Poesie; and in the workmanships of other Arts: of the Romain Empire with the Assyrian, Median, Persian, Macedonian, and Parthian. The birth of Rome, and continuance thereof, and conferred with the 4. Ages of mans life. A comparison of Rome with Babylon, and Constantinople; of the Romain common wealth, with the Lacedemonian, and Carthaginian: of the power of Alexander the great, with that which the Romains had in his time: and if when he had conquered Asia, he had turned his forces against Europe, what might haue hapned by the iudgement of Liuie. Of Pompey the great with Alexander, Hercules, &amp; Bacchus, according to Plinie: Of Iulius Caesar with Alexander, according to Appianus Alexandrinus; of Iulius Caesar and Augustus, with Romulus, and Numa; of Romulus with Cyrus, Theseus, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saces, and Semiramis, who founded Cities, or Kingdomes, or Monarchies.
<pb facs="4"/>
A Comparison of the Romain warfare with the Parthian, Carthaginian, &amp; Assyrian: Of the Romain Learning, and other excellencie, with the Grecian, Egiptian, and Chaldean: Of the Latin Authours with the Greek; namely of Cicero with Demosthenes. The Ciuil Law of the Romains. A Comparison of the Latin tongue with the Greek.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="part">
      <head>THE VIII. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>OF the Religion, Power, knowledge, and other excellency of the Arabians, or Sarasens, and other Mahometists. A Comparison of Mahomet with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus, Minos, Numa, Zoroaster, Charondas, Zaleucus, Trismegistus, and other heathen Lawmakers, or Founders of Cities and Empires. The Power of the Arabians, or Sarasens, compared to the Romain, Macedonian, Persian, Parthian, Assyrian, &amp; Egiptian. A Comparison of the Arabian learning with the Greek, Egiptian, Chaldean, Persian, Romain, or Latin: Of the Arabian tongue, with the Greek, Latin, and Hebrew.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="part">
      <head>THE IX. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>COntaineth the sequence of the Power and Religion of the Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists; as of the first Turks, Corasmians, Tartarians; of the Souldan, of the Ottoman, of the Sophi: where there is mention made of the estates of the great Cham of Cathay, of the king of Narsingue, of the Moscouite, and of Presbiter Iohn; because they began, or grew vp at that time; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they haue other Religions.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="10" type="part">
      <head>THE X. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>HOw that in this age haue bin restored the tongues, and knowledges, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had surceased about almost twelue hundred yeres, hauing newly receaued great light, and increase; where are considered, the meruailes of this present age, thorough Europe, Asia, Africke, The new-found lands, in the East, West, North, and South: beginning at the great, &amp; inuincible Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan, whose power, valiancy, and felicity is briefly represented. During whose raign began the restitution of Learning &amp; of Arts: By what persons &amp; means it hath bin continued in diuers nations: The Princes that most haue fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it. Moreouer how that many goodly things vnknowen to antiquity haue bin newly found out, especially Printing, The direction to sayle by the needle of steele rubbed on the Lode-stone, carying alwaies the point answerable to the place where we imagine the pole Artique, by means whereof the whole Sea hath bin sayled ouer, and the whole world knowne thorough out. Then the skill of Ordinance, and Artillery, which hath made all other auncient military instruments to cease, which by this one are all surpassed in impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osity, swiftnes, and violence. Also how amongst the meruailes of this age haue risen new and strange Diseases vnknowen heretofore, and diuers Sects haue sprong vp in all countries, which haue much altered the common quiet, and weakned the mutual charitie of men.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="11" type="part">
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>THE XI. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>THis Age is compared▪ vnto the former ages most famous in deedes of Armes, conduct of States, excellencie of Learning, perfection of Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship, noueltie of Inuentions, Nauigations neuer attempted heretofore, &amp; discouering of New lands, vnknowen to Antiquitie: to know wherin we are inferiour, or equall to the Auncients; and wherin we ought to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. First of all is conferred our modern Warfare, with the auncient Greek, and Romain; Tamberlan is compared with Ninus, Sesostris, Cyrus, Darius, Alexander, Arsaces, Hannibal, Iulius Caesar, Constantine, Attila, and Charles the great. Then followeth the Comparison of our modern Kingdomes, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, Monarchies, and Common weales, with the Auncient. Of Militarie Nations, Armies, Battailes by sea and by land, Sieges, &amp; Assaults of Fortresses. Of Nauigations, and discoueries of Countries, Peregrinations, and Voiages by land. Of the Wealth of the present time, with that of the time past. Of the Maners of this Age, with the former. Finally of the Learning of this age with the Auncient; in Philosophie, Eloquence, Law, Policie, Physick, Poesie, Astrologie, Cosmographie, and the other Mathematicks. Then commeth the Conclusion of the work, by the which there is a vicissitude resolued on in all matters: And how it is to be feared, that Power, Wisdom, Learning, Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Bookes, Industrie, Workmanships, and the Knowledge of the world, being now come to so great Excellencie, should fall againe: as they haue done in times past.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="12" type="part">
      <head>THE XII. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>COnsidering then, that the variable disposition of humane things, is to be readie to fall, when they are at the highest; and that vertue &amp; vice are come to their top, and perfection; doubting least among so many Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities, and Heresies (wherof the world is full) and the Warres which threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs on euery side, that Learning might come to be dispised; and be as loosely left off, and neglected, as heretofore it hath bin diligently followed, and regarded: To the end to preuent such a mischiefe, and to aduize the studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to remedie it, as much as they may; I haue added an Inquisition on the common speach of men, by which they haue alwaies maintained, and do yet maintaine, That nothing can be now said, which hath not bin said hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Wherein I endeuour to show, that there remaineth yet much to be said; and that the trueth hath not bin thoroughly discouered, neither all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge forestalled by our forerunners: Admonishing the Learned, to adde that by their owne Inuentions, which is wanting in the Sciences; doing that for Posteritie, which Antiquitie hath done for vs; to the end, that Learning be not lost, but from day to day may receiue some increase.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>