<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Master Thomas Powle Esquire, Clarke of the Crowne in hir Maiesties high Court of Chauncerie</title>
           <author>E., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113621_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08545</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18863</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Master Thomas Powle Esquire, Clarke of the Crowne in hir Maiesties high Court of Chauncerie</title>
                 <author>E., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the first booke of the Myrrour of knighthood : in which is prosecuted the illustrious deedes of the knight of the Sunne, and his brother Rosicleer, sonnes vnto the Emperour Trebatio of Greece: with the valiant deedes of armes of sundry worthie knights, very delightfull to bee read, and nothing hurtfull to bee regarded. Now newly translated out of Spanish into our vulgar tongue by R.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 258, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Master Thomas <hi>Powle Esquire, Clarke of the Crowne</hi> in hir Maiesties high Court of Chauncerie</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering (right Worshipful) that such men as haue excelled others in vertue or anie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent quallitie, doe shine through perpetuall fame all abroad, and are like the bright Sunne beames, surmounting (without comparison) the small and speedie decaying candles of the rude &amp; ignoble: and seeing that this brightnesse of fame hath, and doth not onely shine in men by vertuous studies and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue exercises, but also in most worthie feats of chiual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rv and martiall prowesse (the knowledge &amp; practise whereof <hi>Cicero,</hi> that most wise and learned Senator, deemed as necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as learning and other good gifts of the minde, to maintaine an orderlie common weale.) Considering also that as well the spirit of God hath by the hands of <hi>Moses,</hi> and of many good men since, published, and that greatly commending them, the valiaunt acts and puissant exploits of sundrie both good and mightie men at armes, as did <hi>Homere, Titus Liuius, Salust,</hi> with many mo, the right martiall and euer memorable acts of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> &amp;c. All which records of Chiualrie <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ending to animate others vnto imitating the like, and beeing <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s a spur to instigate and prick vs forwards vnto prowesse, who <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lse would bee idle and lie in obscuritie: I haue thought it <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot fruitlesse to publish this <hi>Mirrour</hi> of <hi>Knighthood</hi> also, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ented and set forth rather to encourage dastards and to teach <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he readie minded what excellencie is in puissant and inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le mindes, passing common iudgement, then to feede the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="4"/>
with an vntruth. Now, sithens custome hath made it to bee as a law in mens hearts obserued, that they account bookes published not to haue sufficient warrant, except they bee dedicated to some worthie personage of authoritie, I am bolde to present vnto your Worship this Booke, entituled▪ <hi>The second part of the Mirrour of Knighthood,</hi> done out of <hi>Spanish,</hi> and now newly printed: beeseeching your Worship rather to accept of my good will shewed, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect the simplenesse of the gift. Thus ceasing to be tedious, I commit you to the tuition of the Almightie, who blesse you and all yours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your VVorships most assured:
T. E.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>