<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY MONARCH CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD, of Great Bri∣taine, France and Jreland KING, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113129_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14921</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18416</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113129</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY MONARCH CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD, of Great Bri∣taine, France and Jreland KING, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The double-armed man, by the new inuention : briefly shewing some famous exploits atchieued by our Brittish bowmen: with seuerall portraitures proper for the pike and bow. By W.N. archer</title>
                 <author>Neade, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY MONARCH <hi>CHARLES,</hi> By the Grace of GOD, of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France</hi> and <hi>Jreland</hi> KING, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most dread Soveraigne:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY it please your <hi>Maiesty,</hi> to call to your remembrance, how, that some twelue months since I presēted vnto You the Copy of these few lines following in approbation of Bowes &amp; Arrowes:</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Bowes and Arrowes heretofore haue beene famous weapons of warre, both of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensiue and defensiue against the enemies of these Kingdomes: and thereby victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous battels and famous conquests haue bin gotten, though now they are imployed to no vse but for Recreation and sport; but J by practice, with an Jnuention haue attained to this perfection, that a Souldier with his Corslet and Pike may vse his Long-Bow and Arrowes, with great agilitie, more force and aduantage against the Enemy, then euer heretofore, not hindring the vse of Gunnes or other weapons, nor incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to the Pike or any martiall Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>After which, vpon your Maiesties order giuen for the sight thereof, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it before you by a Souldier in your Maiesties Parke at <hi>S. Iames's:</hi> and after that, I petitioned vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,
<pb facs="3"/>that You would bee pleased to giue order that it might be practised in the two Schooles of <hi>martiall Discipline,</hi> the two <hi>Gardens</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> (vnto which two I gaue vnto each a Pike and a Bow placed vnto it, and a sheafe of Arrowes) and your Maiesties Answer vnto my Petition (as I was informed) was, That it were meeter for them to practise it of their owne accord. Vpon which Answer from your Maiesty, I solicited those Societies for the practice and exercise of the Bow with the Pike: and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly that worthy Societie in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery Garden</hi> in <hi>London</hi> hath practised it euer since. But because many of that worthy Society haue not heretofore exercised shooting, it doth not take that perfection as yet, which I hope time and practice will bring it vnto:
<pb facs="4"/>for it is the exercise of shooting that must make men perfect therein: so that if Statute-Lawes were in force for the exercise of Shooting, as in former times they haue beene, then would this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of mine be perfitted, and the Brittish Bowmen grow famous againe as in former ages they were.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Most Gratious Soueraigne:</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue endeuored my selfe vnto the vtmost of my small abilitie, for the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of this Exercise, and spent my time and meanes for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of my desires therin: which is, to make those worthy Societies perfect therein, and so generally throughout the Land: &amp; hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther supportation, nor countenance, from any (but God alone) I cannot wholly imploy my selfe thereunto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing constrained for the maintenance of
<pb facs="4"/>my poore estate and family, to wrestle in the world, neyther haue I literature sufficient, for illustration of so worthy a thing, as is this Inuention, if it were perfect: yet that it may not die in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion, I haue here presented vnto your Maiesty this vnpolished Discourse, shewing herein the antiquitie of the Bow, with part of the famous exploits which were atchieued by the seruice of our Brittish Bowmen, &amp; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths good in the time of the vse thereof. Also, some directions for the practice of the Pike and Bow in Rankes and Fyles, by this Inuention; with some Portraitures of the proper postures belonging thereunto, and the proper words of command for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise thereof: Humbly beseeching your sacred Maiestie, not to reiect it for the rudenesse thereof, for although
<pb facs="5"/>the tongue be faultering like <hi>Moses,</hi> and the hand be rough like <hi>Esawes,</hi> yet the heart is perfect and constant like <hi>Hushai</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid:</hi> Vouchsafe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, gracious Soueraigne, to grace it with your gracious acceptance; and if it grow to perfection, let God haue the honor, your Soueraigne Maiestie the patronage, and this Common-wealth the benefit.</p>
   <p>Meane while I will euer pray vnto the Almighty for your Maiesties hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Reigne, prosperity, and preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both here and hereafter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties most dutifull and loyall Subiect,</hi> WILLIAM NEADE, Archer.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>