<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A REPROVFE OF M. Dorman in prima fronte libri.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113385_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18741</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113385</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A REPROVFE OF M. Dorman in prima fronte libri.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reproufe, written by Alexander Nowell : of a booke entituled, A proufe of certayne articles in religion denied by M. Iuell, set furth by Thomas Dorman, Bachiler of Diuinitie: and imprinted at Antvverpe by Iohn Latius. Anno. 1564. Set foorth and allowed, according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Nowell, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 125, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="proof">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A REPROVFE OF M. Dorman in prima fronte libri.</head>
   <p>Augustinus contra literas Petiliani. lib. 2. cap. 16. Si quaeras, quibus fructibus vos esse potius lupos rapaces cognoscamus, obijcio schismatis crimen, quod tu negabis, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go autem statim probabo. Neque enim communicas omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus gentibus, &amp; illis ecclesiis Apostolico labore fundatis. That is to say. If thou demaundest (he speaketh to Petilian the Heretike) by what fruictes I knovv you to be rather the rauening vvolues, I obiecte to you the fault of scisme, vvhich thou vvilt deny, but I wil out of hande proue. For thou doest not communicate with all Nacions, nor with those churches founded by th'apostles labour.</p>
   <div type="reproof">
      <head>Nowell.</head>
      <p>M. Dorman had either no greate store of choyse, or some lacke of iudgement, whan he did choose S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustines sentence vpon the woordes of our Sauiour of those false Prophetes who comming in sheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Math.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> are in deede rauening woulfes: you shall know them by their fruites &amp;c. For what sentence of all other in the Scriptures or Doctors dooth more liuely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the aduersaries themselues, who, folowinge the olde Iuishe priestes, Scribes and Phariseis (of whom our Sauiour spake y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saide woords) in walking graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in longe garmentes, pretending longe praiers, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring <note place="margin">
            <hi>Mar.</hi> 12. <hi>d.</hi> 38.</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> amiable titles of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Spiritualtie, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Luc</hi> 20. <hi>g.</hi> 46.</note> that louing mother, yea and of fauorable fathers too: &amp; professing with their foresaid forefathers, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they may kill no man, that they may not enter into the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment place, for feare of pollution of that pure white <note place="margin">
            <hi>Iohan.</hi> 18. <hi>e.</hi> 28. <hi>f.</hi> 31.</note> fleese of their innocencie: yea and whan a condemned person falleth into their handes, to be committed to the fecular power, they pitifully make request, that <note place="margin">Domine i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex rogam vos &amp;c.</note> the wretch suffer no losse of life nor limme. And whan
<pb facs="8"/>
they haue so ouerspread and couered themselues with <note place="margin">Vt in actis Regist. Lō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinensi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note> these and suche like sheepish white flieses, more softer than lambes wull, and haue so sheepishly bleated with woordes abhorring bloud: than proceede they forwarde with their said Fathers, than play they most the most rauening woulfes, &amp; moste shew their insaciable thirst of murder and bloudsheading. Let Hierusalem, and the countreis about sprinkled with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bloud of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Christe, and his holy Apostles and Disciples te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie this as moste true in their forefathers, the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riseis, Scribes, and high Priestes: and let all partes of Englande, Fraunce, Italie, Spayne, Germanie, yea of all Christendome ouerspread with the bloud of the innocent sheepe of Christes folde, men and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>men, yea yonge striplinges, and maydes those little lambes, shead by these rauening and bloudthristie woulfes, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie the same moste aboundantly in our Phariseis, Scribes and high priestes, the successours and children of those their olde Iuish forefathers: of whō, with their saide forefathers as this sentence was spoken, so dooth it moste expressely represent and depainte them moste liuely in their naturall colours, that ye maye well know them by their fruictes. For that they spoile poore wydowes houses, vnder y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> pretence of their longe prayers, their diriges, Masses of <hi>Requiem,</hi> Trentalles &amp;c. is but a trifle with them: but the greatter shalbe their damnation, as our Sauiour saith. Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">
            <hi>Marc.</hi> 12.</note> the schisme which M. Dormā shooteth at chieflie: <note place="margin">
            <hi>Luc.</hi> 20.</note> We answere we haue made none other schisme from you, than did S. Paule make from the saide high prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Act.</hi> 22. <hi>a.</hi> 3.</note> Scribes, and Phariseis your predecessours, from whom (though he were from his childehood brought vp
<pb facs="8"/>
emongst thē) he did wel, &amp; vpon good grounde departe, for that they had before departed, &amp; made a schisme from God, and his most holy lawe, to the traditions of the mother churche of their Pharisaicall fathers: as haue likewise you Papistes departed, &amp; made a schisme from Christe, and his Apostles doctrine, and from the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient churches, founded by the Apostles labour, to your mother the Romishe Sinagoge, and haue by your poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned Popishe traditions, slayne moe soules, than you haue by your crueltie murdred bodies of Christian men and wemen, as we haue prooued, and wyll dayly prooue more and more most euidently vnto the world, vntill all godly in the worlde, knowyng you by your fruictes, dooe forsake you (as did the godly before, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the olde Phariseis, Scribes, and highe Priestes, and folowed Christe and his holy Apostles) as we haue partely already brought to a good forwardnesse.</p>
      <p>Thus you may sée why we haue departed from you, and returned to Christe, and his holy Apostles, and the churches by them founded, from whom you haue departed. Returne you to them, and we will not swarue from you: take away the schisme that you haue made from Christ our sauiour &amp; his holy Apostles, and the churches founded vpon their doctrine, and we wyll ioygne with you. Otherwise, as long as you shall thus swarue from Christe, and his Apostles, and their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, cry you out against schismatikes neuer so much, we will neuer ioygne with you, beinge the very schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes in déede. And thus muche I thought to saye to the sentence of S. Augustine against Petilian, by M. Dorman alleaged, in the fyrst front of his booke, as against vs, but in déede moste directlie detectinge the
<pb facs="9"/>
schismaticall secte of all Papistes our aduersaries, that I might leaue no one sentence of any olde doctour by M. Dorman, though colourably and falsely alleaged, vnanswered.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>