<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the well disposed Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113247_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17539</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113247</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the well disposed Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of Englishe dogges : the diuersities, the names, the natures, and the properties. A short treatise written in latine by Iohannes Caius of late memorie, Doctor of Phisicke in the Vniuersitie of Cambridge; and newly drawne into Englishe by Abraham Fleming student. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Caius, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 44, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the well disposed Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S euery manifest effect</hi> procéedeth frō som certain cause, so the penning of this present a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement (gentle and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reader) issued from a speciall occasion. For <hi>Conradus Gesne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> a man whiles he liued, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable knowledge, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfold experience, being neuer satisfied with the swéete sappe of vnderstanding, requested <hi>Iohannes Caius</hi> a profound clarke and a rauennous deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of learning (to his praise be it spokē though the language be somewhat homely) to write a breuiary or short treatise of such dogges as were ingendred within the borders of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: To the contentation of whose minde and the vtter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishement of whose desire, <hi>Caius</hi> spared no study, (for the acquaintance which was betwéene them, as it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by continuaunce, and established vpon vnfainednes, so was it sealed with vertue and honesty) withdrew himself from no labour, repined at no paines, forsooke no trauaile, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused no indeuour, finally pretermitted no opportunity or circumstaunce which séemed pertinent and requisite to the performance of this litle libell. In the whole discourse wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the booke, to consider the substaunce, being but a pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let or skantling, the argument not so fyne and affected, and yet the doctrine very profitable and necessarye, he vseth such a smoothe and comely style, and tyeth his inuention to such methodicall and orderly procéedings, as the elegantnes and neatnesse of his Latine phrase, (being pure, perfect, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled) maketh the matter which of it selfe is very base and clubbishe, to appeare (shall I say tollerable) nay rather commendable and effectuall. The sundry sortes of Englishe dogges he discouereth so euidently, their natures he rippeth
<pb facs="4"/>
vp so apparantly, their manners he openeth so manifestly, their qualities he declareth so skilfully, their proportions he painteth out so perfectly, their colours he describeth so artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, and knytteth all these in such shortnesse and breuity, that the mouth of th'aduersary must néedes confesse &amp; giue sentence that commendation ought to bée his rewarde, and praise his deserued pension. An ignoraunt man woulde neuer haue bene drawne into this opinion, to thincke that there had bene in England such variety &amp; choise of dogges, in all respectes (not onely for name but also for qualitie) so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse and vnlike: But what cannot learning attaine? what cannot the kay of knowledge open? what cannot the lampe of vnderstanding lighten? what secretes cannot discretion detect? finally what cannot experience comprehend? what buge heapes of histories hath <hi>Gesnerus</hi> hourded vp in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of a large syze? Fishes in floudes, Cattell on lande, Byrdes in the ayre, how hath he sifted them by ther naturall differences? how closely and in how narrow a compasse hath he couched mighty and monstruous beasts, in bygnesse lyke mountaines, the bookes themselues being lesser then Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilles. The lyfe of this man was not so great a restority of comfort, as his death was an vlcer or wound of sorrow: the losse of whom <hi>Caius</hi> lamented, not so much as he was his faithfull friende, as for that he was a famous Philosopher, and yet the former reason (being, in very déede, vehement &amp; forceable) did stinge him with more griefe, then he peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was willing to disclose. And though death be counted terrible for the time, and consequently vnhappy, yet <hi>Caius</hi> aduoucheth the death of <hi>Gesner</hi> most blessed, luckie, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, as in his Booke intituled, <hi>De libris proprijs,</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. But of these two Eagles sufficient is spoken as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, and yet litle enough in consideration of their dignitie and worthines. Neuerthelesse litle or mickle, something or nothing, substaunce or shadow take all in good part, my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is by a fewe wordes to wynne credit to this worke,
<pb facs="5"/>
not so much for mine owne Englishe Translation as for the singuler commendation of them, challenged of dutie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sart. Wherfore gentle Reader I commit them to thy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and their bookes to thy courteous censure. They were both learned men, and painefull practitioners in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions, so much the more therfore are their workes worthy estimation, I would it were in me to aduaunce them as I wishe, the worst (and yet both, no doubt, excellent) hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued a monument of immortality. Well there is no more to be added but this, that as the translatiō of this booke was attempted, finished, and published of goodwill (not onely to minister pleasure, as to affoord profit) so it is my desire and request that my labour therin employed may be acceptable, as I hope it shalbe to men of indifferent iudgement. As for such as shall snarr and snatch at the Englishe abridgement, and teare the Translatour, being absent, with the teeth of spightfull enuye, I conclude in breuity there eloquence is but currishe, if I serue in their meate with wrong sawce, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe it not to vnskilfulnesse in coquery, but to ignoraunce in their diet, for as the Poet sayeth.
<q>
         <l>Non satis est ars sola coquo, seruire palato:</l>
         <l>Nanque coquus domini debet habere gulam:</l>
         <l>It is not enough that a cooke vnderstand,</l>
         <l>Except his Lordes stomack he holde in his hand.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>To winde vp all in a watcheworde I saye no more. But doe well, and Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>His and his Friendes,</hi>
         <hi>Abraham Fleming.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>