<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the reuerende father in god, my Lorde Edmonde Bonor, Bysshope of Lon∣don, Thomas Paynel wissheth all felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113301_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11166</idno>
           <idno type="STC">548.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113301</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the reuerende father in god, my Lorde Edmonde Bonor, Bysshope of Lon∣don, Thomas Paynel wissheth all felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A deuout prayer of s. Ambrose : very expedie [n] t for all suche as prepare them selues to saye masse, or to receaue ye blessed sacrament of the very body and bloud of Christ. Englished by Thomas Paynell. 1.5.5.5</title>
                 <author>Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cawood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the reuerende father in god, my Lorde Edmonde Bonor, Bysshope of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Thomas Paynel wissheth all felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N asmuch as there hathe bene, and yet is (most reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend father) a nūber of leude and vnlearned persones, the which deride and skorne the holy masse, and the blessed sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice there of both god and man: and saye that it is a thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge newely forged, and of late dayes inuented of the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, as they in dirision doo name the true and catholyke seruauntes, of god: I thought
<pb facs="2"/> it very necessary to translate this excellente and deuoute prayer, as a thynge moste ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for those, which dayly doo prepare them selfes (as euery chaste and good preste shoulde doo) to celebrate and offer vppe vnto god thys he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye and blessed sacrifice,<note place="margin">Augusti. ad Laur. Cap. <hi>110.</hi>
      </note> for the quycke and the deade. The whyche prayer, as of it selfe it is verye frutefull, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayninge the hole mystery of the sacrament: so it declareth to suche as hereticallye and peruerslye vnto theyr owne destruccion (as wytnesseth, Saynt Peter) doo racke and wrynge scripture:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> that the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Masse, is no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, no Idoll (as they igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniouslye doo terme it) no
<pb facs="3"/> breade, nor no signification, but Christ hymselfe, hys very fleshe, and very bloude, bothe god and man, whome yf we worshyppe not in the holy sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the aultare,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6.</note> (as a number of wycked personnes refrayne to doo) we shal not es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape (as saith,<note place="margin">De uerbis domini serm. Ioh. Serm. <hi>58.</hi>
      </note> Saynt Austen) the eternall burning fyer and paynes of hell: for as it is no synne at all to adore and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppe Christ being really and presently (as sayeth Saynte Austen) in the sacrament,<note place="margin">Super Psal. <hi>98.</hi>
      </note> so it is a moste detestable synne, not to adore and worshippe Christ in the same. And to preach and affirme the Masse (as they doo moste impudently) to be a newe inuencion of the papistes Saynte Ambrose the whiche
<pb facs="3"/> was twelue. C. yeares ago) in thys hys godly and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prayer, doth playnely and apertly to theyr great rebuke and shame, confute them, and declare the contrarye. Thys prayer thus rudely englishyd I dedicate vnto youre good Lord eshyppe, as to a mooste puisant protector of thys most excellent sacrament of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all body and bloude of Christe the very substaūce and sacrifice of the blessed Masse: wisshynge your Lordeshyppe longe lyfe and continuance, aswel for the tuitiō and defense of the same, as of al other articles &amp; poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the catholike faythe, the whyche in thys oure tyme (moste wycked for the worlde,
<pb facs="4"/> alas for pitie, as yet stuft with many false and hollowe harted bretherne) hath nede of suche stronge and faythfull champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and defenders, as youre Lordeshyppe is, and to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost of your power hath bene to the great honor &amp; glory of God, to whom be all honour and glory for euer and euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>