<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface touching this exer∣cise of Catechising.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113009_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11055</idno>
           <idno type="STC">287.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113009</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface touching this exer∣cise of Catechising.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short, plaine, and profitable catechisme : containing an instruction vnto the foure principal points of Christian religion. Needfull for all those, who doe not as yet perfitly knowe the same</title>
                 <author>Aldem, Mordecai</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bourne, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <distributor>Watkins, Richard</distributor>
                            <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 62, 18 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A preface touching this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of Catechising.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be diuers at this day, which being led with the vanitie of their minds, and hauing their consciences darkned tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ignorance; doe say that this trade of teaching belongeth onely to children: surely then because such are children in vnderstanding, it may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so belong vnto them: for notage but knowledge maketh the difference, which while some haue not, though they be growne men since the time of the Gospell; yet remain they children, hauing neede to be taught in the first principles of the word of God, being become such as haue need of milk, and not strong meate. It were wel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="4"/> for such, euen as new born babes to desire the sincere milk of the word, that they may grow thereby, hauing as yet but onely heard, and not tasted thereof. And therefore being guiltie in themselues, they doe not onely post this kinde of exercise ouer from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to children, but also being loth to haue their ignorance called into question, they like rather to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant still, then with children to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thēselues vnto teaching, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thereby of ignorant they may be made skilfull in the way to Christ. But this kinde of men repute it no disgrace to bee taught, nay they disdaine not to aske the way in their iourny of any whom they thinke able to direct them; being contented to bewray their owne ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in such a sort: and yet in this point it is a maruell to sée howe they faile, for they so stomacke instruction, as they lothe the name and abhorre the thing in themselues, being in their owne conceite both learned and wise
<pb facs="5"/> inough to attaine Christ: but the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle teacheth such sorts another les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:<note place="margin">Cor. 3.18.</note> first, that they deceiue not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; then if any séeme to be wise in this world, let him be a foole, that he may be wise. Also if any man seeme to himselfe to be somewhat,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.3.</note> when he is nothing, he deceiueth himselfe in hys imagination. Selfe loue then, and a conceited opinion so bewitcheth te wits of high minded men, as they are in nothing sooner deceiued then when they affect their own humour, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their owne fancie, being in the meane time so clouded in their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as they sée not the way which leadeth to him, vnto whome they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come without instruction. As then to blunder on in an vnknowne way without a guide, either leading or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing how to go on, and on which hād or turning to take: vttereth great folly: So being called vppon to turne into the way, when they are out, and to keepe on straite, when they are in,
<pb facs="5"/> and yet will not, betokeneth great madnesse. <hi>Salomon</hi> is more plaine with such men then they will thinke him thanke worthy,<note place="margin">Prou. 1.7.</note> who saith that fooles despise wisedome and instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as also,<note place="margin">Prou. 15.13.</note> he that refuseth instruction despiseth his owne soule.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Steuen</hi> the blessed Martir,<note place="margin">Act. 7.51.</note> striketh at such, calling them stifnecked and vncircumcised heartes and eares, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them that they alwaies resisted the holy Ghost as their fathers did: As such sortes of men at this day say: not we haue sinned with our fathers, but sinne that they may die with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Euē so with their great grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers many in this time of the light do shut themselues vp in the prison of wilfull blindnesse, vntill the day of darknesse come vpon them: at what time when they would they shoulde not haue that which once they might haue had and would not. Let the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the fiue foolish virgins ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue that. It is therefore good to be
<pb facs="6"/> in a readinesse because we knowe not when our maister Christ wil come to take an accompt what they haue lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, and how they haue liued: <hi>Nyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> was of a better minde then many of selflyking in these days are: for he though hee were a doctor, and a man well strocken in age, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vtterly ignorant touching his new byrth, did abide Christ his handling him, and our sauiour did beare his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering him, the one not leauing the other: but the one asking and answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the other.<note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> Our sauior taught and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> heard, and tooke foorth such a lesson as hee neuer learned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Iohn 4.</note>The woman also of <hi>Samaria</hi> being ignorant concerning the water of life, by mutuall questioninges and answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes betweene our sauiour and her came to knowledge. The <hi>Eunuch,</hi> the Queene of the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> treasurer being ignorant in the chiefest point of Religion,<note place="margin">Peter 8.10.</note> namely in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="6"/> of Christ, &amp; not vnderstanding that same in the Prophet: he was led as a sheep to the slaughter,<note place="margin">Isay 53.7.</note> &amp;c. thought not skorn in respect of his age and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to take vnto him <hi>Philip,</hi> with whome after hée had read the text, hee began to question of whome it was meant, and hee not ashamed to shewe his ignorance, so reasoned the matter with his teacher, that he became lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the knowledge of Christ. All these as you see couered not their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, but acknowledging the same tooke no skorne being of good yeeres to go to schoole and that with such tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers as they neuer heard afore. These are three such examples as are set downe for all men and women of yeares and ignoraunce to behold, to follow, and do the like: as also with them to be content rather later than neuer: but the sooner the better to loue knowledge, and to seeke after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</p>
   <p>But they will say if wee might be
<pb facs="7"/> taught by Christ or his Apostle, as these were, we would heare, receiue and vnderstand as they did: but I ask thē this question whether they thinke not the ministry of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> word in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall absence of Christ &amp; his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Apostle needfull: Now surely I thinke there is none so past grace, but that hee will say it is needefull: then being needfull, I aske by whome? It wil be answered, by the preachers of the worde. Then I pray marke this, namely, that the elders which rule well are worthie double honor,<note place="margin">Tim. 15.17.</note> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially such as labour in the worde and doctrine: And further to stirre vp <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> seriously to see to his ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and diligently to looke to hys charge, he saith, I charge thee in the sight of God, and before the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, which shal iudge the quick and the dead, at his comming, and in his kingdome, preach the word, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant in season and out of season, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1.2</note> relent, exhort with all long
<pb facs="7"/> suffering and doctrine: in which two places, wée see that the minister must be a labouring man, not in the world, but in the word, as also that hee must be instant at all times? what to doe? euen of ignoraunt, to make skilfull, of simple, to make learned: of children, to make men of vnderstanding: And so to bring from blindnesse, to the light: from error, to the trueth: from infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, to beliefe: from the loue of the worlde, to the obedience of God and his sonne Iesus Christ, that they may be saued. Now then hauing such a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister as is able and willing to teache and to traine vp the people of God, I nothing doubt but that he is sent of the Lord: and set in his place to vse all maner meanes for instruction, whom if ye will not heare as readily as <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus,</hi> and the woman heard Christ: and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> heard <hi>Philip,</hi> ye contemne him, and if ye will not be chastised as willingly by him, as those aboue named were by Christ
<pb facs="8"/> and <hi>Phillip:</hi> you scorne instruction, hate to be refourmed, and despise your teacher: yea, ye scorne, hate, and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pise Christ himselfe: who hath sayde speaking to his threescore and ten dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples on this wise, he that heareth you heareth me,<note place="margin">Luke. 10.16.</note> and he that despiseth you despiseth me, and he that despiseth me despiseth him that sent mee. Let all despisers therefore cease to despise their teacher, because such a despite reacheth vnto Christe, yea and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Almightie himselfe, whoe hath said,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30</note> that they which despise me, shall be despised. And no maruel, for they be none of Gods, for he that is of God heareth Gods worde:<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.47.</note> but they heare it not, therefore are they not of God.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> Againe no hearing, no faith: for faith commeth by hearing, and no faith,<note place="margin">Galat 3.26.</note> no child of God, for by faith are all the sons of God: then no hearing; no faith: no faith, no son of God; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no hearing no heires annexed with Christ and no child of God: No
<pb n="1" facs="8"/> kingdome of God belongeth not to them but children. Thus prayeng God to open the eares, eies, &amp; hartes of all vnbeléeuing Christians, that they may heare, sée, and vnderstande by the mynisterie of the word (in this sort) what belongeth vnto a Christian life, and that they being sette in the right waie by instruction, as also care fully guided by the continuall directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the preaching minister, they may in the end enter into the great Cittie that heauenly Ierusalem, by him that is the only doore thereof the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. To whom with the Father and the holie Ghost, one immortall God, be eternall praise and Dominion for euermore, So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>