<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           <author>N., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113100_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08017</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18382</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113100</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>N., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Quaternio or A fourefold vvay to a happie life : set forth in a dialogue betweene a countryman and a citizen, a divine and a lawyer. Per Tho: Nash philopolitem</title>
                 <author>Nash, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 280 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He punishment of our first Father is heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to his posteritie, he drew trouble and travell, cares and feares vpon himselfe, and wee grone vnder the burthen of them. No man now is admitted into the world, but vpon this Condition, that in the <note n="(a)" place="margin">
         <q>
            <l>In sudore vultus victum acquires.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</bibl>
         </q>
         <q>
            <l>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> shalt thou send into thy <hi>braunchie</hi> veynes,</l>
            <l>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t but bought with price of thousand pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Bartas.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </q>
      </note>
      <hi>sweat of his browes</hi> he shall purchase his liuelihood. Man is borne to <note n="(b)" place="margin">Iob <hi>5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>labour,</hi> as the sparkes flie vpwards. Wee must not thinke to goe to the <hi>Indies,</hi> and enjoy the fruits thereof, but we must passe through the troublesome Seas. Vertue is seated aloft, and the way vnto it is by labour and industrie.
<q>
         <l>
            <note n="(c)" place="margin">Hesiodus.</note> Virtutem posuere dij sudore parandam.</l>
      </q>
It is <hi>action</hi> which giveth a well-being to every living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the little Common-wealth so long flourisheth, as every member in that little body strives to bring hony to the hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e: but when the drones begin to swarme and abound, then it goes to ruine and decay. The <hi>Athenian</hi> Common-wealth so long prospered as the people were in <hi>action and imployment,</hi> but when they brought the delights of the Court of <hi>Darius,</hi> and the gold of <note n="(d)" place="margin">
         <p>
            <q>
               <p>Aurum <hi>Persicum</hi> animos <hi>Atheniensium</hi> labefactavit, &amp; dirâ peste infecit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Alexand: Neap. lib.</hi> 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <hi>Nasica, extinctis</hi> Carthagin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibus <hi>rempub: Romanam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jore in discrimine adversus</hi> Catonem <hi>fore contendit.</hi>
         </p>
      </note>
      <hi>Persia</hi> home vnto them, then they began to giue themselues over to wantonnesse, ease, and delicacie, and to decline their former prosperitie. So long as the <hi>Assy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Common-wealth set forth her selfe, so long she flourished,
<pb facs="9"/>
but when <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> whom <hi>Bocchas</hi> will haue to be the first that induced idlenes into the world, began to invert the course of nature, to turne the dayes into nights, and the nights into dayes, and to giue himselfe over wholly to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie, then the Common-wealth began to decay. It is <hi>indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie</hi> that hath raised the most famous flourishing Common-wealths out of the dust; and idlenes which hath levelled them with the dust. Of this our forefathers were sensible, when they first instituted mechanicall Trades &amp; Occupations, and found out the knowledge of the liberall Arts and Sciences; which had their institution to this end, to set vs in the way which our Creator had appointed vs to walke in, that is, by the way of <hi>labour and travaile</hi> to get our livings, to the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we may live according to our first institution, and banish <hi>idlenes</hi> from our habitations, which like the stupify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note n="(e)" place="margin">
         <q>
            <l>Otium vivi hominis sepultura.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Sen: epist.</hi> 820.</bibl>
         </q>
      </note>
      <hi>Oppium buryes vs alive</hi> in the spring and flourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time of our age. I haue invited you here to the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> to the <hi>Citie,</hi> to <hi>Divinitie,</hi> and the <hi>Law.</hi> And haue first presented vnto you a <hi>Countryman,</hi> shewing vnto you the pleasures and profit of the Country, and the motives that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him to take vpon him that course of life. Then a <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen,</hi> shewing you the Commodities and delights of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the motives that induced him to take vpon him that course of life. Then a <hi>Divine,</hi> shewing you the vanitie of the world, and the motives that induced him to the profession of Divinitie. Then a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> shewing you the excellencie of the Law, and the motives which induced him thereunto.</p>
   <p>Briefly, I haue shewed you a <hi>fourefold way</hi> to a happie life; <note n="(f)" place="margin">Sedentaris <hi>vita ignobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, nam torporē segnitiém{que} corporibus, aequè ac animis conciliat.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>sit no longer still</hi> then, gazing and looking about, but rise vp and walke, try and tread those pathes throughout, and let not the pleasures of the Countrie, nor the profit of the Citie, nor the vanitie of the world, nor any thing hinder thee vntill thou commest to thy journeys end, then pawse a while, and consider of the wayes which thou hast past, and that which thou most affectest, in aftertimes apply thy selfe vnto; in any Case sit not still.
<q>
         <pb facs="9"/>
         <lg>
            <l>Cernis vt ignavum corrumpant otia corpus;<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ovid. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Pont.</hi>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>Vt capiant vitium, ni moveantur, aquae.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>The standing water stinkes with putrefaction,</l>
            <l>And vertue hath no vertue but in action.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
Farewell. Yet stay a while, remember least thou chaunce to goe out of the way, that when thou commest to that rockie, thornie, craggie way which thou must passe, not to turne to thy right hand or to thy left, but to goe straight forward to a pillar which thou shalt see before thee; whereon thou shalt finde his inscription.
<q>
         <l>Dulcia non meruit, qui non gustavit amara.</l>
      </q>
It is a pillar which <hi>Hercules</hi> set vp to direct passengers the way to vertue, and is knowne by his name; and it is the way which <hi>Caesar, Pompey,</hi> and all the noble <hi>Romanes</hi> went. It is the way which <hi>Littleton, Iustinian,</hi> and all the famous <hi>Iusticiaries</hi> went; and it is the way which will leade thee to the end of thy journey, a happie life. Farewell once againe, commend me to our friends and familiars, the Disciples and followers of <note n="(h)" place="margin">
         <hi>Cujus</hi> decus, <hi>nec</hi> vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rina <hi>multorū</hi> ingratitudo, <hi>nec</hi> occulta <hi>malevolorum</hi> infidiae, <hi>nec</hi> apertae <hi>adversariorum</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniae <hi>obscurare possint.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Littleton</hi> and <hi>Iustinian,</hi> but more especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Disciples of <hi>Littleton.</hi> Commend me, I pray you, vnto them, and affoord me that ordinary favour which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be denyed to an enemie, thy loue and good will for my labour and paines, who haue to my losse and detriment gone somewhat out of my way, to no other end and purpose, but to put thee in thy way. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. N.</signed>
      <dateline>From the <hi>Inner Temple</hi>
         <date>the
14. of <hi>May</hi> 1632.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Lege, Relege, Perlege.</l>
         <l>Omnia tentato, quod bonum est teneto.</l>
         <l>Ne minima averseris, in est sua gratia parvis.</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>