<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL THE GOOD-Fellowes in generall, and parti∣cular, that do keep, inhabit, allow, or maintaine the Wine Tavernes, or Inne Tavernes in the ten Shires and Counties before named</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113524_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23764a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113524</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL THE GOOD-Fellowes in generall, and parti∣cular, that do keep, inhabit, allow, or maintaine the Wine Tavernes, or Inne Tavernes in the ten Shires and Counties before named</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The honorable, and memorable foundations, erections, raisings, and ruines, of divers cities, townes, castles, and other pieces of antiquitie, within ten shires and counties of this kingdome : namely, Kent, Sussex, Hampshire, Surrey, Barkshire, Essex, Middlesex, Hartfordshire, Buckinghamshire, and Oxfordshire: with the description of many famous accidents that have happened, in divers places in the said counties. Also, a relation of the wine tavernes either by their signes, or names of the persons that allow, or keepe them, in, and throughout the said severall shires. By John Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL THE GOOD-Fellowes in generall, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that do keep, inhabit, allow, or maintaine the Wine Tavernes, or Inne Tavernes in the ten Shires and Counties before named</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MINE HOSTS,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope I am not much mistaken in calling you Gentlemen, or kind Friends; if you be either, it is as much as I looke for, or can deserve; you onely are the men that do truly merit the name and title of <hi>Mine Hosts,</hi> for alas, our Citie Tavernes have no other entertainment, but <hi>Welcome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, a Crust,</hi> and <hi>What Wine will you drinke?</hi> But you, Brave minded, and most <hi>Ioviall Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danapalitans,</hi> have power &amp; prerogative <hi>(Cum Privilegio)</hi> to receive, lodge, feast, and fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> both man and beast; you have the happiness
<pb facs="3"/>
to Boile, Roast, Broile and Bake Fish, Flesh, and Foole, whilst wee in <hi>London</hi> have scarse the command of a <hi>Gull,</hi> a <hi>Widgeon,</hi> or a <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ock;</hi> and for your further, and more high Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, the most part of your Customers come riding to your houses, where almost all our guests are footmen; with you it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for the Master to drinke pintes or quarts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ut of Pots, whilst his horse is eating of Bottles. Besides, our Citie Tavernes are not troublesome to their Clients with many vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Items,</hi> and Reckonings; but briefly, so much for Sack, Clarret, or White; whilst you have the predominance to assault a man with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Bill, and call him to a strait and strict <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ccount, not onely for himselfe, but for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>oings of his horse; the Iury is divided or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ven into five parts, in the manner of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>y Woolsey; namely, the <hi>Hostes,</hi> the <hi>Drawer,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> the <hi>Tapster,</hi> and the <hi>Hostler.</hi> Who having view'd the Bill of Inditement, They) being themselves, Accusers, Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Plaintiffe, Iury, and Iudges; the finall Sentence is pronounced at their owne <hi>Bar</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ustice, where the Delinquents conscience
<pb facs="3"/>
knowing all to bee justly laid to his charge, with patience and Fortitude, suffers the irrevokeable doome to passe upon him, paies the Reckoning, puts the Bill out of all Force and Vertue, paying his Fees, hee is discharged with a <hi>Heartily Welcome.</hi> Of all, or the most part of such Accounts, Actions, Debts, or Demands, our Citie Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes have a long time pleaded not Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ee tax'd with the deadly Sin of Gluttony, nor are they troubled with the harsh musick of Trencher-Scraping, so that if I were to be transform'd, or metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos'd into a Hogg, I would bee loath to dwell in one of our Tavernes, because I should have such plenty of Wash, and such scarcity of Graines.</p>
   <p>But Gentlemen, though I am bold (a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) to play the (—) with you, yet I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you, I love you well; but for some more speciall love and favour that I beare to my selfe. I have written this my second Booke of Tavernes, I have not written Epigrams here, as I did upon the former, because in
<pb facs="4"/>
City and Country the signes and the Wines are all alike.</p>
   <p>Yet (to give all the respectfull content that I can to my Honorable, Worshipfull, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rs of my good Friends, that are to pay me money, upon the receiving, or this my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>shing this small Booke.) I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in stead of Epigrams, some Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ents of Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>quity, which my hope is, will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ee more profitable and delightfull; And Gentlemen (I meane you that are ingaged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nto mee) in your just payment to mee, you may wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ke a piece of a wonder, (which is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o make a Rich Poet;) but alas! that stile is as much too high for mee, as I am too low for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>(That's a Bull)</hi> so much the better; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most all men are turn'd Grasiers, and speake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ls familiarly, and those are the Mounsier <hi>Vomusses,</hi> who have sold their Wise Akers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>efore they have sowed their Wilde Oates; And these will censure harshly, any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>hey understand hardly, whose knowledge is as much in the validitie and measure of a Verse, as the Asse had that judg'd the Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koo's
<pb facs="4"/>
song to bee sweeter than the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales.</p>
   <p>I have laid the Foundation of this Project my selfe, it is a Vineyard of mine own Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the Grapes of mine owne Pressing, the Wine of mine owne Vintage (or Vantage) the Tavernes of mine owne finding, and the Vintoners my own friends, in lieu of which, I am not mine own man, but theirs, or yours, or his, or hers, that wis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eth mee well, as far as my Intentions and Actions are Iust, Lawfull, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Laudable,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>