<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
honourable, Edward, Lord
Russell, Earl of Bedford,
grace and peace be
multiplied.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113660_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113660</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
honourable, Edward, Lord
Russell, Earl of Bedford,
grace and peace be
multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the Lords praier : in the way of catechisme By William Perkins</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 130+ pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
honourable, Edward, Lord
Russell, Earl of Bedford,
grace and peace be
multiplied.</head>
   <p>RIGHT honourable, if you consider
what is one of the cheife ornaments
of this noble state, vnto which God
hath aduanced you: It will appeare, that
there is none more excellent, then the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of grace and praier. For what doth your
heart affect? would you speake the langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges?
Behold, by praier you may speake the
most heauenly toung that euer was, euen
the language of Canaan. Would you haue
the valor of knighthood? By praier you may
stand in the place where Gods hand hath
made a breach, and do as much as all the
Chariots &amp; horsmen in a kingdome. Would
you enjoy Gods blessings which you want?
By praier, you may (as it were) put your hād
into the cofers of Gods treasures, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche
your selfe. Do you desire the fauour of
Monarks and Princes? By praier you may
come in presence, and haue speeche with
<hi>Iehoua</hi> the King of heauen and earth▪ Lastly,
<pb facs="3"/>
would you knowe, whether now liuing, you
be dead, that being dead you may liue for
euer? By praier a man may knowe, whether
he be dead to sinne, dead to the world, liue
to God, liue to Christ, and liue eternally.</p>
   <p>Praier then, being so excellent a point of
Religion: I am imboldened to commend
this small treatise your honour: not so
much for itselfe, as because it doth set out
the matter and true maner of inuocation
of Gods holy name. And I hope for your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
in accepting of it: the rather, because
I doubt not but your desire is to be answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
to your most honourable, and for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
most worthie ancestors, in the care of
maintaining and countenancing any good
thing, that may any whit serue for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
of the gospell of Christ.</p>
   <p>Now Iesus Christ our Lorde, and God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
the Father which hath loued vs and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
vs euerlasting consolation, and good
hope through grace, stablish your Honor in
euerie good word and worke to the end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your H. to command
William Perkins.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>