<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>G. G. To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113621_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08545</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18863</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>G. G. To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the first booke of the Myrrour of knighthood : in which is prosecuted the illustrious deedes of the knight of the Sunne, and his brother Rosicleer, sonnes vnto the Emperour Trebatio of Greece: with the valiant deedes of armes of sundry worthie knights, very delightfull to bee read, and nothing hurtfull to bee regarded. Now newly translated out of Spanish into our vulgar tongue by R.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 258, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>G. G. To the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF learned <hi>Maro</hi> merited such prayse, for penning downe <hi>Aeneas</hi> trauayles strange:</l>
      <l>Or if to heauen they <hi>Nasoes</hi> name doe rayse, that writ of men and beasts trans form'd by change:</l>
      <l>Then shall our Spaniards toile I trust obtaine, Though no such praise, yet pardon for his paine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For as their pens did paint the rare euents, of things succeeding, fitting for their time:</l>
      <l>Euen so doth hee declare in his contents, the verie meanes to Honours top to clime.</l>
      <l>Accept his will, doe not disdaine his worke, In simplest shew doth truest meaning lurke.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>