<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CONSIDERATION OF THE HONORABLE, WISE, AND LEARNED.</title>
           <author>Norden, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113229_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08306</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18635</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CONSIDERATION OF THE HONORABLE, WISE, AND LEARNED.</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Speculum Britanniae. The first parte an historicall, &amp; chorographicall discription of Middlesex. Wherein are also alphabeticallie sett downe, the names of the cyties, townes, parishes hamletes, howses of name &amp;c. W.th direction spedelie to finde anie place desired in the mappe &amp; the distance betwene place and place without compasses. Cum priuilegio. By the trauaile and vew of Iohn Norden. Anno 1593</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48, 4 pages, 3 folded plates, maps, coats of arms (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CONSIDERATION OF THE HONORABLE, WISE, AND LEARNED.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I cannot but confesse that I am the vnwoorthiest of manie in this lande, (and especiallie in these daies of surpassing knowledge) to vndertake (after other farre more deseruing) so commendable a labor: which requireth arte, industrie, learning, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and charge, wherewith I am not so fullie fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished as some other. Yet it may please you (in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour) to accept of my willingnes, and beare with my wants: And the rather for that it hath beene helde heeretofore an excuse (in curtesie) <hi>Velle bene,</hi> though in this age (more ripe in experience) is expected, <hi>Optimè perficere:</hi> which neither, altogither escapeth without emulation: I, as ouercome with a desire to take pains to profite my Countrey, rest vndoubtfull, that the wise, and learned, will not onely tollerate, but in fauour accept this simple beginning.</p>
   <p>The fruits of my trauell tend not alone to my selfe in priuate, but to the publike ease of many. In lieu whereof, my hope and desire is, that he that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue, will friendly reforme what he findeth iustly faultie. So shall my proceedings grow to more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and I by all endeuour will seeke to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish what may answere discret affections.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Nihil vbique placet.</hi> IO. NORDEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>