<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRAEFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113155_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08112</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113155</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRAEFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver to the Ievvish part of Mr Selden's History of tithes. By Stephen Nettles, B. of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Nettles, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 189, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PRAEFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas diuers Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises haue bin publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed heeretofore in way of answer to the Booke intituled <hi>The History of Tithes;</hi> it may be, after this long silence, it will now seeme strange, and be thought a worke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnseasonable and superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, either to write or speake any more of that subiect. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding because the Historian himselfe and many others, led rather with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, then judgement, doe still much magnifie among the rest, the
<pb facs="5"/>
Iewish part of that History, (as though some hidden matters of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance were involued therein) I hope it shall not be offensiue to any, (sith this passage as yet hath not bin scanned) if I as another witnes in the same cause, endeauour only to bring in some evidence not yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that may helpe to vnfold &amp; cleare sundrie doubts and questions in this kind. For albeit the Author of the History in the Praeface there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, offring it to the triall of the most censorious examination, with a challenge against all opponents in his poëticall phrase;
<q>Si falsa est, accingere contra, &amp;c.</q>
doth thereby insinuate that he hath written nothing but infallible truth: And though also the authoritie of
<pb facs="5"/>
the Iewish Writers against the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right of the Church in Tithes, be alleaged with much confidence and ostentation, and receiued also with great applause, and more then ordinary approbation: yet let praeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and partiality with other sini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster respects be laid aside, and I make no doubt but there will appeare as much defect and errour, euen in this part of the History, as in any other whatsoeuer; and that the writings of the Iewes, though we depend not on them (because in many things they are vaine and fabulous) yet take them as they are, being tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related, will afford more grounds of proofe for the diuine right of Tithes, then either hath as yet from them, or can bee shewed against it.
<pb facs="6"/>
I did wish &amp; expect that a more able workeman would haue vndertaken this taske; and therefore these papers of mine, which long since haue bin viewed and censured, were neither at the first intended, nor after haste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Presse. But seeing in all this time I heare of no other dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of this nature, either perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or promised, I haue at length yeelded to the desire and perswasion of such as might command me to publish this; the rather, because not long after the first appearing of the History, I did in a publike Sermon take exception against diuerse parts thereof, which being distastefull to some hearers, I thought it did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne me for better satisfaction, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the Eye as to the Eare, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie
<pb facs="6"/>
with my pen, what I avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Pulpit; and the same, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other obseruations, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to open view: the intendment whereof ayming at nothing else but manifestation and confirmation of truth, I am not carefull, neither doe I thinke it needfull, for this attempt to make any long apology. Hauing therefore thus much praemised in way of Praeface, I now passe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vnto our purpose.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>