<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Publisher to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Paget, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113906_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08812</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19099</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Publisher to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Paget, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations of death : wherein a Christian is taught how to remember and prepare for his latter end: by the late able &amp; faithfull minister of the Gospel, Iohn Paget</title>
                 <author>Paget, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Esch  (Ash), Hendrik van</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 432 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Publisher to the Reader.</head>
   <p>I Shall doe no more, Christian Reader, then is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually exspected, if in the entrance unto the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Meditations I give some briefe advertisement touching the Author, &amp; the setting forth of this his Treatise which is here offered unto thee. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Author, it may be expedient for thee to know somewhat of his life who teacheth thee to consider thine owne end. Doubtles he had learned to live well, and his good course of life may be also exemplary for studious imitation, that could so well teach the art of dying. To say nothing of his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger but towardly dayes, giving great content and comfort to his pious parents &amp; friends; to say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing neither of his extraordinary piety &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse in good learning, not onely in the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar-schooles, but also in the Vniversity of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, where he was esteemed for the most part to surpasse his contemporanies: that which I will onely touch upon, shalbe how he approoved himselfe while he was imployed in the Lords Vineyard, into which he was timely sent. After some few yeares spent in places of lesse note, yet so as the learne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest &amp; godliest Preachers thereabout tooke notice of him &amp; embraced him with much love &amp; true af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, he was called to the ministery of the Church of Christ at Namptwich a famous towne in Cheshire, about the yeare 1598. The extraordinary dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence &amp; paines he tooke there, both in publick &amp; private, with persons of all sorts, and the blessed successe, hath bene already witnessed by the lively Epistles of Christ ministred by him, and shall more evidently appeare as a crowne of rejoycing unto him in the presence of our Lord Iesus Christ at his comming. But when the times would not beare his continuance in that place where his labours were so profitable, where he was then so beloved, &amp; since that time so earnestly desired againe and longed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he followed the hand of Gods providence gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="4"/>
him into the Netherlands, in the yeare 1605 The two first yeares he attended the Armie, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string the word of grace unto the Regiments of our nation: and tooke such paines in catechising the souldiers as well as preaching unto them, that their benefit and his comfort therein became greater then is ordinarily found in such places. Then the English living at Amsterdam conformably unto the Dutch Reformed Church in the same city, whereof divers of them stood members, requesting him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to order to performe the office of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stour unto them, he hearkened unto that call of God, and was his chief instrument for the constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; setling of that Church, wherein he did the worke of a faithfull shepheard above thirty yeares, untill age &amp; the infirmities thereof growing upon him the Magistrates of that city vouchsafed him the honour of an Emeritus, the favour that is wont to be given unto souldiers from their Prince in whose service they have spent the strength of their dayes. But shortly after, the Lord of the harvest that had made him his labourer in that Vineyard &amp; crowned him with speciall blessings upon his endeavours in the course of his pastorall performances, having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared him by the message of a lingring and langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing distemper, sometimes intermixed with grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous fits of the colick &amp; gravell, and ever accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with rheumes and catarrhes unto which he had bene long subject, did by the fiery chariot of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tertiā transport him unto the place of rest, where he enjoyes the crowne of righteousnes, layd up for them that have fought a good fight, finished their course &amp; kept the faith. Among other graces and vertuous courses adorning the hearts &amp; lives of Christians, these two did most eminently shine in this faithfull servant of Christ; the one respecting his converse with God, the other his communion with the Saints. The first was his exceeding delight in the Law of the Lord, apparent not onely in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb facs="4"/>
practise of those dueties whereby the same is usually manifested; but more especially, first by his committing unto memory divers select portions of H. Scripture, as most of the Psalmes &amp; sundry of the Epistles, in the original languages; wherein he tooke such pleasing paines, that sometimes in the night season also when he had any spare time from his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall rest he would imploy it this way: secondly by his practise of that course which he doth more thē once commend in the ensuing Treatise, in singling out sundry of the choycest passages in the word of God, reducing them to their severall heads, having them ever about him &amp; most constantly feeding upō the comforts thereof. The second sort of Christian dueties wherein he excelled, was that which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the summe of the second Table his love &amp; charity unto the fellow-members of Christ. The lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes of his dispensing to others in this kinde, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to his estate, will not easily be matched. I spare to mention the particulars, whereof the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his abode and the bowels of the poore Saints by him refreshed (he withall drawing out his heart unto them as lovingly as men are wont to doe unto their familiars) are lively witnesses. His ordinary discourse, seasoned with grace, alwayes profitable &amp; pleasing, in special manner did affect the hearers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting much upon these two themes; first the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull wisedome, power &amp; goodnes of God shining in his creatures, even the least of them, &amp; the many profitable lessons which may be learned from them, whereabout he had many singular observations: and secondly the blessed condition of the Saints glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, touching which he had many divine and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly speculations; &amp; towards his end spake so effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually of these things &amp; what appertaines thereunto, that to them that were with him he seemed to be in heaven already, insomuch as they wished themselves in the same way wherein he was carried on so cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. His sufficiency &amp; abilities for the worke of
<pb facs="5"/>
the ministery, wherein he laboured above fourty yeares; how mighty he was in the Scriptures, how skilfully profound in expounding difficult places, &amp; applying them to the benefit of soules; with what evidence and power his preaching wrought into the consciences of his hearers; how cleerly and fully he could refute &amp; convince an adversary of the trueth; how prudent and judicious he was in mannaging Church affaires, &amp; giving counsel &amp; advise in weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty businesses; these &amp; the like pearles shining in that crowne of pastorall endowments wherewith he was qualifyed above many others, are abundantly testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by those that have bene most interessed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, doe in great measure appeare in what is here and elswhere published, &amp; may be in like manner further manifested as occasion serves, &amp; if need were could be confirmed by the testimonies of the learnedest of our age. For other maine helpes whereby men are fitted for the ministery, his skill was rare in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages that conduce unto the understanding of the Originall text of the Scriptures &amp; the severall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters thereof. Besides what is ordinarily required in this kinde, he could to good purpose &amp; with much ease make use of the Chaldean, Syriack, Rabbinicall, Thalmudicall, Arabick &amp; Persian versions &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries. Now whereas the station which God had appointed unto him was for the chiefe &amp; latter part of his time at Amsterdam; yet (as the godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned have professed) none hath more soundly oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that insolent sect for which that place hath bene so much reproached by many in our native country. Witnesse his Arrow against the Separation of the Brownists, which yet stickes in the sides &amp; heart of their cause, though some impenitēt of their Schisme, gnaw their tongues and cease not to blaspheme the Churches of Christ. If he had bene as forward to send forth what he had done in those controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, as they are to trouble the presse with their pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets; the world had seen at least thrice so much as
<pb facs="5"/>
it hath already of his paines in this kinde. As for the unhappy differences raysed of later yeares in &amp; about the Church committed to his charge, what ever some have deemed, they that have bene rightly informed and impartially weighed what hath bene done, have approoved his wisedome, faithfulnes &amp; uprightnes in the whole carriage of those businesses. We that have in great part bene privy to his retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest thoughts &amp; demeanour at those times, have had assured evidence of the integrity of his heart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which he hath also witnessed unto the end. For the controversies themselves, God hath therein, greatly pleaded his cause sundry wayes, both at the very time of their rising &amp; since especially. And as opportunity shall require, others may in due time behold what he hath done in defence of himselfe &amp; the trueth against that which is published by others.</p>
   <p>But of those and the like his paines in their sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: now somewhat must be sayd of this Treatise which is here put into thy hands. It containes the summe of that which was delivered in divers sermōs to his owne flock in the yeare 1628. At the same time it was penned in such manner as we found it after his decease. Divers passages, especially towards the end, were reserved for second thoughts, when he might returne to a further survey. Though he had bene often importuned by others to publish these his Meditations; yet partly by his owne slownes to come abroad in that manner &amp; partly by the urgency of other occasions their desires could not then take place. But being moved againe when his end drew neere &amp; his weaknes would not suffer him to review it and perfect what was wanting, he was content I should set it forth in such manner as I could. Albeit I have had some trouble in bringing together what was scatteredly set downe, &amp; in some places exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into plaine words what was left in concise notes and short intimations; yet I have purposely avoyded the adding of any thing that was not in the Authors
<pb facs="6"/>
Manuscripts, though I should leave some abruptnes in the discourse and harshnes in the phrase. I have onely adventured to set downe the contents at the beginning of every Chapter, so as thou mayest with ease possesse thy minde with the whole matter of it, &amp; readily turne unto what thou desirest. I need not here discourse of the excellency &amp; usefulnes of this Treatise. When thou hast read it attentively &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, then judge whether the matter inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded be not carried along with all soundnes of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and demonstration of the spirit of life &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; whether here be not pithily comprised the summe of what the Scriptures afford of life &amp; death; whether most poynts of Christian Religion be not here illustrated with some singular observations; and in a word, whether the whole doe not argue that he was a Scribe excellently instructed unto the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. The God of all grace &amp; glory make thee wise in closing thy thoughts with these Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; happy in the enjoyment of that blessed end unto which they give directions.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> R. PAGET.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>