<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113385_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18741</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113385</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reproufe, written by Alexander Nowell : of a booke entituled, A proufe of certayne articles in religion denied by M. Iuell, set furth by Thomas Dorman, Bachiler of Diuinitie: and imprinted at Antvverpe by Iohn Latius. Anno. 1564. Set foorth and allowed, according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Nowell, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 125, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THOVGH many simple soules may muche meruell at suche plentie of Englishe bookes, as are of late so so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deinly sente vs from beyonde the seas, by our countrey men there, and bothe the authors themselues doo muche bragge <note place="margin">M. <hi>Rastell in his prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face: to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue the memorie of the chalēge &amp;c. and to moue an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation vvhich part shall firste shovv her weakenes. &amp;c.</hi>
      </note> therein, and their fautors doo magnifie the same exceedingly: yet the learned and discrete Readers, accustomed rather to vveigh and iudge, then to counte and numbre, vvill easely consider that it is no harde mater for our aduersaries, aboūding vvith leasure, <note n="*" place="margin">And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he saith: speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vvhere the nūbreis great. &amp;c.</note> and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, by common conference of many to patche vp a sorte of suche bookes in Englishe, vvherein there is nothing to any purpose vvritten, but that vvhiche vvas longe before vvritten in sundry latine bookes, and readie to their handes, to translate thereout into their Englishe bookes, as they thought meete for their purpose: so that they be but seely translators, or borovvers of those bookes, vvhose first authors they vvoulde appeare to be. In the vvhiche poincte yet M. Stapleton translating Staphilus his longe Latin booke, so longe before vvritten, vvorde for vvoorde into Englishe, and not dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the matter, hath dealt therin more simplie, thē the rest of his felovves haue doone. By vvhose example, the meanest men in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge and vvitte amongst them all (haue they onely a litle vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>nding in the Latin tongue) may lode vs vvith hauocke of bookes vvhen they list. For it is vvell kuovven to all that be learned, that nothing of vveight, or to any purpose, can novv nevvly be vvritten for the mainteinance of the Popes vsurped supremacy, or any other their matters, vvhiche they novv treate of, but suche as hath been alreadie both vvritten, and printed many yeres agoe, in bookes as vvell of the Latin tongue, as other languages, and the same to be fully ansvvered vnto also, to the satisfiynge of the Readers, and daily vvinning of greate numbres of men and vvemen of all sortes and degrees, from their popishe superstition, vnto the truth of the Gospell: such bookes as vvell of the one sorte, as of th'other, beinge rise in the handes of such as vnderstande, to such decay of their saide superstition, and successe of the truthe, as to the vvorlde at this day cannot be vnknovven. VVherefore our aduersaries mistrustinge that such kinde of vvriting, or rather translating, should not appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are vvoorthie to be accōpted the earnest dooing of any learned, or
<pb facs="3"/>
vvise man: haue doone vvittely, ether to pretende that to be vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">D. <hi>Hard. saith he did prepare his booke but for one friend, and</hi> M. <hi>Rastell, his booke, for one friende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces to the Reader.</hi>
      </note> but lightly for a priuate friende or tvvaine, and not mente to be printed, but by persvvasion of friendes, against their ovvne pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose suffered to come abroade (vvhiche yet they in deede haue of longe, by common conference elaborated at conuenient oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be put in printe to the publike patrocinie of their decaied, and almost desperate cause) or els to appoincte suche, to beare the name as the authors of their bookes, as may seeme moste meete therefore, beinge accompted of all that knovv them, for learninge and discretion, the simplest men amongst them. The same di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust of their ovvne dooinges, (or rather other mens dooinges set foorth for their ovvne) may seeme a cause vvhy they directe their vvritinges either onely, or chiefely against the Bishoppe of Saris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie: thinkinge that though they shall absolutely of the matters they take in hande be hable to say nothinge, but that is alreadie saide, and is likevvise, or easely may be ansvvered: yet may they seeme abundantly to say to him, vvho chalengeth them that they can say nothinge at all: and vvho also doth not tie them streightly to the triall of the scriptures, the certaine and onely iudges in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies of Religiō, and vvherin in deede they can say nothing at all (as shall hereafter be plainly proued) but geueth them a moste large scope of all Doctours of the Churche, vvho haue vvritten for the space of sixe hundreth yeres after our Sauiour Christes beinge here in earth, and of all Councelles kept in the saide continuance of <note place="margin">D. <hi>Harding in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the</hi> B. <hi>of Sarum fol.</hi> 1. <hi>a. &amp;</hi> 2. <hi>b. and</hi> M. <hi>Rastell fol.</hi> 1. <hi>b.</hi>
      </note> time. Out of the vvhiche Doctors and Councelles for that the said Bishop hath aduouched that the best learned of all the aduersaries, or all the aduersaries togeather, are hable to bring nothing to any purpose for them, he hath set all the aduersaries learned, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned a vvoorke, by cōmon conference to deuise to say somthing for themselues, and against him, vvho affirmeth they can say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all. And yet fearing least that somthinge, vvhiche they all are hable to say▪ vvill fall out at the lengthe to proue nothinge to purpose: they haue all, like vvise men, agreed, that some fevv shall take vpon them to be the onely authors of that something vvhich they all can say: least if that somethinge, as it is deuised by them all, so it should passe abroade in all their names, and in time proue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, all their estimation vvere lost at once. And for more cautell, suche some also to be named for the saide authors, as haue not all learninge, vvit, nor discretion, but men of a diuers profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
<pb facs="3"/>
vvho haue yet some fight in Diuinitie, as studientes of the same, for so they professe them selues. VVherin they seeme to me to deale vvith vs, as did the Phariseis vvith Christe, vvho vvould not <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 22. <hi>b.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> come them selues to dispute vvith him, but sent their Disciples, (vvell instructed, and furnished vvith all, that themselues coulde possibly say) to oppose him, to th'ende, that if their Disciples should obtaine the victorie, the glory of their maisters, vvho had suche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent scholers, might mount aboue the Moone. But in case the scholers should be blanked, it might for excuse yet be saide, vvhat maruell, if yonge men, and yet but studientes in the Scriptures, tooke a litle foyle? But if the olde Doctors come themselues, I vvarrant you, this nue Prophet shalbe othervvise handled. And yet like vvise men, they aduentured not to come aftervvard thē selues, assuredly knovving that all that they coulde say, vvas already vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by their scholers mouthes, but yet trustinge, that all men did not so knovv the same, but that they might still mainteine vvith some, their olde opinion and doctoral estimation. And though one <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 22. <hi>d</hi> 35.</note> Doctor came, and vvas handled as vvere the disciples, yet vvas the rebuke but one mans: but had he gotten the victorie, the prayse had been cōmō to them al. This is the effecte of S. Chrysostome his <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. <hi>d.</hi> 25</note> exposition vpon the sendinge of the disciples, and the comminge of one Doctor, vnto our Sauiour Christe. VVhiche our aduersaries like men of muche discretion, haue politikely folovved. But all men that haue any vnderstanding at all, may easely vnderstande, that thei all vvoulde not commit the handlinge of matters of suche vveight (and for the vvhiche they all, as it vvere <hi>Pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> for life and death, as one might terme it, doo fight) to those fevv, beinge very yonge men, and of meane learninge, and small experience, in comparison, and of a diuers studie, and professing themselues (vvhich they can not hide) to be yonge studientes in diuinitie: all men, I say may vvell knovve, that they vvoulde not committe suche matters to such men, vvithout their common aduise, and helpe ioyned vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hem. Seeinge that D. Hardinge himselfe do the plainely confesse, <note place="margin">In his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> that he in the vevv of his vvorke vsed the aduise of his learned frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: and that it is not credible, that M. Rastell vvould let his booke lie by him foure yeres in a readinesse, vvithout a suruey therof made <note place="margin">Rastell in praefat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ne▪</note> by some of so many remayning with him at Louane. VVherfore it is not harde for any of any vnderstandinge, to vnderstande that this
<pb facs="4"/>
publishinge of their common deuise vnto the worlde, in the names of a few of the simplest sorte among them, is but a practise of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. For they perciuinge that they cannot write nor set abroade bookes worthy to be compted learned mens doynges, doo prouide authors meete for suche bookes, as they can set foorth. VVhereby they shall not onely keepe their owne autoritie and cause without all daunger, what so euer be iudged of these authors, or their bookes: but shall also maintein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>n the mindes of men a great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and expectatiō of themselues, as <note place="margin">M. <hi>Rastell in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face &amp; fol.</hi> 1. <hi>saithe: I am but a comon soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the orders of diuines and therfore I must stande behinde so manie bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and scholars in diuinitie. I vvill vvith a penknife deminish his lustie bloud. Let the olde souldiours vvith great svvoordes and pikes kill his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie.</hi>
      </note> Veteranes, and olde Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours: whose brunt, when they shall come to the matter, wil be, as may seeme, of greater force and violence, than that it can possibly be resisted, <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine</hi> M. <hi>Rast. saith he will proue</hi> M. <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell may be answered by a meane Scholer in Diuinitie, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to prouoke the best of the Catholikes lyuinge.</hi>
      </note> seing these yonge souldiours haue geuen such a fresh onset. But I dare assure you that either these matters shal thus stil be handled by scholers and yonge studientes (as they call thēselues) or if th'olde doctors dare aduēture (which yet many doctors doubt of) they shal handle the saide matters but scholerlike, as hath that one Doctor already doone: and I doubt not, but it shall to the worlde be made most manifest, that he hath so doone. And to speake more particularly: as it was no greate matter for D. Harding out of Pighius, Gropperus, Hosius, and certaine others (who haue intreated of the same matters in common places before him) to haue translated into English what he thought meete for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, whiche he hath lately put abroade as his owne dooinges: so might M. Dorman with farre lesse labour, and better right also a greate deale, out of his maister D. Hardinges booke, so lately before written, borow of authorities and reasons ready framed to his hādes, as much as liked him, and so of a peece of his maisters booke (conteining onely .iiij. articles of .xxvi.) with greate ease make vs an other new booke, as greate, as is his maisters: the ordre here and there being a litle transposed, to obscure the matter, and to make a show of new inuention: and the stile somewhat floorished with M. Dormans railing rhetorike. For they that doo know M. Dorman better than I doo, marueiling of his dooinges in Diuinitie matters, doo thinke that he hath all his learninge, not of inheritance, but by l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gacie: supposinge that he hath mette with Doctor Smith his written bookes, who of late deceasinge, did, as they say, put M. Dormā in some trust. Els they thinke, he coulde not so shortly, and sodenly, before he was knowen to be a student in Diuinitie, become a Bacheler of the same. Vnlesse perhappes he sometime stoode vpon
<pb facs="4"/>
the bridge with others, whiles the creator saide, <hi>Omnes vos qui statis in ponte, estote Bacchalaurei: dixit, &amp; fatui sūt.</hi> But the same his acqueintance, so marueiling of his new degree in schoole of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>initie, affirme, that in iesting, scoffing, mockinge, and railinge, he is suche a Veterane, and so olde a practicioner, that he doth plainely raigne, yea and triūphe too, in the schoole of scolding: and though they helde their peace, his dooynges in this booke doo wel declare the same. And it is not vnlikely but that M. Dorman with others, vpon vew of D. Hardinges booke, iudgeing that he, as a graue and learned man, had sufficiently reasoned against vs, but had otherwise dealte to coldely with vs (as of purpose auoidynge glikes, nippes, <note place="margin">D. <hi>Harding fol.</hi> 5.</note> scoffes, bittes, cuttes, and girdes, for so himselfe saithe) thought it good by common aduise, that M. Dorman takinge D. Hardinges reasons, and so eased of that greatest parte of the labour, should set foorth the matter, and amplifie it (specially that of the Popes supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, in the whiche he saw his Maister had professed breuitie) after <note place="margin">D. <hi>Harding fol.</hi> 75. <hi>b.</hi>
      </note> his and certaine others deuise, and not only with nippes, and girdes pinche, and wringe vs, but also with whole cartlodes of railynges (in the whiche facultie M. Dorman excelleth) should ouerwhelme vs, that wee might seeme to all their fauourers, not only borne downe and cleane ouerthrowen by D. Hardinge, but also by M. Dorman torne all to peeces, according as M. Dorman hath in this booke, for his parte well endeuoured himselfe to accomplishe.</p>
   <p>Novv if any doo maruell that I, not prouoked, as may seeme, doo purchase to my selfe so great and grecuous an aduersarie, as is M. Dorman, by ansvvering his booke vvritten, as he professeth, against the bishop of Sarisburie, I make them this ansvvere: Though this and other like bookes appeare in name and vvoorde, to be vvritten againste the saide bishop onely, yet be they in deede and meaninge vvriten againste vs all, as vvell as him: for that they doo oppugne and assaulte the cause, vvhiche is common to vs all vvith him, vnder his name onely: goeinge about through his sides (as it vvere) to thrust vs all through the hartes. Further, seeinge suche a number of bookes, as it vvere dartes, directed at his head, vvhereof the moste parte are suche, that had he leysure enough therto, yet vvould he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ansvvere them, but by contempte of them, vvhiche yet not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvered, might seeme therfore to be let alone, for that thei vvere not ansvverable, (suche is, either the sclender discretion of some sielie soules, either the bolde braggerie of many malaperte aduersaries) I
<pb facs="5"/>
thought for the satisfiynge of the symple, and repressinge of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solente, to say somevvhat to some one of those bookes: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to M. Dormās, rather than any others, for that it came abroade nexte in ordre after D. Hardinge his booke. Of vvhiche booke yet, had I, before I did beginne, vnderstanded, (that I novve in processe doo) that it had bene in substance so agreable vvith D. Hardinge his booke, that the Bishoppe of Sarum should in ansvveringe the one, in effect haue ansvvered bothe, (as he must needes doo) it should for me haue bene let alone, vntill the bishoppes ansvvere had come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade in printe: and than, (the conclusion onely excepted, vvhiche is somevvhat seuerall to M. Dorman) should it by me haue none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise bene ansvvered, but onely by notinge in the margent, in vvhat places of the bishoppes ansvvere to D. Hardinge, euery place of M. Dormans booke is ansvvered, vvhiche order I vvill hereafter folovve: and vvhere M. Dorman shall haue any thinge peculiar, that vvill I directly ansvvere my selfe. Novv as the ignoraunce of the affinitie betvvene the Maisters and the scholers bookes caused me to beginne vvith M. Dormans booke, as an other nevve vvoorke vntouched be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, intending verefy to goe through vvith the same: so in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of the booke, the knovvledge therof did grovv more and more, and so much at the laste, that I did not onely by the style (as did Tullie Theophrastes Disciple) but by the matter it selfe also, knovv D. Harding his scholar, so like to him, that he might seeme his sonne also, and spitte out of his mouth, as they say: so that in deede he may professe D. Hardinge to be his mayster of very good righte, as of vvhome he hath the learninge that he shevveth in this booke. And had he not dedicate the booke to D. Hardinge, as to vvhome of right it apperteineth, beyng as a man learned in the lavve, not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the chiefe propertie of iustice, <hi>suum cui{que},</hi> he mighte haue bene iustly accused of some vniuste compilation of his maisters al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meries: seeyng he is not yet his exequutor, as vvell as D. Smithes. This matter, I say perceiued, inforced me to stay, least I might seeme of sette purpose, though colorably, to haue hasted to preuent the bishoppe of Sarisburie in ansvveringe D. Hardinge, by ansvveringe M. Dorman: and so to haue seemed vvillinge, to goe before him one vvay in hastie dooynge, vvhome I must needes folovv a great vvay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde in all vvell dooinge. And vvere not this cause, (vvhich yet is a great, and a iuste cause) I haue not suche leasure (vvhiche is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon case of vs all) as to ansvvere that, vvhiche I doo heare say is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb facs="5"/>
ansvvered, and ready to printe, as M. Dorman had leasure to vvrite againe, that vvhiche vvas before vvriten by his Maister: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had I such leasure, liste I, as he dothe, blotte paper vvith other mens dooinges. These are the very causes vvhy I haue staied, and as yet haue proceeded no further in the ansvveringeof M. Dormans booke. But vvhen I had passed thus farre, and the bishoppes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvere▪ as the reporte than vvent, vvas not fully finished, and many good mèn muche desired somme ansvvere, and as many aduersaries as much bragged, that their bookes vvoulde neuer be ansvvered: the councell of some friendes, and suche continuall bragge of so many aduersaries caused me to suffer this little taste, as vntimely fruite, the sooner to come abroade: that suche as finde double faulte vvith vs, for not ansvveryng speedely, or fully, might in parte be satisfied. And the rather haue I consented to suche aduise of my friendes, for that by this taste that I haue giuen the readers of M. Dorman, they shall knovv him throughly not a lyon (as they say) by his longe nayles, but a lyar by his leude tales. For by the vevve hereof, they may not onely iudge of his vvhole treatie: but also, this principall parte, and firste fronte, (in the vvhiche M. Dorman, as a skilfull man, hath placed the chiefe strength and force) or rather this, the very funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vvhole beynge cleane ouerthrovven, (as I doubt not but it is) all the reste muste needes come to ruine vvith all. At the least, I trust, I haue so farre satisfied the discrete reader concerninge M. Dorman, that it shall suffice hereafter to passe ouer the residue of his booke by briefe notes. And I doo truste also, that suche as shall blame me moste for not ansvvering the vvhole, shalbe greued moste that I haue ansvvered so much: and that those, that shall finde moste faulte i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vvoordes vvith our slacke ansvveringe, shall be moste vexed in minde vvith our speedy ansvvering. For as their bookes vvere not therfore sodenly vvriten, for that they came sodenly abroade, so shal <note place="margin">M. <hi>Rastell in his prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa econfes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth his booke to haue bene begun four yeeres agoe.</hi>
      </note> they, I doubt not, be ansvvered spedely: that is, in shorter space then they vvere vvriten in. And yet all speede is not alvvay in most haste. For it may so fall out that M. Dorman vvith the vvhole company of his adhaerentes the Papistes shall more easily write tenne such boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes more at randon, as this is written, then be hable to mainteine and to defende directlie this little parcel of his booke, as eyther tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or learnedly written. And thus muche I thought good to saie concerning our not speedie answeringe (as some men thinke) and my parcel answering (which some men wil blame) for the satisfiyng
<pb facs="6"/>
of some, for all looke not to satisfie, though al Dormans, and al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Papists, were altogether already so answered as they al might be ashamed of their dooinges, as I doubt nothinge, god willinge, but it shall shortely so come to passe, though peraduenture not one emongst them all will euer confesse the same.</p>
   <p>Now that I haue so diligently and largely, and as it may seeme care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully also, answered M. Dorman (whose owne dooynges, I affirme to be more woorthy of laughter, than of any earnest answere) which shall. I am sure, be layde also to my charge, I doo certifie the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I doo not answere the reasons alleaged in this booke, as M. Dormans, but as the reasons of D. Hardinge, of whom M Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath borowed them: and not onely Doctor Hardinges, but Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>krus, Pighius, and Hosius reasons also, yea and of all those, that haue written in Latine for the Popes vsurped power, and suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in whose writinges the like reasons are to be found, and out of whom D. Hardinge (as out of him M. Dorman) hath translated <hi>adverbum</hi> almost, such places as he thought for his purpose: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue vsed the more diligēce, as vnder the name of one, answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe so many. An other and most weightie cause why I haue vsed such diligence and prolixitie, is this: M. Dorman though he be a weake assaylant and sclender reasoner, yet is he a great lyar, and a venemous sclaunderer: and therefore hath he sette abroade a lewde booke in deede, but not so lewde as sclaunderous: and sclaunderous not to seueral persons onely, but to our whole countrey, to our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and to our gratious soueraigne, whom he chargeth as vsurping vndue authoritie: sclaunderous I say, not here at home onely, but abroade also in foraigne countreis. VVherefore whom so euer M. Dorman sheweth him selfe to be, and how sclender an aunswere so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer might best become him: I thought it should become me, not sclenderly to esteeme the honour of my prince, my d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etie to my countrey, and to the lawes of the realme: but with earnestnesse to repell suche reproches, as M. Dorman hath attempted to blemishe them withall. Thirdelie for that the simple and vnlearned readers haue often best liking in bookes more boldely then learnedly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and are most in daunger to creadite most lewde and sclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse lyes (in so muche that a great many for the commendation of these vertues, doo praeferre the Scholar before the Maister, M. Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man I meane, before D. Hardinge, suche is their iudgement) I haue therfore in answering more at large, applied my self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to such as be
<pb facs="6"/>
of meane vnderstandinge, to whom the guilefull dealinges of the Papistes can not with breuitie be made manifest. For as a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent at a touch thrusteth in his stinge and venime: but the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheafe in like wise can not be as sodeinlie cured, but requireth lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time, and businesse: so can not the sclaunderous and venemous lyes by M. Dorman quickely tould, be so quickely and brieflie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, with such plainenesse, as is mete for such who are most in daunger to credite such false tales. VVherfore (good reader) if I shal seeme to be too prolix and tedious, yea and to careful too in answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe so largely and diligently such a one as M. Dorman sheweth him selfe to be, specially in the beginninge till I haue made thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his kinde of writing, I trust thou shalt the better beare with me therein, if thou wilt beare these considerations in memorie. Yet haue I laboured to serue also the learned and occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed readers turne: For I haue in the conclusion of this mine answere <note place="margin">
         <hi>fol.</hi> 119.</note> in fewe wordes touched the summe of the whole processe before, whereunto if it shall please them at the first to resort, it may so sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie them perhappes, that they shall not neede to stay about the larger explication of mine aunswere in the formar processe of this booke. And this for my earnest aunswere to so merie a mans booke as is M. Dorman. Now as I haue not dealt with him in his <note n="*" place="margin">Raylinge, Reuilynge▪ Ribalrie.</note> facultie, in the which I cōfesse him to be inuincible, and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be not onely Bachilar, but double Doctour thereof: so yet if M. Dormans outragious railinges, and shameles lyes shall cause me sometime to shape him an answere meete for such a man, as he is, I trust the reasonable reader wil consider my not occasion, but inforcement rather thereunto: not onely looking vppon my sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges, and vewynge how meete or vnmeete they be for me: but how meete they be for his saiynges and him, to whom I doo make answere. VVho doth so confidently affirme, and solemnely aduouch that if our stomakes shall serue vs to replie, he is sure that our eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dorman. fol.</hi> 110. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> so much, that sixe lynes (to speake with the moste) wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vvith ease all that vve haue to vvrite. vvhich hovv truely it is spoken, shall be tried, I trust, by this litle euidence that I haue here geuen in, to thee (good Reader) against his counterfaite, and false forged vvritinges: vvherein is not of matter of truthe, so muche as sixe lynes any vvhere to be founde.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>