<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE FAIRE, and hopefull Branch, of the renowmed FAMILY of the LEWKENORS in Suffolke, Edward Lewkenor Esquire.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113488_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08481</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18805</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE FAIRE, and hopefull Branch, of the renowmed FAMILY of the LEWKENORS in Suffolke, Edward Lewkenor Esquire.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods rebuke in taking from vs that worthy and honourable gentleman Sir Edward Lewkenor Knight, the first day of May this present yeere 1618, he being at that time high Sheriffe of Suffolke : whose Christian life and comfortable end are here faithfully recorded. Together wit diuers profitable and necessarie instructions; deliuered first in a discourse at his funerall, and now inlarged, and published, for the benefit of others not then present. By T.O. aliàs P. minister of the word of God at Denham in Suffolke</title>
                 <author>Oldmayne, Timothy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 98, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE FAIRE, and hopefull Branch, of the <hi>renowmed</hi> FAMILY <hi>of the</hi> LEWKENORS in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> Edward Lewkenor <hi>Esquire.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been my continuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, euer si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence it was the Almighties pleasure, to take from vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himselfe, your worthy and
<pb facs="4"/>
honourable Father, that some skilfull hand, would haue enterprized this worke, thus rudely by me both begunne and finished. For the more beautifull the face is, the more exquisite is the Limmer that it challengeth. (<hi>Let the Cobler meddle with his slipper, and let</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles <hi>only draw the picture of that great Alexander.</hi>) If such a one would haue vndertaken it, how happie should I haue thought my selfe if as his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, I might but haue ground his colours. But see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none would; I as you see haue done it; Plainely I must needes confesse, howbeit as
<pb facs="4"/>
neere the life as possibly I could. And to you, his only sonne, doe I deuote this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, of so rare and onely a father. Your tender yeeres perhaps, will for a time dim your eye, that you shall not be able so clearely to discerne, that deale of worth that is here pourtraied, and shadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out. But <hi>Pictures,</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies best discerned some distance off; and therefore my comfort is, that although, not now, yet in time you wil: The which time being once come, let me desire you, that whatsoeuer excellencie you finde here expressed, you
<pb facs="5"/>
would be pleased, to imbrace, and follow; shaping your selfe and all your actions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to so noble, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Patterne. So, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer honours, your Father in his life possessed, you his sonne after him shall be sure to inherit, and the same bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings that attended him, shall questionlesse, be doubled vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. The which I shall not whilst I liue cease beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at the hands of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly FATHER. Alwaies resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your poore friend, Timoth: Oldmayne,</hi> aliàs <hi>Pricke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>