<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CVRIOVS PAINTERS OF CIRCLES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113946_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14305</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24623</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113946</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CVRIOVS PAINTERS OF CIRCLES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arraignment of slander periury blasphemy, and other malicious sinnes : shewing sundry examples of Gods iudgements against the ofenders. As well by the testimony of the Scriptures, and of the fathers of the primatiue church as likewise out of the reportes of Sir Edward Dier, Sir Edward Cooke, and other famous lawiers of this kingdome. Published by Sir William Vaughan knight</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Constable, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 351, 21 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_note">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>TO THE CVRIOVS PAINTERS OF CIRCLES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F these <hi>lines</hi> or leaues of my <hi>Circles</hi> drawne from the Center to the circumference be not all equall, or if the <hi>points</hi> and <hi>prickes</hi> of euery <hi>line</hi> answere not the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall proportion of the <hi>Circle,</hi> thou knowest, that <hi>Veritas non quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit angulos,</hi> truth respects not angles, triangles, quadrangles, nor artificiall curiosity. I care not for the enticing words of worldlings wisedome, but I couet <hi>the Spirit of euidence and power.</hi> I couet matter more then method. And yet I labour so to linke them, that the line of nature may
<pb facs="11"/>
stand coupled with the points of Art, that both from the Center of truth be caried to a <hi>Christian</hi> circumference: for euē as the gifts of the <hi>holy Ghost</hi> be distributed diuersly, and in diuerse measures to <hi>Gods</hi> children, some ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but one grain of faith being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in the euening of their liues, and yet by grace adopted &amp; adiudged worthy to receiue the like equal crown of glory, the like equall wages, as those, which laboured longer in the <hi>Lords</hi> haruest: so (to cōpare little things with great) let thy Grace (Ingenuous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) or gracious construction counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail the vnequal <hi>lines</hi> of my <hi>Circles.</hi> Where they exceed in their dimensiue quantity, there oppose their distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue quality for a counter-ballance,</p>
   <p>Et sic omnes lineae ductae à centro ad circumferentiam sunt aequales.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>