<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL MR. EDWARD SHELDON of Beoley, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Bell, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113723_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07625</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1802</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113723</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL MR. EDWARD SHELDON of Beoley, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Bell, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The testament of William Bel. Gentleman : Left written in his owne hand. Sett out above 33. yeares after his death. With annotations at the end, and sentences, out of the H. Scripture, fathers, &amp;c. By his sonne Francis Bel, of the Order of Freers Minors, definitor of the province of England: guardian of S. Bonaventures colledge in Dovvay: and professor of the sacred Hebrevv tongue, in the same. Electo meo foedus excidi</title>
                 <author>Bell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bellerus (Bellere, Beelaert), Balthazar</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>180 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<seg rend="sup">R</seg>. EDWARD <hi>SHELDON of Beoley, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Anciently, when after the rihgt of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, the earth was Cōmon, and all the gooddes therof: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat a man Could say to his
<pb n="4" facs="4"/> neighbour <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> hast thou not all the earth before thee?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Genes.</hi> 13.9.</note> separate thy selfe from mee, if thou go to the lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hand I will keep the right, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thou go to the Right hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> will howld the left. Men gau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in theyr testaments to they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> children only coelestiall doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, that to whom they had given being, they migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> also giue well-being.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi> 77,</note> By thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> meanes wee haue heard an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> knowne so manie things: de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared to vs by our fathers which in the next generatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> were not hid from they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> children, declaring the pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses
<pb n="5" facs="4"/> of our Lord, his virtues, and mervailes done by him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat reised vp testimonie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>acob: and gaue a lawe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sraël▪ how manie things did hee commande our fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o make knowne to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>onnes to the end that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ext generatiō might know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hem, that the children that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hould arise and bee borne of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hem, might tell them againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o theyr children, and all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat they might sett theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ope in God, not forget his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orckes, and search out his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ommands. Moyses.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ember the dayes of oulde
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> thincke vpon everie severall generation, aske thy father &amp; hee will declare, thy elders and they will tell thee. Men gaue, I say, from hand to hand the lawe of God, his feare, &amp; loue: with benedic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the keepers, maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the breakers of it▪ Commending vertue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning vice: foretelling payne and glorie the reward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of both.<note place="margin">Epist. Iud. ca. <hi>1.14.</hi>
      </note> Such testament▪ the seaventh man from A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 48 49.</note> Enoch made. Such wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the Patriarch Iacobs testa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment disposed to his 12. son<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes: such also those, of thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="7" facs="5"/> 12. Patriarches themselves.<note place="margin">A most ancient Hebrev booke, called, the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stamēt of the <hi>12.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</note> But of that new &amp; everlas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting testament of IESVS-CHRIST the sonne of God what shall I say? therin is all knowledge of the heavenly kingdome: the aeternall beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and foelicitie of man. After this incomparable Testament, in which are all the treasures of the riches and wisedome of God, I may bring in that godly testamēt of my holy Father S. Francis, which after he was signed with the sacred stigmats of our Sauiour IESVS CHRIST, full with fervour, and the
<pb facs="6"/>
      <pb n="6" facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="7" facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="8" facs="8"/> holy ghost, neer the end of his life, he left to vs his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that more sincerely and catholickly we might keep his Evangelicall rule.</p>
   <p>Divers pious testaments haue been by sundrie devout persons, at severall times or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained: And not among the last doe I accoumpt this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament of my father, a man knowne and esteemed of your worship no less then of M.<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Raphe your father of happie memorie. It hath been kept in his owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuscript thees 44. yeares and more. By divine providence,
<pb n="9" facs="8"/> it hath at last come to my hands: who hauing been aboue 18. yeares out of my countrie in forraine lands, neither sought for, nor thought of anie such thing (although seing it now, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in my younger yeares I haue seen it before) when a graue father of our seraphicall order venerable for his well spent, yeares from his infancie till 67. (so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owld he is at this day) and no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ess for his profownde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and eloquence both in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>peach and style, lighting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pon it sent it out of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb n="10" facs="9"/> to mee, with no small commendations therof. His censure animated me to put it in print. And for a patrone to whom I might dedicate it I had not farre to seeke: your Constant Christianitie and professing of the Catholike Religion: who like the great Patriarch Abraham, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God, haue gone out of land and Countrie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers house and friends and kinred, and familiars, or like Saint Peeter out of all, doth Chalenge so christianlike a testament: especially from mee who, as appeareth in the
<pb n="11" facs="9"/> 34. §. of it, am severely char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bee serviceable towards you and yours.</p>
   <p>That service together with my selfe I offer here to your worship, for vs all that haue the charge there layde vpon vs: that we be not chalenged with the vile vice of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: or breach of the dead mannes will. my selfe haue had part of my education frō M.<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Frācis Daniel, my vncle, of whom mention is made in the 32. §. who now liveth not on earth. Of the Throckmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tōs of Coughton or Fekenhā mentioned in the 33. §. I
<pb n="12" facs="10"/> haue yet no knowledge, nor of Sir Ihon Littletons house, spoken of in the end of the 34. §. I may liue to doe them service. your selfe only remaines the man that most extended his godnes towards vs in accomplishing this wil: in bringing vp my brother Edmund together with your owne sonnes to learning to musicke, &amp; to the vniversitie of Oxforde, as was required. your sister also the Religious Ladie Russell gaue educatiō successiuely to two of my si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Margarit &amp; Dorothe.</p>
   <p>Receiue therfore from me
<pb n="13" facs="10"/> this last will of my father as my first will to serue you, which with my life shall last, and bee my last▪ so shall I fulfill that iterated precept of the holy ghost
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb.</hi> 1.8.</note>
         </l>
         <l>hear o my sonne the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thy father.</l>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb.</hi> 6.20.</note>
         </l>
         <l>keep o my sonne the precept of thy father.</l>
      </q> God praeserue your worship long to his highest glorie, the good of our familie, and chiefly of our seraphicall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which you haue alwaies shewed a charitable affectiō:
<pb n="14" facs="11"/> and finally chosen in our Convent at Namur Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams double caue for buriall to your happilie decessed wife and you. From our celle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in S. Bonaventures Colledge in Doway this 7. of Ianuarie▪ 1632.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships obliged</hi> Br. FRANCIS BEL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>