<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all the Young-men of my Parish, especially to late Companions of William Rogers, Apothecary, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113008_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19568</idno>
           <idno type="STC">60.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113008</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all the Young-men of my Parish, especially to late Companions of William Rogers, Apothecary, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The yovng-mans vvarning-peece: or, A sermon preached at the buriall of William Rogers Apothecary : With an history of his sinfull life, and wofull death. Together with a post-script of the use of examples. Dedicated to the young-men of the parish, especially to his companions. By Robert Abbot, Vicar of Cranebrooke in Kent</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Badger, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 76, 79-102 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all the Young-men of my Parish, especially to late Companions of <hi>William Rogers,</hi> Apothecary, <hi>Grace, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eerely belo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved Young-men, that this Sermon (in effect) was preached by mee, among you, you know, and the occasion you know too When I preachd it, it cam to your eares, &amp; it wrought something in some of your eyes, but I little thought
<pb facs="3"/>
to have presented it to your eyes againe. Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities from abroad, and at home, have pressed mee to make this adventure. And now it is come, to whom should it come, but unto you? It is true, my love to that dead Young-man, made me willing to satisfie his desire: and your desires to have it, have not made mee willing thus to send it unto you. Yet your courses being the occasion of it, and your welfare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end of it; you may justly chalenge it, and shall not by mee bee robbed of your right. Who knowes whether God may leave a blessing behind? I cannot bee assured, that, for the
<pb facs="3"/>
word of God handled in it, or for me the poore instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is used in it, ye will make much use of it for your good; because (I feare) ye so often prefer an ale-house before the house of God. It may be, ye had rather be without it, than have it; because the sight of it, to you, will be a sting; the sight of it, to others, will bee but a remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to them, to call upon you still to forsake those courses which ye love. Yet herein have I hope, that you will love to see the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of him being dead, whom yee loved and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed as your Doctor while he lived. If it be not drawne to life, my eyes,
<pb facs="4"/>
eares, and understanding much faile me, besides, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny witnesses will not faile to say, that all is true. I am sure, it is so for substance: and if it be coloured other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, even at the first it was rudely drawne, it is for your sakes, that you may still see him the more perfectly, and know your owne estate.</p>
   <p>You have had (in your daies) many examples, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that there is no bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to be had in a wicked way; it is folly to lay out your silver, and not for bread. But to have two in one yeere, layes the axe to the root of the trees of the Wood, and preacheth, that except ye amend, <hi>yee shall
<pb facs="4"/>
likewise perish.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Not onely as they but worse.</note> Yee have seene two Apothecaries different in their course. The one so many wayes looking home-ward,<note place="margin">So he was accounted of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us some years before he dyed.</note> that he <hi>died miserably rich</hi>; the other so lashing outward, that hee dyed miserably poore. Both of sweet and mild natures, and of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent waies in life:<note place="margin">So may a good man have, by some di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper or over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to lash some sin for the example of others.</note> yet both of <hi>uncomfortable passages out of the world.</hi> The one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving first the devill presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himselfe unto him to be his Physitian: and next CHRIST sitting on the Throne, condemning his unprofitable life, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him shift for himselfe, for he would have nothing to do with him. The other, as if hee would prevent
<pb facs="5"/>
Christ, condemning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to hell for ever, and ever. The one (being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rich, and having no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) was pressed by me, <hi>while hee was in peace, and before his last Will was settled,</hi> of his thousands to give but one hundred pounds, for the repairing of the Church, or other pious workes. But if hee were worth ten thousand (as he said) he would not give a penny, beside what he had given by will; that is, twenty Marks to the poor, ten pounds to me, and some other petty Legacies.<note place="margin">I meane an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable death, not judging his eternall estate.</note> If I were rich, I should be loth <hi>to pay so deare</hi> for such a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall, as he did in the end, full of horror to the last.
<pb facs="5"/>
The other (being very poore) was pressed by me againe and againe, <hi>but to beleeve in Christ for salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But I could not (for ought I saw) prevaile nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The one had lived well, except his misery: the other had lived ill, and so in misery worse. I know you feare not the danger of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he first example: for you are out of the way of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too rich. If you have enough to goe like gallant Blades, it is all you desire: yet if you have not, your credite must bee good till the quarter day, or the good market comes. But may you not feare the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the second? Him ye loved enough, his courses
<pb facs="6"/>
yee love too well. The Ale-house must bee your Chappell, Kitchin, Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house: the first draught is your prayer, the next your breakfast, and the last your worke. Yet if ye had but a Priest that would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Wine and strong drinke, and say, Come let us fill our selves with Wine and strong drinke, to morrow shall be as this d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, and much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant, hee were the only man, and you the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people of the world I know you think yourselv's very familiar with Christ, as if hee would passe by these slips of youth, and imbrace you in the armes of his mercy upon the least
<pb facs="6"/>
call. But you forget that <hi>Christ</hi> hath now taken state upon him. He was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant crying in the Cratch, and then he was circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by wicked Priests, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by an Asse into Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Hee was a Preacher in <hi>Israel,</hi> and then he was pressed upon by all, and sought to be intangled by his enemies. Hee was a worker of miracles here, and then sicke soules and bodies troubled him▪ He was under arrests and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions▪ and then <hi>Iudas</hi> did kisse, Souldiers buffeted and spit upon him, and <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> killed him. But now the case is altered, his present state admits no such neere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.
<pb facs="7"/>
Will you say hee is my sweet Saviour still? Go then and tell him so: say; Lord, I am idle, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and luxurio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, but thou art my sweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour still. Say yee to your fathers and mothers, I am drunken, idle, warton, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bellious, but ye are my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother still, and I expect your blessing, and your p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rse. Surely such proud and dissolute carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age shall a thousand times sooner please men on earth, than it shall please Christ in heaven. He hath redeemd you that ye might serve him in righteousnesse and holines all the daies of your life. He hath bought you with a price, that yee
<pb facs="7"/>
might glorifie God in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and soule, and (by the grace of God) save your selves from the midst of this wicked generation wherein ye live. Perhaps you may think your sinnes not to be so great, but that you may keep your fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in the salvation of Christ too. But they are not worthy of pitty who wilfully deceive their own soules: For in foure cases your least sins prove dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the issue. If they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
be committed against your consciences. Conscience is in Gods roome to guard you, and if that be affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it is given to God, and so you build downeward to hell. Then if they bee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <pb facs="8"/>
committed with pleasure and delight; there is no sin so small, which smels not unsavorily if it pleaseth. It pleased the man to gather <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> sticks, and he died for it. It pleased <hi>Lots</hi> Wife to look backe, and she was turned into a pillar of Salt. Next, if small sins dispose you to greater. For he that hath avoided the great Rockes, may be swallow'd up in the sand: and he that can keep out great Theeves, may have his house opened by a little Boy who creeps in at <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the window. Lastly, if the smallest sinnes have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, and go on. A little ball of snow, rowled, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, and many drops make a floud. Can you say
<pb facs="8"/>
that you sin not when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science checks, and saith, Doe it not? Or that you have not taken pleasure in what you have done? Or that you have not bin dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>posed by your houres of error, to scandalize others, and neglect God and his worship? Or that your lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle sins have not multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed so long, as that they may (for any thing you are sure to the contrary) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Ocean to drowne your soules in eternall hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror? What now is to bee done, but that you see your wickednesse, and amend all? I am sure it would bring comfort to your friends, to see you in the way to Heaven. I am more
<pb facs="9"/>
sure it would bring glory to God, and honour to the Gospell, to have his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the professors of it from your youth, to live in the obedience of faith. And I know assuredly too, that it shall adde to my crowne of rejoycing, to see all, Christs Lambs, Babes, and Children to walke in that truth which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to godlinesse. Vp and be doing, and the God of Heaven be with you. There is no delay must have place now. It is enough (yea <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oo much) that yee have spent the time past after the course of the wicked world. God hath held his peace, and not unsheathed his sword, and you have
<pb facs="9"/>
lived as if God were a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of sinne. But hath he not now begun to strik? Hath hee not let you see that there is no peace to the wicked? If ye yet goe on, yee kicke against the pricks. If ye come in with bleeding soules: behold your blessed Saviour han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the crosse; he bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his head, as if he meant to kisse you; he stretched out his armes, as if hee meant to imbrace you; and his blessed side was broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as if he meant that even you should drinke his bloud, to pacifie your souls against conscience of wrath, and his water to purifie your bodies and soules from the dominion
<pb facs="10"/>
of all uncleannesse. Will you yet neglect so great salvation? My soule shall weepe for you in secret. Yet that there may not be a cause, I hope that you will reade this that I p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent unto you, and so make a stand. I hope you will pray to God that the cause may have accesse unto your hearts, and so make an entrance into the good way. And I hope that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred, you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end; and then as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Thessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> so I of you; Now I live if ye stand fast in the Lord. Even I, who have bin often grieved by you, and have often prayed for you with groanes and
<pb facs="10"/>
sighs, but now hope to be comforted in my bowels over you, upon your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment; and ever after to continue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Pastour rejoycing in the conversion of such sinners,</hi> Robert Abbot.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>