<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The argument of the Admonition following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113871_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69004</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3892</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113871</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The argument of the Admonition following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two little workes defensiue of our redemption : that our Lord went through the veile of his flesh into heaven, to appeare before God for vs. Which iourney a Talmudist, as the Gospell, would terme, a going vp to Paradise: but heathen Greeke, a going downe to Hades, and Latin descendere ad inferos. Wherein the vnlearned barbarous, anger God and man, saying, that Iesus descended to Hell: and yeelde vnto the blasphemous Iewes by sure consequence vpon their words, that he should not be the Holy one of God. By Hugh Broughton</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <head>The argument of the Admonition following.</head>
   <p>BR. wrote vnto Queene Elizabeth, that King Edward the sixt and her Maiest.
swearing to the Gospell, sware to this, That to goe to Hades in the Creede,
was to goe to Paradise, euen by Heathen Greeke: to whom Hades is the
world of soules: in which the holy haue Paradise, and the godles, Gehenna. Both
be on high before Gods throne. And Br. commended the cause to Q. Elizabeths
M. and the King of Scots Maiestie. Against that a libell was allowed to scoff the
Scottish mist, penned by some Belial Bar Lo: and against saluation Bilson raged:
as this short worke telleth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>