<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Ouerseers: the Author wisheth Care to their office, health to their bodies, and Heauen to their oules.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113911_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21081</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7446</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113911</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Ouerseers: the Author wisheth Care to their office, health to their bodies, and Heauen to their oules.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ease for overseers of the poore : abstracted from the statutes, allowed by practise, and now reduced into forme, as a necessarie directorie for imploying, releeuing, and ordering of the poore. With an easie and readie table for recording the number, names, ages, exercises and defects of the poore, fit to be obserued of the ouerseers in euery parish. Also hereunto is annexed a prospect for rich men to induce them to giue, and a patterne for poore men to prouoke them to labour, very pertinent to the matter. The principall heads hereof appeare in the next page</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 2 folded leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="4"/>
   <head>To all Ouerseers: the Author wisheth Care to their office, health to their bodies, and Heauen to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oules.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander</hi> that magnanimious and mightie Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, in his martiall affaires would admit confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with his meanest followes: holding it for a principle of experience, that as many threddes are stronger then one by cōbination, so many heads are better then one in consultation.</p>
   <p>By which president we may learne in businesse tending to a common benefit, not to reiect or pretermit the iudgement of any well affected writer: for as the Philistim was slaine by Dauid whome Saul thought a man disable to doe it, so a worke of some worth may be performed by him, whome the world deeme very weake to accomplish it.</p>
   <p>In cases of Common-wealth euery one must be readie to extract his talent to the best, as the Iewes did stretch their estates to fortifie the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous walls of Ierusalem at the worst; and he which doth his best is not to be blamed for his forwardnes, no more then the souldiour in the field which giues the first on set to fight.</p>
   <p>He that is most skilfull in Architecture doth finde more trouble in contriuing the frame, then in finishing the worke: and so it is with the best Artist, the forme of inuention is more busie then the action it selfe: and therefore seeing I haue framed an easie platforme to begin a good worke, I must leaue the finishing, to them which are better able to build it. For this worke is brought to best perfection by protraction of time: because practise and experience doe alwaies adde somewhat to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
   <p>Excellent is that law which is last prouided for the poore, but yet as gold be it neuer so pretious is vnprofitable without vse, so Laws be they neuer so laudable want life without execution: therefore such as be <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersees</hi> for the poore must consider that the letter the lawes be, which
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> are prouided for the poore, the more they are condemned that neglect the looking to the poore: and the greater glorie a Prince getteth by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting good lawes, the greater shame the subiects reape by disobeying the lawes.</p>
   <p>I haue set forth this Treatise, not for ambition, as Nimrod did the tower of Babel to get a name, nor for vaine glorie, as Absalom did a pillar to preserue his name (for that cause I forbeare my name:) but of meere affection to my natiue countrie to further it.</p>
   <p>If there be any thing omitted, amend it: if there be something worth the following, vse it: if it be a little defectiue, excuse it: for Argus could neuer see all, nor Christ himselfe content all.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>