<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113319_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68976</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3552.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113319</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly wil and confession of the Christian faythe, made by Rychard Brasier, late auditour to the kinges maiesti in Ireland, whiche be dydde most constantly cleaue vnto during the time that he lyued, worthy to be read by all Christians</title>
                 <author>Brasier, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere hast thou (gentle reder) y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true copy of the last wil and testament of Richard Brasier, late Auditour for the kyngs maiesty in Ireland, wherin is briefly, but yet clearely declared the fayth in Christ, which the said Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard did professe in hys life time, &amp; constantly cleaue vnto in the tyme of hys departyng oute of this lyfe. Whych hys last wil and confessiō of the Christian faith, the sayd Rychard wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be openly declared in a Sermon made at his funeral in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church of S. Patrike in Diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyn, wher he lyeth buryed, to the entent that the mouthes of such slaunderers as do commonly imagine the recātacion of faythful Christians at the time of their departing out of this world, myght be stopped. And because y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> report of this confession of fayth is not yet beleued of manye superstitious mē, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> would al Christē mē shuld in their last houre recant their assured hope of saluation through Christ only without any our deseruinges: it hath bene thought good to such as the said Richard put in trust to se his wil ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filled, to cause this (the very true copy hereof) to be imprinted, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al mē might se &amp; iudge. Bese<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the to read &amp; remēber what Christē faith Richard Brasiar stode vnto in the end, &amp; what euery true mēber of Christ must cōfesse &amp; stand vnto. The merciful goodnes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord preserue the to the ende, that y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> maiest be salfe. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>