<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Aduertisements touching the vse of this labor.</title>
           <author>Norden, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113229_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08306</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18635</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Aduertisements touching the vse of this labor.</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Speculum Britanniae. The first parte an historicall, &amp; chorographicall discription of Middlesex. Wherein are also alphabeticallie sett downe, the names of the cyties, townes, parishes hamletes, howses of name &amp;c. W.th direction spedelie to finde anie place desired in the mappe &amp; the distance betwene place and place without compasses. Cum priuilegio. By the trauaile and vew of Iohn Norden. Anno 1593</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48, 4 pages, 3 folded plates, maps, coats of arms (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_note">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Aduertisements touching the vse of this labor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be noted, that for your ease I haue in the list of the Map of the Shire, set downe certaine deuisions, letters, and figures: the deuisions are in steed of a scale of the miles, the lesser cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining one, the greater two miles. The letters and figures serue for the present finding of any place desired in the Map, which places are found in the Alphabet with the letter and figure that direct to the place desired. A matter of so great facilitie as needeth no example.</p>
   <p>He that desireth to know the distance betweene places in the Map without compasses, the vse of the crossing lines, which serue for a vniuersall scale through the Map, answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his desire.</p>
   <p>Whereas in the collection of the Alphabeticall table, there are heere and there dispersed houses of Nobility &amp; Gentrie. I craue fauorable consideration, though I haue not so narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquired their interestes, as that may assure me, that they be all the true ownoures in fee, of the places which they are resident in, which thing to obserue; as it doth not meerely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to my purpose, So were it a matter intricate, and the more, for that information (often vncertaine) must be of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie, the chiefest guide therein. Such therefore as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue most doubtfull for want of certaine certificat, I haue noted with two starres thus, **.</p>
   <p>Also in this commencement of my trauailes, I haue obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued certain funeral monuments with the armes (if any ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rest vndefaced) which if it may be fauorably conceiued, I shall with more diligence obserue the like hereafter, whereby may be preserued in perpetuall memory, that which time may deface, and swallow vp in obliuion. Also by this obseruation, many may be certified of the places where their auncestors and allies are interred, and by the coates finde out their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne kinred.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Negotium ex negotio seritur. <hi>IOHN NORDEN.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>