<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113275_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08326</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18658</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113275</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An antidote or treatise of thirty controuersies : vvith a large discourse of the Church. In which the soueraigne truth of Catholike doctrine, is faythfully deliuered: against the pestiferous writinges of all English sectaryes. And in particuler, against D. Whitaker, D. Fulke, D. Reynolds, D. Bilson, D. Robert Abbot, D. Sparkes, and D. Field, the chiefe vpholders, some of Protestancy, some of puritanisme, some of both. Deuided into three partes. By S.N. Doctour of Diuinity. The first part</title>
                 <author>S. N. (Sylvester Norris)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 335, 1, 8, 207, that is 307, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>WO of the first &amp; stoutest Champions of the <hi>Primitiue Church, Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> writing against the <hi>Pagans,</hi> auouch,<note place="margin">Tertul. &amp; Arno. cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Gent.</note> that many of them impugned at the beginning our <hi>Christian</hi> fayth, not so much of inueterate hatred, as either of ignorance not knowing what we maintainde: or of weaknes, transported by the streame of Idolatry, which euery where disgraced, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it selfe against it. <hi>S. Augustine</hi> likewise writeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,<note place="margin">Aug. l. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Confess. c. 19.</note> and his friend <hi>Alipius,</hi> how slowly they imbraced, or rather refrained from the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> by reason of some erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous conceits they framed of our beliefe; the one, that we were infected with the heresy of <hi>Apollinaris;</hi> the other, not discerning the purity of our doctrine, from the dregges of <hi>Photinus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. The same opinion I haue of sundry <hi>Protestants,</hi> who renounce our <hi>Religion,</hi> not of any malicious mind, but for that they ignorantly mistake the true grounds of faith, or easily giue eare to the pernitious obloquies of their fayth-lesse Ministers, who without feare of God or regarde of conscience perfidiously appeach vs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable
<pb facs="8"/>
Sacriledges; of such worship of Images as was vsed by<note place="margin">Reyn. de ido. Rom. Eccles. lib. 1. c. 2. &amp;c. Fulke in c. 2. ad Col. sect. 3. Fulke in 1. ad Tim. c. 4. sect. 4. &amp; 5. Sutclif. in his suruey of Popery cap. 8. Sparks in his answer to M. Iohn D'Albines p. 219. 120. VVhitak. contro. 1. quaest. 5. Rich. Stoch in his ep. Dedica. to the Lord Knowles prefixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore M. VVhitak. answere to M. Camp. 10. reasons Bils. in his booke of Christian subiection &amp;c: 4. par &amp; part. 1. Reyn. in his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with M. Hart.</note> the <hi>Carpocratians;</hi> of such inuocation of <hi>Angels</hi> as the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolikes</hi> practised; of deniall of Marriage with the <hi>Tatians,</hi> and <hi>Encratites;</hi> of selling the guifts of the holy Ghost with <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> of honouring our Blessed Lady, in offering her a wafer cake with the <hi>Collyridians;</hi> &amp; of many such execrable blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which our harts detest farre more then theirs. Wherefore after the excellent and worthy labours of diuers memorable men, both forraine and domesticall, who with large volumes and inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible reasons haue purged vs of these slaunders &amp; manifestly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the vnconquerable truth of our ancient beliefe: I haue endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to make a short abridgment of all our most weighty and important proofes, that heere the Reader may see as in a mappe described, or pourtraited in a table, what in the spacious feild of sundry mens workes, is in diuers things more amply enlarged.</p>
   <p n="3">3. My purpose is not seuerally to encounter any one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r aduersary, but to trace the steppes, and ioyntly to des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ry the errours of many, according as the proiect of my intended discourse, or force of their opposition shall minister occasion: for my intention is to wade, by Gods help, into the maine Ocean of all the greatest and most difficult questions controuerted at this day betweene our English <hi>Protestants</hi> and vs. Therfore because I could not single forth any one person vnanswered, who learnedly, methodically and sufficiently treateth of them all; I made choyce to enter combat with diuers the most eminent I could find in euery particuler point, that ouerthrowing them, I might easily put their adherents to flight. To vphold, for example, the Scripture alone to be Iudge of Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, who spendeth more tyme, sheweth more skill, imployeth better talents, then <hi>M. Whitaker,</hi> stiled by one of his fauourits, <hi>An excellent instrument of Gods glory, and one of the most glorious lights of our English Church?</hi> To depriue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Reall Presence, hath any vsed like art, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed more diligence, mustered more obiections, then <hi>M. Bilson?</hi> who need not borrow any prayse from the pens of flatterers, he hath I confesse, too many good gifts for such ill imployments.</p>
   <p n="4">4. Againe, who trauaileth more painfully, then he, and <hi>M. Reynolds,</hi> to shake (if it were possible) the impregnable
<pb facs="8"/>
rocke of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> but chiesly of the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacy? Is there any at length (not to instance any further) more eager against Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and Prayer for the dead, then M. <hi>Fulke,</hi> and <hi>M. Field;</hi> He, in his Confutation of Purgatory, and in diuers other workes; This, in his third booke of the <hi>Church,</hi> and in his Appendixor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sivere to M. <hi>Higgons?</hi> And are not these the chiefe Captaynes and Coronels of <hi>Protestant</hi> rebellion, in whom the life breatheth, and mayne strength of their faction consisteth? Wherefore if he who often giueth victory to the weakest on his side, shall giue me grace to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quish these his stoutest enemies, little need we feare the after-skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishing of other their scattered and appaled troupes. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you must not expect I should runne through all their erring paths, or ferret euery one out of their starting holes: my drift is only to ouerthrow their grounds, and blunt the edge of their shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest weapons, yet with such euident conquest and demonstration of our <hi>Catholike Doctrine,</hi> as may be in all points sufficient to instruct the ignorant, strengthen the weake, discomfort the proud, and recall the straied to the right way of life.</p>
   <p n="5">5. For besides the assaults I make against them, the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I produce on my owne side shal in euery Controuersy be chiefly drawen out of the Word of God, the heauenly treasure and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone of truth, out of the auncient Fathers, and for the most part<note place="margin">Aug. con▪ Donatist▪ post Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. c. 34. Matth. c. 12. v. 27. Lact. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. insti. Arnob. aduers. Gē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Euseb. de praep. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alex l. Strom. Cicero pro A. Caecin.</note> also out of Generall Councells, out of the secret bowels and instinct of Nature, out of the discourse of reason, and lastly out of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable writings and testimonies of our Aduersaries; who, as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> heretofore noted of the <hi>Donatists, write &amp; speake manie things in our behalfe, forced by truth, not inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Charity.</hi> Therefore as <hi>Christ</hi> alledged the <hi>Pharisies</hi> Children to be iudge against the <hi>Pharisies,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius, Eusebius, Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and many more did bring the writings of <hi>Hermes, Orpheus,</hi> the <hi>Sybils,</hi> and other Gentiles, <hi>To conuince</hi> (sayth <hi>S. Augustine) by them the vanities of the Gentiles:</hi> So we propound the cheife <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of <hi>Protestancy</hi> to beare witnesse against the <hi>Protestants;</hi> with this <hi>prouiso,</hi> which the Prince of Oratours <hi>Marcus Tullius</hi> made in like case, who vsing in his owne behalfe the confession of one of his Opponents, intreated the Iudges, <hi>Not
<pb facs="9"/>
to belieue him the lesse, because he was a man of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe little worthy of credit; but rather to belieue him the more, because he spake in that point, both repugnant to his cause, and contrary to himselfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="6">6. Soe I desire my Reader, not to make lesse reckoning of the testimony of <hi>Protestants</hi> in fauour of vs, for that their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of it selfe is of small account; but to esteeme it the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their owne consciences induce them, in matters of such weight, to depose against themselues, and against the oath of their owne confederacy. Especially, seeing <hi>M. Whitaker</hi> (with many of his<note place="margin">Vvhitak. de Eccles. cont. 2. q. 5. cap. 10. Tertul. de testimonio animae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersus gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> associates, whome I let passe) contesteth; <hi>It must needes be a stronge and forcible argument, which is taken from the confessiō of the aduerse part.</hi> It must needs moue any reasonable man, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> vpon an occosion not much different affirmeth, to see, <hi>The very enuiers and persecutors of Christian veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty condemned by their owne records, as guilty of errour in themselues, and iniquity against vs.</hi> Which when many of my deare Countrimen shall read and peruse, few I trust will be so wilfully bent, as to persist in their follie, so many festly opened &amp; discouered vnto them. Few will be such enemies to their soules, as to forsake the path, which assuredly leadeth to the house of Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">August. in Psalm. 32.</note> The giuer of light and God of all goodnes open their eyes, and inspire their harts, <hi>That they may recouer themselues, and see, that they haue nothing at all, to oppose against the Truth.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>