<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A SHORT VIEW OF THE LIFE AND VERTVES OF THE AVTHOVR.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113140_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04985</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15134</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113140</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A SHORT VIEW OF THE LIFE AND VERTVES OF THE AVTHOVR.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vvith some religious and diuine meditations. By the Right Reuerend Father in God, Arthure Lake, late Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells. Whereunto is prefixed by way of preface, a short view of the life and vertues of the author</title>
                 <author>Lake, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 80, 91-250, 281-547, 3, 298, 295-322, 187, 53 pages, 1 leaf of plates, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A SHORT VIEW OF THE LIFE AND VERTVES OF THE AVTHOVR.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian Reader:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast here a taste of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that Reuerend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, whom if thou knewest not in his life time, I suppose it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes thee to bee acquainted with now, as with a man rare and eminent for all kind of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, naturall, morall, theologicall, personall, pastorall; and indeed one of the examples of his time. If the lawes of a Preface did permit so much, I suppose it would be a labour worth thy acceptance, to giue thee a iust storie of his life, whereof there is no part but would yeild thee good matter of imitation: But leauing that to the pen of some able Historian, whom God may stirre vp to write a speciall Ʋolume of the Worthies of our age; I hold it my dutie to impart to thee, some few of those obseruable passages concerning him, which retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to my minde vpon the publishing of this worke, not
<pb facs="4"/>doubting but that by the attentiue reading thereof, thou mayest bee as well edified, as by the Worke it selfe.</p>
   <p>First, then be thou pleased to take notice, that this holy man hauing beene noursed vp from his tender age in the exercises of true Pietie, and in the studies of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and exquisite Learning (first, in the famous Schoole of <hi>Winchester,</hi> where he was placed a <hi>child,</hi> and after in <hi>New Colledge in Oxford,</hi> whether he was elected to bee a fellow) was in his riper yeares aduanced to diuers eminent places of dignitie in the Church, not by any ambitious suit or seeking of his own; but by the speciall, and J had almost said; immediate prouidence of Almightie God, who beyond his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation or desire, raised him by insensible degrees to the heighth of Episcopall dignitie: thereby giuing vs one proofe among many, that notwithstanding our great and manifold sinnes he hath not altogether abandoned the care of his Church. For while this man by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination and bent of his owne minde, affected rather the
<note n="f" place="margin">Iudges 9.11.</note>
      <hi>fruitfulnesse of the Vine,</hi> and <hi>the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Oliue,</hi> in a more priuate and retired life then to be a Gouernour ouer the <hi>trees;</hi> as appeared by his willing acceptance of a Fellowship in the Colledge neare <hi>Winchester,</hi> where for a time he liued, and could haue beene contented to haue ended his dayes there in sweet contemplation if he had beene let alone. Yet God, that rules all things, so disposed of him, that one while by the conspiring votes of a numerous Society hee was, euen before he thought of it, recalled to the Wardenship of that
<note n="g" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Marie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Colledge whereof he had beene
<pb facs="4"/>formerly fellow: another while by the speciall grace and fauour of his Maiestie, without any suite of his owne likewise, preferred first to the Prefecture of the Hospitall of <hi>Saint Crosses</hi> neare <hi>Winchester,</hi> then to the Deanerie of the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and lastly to the Bishopricke of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wels,</hi> where he died.</p>
   <p>Jn all which places of honour and employment, first, he forgate not the practice of those vertues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he had made shew in his more priuate life, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the same in his Rotchet, which he had beene in his Schollers gowne; thereby shewing that his vertues were vertues indeed, and that hee vsed them not as Stage-players doe their vizards, only to act a part in, which being done, they pull them off, and cast them into a corner.</p>
   <p>Jnstances of this kind may be, First, his <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> the <hi>Basis,</hi> as it is well called, of all vertue, which being a fruit of true Christian mortification, and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in a low-prising of a mans selfe, and his gifts, he had studied so well in his younger yeares, that in the whole course of his life, afterwards there was no tumor of pride appeared, but as well in his actions as in his speeches, he euer
<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>made himselfe equall with those of the lowest sort.</hi> and that notwithstanding the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations which hee had both from the eminencie of his place, and excellencie of his parts to doe and speake otherwise.</p>
   <p>Secondly, From this, and not from the goodnesse of his nature only, though that were very good, did
<pb facs="5"/>proceed that singular <hi>Affabilitie,</hi> and easinesse of Accesse which he euer retained to all sorts of men, and to those of his owne Coate especially. There was no place nor time almost, except it were his times of deuotion, wherein hee might not bee spoken with by the meanest person; and in his speech so farre as lawfully he might, hee euer studied to giue the partie content; so that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were not in his power to grant euery mans suite, (for who can doe that?) yet I thinke no man can say, hee was euer sleighted or superciliously vsed by him.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> Adde hereunto his rare <hi>Tranquillitie</hi> and <hi>Contentednesse of minde:</hi> which though a man would thinke should agree best with an honourable and plentifull estate, yet experience teacheth, that it is farre otherwise. Accesse of fortunes in most men, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enlargeth then satisfieth desire, and new honours breed new ambitions: besides the verie employment of great men occasioneth many troublesome &amp; disquieting thoughts which a priuate life is naturally free from.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="f"/> But this man hauing first framed his mind to haue true contentment in his more priuate fortunes, retained the same temper in all the alterations of his estate; so that whatsoeuer outwardly befell him either to the better or the worser part, he seemed very little to be affected, surely nothing disquieted therewithall. A strange sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of minde in him; whereof I take it also to haue beene a good argument, that (as I haue often heard him say) so long as he was in perfect health of his bodie, he did neuer
<note n="g" place="margin">Ʋide Arist. de hist, animal. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap <hi>17.</hi> Item <hi>Plutarch.</hi> de Oraeulorum desectu, vbi hoc idem refert de <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>one</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> &amp; <hi>Thrasyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</hi>
      </note> dreame.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>4.</hi> But a speciall cause of that also may haue beene his great <hi>Temperancie</hi> or rather <hi>Austeritie</hi> in diet, which was another vertue that hee retained from the time he first tasted Ʋniuersitie Commons vnto his dying day. For as at the greatest and best furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed meales whereat the condition of his place required his presence, his feeding was commonly vpon one dish, and that none of the daintiest; so it is well knowne, that when he was not hindered by the extraordinarie resort of strangers vnto him, he fasted commonly foure times in the weeke from his supper, and spent that time vntill eight or nine of the clocke at night in fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming some Meditation or other vpon a piece of holy Scripture, the copies of diuers whereof remained in his Studie at his departure; some few of which thou shalt find annexed to this worke for thy vse and benefit.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> As hee was in his diet, so in his apparrell, recreations, and all other outward things belonging to this life a most sparing and temperate vser of Gods blessings, and that as well in his richer as in his meaner fortunes: so that vnlesse it were in the companie of schollers, and in such ingenious and pleasant discourses, as are incident thereto, (wherein he would sometimes expresse much freedome of innocent mirth) a man could not obserue that he tooke much delight in any wordly thing whatsoeuer; an euident argument, that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall part had the predominancy ouer his sensuall, or rather indeed that grace ruled them both; and that the <hi>Man</hi> in him was subordinate to the <hi>Christian.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>With these vertues did this good man come fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht
<pb facs="6"/>to the Episcopall Chaire; and being there hee kept them: like as he did also his firme purpose of single life, which though it be not of it selfe a vertue
<note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> part. <hi>3</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> but a <hi>State;</hi> yet he that could liue in that state, free not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the act, but from all suspition of vncleannesse, as J thinke no man in this age liued more free; had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly attained that excellent gift, which our Sauiour commends, and wisheth them that haue it to make vse of as of a great aduantage, and helpe to godlines, <hi>Matth. 19.12.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now as the varietie of his preferments in the world, did no way hinder him in the practice of these his priuate and personall vertues; (as hath beene said:) so did they yeild him a greater furtherance or opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie at least of acting some others, which J may call publike or <hi>Pastorall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For first, as he had beene alwayes liberall, from the time he had any thing to giue; so vpon the increase of his fortunes hee improued that vertue euen to a kind of <hi>Magnificence.</hi> I am verily perswaded, if hee had attained to that wealth which some of our English Prelates heretofore haue done: hee would haue built Churches and Colledges. But his forwardnesse in this kind, could neuer stay till his purse were full: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee neuer attained to the doing of any pompous worke. But if it were possible to lay together his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie largesse to the poore at his gates, and in the streets; his contributions to pious workes of all sorts vpon his owne and others motions: his Exhibitions to poore Schollers both abroad and in the Ʋniuersitie, of
<pb facs="6"/>all which he kept no <hi>Kalender.</hi> J assure my selfe they would arise to as great a summe as the workes of one of the greatest Benefactours of our time. Besides his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing of the allowance of the poore Brethren of Saint <hi>Crosse,</hi> both in diet and otherwise, (which was worthily continued by his
<note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Sir</hi> Peter Yong.</note> Successour) his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of two Lectures in <hi>New Colledge in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> one for the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue, another for the <hi>Mathematickes:</hi> his leading the way to the setting vp of the great Organ in the Church of <hi>Worcester,</hi> and to the founding of a Librarie there, as also of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Welles,</hi> might well be reckoned as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular instances of his farre extended bountie in this kinde.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> Next his <hi>Magnanimitie</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> appeared well in the gouernment of the Ʋniuersitie, that one yeare wherein he bare the office of <hi>Vicechan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour;</hi> For as they well know that haue had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of that place, the animosity of some spirits there, being like
<note n="k" place="margin">Plutarch, in Alexanaro.</note>
      <hi>Alexanders</hi> horse, generous indeed, and fit for great seruices, but yet fierce and vntractable for the time, requires no lesse then an <hi>Alexander</hi> to curbe them, and to bring them to their due temper and pace. And such an <hi>Alexander</hi> was he. For, notwithstanding all opposition that is vsually made in that kind, hee reuiued much of the ancient Discipline there: and indeed wrought such a sensible reformation vpon the more distempered parts of the Ʋniuersity, that as J haue credibly heard, it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated by those that had the highest care of that place
<pb facs="7"/>to haue continued him longer therein, though a conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Bishop: had not he of his owne minde desirous to attend his greatest charge, shewed himselfe auerse from receiuing any such dispensation.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> Next to his <hi>Magnanimitie,</hi> if not a part of it, I may reckon his <hi>Contempt of wealth,</hi> and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of that manner of getting wealth which is too commonly in vse among them which seeke <q xml:lang="lat">
         <note n="m" place="margin">Horat. Epist. <hi>1</hi>
         </note>—<hi>quocunque modo rem.</hi>
      </q> Had he made that his rule, he might haue beene a rich man. But J dare say, that in all Elections of Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Collations of Orders, and Benefices, Dispositions of Offices, and Grants of Colledge and Church-leases that passed through his hands, as there passed in his time very many, he neuer fouled them with the least touch of a <hi>Gehazi's</hi> reward; which Integrity of his, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his open-handednesse and house-keeping, were the onely causes that he left no greater estate behind him.</p>
   <p>But to come yet more nearely to the discharge of his Episcopall Function. His <hi>Abilitie to teach,</hi> (which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes one of the principall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of a
<note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>3 2.</hi>
      </note> Bishop) as it was very great, so did it neuer appeare more, then after he came to speake <hi>ex cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drâ,</hi> for although the acts of gouernment alone may seeme sufficient to take vp a man in that place: yet he knowing that there is <hi>a double honour</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> allowes to such as doe <hi>not only rule well, but also labour in the Word and Doctrine, 1. Tim. 5.17.</hi> did after the example of Saint <hi>Chrisostome,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great, and other ancient Bishops, whose Homilies wee enioy and read at this day, and neuer ceast after he was a Bishop to adorne the Pulpit with his no lesse frequent and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siduous, then learned and pious labours. Witnesse his ordinary preaching in the <hi>Cathedrall Church of Welles,</hi> his frequent excursions into the Parishes adioyning; and indeed his leauing of no place where he came, if it were a sit time of preaching vnsupplied. Besides all which, his ordinarie Discourses were in one kind or other as good as Lectures to those that heard them: for indeed, he was a man of rare sufficiencie in all parts of Learning; and for any doubts that were proposed to him, whether historicall, textuall, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or controuersall; as his readinesse was singular to take notice of them; so was his dexteritie no lesse happy in resoluing them: So that to conclude for this point, J may say he was a
<note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>1 10.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Salomon</hi> to his houshold Seruants; to the City where he liued an
<note n="r" place="margin">Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>alum Ci <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Oracle:</hi> to any Scholler that resorted to him a
<note n="s" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>liuing librarie:</hi> &amp; to the whole Church such a <hi>Priest</hi> as God himselfe describes by his Prophet <hi>Malachie,</hi> one <hi>whose
<note n="t" place="margin">Ma. <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 7.</hi>
         </note> lips did preserue knowledge: and men did seek the law at his mouth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But it is required of a Bishop, that hee should <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere cibo</hi> too as well as <hi>verbo:</hi> and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> among other things sayes hee should bee
<note n="u" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Tim <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>giuen to hospitalitie.</hi> So was this man in a very extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie and remarkable degree. For to omit his house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping, first at Saint <hi>Crosse,</hi> (where hee made it his studie and profession to refresh the bowels of the poore
<pb facs="8"/>not with drie Pensions as his Predecessors for the most part had done, either for the sauing of trouble or char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or both: but as became the honour of that place, with constant, solide, and substantiall meales:) and then afterward at his Deanerie of <hi>Worcester,</hi> (where he entertained the better sort with that splen, dour, and the meaner with that bountie and munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, that the whole Countrie rings of it to this day:) to omit these, J say; the list of his ordinarie Family which he kept in diet after hee came to the Bishopricke of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Welles</hi> did commonly consist of at least fiftie persons; a great part whereof hee kept not so much for any state or attendance vpon his person, as out of pure charitie in regard of their owne priuate needs. Besides all which, his gates were the daily refectorie of his poore neighbours; and for superuenient stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers be was another
<note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>1</hi> Gen <hi>18 5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Abraham,</hi> a
<note n="i" place="margin">Gen <hi>19.3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Lot,</hi> neuer suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any man of fashion, Schollers especially, that came to him vpon businesse or otherwise to depart emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie away.</p>
   <p>Now in this rankenesse of housekeeping, I know it is a disease that commonly fals vpon great Families, that they grow disorderly and riotous, abusing often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the bountie of a good Lord or Master to their owne hurt and the scandall of others. Which fault lest any man should suspect to haue beene in his house, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but remember another vertue of his (which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commends also in a Bishop) and that is the
<note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>3.4</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>ruling of his house well:</hi> and hauing those that are vnder him <hi>in subiection with all grauitie.</hi> Surely this
<pb facs="8"/>man had so. For notwithstanding his large allowances of all things fit for the entertainment of strangers, you should see no footsteps of riot or excesse in his house: No tipling or carowsing of healths; no casting of the childrens bread vnto dogs; not so much as any hawkes or hounds kept, vnlesse it were
<note n="l" place="margin">Hi sunt catu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> quibus venor regnum Coelorü</note> those wherewith hee hunted after the Kingdome of Heauen. And the reason of all this J take to haue beene first his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, who was indeed a patterne of sobrietie, and of all good conuersation, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wisheth
<note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Tim <hi>4.12.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> to be: then the choice of his seruants wherein he imitated <hi>Dauid, Psal. 101.8.</hi> and lastly his training them vp whom he entertained in true pietie and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For besides his ordinary Chappell houres which he saw duely and by all frequented: hee caused many of his household to assist euery morning at the sixe a clocke Prayers in the Cathedrall Church adioyning: Hee neuer sate downe to his meales, but he had according to the ancient fashion of Bishops a Chapter of the holy Bible, read by one whom he kept for that purpose; and lastly, at the close of the night, he called his whole Family into his ordinary dining roome, and there in his owne person most deuoutly commended them by his prayers vnto Almightie God. Which thing though it be no more then euery Christian housekeeper in his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular charge doth or should doe; yet I account it the more memorable in a man of his place, because the multitude and different qualitie of their attendants seemes ordinarily vnto such a sufficient pretence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that dutie to their Chaplaines, if not to lay it quite aside.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
Now as the Philosopher sayes, that each priuate Family is the modell of a Common-wealth: so may I say that each Christian Family is the modell of a Church: and therefore no wonder if he that was so good at the ordering of the one, proued no lesse excellent in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration of the other. The care of his <hi>Diocesse</hi> as it was of all other his greatest, and that which most tooke him vp; so did it bring forth in him fruits of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary diligence, and such as deserue not to be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the World.</p>
   <p>For first, whereas the foundation of all good order in a Church, is the planting of an able and learned Ministery, which thing appertaines to the care of the Bishop, and hath euer beene accounted a chiefe
<note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> this Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ut I the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> creete, <hi>that thou shouldst or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. Fliers, &amp;c.</hi> Trus <hi>1.5.</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>75.</hi> Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>id facit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d erdinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aciat; Hic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>: ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um</note> branch of his supereminent power: in the discharge hereof he was so carefull and precise, that he neuer conferred holy Orders vpon any person, whom he did not first examine strictly according to the Canons of the Church; neither did hee trust herein any Chaplaine or other Deputie; but himselfe personally performed the office for the satisfaction of his owne conscience, as one that meant to giue an account to God for what hee did. A worthy example doubtlesse, which if it were imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all the rest of that Ʋenerable ranke, neither on the one side would they bee troubled with so many cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the Laitie against the vnsufficiencie of their Clergie: nor on the other would they haue such cause as oftentimes they haue to
<note n="p" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ianies <hi>Bishop of the</hi> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tatians <hi>at</hi> Constant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="5 letters">
            <desc>•••••</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>hamm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>abbatius <hi>a</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Priest, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to hee a turbulent man wished he had laid his hands on the briars rather then on such a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ad</hi> See Secrat. lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>1.20</hi>
      </note> beshrew their owne fingers for ordaining them, who are no sooner put into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, but they become the ring-leaders of faction and
<pb facs="9"/>schisme against that very authoritie which ordained them.</p>
   <p>As he was thus prouident to plant a good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie in his Diocesse, so was hee no lesse carefull to cherish those who were alreadie planted. His care of them all in generall was most tender and fatherlike. The most eminent among them for Pietie and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he did not only vse most familiarly; but studied to draw them nearest to himselfe by prouiding them of Prebends in his Church, wherein it was his want of opportunitie rather then of desire and forwardnesse that he did no more. And lastly, to the weaker sort of them he spared not to giue his aduice and direction vpon all occasions how they might enable themselues for the better discharge of their calling; to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he had both intended and begun a plaine and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar explanation of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> contained in the Catechisme and thirtie nine Articles which he meant to haue communicated to them for their proper vse and instruction; but the interruption of Parliaments and other great affaires toward his later time, and at last his vntimely and much lamented death, as it seemes, put an end to that worthy and religious designe.</p>
   <p>In the exercise of the Discipline of the Church hee carried himselfe so, that by his own practice he wrought a great reuerence thereof, euen in those who were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise not well affected thereunto. For when any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normous offender was censured in his Consistorie, whose punishment and penance was fit should be performed in
<pb facs="10"/>the Cathedrall Church as incestuous persons, notorious Adulterers, notorious Schismatickes, or the like; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe was vsually the Preacher at such times: and this he did often and vpon diuers occasions: and in such his Sermons, (sundry of which thou shalt find in this Worke) did so open the grieuousnesse of those offences, and the authoritie of the censures and discipline of the Church, as for the most part wrought great contrition in the parties punished; and after Sermon before the the whole Congregation himselfe gaue them absolution. All which he performed with that grauitie, learning, and power, as gaue great comfort to all, and bred, no doubt, a generall reuerence and awe of the censures and authoritie of the Church.</p>
   <p>And here by the way I cannot but acknowledge (as himselfe often did) what a helpe he found toward the ordering of his iurisdiction in the assistance of a wise, honest, learned, and discreet
<note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Doctor</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>k.</note> Chancellour, whom as it was his happinesse to find there, so it was his vertue euer to make much of his person, and to vse his counsell as occasion serued. By meanes whereof hee not only was neuer crost, nor contested with in any cause wherein he thought fit to inter-medle, but also for the legall and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly carriage of such things as came before him, no man could euer take iust exception to the formalitie of his proceedings.</p>
   <p>His trienniall Ʋisitations, he alwayes kept in his owne person, and kept them so; that to say no more, he was euer welcome where he came; for indeed his comming was like Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>not
<note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>12.14.</hi>
      </note> burthensome but beneficiall to those he came too: for he sought <hi>not theirs, but them:</hi> yea, as occasion serued, he did <hi>gladly spend, and was spent for them:</hi> though I cannot adde as it is in the same place, that
<note n="t" place="margin">Ibid. v. <hi>15.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the more he loued, the lesse he was loued againe:</hi> for surely it was a great argument of their loue, that they resorted &amp; flockt to him in euery place
<note n="u" place="margin">Senec. de Clem. Lib. <hi>1</hi> Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>tanquam ad salutare &amp; beneficum sidus,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> speakes of good Princes going their Progresses; yea, they brought their children and whole Families to receiue his blessing, and to be confirmed by him; which act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of those that
<note n="x" place="margin">Vide <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym.</hi> aduers. <hi>Luciferianos</hi> vbi tamen affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat hoc factum esse ad honorem sacerdotij potiùs quam ad leg is necessitatem.</note> antiquitie hath euer reserued to the Episcopall power, he performed not in a tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie manner, or as we vse to say, hand ouer head; but with aduised deliberation and choice, admitting only those, whom either by the certificate of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, or the examination of his owne Chaplaines, hee found to be sufficiently instructed in the Principles of Religion, and so by the intention of our Church
<note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>See the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Booke, in the. Order for Confirmation.</hi>
      </note> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the benefit of that sacred action.</p>
   <p>Of his care of the Cleargie in generall I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die spoken: yet it is not to be omitted heere, how in those Ʋisitations of his he particularly exprest it. Wherein his fashion was to examine strictly all those of whose sufficiencie hee any way doubted, as well touching their course of studie, as of their preaching: and as he would restraine those from preaching for a time, whom hee found weake and ignorant: so would hee with all direct them both for the Bookes they should reade, and the method they should vse for the better enabling of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="11"/>to that exercise: and thereof would he take ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as occasion serued: by which meanes he alwayes quickned their industrie, and drew many of them to such a commendable improuement of their talent, that the Countrie was much edified thereby.</p>
   <p>J will adde but one thing more of the cariage of this man in his Episcopall Function; which though it were a thing small in it selfe, yet J know not how, it ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to increase much as well the peoples deuotion to God, as their reuerence to his person. In the <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church of Welles,</hi> whether it were so that himselfe preacht or no, (as indeed very often he did; but though he did not) after the Sermon done, and the Psalme sung as the manner is, himselfe standing vp in his Episcopall seat, gaue the benediction to the people, after the example of the High Priest in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, <hi>Numb. 6.23.</hi> which thing as hee performed like himselfe, that is to say, in a most graue and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like manner; so any man that had but seene with what attentiue and deuout gestures all the people receiued it, what apparant comfort they tooke in it, and how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full euery particular man was not to depart the Church without it; could not but conclude, that there is a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<note n="r" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> ò ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> quod sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erdota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis benedic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>a, non tant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m est simplex ena precatio, sed etiam v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ti pig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium sauo is Dei, &amp; omninò habet quandam v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m ac efficacia clauis soluentis &amp; absoluentis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>. Clau. Script. in verbo Benedicere.</note> vertue in the Prayers and blessings as of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall so of spirituall Parents, which as they are neuer the worse for giuing, so those that haue the relation of sonnes vnto them, are much the better for the receiuing; and it is not for nothing that the Apostle saith:
<note n="s" place="margin">Heb. <hi>7.7.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>The lesser vseth to be bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of the greater.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
By these few things which J haue set downe (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader) thou mayest easily perceiue what an eminent patterne of all vertue as well personall as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storall God hath bestowed on our Church in the person of this one man, whom as oft as J reflect on considering the rare integritie and synceritie of his life, together with his singular pietie and Deuotion, whereof no man that knew him but was a witnesse; me thinkes J may well ballance him with any of those whom the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> boasteth of, and whom she daily canonizeth among the Saints. Neither doe J doubt but those of that Church that either knew him or shall read of these things, are by this time ready to say, <hi>Talis quum fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vtinam noster fuisset.</hi> Yea, who knowes whether they may not by some forged plea goe about to claime him after his death, who liued in a Church opposite to theirs all his life time? For such trickes haue they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised of late vpon some of our most eminent Prelates; and it is no new art; but that which they may haue learned from that old
<note n="m" place="margin">Cacu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> apud Liuium lib. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Italian</hi> Thiefe, who was wont to draw all the faire Oxen he could lay hands on, though it were <hi>obtorto collo, &amp; auersis vestigijs</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his owne Den. But to preuent all such practises in this particular, I hold it not amisse to acquaint thee somewhat more particularly with his resolutions tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching matter of Religion, and how hee stood affected to the controuersies of our times. It is true that of his owne disposition (whether framed so by nature or by grace or both) he was <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, of a most peaceable and milde temper, apter to reconcile differences then to make
<pb facs="12"/>them, and to interprete the sayings euen of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries where they were ambiguous in the better part: in regard whereof if there be yet any hope left of sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp those innumerable rents which Faction hath wrought in the seamelesse coat of Christ, and of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the distracted parts of his Church to some tolerable vnitie, J thinke he had beene such a man as is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found amongst many to bee imployed in that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Howbeit as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> sayes of the wisdome which is from aboue, that it is
<note n="k" place="margin">Iames <hi>3.17.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>first pure,</hi> and then <hi>peaceable:</hi> so J may be bold to say, that this mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of peace came euer in the second place, and that his first care was to maintaine the puritie of Religion, as it is now taught in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> For proofe whereof, though I might thinke it enough to referre thee to these and other of his Sermons, wherein he hath as his matter led him confuted and cut the throat of most of the errours currant at this day in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> yet because it may be excepted that a mans o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are in some sort (as the Lawyers say of ones Will) <hi>ambulatorie</hi> while he liues: and that no man is bound to stand to any Religion but what he dies in: I will rather impart to thee a late profession of his made in his last Will and Testament, which is the most au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentike Record of a mans minde, and such, as <hi>when hee is once dead,
<note n="l" place="margin">Gal <hi>3.15</hi>
         </note> no man disanulleth or addeth thereunto,</hi> as the Apostle speakes. Jn this last Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his, amongst other pious recommendations of his soule to God, he hath these words:</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>I Desire to end my life in that faith, which is now established in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am a member, and haue beene by Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing well nigh thirtie yeares a Preacher: and my soules vnfained desire is, that it may euer flourish, and fructifie in this Kingdome, and in all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Dominions, and from thence be propagated to other Countries which sit in darknesse and in the shadow of death, whether</hi> Jnfidels <hi>or</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Behold here not only a sound but a zealous Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor of the Religion established: and I would to God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man of learning and conscience whether of the one, or other side, would but make the like declaration of himselfe in his last Will: perhaps it would be as good a Legacie as any hee could bequeath to Gods Church. For by it would it appeare what euery man thinkes of the summe of Religion truly and indeed, when all worldly hopes, feares, preiudices, dependances, and engagements being set aside, he hath none but God, and his owne conscience to satisfie: And then I doubt not but as an eminent Prelate of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> said of the <hi>doctrine of Iustification by faith only,</hi> that it was a good <hi>Supper-doctrine,</hi> though not so good to breake fast on: so it would bee acknowledged of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion in generall, that although it be not so plausible and pleasant a religion to liue in, as some other may be, yet it is the only comfortable Religion to die in; as being that which settles a man vpon the true rocke, and giues a sure footing to his faith, when all the
<pb facs="13"/>superstitious deuises of mans braine, doe like sand, faile and moulder away.</p>
   <p>But to returne to this Reuerend Prelate of whom we are speaking, being fallen vpon the mention of his last Will and Testament, it may haply bee expected that I should here relate what Legacies he gaue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the Church, what summes of money he bequeathed <hi>ad pios vsus, &amp;c.</hi> for that is the pompe of Willes in these dayes. But for that J haue said enough alreadie. He that gaue all whilst he liued (euen his very Bookes a great part of which I thinke to the value of foure hundred pounds worth, bee disposed to the Librarie of <hi>New Colledge in Oxford,</hi> by a Deed of Gift di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers yeares before his death, reseruing the vse of them only for his life time:) could not haue much left to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow at his death. Only a name hee hath left behind him, and that more precious then any ointment a name that filleth the Church for the present, with the sweet sauour thereof, and I trust that euen Posteritie also shall be refreshed by it. <hi>For
<note n="r" place="margin">Wisd. <hi>4 1, 2.</hi>
         </note> the memoriall of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> (as he saith) <hi>is immortall; because it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued both with God, and Men. When it is present men take example at it, and when it is gone they desire it: it weareth a Crowne and triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for euer, hauing gotten the victorie, and stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for euerlasting rewards.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As touching the manner of his death, though any man might guesse at it that hath beene acquainted thus farre with the passages of his life, (for seldome doe a mans life and his end varie) yet it will not bee amisse
<pb facs="13"/>to acquaint thee with thus much, that hauing some few houres before his departure made a zealous and deuout confession both of his faith and sinnes, to the Bishop of <hi>Elie</hi> there present, from whom also he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued absolution according to the order of our Church: and being assisted to the last gaspe with the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heauenly prayers of that diuine Prelate; after he had taken particular leaue of all about him, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them respectiuely both his counsell and benediction: he speedily yeilded vp his soule to God.</p>
   <p>There passed not many moneths before that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Bishop, whom J last mentioned, followed him to his graue: with whom as he had liued many yeares in a most entire league of friendship, not vnlike that which Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> describes to haue beene betwixt himselfe and Saint <hi>Basil (Lib. 1. de Sacerdotio)</hi> so J doubt not but they are now vnited and incorporated together in a farre more firme and vndiuided societie, euen that of <hi>the first-borne which are written in Heauen, (Heb. 12.23.)</hi> and as they were heere <hi>gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num sidus,</hi> a paire of Lights of our Church, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable euen to those Primitiue ones, whose lustre and influence remaines with this day: so they haue by this time receiued the reward of such as <hi>turne many to righteousnesse,</hi> euen to be <hi>Stars in the Firmament for euer and euer, Dan. 12.3.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now although an
<note n="k" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note> Epitaph be a good mans due after his departure, J should haue thought it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse to set any vpon him, who as yet liues so freshly in the mouthes and hearts of all that knew him, did I not
<pb facs="14"/>find himselfe had meditated somewhat that way in his life time, not for the perpetuating of his Name, for he doth not so much as name himselfe in it; but only for the expressing of his firme hope in the Resurrection, and his charitable desire of their good that should sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue him: for whose sake he wrote this, and desired it should be grauen only vpon a stone, where he should lie without any further cost or ambition.</p>
   <q>
      <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
         <body>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <head>Viator consiste, paucis te volo; Me Vide.</head>
               <l>EXuviae hîc reponuntur hominis, sed Christiani</l>
               <l>Quibus nihil vilius propter peceatum hominis;</l>
               <l>Nihil pretiosius propter spem Christiani.</l>
               <l>Non eas deseruit anima, sed hîc deposuit.</l>
               <l>Custos bonae fidei Spiritus Sanctus,</l>
               <l>Qui cauet ne quis in vacuum veniat</l>
               <l>Dum legatione pro ijs apud Redemptorem</l>
               <l>Defungitur Anima: cui reduci cum Christo</l>
               <l>Eas reddet gloriosas gloriosè induendas,</l>
               <l>Et cum beatâ beandas in aeternum.</l>
               <l>Libentèr mortalis sum, qui sim futurus immortalis.</l>
               <l>Ne tantuli in me contemplando te poeniteat</l>
               <l>Laboris, non dimittêris sine praemio,</l>
               <l>Voueo haec historia Mei, prophetia sit Tui.</l>
               <closer>Perge.</closer>
            </div>
         </body>
      </floatingText>
   </q>
   <p>Jf all this be not enough to continue the memorie of so worthy a Prelate; behold another Monument of his owne making too. A Monument of his wit shall I say, and of his Learning? or rather of his Pietie and Deuotion? Surely, if thou take the paines to reade
<pb facs="14"/>attentiuely the Sermons here published to thy view, thou shalt find in them a more then ordinarie expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both. For howsoeuer they are not set forth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordinary fashion of these times, wherein ornaments of speech, varietie of illustrations, allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, allusions, and the like, are affected and vsed euen to an excesse (you must not expect too much of them, from a man that neuer tooke more time for the preui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any sermon then some part of the weeke prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that day whereon he was to preach; and then also betooke not himselfe to the helpe of his pen, but out of his strength of memorie, and naturall readinesse of speech, in both which he excelled, deliuered those things which he had first exactly digested in his mind, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dictated to his <hi>Amanuensis</hi> in such sort as they are here published:) yet J dare be bold to say, that to an attentiue, and iudicious Reader they will appeare to containe not only matter of excellent obseruation for the increase of knowledge and pietie in our Christian profession: but also an exact <hi>Idea</hi> of the true forme of a Sermon, so farre as concernes the essentiall parts of of it composed according to those rules of art which all men acknowledge to be of most vse in <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Oratorie. For whereas speech is fitly compared by the ancients to a picture,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Plutarch.</hi> de audi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ndis poeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; alibi.</note> in the framing whereof the chiefe thing that requires the Artisans skill, is to draw his lines in their iust number and proportion, so as may expresse all the parts of the thing described, and the postures of them: which when it is done, it is no hard matter to adde the colours thereunto: it followes
<pb facs="15"/>that the principall point of art likewise in making of a Speech or Sermon is the delineation of the parts of it, and the apt connecting of them together, or opposing them one to the other: whereupon the seuerall exorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them with words and sentences, does either
<note n="k" place="margin">Verba{que} prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisam rem non muita sequetur. Horat de art. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> of it selfe follow or is without any great difficultie put too. Now in that was our Author alwayes so elaborate and exact that J thinke there was no point or circumstance in any Text that euer he handled, so closely concealed, which he did not both fetch out, and propose, and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, in such order and method, as might best giue illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration to the whole. Wherein what singular vse he made both of his Logicke, and skill in the Tongues, which are the two Spectacles, that I may not say eyes, that enable a man to looke exactly and distinctly into a Text: I thinke there is no man of iudgement that doth not easily discouer. In this respect then (as I said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) he hath left vnto yonger men a patterne of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: And for the rest, though his fashion were not to lay on much colour: yet that which he did lay on will appeare to him that markes it, to be very proper. His illustrations so naturall, his allegations so preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, his words where the <hi>emphasis</hi> and weight of the sentence lies, so choice and significant; that if hee had vttered <hi>plura,</hi> farre more in lines, hee could hardly haue said <hi>plus,</hi> more in substance and effect to any point that he hath handled.</p>
   <p>But J had rather thou shouldest discouer these things (Christian Reader) by thy owne iudgement and obseruation, then by my aduertisement: therefore J
<pb facs="15"/>wil detaine thee no longer at this time from the reading of so vsefull and precious a worke. Only thus much J will promise thee for thine encouragement before thou begin; that if thou take the paines to goe thorough with attention, these or other Sermons of this Authour, that are genuine (and I hope no other will be published) First, thou shalt gaine thereby an exact knowledge of the meaning of the Text he handles, and of euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular word and phrase in it: Secondly, thou shalt meet with as great varietie of choice obseruations both theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall and morall, aptly deduced, and methodically laid downe, as thou art like to find any where in so few leaues againe; lastly, if thou bee indued (as J hope thou art) with the same spirit of grace and regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Author was, thou shalt find thine affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons kinaled and stirred vp thereby to a reall practice of Pietie and good Workes, more then by a great many more flourishing Discourses, then these at first sight seeme to be. And these things when thou hast found by thine owne experience: J doubt not but thou wilt bee moued together with me and all others that haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued beneht by the godly example and pious labours of this holy, and learned man, to glorifie that great God and Father of Lights, who out of his abundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hath done, and doth daily raise such excellent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments as he was, for the aduancement of his owne glorie in the propagation of his Gospel, and aedification of his Church.</p>
   <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>