<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Churches Lamen∣tation, by reason of her sorrow.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113555_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12309</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6163.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113555</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Churches Lamen∣tation, by reason of her sorrow.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A memento for Christians : In some short meditations on the third verse of the thirteenth chapter of the Epistle vnto the Hebrewes [...] Published by the author, for the comfort of all those that mourne in Sion, and very fit to be seene in the hands of all men in these troublesome dayes of the Churches sorrow</title>
                 <author>Doolittle, E.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clifton, Fulke</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 85, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="lamentation">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Churches Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, by reason of her sorrow.</head>
   <q>BEhold O Lord, for I am in distresse, <note place="margin">Lam. 1. 20</note> my bowels are troubled, my heart is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within me: abroad the sword bereaueth, at home there is death.</q>
   <q>They haue heard that I sigh; there is <note place="margin">Verse 21.</note> none to comfort me: All mine enemies haue heard of my trouble; they are glad that thou hast done it.</q>
   <q>Heare I pray you all people, and behold <note place="margin">Verse 28.</note> my sorrow: my louers and my young men, are gone into captiuitie.</q>
   <q>I called for my louers, but they deceiued <note place="margin">Verse 19.</note> me; my Priests and mine Elders gaue vp the ghost in the Citie, while they sought their meate to relieue their soules.</q>
   <q>
      <pb facs="4"/>For these things I weepe; mine eye, mine <note place="margin">Verse 16.</note> eye runneth downe with water, because the Comforter that should relieue my soule is farre from me; my children are desolate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the enemy preuailed.</q>
   <q>Sion spreadeth forth her hands, and there <note place="margin">Vers. 17.</note> is none to comfort her; the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded concerning <hi>Iacob,</hi> that his aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries should be round about him; Ierusalem is as a menstruous woman among them.</q>
   <q>Is this nothing to you all yee that passe by? <note place="margin">Vers. 12.</note> Behold and see, if there be any sorrow like to my sorrow, which is done vnto mee, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>