<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull, in all vertues accomplisht, and his especiall Friend M. William Willoughby of Grayes Inne Gentleman.</title>
           <author>A., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113628_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08551</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113628</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull, in all vertues accomplisht, and his especiall Friend M. William Willoughby of Grayes Inne Gentleman.</title>
                 <author>A., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seuenth booke of the Myrrour of knighthood : Being the second of the third part. Englished out of the Spanish language</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>316 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull, in all vertues accomplisht, and his <hi>especiall Friend M.</hi> William Willoughby <hi>of Grayes Inne Gentleman.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>IT is recorded in holy writ (most worthy Sir) how that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Emperor &amp; Cōmander of <hi>127</hi> Prouinces, being by deserts of a strāger subiect, bound to deeds of gratitude, the which as thē, hauing no occasion to expresse, &amp; fearing to drowne them in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion, caused it to be enrolled in the Annales of his acts, that the reading thereof might after remember him, how those merits being by him left vnrecompenced, he still ought to guerdon. So fell it out that turning ouer the Chronicles of his age, and calling to memorie his debt, he did with magnifike honor sufficiently discharge it. This consideration many waies well pondered, whether, ô whether may I fly for refuge? For not content to haue transgrest against the sacred vertue of thankefulnes, due for your benefits in number infinite, I haue (but vnwilling) sinned against your loue, and wronged your kindnes, by violating my willing promise made to your request (yet due by dutie) to visite you this last vacation in the countrey: which fault I greatly feare hath, (I must needs say) deseruedly incurred your disfauour. But as the incensed heauens are by true contritiō and vnfained penitence appeased of their wrath: So doe I not doubt but my lawfull excuse, &amp; this cause thereof shall purchase an exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuatiō of your displeasure, &amp; my offēce, which first of all by confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siō, I hope wilbe lessened, &amp; thē your pardon washing away my sinne, in signe of a thankefull debtor for all your bounties, I sacrifize my selfe &amp; this motiue of my transgression on the Altar of your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, where the fier of my penitent hart, consuming the oblation, it may cleare my passage to your reconciled grace from all obsticles of your anger. I must of force confesse it is an idle toy, hacht and brought forth at idle times, and therefore neither worthy your coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, nor yet to be interposed among the exercises of your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cāt howers: yet if at any you will vouchsafe to looke thereon, thinke that the <hi>Persian Monarch,</hi> did not refuse to drink out of a sheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds greasie bottle, &amp; therwithall waighing the loue &amp; hart of the presenter, I shall hope your fauour, &amp; no more feare to be reiected from your grace.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Euermore deuoted to your seruice.</hi> L. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>