<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Bentham, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113626_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08552</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1887</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113626</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Bentham, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian conflict : a treatise, shewing the difficulties and duties of this conflict, with the armour, and speciall graces to be exercised by Christian souldiers. Particularly applied to magistrates, ministers, husbands, wives, parents, children, masters, servants. The case of vsury and depopulation, and the errours of antinomists occasionally also discussed. Preached in the lecture of Kettering in the county of Northampton, and with some enlargement published by Ioseph Bentham, rector of the Church of Broughton in the same county</title>
                 <author>Bentham, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 364, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, good men have a notable hap and happinesse to be borne in one age ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than another: We in this, wherein wee enjoy extraordinary plenty of profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table excellent meanes of knowledge, by Pen and Preaching, in Presse and Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit: Yea so many and such, that I had not any inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to adventure in this kinde, untill by my betters encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement I published a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reatise of the <hi>Societie of Saints,</hi> the approbation of which with judicious men, who perused the same, hath occasioned and animated me to second the same with this of the <hi>Christian Conflict.</hi> In which had I medled with no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, or onely meane men, I could not but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect rash and uncharitable censurers, since vertuous men (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though men studious of vertue) can scarce find one hand to further them in working, yet commonly have often a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of evill tongues to speake against their honest doings: much more addressing my selfe not onely against Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists a lawlesse and licentious kind of evill speakers, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so against usurers and depopu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atours the devourers of our common-wealth, and other such like disorderly dealers, which swarme in and swallow up our common weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke to escape the scourge of tongues. But, the best is, I am as little ambitious of such mens good word as guilty of their bad: and I had rather be dispraised for true speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than honoured for lying (although I know the most had
<pb facs="7"/> rather be comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nded with lies, than reproved with truth) being perswaded that he in heart hath no true sincerity, which keeps his mouth shut to reprove vice. Many of these I encounter with have faire and plausible pretences, but by that meanes they are the more pernicious. A fowle scarre may be covered with a faire cloth, <note n="*" place="margin">Dum gravior sit &amp; magis noxia impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitas: benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is obumbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta velamine. <hi>Amb. Hexam. Lib. 5. Cap. 8.</hi>
      </note> and masked meaning doth more harme than bare-fac'd errour. I know it is a hard matter to make them see any thing, which have resolved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand to close their eyes: that none are so blind as they who will not see: that no paradox is so strange but some Philosopher will undertake to defend it: no vice so foule, but it will have some refuge of apologie to maintaine it for good: yet will I speake the truth, not caring if they who brow-beat authority and antiquity, backbite me. Perhaps some will disparage me to discredit the booke: if so, I shall not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell; since as vertue, riches, honour, &amp;c. so putting of books to presse, is but a br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd to light envy to the world, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice leaves nothing unsearched that may nourish the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime of the humour. For my selfe, as I am a man, so have I written it for men, and as a man I may have erred: For, there is not so perfect a painter, but another will presume to amend his worke: neither is any man so just or cleare of judgement, that doth never shew himselfe fraile; especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in matters which concerne his owne interest. But this is my comfort, it is better to erre ignorantly out of a well-dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed charity, than peremptorily to affirme any thing out of an ungrounded obstinacy. And of thee let me intreat this cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie, not to impute the Printers faults unto me, nor to let an oversight or slip in me, if any such thou espiest, prejudice the matter. A good letter should be nothing lesse esteemed because written with an evill pen, neither doth an angell of gold cease so to be, wanting a graine, which is allowed to
<pb facs="8"/> make it currant. For my part (in this unhappy age which overfloweth with numbers of malignant spirits) I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that the best course is (and so I do endeavour) through the grace and goodnesse of God, to direct our course in such sort, as evill-minded men may rather shew their will through malice, than with just cause by desert say evill, or deface by speech or writing. In this booke I have observed the same method and order as in my former, with Tables, Chapters, and bare Quotations of Scriptures, without words generally, that it might not be too voluminous: and upon the advise of a godly, learned and judicious Divine who perused my copie, I have left out the words of alledged Authours, taking onely the meaning, and referring them to the places that please to examine them, to keepe downe the bulk and bignesse of the booke. And thus good Christian Reader, hoping thou wilt take in good part that which with no little paines I have penned for publike good. I commend thee to God and the Word of his grace, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in him who is the LORD of all. IOSEPH BENTHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>