<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir HENRY YELVERTON Knight, His Maiesties Atturney Generall, all happinesse of this life, and the next.</title>
           <author>C., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113832_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05995</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1635</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir HENRY YELVERTON Knight, His Maiesties Atturney Generall, all happinesse of this life, and the next.</title>
                 <author>C., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie vpon the first chapter of the epistle of Saint Paul, written to the Ephesians : Wherein, besides the text fruitfully explained: some principall controuersies about predestination are handled, and diuers arguments of Arminius are examined. By Mr. Paul Bayne, sometimes preacher of Gods word at Saint Andrevves in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Bartlet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 409, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir HENRY YELVERTON Knight, His <hi>Maiesties Atturney Generall, all happinesse</hi> of this life, and the next.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost respected Sir, I need not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie you bow singular is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of greatnesse it is, to haue goodnesse linked with it; whether it be that goodnes which is conuersant in doing kinde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to the liuing, or to the dead: Nay surely, that good which is stretched forth to the liuing, in some regards is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour of the two, as which may eyther in heart or deed be recompenced; but that which is performed toward the deceased, can not at all by him that is <hi>not,</hi> be known; much lesse can it be any way requited: Onely it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines as an high commendation to the liuing, that they still exercise acts of Loue and goodnesse toward such as are departed this present life. This I speake, Right worshipfull Sir, to prouoke you at this time to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe the gracious aspect of your countenance, and your
<pb facs="3"/> worthy Patronage to this ensuing Commentary of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned man, now at rest in the Lord. He was once of the same Colledge where your Worship began to lay the foundation of your owne studies; and was not vnknown to your selfe: In which regards I haue made the bolder with you, in becomming an humble and earnest suiter, that you would be pleased of your goodnes to suffer this Orphane-Treatise to repose it selfe vnder your wings; whereof, if it shall please you, Worthy Sir, (as your many and great affaires will permit,) to reade some passage or place, I doubt not but you shall meet with matters, which at once may both profit and delight you. The Author whilest hee liued, had an indisposition and antipathy to the Presse; but since his death, diuers learned men haue pressed mee, not to conceale some writings of his, which came to my hands; yea, they haue challenged mee, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to the Church and common good, touching the publication of this part especially: Accept therefore, I pray you, Right Worshipfull Sir, my tendred duty of Dedicating this worke to your name; which, if it shall please you to doe, I shall rest exceedingly bounden to pray for the continuance and increase of all prosperity to you, from the God who is neuer wanting to honour those who honour him.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships ready bounden to all good seruices, <hi>E. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>