<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The preface to the gentle reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1134_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22818</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1134</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The preface to the gentle reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brief treatyse : settynge forth diuers truthes necessary both to be beleued of chrysten people, [and] kepte also, whiche are not expressed in the Scripture but left to [the] church by the apostles traditio [n] . Made by Rychard Smyth doctour of diuinite, [and] reader of it i [sic] Oxford. Cu [m] priuilegio ad imprimendu [m] solu [m]</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Petyt, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>340 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div rend="blackletterType" type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The preface to the gentle reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr sauyoure Iesus Chryst, good chrystē reader, came in to this wretched &amp; my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable worlde, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge our nature on hym in the wombe of the moost blessed, and gloryous virgyn Mary his mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / to beare wytnesse vnto the truth, as he affyrmed, saynge to Pylate. <hi>Ego in hoc natus sū, et ad</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iohan. 19.</note>
      <hi>hoc veni in mundû, vt testimoniū perhibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> veritati.</hi> That is to saye I am borne therfore, &amp; I came therfore in to the worlde, that I maye beare wytnesse vnto the truthe. Seynge therfore that chryste the truth it selfe came to testyfye and defende the truthe, suffering for it deth most sharpe &amp; shamefull, to the ende that we
<pb facs="4"/> myght knowe the truth, and the truth at the length myght dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from all errour, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serye,<note place="margin">Iohan. 9.</note> as he him self doth say, Is it not mete that we folowe his example therin, and defende the truth to the vttermost of our po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer, not fearyng to dye therfore Yf nede shal require, as our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure hath already done? For the dyscyple is not aboue his<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0.</note> mayster, nor the seruante grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his lorde. If we be the folowers of Chryst, we shall be partakers of glorye and honor with hym, whiche he obtayned<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> throughe death and passyon su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferynge (as saynte Paule wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth)<note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> and vpon the other syde yf we deny him, beyng the truth (whiche we shall do not defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge the truth) he wyll deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vs before his father As he seyth<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note>
      <pb facs="4"/> hym selfe. Lactancius a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry olde wryter sayde to Tullye the great Oratour. <hi>Quid profuit</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 2. de Orig. erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. ca. 3.</note>
      <hi>vidisse te veritatē, quâ nec defensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus esses, nec secutur{us}?</hi> What hath it profyted the: sayth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to haue sene or perceyued the truth / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che neyther thou shuldest defēde nother folowe? <hi>Socratis carce tē times ideo{que} patrociniū veritatis nô audes suscipere. At mortē vt sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens contēnere debuisti.</hi> That is to say. Thou doest feare Socra tes presō, and therfore thou da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest not take on the, the defence of the truth But thou oughtest to haue dispysed deth, as a wyse man. Are not, good christen rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, many men nowe among vs chrysten people, in lyke dreade? Do not we greatlye feare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the truth, lest we shuld su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffre for it ympresonynge, yea y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <pb facs="5"/> lesse is, lest we shulde eyther lose therby our good{is} &amp; promotions or els not come vnto theym?</p>
   <p>We do forgette the greate and dreadefull thretnynges of God set furth in scrypture agaynste them, that wyl not teach, preach maynteyne and defende y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth Sayed not the holye prophete Esaye, <hi>Ve mihi, quia taecui.</hi> Woo<note place="margin">Cap. 6.</note> to me, bycause I kept sylence, &amp; dyd not boldly reproue the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked kynge Ozias. Howe manye men now feare this gods curse. Wo to you, that say yll is good and good is yll, puttyng darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse<note place="margin">Cap. 6.</note> lyght, and light darkenes, puttynge bytter in to swete, and swete in to bytter. Do we not so, I pray the, good chrysten reader, as ofte as we do hyde &amp; dyssemble the truthe for feare or any other carnal affeccyon / and
<pb facs="5"/> set it not forth to the edifyenge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people. God also curseth thē<note place="margin">Hiere, 23.</note> by the mouthe of his Prophete Hieremy sayenge. <hi>Vae pastorib{us} qui dispergunt, et la cerant gregem pascuae meae.</hi> That is to say. Wo be to the shepeherdes, which do scatter abrode, &amp; rente the flocke of my pasture. This curse tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not onely yll p̄achers, whi do fede theyr flocke w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> erroneus doctrine, but also al other that do suffre heresyes to be taughte the people, &amp; do not agayne saye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> teachers of thē, neither defend y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth according to that grace, whyche God hath gyuen them. Whom the prophete Ezechiell in the personne of god thus cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, terribly sayng. <hi>Ve pastorib{us}</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. 34.</note>
      <hi>Israel, qui pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ebant seme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ipsos.</hi> Wo be to the shepeherdes of Is<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael,<note place="margin">Beware yt that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> sent from your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ures or beyng ther preach not the worde of god to the flocke.</note> which did fede them selues
<pb facs="6"/> It foloweth. Dothe the shepe fede the shepeherdes? Ye haue eaten the milke and are clothed wyth the wolle, &amp; ye haue kylled y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, whyche was fatte, but ye haue not fedde my flocke. Ye haue not made strong that which was weake &amp; ye haue not healed the sicke. Ye haue not bounde toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> brokē, niether brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which wādered away. Ye sought not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which was lost, or peryshed. Itē my shepe are scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abrode, or dyspersed, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they had no shepeherde, &amp; they are deuoured, of all beastes of the felde. Hitherto god by his prophete hath cursed all yll pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturs, or shepeherdes, whyche do not fede theyr flocke w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the fode of gods holy worde, accordynge to theyr bounden duetye, but do fede them selues, spendynge the
<pb facs="6"/> goodes of theyr promotions w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> out preachynge to the people, which are due only as a stypend to thē that do preach gods word or ministre hys sacramentes as it appereth not only here in this place of the prophete, but also in this Pauls saynge. Who war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> with his owne stipend or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pō his owne wages? Who doth plant a vyne, and eateth not of the frute? Who fedeth a flocke, &amp; eateth not of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> flockes mylke? Ment not S. Paule here, that lyke as the man of warre ought to lyue by hys wages, yf he do go to warre, or els not, and as he that planteth a vyne shulde eate of the frutes of it, or els he ought not to eate of them. Final<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">many now lyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of the tē<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hes and churches goodes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst this doctrine. of saynt Paule.</note> and as the herdman or shepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde, whyche fedeth the flocke ought to eate of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flockes milke
<pb facs="7"/> or els not, euen so he that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and teacheth the worde of god warring manly agaynst the enemyes of the truth, plantyng the vyneyarde of Chryste the church, and fedynge the lambes and shepe of god the christē peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, oughte to lyue wyth, and by hys the tenthes and other the reuenues and frutes of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, benefice, or byshoprich, whyche thynge yf he do not, let hym beware lest he take y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> frutes vniustly to his dampnation, as which are due onely to him y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth ī preachīg, teaching, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramētes ministryng and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the people, prouydynge for them all thynges necessarye for theyr soules helth, defēdinge them frō the wolfes deuouring, and geuyng them a good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of vertuous liuing as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
<pb facs="7"/> in Iohns gospell, &amp; the fyrst of saynt Peters epistles.<note place="margin">Io. 21. 1. Pe. 5.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Saynt Paule preached the gos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel frely, and toke not so moche as meate and drinke of certeyne people to whō he preached, and yet he sayde. Wo to me yf I<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> preach not the gospel, but many of vs preestes, and byshoppes, cleane contrarylye to that hys godly example, do lyue meryly vpon the tenthes and other the goodes due to preachers &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for theyr wages, stypende, &amp; sustentation, nother preaching nor teaching, and yet we thynke no thyng vpon that woo, whych god so often tymes threteneth to them, that do not theyr duety.</p>
   <p>Cometh not by thys meanes. I beseche the, good reader, a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull decay vnto Christes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, fayth, and vertuous ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng?
<pb facs="8"/> Are not the wolfes bolde then to entre in to the flocke of shepe to disperse theym / to take some of them, and to deuour thē when the shepeherd is eyther ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sent from thē, as many nowe are other to get mo {pro}motyōs or els to spare theyr purses, or els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge present, barketh nothynge at all agaynst thē? Why do we not open our eies closed w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tousnesse, &amp; other carnall affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions / &amp; se how moch hurt riseth<note place="margin">Ezec. 19. 34</note> vpō this defaulte, &amp; remembre that the blood of all the shepe / which do peryshe through oure neglygence, shall be required of vs. For we shal make a rekenīg to god for euerye soule cōmitted to vs, as Paule saieth to the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> where he wryteth thus. <hi>Obedite praepositis vestris, et lubia cete eis Ipsi enim pervigilant quasi
<pb facs="8"/> rationē {pro} aīabus vestris reddituri.</hi> That is in englishe. Obey your ouerseers &amp; be ye obedyēt to thē for they watch for you as though they shulde gyue an accōpte for your soules. Vpō the which text the greate clerke saynt Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome thus wryteth dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dfullye to withdrawe mens ambitions mindes through feare of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger / ī the which curates are, frō the desyre of {pro}motions, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge charge of mennes soules <hi>Quid dicamus infaelicibus illis, et miseris, qui semetipsos ad alios re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendos precipitant, et se in tantorū supplieiorum abyssum iactant?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Oīm quos regis, mulierū puerorū at{que} virorū, tu rationē redditur{us} es, tâto igni tuū subiicis caput. Miror si potest saluari aliqu is rectorum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That is to saye. What may we say vnto those vnhappy &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb facs="9"/> men, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> do throw thē selues hedlyng to rule other: &amp; do caste thē selues in to the botōles dep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of so great ponyshementes? Thou shalt make an accōptefor all womē, chyldren, &amp; men / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thou dost gouerne: thou put teste thy head vnder so greate a fyer. I merueyle yf anye of the rulers can be saued. Hyt herto. s. Chrysostome, whose word{is} may &amp; ought also to feare euery man frō the desyre of any promotiōs wherby he shulde be charged w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the cure of soules. Are not they worse thē pyuyshe, &amp; blynded w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ambition, whiche do not onelye couet bysshopriches, / benefyces &amp; other lyke {pro}motions / byndīg thē selues to make aunswere for all theyr soules, that be in theyr cure, but also do make frendes: for the obtaynyng of thē, go to
<pb facs="9"/> seruyce, &amp; giue money very larg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for thē: For benefices are now cōmon marchādise, &amp; sold to thē that wyl giue most for thē: with oute all regarde, &amp; respecte had vnto the learnyng, &amp; honesty of the preest, to whom they are sold Wherby aryseth greate decaye in christ{is} fayth, &amp; moch leudnes amōge the people, throughe the ignorance of such persōs, &amp; vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars. For whē the blynd leadeth the blynde: both do fall in to the den as chryst sayeth. Let the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons &amp; gyuers of suche benefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> beware in tyme, remēbrynge that they shall make an accōpte to god for the soules, whiche do perish by theyr {pro}motīge the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, &amp; vnmete persons vnto theyr benefices, accordīg to this saynge of saynt Panl. Not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye<note place="margin">Ro. 1.</note> they that do suche thynges,
<pb facs="10"/> are worthy of deth, but they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, whyche do consent to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. In the beginnyng of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes church men were promoted, that were apte to rule the people &amp; not the vnworthye for money, as they now cōmenly be. Tertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyan, whyche was wythin. CC. yeres after Christes byrth thus<note place="margin">In apolog. aduersus gentes. Religioni ac doctrine opprobriū nascitur {quod} sacerdocia vel ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>{us} et gr̄a, {quam} meritorū iudicio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feruntur Greg Nazā in apoligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne de spie. sancto.</note> wryteth. <hi>President probati qui{que} seniores, vel presbyteri, honorem istum non precio, sed testimonio adepti.</hi> That is to say, euery pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued or tryed elder, or preest doth rule, or is in auctoritie, whyche haue gotten that honour or dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie not wyth money, but by witnesse borne of theyr learning and vertue. Oure lord wolde it were so now, for then honesty, &amp; learnyng shulde moch more flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rysh, then now they do, &amp; therby heresies, and errours shuld ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="10"/> lytle preuayle, where nowe they preuayle greatlye thorowe the ignoraunce of curates.</p>
   <p>Let therfore sellers of benefices marke what the holy martyr S Cypryan, sayeth of suche mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunte men by these wordes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Spiritus sanctus Giezi mercenarium lepra condemnat, et Iero boam vendentem sacerdocia cum apostatis locat.</hi> Whyche is thus muche to saye in englyshe. The holye ghost condempneth <hi>Giezi</hi> wyth a lepry whych was an hyred ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte made marchandyse ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king money for his maisters cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of Naamās dysease, and placeth Ieroboam, sellynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenefices,<note place="margin">Sellers of benefices are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postatayes</note> wyth them, that do forsake Christes religion. Lo here saynt Cypryan sayeth, that the holy gooste setteth sellers of benefices wyth them that do for
<pb facs="11"/> sake Christes religion, whyche thynge declareth manifestlye howe great synne it is to sell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, though men nowe these dayes do esteme and iudge it no faute at all, such is theyr blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therein, rysyng of couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. What vengiaūce god hath taken vpon them that came to theyr promotions by any vnle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful meanes. It apeareth by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hystoryes. Of the whyche I wyll allege a fewe to withdrawe men from the bying and sellyng of spirituall dignities. Fyrst we reade in the seconde of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabeis,<note place="margin">Cap. 7.</note> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> one Alchim{us} by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius thrust into the office of the high preest lyued wōderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yll, as all do for the greatest numbre whych are promoted by money, and he was stryken with the palsey, and made dome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb facs="11"/> w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out any testament. Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son also boughte a benefice of Antiochus, but he escaped not<note place="margin">2. Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 2. Mach. 4.</note> vnpunyshed therfore, for he wā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng and fleyng from citie to citie departed this lyfe wythout lamentation of the people, and was cast away wyth out burial. Menelaus supplāted Iason bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng<note place="margin">2. Mach. 5.</note> hys benefice of Antiochus, but he payed dearelye for it, whē he was cast do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ne headling frō the toppe of a tower, and turned into asshes. Antiochus whyche<note place="margin">2. Mach. 13</note> solde the preests benefice to Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Menelaus escaped not clere, as the whych rotted beyng alyue, and hys fleshe was ful of vermyne or wormes. Wherfore let both the biers and the sellers also of benefices beware of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vēgeaunce, which thus gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uously hath punyshed these men
<pb facs="12"/> for oure ensample, and that we shulde be assured nothyng dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, but yf we lyke offende, we shal suffre lyke punyshmente in thys lyfe, and moche more in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, excepte we repente, and amend in due seasō. To be short the sellers of benefices vnto the vnlearned or yl lyuyng preestes for money do sinne deadly by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte of person, whyche is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddē<note place="margin">Jacob. 2.</note> in sūdry places of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but specially in saynte Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seconde chapter. I speake here nothyng at all of them that do gyue theyr benefices, and dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nityes vnto theyr seruauntes, chaplyns, kynsfolke, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being vnapte to preach and teach goddes worde vnto theyr flocke, leauyug them vnpromo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whyche both for theyr ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and learnyng also are very
<pb facs="12"/> worthy to be preferred therunto &amp; shulde do therein moche good where the other do verye lytle, yea some tymes muche hurte.</p>
   <p>Is not thys <hi>acceptio vel respect{us} personatum</hi> the regarde of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons agaynst gods lawe? Thys vice dothe almooste as moche harme in Christes churche, and is nygh as yll, as is the sellyng of spirituall promotions. I let passe at this tyme, theyr abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable couetousnes that do giue their benefices vnto blocke heades, not mete for theyr lytle discretion, and lesse learnyng to any suche thynge, and do take them selues a parte and portion of the frutes belongyng to such promotions. These men are bounde to make restitution of that goodes, whyche they haue inioyed agaynste goddes lawe,
<pb facs="13"/> whyche declarethe that the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of benefices are dew onely to them that do preach, &amp; teache<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> the scripture, rulynge, &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng wel the people to them cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. For oure Lorde hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined (sayth Paule.) That they lyue by the aulter, that do serue it, and lyue of the gospell, which do preache the gospell. Therfore<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Cor 9.</note> he that neyther serueth the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor prcacheth the gospel can not iustlye lyue by the tenthes &amp; other the reuenues and frutes perteynynge to the ministers of the aulter, and the gospell. Let me not haue a iust occasiō to say vnto you, that hath or do offend in this poynte, as Christe sayed vnto the Iewes. <hi>Si veritatem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iohan. 9.</note>
      <hi>quare non creditis mihi?</hi> If I saye the truth, why do ye not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue me? He that ys of god hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="13"/> the wordes of god, therfore you do not heare, bycause ye are not of God. I am well assured that to no good mā I shal be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened an enemy, tellīg the truth<note place="margin">Gala. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> as Paule was estemed of the Galathyans bycause he taught them the truth. Nowe to finysh thys preface, I most humbly be sech euery patron, and gyuer of any benefice, and other spiritual promotions to chose frely wyth out money apte &amp; mete preestes therunto, layed asyde all carnal affection, both for the discharge of theyr owne consciences, and also that by the studye &amp; labour of learned, and godly beneficed mē the truth of Christes religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; vertue of lyfe may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter go forwarde, and florish, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylyng agaynst falsitie, &amp; vice. Also I do exhorte all preestes to
<pb facs="14"/> cast away theyr inordinate am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and desyre of promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neyther procuryng them to them selues by money, or anye other vnlefull meanes, nor yet receyuyng them beynge offered, excepte they be apte, and able to discharge the same cures. And yf they so be, &amp; do therupon take anye suche dignitie of Christes churche, lette euerye one of them beare in hys mynde the strayte accompte, whiche he shall make vnto God for the soules cōmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him to be ruled, &amp; taught, euer folowing saynt Peters les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, saying to all bishoppes and preestes hauynge cure of soule. Fede ye the flocke of god, which is amonge you, prouidynge (for thē) not as constrayned, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly accordynge to god, Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fylthy lucres sake, but
<pb facs="14"/> voluntaryly, nother rulyng like Lordes ouer the clargye, or els<note place="margin">1. Petri. 5.</note> christen people, but hartely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge come an ensample of the flocke. And whē Christ the chefe of the shepeherdes shal appere, ye shall receyue the crowne of glorie, that cā not be corrupted. The which our lorde god graūt vnto vs, for Christe hys sonnes sake, heade of all shepeherdes, that boughte the same for vs w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the shedyng of hys most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, to whō with the father, &amp; the holye goost, be impery, glorie, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour world wythout ende.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>