<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MAGNIFICENT, and euer honoured, Syr Edward wootton Knight.</title>
           <author>A., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113629_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08553</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18870</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113629</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MAGNIFICENT, and euer honoured, Syr Edward wootton Knight.</title>
                 <author>A., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eighth booke of the Myrror of knighthood : Being the third of the third part. Englished out of the Spanish tongue</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>296 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MAGNIFICENT, and euer honoured, Syr <hi>Edward wootton Knight.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He grateful remembrance (right Noble Syr,) of your many fauors extended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my deceased vncle, &amp; nothing extenuated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my liuing Aunte, crauing a supreame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund ouer my oblyged thoghts, inforceth (where satisfactiō cannot equally ballance those deserts) an acknowledgement of an euerlasting thankfull mind. If therefore the hopes of an vntried seruant, may by future merites deserue any liking, or the merits of your own Heroicke worths (whose sole shadow inables my weaknesse) may adde corage to a discoraged spirit, thus to passe the limits of welbecomming dutie: Oh then pardon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptiō, that dares choose this means to expresse his true zeale vnto your seruice. For though the matter nor the methode, befits neither your wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor authoritie, yet let the innocency of my vnstained soule, be made happie by your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of these fewe sheetes of blotted paper. And
<pb facs="3"/>
if my audacitie (which I confesse) haue offended, impute it to proceede by motiue from the praises of your immortall vertues, whose excellencies the shril voyce of fame hauing borrowed the mouths of those, that they, with adamantiue power haue attracted to your affectiō, hath amply propagated through the worlds wide cōtinent. Or if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be impleasing, be that fault attributed mine, in selecting so fabulous a subiect, to be protected by so great a Patron. But yet (Magnanimous sir) suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the pleasing inuentiō for the original language sake, excusing that error, drown the memory of the offence, in the black center of obliuion. But for the rude stile, &amp; harsh vnpollisht phrase, oh there is no comfort can expel that discōsolated fear, vnles the euer memorable noblenes of your grace (thinking me to be what I am not) shall (lightning my dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) make me seeme gratious in your all-gracing sight, omitting, and remitting what euer deserueth blame, &amp; by smiling on so smal a talent, not vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cōdemne my immaculate sinceritie, to your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-dying worthines. Whose perpetuitie, togither with all your most happie desires, may the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent powers of that almightie maiestie, whose breath commands both heauen, earth and seas, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuate with eternall felicitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Euermore deuoted to your Worships seruice,</hi>
L. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>