<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113062_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01492</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11617.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of c [hri] stian renunciation : Compiled of excellent sentences [and] as it were diuerse homelies of ancient fathers: wherin is shewed how farre it is lawfull or necessary for the loue of Christ t [o] forsake father, mother, wife and children, and all other worldl creatures. Against the enemies of the crosse of Christ, ... Wherunto is added [a shorte discourse against going to hereticall churches.]</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Garnet’s First Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 169, 3, 39, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>IT hath alwaies bene an auncient custome euen from the very beginning of Christian religion,<note place="margin">The nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciatiō</note> that whosoeuer geueth his name to our Sauiour Christ, professing him selfe a sworne souldier of his spirituall Campe, therin to fight vnder his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious standard; should by no other oath be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to this holy warfare: than by a solemne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessiō either made by him selfe, or by his godfathers in his name, of renouncing the Deuell and all his workes with all his pompes and vanities. This ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renunciatiō hath euer bene accounted in the wholl life of a Christian, not only most forceable for the most strict obligation; it being an homage &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise vnto the greatest Soueraignty which possible may be, that is to God himselfe: but withall, a most effectuall remedy and a most sure protection for the comfortable memory therof, against all tentations and incounters of our ghostly enemies.</p>
   <p>For who is he, w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> being assaulted with proude and haughty cogitations, or tickled with the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering representations of vnlawfull delightes, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured with the transitory vanitie of worldly riches, or terrified with the barbarous manacings of bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy persecutours, or daunted with the manifold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficulties of the dayly and continuall combate with flesh and blood, or finally enuironed on euery side with neuer so diuers troupes of the world the flesh and the Deuell all conspiring in one against the welfare of the soule: by the remembrance of this irreuocable profession, and indispensable promise vnto God, will not presently be encouraged therby
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>vtterly ouercoming all manner of difficulties, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently to say either with that heathen Capitaine lacta est alea, my chaunce is cast: or with the deuout and spirituall soule, Inceptum est, retro abire non licet: I haue begone, I may not returne backward: or with our Sauiour himselfe: no man putting his hand to the plough,<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> and looking back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is fitte for the kingdome of God. For this cause did holy S. Chrysostome exhorte vs that we should continually haue this word in our mouth,<note place="margin">Hom. 21. ad pop. Antioch.</note> I renounce thee o Satan, affirming that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more safe than this word, if in all our works we remember it.<note place="margin">lib. 1. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. c. 2.</note> Yea this moreouer he addeth &amp; therunto doth S. Ambrose consent, that all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> we must in the day of iudgement yeeld vnto almighty God, is but of the obseruation of this one worde, and of the dilligent fulfilling of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> strict obligation conteined in the same. As there is none of you (saith S. Chrysostome) who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out shoes and vestments would choose to go into the market-place, so neuer go abroad without this word: but whan thou arte stepping ouer the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sholde, first speake this word, I renounce thee O Satan, &amp; I ioyne my selfe vnto thee O Christ. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer go forth without this voice. thou shalt finde this voice a staffe, thou shalt finde it thy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, thou shalt finde it an inuincible fortresse. with this word also make the Crosse in thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,<note place="margin">The Crosse in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</note> for so not only any man whom thou maiest chaunce to meete, but the Deuell himselfe can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hurt thee, whan he shall see thee euery where appearing with this armour. thus S Chrysostom.</p>
   <p>Neither doe we want moste euident places of
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>scripture, which doe plainly testifie vnto vs the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of this renunciation, it being the very sūme of Christian religion, &amp; the only end of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the sonne of God into the world: neither did hee come to bring peace into the earth, but a sword: neither can that man follow him which daily taketh not vp his Crosse: neither can any one be his Disciple which renounceth not togither w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> him selfe, whatsoeuer other thing may be vnder God. What greater renunciation can there be of any thing, than the hatred of the same? What thing can be more deare vnto vs than our owne life or soule? &amp; yet is this a necessary rule for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer cometh vnto Christ, that he cary a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all &amp; rooted hatred euen to his owne life &amp; soule. than is our life hated when it is dispised for Christ: thā is our soule hated whā it is afflicted, mortified, and clensed from the filthy disorder of seculer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes for the loue of the same Christ: who for one brittle and transitory life, either despised or lost for his name, will repay an eternall and most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py immortality: and for an imperfect, vncleane, rebellious soule; humbled, mortified, and purged through the assistance of his grace according to the measure of this life: will tender the same soule in the other life without spotte or wrinckle, adorned with all the bewtifull giftes of his vnspeakable glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.<note place="margin">How little regarde there is now of renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</note>
   </p>
   <p>This is the wholle occasion of this present trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise. For I see (and that not with small griefe) that for want of dew consideration of this so necessary a precept of Christian life, infinite multitudes of all maner of estates do daily perish: I see that such is
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>the forgetfulnes of those which should be the soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Christ, that as though this vertew of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation were a ceremony only of Monkes, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes, Freers and other religiouse persons, they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme the same as no parte of their Christian dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I see that in steed of that vertuous and fruitfull hatred of ones selfe (the necessary effect of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation) euery one almost is ouercome with a blinde flattering perniciouse selfeloue; and in steed of building in him selfe a spirituall Hierusalem by loue of God, buildeth a confused Babylon by loue of the world. And that we may bring examples onely of our owne countrey, and those in one kind onely of iniquity (although what iniquity is there committed amongst Christians but for want of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation into the handes and will of God?) who is there in our poore and lamentable estate, either withhoulden from God, holy Church their tender mother, or made shamefull by reuolte and fall frō the same; but for want of renunciation? where do we not see, that either parents by children, or children by parents: husbandes by wiues, or wiues by husbandes: one frend by an other: the subiects by the superiours, and superiours by subiectes, are hindered from the seruice of God? and that as our Sauiour saide,<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> inimici hominis domestici eius; the enimies of a man are those of his owne hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould? Which generall pestilent disease we can surely impute to no other cause, than to the want of renunciation. So that we see nothing in the world, so ordinarily, so daily, so generally renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as God him selfe and Christian dewty. Those which are by Gods law,<note place="margin">Parents</note> and the very law of nature
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>commanded to bring vp their children in the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and correction of our Lord;<note place="margin">Ephes. 6.</note> are now bent to no other thing so much as to dedicate them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Deuell:<note place="margin">Psal. 105. Maried per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</note> as Dauid also complained of the like case. those which should in the holy estate of wedlocke represent the vnspotted and vnseparable coniunction of Christ and his Church: Sicut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quus &amp; mulus in quibus non est intellectus,<note place="margin">Psal. 31.</note> not regarding any other thing but base affections: seek to draw one another frō Christ the spouse of their soule, and doe deuide Christ his spouse frō Christ, whose perpetuall lincke they should resēble.<note place="margin">Obedience.</note> And that which is most sacrilegious and blasphemous to speake or thinke: all these so great and hainous disorders are oftentimes fathered either vpon that sacred power w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> God hath ordeined wherby either wiues vnto their husbandes, or children to theire parents, or other subiectes to their superiours doe owe a kinde of dewty and obedience: or vpon the most honest lincke of humane frendshippe. as though either wiues had sould both body &amp; soule to be by their husbandes morgaged to perpetuall slauery of the Deuell: or parents had autoritie to kill the soules of their children ouer whose bodies they haue no such power: or those which are as it were Gods Lieuetenants in their seuerall offices, might conuert theire forces to fight for hell, and lawfully constraine their souldiers and subiectes to rebell against God: or finally as if there were any perfect frendship, where there wanteth honesty. All these &amp; many other iniquities in the like sorte, as by defaulte of renunciation they are committed: so by the performance of the same according to
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>the most sacred law and will of Christ, they may easely be auoided.<note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of this Treatise.</note> I purpose therfore by Gods assistance to whose glory I direct my labours, in this treatise briefly to shew how necessary and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious a thing Christian renunciation is, and that for no respectes of kinred, obedience, or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the world it is to be neglected.<note place="margin">Renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō is som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of Counsell, sometimes of precept. See chap. 2 out of <hi>S.</hi> Augustin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p. 89. q. 4</note> And that the same sometime is of counsaile to those which are free: but many times of necessity from which none can be free. It is of counsell: whan voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he which aspireth vnto perfection without any bond at all, selleth that which he hath and geueth to the poore &amp; followeth Christ, that he may haue a great treasure in heauen. Yet I say that this is of counsaile, for those which are free. For those w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> are in the estate of mariage cannot without mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all consent seuere them selues except in some cases as we will declare herafter. Bishops also, bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slaues and whosoeuer for some condition or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance haue not free power to alter the estate of their life, cannot vndertake a religious or solitary life.<note place="margin">Parents can not hinder their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from religion.</note> Yet this we say that neither parents may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their children, nor any other superiour his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> is free in this point: from such a resolution.</p>
   <p>We vrge also &amp; defend: that in some case: that which is of counsaile may be of necessity: and that which is of counsaile for some onely because it is not lawfull for all: may be a thing so absolutely required of all maner of persons: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they may vnder paine of dānation be bound to forsake not only ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; externall goods of fortune; but parents, hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, wife, children, &amp; all whatsoeuer is not God him selfe. The child is not bound to forsake his
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>parents: but yet he may doe it with meritt for the seruice of God.<note place="margin">A wife may be bound to forsake her husband. See chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> The wife may not forsake her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band at her pleasure although it were for to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious: yet if either the sonne must forsake his faith or his father: or the wife her husband or her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: most certaine it is, that the thing which was lawfull before in the sonne is now necessary; and that which the wife could not doe before but sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: now she cannot neglect but dānably. Hence shall it easely appeare what account as well childrē as wiues, ought in this lamentable contagious time for to make, either of the euell examples or of the peruerse commandements of their superiours: the first wherof sheweth them the way:<note place="margin">wherfore this treatise was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled of sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> the second euen driueth them to hell. And of this matter we will not bring our owne discourses, but the most graue sentences of auncient holy Fathers at large: for three causes. First for that they doe not onely declare vs their vncorrupted iudgemēt in these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which we desire to perswade: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> but according to the aboundance of that spirit which dwelled w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, they are very earnest and copious in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting vs to all Christian feruour and perfect ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negation of our selues. Wherfore I doubt not but hence it will come to passe, that although both y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> searching and translating of these places haue cost me no lesse labour, than if I had vndertakē a wholl worke of my owne: yet this treatise shall be reade with exceeding more fruite than if it had proceded from my owne inuention: here being conteined for the most parte as it were so many godly &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ute homelies as there are diuerse allegations of Fathers: so that this treatise may serue euery di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed
<pb n="12" facs="7"/>Catholicke in steed of a comfortable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon whansoeuer he wāteth other meanes of fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full encouragements. Wherin also euery one shall so much more effectually be moued: because he is sure that he readeth the deuout speaches of those in whom he may not doubte but God inhabited, and he may very well hope that euē in these parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer discourses it is not they them selues w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> speake,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> but the spirit of their Father within them.</p>
   <p>Secondly for that the misery of our tempestuous time continually more and more increasing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and the huge billous of our troublesome sea daily with more violence seeking to beat against the fortresse of our faith: vntill such time as it shall please him who hath shutte the sea within his fludgates and bolted it within the compasse of certaine bounds:<note place="margin">Iob. 38.</note> to say: hitherto thou shalt come, and not proceed any farther: and here thou shalt breake thy swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling waues: it may surely happen that this worke may be more necessary hereafter than at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. For wheras now perhaps parents and hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands are ready to preuent vniust lawes, and to do before they be vrged, that which hereafter may chaunce to be vrged vnto all: it will be no small aduantage at that time to haue in readines a Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of Gods Saintes, and of his most holy and auncient Pastours, for the declaration of our dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in so waighty a matter. The third cause w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me to make this a worke of auncient Fathers, rather than mine owne: is least happely the like befall in this question which we handle,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> here to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> doth ordinarily happen in other questions of the same importance. Our present difficulty is (I call it a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficulty
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>although in deed the case be most euidēt, because to worldly riche men there is nothing but seemeth difficult: an inheritance which Christ hath permitted them,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> vntill they leauing their Camells hugenes, will submit themselues vnto the lowlines of Christ) But this our present question is; whether a child by the commandment of parents: or a wife for obedience to her husband: or a seruant or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour for dewty to his Superiour: or a father for prouiding for his children: may lawfully doe that which of it selfe is against the law of God, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to the necessary confession of his faith: &amp; contemptuous withall vnto Christ his Church, &amp; a very separation from the same: Whether I say by these respects of temporall dewty, these hainous deformities may be taken away: and a contrary bond caused of such tēporall obedience or duety: or rather any of those may with meritte in case of perfection, yea &amp; be bound necessarily whan Gods honour so requireth, to renounce all worldly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and temporall respects, onely cleauing vnto Christ and his holy will. This is our case, this is our question. But what do we see in the like? who knoweth not how often the question of going to hereticall Churches hath bene tossed in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? And who is ignorant of the generall resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all those learned reuerend and godly Priests which are and haue bene in the same?<note n="*" place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Crosse of Christ whose end is destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whose God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> belly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fufiō, which mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Philip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> But what hath happened? Certaine priuate persons, who haue wholly addicted them selues to make them Gods either of their belly and ease, or of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mammon; setting God behind all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> may delight them; will not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="14" facs="8"/>their pernicious custome of frequenting hereticall conuenticles (w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> were a crime more tolerable) but they refuse also to beleeue that they do amisse: and that which is more hainous and a most high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of pride; they defend their wickednes: neither content with this, (as though it were no comfort to perish alone) they induce and by all possible meanes allure their frendes &amp; subiectes to the same iniquitie. But w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> what foundation &amp; groūd? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause forsooth the cōtrary doctrine proceedeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the persuasions, terrours or feares of some selfe minded and wilfull persons whom if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to know: they will tell you they be the young clergy. These men vndoubtedly after they haue once learned to conster latin, and to turne our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Primer, and perhaps the Breuiary, or at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to talke a little of logicke,<note place="margin">Dion. c. 2 de diuin. nom.</note> where it may be they haue looked into the Diuinitie schoole (as for Diuinitie who knoweth not that amongst here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes none can be learned:) these men I say beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them selues afterwardes to the study of Buco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall and georgicall affaires, and attending to that worldly substance which God hath cast vpon thē: no otherwise than that young man, which, as the Poets faine, being sent by his father to keepe sheepe by dreaming that he was made a Poet, became in deed a Poet:<note place="margin">Hesiodus</note> haue so soudainly become Deuines, that they are more learned, more humble, discreet and vertuous, than those which scornfully they call the young clergy: but should in deed if they were such as they flatter them selues to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as the rulers and shepheardes of their soules.</p>
   <p>For otherwise what clergy must we send these
<pb n="15" facs="8"/>men vnto for their spirituall reliefe? or wherin dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth the young clergy from the ould? or what Catholicke clergy can they find in the wholl world of contrary iudgement? But let vs send them to the Conuocation house, there shall they find the auncient reuerend clergy which they appertaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for vnto the clergy of Christ his Church they nothing belong: And let vs permitte these new Doctours with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ould Prelates to gage theire soules so often soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> already to the Deuell, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding (as S. Paule saieth) neither what thing they speake, nor of what they affirme:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.</note> daily pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering to the worse: erring &amp; driuing into errour.<note place="margin">2. Tim 3</note> It is no maruaile if refusing to be of the sheepe of Christ, they disdaine to acknowledge the shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes of Christ. Those who esteeme their soules and tremble at Gods iudgemēts: in so ruled a case, will flye from such Counsailours as from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells instruments. This am I willing and desirous that they should know, that although the Church of Christ hath learned by the mildnes of her spouse to tender the case of those which of humane frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fall into sinne, and can handle with lenitie such as go from her, and yet in hart are with her: yet doth she and all her trew children professe an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hatred vnto those which are peruerters and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers of soules as vnto heretickes themselues: as I hope they shall shortly be discouered what they are if after the definition of the cheife Pastour, they will remaine selfe minded and wilfull in theire so pernicious opinion.<note place="margin">Of the young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>. Ser. o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Virg.</note>
   </p>
   <p>As for the young yeares of Gods trew clergy w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> these men seeme to contemne, we may first say,
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>as the Church singeth out of S. Ambrose of the glorious virgin S. Agnes.<note place="margin">Ser. 90. ad Virg.</note> Infantia quidem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putabatur in annis, sed erat senectus mentis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensa. Infancy truely was reckoned in her yeeres but deepe ould age was in her mind. and that of the wise man Senectus enim venerabilis est non diuturna,<note place="margin">Cap. 4</note> neque annorum numero computata. cani autem sunt sensus hominis, &amp; aetas senectutis, vita immaculata. honourable ould age is not that which is of great and long time, neither is measured by the number of yeeres. for the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of a man are his gray heares, and the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entnes of olde yeares is an vnspotted life.</p>
   <p>Besides it is very well knowen that both in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and out of England, there are euen of this young clergy which they speake of not onely more wise, more learned, more vertuous, than these re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend men, thinke them selues (for perhaps they thinke better of them selues than their neighbour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> do) but also euen as farre growen in yeares as they. although this maketh nothing to the verity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; iurisdiction which they haue ouer soules wherin our Sauiour Christ respecteth not age, but his owne will and pleasure in bestowing his holy gifter. S Iohn was the youngest of all the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and yet he was eleuated to more high contē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation than the rest. S. Peter was not the eldest of them all, as being younger than S. Andrew his brother: and yet did our Sauiour geue him charge a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ouer all.</p>
   <p>But if these men call it the young clergy, because it is succeeded vnto that ould reuerend company which for the most parte many yeares sithence is
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>dead and rotten: than do they shew the base con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> they carry of Gods Church, as though it were at any time forsaken of Gods spirit, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that assistance in latter ages which it hath had in the former. and so they will rotte in their sinnes, because the clergy of our Fathers age is rottē in the graue. Yet this must they of necessity acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that as the holy Church of Christ now dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed ouer all the world, although in most diuers places, yet is but one: euen so if we compare that Church w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> now is with times forepast: although in most diuerse times, yet hath it alwaies bene but one, and is now and shall be to the worlds end, that which alwaies it hath bene, that is the selfe same one. and in like maner although the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler members of this same Church do necessarily al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the mortality of our nature: yet in respect of the same vniuersall and Catholicke vnity, and of the same spirit which gouerneth the Church: it is alwaies the same. and so this very young clergy as they call it cannot be differēt in maner of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and doctrine from any clergy neuer so ould which hath bene Catholicke, so long as this clergy which now is though different in persons from the ould, yet obserueth all maner of subiection &amp; vnity to the one onely roote which is the sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicke. As without all arrogancy we may say thus much, that neuer since the first conuersion of our Countrey such vnity was greater. there being not one person of the same either ordered, or endowed with necessary iurisdiction, but receiuing it not frō any particuler Bishop, or ordinary autority of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocesans, but by the immediate delegation or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="18" facs="10"/>commission of the onely cheife Bishop: from whose particuler knowledge they doe not swarue, in the resolution and managing of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the cheifest moment, appertaining vnto our religion. So that of the soundnes of this very new Clergy these scrupulous Grāmarian Deuines need not for to doubt: and if there be any ould Clergy wilfully and obstinately opposite vnto this w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> now it pleaseth them to terme the young Clergy: that Clergy surely is not the Clergy of the Catholicke Church, because it hath swarued from the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble direction of the spirit of the Catholike Church, speaking and teaching in Peters chaire. Neither can they proue this of that most Reuerend and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant ould Clergy which spent their liues in Durāce for Christ. of whose perpetuall vnion vnto the young Clergy our wholle countrey can be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Neither can the being ordered in forraine countreies, make a new and distinct Clergy from such as liue at the same time in our owne countrey, but that they must in all respects be of one and the same Clergy, &amp; therfore all Clergy persons of one age make not two Clergies, but one onely. So that very vaine is that distinction of theirs of an ould &amp; new Clergy. But whatsoeuer they meane by this new Clergy: Sure it is that either of this Clergy which now is they must haue their spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all foode &amp; reliefe if they will haue any (which I scarce can hope for) or of none.</p>
   <p>Finally of our wholle Clergy for the most parte, onely excepting those who by this flattering do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that it is lawfull to go to the Church haue sought to feed the couetous and fearfull humours
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>of these sonnes of this world, and therfore haue cast thē selues out from the sight of God, by figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting against his Church: and as so many Cains are noted with markes of wicked licentiousnes; (a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy punishment that those which do fornicate frō God and his Church, are suffered also to runne headlong into that other fleshly and beastly forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:) excepting I say those few whom God hath permitted to renew vnto vs the examples of Iudas, Simon Magus, Nicholas the Deacon, and others of those most high and most auncient Colleges: we may by Gods especiall grace in the rest see that counsell fulfilled which S. Paule geueth vnto Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy: Let no man contemne thy youth:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> but be an example of the faithfull in word, in conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in charity, in faith, in chastitie.</p>
   <p>A wonderfull young man (saith S. Ambrose was the most holy Timothy,<note place="margin">in hunc locum.</note> by whose example disordered youth was to be bridled, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewtifull irreuerence of the aged was to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. But the holines and learning and purity of life, of this very same young Clergy, in so many daungers, amongst so feculer behauiour, in this great decay of discipline in all ages: as it is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed all abrode whilest these senseles defenders of schisme wallow in flesh and blood: so shall it be celebrated in all ages whan their bodies are rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the graue, and vnlesse they repent, whan their soules, as the Psalme saieth, like sheepe shall be consumed in hell. Sufficient it is for trew Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, that the worthines of the young Clergy is acknowledged and feared by the Deuell him selfe.</p>
   <p>That questiō therfore of Going to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing supposed)
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>as sufficiently resolued by diuerse meanes hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs heare for our Catholicke brethrens cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte the doctrine of the ould Clergy of Christ his Church, concerning Christian renunciation: that so all hope may be taken away from the renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Gods auncient Church, to blame the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of any young Clergy;<note place="margin">How im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant this case was in <hi>S.</hi> Ambrose his opiniō.</note> The matter trewly seemeth vnto me so important, and the case so vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: that if the holy Bishop of Milan S. Ambrose accounted it to be the necessary dewty of Gods Priestes euen vnto death to resist those Parents w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> withdrew their daughters from being Nunnes, a thing of indifferent choice vnto euery one:<note place="margin">l. 3. de Virg.</note> farre greater necessity will there be in confuting those euen with daunger of death, which seeke to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe them from all Christian dewty. Et potest esse (saieth that most godly Doctour) patientia Sacerdotum, vt non vel morte oblata, si ita necesse est, integritatis sacrificium vindicetur? And can a Preist haue patience that euen with manifest pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of death if occasion be offered, he reschue not the sacrifice of integritye? maruaile not therfore (good reader) if I one farre vnworthy of the least credit of any Catholicke Clergy man seeme ouer earnest in this my preface: for by reading ouer this treatise thou shalt see that I differ not herin from the zeale of most graue Sainctes of God. if I shall profit thē any thing by my reprehension: I shall be gladd, because they are made sory vnto penance: if I shall do no more but incense them; yet I hope I shall profit many: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Let them in the meane time take it for parte of penance, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> wheras in deed this is but a pibble stone in respect of the milstone which
<pb n="21" facs="11"/>they must expect from the iudgement of Christ if they will not be reformed, and except they hould their handes from paper, and auoid publicke occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of scandalous doctrine in this behaulfe: they must needs thinke that if Priests for wāt of meanes and commodit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> haue patience and hould theire peace: there wil be notwithstanding some one or other alwaies ready to reuenge Gods cause, and to stand in the defence of the necessary confession of Christ our Redeemer, and of his holy Crosse.</p>
   <p>Thus much therfore being spoken of the cause and generall maner of this Treatise:<note place="margin">The order of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tise.</note> I will now set downe the order of proceeding therin for although I could not easely distinguish the seuerall matters handled by the Fathers, and almost in euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer allegation there is occasion of speaking of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing belonging to our purpose: yet haue I for the more perspicuity, and for the more ease of the reader so deuided the wholle, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all to a few principall points. The first chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therfore shall be, to shew that it is very merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and acceptable vnto God, to renounce pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and all things for perfection. For if this be once fully perswaded, lesse difficulty will it be to proue that it is lawfull in cases of necessity. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The second. That a man is bound vnder paine of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation, vnto a perfect renunciation of all frendes, kinsefolkes, parents and superiours, their intreaties examples and commaundements: yea and him selfe also, and all that he hath, whan o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise he should be hindered from the dewty of a Christian. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third shall intreate in particuler of the necessary renunciatiō sometimes to be made
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>of husband and wife. where as well for to take away occasion of errour, as for to represse the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant peruersnes of some husbands which chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge more autoritie ouer wiues than God or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath geuen them. We must necessarily intreat of some lawfull separations of man and wife: w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> we must be forced to doe of our owne: although (if leasure will permitte) we purpose to proue it out of Gods word and auncient Fathers. which if we shall not for haste be permitted to perfourme: yet this will we promise that we will set nothing downe, but according to the common opinion of Catholicke Doctours.</p>
   <p>The fourth chapter we will make, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly of renunciation of a mans patrimony, and care of prouision for children.</p>
   <p>The fifth besides that which was saide in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter shall intreate of renunciation of a mans selfe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and necessary obligation to suffer mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, whā otherwise God might be offended. with diuerse forceable exhortations to the same.</p>
   <p>Finally shall follow the Conclusion. So that in no parte of this Treatise except onely in this preface in the conclusion and in some parte of the third chapter thou must thinke that I speake (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) but imagin that the Saintes of God do speake vnto thee. I haue vndoubtedly lest infinite places, and many Doctors w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> might haue bene brought: but this is as much as my time and cōmodity could afford thee: others perhaps may take occasion hereby to adde other like, these I hope will no lesse moue them which with sincere mindes shall read them, than they haue comforted my selfe
<pb n="23" facs="12"/>whan I haue wrotten them. This onely I desire of the deuout Readers, that as I haue sought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else in this small labour, but my Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Brethrens comfort: so I may reape againe the comforte of their gratefull acceptation.</p>
   <p>S. Bern. lib. de praecept. &amp; dispens.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Siue Deus siue homo vicarius Dei man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum quodcunque tradiderit, paripro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto obsequendum est cura, pari reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia deferendum, vbitamen Deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria non praecipit homo. quod si con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigerit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 5.</note>
      <hi>pergendum indubitanter consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo in Petri sententiam, quia obedire o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet Deo magis quam hominibus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Whether God, or man, being the Vicar of God do geue any commandment: with the like care it must be obeied, with equall reuerence it is to be esteemed, yet so long as man commandeth not contrary vnto God. which if it happen, than do I counsell euery one to follow Peters counsell, that we must obey God rather then men.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>