<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST CHRI∣STIAN KING OF FRANCE and POLONIA, HENRIE the third of that name.</title>
           <author>Primaudaye, Peter de la</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113143_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05105</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15241</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113143</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST CHRI∣STIAN KING OF FRANCE and POLONIA, HENRIE the third of that name.</title>
                 <author>Primaudaye, Peter de la</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French academie : Fully discoursed and finished in foure bookes. 1. Institution of manners and callings of all estates. 2. Concerning the soule and body of man. 3. A notable description of the whole world, &amp;c. 4. Christian philosophie, instructing the true and onely meanes to eternall life. This fourth part neuer before published in English. All written by the first author, Peter de la Primaudaye, Esquire, Lord of Barre, Chauncellour, and Steward of the French Kings house</title>
                 <author>La Primaudaye, Pierre de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 330, 10, 331-634, 4, 635-643, 646-1031, 1034-1038, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN KING OF FRANCE and POLONIA, HENRIE the third of that name.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, if we credit the saying of <hi>Plato,</hi> Common wealths begin then to be happy, when Kings exercise Philosophie, and Philosophers reigne. The Wiseman speaking more diuinely, exhorteth Kings to loue and to seeke after wisdome, that they may reigne vpon earth righteously, and in heauen e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ernally. And truely from wisdome and Philosophie, as from a liuely fountaine floweth the gift of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning by good lawes &amp; good example, of defending by prowesse and of nourishing by wisdome and prouidence, which are the band<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of al perfection requisit in an excellent &amp; absolute Prince; that desireth to gouern his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome according to pietie &amp; iustice. These three great &amp; excellent gifts depending of God, as euerie other grace doth, one of those meanes wherby he vseth most commonly to enrich them that haue the reines of worldly gouernment in their hand, is to imprint in their hearts a loue and desire of learning and sciences. But because they cannot so perfectly vnderstand them by reason of their great and burdensome charge, as priuate men may, who quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the fruit and benefit of their Kings labors, addict themselues to no other profession, their Maiesties are so much the more pricked forward to loue, to inquire after, and to honor such their subiects, as are best able to set before their eies those vertuous and learned instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that are drawne out of the fountaines of arts and disciplines. This moued <hi>Antigonus</hi> king of Macedonia to write thus to <hi>Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o</hi> the Philosopher: <hi>I am assured that I excell thee in the goods &amp; fauour of Fortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, and in the renowne of such things, but I know withal, that thou art f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r aboue me, and goest beyond me in that true felicitie, which consisteth in the knowledge &amp; discipline of studies. Therefore I desire earnestly that thou wouldest come vnto me: wherein I pray thee denie me not, that I may enioy thy conuersation and company, as well for mine owne profit, as for the profit of all the Macedonians my Subiects. For he that instructeth a Prince, doth also profit as many as are vnder his charge.</hi> The selfe same loue of knowledge was the cause, that all the fes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iuall ornaments of that great louer of vertue <hi>Ptolemie Philadelphus</hi> King of Egypt, were graue questions as wel of pietie as of Philosophie, which hee propounded to be handled and concluded by those learned men whom he ordinarily maintained in his traine.</p>
   <p>Sir, the example of these two noble Kings shining wholy in you, who greatly loue and fauour learning, and the professors therof, and open the gate of that holy and vertuous dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, which was so much cherished by auncient men, that they may daily bee instructed the better in the dutie of their charges, doth promise to your good subiects &amp; vassals, that by the grace of God they shall see vnder your reigne, the euill of those sinister effects defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, which haue issued from these long troubles and ciuill warres. Whereof all men haue conceiued a more certain hope, because they see that you labor with a holy zeale and good affection, to restore pietie and iustice to their former strength and beautie, which were in a manner buried in France: and that you haue gloriously crowned that worke, which that great King <hi>Francis</hi> your grandfather did happily begin, to the end that artes and sciences might flourish in this kingdome. The dinner of that Prince of famous memory, was a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table of <hi>Solomon,</hi> vnto which resorted from euery nation such as were best learned, that they might reape profite and instruction. Yours, Sir, beeing compassed about with those who in your presence daily discourse of, and heare discoursed many graue and godly matters, seemeth to bee a Schoole erected to teach men that are borne to
<pb facs="5"/>
vertue. And for my selfe, hauing so good hap during the assembly of your Estates at B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ois, as to be made partaker of the fruit gathered therof, it came in my minde to offer vnto your Maiestie a dish of diuers fruits, which I gathered in a Platonicall garden or orchard, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called an ACADEMIE, where I was not long since with certaine yong Gentlemen of Anion my companions, discoursing together of the institution in good manners, and of the meanes how all estates and conditions may liue well and happily. And although a thousand thoughts came then into my mind to hinder my purpose, as the small authoritie which youth may or ought to haue in counsell amongst ancient men: the greatnes of the matter subiect, propounded to be handled by yeares of so small experience: the forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the best foundations of their discourses, which for want of a rich and happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie might be in me: my iudgement not sound enough, and my profession vnfit to set them downe in good order: Briefly, the consideration of your naturall disposition and rare vertue, and of the learning which you receiue both by reading good Authors, and by your familiar communication with learned and great personages that are neere about your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, (whereby I seemed to oppose the light of an obscure day, full of cloudes and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to the beames of a very cleere shining Sunne, and to take in hand, as we say, to teach <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erua)</hi> I say, all these reasons being but of two great weight to make me change my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, yet calling to mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>de many goodly and graue sentences taken out of sundrie Greeke and Latine Philosophers, as also the worthy examples of the liues of ancient Sages and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous men, where with these discourses were inriched, which might in delighting your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minde renew your memorie with those notable sayings in the praise of vertue, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praise of vice, which you alwaies loued to heare: and considering also that the bountie of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> that great Monarch of the Persians was reuiued in you, who receiued with a cheerefull countenance a present of water of a poore labourer when he had no neede of it, thinking it to be as great an act of magnanimity to take in good part, and to receiue cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully small presents offered with a heartie and good affection, as to giue great things liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ouercame whatsoeuer would haue stayed mee in mine enterprise. For I assured my selfe thus much of your bountifull and royall greatnesse, (which I craue in most humble manner) that you would measure the gift and offer of this my small labour, not according to the desert thereof, or by the person of one of your basest seruants and subiects, who presenteth it vnto you, but according to the excellency of those things, which you shall see handled in this <hi>Academie,</hi> and according to the seruiceable and most effectionate desire, wherewith I dedicate and consecrate both goods and life to your seruice. I beseech God, Sir, to preserue your Maiestie in great prosperity, increase of honour and continuance of a long and happy life.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Barree <date>in the moneth of February. 1577.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your most humble and most obedient Seruant and Subiect, PETER de la PRIMAVDAYE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>