<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT and learned Shepheard Collin Cloute.</title>
           <author>Smith, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113473_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12550</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22872</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113473</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT and learned Shepheard Collin Cloute.</title>
                 <author>Smith, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Chloris, or The complaint of the passionate despised shepheard. By William Smith</title>
                 <author>Smith, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT and learned Shepheard Collin Cloute.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>COllin</hi> my deere and most entire beloued,</l>
      <l>My muse audatious stoupes hir pitch to thee,</l>
      <l>Desiring that thy patience be not moued</l>
      <l>By these rude lines, written heere you see,</l>
      <l>Faine would my muse whom cruell loue hath wronged,</l>
      <l>Shroud hir loue-labors vnder thy protection,</l>
      <l>And I my selfe with ardent zeale haue longed,</l>
      <l>That thou mightst knowe to thee my true affection.</l>
      <l>Therefore good <hi>Collin,</hi> graciously accept</l>
      <l>A few sad sonnets, vvhich my muse hath framed,</l>
      <l>Though they but nevvly from the shell are crept,</l>
      <l>Suffer them not by enuie to be blamed.</l>
      <l>But vnderneath the shadovv of thy vvings,</l>
      <l>Giue vvarmth to these yong-hatched orphan things.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Giue vvarmth to these yoong-hatched orphan things,</l>
      <l>VVhich chill vvith cold to thee for succour creepe,</l>
      <l>They of my studie are the budding springs,</l>
      <l>Longer I cannot them in silence keepe.</l>
      <l>They vvill be gadding sore against my minde.</l>
      <l>But curteous shepheard, if they run astray</l>
      <l>Conduct them, that they may the path vvay finde,</l>
      <l>And teach them hovv, the meane obserue they may.</l>
      <l>Thou shalt them ken by their discording notes,</l>
      <l>Their vveedes are plaine, such as poore shepheards weare.</l>
      <l>Vnshapen, torne, and ragged are their cotes,</l>
      <l>Yet foorth they vvandring are deuoid of feare.</l>
      <l>They vvich haue tasted of the muses spring,</l>
      <l>I hope vvill smile vpon the tunes they sing.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. Smith.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>