<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER, TO the READER.</title>
           <author>T., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113579_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6618</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113579</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER, TO the READER.</title>
                 <author>T., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and fruitful exposition vpon the Lords prayer. By Arthur Dent, sometime minister of the Word of God at South-Suberry, in Essex</title>
                 <author>Dent, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER, TO the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as deuoute Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, when they haue found comfort in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of any learned man, it causeth in them a further desire, not onely to reuiew what they haue read, but also to haue a longing, as it were, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their further paines, vpon any other subiect. I doubt not, but am verily perswaded, that this Expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Prayer, which our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus taught his disciples; penned by one that hath so well deserued of the Church of God; by publishing so many good &amp; profitable Treatises, shal finde some
<pb facs="3"/>
place among thy heauenly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, although it be not as I thinke so perfect, as the Author intended it if hee had not beene preuented by death. For what wilt thou doe, either for all the benefits that thou hast re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or for those things that are required for thy vse, or to preuent any dangers, that may be feared? I say, what wilt thou doe, if thou wilt not imitate the holy Prophet, and call vpon the name of the Lord? and how canst thou better call vpon it, then as the Lord hath appointed? and what profit shalt thou haue by calling vpon him after that manner, except thou knowest the meaning of the spirit, in those words which thou pourest out before him? Wherefore seeing (as an auncient Father saith) <hi>when thou prayest for thy selfe, necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enforceth thee; and Charity bindeth thee to pray for others</hi>: and seeing
<pb facs="3"/>
the <hi>holy one of God</hi> hath giuen thee in charge, <hi>after this manner, pray ye;</hi> this seruant of God shall so instruct thee, that according to the practise of the holy Apostle, thou shalt <hi>pray with the spirit, &amp; with vnderstanding also,</hi> and this <hi>one thing is necessary</hi>: For all the commandements of the Lord, are so full of counsell, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie word hath his weight, yea euery sillable containes a secret, so that we may all say with the Eunuch, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. <hi>How can I vnderstand, except some man should guide me</hi>? And albeit I am perswaded that thou art <hi>full of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, filled with knowledge, able also to admonish others</hi>: yet thou maiest be content with skilfull <hi>Apollos,</hi> so elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in speach, mightie in the scriptures, and feruent in spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 18. to haue the <hi>way of God</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto thee by another man <hi>more perfectly.</hi> And this is that which I
<pb facs="4"/>
offer to thy Christian deuotion. Vse it then as becommeth thee, with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse. Peruse it often. I hope I am truely informed of the Author, I am but the Minister to publish it for thy good. Giue thankes to GOD, that hath brought it to light. And the GOD of all power, when thou prayest, <hi>graunt thee thy harts desire, and fulfill all thy minde.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>S. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>