<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the dutifull Subiect.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113808_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68537</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18983.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the dutifull Subiect.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled: or The concord of papist and puritan (against Scripture, fathers, councels, and other orthodoxall writers) for the coercion, deposition, and killing of kings. Discouered by David Owen Batchelour of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the right Honourable Lord Vicount Hadington</title>
                 <author>Owen, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 75, that is 57, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the dutifull Subiect.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Puritan-Church-Policie,</hi> and the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suiticall societie</hi> began together:<note n="a" place="margin">See M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers preface. And the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. before his examen against the first part of the Councell of Trent.</note> the one in <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1536. and the other in <hi>Rome,</hi> 1537. since their beginning, they haue bestirred themselues busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>(as he that compasseth the</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note>
      <hi>earth, or they that coasted</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 23.15.</note>
      <hi>sea &amp; land,)</hi> each one in his order. The <hi>Puritan</hi> to breake downe the wall of <hi>Sion,</hi> by disturbing the peace of the <hi>reformed Church:</hi> the <hi>Iesuite</hi> to build vp the ruines of <hi>Babylon,</hi> by maintaining the abhomination of the <hi>deformed Synagogue.</hi> These (though brethren in sedition and headie) are <hi>head-seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> the one staring to the <hi>presbyterie,</hi> and the other to the <hi>Papacie,</hi> but they are so fast linked behind, and <hi>tayle-tied</hi> together with <hi>firebrands</hi> betweene them, that if they be not quenched by the power of Maiestie, they cannot chose (when the meanes are fitted to their plot) but set the <hi>Church</hi> on fire, and the <hi>state</hi> in an vprore. Their <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and long prayers,</hi> their <hi>much vehement preaching,</hi> and stout opposition against <hi>orders established,</hi> their shewe of austeritie in their conuersation, and of singular learning in their profession, <hi>(as the euill fiend transformed into an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light)</hi> brought them first to admiration. Whereby they haue not onely <hi>robbed widows houses</hi> vnder pretence of prayer, and ransacked their <hi>seduced disciples</hi> by shew of
<pb facs="7"/>
deevotion, but also battered the <hi>courts of Princes,</hi> by ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating the <hi>Peeres</hi> against <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> against the <hi>Peeres</hi> for pretended <hi>reformation.</hi> And whereas God hath inseparably annexed to the <hi>crowne of earthly maiestie, a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme ecclesiasticall soueraigntie</hi> for the protection of <hi>pietie;</hi> and an absolute <hi>immunitie</hi> from the iudiciall <hi>sentence,</hi> and Martiall <hi>violence,</hi> for the preseruation of <hi>policie:</hi> These sectaries bereaue Kings of both these their <hi>Princely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues,<note place="margin">2. Thess. 2.3.4.</note> exalting themselues</hi> (as the sonne of perdition) <hi>aboue all that is called God:</hi> Least they might seeme <hi>sine ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione insanire,</hi> to sowe the seedes of sedition without shewe of reason, <hi>Caedem faciunt scripturarum</hi> (as the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time were wont to doe) <hi>in materiam suam,</hi> they kill the Scripture to serve their turnes: and pervert the holy word of the <hi>eternall God,</hi> by strange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and wicked application against the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by whom it was penned; the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> to whom it was deliuered; and the practise of all the <hi>Godly,</hi> (as well vnder the <hi>Lawe</hi> as the <hi>Gospel</hi>) that did beleeue, vnderstand, and obey it; to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their late, and lewd opinions. I haue in my hand <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fortie several places of the old and new Testament,</hi> which both the brethren of the enraged opposite faction doe indifferently quote, and seditiously apply, in defence of their dangerous opposition, and damnable error, against the <hi>Ecclesiasticall supremacie,</hi> and the <hi>indeleble character of royal invnction.</hi> Vnto the which places, falsly expounded, perverted, and applyed, I haue added the interpretation, of the learned <hi>Protestants</hi> since the time of <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> who began to discouer the nakednesse of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Church,</hi> 1517. More especially insisting in the<note n="a" place="margin">K. Henry 8. K Iames. Th. Cranmer. lo. Whitgift. Rich. Bancroft Archb. of Cant. Henry Earle of Northampton. Robert Earle of Salisbury.</note> most
<pb facs="7"/>
mightie Kings, the most reuerend Prelats,<note place="margin">The L. Burleigh L. treasurer of England. The L. Els nere L. chancelor of England. The L. Stafford. The L. Cooke. B. Iewell. B. Horn▪ B. Pilkington. B Elmere, B Couper. B. Bilson. B. Babington. B. Andrewes. B. Barlowe. B. Bridges. D Ackworth. D. Sarania. D. Cosen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. D. Sutchliffe. D. Prvthet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h. D. Wilkes D. Morton. D. Tochen. M. Bekinsaw. M. Foxe. M. Nowell. M. Hooker &amp; many others.</note> honourable Lords, loyall Clergie, and other worthie men, that haue in the Church of England, learnedly defended the Princely right, against disloyall, and vndutifull oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents: which by <hi>Gods</hi> helpe I meane to publish, when I haue added the exposition of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> to confute the falshood of the <hi>Puritan-popish-faction,</hi> &amp; to confirme the truth of the <hi>Protestants Doctrine</hi> in each particular quotation. I protest in all sinceritie, that I neither haue in this treatise, nor meane in the other, <hi>hereafter to be published,</hi> to detort any thing, to make either the <hi>cause</hi> it selfe, or the <hi>fauourers</hi> of it more <hi>odious,</hi> then their owne words, (published with the generall approbation of their seuerall fauorites) doe truely inferre, and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inforce. I hope the loyall subiect, and <hi>Godly</hi> affected, will accept in good part my endeauour, and industrie, intended for the glorie of <hi>God,</hi> the honour of the <hi>King,</hi> and the discouerie of <hi>the seditious.</hi> The displeasure of the <hi>malecontented-factious</hi> (which can no more abide the truth, then the owles can light, or the frantique the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitian) I neither regard nor care for. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>