<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Readers, and to the byting Censurers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113457_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08531</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18850</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113457</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Readers, and to the byting Censurers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The picture of a papist: or, A relation of the damnable heresies, detestable qualities, and diabolicall practises of sundry hereticks in former ages, and of the papists in this age : Where in is plainly shewed, that there is scarse any heresie which the auncient Church knew, and withal condemned to the pit of hell, which the Romish Church hath not raked vp againe, and propounded to the world with new varnish and fresh colours. Together with a discourse of the late treason, and of the late execution of some of the traitors ... Written to stop the mouthes of those that complaine of rigour, and scandalize the state of cruelty, in their iust seueritie. Whereunto is annexed a certain treatise, intituled Pagano-pagismus: wherein is prooued by irrefragable demonstrations, that papisme is flat paganisme: and that the papists doe resemble the very pagans, in aboue seuenscore seuerall things</title>
                 <author>Ormerod, Oliver</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fosbrooke, Nathaniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 83, 90-137, 168-203, 264-275, 1, 56, 47-62 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the gentle Readers, and to the <hi>byting Censurers.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lutarch</hi> mentioneth a certaine painter, who when he had made a goose &amp; a cocke both alike, was faine to write ouer their heads for distinction sake▪ <hi>this is a goose, this is a cock.</hi> I <hi>haue now</hi> drawn (<hi>curteous Readers</hi>) the pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of a Puritane and of a Papist, and haue set ouer theyre heads with <hi>Plutarches</hi> painter, <hi>this is a goose, this is a cock: this is a Puritane, this is a papist.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And since I drew the former, (I speake to you byting Cē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers) I haue found that Poeticall prouerb most true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by thar Auncient Alceus: <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der euery stone there lieth a serpent:</hi> for there are certaine ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine and venemous tongued Puritanes, that haue bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted abroad in london, that the Author hereof, was an <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant papist, &amp; eyther one of the late traitours, or a special fauo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer of theire Religion.</hi> So that J haue good cause to say of<note place="margin">b Master Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kins in his treatise of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Gods word to the conscience <hi>page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>lt,</hi>
      </note> them as a zealous preacher saide of them long since; <hi>The poyson of Aspes is vnder their lippes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But why art thou so vexed O my soule? and why art thou so disquieted within me? <hi>They haue called the maister of the house Belzebub, much more those of the household▪ they haue cald our reuerēd Fathers Petti-popes, and (as Elias said in an</hi>
      <note place="margin">c As I haue shewed in my Picture of a Puritane,</note>
      <hi>other case) am I better then my fathers?</hi> Nay the <hi>Bishop of our souls Christ Iesus,</hi> when he was vpon the earth, was slaundered of the Scribes, and pharises to bee a drun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kard and <hi>a glutton, a friend to publicans and sinners:</hi> &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest thou to liue vpon the earth, and that among the like
<pb facs="5"/>
slanderers, and liue without the like slaunders? Thou art but the son of mā, but thou oughtest to say with the son of God, <note n="d" place="margin">Iohn 18, 37.</note>
      <hi>For this cause am I borne, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d for this cause came I in to the world, that I might bear witnes vnto the truth.</hi> Thou art ordained (as the Apostle saieth) <hi>to approoue thy selfe in all kind of patience: by honour and dishonour, by good report and ill report, as a deceiuer, &amp; yet behold thou art true, &amp; as a treacherous Papist, &amp; yet behold, thou art a loyall Protestant</hi> To Conclude, say to those <hi>Gnat-strainers &amp; Camel-swallow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">If one name will not make an idle booke sel, the Stacio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners will bee Godfathers to it, and giue it a new name, and father it on an other man.</note> as saint Paule said to the like byting Censurers, and sharp-toothed Carpers in his time: I <hi>passe very little, to bee iudged of you, or of mans iudgment.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And thus I leaue you, beseeching you to suspend your iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of me, vntill you see the <hi>True picture of a Protestant</hi> which I am now drawing and shadowing with orient co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lours, wherin I purpose to make knowne to the worlde, in what religion J haue hitherto liued, and wherein <hi>I</hi> will die, though the world should turne vpside downe,</p>
   <q>Nulladies siue linea.</q>
   <div type="postscript">
      <head>A Post-script.</head>
      <p>There is a certaine book latelye published, entituled, <hi>the double PP,</hi> *alias, <hi>the picture of a Iesuite, altas the pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of a traiterous Iesuit:</hi> which som in london haue repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be of my drawing: But be it known vnto you, that <hi>I</hi> am so farre from being the Author of that friuolous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, as that J hold both it, and another that was thrown abroad vpon the stage at the late execution of the traitors, together with many other <note n="e" place="margin">Among the rest there is one book lately printed against the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pists, wherein the author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>latly denieth the Epistle of Saint Iames to be Canonicall scripture. It is a very vn fit thing, that histrionicall iesters and stage play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers should bee suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ed to writ books of such matters and in deed a greate disgrace to our Religion.</note> toyes lately printed againste the Papists, as fit for the fire as the coniuring bookes in the 19 of the <hi>Acts, verse,</hi> 19, And were J worthy to giue myne aduise to those that are in authority, those that did publish any such <note n="f" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor</hi> 68 2 Cor 43,</note> Phātastical books hereafter, as the double PP is, shoulde haue for their paynes, eyther a single Greeke Π, or at the least, <hi>nigrum theta.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>