<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
           <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113515_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19292</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5700.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113515</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mysterie of the holy government of our affections : Contayning their nature, originall, causes, and differences. Together with the right ordering, triall, and benefit thereof: as also resoluing diuers cases of conscience, incident hereunto. Very necessarie for the triall of sinceritie, and encreasing in the power of Godlinesse. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 67, 6 leaves, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="80"/>
   <head>To THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>ACcording to my Promise, in my last Treatise of the</hi> Gouernment of the Thoughts; <hi>I haue now supplyed thee (deare Christian) with some fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directions for the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordering and subduing of thy vnruly and rebellious Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: A Taske as so much the more difficult, then the former, of ruling the Thoughts, by how much
<pb facs="81"/>
carnall Reason and fleshly wisedome, beares more sway heerein, and so giues more strength and warrant to the excesses thereof: so in this respect also the more neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie to be vndertaken, as being that wherein euen the best doe much faile in the wise temper thereof, and yet are very hardly brought to discerne their aberrations therein. For what one the one side through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the right Obiects whereon our affections are to be placed, and the right measure of Proportion to their Obiects: And on the other side, by reason of such collusions of carnall wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, making good our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers therein: very la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable
<pb facs="81"/>
it is to obserue how easily many, other wise good men, haue beene miserably transported into these aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations either in the excesse or defect. As also how hardly they haue beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to the right temper againe: nay, not so much as to discerne wherein they haue fallen. May we not obserue both these true in</hi> Ionas <hi>his case? how easily fel he through ignorance, and selfe loue into a violent fit of rage, and how hardly was he reduced to see his error heerein. That which he should haue reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in, in the truth of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Lord had mercie vpon that People, voiced to destruction: wee see proues an occasion,
<pb facs="82"/>
through spirituall Pride and Selse-loue blinding of him; that I say, proued a meanes to make him euen burst with anger, not spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God himselfe in his rage and furie: And with what great Patience doth the glorious Lord seeke to allay his heat? how hardly is he brought, so much as to the sight of his distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but that he is still rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Iustifie his fumes, though it were to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning of God himselfe?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The like we might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplifie in the other affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And had wee not then great neede of some light to further vs heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, both that we may see our owne errors heerein, and
<pb facs="82"/>
also be gratiously enabled to moderate the same. Accept then I pray you my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour heerein: And in the feare of God make vse of such directions as are affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hereunto. I doubt not but as thou shalt perceiue a right ayme heerein, so thou wilt not measure the truth of God by my infirmities, but rather take occasion heereby to glorifie God the more, if that his power shall any whit shine throughout such mists of humane corruption. In the conclusion of my last Booke howsoeuer I may be censured to giue way to too much passion, yet for mine owne part, I blesse God with my soule, for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mee so much Patience,
<pb facs="83"/>
as that when I might haue righted my selfe by deeds to the vtter wracke of such who haue sought by slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and desperate practises my vtter vndoing. It hath pleased my gratious God so to guide me therein, as only to giue them a generall</hi> Item <hi>of their wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, that so they may be brought to Repentance: which as I doe heartily pray for, so my endeauour by Gods mercie shall be to watch ouer my affections with more heede and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: that so I may keepe my peace more comfortably with my God, howsoeuer I make account still to be more and more encounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by vnreasonable men.
<pb facs="83"/>
And so I desire thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to walke after the same Rule, labouring so farre as possibly thou maiest to be at Peace with all men, by possessing thy soule in patience and ouercomming euill with good.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And so I commend thee (heartily) to the Grace of God: wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee to expect shortly as heere a generall directs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Affections in generall: so a particular discouery of each Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their liuely collours, that so thou maiest bee furnished with what may particularly informe thee heerein, and thereby bee enabled to walke peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with God and Men,
<pb facs="84"/>
to thy comfortable being in this thy Pilgrimage, and so to the better preparing of thee to thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>To this end, And so I rest Thy poore Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer at the Throne of Grace. Th. Cooper.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="84"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>