<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To </title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113712_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10341</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20620</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To </title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A replye answering a defence of the sermon, preached at the consecration of the bishop of Bathe and Welles, by George Downame, Doctor of Divinitye : In defence of an answere to the foresayd sermon imprinted anno 1609</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Thorp, Giles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 293, 11, 164 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="158"/>
   <pb facs="158"/>
   <head>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hose two motives which doe most usually and not unjustly perswade the Reader to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive his author, (the credit of the man, &amp; the apparāt evidence that he bringeth) have by many been thought to have united their forces in Doctor Downames defense. For the man himselfe, he hath been generally accounted judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, learned, painfull, religious, syncere, and ingenuous, the defense he hath made carieth such an appearance of learning, antiquity, &amp; truth with it, that not onely to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe (through too much love of his owne) but to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse others also, it seemeth not subject vnto any replie or refutation, so that, this attempt of his adversaries in gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saying, and that so confidently, fully, and roundly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any fear, fainting, or staggering, will doubtless be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, before it be pondered.</p>
   <p>But if such thoughts can be brought to endure but the calling back a while, to the reexamining of the groundes they are built on: the hollowness of them will soone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray it self. For be it graunted, that sound learning and good conscience is this mans praise and priviledge above the most of his fellow-champions (though this defense doth so beare it selfe on the former, that it giveth small proof of the later) yet that doth not free him from dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deceit and errour; especially in quaestions of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which have on the one side so much to sway with beside the cause, and on the other, nothing but naked &amp; despised truth. Neyther can it be thought, that imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all desire and search of truth, did so take up his minde in all this enterprize, as that blinding praejudice had no place in it. Let the wise consider &amp; give sentence, whether he that was the sonne of a Bishop, the servant or Chaplain of a Bishop, and that none of the best, the favourite also
<pb facs="159"/> of a third Bishop, whose consecration he desired to grace, one that sought needily to raise himself in Bishops favour; whether such a man (I say) be likely to preach and write in these causes even to the overflowing of passion, with a minde so cleare and free from prejudice!</p>
   <p>It is the most charitable excuse that can probablie be affoarded to diverse of this guise, that such beames as those are doe lie in their eyes, which hinder their sight where the light is cleare. Nay most of our climers doe look so strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon these questions, as if their eyes stood cleane awry. Platerus reporteth of a Germane soldjer, that being shott in the face, he had his eye so turned, and his nose so peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that alwayes after his eye could see nothing but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the passages of his nose. Iust such a shot have these men received frō the world; all that they see is thorough their nose: and except they can smell some profit or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment by the way, their eyes will not serve them to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of any thing. I affirme not this of Doct. Downame, (though he among other alehouse jests which he rudely breakes upon his adversarie, doth tell him of seeing to his nose end) yet he hath also plainely bewrayed, that he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked through a false glasse of his owne imagination, when viewing the scriptures, he spied such a Church &amp; Bishop in them, as in his book he tels us of. The Phylosophers wright of certain colours, which they call <hi>intentionall,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are not such in deed as they seeme to be: as when thorough a glasse that is red or greene, the bodies adjoyning doe appear so also. Such a glasse it was without doubt that made this man to think that he saw an <hi>intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> Church and an <hi>intentionall</hi> Bishop, that vvere diocesan and provinciall, such as the Popish and English are, <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally</hi> as he saith, though not really and truely. The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Doctors make too too much of intention in giving of orders &amp; other sacraments: yet that is an intention answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="159"/> to the words pronounced. But now we are told of an intention that the state of all Churches dependeth upon, which was not expressed by any words; but so farre fecht and hardly gathered, that it giveth suspition of such a trick as once was taught Themistocles, by a man of Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia; that because he might not take the tables away where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a law was engraven, he would therfore turn them upside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downe, which was as good as to take them quite away? for when the institution of a Church and Bishop which is found in the scriptures may not be wholly removed, the next course is to give it a turne, by carying the intention to a contrary point. To such strange shiftes they must needs be driven, which will stretch the scriptures, as sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> leather, with their teeth, that they may bring them to agree with humane inventions.</p>
   <p>The vnlikelinesse of this devised intention, will easily appeare to any, but him which hath been so accustomed to cathedrall churches, that every thing sounds in his head to the tune of the organs that he hath heard there.</p>
   <p>The papist, he telleth us (just as the organs goe at Rome) <note place="margin">Boz. de jur. nat. &amp; div. eccl. pot. l. 1. c. 18.</note> that the extent of a Byshops jurisdiction is not any wayes limited, but by the Popes appointment; his power of it selfe indifferently reaching over all the world. Our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latists, they would perswade us (to the tune of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) that neyther Church nor Byshop hath his bounds determined by the Pope, nor yet by Christ in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but left to the pleasure of Princes, for to be cast in one mowld with the civill state. Now the plaine Christian finding nothing but humane uncerteinties in eyther of these devises, he contenteth himselfe with plaine song, &amp; knowing that Christ hath appointed Christians to gather themselves into such societies as may assemble togither for the worship of God, and that unto such he hath given their peculiar Pastors, he (I say) in his simplicity, calleth these
<pb facs="160"/> assemblies the churches of Christ, and these pastors his Bishops, as for other intentions, extentions, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions, which come from men, he dares not receive them, for fear they should lead him from that certainty he findeth in Christs institution, and leave him floating amōg mens presumptions.</p>
   <p>Besides, it must needs seeme strange to a serious well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning Christian, when it shall be told him, as these Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall men will have it, that his pastor whom he depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth upon at home, hath not the charge of his sowl com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him from Christ, who appointed no Bishops nor Presbyters but Diocesan; that the L. Bishop vvhom he never savv, is properly his pastor, the parish minister be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the Bishops curate or vice-gerent, and therefore standing no further bound then as the Bishop appointeth; so that by his permission he may be a non-resident, or resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there he may onely read divine service (so the crosse &amp; surplus be not neglected) or howsoever he makes his agreement. Will not this seeme uncouth to simple men, who have alwaies been told of a straighter bond to tie their ministers unto dutie? especially when they shall hear on the other side, their ovvn dutie so strictly urged, of keeping to their minister though he be but a reader, of paying al tithes to him even by Gods appointment, though he never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him to whom they are payd? certainly if Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Sumners brought not more terrible argumentes from the carnall courts, then D. Downame hath from holy scripture to prove &amp; perswade these paradoxes with, there must a new generatiō arise, that knew not the L. nor what he hath done for Israel, before they would be embraced.</p>
   <p>As for the scripture proofes which are gathered by him, the foundation or principall corner-stone of them, which he deemed to lie in his text, that is utterly dashed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part. Which being done, the rest that dependeth on
<pb facs="160"/> that, were ready to fall of themselves. Yet it hath pleased his adversary, for their more thorough scattering, in this second part to give every one his severall knock. A labour not necessary, were it not that the insolent confidence wherevvith they are avouched, hath I knovv not how ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and scared some vveak and fearfull mindes, but for the better bringing both of him &amp; them to themselves againe, that course is taken, then which there is no shorter or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recter. For when the question is, vvhat Church &amp; Bishop is Apostolicall, the next vvay is, to search the scriptures, &amp; hear vvhat they say of themselves, before vve regard what fathers or councels doe make them say. D. Dovvname therefore hath no reason to take it unkindely (which yet I knovv he vvill) at his adversaries hand, that he hath for evidence divided the house, causing holy scriptures to goe by themselves in this second part of his Reply, remitting the voices of men to the last place, that they also may speak by themselves. When divine &amp; humane suffrages are shuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled togither in one, the simple hearer perceiving a sound which seemes glorious to him, though they be men that speak, yet he is presently ready to cry as the people did to Herod, <hi>the voice of God and not of man.</hi> In confidence of this stratageme, the beggerly ceremonies which we borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed of Papists have been lately mainteyned as Apostolical.</p>
   <p>The methode therefore which this writer hath followed, is for the readers good. His answers are such as wil speak for themselves. Onely this I may forespeak, in their behalf, that if they seem (as in the former part I feare they will) in the logicall termes and formes of reasoning, to be over troublesom for the cōmō reader; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of that blame must rest vpon the defense, which they were bound to follow. For the defendant taking it too much in scorne, that his logick (wherein of all other thinges he would be thought to excel) was somewhat impeached by his Refuters analysis, be did so vehemently strive to maintaine that part of his credite, that his Refuter was forced to give him that triall which such logicians trust to. The studious reader will beare with this necessity, and seek out the truth, though it lie among thornes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>