<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣FVLL, MASTER Thomas Smith, Sheriffe of the honorable Citie of London, and Gouernor of the famous companie of the English Marchants trading to the East Indies, Sumatra, Iava, the Isles of the Malucos, Banda, and the rich and mightie Kingdome of Chyna: and to the right VVorshipfull the Aldermen, and the rest of the Commit∣ties and societie of the said corporation. William Walker vvisheth all prosperitie and happie successe.</title>
           <author>Walker, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113132_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08052</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18417</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113132</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣FVLL, MASTER Thomas Smith, Sheriffe of the honorable Citie of London, and Gouernor of the famous companie of the English Marchants trading to the East Indies, Sumatra, Iava, the Isles of the Malucos, Banda, and the rich and mightie Kingdome of Chyna: and to the right VVorshipfull the Aldermen, and the rest of the Commit∣ties and societie of the said corporation. William Walker vvisheth all prosperitie and happie successe.</title>
                 <author>Walker, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The iournall, or dayly register, contayning a true manifestation, and historicall declaration of the voyage, accomplished by eight shippes of Amsterdam, vnder the conduct of Iacob Corneliszen Neck Admirall, &amp; Wybrandt van Warwick Vice-Admirall, which sayled from Amsterdam the first day of March, 1598 : Shewing the course they kept, and what other notable matters happened vnto them in the sayd voyage</title>
                 <author>Neck, Jacob Conelissoon van</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Flasket, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 58, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="1" facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL, MASTER Thomas Smith, Sheriffe of the honorable Citie of London, and Gouernor of the famous companie of the English Marchants trading to the <hi>East Indies, Sumatra, Iava,</hi> the Isles of the <hi>Malucos, Banda,</hi> and the rich and mightie Kingdome of <hi>Chyna:</hi> and to the <hi>right VVorshipfull the Aldermen, and the rest of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and societie of the said corporation.</hi> William Walker <hi>vvisheth all prosperitie and happie successe.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, who so takes but a sleight surueigh of the present state of things, must needes be forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge both the great and generall benefite likelie to ensue of this your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>East Indie</hi> voyage, the successe prouing answerable to these forward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings: and also the danger and losse on your parte, if it should (which God defend) fall out otherwise then well.</p>
   <p>The benefit is most apparant, if we do but consider either the necessitie of the enterprise, or the gaine depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereon. That the searching of new trades, &amp; aboue all other, this to the <hi>East Indies,</hi> is more then necessary, both the restraint of traffique in the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> dominions, and also the vnder-rate of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> spices, in regarde of those brought out of the <hi>Indies</hi> by the way of <hi>Turkie,</hi> doe too plainelie demonstrate. Hereunto you may adde the venting of diuers naturall commodities, which otherwise would lye dead, and likewise the employment of tall and seruiceable Ships, and the increase of our Marriners knowledge in Nauigation: the gaine both to the augmenting of her Maiesties Customes, and the enriching of all the Aduenturers cannot chuse (as your selues best knowe) but proue in time extraordinarie Wherein, though I were silent, yet the <hi>Portugale</hi> Carracks, and within these few yeares also the Ships of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> doe in a manner proclaime so much to all the world.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
The danger in attempting this action no man can doubt of: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing subiect to like difficulties and misaduentures with other honorable exploytes of the same kinde, and in that respect also farre more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and praise-worthie: and so the losse (if matters should mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrie, which God forbid) cannot be little, seeing the charges haue been so great.</p>
   <p>These considerations (right Worshipfull) being seconded by the perswasion of M. <hi>Richard Hacluyt,</hi> a man for his matchles industrie in collecting the <hi>English Voyages,</hi> most incomparably wel deseruing of this state, preuailed so much with me, that being stirred vp with the zeale of a true <hi>Patriot</hi> or well willer to my natiue Countrie, I could not lesse doe, then cast into your <hi>East Indie</hi> treasurie this poore myte, I meane my labour in translating this little pamphlet, which containeth matter so agreeable and pertinent to this your present purpose.</p>
   <p>For herein the <hi>Hollanders</hi> (who borrowed a great part of their light <note place="margin">All these Ʋoya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and sundrie other important discourses of the <hi>East Indies, Pegu, China,</hi> the <hi>Malucos, Philippinas</hi> and <hi>Iapan,</hi> are to be found in the second and third volumes of M. <hi>Hakluyts</hi> English Ʋoya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</note> from vs, namely out of the famous Voyages of Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Thomas Candish,</hi> Master <hi>Iames Lancaster, Ralph Fitch,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Stephans,</hi> their forerunners in those parts, and haue had speciall assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in their late Nauigations by the meanes of Master <hi>Iohn Dauies,</hi> Master <hi>Timothie Shotton,</hi> and other skilfull Pylots of our Nation) doe in ample manner requite vs with the like: acquainting vs with their Voyages, discoueries and dangers, both outward and homeward; with their negotiation and traffique at <hi>Iava,</hi> the <hi>Malucos,</hi> and other places, with the disposition of the naturall inhabitance, and the slye sullen practises of the <hi>Portugals,</hi> and likewise with the quantie and value of Spices and other commodities which they brought home.</p>
   <p>Heere therefore your Captaines, Masters, and Factors (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they are very sufficiently informed alreadie) may in some sorte be directed how to shape their course to auoide many perrils, and to enioy seuerall kindes of Marchandize for which you send them.</p>
   <p>And albeit both your selues and they also, in regarde of your deepe insight and experience in these matters, may seeme not much to stand in neede of this my endeuour, yet remembring an olde rule in lawe, that <hi>Superabundans cautela non nocet:</hi> sure I was, that some good might come hereof, but harme none at all.</p>
   <p>It may please you therefore (right Worshipfull) to take it in kinde part, if not for the worthines of the matter, yet for the sincere intent of him that offers it, who in this, and in all other your worthie disseignes, wisheth you most prosperous successe, and stands continuallie deuoted to your seruice.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships most vnfainedly affected, WILLIAM WALKER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>