<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ THE PREFACE OF the Slaunders against the Doctrine of Iohn Caluin, (or rather of euery faithfull Congregation) of the secrete Prouidence of God.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113313_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09918</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2018.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113313</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ THE PREFACE OF the Slaunders against the Doctrine of Iohn Caluin, (or rather of euery faithfull Congregation) of the secrete Prouidence of God.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An euident display of Popish practises, or patched Pelagianisme : Wherein is mightelie cleared the soueraigne truth of Gods eternall predestination, the stayd groundworke of oure most assured safetie by Christ. Written in Latin by that reuerend father, mayster Theodore Beza, and now lately Englished by VV.H. preacher of the Gospell</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 263, that is 275, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ THE PREFACE OF the Slaunders against the Doctrine of Iohn Caluin, (or rather of euery faithfull Congregation) of the secrete Prouidence of God.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HY Doctrine, Iohn Caluine, (a man muche renowmed in all the worlde) hath many fauourers, but therewithall the same in like sort hath many aduersaries. But I who wishe there may be one doctrine as there is one trueth, and all to consente therevnto, if it maye bee, haue thoughte conuenient to admonishe thee familiarly of those things whiche are vsually bruyted agaynst thy doctrine, that if they be false, thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest refute them, and sende thy refutation to vs, that we maye the rather withstande them, and do it with suche proofes as the people maye vnderstande. And there be many things wherein many dissent from thee: but for the present, (leauing the rest to some other conuenient time) I will deale with thee of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Destinie or Predestination: bicause both this Article mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth much controuersie in the Church, which we wish may be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed: and also the Aduersaries reasons in this Argument seeme to be suche, as can not be refelled by those Bookes whiche hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto thou haste published.</p>
   <p>There are caried here and there of this matter certayne Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles gathered out of thy bookes, whiche I will heere tumultuously set downe, and then I will shewe those things which vsually are alleaged agaynst euery of them, that thou mayste the rather see where vnto to answere.</p>
   <div type="answer">
      <p>
         <hi>THE ANSVVERE.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT</hi> we haue euer endeuored to set forth that doctrine whiche is not oures, but Iesus Christes, in such sorte that we might winne many to the delight and loue thereof, yet arte thou Sycophant much deceyued, if thou thinkest that wée
<pb n="2" facs="6"/>stande vpon the multitude eyther of foes or fauourers. For neither are we so much vnskilfull of the state of men, or vnmindefull of the very wordes of Christe, that wée should forget that there haue bene euer moe founde who haue withstoode the truth, than defended it. Thou truely, as I perceyue, bethinkyng thy selfe of some wise preface, haste chosen that one, whiche did moste accorde with thy nature and inclination: for so almoste it falleth amongst men, especially of guiltie consciences, that they déeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by their owne disposition. Therefore bycause thou (shrowding thy selfe as it were vnder the shadowe of thy pretended modestie) dost of olde ayme at this marke, that the moste may thinke thée some body, haste in déede dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that we are grieued with the same infirmitie, and therfore that thou couldst not worke vs a greater dispite, than if with a certaine sottishe kinde of chattering thou mightest pretend to haue done this as bewayling our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie, &amp; carefull for the defence of our cause, thou shouldest friendly &amp; familiarly write vnto vs. But in déede we mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel that any man so practised in deceit, could so forget him self, as not to think that men would straight enquire how it could be, that in so waightie a matter writing so famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly to thy friends, thou shouldst suppresse thy name. But what if they also should know that which is manifest to vs, that thou hast not letted but that these broched Slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders might haue bin bruted in all the worlde, before we should heare any whit of thē; truly they would not doubt to report thée, as mostly all other diuine things, so also to haue lewdly &amp; wickedly abused the sacred name of amity. But we, if thou knowest it not, do leaue for thée to regard the multitude of fauourers: thine (I say) it shal be for vs. For neither doe we defende that cause, wherin thou art worth one rushe. And thou art the very man (albeit this time hath others) whose protection if the truth require it,
<pb n="3" facs="6"/>should do in such sort, as if the improuident shéepe should thinke them selues in safetie under the defence of some gréedie Wolfe. Truely thou art muche deceyued if thou supposest thou canst go vnknowne, thy trifling scurilitie, thy foolish ambition, thy babbling subtilties, thy great fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, thy indeuour voyde of all godlynesse, finally thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable vanitie in euery parts of this writing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth it selfe. All which as thou hast them common with manye, yet so they doe apparantly shewe forth in thée, that whether thou termest thy selfe Bellius, or Theophilus, or <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> no body, finally whatsoeuer Phys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie thou dost pretende, yet those thine entries bewray thée to be a Cumane Asse. Whom therfore thinkest thou to be so sadde that would not deride thée, or so pleasaunt that would not be in fume with thée, if he should heare thée giuing out that thou wishest nothing more than one doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine? Thou (I say) who first presumedst to bring into these partes where the diuine light hath shined, a freshe Academicall <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, great doubt, or impossibilitie to conceyue. But in déede is this the way and meane to establishe one doctrine, to reporte the worde of God to be so doubtfull and vncertayne, that which way soeuer thou takest it, it suffiseth not to decide the controuersies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and we must looke for some other newe reuelation from heauen: For thou mayst easily recount all these, sith thou haste so often written them. Away with this hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie: why commest thou not out of thy lurking corners? why doste thou hyde thy name? why doste thou not bidde open warre to the trueth? For truely thou canst not now be vnknowen: and though it be agaynst our willes, thine obstinacie will bring to passe that we shall name thée.</p>
      <p>Thou requirest of vs proofes that the people may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande. We aunswere, that we professe that doctrine whiche can séeme to the worlde nothing but foolishnesse,
<pb n="4" facs="7"/>And howe true this aunswere is, we may very well ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the example of Christ himselfe. For except he sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thée, whom may we thinke shall? But thou muste néedes confesse that those people did very little profite in his doctrine, which continually followed him, when those twelue his dearest familiar friends, to whome he impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his secrete mysteries, when he their master was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently to ascende into heauen, séemed not sufficiently to haue knowen what is the nature of his kingdome.</p>
      <p>But I knowe where vpon thou standest. Bicause thou haste read that the wisedome of God is hidde from the wise and prudent of this worlde, therefore howe muche the more any man is vnskilfull of good artes &amp; discipline, so muche the rather thou déemest him worthy to be iudge of diuine mysteries. Thou therfore most allowest y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mind of the multitude, and I know not what vulgar kinde of proofe doth best please thée: for neither doest thou it (as I thinke) as if thou diddest in déede beléeue it were so, but that in déede thou mayest knowe more to deceyue the vnskilfull &amp; common multitude. But if thou art ignorant <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, the wisedome of the fleshe is the very thing that letteth vs to sée the light of God: neither is it only in those wise men, but in euery one. Who soeuer is subiect to this disease (as all be that are not renued of the spirite) thou labourest in vayne to teache him the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Christian Religion, whether thou shouldst maffle with the multitude, or labourest to be wise with the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that is, to doate of purpose. We must receiue these things by fayth. But fayth is the gift of God, &amp; compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth arguments not deuised of our owne brayne, but takē out of the word of God: which if thou dost not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stād, ther is yet no cause why thou shouldst blame the too much darkenes of things, or require more perspicuitie in Caluin, or any other. Thou thy selfe hast within thée that
<pb n="5" facs="7"/>darknes, which causeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou art blind in the cleare light. Thou contemnest the writings of learned men, ere thou comost to them, not that thou mayst learne, but that thou mayst reproue them. Thus <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> selfloue, this pride doth blinde thée, howsoeuer thou doest shadow these with a certaine false counterfayte of libertie and simplicitie. Giue glory to God, &amp; pray him hartely that he will open thine eyes: then shalt thou proue those arguments to be both playne, euident and necessarie, whiche now thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouest as weake and beggerly. Thou saydest before that thou hadst determined to deale of that one argument of Destinie, or Predestination. We truly who haue long si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence much hearde thée to be out of measure impudent, and by experience knowe it to be so, doe yet maruell that thine impudencie could be so great, that thou durst obiect to Caluine that hatefull name of Destinie: wherof what he hath tofore written, it shall not repent vs to set downe in his owne wordes, both bicause, albeit thou arte full of enuie, they are excellently, plainely, learnedly and godly written: &amp; also that by the entrance, euery one may know, with what faithfull minde thou vndertookest this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thus therfore saith Caluine: <q>Those that endeuour to worke despite to this doctrine, doe falsly vrge that it is the Stoickes opinion of Destinie:<note place="margin">Chrys. Iust. cap. 14. par. 40.</note> whiche also was obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to Augustine in his time. Albeit we contende of wordes against our will, yet we admitte not in any wise the name of Destinie, bothe bycause of that kinde whose prophane straungnesse Paule hath taught vs to auoyde, and also bicause they indeuour to burthen Gods truthe with the hatred of it.</q> These hath Caluine written in so many words, which if thou diddest not know, what rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is it to reproue that thou knewest not? but if in déede thou diddest, thē what impudencie was it to charge him with that crime whiche thy selfe knewest to be false?
<pb n="6" facs="8"/>
         <q>But here I will pleasure thée. For thou wilt say it is not Destinie in name, but in effect. It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o. Heare therefore what in the same place he adioyneth: The very opinion of the Stoiks (sayth he) is falsly &amp; malitiously obiected vnto vs. For we deuise not with the Stoicks a necessitie of the perpetuall bonde of causes, and of a certaine intricate or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which is contemned in nature: but we determine God the arbiter and moderator of all things, who in his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wisedome hath before all worldes decreed that hée would doe, and now in his power accōplisheth that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, wherevpon we affirme that not onely heauen and earth and insensible creatures, but also the purposes and myndes of men to be so gouerned by his prouidence, that they are brought to that ende whiche is determined of the same.</q> And then he addeth, by what meanes if thou shouldest consider the seconde causes by themselues, any thyng may come bothe at aduenture, and vnlooked for. Whiche disputations if thou vnderstandest not, thou oughtest to blame thy selfe, who at the least knowest not by <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Plutarche;</hi> what was the controuersie of <hi>Chrysippus</hi> and <hi>Diodorus.</hi> But what of these? verily that all may sée howe muche credite is to be gyuen to that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser, whiche so shamefully lyeth in the very begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, saying that euery and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very worste in that part of their speache are wonte to pretende some shewe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie. For that whiche concerneth the matter it selfe wée will further examine in his place. At laste thou ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest that wherein veryly thou haste excéeded thy selfe, and in déede thou séemest to haue well obserued this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Rothorique, that those thyngs whiche wée would moste firmely shoulde bée kepte in minde with the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, may bée spoken in the laste place. There are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried aboute (thou sayest) of this argument certaine Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>gathered out of thy bookes which I will tumultuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sette downe. And, is it so, a greate chaunter of the truthe, that thou shouldest take suche paynes to make tumultes in the Churche of GOD? Is it so, (I say) waste thou not well in thy wittes, that thou shouldest forgette to aske of these rogues, that carrie aboute these Slaunders, whether they woulde firste with sufficient witnesses proue these thyngs they caried, to be true? For tell mée what wouldest thou answere if I shoulde one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly say that all these are false whiche are obiected against Caluine. Truely thou wouldest eyther suddenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse thy selfe a false accuser, whiche thou clokest as well as thou canste: or truely thou wouldest be constrayned thy selfe to accuse thyne owne foolishnesse, whiche wilt thynke that thou oughtest to inquyre whether the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation were iuste or vniuste, then whether it were true or false. And in déede, as thou shalte shortly vnderstand, the moste parte of these Articles (as thou callest them) is suche stuffe, that bare deniall is sufficient.</p>
      <p>But goe too, that great care to reconcile the Churche hath euen nourisht thée. And those that knowe thée say thou arte a simple man, so that often tymes thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est not whether thou speake with or agaynst thy selfe, therefore in déede it shall not bée amisse that wée beare with thy infirmitie of nature. Moreouer thou beyng so good a manne and so muche our friende, thou couldest not choose but bée muche chaffed when thou heardest those Churches wherein thou haste bene nourished, and those menne whose liberalitie hath long done thée good, to be charged with such impietie. Therfore thou diddest that is too muche proper to fumishe men, sodaynly to sette thy self to shuffle in our cause: and when thou hadst no sufficient defence, thou wouldest certifie vs of the whole mater. So it is, that the greatest matter esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>thée, that is, to approue how true the accusation was. It were pitie but thou shouldest be pardoned of this too. But I pray thée, what meanest thou by this, to deale <hi>Tus multuously</hi> in so waighty a cause? Beware in déede that some suspect thée not (as men be no fooles now) to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this matter in very good sooth, and in earnest. But no doubte, as thou arte craftie inough, thou haste an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere readie, publishe it therefore, that whilest thou inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourest to pleasure thy friends, thou lose the credite both of wisedome and honestie.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>