<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull the towardly young Gentleman, and of great good hopes, M. William Caven∣dish, sonne and heire to the right Hono∣rable William, Lord Cavendish, increase of all true honour and happines is most har∣tily wished.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113787_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09077</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1936</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113787</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull the towardly young Gentleman, and of great good hopes, M. William Caven∣dish, sonne and heire to the right Hono∣rable William, Lord Cavendish, increase of all true honour and happines is most har∣tily wished.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A double catechisme : one more large, following the order of the common authorized catechisme, and an exposition thereof: now this second time published: the other shorter for the weaker sort: both set forth for the benefit of Christian friends and wel-willers. By Richard Bernard, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at Worsop in Nottingham-shire</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 43, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull the towardly young Gentleman, and of great good hopes, <hi>M. William Caven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish,</hi> sonne and heire to the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>William,</hi> Lord <hi>Cavendish,</hi> increase of all true honour and happines is most har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wished.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Worshipfull, it is written of one, a kings sonne, that he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked 3. things at Gods hands, outward pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and such glorie as shold be neither false nor fained. What more to be happy? The first of these you haue by birth, and your parents wealth &amp; honor: the second, <hi>Salomon</hi> tels you, how you may haue, by the getting &amp; keeping a <hi>good conscience,</hi> which is a continual feast: and the third is purchased for you by Christ, if you by faith can take hold of him, by whom (which is the true and greatest glorie) we are made the sonnes of
<pb facs="3"/> God, and coheires with him of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise of God, and the vnspeakable ioyes thereof. All these three must concurre to make a man blessed: no happinesse in the first without the second: no soundnesse in the second to abide without the third. Loose Christ, a dew conscience comforts: and outward goods and honour without inward health of grace, is an estate car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of estimation, but indeed hopelesse of the Saints blessed condition. Great wealth, &amp; noble birth, without the soules spirituall breath, is as a shippe vnder full saile in a tempestuous Sea without sterne or Pylote: a case most daungerous: more like it is there should be shipwracke, than that it should come in safety to the hauen. Your ship is not yet at the sea, you are but launching out, hitherto you haue lyen in harbour: ballance your soule with sound knowledge, and holy affections before you aduenture: take with you your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision, and be sure you season your flesh with the salt of Gods word, lest it corrupt at sea, and you want necessaries, and be forced to go a shore before you come vnto your determined place.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth vs, that the young man which cheareth his heart vp in the dayes
<pb facs="3"/> of his youth, to walke in the euill waies thereof, and in the sight of his eyes, must know, that for these things <hi>God will bring him to iudgement:</hi> and therefore he adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth him to remember his Creator in the dayes of his strength, before the time come, when he shall confesse, that sinne hath as much left him, as he it. Surely, Sir, if you betimes, as I hope you do, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord, and seeke him, as <hi>Dauid</hi> said to the child <hi>Salomon,</hi> he will be found of you: which he of his mercy graunt: but if you forsake him, he will forsake you; which God of his goodnesse forbid. The aduancement of <hi>Ioseph</hi> amongst <hi>Pharaoes</hi> Princes, and <hi>Daniels</hi> honour aboue the great Bassaes of Babylon, may shew you the truth of the one: and that young mans miserable end, beautifull <hi>Absolon,</hi> and <hi>Dauids</hi> deare sonne, may ratifie the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of the other. Gods fauour is the fountaine of blisse, and in those onely he delighteth that feare him.</p>
   <p>The good tokens of your good affectiō towards me, and towards the preachers of Gods word, the loue you do shew to further the passage of the Gospell, both in word and liberall deeds, hath mooued me to offer this my labour vnto you: both
<pb facs="4"/> to testifie my thankfulnesse, and to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest vnto the world our good hopes of you, which I desire that you may daily occasion by holy fruites of obedience to be iustified of many, to Gods glory and your owne welfare.</p>
   <p>The Lord Almightie protect you and that honorable house whereof you are, and enlarge the name thereof, as with earthly renowne, so euer much more with spirituall blessings, that it wishing well to the Israel of God, peace and mercie may be vpon it: and the louing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God now shine vpon all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that hartily desire the welfare of Sion, and the peace of Ierusalem for euer.</p>
   <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Worsop,</hi>
         <date>the 28. of <hi>Nouember.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships euery way readie in all things in Christ Iesus, <hi>Richard Bernard.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>