<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The translatour of this worke vnto a certayne frende of his, sendeth gre∣tynge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1534</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113316_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16003</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2792</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113316</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The translatour of this worke vnto a certayne frende of his, sendeth gre∣tynge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epistle of the p [ro] phete Hieremie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Redman, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Redman, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Southwark</pubPlace>
                    <date>1534</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_friend">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶The translatour of this worke vnto a certayne frende of his, sendeth gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SYr</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>after most hartie recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, it may lyke you to vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stande that I write vnto you at this tyme for the accomplysshement of my promyse, for you remembre (I am sure) that in our laste cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication had together, you desyred effectually to knowe myne opinion concernynge Ymagery, wherin at that tyme, thoughe {per}aduenture for defaute of lerning, I was not able to satisfie your mynde, yet for as moche as at this day, the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is put in question, and dyuers great lerned mē do vary in opiniōs vpon the same, I thought it not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cōueniēt to take some further payne for to enserche the treuthe therof. And so perusynge dyuers great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
<pb facs="3"/> I fortuned in the redyng of the olde testamēt, otherwyse called the Byble, to fynde out y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sixte chap. of Baruch the prophete, whiche by cause it entreateth principally and all together of Ymagerye, for the satisfieng of your desyre, I transla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; drewe in to englysshe as nere as I myght, accordyng to the pure truthe of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> texte: wherby, I doubt nothyng, but you shalbe clerely put out of all doubte and errour / if ye can fynde in your harte to bestowe a lytle of your leasure in the reding of hit. For I do aduertise you not onely rede it / but also exactely and throughly to ponder &amp; marke euery poynt therof. And for the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my mynde herin / I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thought that for bicause these Ymages lacke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vse of the .v. sensis, and besydes that in processe of tyme do both corrupte and consume lyke
<pb facs="3"/> as dothe golde / syluer / stone / and wodde / and the stuffe and mattiere wherof they be made, I suppose thē to haue none other supernaturall vertue / than they had before they were made into Ymages. And not withstandyng that there hap some true and vnfayned myracles to be done at the places wher suche yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be worshypped / yet I thynke that they be not done by the vertue of those ymages / nor of god for the ymages sake / but to thentent that the people shuld know y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the saynt{is}, whom thymages do represent and bringe vnto our remēbrance, were y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true &amp; faythfull seruantes of god in prechyng &amp; teachyng his worde. But I wyll deteyne you no longer from the redynge of Baruch his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle, wherin (bicause it is the very scripture &amp; worde of god) you shall perceyue the effecte of this matter
<pb facs="4"/> moche better than I or any other can open or declare vnto you. And thus fare ye well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>