<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faultes escaped in the printing, to be corrected. In the first Part.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113275_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08326</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18658</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113275</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faultes escaped in the printing, to be corrected. In the first Part.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An antidote or treatise of thirty controuersies : vvith a large discourse of the Church. In which the soueraigne truth of Catholike doctrine, is faythfully deliuered: against the pestiferous writinges of all English sectaryes. And in particuler, against D. Whitaker, D. Fulke, D. Reynolds, D. Bilson, D. Robert Abbot, D. Sparkes, and D. Field, the chiefe vpholders, some of Protestancy, some of puritanisme, some of both. Deuided into three partes. By S.N. Doctour of Diuinity. The first part</title>
                 <author>S. N. (Sylvester Norris)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 335, 1, 8, 207, that is 307, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="179"/>
   <head>Faultes escaped in the printing, to be corrected. <hi>In the first Part.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>IN the Epist. to the Reader. pag. 3. line 3. <hi>ferrret euery one out.</hi> reade <hi>ferret them out of euery &amp;c.</hi> Ibid. Epist. pag. 4. l. 14. <hi>occosion.</hi> reade <hi>occasion.</hi> Pag. 7. l. 24. on. <hi>reade</hi> of. pag 34. l. 5. <hi>Canon. the Canon.</hi> pag. 40 l. 29. one another. to one another. pag. 49. l. 25. which. with. pag. 50 l. 17. out the. <hi>reade</hi> out of the. pag. 51. l. 13. their. other. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 28. is. it pag. 74. l 6. depth. the depth. pag 80. l. 1. waiteth writeth, pag. 82. l. 30. in. the. pag. 84. l. 6. same substance. same in substance. pag. 91. l. 9. corruption. incorruption. pag. 95 l. 11. <hi>euen. euer.</hi> pag. 104. l. penult. glorifieth. glorieth. pag. 110. l. 18 purchased. purchase. pag. 11o. l. 18. cruell a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ell. pag 15. l. 15. of. to. Ibid. line. 28 clamous. clamorous. pag 136. l. 1. refragable. irrefragable. pag. 115. 11. <hi>glorifieth. glorify,</hi> pag. 188. l. 5. Not. Nor. pag. 190. l. 1. out these. out of these. pag. 201. l. 25. others. other. pag 207. l. 19. <hi>Carninall. Cardinall.</hi> pag. 221. l. 14. But. By. pag. 227. 9. <hi>Leo.</hi> of <hi>Leo.</hi> pag. 229. l. 5. <hi>makes. markes.</hi> Ibid. l. 29. <hi>Paul not bad. Paul had not had.</hi> pag. 233. l. 9. stying. styrring. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. vlt. <hi>Crinthus. Cerinthus.</hi> pag. 237. l. 29. sinne. signe. pag. 238. l. 1. <hi>partes. are partes.</hi> pag. 239. l. 3. far. and far. pag. 240 l. 15. worships. worship. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 24. <hi>Abias. Abdias.</hi> pag. 241. l 15. lawfull awfull. pag. 242. l. 4. as curteous. as a courteous. Ibid. l. 20. nuture. nurture. pag. 245. l. 16. sonne. sonnes I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. l 29. no. not. pag 246. l. 27 <hi>honour. I honour.</hi> pag 252. Image Christ. Image of Christ. pag. 263. l. 20. expect from. expect it from pag. 277. l. 3. and. of pag. 278. l. 19. <hi>a as. as a.</hi> pag. 275. l. 15. <hi>deleatur</hi> the. pag. 285. l. 8. some. solemne. pag. 331 l. 3. of the Iudgement. of the day of Iudgement. pag. 333. l. 26. prayers. prayers. pag. 335. l. 21. <hi>deleatur</hi> of.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Other lesse faultes, by reason of the obsoure Copy in many places, &amp; absence of the Authour, the Reader himselfe will easily obserue, and courleously correct as he readeth.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>