<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>H., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113744_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22478b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113744</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>H., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The brides longing for her bride-groomes second comming : A sermon preached at the funerall of the right worshipfull, Sir Thomas Crevv, knight, sergeant at law to his maiestie. By the late learned and reverend divine, Rich. Sibs</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Langham, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 138 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Loving Readers:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oe here the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of that ancient adage, <hi>quod differtur, non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur,</hi> for long look't for comes at last. That which before a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and sad assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, was publikely preached and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the eares of some, is now printed
<pb facs="3"/>
and committed to the eyes of all that have a minde to reade it; which thing hath with a long and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing desire bin wished and waited for by sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry. This Funeral ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bespake your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving and respecting of it in a double consideration, each of which, in my opinion, hath an important, rare, and singular pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Behold, first the Man; secondly, the matter. The Man by
<pb facs="3"/>
whom, and the man for whom, it was made: the one that worthy Divine, Dr <hi>Sibs,</hi> who in his life time intended and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved it for the presse, as it now comes forth; the other that Worshipful Serjeant, Sir <hi>Thomas Crew,</hi> men of more then ordinary worth and goodnesse; whom to name is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to those that knew them: for if I should enter into a particular discourse,
<pb facs="4"/>
and discovery of their deserved worth, I feare I should more disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour my undertakings, and wrong your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, then in any proportion answer the excellency of two such worthy Theames. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for the matter, as the occasion &amp; mens expectations were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, so shal you finde his preparation; Read, &amp; then judge. It sweetly, and to the life sets forth the duty, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and disposition of
<pb facs="4"/>
the Church, &amp; Spouse of Christ, Ecchoing a faithful and prayerful <hi>Amen,</hi> to all the truths of God, especially to the precious promises, and chiefly to that promise of promises, Christs second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; which in cold bloud, undauntedly to desire, is an unfallible marke of a true and through cōvert: which that we may doe, wee must make sure our es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pousall to Christ here, and get to be clad with
<pb facs="5"/>
the wedding garment of faith, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, teaching us to ponder &amp; pray much, and then admirable shall be our confident standing before God; our rich hope, our qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnesse and hearts ease, our joy, as if wee had one foot in heaven al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Wee shall bee able with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to cast downe our gantlet, and bid defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Divels, to men, to height, to depth, to things present, and
<pb facs="5"/>
things to come. If all the hearts in the world were one Heart, it could not comprehend those rich blessings, wherewith true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians are richly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, and those spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ioyes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts which shall rain upon them in sweet showers from heaven: rich they are in hand, but richer in hope: rich in possession, but richer in reversion. For what ravishing Ioy, what inexplicable
<pb facs="6"/>
sweetnesse shal then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting possesse our soules? when as wee who have bin a long time contracted to our Lord &amp; husband, shall see that blessed time come, when we shall have that glorious marriage between him and us, really and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally solemnized, in the presence of God, and his holy Angels, and shall have the fruition of him and all his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, and enioy such heavenly fellowship,
<pb facs="6"/>
familiarity &amp; acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendantly above all the sweetest relations here below, I say with him who is <hi>The Prince of Peace, the King of glory, yea the very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Heaven and Earth, the expresse image of his Fathers person, in whom those things which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible are seene, the brightnesse of everlasting light, the undefiled mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Maiesty of God; and the desire of all Nations.</hi> Blessed are
<pb facs="7"/>
they which are called to the marriage sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 9 Wherunto that you may be admitted as a welcome guest, you must both know and practice, what in this Treatise is contained. To conclude, I am bold therefore in the cause of Gods honour, and your salvation, to intreat you (as ever you would have interest in <hi>Christs</hi> blood and bles sednesse, sufferings and satisfactions; as you
<pb facs="7"/>
meane to have any Fellowship or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in Heaven, with the Blessed Saints and Angels; as you intend to have any part in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which the <hi>Lord Iesus</hi> hath purchased with his owne bloud) that you would up, and bee doing, that which the wife of the Lambe is said to have done; <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 7. <hi>make your s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lves ready,</hi> which if you doe, his speedy accesse, shall bring to
<pb facs="8"/>
you speeding successe: which that you may doe, you shall not want his constant, and instant prayers, who is</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your christian and cordiall wel-wisher, <hi>G. H.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>